<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dirge? No. It's a Love Song.</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="543952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="CLASSICAL MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAPLAN, GILBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAHLER, GUSTAV (1860-1911)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D7143FF93AA25754C0A964958260" item-length="2019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dirge? No. It's a Love Song.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GILBERT KAPLAN;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAPLAN, GILBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Adagietto. For most music lovers, there is but one: the tender and supremely lyrical fourth movement of Mahler's Fifth Symphony. Scored only for strings and harp and often performed as an independent work, it is surely the composer's best-known piece. It has inspired more than 20 choreographers, among them Gerald Arpino, Maurice Bejart and John Neumeier, to create ballets and served as the principal theme for several films, including Luchino Visconti's "Death in Venice."</p>
        <p>Yet in spite of its popular appeal, the Adagietto is in danger of succumbing to a false tradition, characterized by ultra-slow performances. Many of the most experienced conductors of Mahler's music seem to believe that the music was intended as a lament, conveying feelings of melancholy, despair or even death, a notion surely reinforced by the Visconti film, in which the principal character, a composer, bears an unmistakable resemblance to Mahler.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Adagietto. For most music lovers, there is but one: the tender and supremely lyrical fourth movement of Mahler's Fifth Symphony. Scored only for strings and harp and often performed as an independent work, it is surely the composer's best-known piece. It has inspired more than 20 choreographers, among them Gerald Arpino, Maurice Bejart and John Neumeier, to create ballets and served as the principal theme for several films, including Luchino Visconti's "Death in Venice."</p>
        <p>Yet in spite of its popular appeal, the Adagietto is in danger of succumbing to a false tradition, characterized by ultra-slow performances. Many of the most experienced conductors of Mahler's music seem to believe that the music was intended as a lament, conveying feelings of melancholy, despair or even death, a notion surely reinforced by the Visconti film, in which the principal character, a composer, bears an unmistakable resemblance to Mahler.</p>
        <p>The Adagietto can indeed be made to project such moods, and performances at extremely slow tempos can be moving. This conception of the music may have culminated in the autumn of 1990, when, after Leonard Bernstein's death, orchestras around the world added the Adagietto to their programs in his memory. The choice seemed particularly fitting since Bernstein was so closely identified with Mahler's music. Years earlier, in fact, he himself had conducted the Adagietto to commemorate the death of his mentor, Serge Koussevitzky, and again at the funeral of Senator Robert Kennedy because of what he called the music's "great solemnity."</p>
        <p>So why is the tradition of ultra-slow interpretations false? The answer lies in information -- some newly discovered -- that provides compelling evidence that Mahler never intended the Adagietto to be music of great solemnity. Nor is it likely that he would have approved of somber interpretations performed at a funereal pace. For Mahler, the piece was a simple expression of love.</p>
        <p>The Adagietto served as a love letter from the composer to Alma Schindler, probably shortly before they were married in 1902. The Dutch conductor Willem Mengelberg, in his personal copy of the Fifth Symphony, wrote: "This Adagietto was Gustav Mahler's declaration of love for Alma! Instead of a letter, he sent her this in manuscript form; no other words accompanied it. She understood and wrote to him: He should come!!! (both of them told me this!)." Mengelberg's own description of the Adagietto was "love, a love comes into his life."</p>
        <p>Alma often inspired Mahler's work. The Fifth Symphony was a special bond that united them in the early years of their marriage. Alma said that it had been her "first full participation in his life and work," and she played a role in its creation. While Mahler was scoring the symphony, Alma copied it out. "We had a race to see who got through first," she said, "he scoring or I copying." In the 1930's, when Alma donated her copy of Rodin's bust of Mahler to the Vienna State Opera, the Vienna Philharmonic played the Adagietto at the presentation ceremony at her request.</p>
        <p>By using the Adagietto as a love letter, Mahler clearly pointed to the mood he wanted. And this, it would seem, determined his choice of tempo. The message of romantic love puts limits on how slowly the music can be played without distorting its character. Donald Mitchell, a leading Mahler authority, suggests that the Adagietto is really a song without words. "The successful interpretation of the Adagietto," he argues, "will be that which sustains the long melody as if it were written for the voice. No singer could possibly sustain the very slow tempos some conductors have adopted."</p>
        <p>A very slow tempo might be justified if Mahler meant the Adagietto to be a sad love song, and there is no denying the bittersweet quality of some of its music. Still, it is difficult to imagine that Mahler, in the first blush of his passion for Alma, would have composed a musical love letter of a melancholy nature. And even if he had sketched the movement before he met Alma, it seems inconceivable that he would have chosen music he intended to be somber to deliver, without the support of words, his declaration of love.</p>
        <p>The idea that Mahler's concept of the Adagietto would have translated into much faster tempos for his own performances is not just theory. In his personal score of the Fifth Symphony, most likely the one he used in 1904 for the work's premiere, a timing of seven and a half minutes is given for the Adagietto. (Performances today may run twice as long.) The timing was apparently written by the conductor Bruno Walter, who attended the premiere; whether it stemmed from Mahler's performance that evening or from one of Walter's own subsequent performances, its appearance in this historic score is significant.</p>
        <p>That timing closely matches Mahler's last performance of the Adagietto, in St. Petersburg in 1907. There, a player at the second desk of double basses wrote timings for several movements into his part. The Adagietto ran seven minutes.</p>
        <p>A timing of nine minutes appears in a set of printer's proofs corrected by Mahler for the first edition of the score, though not necessarily in Mahler's hand. An identical timing was recorded at the last rehearsal for a concert given by Mahler in 1905 in Hamburg.</p>
        <p>Mahler's timings are reinforced by recorded performances of his disciples. Mengelberg made the first recording of the Adagietto in 1926, running just over seven minutes. Like Walter, he had witnessed Mahler's own performances of the Fifth Symphony. Mahler once said of Mengelberg: "There's no one else I could entrust a work of mine to with entire confidence." Walter recorded the Adagietto in 1938, taking 7 minutes 58 seconds, and the full symphony in 1947, taking the Adagietto in 7 minutes 37 seconds.</p>
        <p>What all this evidence reveals is that performances of the Adagietto by the composer and his closest associates averaged about eight minutes. On recordings, Bernstein took some 11 minutes, and noted Mahler conductors today range upward to about 14 minutes (Bernard Haitink). In concert, Bernstein and Hermann Scherchen could take more than a quarter of an hour.</p>
        <p>Mahler often complained that conductors tended to "exaggerate and distort" his indications -- "the largo too slow, the presto too fast." But in the case of the Adagietto, he left room for some confusion. The term "adagietto," rarely used by composers, has left most conductors puzzled. And though the preferred definition in musical dictionaries is "slightly faster than adagio," Mahler complicated matters further by adding "sehr langsam" ("very slow").</p>
        <p>Yet he could not have anticipated the distortions to which his Adagietto would be subjected over the decades. As the noted Mahler biographer Henry-Louis de la Grange puts it: "Clearly, Mahler had not foreseen or feared the excessive slowness to which certain conductors are addicted today in this short composition, which in their hands loses its tender and meditative character to become a saccharine elegy."</p>
        <p>Some will undoubtedly argue that Mahler did not expect other performers to follow his interpretations. After all, he himself said, "Tradition is slovenliness." As a conductor, he was often accused of taking liberties with other composers' music. So, the usual argument goes, Mahler would surely have approved of -- or at least understood -- the treatment of his own music in the same manner by other conductors.</p>
        <p>This is one of the many Mahler myths. In fact, he was adamant that conductors should not freely interpret his music, an attitude entirely consistent with his own behavior. He was indeed a great interpreter, but he believed he was fulfilling the composers' wishes. When his performances of others' works were criticized for failing to follow "tradition," he argued that his fellow conductors had relied too long on a false tradition that had no relation to how composers might have conducted their own works or wished them to be performed. "Then," he complained, "if someone comes along and fans the nearly extinguished spark in the work to a living flame again, he is shouted down as a heretic and an innovator."</p>
        <p>Mahler did approve of certain adjustments to his orchestration to "suit the acoustics of the hall," but when it came to interpretation and especially to tempos, his view was different. According to Alma, "It was Mahler's wish to hand down his own interpretations as a tradition." His "slovenliness" comment notwithstanding, Mahler believed in tradition, but only when it emanated from a composer.</p>
        <p>After the poor reception of his Fifth Symphony in Berlin and Prague in 1905, Mahler said to a friend: "So I thought to myself: Is it the fault of the symphony or the conductor? . . . We musicians are worse off than writers in that respect. Anyone can read a book, but a musical score is a book with seven seals. Even the conductors who can decipher it present it to the public soaked in their own interpretations. For that reason there must be a tradition, and no one can create it but I."</p>
        <p>Still, Mahler would have been the last to argue that there was only one correct tempo for any of his works. His own performances always differed somewhat from one another. For Mahler, music was "something living and flowing that could never be the same even twice in succession." But that didn't mean he approved of any tempo. "Even if conductors follow my every indication," he said, "all is lost if they make a mistake in the first tempo." He thought that a tempo could be only "a degree" faster or slower, depending on the mood of the conductor, without harming his work.</p>
        <p>So there seems little doubt that Mahler wanted conductors to follow his tempos, within reasonable limits. But for the Adagietto, all most conductors know is Mahler's opening tempo indication, "sehr langsam." Now, the information about Mahler's use of the movement as a love letter, buttressed by timings of his own performances and other compelling evidence, makes clear that playing this music excessively slowly can no longer be justified as interpretive license. It is simply wrong. AND NOW, THE FIFTH</p>
        <p>Wait. It was Mahler's</p>
        <p>Second</p>
        <p>Symphony that Gilbert Kaplan pursued for so long, not the Fifth, right? Well, yes, and he's still at it, having conducted the Second Symphony in Red Rocks, Colo., just last weekend.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan (in photograph), who is the chairman of the magazine Institutional Investor, which he founded in 1967, traces his obsession with Mahler and the Second Symphony back to 1965, when, as an economist working on Wall Street, he heard Leopold Stokowski rehearse and perform the work with the American Symphony Orchestra.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan started chasing down every performance and recording of the work he could. In 1981, after turning 40, he began to study the score intensively. And improbably, in September 1982, this publisher with no formal musical training beyond childhood piano lessons led the American Symphony in Mahler's Second.</p>
        <p>Since then, he has conducted the work at the invitation of more than 15 orchestras around the world and he recorded it with the London Symphony in 1988 for MCA Classics. He bought the composer's manuscript in 1984, and had it published in a limited-edition facsimile.</p>
        <p>But lately Mr. Kaplan has also set his sights on the Adagietto of Mahler's Fifth Symphony. This fascination began after Leonard Bernstein's death in 1990, when he began to fear that the many dirgelike performances given in Bernstein's honor would congeal into a false tradition. To pin down Mahler's own concept of the movement as an expression of romantic love, he examined every document he could find relating to its history and performance.</p>
        <p>He has just published a facsimile edition (Faber Music, $125), including Mahler's 17-page manuscript and a copy made by the composer's wife, Alma. The edition also includes a CD of the Adagietto, performed by Mr. Kaplan and the London Symphony. The recording, which illustrates a tempo close to Mahler's own, will be released more widely in August by Pickwick. -- James R. Oestreich  CLASSICAL MUSIC Gilbert Kaplan has published a facsimile edition of the Adagietto of Mahler's Fifth Symphony and recorded the movement with the London Symphony.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gilbert Kaplan has published a facsimile edition of the Adagietto of Mahler's Fifth Symphony and recorded the movement with the London Symphony.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
