<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MAJOR SHIFT LIKELY AS LAW BANS BIAS TOWARD DISABLED</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="543933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HANDICAPPED</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OF 1990</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HIRING AND PROMOTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KILBORN, PETER T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DE133CF93AA25754C0A964958260" item-length="1776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MAJOR SHIFT LIKELY AS LAW BANS BIAS TOWARD DISABLED</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER T. KILBORN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KILBORN, PETER T</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A law to ban job discrimination against disabled people takes effect in a week and is widely expected to force changes in employment practices as far-reaching as those that followed the laws that opened jobs to women and blacks.</p>
        <p>As half a million businesses -- all those with 25 employees or more -- prepare to comply with the law, organizations representing people with disabilities are calling it their own emancipation proclamation. The law, the Americans With Disabilities Act of 1990, challenges the myths, attitudes and working conditions that its bipartisan authors blame for keeping many disabled adults housebound and impoverished. Applying to Many Businesses</p>
        <p>The provisions that take effect July 26 are intended to outlaw discrimination against the 14 million working-age Americans with physical or mental impairments. In two years, the provisions will be extended to three-quarters of a million other businesses with 15 to 25 workers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A law to ban job discrimination against disabled people takes effect in a week and is widely expected to force changes in employment practices as far-reaching as those that followed the laws that opened jobs to women and blacks.</p>
        <p>As half a million businesses -- all those with 25 employees or more -- prepare to comply with the law, organizations representing people with disabilities are calling it their own emancipation proclamation. The law, the Americans With Disabilities Act of 1990, challenges the myths, attitudes and working conditions that its bipartisan authors blame for keeping many disabled adults housebound and impoverished. Applying to Many Businesses</p>
        <p>The provisions that take effect July 26 are intended to outlaw discrimination against the 14 million working-age Americans with physical or mental impairments. In two years, the provisions will be extended to three-quarters of a million other businesses with 15 to 25 workers.</p>
        <p>Although the law does not require employers to set goals for hiring or promoting the disabled, it could have much the same effect. It tells employers that in hiring, promotion and compensation they cannot discriminate against an otherwise competent worker who has a "physical or mental impairment" that "substantially limits" a major life activity, like seeing, walking, thinking or breathing. Effect Hard to Gauge</p>
        <p>With the law still to take effect and the hiring slow everywhere because of the sluggish economy, no one ventures to guess yet how many people with disabilities will get jobs because of the law or what business will spend to accommodate them.</p>
        <p>But few experts doubt that the impact will be widespread. "It means that Government and the private sector must take steps to assure that people with disabilities have access to the mainstream of American life," said Robert A. Katzmann, a specialist in legal and disability issues at the Brookings Institution.</p>
        <p>Agencies specializing in placing people in jobs report more contacts with employers. Steve Weiner, placement director at Gallaudet University, a college in Washington for deaf students, reports a surge in companies visiting the campus to interview. "The act is generating a lot of possible hires," he said.</p>
        <p>The law is an unabashed venture into social engineering and Government intervention into the private economy, normally anathema to many conservatives and business associations. But although many employers say they fear the cost of complying, others say the law will expand the pool of workers available to industry at a time when there is a shortage of workers with essential skills.</p>
        <p>"We'll have a new sector of the work force that we can take advantage of," said Edward Potter, president of the Employment Policy Foundation, a research group financed by 200 major companies.</p>
        <p>An example of how the law is intended to work is James Holland, 28 years old, who has been completely blind since he was 12 and works for United Parcel Service, which like some other major companies has established programs for people with disabilities. Mr. Holland has been with the company for four years and is a computer programming instructor at an office in Mahwah, N.J.</p>
        <p>He has a voice synthesizer and a headset attached to his computer. The synthesizer reads words on his computer screen and converts the words to speech. It also reads back to him anything he types into the computer. He has another device that scans memorandums and other written documents and feeds them to the computer. U.P.S., he said, has been open to providing the tools he needs to work.</p>
        <p>The cost of the equipment was about $11,000. "Their attitude is, 'Except for adaptive equipment, we're going to treat you like anyone else,' " he said. "I've always been thankful for that. I'm a firm believer that people's abilities come from within. You have limitations. Everyone has. You have to overcome your limitations and work with your abilities." Satisfied Employer</p>
        <p>For what they consider a very small investment, U.P.S. officials say they have found an unusually competent programming instructor. "For us, the disabilities act does not present itself as some horrific new regulatory problem," said Fred Fernandez, the official in charge of the company's equal employment opportunity programs. "We're looking at it as an opportunity."</p>
        <p>The disabilities act requires employers to promptly provide a "reasonable accommodation," except where it causes "undue hardship," to help the workers cope with their disabilities -- scheduling their hours to permit visits to doctors, for example, widening bathroom stalls to help people in wheelchairs or providing special tools.</p>
        <p>The law does not ask employers to hire people who lack vital faculties for a particular job -- blind people to drive trucks, for example. But a disability alone, said Christopher Bell, a senior lawyer for the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, cannot be grounds for rejection. "It's not enough just to have something wrong," said Mr. Bell, who is blind.</p>
        <p>Various studies show that workers with disabilities are at least as effective as others. The Du Pont Company does periodic polls of its disabled workers. The latest survey, of the supervisors of 811 disabled workers in 1990, rated the workers on a par with others in attention to safety, marginally below them in job performance and well above them in attendance. Other surveys show much less turnover among the workers, no doubt in part because it is harder for them to find other jobs.</p>
        <p>More broadly, experts say, discrimination against people with disabilities is costly to society as a whole. Of the 14.2 million disabled people 16 to 64 years old, Mitchell P. LaPlante, director of the Disability Statistics Program at the University of California in San Francisco, says only 30 percent worked in 1989, mostly at part-time and irregular jobs, while 76 percent of people without disabilities worked, most of them in regular, full-time jobs. Many Need a Lot of Help</p>
        <p>Mr. LaPlante says that many of the 7.9 million disabled he classifies as severely limited would need a lot of help to take jobs, like people to dress them and feed them, but that 6.3 million are more easily employable. Of that group, 58 percent had jobs, and most of the rest could have worked, he said.</p>
        <p>He said 23 percent of the disabled adults were poor, almost three times the rate for the rest of the population.</p>
        <p>Many survive on largely on food stamps, Medicaid and Social Security checks. Phil Gambino, a spokesman for the Social Security Administration, said 3.2 million former workers who have become totally disabled receive an average of $7,125 a year from Social Security Disability Insurance.</p>
        <p>He said three million other adults were ineligible for the insurance because they had not worked enough to qualify. They receive an average of $4,114 in Supplemental Security Income, a form of welfare. The cost of both programs is $3.1 billion a year.</p>
        <p>With the law still to take effect, no one knows if the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, the principal enforcement agency, will be deluged with complaints from aggrieved job seekers. But Evan J. Kemp Jr., chairman of the commission, predicts the complaints of civil rights violations workers bring to the commission over the next year will increase 20 percent, or 15,000 new cases.</p>
        <p>Joanne Frankfort, a lawyer at the Employment Law Center in San Francisco, which represents workers in occupational disputes, said: "I think we will see significant amounts of litigation. Any action taken against a qualified individual because of his disability could be a violation. And there are teeth in the law."</p>
        <p>But advocacy groups and the commission expect many complaints to be summarily rejected because the workers will be found unqualified for the jobs they are denied and than many others will be resolved through negotiation and arbitration. Only the most extreme cases are expected to bring monetary penalties, which can be as high as $300,000.</p>
        <p>Even then, enforcement is likely to be slow. The commission says that because of budgetary constraints, it may not be able to hire the 250 new compliance officers to investigate complaints under the act.</p>
        <p>Some advocates of disabled people want to avoid litigation. Paul Marchand, chairman of the Consortium for Citizens with Disabilities, a lobbying group in Washington, said: "We are not out to clobber anybody. We hope it would be the last resort. It makes no sense to put business out of business."  Vagueness Invites Lawsuits</p>
        <p>But some lawsuits seem inevitable because Congress deliberately left central provisions of the law vague. What is a "reasonable accommodation" and not an "undue hardship" for a company depends largely on its resources.</p>
        <p>Smaller businesses, especially, say they fear the cost of compliance. The $11,000 that U.P.S. has spent to accommodate Mr. Holland might be judged an undue hardship for a very small company. But Rick Douglas, executive director of the President's Committee on Employment of People With Disabilities, says the average disabled worker's accommodation costs less than $500. Some adjustments, like scheduling work around doctors' appointments or raising the desk of a worker in a wheelchair, cost nothing.</p>
        <p>A large company might be expected to be able to employ a full-time interpreter for deaf workers, but a small company might comply by teaching a deaf worker's supervisor sign language. But many other questions are murkier. Some people are confined to their homes but can do the essential functions of a job. Will a company be required to let the employee work at home? As yet, no one knows.</p>
        <p>Here and there, even a very small employer finds that hiring people with disabilities so desirable that Government goading is unnecessary. Two years ago, James W. Snow was opening a business, a commercial laundry in Russellville, Ark. "It was hard to find people who would start at the minimum wage," Mr. Snow said.</p>
        <p>"So this friend of mine said, 'You know what might work? These people from the Russell Skills Center.' " There, as at hundreds of other centers in other communities, people who are retarded and have other mental disabilities learn to work and to live independently. " 'They can do the folding, the sorting and the processing of your laundry.' "</p>
        <p>Mr. Snow said 5 of his 16 employees come from the center, which provides coaches for the workers until they learn their routines. The workers are paid the same as others without disabilities. "It all works well for me," Mr. Snow said. "I'm ecstatic. If I could do more, I would do more."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
