<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BARCELONA - A VIEWERS GUIDE: The Sports; Canoe/Kayak</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="544031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1992)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CANOES AND CANOEING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KAYAKS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALLACE, WILLIAM N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Canoeing and Kayaking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Kayaking and Canoeing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Canoes and Canoeing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DE1631F93AA25754C0A964958260" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BARCELONA - A VIEWERS GUIDE: The Sports; Canoe/Kayak</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM N. WALLACE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALLACE, WILLIAM N</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOW IT'S DONE: The Olympic competition in canoeing and kayaking will be in two disciplines: flatwater and whitewater.</p>
        <p>Flatwater racing, the traditional format, has been held since the 1936 Games. These sprint races take place on calm, (and yes) flat water over buoyed, straightaway courses. This year's races will be at the Castelldefels Speed Canal near Barcelona.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOW IT'S DONE: The Olympic competition in canoeing and kayaking will be in two disciplines: flatwater and whitewater.</p>
        <p>Flatwater racing, the traditional format, has been held since the 1936 Games. These sprint races take place on calm, (and yes) flat water over buoyed, straightaway courses. This year's races will be at the Castelldefels Speed Canal near Barcelona.</p>
        <p>Then there will be -- for only the second time in the Olympics and the first time since 1972 -- the exciting whitewater slalom competition. One by one, the athletes paddle through 25 slalom gates over a 340-meter course with its turbulent rapids formed by water running over boulders at 450 cubic feet a second. If the athletes hit or miss any of the slalom gates, they will be assessed time penalties of 5 or 50 seconds. Each competitor takes two runs and the better time counts. The location is a manmade course on the River Segre in La Seu d'Urgell.</p>
        <p>In flatwater, there are eight classes with 500 and 1,000 meters the distances. Men race at both distances in single and double kayaks and canoes (K-1, K-2, C-1 and C-2) and also in four-man kayaks (K-4) for a total of nine events. Women race in single, double and four-women kayaks but not in canoes.</p>
        <p>The single flatwater kayak is about 17 feet in length with a maximum beam of 21 inches and it weighs only 26 pounds. The canoes are open, without a deck, and a little larger and heavier at 17 feet by 30 inches and 35 pounds for a single. Kayakers use twin-blade paddles and sit in their decked craft with legs extended. They paddle with a rocker-like motion and at full bore they will be taking 115 strokes a minute. The flatwater canoeists use single-blade paddles and kneel on one knee, the upper body erect.</p>
        <p>In whitewater racing, there are four classes: men's and women's single kayak; men's single and double canoe (K-1, KW-1, C-1 and C-2). Both whitewater canoes and kayaks, which measure 14 feet in length and weigh under 25 pounds for the singles, are decked over and ride low to the water.</p>
        <p>Paddlers wear helmets, life jackets and spray skirts to keep water out of their boats. HOW TO WATCH: A series of heats, repechage or second-chance heats, and semifinal races produce nine finalists for each event. The races go quickly and demand lightning starts and a furious early charge. Winning times at 500 meters are about 1 minute 40 seconds for single kayakers, 3:30 over 1,000 meters. In both flatwater and whitewater, the relative short Olympic distances make for keen competition with places often decided by tenths of seconds. WHO TO WATCH: Because Olympic medals are so hard to come by, it is astonishing that the United States will have a good chance to win a few in this relatively obscure sport. The American team will be the third largest at Barcelona and the 36 athletes are the product of a pool of about 300 American competitors.</p>
        <p>Greg Barton, 32, is the defending Olympic champion at 1,000 meters. Barton and Norm Bellingham, 27, are the defenders in the 1,000-meter pairs, and Bellingham is currently ranked No. 1 in the world at 500 meters.</p>
        <p>Their chief competition for medals is expected to come from Renn Crichlow of Canada; Knut Holmannmof Norway, and Ferenc Csipes and Zsolt Gyulay of Hungary.</p>
        <p>Jon Lugbill, 31, is a four-time world champion in whitewater single-canoe racing although at last year's world championships he dropped back to fourth. He overpowers the course, outmuscling the rapids in contrast to the delicate touch of Richard Fox, Britain's cerebral kayaker. Lugbill and Fox have set the style in their events: a C-1 canoe powered by a single-blade paddle, and a K-1 kayak with its double-blade paddle.</p>
        <p>Lugbill's leading challengers in the canoe will be Gareth Marriott of Britain and the veteran Thierry Humeau of France.</p>
        <p>Besides Lugbill in whitewater canoeing the United States medal potential lies with his longtime partner, Davey Hearn, and 19-year-old Adam Clawson, a silver medalist at the 1991 world championships.</p>
        <p>In women's whitewater kayaks, Dana Chladek was second best in the world last year. Myriam Jerusalmi of France, who is married to Fox, will be the one for Chladek to beat. Traci Phillips and Cathy Marino are potential medalists in women's flatwater kayak as are Mike Herbert and Mark Hamilton in men's flatwater kayak.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
