<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Residents Reclaim Their Old Way of Life</title>
    <meta content="14HOUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="871309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chester (Pa)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6D61731F937A2575BC0A960958260" item-length="1037" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Residents Reclaim Their Old Way of Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>CHESTER, Pa., Aug 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tenants of Bennett homes housing project in Chester, Pa, are celebrating reopening of first 97 of nearly 400 units to be renovated six years after lawsuit was filed by residents against local housing authorities to reverse years of decay and neglect; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As an original tenant in the Ruth L. Bennett Homes, Yvonne Carrington never forgot what the rows of modest brick town homes in her community looked like when she moved in 43 years ago. ''It was a lovely place to live,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In a way, her memory has been a curse. Built in the 1940's for the families of local shipyard workers, the homes soon passed into public housing and began a slow descent into decrepitude. They were eventually overwhelmed by rats, grafitti, drug dealers, poor management and  crime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As an original tenant in the Ruth L. Bennett Homes, Yvonne Carrington never forgot what the rows of modest brick town homes in her community looked like when she moved in 43 years ago. ''It was a lovely place to live,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In a way, her memory has been a curse. Built in the 1940's for the families of local shipyard workers, the homes soon passed into public housing and began a slow descent into decrepitude. They were eventually overwhelmed by rats, grafitti, drug dealers, poor management and  crime.</p>
        <p>But a rising level of anger among tenants and a new approach to rehabilitating public housing has enabled Mrs. Carrington to push aside images of squalor and foreboding and recall the old days. Today, tenants of the Bennett homes, housing officials and local leaders joined to celebrate the opening of the first 97 of nearly 400 units to be renovated. The remaining units are scheduled for remodeling within a year, followed by work on Chester's three other public housing projects. Altogether, 1,000 units will be restored.</p>
        <p>''A truly remarkable transformation is taking place before our eyes,'' said Judge Norma L. Shapiro of the  District Court for eastern Pennsylvania, whose ruling in a 1990 lawsuit set the renaissance in motion. ''It's a wonderful example of what can happen when initiative, creativity and community are applied.''</p>
        <p>The lawsuit was the first of its kind, filed by public housing residents against the local housing authority to reverse years of decay and neglect.</p>
        <p>At the time, the action was considered a radical adversarial approach. When public housing decayed, it was more common for the Department of Housing and Urban Development to form a friendly partnership with local officials eager for Federal assistance to improve existing stock, build new units or relocate tenants into other areas. These partnerships exist in Chicago, Philadelphia, New Orleans and San Francisco, among other cities.</p>
        <p>The Chester initiative is under way while a House-Senate conference committee is negotiating final language of a bill that would change much of nation's housing policies for the first time in 60 years by shifting more power and discretion to the local authorities. A key component would be to hold the local authorities to certain performance standards and replace them with a private management group if they fail to uphold them.</p>
        <p>The Administration has indicated it supports the Congressional overhaul so long as public housing remains affordable for the neediest Americans.</p>
        <p>In the Chester case, local officials resisted the housing agency's intervention, and a group of tenants dissatisfied with the agency's efforts decided to sue the Chester Housing Authority.</p>
        <p>Judge Shapiro ruled for the tenants in 1993 and placed the Chester Housing Authority in receivership, later approving a former New York City housing official, Robert C. Rosenberg, as the receiver in 1994. Since then, tenants' groups in two other cities, Washington and Kansas City, Mo., have sued their local housing authorities, resulting in court-appointed private receivers.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if this gets things done any faster,'' Maryann Russ, the H.U.D. deputy assistant secretary for public and assisted housing operations, said of the court-ordered approach to improvements. ''But in certain situations, because of a combination of political intransigence and deep-seated suspicions housing residents have about local administrations, this is the only way to bring in a new broom.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosenberg, now chairman of the Grenadier Realty Corporation in Brooklyn, discovered quickly that no broom was big enough. In assessing the local housing authority and H.U.D.'s early efforts at reform, he said he found deterioration everywhere, from an unresponsive maintenance system to crumbling interiors to grounds littered with glass and garbage.</p>
        <p>''The tenants hated the management, and management despised the tenants,'' he said in an interview. ''It was a bunker mentality.''</p>
        <p>Bookkeeping was so shoddy, he said, unpaid rents from before 1992 were forgiven.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Carrington, 55, one of the forces behind the lawsuit and now president of the Bennett Homes Tenant Council, said the deterioration began in earnest in the 1970's when the community was hit by a rising incidence of drug use, teenaged pregnancies and unemployment. Almost any night, she said, drug dealers roamed dark passageways between rows of units, and gunshots were common.</p>
        <p>One claimed the life of her daughter, Carla, 17, just days before she was to leave for college in Ohio. Caught by a stray bullet when a fight broke out among young men leaving a playground basketball game, the honors student at Chester High School was killed -- eight years ago this Saturday.</p>
        <p>''I had never been afraid here before that,'' Mrs. Carrington said. ''They were drug dealers, kids that just didn't have anything to do with their lives, kids just fussing over one another over who owns which territory.''</p>
        <p>Today, the rehabilitated units, paid for by $22.8 million in Federal housing grants, stand in gleaming contrast to those still waiting for repair. The new town homes have new peaked roofs, brightly colored entrances, remodeled kitchens and modernized radiator systems. Outside, children's play areas, trees and landscaped lawns have replaced the desolation and debris.</p>
        <p>''When I first came here,'' Judge Shapiro said, ''I saw no children playing outside. They were all inside, in darkened units, some watching TV, some just staring out.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Carrington said her only concern now is that residents will appreciate what they have and what others have done for them. ''We've gotten everything we were entitled to,'' she said. ''But now we have to be responsible for ourselves. People need to see what they have here and make sure it stays that way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
