<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Networks vs. the Organizers: Early Rounds Go to G.O.P.</title>
    <meta content="14MEDI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THE REPUBLICANS: THE BROADCASTS" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="871367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: THE BROADCASTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Diego (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co (NBC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Broadcasting Cos Inc (Abc)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennet, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Diego</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6DA1431F937A2575BC0A960958260" item-length="1434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Networks vs. the Organizers: Early Rounds Go to G.O.P.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bennet, James</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many television network executives, day after start of Republican National Convention in San Diego, are unsure whether they made right choice televising scripted prime-time images supplied by Republican Party; some say they were misled by convention planners, while others defend coverage; all three major networks devoted almost all of hourlong broadcasts to scenes supplied by Republicans; photo; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Colin L. Powell spoke about Republican diversity here on Monday night, at least a fifth of the faces the major broadcast networks focused on were black, though only 3 percent of the delegates are.</p>
        <p>Two networks, NBC and ABC, broadcast a six-minute videotape  about Ronald Reagan, whose image Bob Dole, the imminent Republican nominee, is trying to borrow. And all three devoted most of their hourlong broadcasts to scenes the Republicans had scripted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Colin L. Powell spoke about Republican diversity here on Monday night, at least a fifth of the faces the major broadcast networks focused on were black, though only 3 percent of the delegates are.</p>
        <p>Two networks, NBC and ABC, broadcast a six-minute videotape  about Ronald Reagan, whose image Bob Dole, the imminent Republican nominee, is trying to borrow. And all three devoted most of their hourlong broadcasts to scenes the Republicans had scripted.</p>
        <p>Round 1 went to the Republicans in the prime-time bout between party planners trying to present a coiffed image and network producers willing to muss it, a quadrennial struggle that is more intense than ever this year.</p>
        <p>Some network executives said convention planners had misled them about the content of the Reagan video, had not given them advance copies soon enough to allow them to screen it thoroughly for news value, had similarly delayed releasing the texts of speeches and had shifted the schedule forward at the last minute, throwing them even further off balance. Others said they had had plenty of time and information to do their jobs. All defended their coverage.</p>
        <p>But today, during a lull between prime-time storms, at least one producer re-evaluated some decisions. Jeff Zucker, the executive producer of NBC's coverage, which drew the largest audience, paused and then sighed when asked whether he had made the right choice in showing the Reagan video.</p>
        <p>''Let me say if I had to do it again, I would really give that a second thought,'' he said after a couple of false starts. ''I'm not as convinced, Monday morning quarterbacking myself, that it was as newsworthy as I thought it was going in.''</p>
        <p>In dozens of split-second decisions during their coverage of the major parties' conventions, network producers must reconcile several competing needs: to resist becoming propagandists for the parties, to woo viewers with compelling images and to present a fair picture of the proceedings.</p>
        <p>Jeff Gralnick, an ABC News vice president who is executive producer of convention coverage, said he had done the right thing in broadcasting the Reagan video. ''We thought it was going to be the emotional centerpiece,'' he said, ''if not of the night, then possibly of the entire convention.'' He said it had met his expectations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gralnick also pointed out that ABC News had provided context and commentary dealing with the convention on several news programs during the day.</p>
        <p>But Lane Venardos, a CBS vice president, sounded equally comfortable with his decision to ignore the video almost completely. ''We decided on news value alone not to run it,'' he said. ''There was not one scintilla of new information.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Venardos said convention planners had promised that the video would include ''new pictures of the former President, never-before-seen post-Alzheimer's-onset pictures.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gralnick said he had received no such promises about the video's content. And Paul J. Manafort, Mr. Dole's convention manager, said, ''We never said, as recently as this week, that there would be new footage of Reagan.'' Mr. Manafort also denied that the networks had been promised advance copies.</p>
        <p>In place of the video segment, Mr. Venardos substituted a live interview with Representative Susan Molinari, the keynote speaker, in which Dan Rather pressed her on whether the convention's images suited its reality.</p>
        <p>''I'm a little confused,'' Mr. Rather said. ''Bob Dole says this is the party of inclusion. But Governor Weld, of Massachusetts, who's pro-choice, is not allowed to speak here.''</p>
        <p>None of the networks showed the speech by former President Gerald R. Ford, but they disagreed on former President George Bush. While CBS and NBC carried Mr. Bush's speech, ABC skipped most of it, cutting to him only as he introduced his wife, Barbara, as ''a woman who unquestionably upheld the honor of the White House.''</p>
        <p>Scores of media outlets, from print to radio to cable to computer services, are covering the convention. The Republicans are even televising  it themselves, on two cable channels.  The convention planners have arranged their schedule to meet the needs of the major broadcast networks, however, because those networks command the largest audiences.</p>
        <p>But viewers seemed generally unimpressed with the convention, or with the coverage, or perhaps some were drawn to another medium. About 23 percent of the nation's television sets in use were tuned to the convention on Monday night, compared with 30 percent on the first night of the Republican convention in 1992, when the coverage lasted longer.</p>
        <p>''We go through a great deal of effort -- the three of us do, and CNN does -- to put out programs that the American public in general does not want,'' said Mr. Gralnick, of ABC.</p>
        <p>The broadcast networks each showed an hour of the convention on Monday, from 10 P.M. to 11 P.M., Eastern daylight time, a plan the Republicans had known about and scheduled for. CBS and ABC each carried about 35 minutes of the convention planners' program itself, while NBC devoted about 20 percent more time -- 42 minutes -- to it.</p>
        <p>The networks certainly strayed far enough from the official convention script on occasion to make Republicans grind their teeth. For example, while Mr. Ford was speaking, Mr. Rather, on CBS, was describing the various cameras the networks had secreted around the hall, including what he called ''the Bobcam.''</p>
        <p>''We've once again installed a camera on the headset of Bob Schieffer,'' Mr. Rather said.</p>
        <p>At least one Republican relished the networks' independence. Patrick J. Buchanan, the failed Presidential candidate, may have been denied a speaking role here, but both NBC and CBS interviewed him on the convention floor.</p>
        <p>When asked on CBS whether he was disappointed that only moderates were speaking in prime time, Mr. Buchanan grinned. ''You're talking to a conservative in prime time,'' he observed.</p>
        <p>The anchors warned the audience that the planners were trying to script the convention. On ABC, Peter Jennings referred to Mr. Bush as ''a man who didn't control his convention as well as Bob Dole would like to control his.''</p>
        <p>Early in his broadcast, Mr. Rather described the delegates as overwhelmingly white and conservative. ''You aren't going to be seeing many of the delegates at home,'' he said with a chuckle. ''That is, not if the party has its way. Instead, you'll be seeing a quite different party, the one that Bob Dole wants you to see.''</p>
        <p>At times, however, the networks seemed to be collaborating in showing that different party. During General Powell's speech, time after time the networks, particularly ABC and NBC, cut to black people on the floor. One black woman shown by ABC was not a delegate at all but instead a correspondent for Time magazine, Tamala Edwards.</p>
        <p>Ms. Edwards said today that she had simply been sitting with the Virginia delegation to interview conventioneers and had been wearing her press credentials. ''I had no idea,'' Mr. Gralnick said. ''There are 18,000 people down on the floor. They're not wearing signs.''</p>
        <p>Armed with a copy of a speech, network directors try to illustrate sections of it with reaction shots from delegates who fit the text. But as General Powell spoke about affirmative action and race relations,  ABC realized, Mr. Gralnick said, that ''we're not giving a fair picture of the hall.'' ABC then stopped cutting to so many black faces, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zucker, of NBC, said of the emphasis on shots of blacks, ''We fell into that trap, and that's a valid criticism.''</p>
        <p>To keep viewers interested, the networks tried hard in their broadcasts to suggest that there would be drama at the convention. CBS opened its broadcast with the announcement that ''the fireworks are about to begin.''</p>
        <p>Appropriately enough, the pictures of fireworks that filled the screen were from a display here on Saturday night that was staged for the media.</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: THE BROADCASTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
