<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="463183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DC1639F93BA15754C0A967958260" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 3-13</p>
        <p>New steps to topple Saddam Hussein are the aim of consultations between the United States and its allies. But holding together the international alliance that defeated Iraq is proving to be a formidable task. Page 1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 3-13</p>
        <p>New steps to topple Saddam Hussein are the aim of consultations between the United States and its allies. But holding together the international alliance that defeated Iraq is proving to be a formidable task. Page 1</p>
        <p>Baghdad is becoming normal again, almost six months after the end of the war. Traffic lights are working and air-conditioners hum in the heat. With the recovery, Saddam Hussein's Government digging in as well.  12</p>
        <p>Britain exported radioactive material to Baghdad 13</p>
        <p>A major issue in U.S.-Soviet relations is how the Bush Administration will answer a basic question: Are American interests best served by a united Soviet Union or a group of smaller states built from its republics? 1</p>
        <p>Economy sulks as Gorbachev enjoys his encore 10</p>
        <p>Americans share Soviet economic pessimism 10</p>
        <p>Europeans try again to calm Yugoslavs 3</p>
        <p>Eastern Europeans are seeing Paris this summer, most for the first time. It doesn't matter that they don't have much money to spend. For tens of thousands, what really counts is that they are no longer so different. 1</p>
        <p>Swiss protester fighting for world's forests 6</p>
        <p>The mood of West Bank Palestinians is one of bitterness, dejection and frustration about the American-led peace process. Many fear they will be isolated again in trying to gain an independent state.  8</p>
        <p>Price rises rule postwar Cairo's scuttlebutt 8</p>
        <p>Support for Japan's Finance Minister came from an unusual source: Treasury Secretary Nicholas Brady, who backed the minister in comments about the rising furor over the Japanese stock market scandal. 3</p>
        <p>Beijing cracks down on Mongol dissidents 11</p>
        <p>National 14-22</p>
        <p>Job seekers in three American cities, New Bedford, Mass., Iowa City and Tyler, Tex., are encountering trends that are more unsettling than the usual lag between economic recovery and unemployment rates. 1</p>
        <p>Court papers on a huge seized bank, the Bank of Credit and Commerce International, allege that the bank was involved in various shady deals, including smuggling coffee, hushing witnesses and selling helicopters. 1</p>
        <p>The servicemen missing in Vietnam are receiving renewed attention because of a photograph said to show three men lost in the war. For the families, any bit of news stirs old pains and fresh disappointments. 1</p>
        <p>Black elected officials in Milwaukee plan to call for an investigation of the police department, which has been embarrassed by the way it handled complaints in May about a man now accused of mass murder. 14</p>
        <p>Rights group says Bush's approach to rights bill is lacking 14</p>
        <p>Black journalists fear setback from recession 15</p>
        <p>Two major decisions by the F.D.A. seem to show that it is willing to relax its strict requirement that drugs be proved effective before being sold. The new position has dismayed some and delighted others.  22</p>
        <p>A request to remove the feeding tube of a woman who had been unconscious since 1987 will be heard in Indiana, even though the woman has died. The trial could provide legal guidance in an especially thorny issue. 14</p>
        <p>First child treated with gene therapy said to be thriving 20</p>
        <p>Regional 23-31</p>
        <p>Political memo: The redistricting of the New York City Council opened wounds between black and Hispanic politicians. In the struggle to share power with whites, minority groups frequently fought each other. 1</p>
        <p>Redrawing of districts results in dissent among candidates 27</p>
        <p>Political Talk: Alarums about Athens and Troy 28</p>
        <p>A real-estate office was firebombed in Canarsie for the second time in less than two weeks. Before the first incident, a caller told an employee that the agency would be punished for selling to blacks. 25</p>
        <p>The police presence in Central Park has been increased because of the related shootings there. But they have few leads -- and the gay men who are believed to be the suspect's targets are staying away. 25</p>
        <p>Correction captain accuses supervisor of harassing her 23</p>
        <p>Reporter's notebook: The trial of the man accused of starting the fire that killed 87 people at a Bronx social club is unfolding slowly and eerily. The trial's six days so far have been a long roll call for the dead. 26</p>
        <p>Owner of Happy Land building faces foreclosures 26</p>
        <p>Man kills wife with hammer and slits his wrists, police say 24</p>
        <p>Informer insists bid-rigging testimony was truth 29</p>
        <p>Some people call them Jet Skis, the jet-pump propelled craft that make noise and dart through waters everywhere. But at Lake George, people are divided on whether to call them the new scourge of summer.  24</p>
        <p>No car flips this summer for child in Fresh Air Fund 28</p>
        <p>Hospitals flooded with calls on HIV-infected doctor 27</p>
        <p>92d Street Y tries to raise $40 million 23</p>
        <p>Obituaries 30</p>
        <p>Earl Attlee, a founder of Britain's Social Demoratic Party</p>
        <p>Arts/Reviews 45</p>
        <p>Campus Life 35</p>
        <p>Fashion 38-39</p>
        <p>Life Style 36</p>
        <p>Pastimes 46-47</p>
        <p>Weddings 42-44</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
