<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sometimes Titles Are the Whole Story</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="463301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHULEVITZ, JUDITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD8113BF93BA15754C0A967958260" item-length="2091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sometimes Titles Are the Whole Story</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH SHULEVITZ;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHULEVITZ, JUDITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They career on screen at the beginning as if they've taken a wrong turn, pause briefly, then whoosh off -- New York street signs with stars' names on them instead of traffic instructions, caricatures with red slashes through them to communicate some edict like "no interracial couples here."</p>
        <p>Or they break in a full 10 minutes after the movie has started, letters rippling into focus over silhouettes of somersaulting women, themselves superimposed over spurting volcanoes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They career on screen at the beginning as if they've taken a wrong turn, pause briefly, then whoosh off -- New York street signs with stars' names on them instead of traffic instructions, caricatures with red slashes through them to communicate some edict like "no interracial couples here."</p>
        <p>Or they break in a full 10 minutes after the movie has started, letters rippling into focus over silhouettes of somersaulting women, themselves superimposed over spurting volcanoes.</p>
        <p>Or they crop up at the end, blood-red words below a television screen showing Ronald Reagan -- bitter, understated commentary on the scenes of massacre that preceded them.</p>
        <p>They, of course, are title sequences, that felicitous conjunction of type, music, cinematography and even animation that captures a movie's look, mood and message in a single eye-catching motif. The street signs introduce a picture in theaters right now, "Jungle Fever"; the female silhouettes embellish the titles to a James Bond movie called "You Only Live Twice"; and Ronald Reagan's face concludes a 1987 film by Alex Cox called "Walker," the true story of a 19th-century American madman who invaded and ruled Nicaragua.</p>
        <p>Although each sequence differs utterly from the others, they are all, visually speaking, the densest, most experimental 2 or 3 minutes in the 90 to 120 minutes of film they usher on or off the screen. And not one of them, it turns out, is the work of the film's credited director.</p>
        <p>Anyone who has been to a movie in the last decade knows that titles came back in the 1980's after fading from the screen in the 70's. And they're bigger, bolder and more expensive than ever before, only in part because they have to compete for the audience's attention with bombastic trailers and theater companies' flashy "Feature Presentation" logos. In the blockbuster era, a conspicuous title sequence was also a status symbol: no self-respecting megahit went out of the studio without one.</p>
        <p>Conjure up any memorable title sequence -- the Etch-a-Sketch spirals of "Vertigo," the eminently quashable feline of "Pink Panther," the zooming block letters of "Superman," the balletic boxer of "Raging Bull," the 60's-style fashion collage of "Soapdish" -- and chances are it was created by a professional title designer. Odds are even greater that audiences have never heard his or her name.</p>
        <p>Whenever studios have had disposable cash to sling around, as they have, say, in the last few years, titles have becomes splashier, artier and more wanton than ever before -- but their creators stayed put in the background. Title designers are Hollywood's unsung poets, condensing all the noise, color and action of celluloid drama into a few striking images, sometimes even white-on-black type. (Think of the titles to all the Woody Allen movies of the last 10 years.)</p>
        <p>How could a director possibly entrust the opening gambit, that all-important first impression, to the hands of a total stranger? Easily. Titling is literally the last thing a director wants to think about. The final stage of postproduction, titling invariably occurs long after exhaustion -- and sometims poverty -- have set in. Directors come to title designers, final cut in hand, the way harried professionals might approach personal shoppers: with no time to spare, and even less cash.</p>
        <p>That means a title designer's job is not only thankless, it's usually hard. Once designers have seen a movie, they must come up with ideas, shoot a sequence if none has already been shot, reshooot it with titles over it, and edit it -- all in a matter of weeks, sometimes days, and, relatively speaking, for pennies. The fee for designer titles ranges from $25,000 to $50,000, a drop in the average studio movie's $25 million bucket. But "many of the people who come to me have borrowed from the title budget along the way," said Dan Perri, title designer for "Raging Bull" (and for "Nashville," whose opening parody of a late-night commercial for country-and-western's greatest hits is among the funniest spoken title sequences ever made). To economize, directors will sometimes create titles themselves, turning to a designer when things go wrong. "They'll go to the optical houses themselves and pick out a typeface," said Mr. Perri. "Then they'll preview it and say, hey, we need a better opening."</p>
        <p>Meeting deadlines on the cheap and summing up in a few images what the director took thousands to say are, moreover, the least of a title designer's worries. The real headache is caused by lawyers, long before production of the film itself has begun. Before stars will sign film contracts, their lawyers must negotiate down to the smallest detail the minutiae of title protocol: whose name comes when, how long the names stay on the screen, how tall they are, how wide, even, at times, what color.</p>
        <p>And when the movie finally flickers onto the screen, it had best not deviate a whit from the clauses in the agreement. In the entertainment industry, billing is among the most precious of commodities and breach of billing contract among the most actionable of sins. The "Superman" title designer Richard Greenberg recalls having to hire an assistant whose entire job consisted of taking calls from Marlon Brando's lawyer. "He called me every day and wanted to measure the size of the type against that of the other titles," said Mr. Greenberg. "I almost told him to go to hell."</p>
        <p>Mimi Everett, one half of the New York-based husband-and-wife team of Balsmeyer &amp; Everett, who designed jumpy, street-smart titles of "Jungle Fever" (as well as the stylish ones with the blowing hat for the Coen brothers' "Miller's Crossing" and the gruesome ones with medieval drawings of gynecological instruments for David Cronenberg's "Dead Ringers"), thinks of herself as half artist, half psychoanalyst. Directors, she said, often cannot envision the many ways designers can combine type and image, so she tries to base her title sequences on the emotions she senses behind a director's words, rather than the words themselves.</p>
        <p>"She listens to people's body language, not their words," said her husband, Randy Balsmeyer, "and she's usually right."</p>
        <p>For the titles on "Jungle Fever," Spike Lee told them: "I see signs. Maps. A 'No Niggers' sign." Balsmeyer &amp; Everett, who have worked with Mr. Lee since "School Daze" (1988), took it from there -- and felt free to go a long way. "He never plays it safe," said Mr. Balsmeyer. "He never asks what people normally do. That's the last thing he wants."</p>
        <p>For the titles themselves, the team relettered official New York City street signs. When the city made it impossible for them to get hold of a pole ("we kept having to talk to some different department," explained Ms. Everett), they filched a damaged one from their own street. For the background, they used the cinematographer's aerial views of city blocks. They concluded the montage with an animated map of New York that traced the path from Harlem to Bensonhurst. "Actually, Spike finally distilled it down to this: this is a film about boundaries," said Mr. Balsmeyer. "And what it would look like if all the conventional prejudices that people usually hide on the inside were on signs for people to see."</p>
        <p>Title designers can also use their art to make allusions that the film itself may not make, be they to other movies, paintings or moments in history. For the jaunty title sequence of "Soapdish," the graphic artist Sarajo Frieden wanted to build a bridge between the fast-paced soap-opera spoof and the frothy comedies of the 1950's and 60's. "I looked at Doris Day-Rock Hudson movies like 'Pillow Talk,' " she said. "I looked at the titles for 'Funny Face,' which Richard Avedon did." Those jazzy collages of clothing and household items suggested to Ms. Frieden that she could "create a style, an ambiance with color, movement, objects, with a glove."</p>
        <p>Movies have obviously always had titles: how else would audiences know what they were were watching? Silent films had beautifully lettered billboards that gave audiences all the information they needed in one or two screensful. That convention gave way to others: the playbill before and after, the gloved hand leafing though the first pages of a book, the engraved invitation (as in the 1939 Bette Davis vehicle "The Old Maid").</p>
        <p>Occasionally, a director would depart from tradition. Preston Sturges, for example, came up with a curling, irrepressible snake for his 1941 comedy "The Lady Eve" that is one of the earliest animated title sequences and still among most amusing.</p>
        <p>The notion of title design as a profession, however, dates back to one film, "The Man With the Golden Arm" (1956), and one Hollywood graphic designer, Saul Bass. Two years earlier Mr. Bass had designed the poster for Otto Preminger's "Carmen Jones," and Preminger appropriated the poster image for the title sequence of the movie itself. For "The Man With the Golden Arm," starring Frank Sinatra as a Chicago poker dealer with a drug habit, Mr. Bass came up with a drawing that wedded movement to the abstractions for which he was known, all fitting together as a squarish crooked arm.</p>
        <p>Paired with Elmer Bernstein's jazz score, the logo was so arresting it substituted for the title of the film on the marquee of the Broadway theater where the movie had its premiere. Mr. Bass thus won a new on-screen credit -- "Main Titles by . . ." -- and went on to create bold designs for such Hitchcock films as "Vertigo," "Psycho" and "North by Northwest" and endlessly delirious cartoons for "Around the World in 80 Days," "It's a Mad, Mad, Mad, Mad World" and "The Seven Year Itch" (in which the "t" in "Itch" scratched itself).</p>
        <p>"I created a categorical activity," said Mr. Bass, now 71, in a recent interview. The activity quickly developed categories of its own: title sequences began telling "backstory" (as in "The Electric Horseman," where the titles recount the whole story of the main character's life up to the point where the movie begins), elevating some obscure object to the status of icon (photographs of farm families in "Bonnie and Clyde") or coining a potent metaphor (the slinky black cat in "A Walk on the Wild Side").</p>
        <p>But after a burst of wild experimentation in the 1960's -- when even Woody Allen, in "Bananas," punctuated each credit's appearance on screen with rifle shots and a lively Latin beat -- titles settled down for a period of dutiful serviceability, often becoming little more than words placed artfully over live action.</p>
        <p>"Titles slid out of fashion," said Mr. Bass, who took to designing corporate logos and even gas stations during this spell. "When directors began to understand how valuable they were, they reappropriated them. But directors have so much on their hands, they couldn't give titles the care and attention they need." In the 80's, even Mr. Bass went back to the drawing board, designing titles for "Big," "Broadcast News," "Goodfellas" and "War of the Roses" (in which what seem to be luxurious satin sheets turn out, retrospectively, to be a hankie -- into which Danny DeVito blows his nose).</p>
        <p>One of the most successful title design companies is the New York concern R/Greenberg Associates, which doubles as a production company for commercials and special effects. Located in a 50,000-foot Bauhaus-style office building in the heart of Hell's Kitchen and specializing in inventing computer-aided equipment to overcome technical limitations, R/Greenberg has created several unforgettable sequences over the last 15 years: "Superman," the ominous shadows cast by letters in "The Untouchables," the staccato black-and-white dancers of "Dirty Dancing," the heaven-tossed baby of "The World According to Garp" and recently, the time-lapse view of Manhattan for "The Bonfire of the Vanities."</p>
        <p>Richard Greenberg's brother, Robert, a founder of the company, which has branched into digital image processing, said, "I'm looking forward to the first 3-D title sequence without glasses." Other title designers, however, are less sanguine. Pointing to Hollywood's current cost-cutting mood, they worry that their job will increasingly become little more than picking out an attractive typeface. "With the change of viewpoint on budgets, many things considered valuable to a film but a luxury are being eliminated," said Mr. Perri. That may not, however, be altogether bad: economy often presents opportunities. As Mr. Perri went on to observe, "Maybe titles will return to storytelling, instead of glitz and effect."  FILM Judith Shulevitz writes about film for Mirabella and The Village Voice.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Judith Shulevitz writes about film for Mirabella and The Village Voice.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
