<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the 30's, Black Swing Was Golden</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="463261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="CLASSICAL VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLASSICAL MUSIC</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LUNCEFORD, JIMMIE, ORCHESTRA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHIFF, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HENDERSON, FLETCHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEBB, CHICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HINES, EARL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BASIE, COUNT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELLINGTON, DUKE (EDWARD KENNEDY ELLINGTON)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D7173BF93BA15754C0A967958260" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the 30's, Black Swing Was Golden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Schiff;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHIFF, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American music always looks for its past in all the wrong places. The latest instance is an attempt to revive symphonies from the "Golden Age," the 1930's. It's a noble effort to dredge up these waterlogged vessels in search of sunken treasures. But except for Copland's Short Symphony, a 24-karat nugget, this Golden Age yields only fool's gold.</p>
        <p>A symphony is more than a display of orchestral know-how and developmental skill; it's a vision of human experience on an epic scale, like a novel. Though skillfully written, at times even stirring, the "Great American Symphonies" of Hanson, Harris, Piston and others were not visions of experience, but escape routes from it. Lacking the intensity and drama of Faulkner or even Steinbeck, they depict America as a Wild West Eden (plenty of cowboys, no Indians) or a prepubescent Playland. Howard Hanson's Second Symphony, a work of consummate, terrifying professionalism, is a rhapsody in cotton candy, emotionally gaga, and seductively so. Roy Harris's Third Symphony endows prairie tunes with spiritual authority through Baroque devices of chorale and fugue, Beethovenian fate motifs and Brahmsian pedal points. This is as good as it gets; your heart pounds at times, but it's still B-movie territory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American music always looks for its past in all the wrong places. The latest instance is an attempt to revive symphonies from the "Golden Age," the 1930's. It's a noble effort to dredge up these waterlogged vessels in search of sunken treasures. But except for Copland's Short Symphony, a 24-karat nugget, this Golden Age yields only fool's gold.</p>
        <p>A symphony is more than a display of orchestral know-how and developmental skill; it's a vision of human experience on an epic scale, like a novel. Though skillfully written, at times even stirring, the "Great American Symphonies" of Hanson, Harris, Piston and others were not visions of experience, but escape routes from it. Lacking the intensity and drama of Faulkner or even Steinbeck, they depict America as a Wild West Eden (plenty of cowboys, no Indians) or a prepubescent Playland. Howard Hanson's Second Symphony, a work of consummate, terrifying professionalism, is a rhapsody in cotton candy, emotionally gaga, and seductively so. Roy Harris's Third Symphony endows prairie tunes with spiritual authority through Baroque devices of chorale and fugue, Beethovenian fate motifs and Brahmsian pedal points. This is as good as it gets; your heart pounds at times, but it's still B-movie territory.</p>
        <p>Ironically, the 30's were indeed a golden age of American music -- the age of big-band swing created by black musicians in Harlem, Chicago and Kansas City. But out of snobbery, racism or some misplaced notion of seriousness, the guardians of high art never count this repertory as part of American music. No wonder we don't have a past.</p>
        <p>While the cognoscenti keep their heads in the clouds, lesser mortals can enjoy the riches of black swing, for too long available only to jazz discophiles, thanks to an abundance of reissues on CD. For the last month I have been wallowing in just part of a 100-disk series called Chronological Classics, released by Qualiton Imports. With Albert Murray's classic "Stomping the Blues" and Gunther Schuller's encyclopedic "Swing Era" as my guides, I have journeyed to the mother lode of American music.</p>
        <p>The biggest revelation has been the Jimmie Lunceford Orchestra. It was considered the swingingest band in Harlem, and you can immediately hear why. The famous two-beat bounce is light, tight and irresistible. But the music does far more than is needed to keep the dancers jumping. Sy Oliver's arrangements are packed with harmonic daring and instrumental invention, and the ensemble playing has an elegant precision matched only by the Cleveland Orchestra performing Haydn.</p>
        <p>When I play Lunceford's 1934 recording of Oliver's "Swinging Uptown" for musicologists, composers or jazz musicians, their jaws drop in astonishment (not a reaction I get to Hanson or Harris). The saxophones shape the most sinuous phrase as one; each chorus intensifies the rhythm effortlessly, driving but never pushing the tempo, and the saxophone soloist, Willie Smith, turns a simple rhythmic figure into an Olympic event. The total effect is one of dizzy sophistication verging on bliss -- like no other music I know.</p>
        <p>And yet "Swinging Uptown" reveals just one aspect of the Lunceford repertory, which ranged from zany novelty numbers like "I'm Nutty About Screwy Music," executed with a sublimely sly delicacy, to miniature tone poems like "Organ Grinder's Swing" and "Uptown Blues," which rival the moody masterpieces of Ellington. The Lunceford Orchestra encompassed the full range of black American -- and just plain American -- experiences, from the most intimate blues to the peppiest pop tune, without making a false move. It was the musical counterpart to Fred Astaire.</p>
        <p>The dimensions of this true golden age begin to appear when you move from Lunceford to Fletcher Henderson to Chick Webb to Earl Hines and Count Basie. And finally to Ellington. Swing was not a genre or a style but a cultural constellation. It was also not just dance music, but pop music, novelty music, educate-the-audience music, virtuoso show-off music and art music -- even, as in Ellington's "Diminuendo and Crescendo in Blue," High Art music. It functioned, therefore, precisely like the "classical music" of the 18th century, whose style could link a simple peasant dance, a court entertainment, a symphony or a Mass.</p>
        <p>It is hard to imagine how this music of wit, grace and sophistication flourished in the depths of a Depression that was particularly brutal on blacks. Seen in this context, the music seems heroic in its capacity for "laughing at life" (as Billie Holiday intoned it) and exposes all too painfully the fake heroism of the Great American Symphony.</p>
        <p>Why revive that paltry handful of kitsch epics and yet deny a legacy of abundant creativity and emotional scope? Certain prestigious genres seem to have a monopoly on cultural value. Yet in the music of the 30's, it was precisely the high genre of the symphony that served up regressive and nostalgic illusions, while the best works of the big bands (and the best popular songs) had the elegance, vitality and riskiness that we seek in high art. There's more life, and more music, in "Moten Swing" or "A Foggy Day" than in all the Great American Symphonies put together.</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL VIEW David Schiff is a composer on the faculty of Reed College in Portland, Ore., and the author of "The Music of Elliott Carter."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Schiff is a composer on the faculty of Reed College in Portland, Ore., and the author of "The Music of Elliott Carter."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
