<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peale Remembered for Instilling Hope and Peace</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="659011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEATHS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEATHS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEALE, NORMAN VINCENT (REV) (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINFELS, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEALE, NORMAN VINCENT (REV) (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINFELS, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DD1638F933A05751C1A965958260" item-length="395" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peale Remembered for Instilling Hope and Peace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER STEINFELS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEINFELS, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The three children of the Rev. Dr. Norman Vincent Peale offered poignant recollections of their father at his funeral yesterday, which ended with his widow, Ruth Stafford Peale, announcing her determination to wage a national campaign in behalf of positive thinking.</p>
        <p>Speaking from the pulpit of Marble Collegiate Church in Manhattan, the church where Dr. Peale was pastor from 1932 to 1984, Mrs. Peale said she would blanket the country with copies of her husband's best-seller, "The Power of Positive Thinking."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The three children of the Rev. Dr. Norman Vincent Peale offered poignant recollections of their father at his funeral yesterday, which ended with his widow, Ruth Stafford Peale, announcing her determination to wage a national campaign in behalf of positive thinking.</p>
        <p>Speaking from the pulpit of Marble Collegiate Church in Manhattan, the church where Dr. Peale was pastor from 1932 to 1984, Mrs. Peale said she would blanket the country with copies of her husband's best-seller, "The Power of Positive Thinking."</p>
        <p>Among the 1,900 people drawn to the church for the funeral service, 700 of them watching closed-circuit television in adjoining rooms, was Richard M. Nixon. The former President was a friend of Dr. Peale for many years.</p>
        <p>Dr. Peale died on Christmas Eve after suffering a stroke earlier this month. He was 95.</p>
        <p>At the funeral, the Rev. Arthur Caliandro, Dr. Peale's successor as senior minister at the church, read passages from the Gospel of John and the Epistle to the Romans, interwoven with reminders of Dr. Peale's ability to instill hope, peace and prayerfulness in lives full of turmoil. Remembering the Humor</p>
        <p>Dr. Peale's two daughters, Margaret Peale Everett and Elizabeth Peale Allen, and his son, John Stafford Peale, spoke of their father's abundant energy, the small-town values that he had brought from his southern Ohio childhood and his "deep faith rooted in the belief that Jesus Christ can change lives."</p>
        <p>Dr. Peale's greatest challenge, Mrs. Everett said, was facing old age and particularly the physical decline and loss of speech in the last year because of Parkinson's disease. She recalled that when he was complimented on turning 90 four years ago, he had replied: "That's no big deal. It just means you're not dead yet."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Peale also recalled her husband's unpredictable humor, including his first words in the limousine after their wedding, "We had such a big crowd, it's too bad we couldn't take up a collection."</p>
        <p>"I've had a vision that if some way or other we could sweep this country with that simple book it might make a difference in this generation," Mrs. Peale said, proposing to place copies of "The Power of Positive Thinking" in churches, drug rehabilitation centers, small self-help groups and "on the desks of C.E.O.'s and middle management."</p>
        <p>Dr. Peale will be buried tomorrow in Pawling, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
