<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Starters</title>
    <meta content="16DINE$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1400987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aladin's Restaurant (Somerville, Nj)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Karla</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DD153CF935A25755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Starters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARLA COOK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cook, Karla</byline>
      <dateline>SOMERVILLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karla Cook reviews Aladin's Restaurant in Somerville, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE'S a modest proposal: Take every other fast food joint along the New Jersey Turnpike and turn it into an adaptation of Aladin's Restaurant. Lose the boring burgers with American cheese and serve falafel wrapped in pita with tahini sauce instead. Drop the fries; replace those gut expanders with kibbeh balls, delicate spinach pies or stuffed grape leaves. And deep-six the hot dogs; substitute Elie Chedid's delectable kebabs, mild sausage wraps or, for the spice-lovers, the spicy version of sausage called sujok.</p>
        <p>Wouldn't it be lovely? Good food with assertive flavors, and just as fast as a burger and fries. It's a dream. In the meantime, there is a Mediterranean oasis named for the young man (whose name is usually spelled Aladdin) who found the magic lamp, and I'm delighted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE'S a modest proposal: Take every other fast food joint along the New Jersey Turnpike and turn it into an adaptation of Aladin's Restaurant. Lose the boring burgers with American cheese and serve falafel wrapped in pita with tahini sauce instead. Drop the fries; replace those gut expanders with kibbeh balls, delicate spinach pies or stuffed grape leaves. And deep-six the hot dogs; substitute Elie Chedid's delectable kebabs, mild sausage wraps or, for the spice-lovers, the spicy version of sausage called sujok.</p>
        <p>Wouldn't it be lovely? Good food with assertive flavors, and just as fast as a burger and fries. It's a dream. In the meantime, there is a Mediterranean oasis named for the young man (whose name is usually spelled Aladdin) who found the magic lamp, and I'm delighted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chedid and his wife, Nada Chedid, opened the 80-seat Aladin's in mid-January after selling Evelyn's, a Lebanese restaurant in New Brunswick about three years ago. Mr. Chedid is at home in restaurants; he grew up under the feet of chefs at the upscale hotel his father managed in Beirut. He tried another path when he came to Rutgers in the mid-70's to earn his bachelor's and master's degrees in civil engineering, but kitchens were forever luring him. He worked weekends and summers at Bedminster Inn, where Lebanese specials occasionally supplemented a solid American menu. After graduation, he worked for several years in Saudi Arabia as a civil engineer, but eventually opened a Lebanese restaurant there. When their children reached school age, he and his wife returned to New Jersey -- and continued their restaurant careers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chedid's appetizers are the stars of his menu, and that's a good thing, since the number of appetizers and their quality often indicate hospitality in homes in the Middle East. The hummus was a familiar basic, and the baba gannouj, with charcoal-grilled eggplant, was better than most. The fattoush, a salad with lettuce, tomato, cucumber, parsley and mint made hearty with toasted pita bread, was a welcome sight and taste, with its fresh dressing of lemon juice, Lebanese olive oil and sumac. The tabbouleh was magnificent. More parsley than bulgur, it contained the typical mix of onions, mint, lemon, olive oil and tomatoes, but from there it ascended on a dash of allspice to a place all its own.</p>
        <p>Then there are the lesser-known dishes, which will draw me again and again. The eggplant salad was summer on a fork, baba gannouj without the tahini and left in beguilingly smoky chunks of grilled eggplant and tomatoes, chopped white onions and parsley dressed with the standard lemon juice and olive oil.</p>
        <p>The awaniss, chicken livers with onions and mushrooms, could turn Colonel Sanders's head -- each tender morsel fork-tender and made sweet with onions and green pepper, earthy with mushrooms, then balanced with a sauce of red wine, allspice, cumin and white pepper. The ful medames, an Egyptian dish of slow-simmered fava beans, came spiced with crushed garlic and dressed with chopped parsley and mint, olive oil and lemon, but suffered only a little without the traditional hard-boiled egg cut into quarters. The makanek, which are mild, dry Lebanese beef and lamb sausages dotted with pine nuts, were earthy, slightly dry and delectable, but my favorite was the sujok, a hot version that left a spicy chorus of remembrance in my mouth.</p>
        <p>Another favorite of my table was house-made shanklish, a small platter of light brown dice of aged feta cheese mixed with fresh thyme and cayenne, then garnished with tomatoes, onions and olive oil. Salty and mysterious, it seemed as old and fascinating as its region, and as addictive as the beet-red pickled turnips with the bite of garlic and the accompanying Armenian cucumber pickles. Lebanese olives were equally delicious, each orb holding the essence of chili pepper and vinegar.</p>
        <p>The entrees list is less rewarding, each dish with its side of plain, rather taste-free rice, though the Frenched green beans cooked with onion, garlic and tomatoes would be a nice addition to the mezze menu. Each entree comes with a choice of soup or salad; skip the thin lentil soup and pick the plain green salad with an appetite-perking dressing of olive oil and lemon. Though the filet mignon and the cutlets of lamb, pork and chicken are still on my list to try, I can recommend only two selections that either don't replicate or fail to meet the quality of the appetizers. Pick either the grape leaves stuffed with lamb and rice or the mixed grill, which is a trio of kebabs: lamb, chicken and a mixture of ground beef and lamb with chopped parsley (think meat loaf on a skewer) called kafta. Better yet, order the grape leaves and the kebabs minus the rice, plus a bowl of the green beans. The table will be full of delicious foods and you will feast.</p>
        <p>Of the small collection of desserts, baklava is the standout, with its crisp and soft layers of phyllo alternating with coarsely ground nuts and drizzled with syrup flavored with rosewater; the ma'moud (cookies stuffed with either a walnut or pistachio mixture) are overwhelmed with rosewater, and the texture of the shredded pastry in the k'nafi suffers greatly from a rewarming in the microwave.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Chedid is providing much-needed balance of cuisine in south central New Jersey. After only five months in business, Aladin's has found its strength in appetizers, the first of three essential culinary elements of a balanced restaurant. It will be exciting to see this menu grow stronger in entrees and desserts in the coming months.</p>
        <p>Aladin's Restaurant  45 West Main Street, Somerville  (908) 722-9001  GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Spartan and cool, with plenty of seating.</p>
        <p>SERVICE -- Bemused yet capable.</p>
        <p>SMOKING -- No smoking.</p>
        <p>WINE LIST -- Bring your own.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- All appetizers, all kebabs, grape leaves, baklava.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers, $2.75 to $6.50; entrees, $13 to $22; desserts, $3.50 to $4.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Tuesdays through Thursdays, 11:30 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 11:30 a.m. to 10:30 p.m. and Sundays, 2:30 to 9 p.m. Lunch is served until 3 p.m. Mondays through Saturdays.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- Visa, Mastercard, but no American Express.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Suggested, but there was ample seating available on our visits.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- The restaurant is on one floor.</p>
        <p>RATINGS -- Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent,  Extraordinary.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
