<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Typewriter Seized in Bombing Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="598749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORLD TRADE CENTER (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOMBS AND BOMB PLOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TYPEWRITERS AND TYPEWRITING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLOSIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LIBERATION ARMY FIFTH BATTALION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TABOR, MARY B W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KUNSTLER, WILLIAM M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELGABROWNY, IBRAHIM A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Typewriters and Typewriting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Secretaries, Stenographers and Typists</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DA1139F93AA15750C0A965958260" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Typewriter Seized in Bombing Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARY B. W. TABOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TABOR, MARY B W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Law-enforcement officials searching for clues in the bombing of the World Trade Center seized a typewriter and computer disks from the apartment of one of the five men arrested after the blast, the man's lawyer said yesterday.</p>
        <p>William M. Kunstler, who is representing Ibrahim A. Elgabrowny, said the equipment was confiscated shortly after the F.B.I. arrested his client earlier this month. Mr. Elgabrowny, 42, is being held without bail on charges of interfering with Federal agents who arrived to search his apartment in connection with the bombing investigation. Though Mr. Elgabrowny was not charged directly in the bombing, law-enforcement officials consider him a suspect and say he is associated with others charged in the blast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Law-enforcement officials searching for clues in the bombing of the World Trade Center seized a typewriter and computer disks from the apartment of one of the five men arrested after the blast, the man's lawyer said yesterday.</p>
        <p>William M. Kunstler, who is representing Ibrahim A. Elgabrowny, said the equipment was confiscated shortly after the F.B.I. arrested his client earlier this month. Mr. Elgabrowny, 42, is being held without bail on charges of interfering with Federal agents who arrived to search his apartment in connection with the bombing investigation. Though Mr. Elgabrowny was not charged directly in the bombing, law-enforcement officials consider him a suspect and say he is associated with others charged in the blast.</p>
        <p>It could not be learned yesterday whether there was any link between the typewriter and disks and a letter that the authorities believe sets out the thinking and demands of the suspects.</p>
        <p>But the authorities say they have "incontrovertible" evidence to prove that the letter from the Liberation Army Fifth Battalion, which claims responsibility for the bombing and attributes the action to deep resentment against United States policy in the Middle East, is authentic and tied to the men. Debate Over Letter</p>
        <p>Mr. Kunstler disputed any possible link between the letter and Mr. Elgabrowny's belongings. "If they had matched the typewriter up, wouldn't they have indicted him for the bombing?" Mr. Kunstler asked.</p>
        <p>So far, four people have been charged with taking part in the bombing: Mahmud Abohalima, 33; Mohammed A. Salameh, 25; Nidal A. Ayyad, 25, and Bilall Alkaisi, 27. Mr. Elgabrowny is being held on separate charges, including possession of forged passports, and while officials say he is connected with the bombing, they have refused to disclose what evidence they may have as proof.</p>
        <p>All the men, through court appearances or their lawyers' statements, have maintained their innocence.</p>
        <p>The letter, while providing clues to a possible motive for the bombing, has prompted debate among law-enforcement officials and Middle East experts.</p>
        <p>Some Federal investigators and police officials yesterday discounted the group's claim, stated in the letter, that they have "more than 150 suicidal soldiers" ready to attack other United States civilian and military targets. The letter said that unless the United States severed relations with Israel and met other demands involving Middle East policy, additional attacks would be carried out.</p>
        <p>"There's no reason to believe that threat is real," said one top investigator. "We can try to prepare for everything, but we can't lock up the city."  Important Evidence</p>
        <p>Some Federal authorities said yesterday that they were unaware of specific evidence directly linking any of the suspects to the letter. They said they knew investigators considered the letter to be "extremely important." But they could not confirm, as other law-enforcement officials had, that the writer or writers had been identified. The reasons for this disparity were not immediately clear.</p>
        <p>Several top law-enforcement officials in Washington said they had never heard of the Liberation Army Fifth Battalion. A database run by the Rand Corporation in Santa Monica, Calif., had no listing for such a group.</p>
        <p>Middle East experts have raised questions about the tone and wording of the letter as well.</p>
        <p>Signed AL-FAREEK AL-ROKN, Abu Bakr El-Makee, which translates loosely from Arabic to mean "The Lieut. General Abu Bakr, of Mecca," the letter appears to be from a militant, secular group, not religious fundamentalists, said As'ad AbuKhalil, scholar in residence at the Middle East Institute in Washington. Authorities have said all five suspects are considered fundamentalists.</p>
        <p>Dr. AbuKhalil said that while the letter was signed Abu Bakr, suggesting a possible link to the Brooklyn mosque where the fundamentalist cleric Sheik Omar Abdul Rahman preached and several suspects worshiped, the name is common in the Middle East and was likely used as a nom de guerre.</p>
        <p>The letter was sent to The New York Times four days after the Feb. 26 bombing that killed six people, injured more than 1,000 and closed the Trade Center's 110-story twin towers for weeks. It was immediately turned over to authorities, who have linked it to one of the five men in custody. Lawyers Deny Any Link</p>
        <p>But attorneys for the suspects were quick to distance their clients from the group claiming responsibility for the bombing.</p>
        <p>"I talked to Mr. Elgabrowny today and he said he's never heard of this group," said Ronald L. Kuby, who is co-counsel with Mr. Kunstler, referring to the Fifth Battalion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kunstler said that in addition to forged passports, the search of Mr. Elgabrowny's apartment produced a typewriter, along with dozens of cassette tapes, computer disks, books, construction blueprints and other documents.</p>
        <p>Jesse Berman, who is representing Mr. Abohalima, also denied that his client had any connection with the liberation front.</p>
        <p>Robert Precht, the lawyer for Mr. Salameh, said his client told him that he knew nothing about a letter.</p>
        <p>The authorities say they are still searching for a sixth person in connection with the bombing. That person is said to be a former roommate of Mr. Salameh, who is accused of renting a van used to carry the bomb.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
