<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The F.A.A.'s No-Bids Proposal</title>
    <meta content="09FRI2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/09/opinion/09FRI2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1276473"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Aviation Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lockheed Martin Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Transportation Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mineta, Norman Y (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Aviation Administration</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Lockheed Martin Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Raytheon Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">The Boeing Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">International Business Machines Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wald, Matthew</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jackson, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E3DC173AF93AA35750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="486" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The F.A.A.'s No-Bids Proposal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial opposes Federal Aviation Administration decision to forgo its usual competitive bidding procedures and simply designate Lockheed Martin Corp to upgrade computer system crucial to nation's air traffic control network; says this choice is open to debate on the merits and raises apparent conflict of interest, given that Transportation Sec Norman Mineta is former Lockheed vice president and Michael Jackson, who is expected to become his deputy, was executive of Lockheed subsidiary</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A competitive and transparent bidding process for government contracts is an important means of ensuring that public needs are met in the most cost-effective manner by the most qualified enterprise. Thus it is disturbing that the Federal Aviation Administration, as reported this week by Matthew  Wald of The Times, is proposing to forgo its usual competitive bidding procedures and instead simply designate the Lockheed Martin Corporation to upgrade a computer system crucial to the nation's air traffic control network. The choice is open to debate on the merits and raises an apparent conflict of interest, given that Transportation Secretary Norman Mineta is a former Lockheed vice president,  and the man expected to become his deputy, Michael Jackson, was an executive of a Lockheed subsidiary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A competitive and transparent bidding process for government contracts is an important means of ensuring that public needs are met in the most cost-effective manner by the most qualified enterprise. Thus it is disturbing that the Federal Aviation Administration, as reported this week by Matthew  Wald of The Times, is proposing to forgo its usual competitive bidding procedures and instead simply designate the Lockheed Martin Corporation to upgrade a computer system crucial to the nation's air traffic control network. The choice is open to debate on the merits and raises an apparent conflict of interest, given that Transportation Secretary Norman Mineta is a former Lockheed vice president,  and the man expected to become his deputy, Michael Jackson, was an executive of a Lockheed subsidiary.</p>
        <p>The Transportation Department insists that there is no actual conflict. Mr. Mineta has removed himself from participating in the F.A.A.'s upcoming decision on whether to forgo competitive bidding and all other matters affecting Lockheed. The agency says it settled on the company before Mr. Mineta had even been tapped to serve in President Bush's cabinet.</p>
        <p>Still, the impression that shortcuts are being taken in Lockheed's favor will further erode public confidence in the F.A.A.'s exploration of new ways to ameliorate gridlock in the skies. The contract, worth hundreds of millions of dollars, is to rewrite 30-year-old software code and replace computers that process radar data and track planes at high altitudes.</p>
        <p>Raytheon, a Lockheed competitor, has filed an objection to the agency's proposal, arguing that it is  qualified to bid on the project. Boeing has also  expressed disappointment at not being given a chance to make its pitch. The F.A.A. must now consider these companies' objections, and presumably gauge the issue of appearances, before deciding whether to alter its plans and open the process.</p>
        <p>The agency believed that competitive bidding was unnecessary because of what it considers Lockheed's unique familiarity with the existing computer system. Further, Lockheed recently delivered upgrades to other equipment used at air traffic centers on time and under budget. On the other hand, Lockheed now owns most of the company that served as the main contractor on an earlier failed effort to automate the agency's systems, so its track record is hardly unblemished.</p>
        <p>The F.A.A. argues that because the new software's ''open'' design will enable it to work with features that are developed later, the Lockheed deal will not preclude other companies from participating in the modernization of the air traffic control network. It also suggests that there is no time to evaluate competing proposals, as I.B.M. will stop servicing the current computers after 2008. Surely there are ways to deal with that contingency without abandoning fair bidding. It may well be that Lockheed is the most suitable contractor, but it should prevail on the merits in an open competition.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
