<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Delhi Journal; TV Comes In on a Dish, and India Gobbles It Up</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="483569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CENSORSHIP</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABLE TELEVISION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CABLE NEWS NETWORK</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MUSIC TELEVISION NETWORKS INC (MTV)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GARGAN, EDWARD A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEHROTRA, RAJIV</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DE1330F93AA15753C1A967958260" item-length="1084" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Delhi Journal; TV Comes In on a Dish, and India Gobbles It Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD A. GARGAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GARGAN, EDWARD A</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Oct. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Inder Kumar Gujral, former Ambassador to Moscow, former Foreign Minister, impeccably turned out in an ivory safari suit and delicate black loafers, stroked his white goatee with his hand, coughed slightly and then admitted that he did not watch MTV compulsively.</p>
        <p>"Occasionally," he confessed, "but not all the time."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Inder Kumar Gujral, former Ambassador to Moscow, former Foreign Minister, impeccably turned out in an ivory safari suit and delicate black loafers, stroked his white goatee with his hand, coughed slightly and then admitted that he did not watch MTV compulsively.</p>
        <p>"Occasionally," he confessed, "but not all the time."</p>
        <p>Maybe Mr. Gujral isn't glued to the gyrations of Madonna, Prince and Fine Young Cannibals, but increasing numbers of Indians are basking in the rays of rock videos and uncensored television for the first time.</p>
        <p>On rooftops across New Delhi, and in Bombay, Calcutta, Madras and countless other cities and towns, satellite dishes are transforming the way in which Indians see the world.</p>
        <p>The very rich prominently display their very own dish on their roof. But most urbanites, India's growing middle classes, are plugging into the new world of television through rapidly proliferating cable services.</p>
        <p>"The gulf war was the turning point, followed by the Moscow coup," Mr. Gujral said. "  War Spurs the Craze</p>
        <p>For decades, Indians have been restricted to the fare served by state television, known as Doordarshan, a diet of tedious discussions by Government bureaucrats, ancient Hindi movies, generous amounts of singing and dancing, and news programs often distinguished by their heavy censorship and age.</p>
        <p>But during the Persian Gulf war, India, particularly urban India, was swept up in the Cable News Network craze. Satellite dish manufacturers worked overtime to provide equipment to hotels and apartment buildings and many people spent hours riveted to the first war seen live in this country. But after the war, the repetitiveness of CNN and its concentration on American news caused many Indian viewers to drift away from the American network.</p>
        <p>This fall, new channels began appearing on Indian televisions -- MTV rock videos, an all-day sports channel and, making its debut earlier this month, the BBC's new World Service Television, a mix of news and entertainment.</p>
        <p>All of this is possible because of AsiaSat, a satellite now positioned over Asia that is available to television broadcasters who wish to reach a audience estimated at nearly three billion people, and the new programs are being beamed up and back down courtesy of the Hong Kong-based Star TV. For India, a nation long padlocked to the Government's version of reality, the candy-store variety of programming has brought a poorly contained giddiness.</p>
        <p>"The younger generation is seeing a lot more," said Anita Luthra, a housewife in the affluent Maharini Bagh neighborhood of the capital who recently subscribed to a local cable network offering the new satellite channels. "It's definitely making a difference. They get to see Western movies, things we never had as children."  State's Grip Is Broken</p>
        <p>Although the Indian Government has tried to impose rigid censorship on all forms of visual productions, not only movies, but also popular news videos that are sold monthly in cassette form like magazines, the new satellite technology has broken the state's grip on the living-room tube.</p>
        <p>Young entrepreneurs are sinking their life savings into satellite dishes and spreading cables through neighborhoods as they wire up homes and apartments for the new service. Dish manufacturers are delirious at the new opportunities.</p>
        <p>The rush of satellite technology has overwhelmed India's glacial bureaucracy and charged into uncharted, and unregulated, waters. And no one is waiting for the Government to act.</p>
        <p>"All of us are new in this," said Kalidas D. Khanna, one of New Delhi's new breed of cable operators, who number more than 100 so far. "The cable business is new in India. Most of us don't know what we are doing. There is no law. It is such an infant industry."</p>
        <p>Mr. Khanna, who until now has earned his living by exporting cotton sweaters to Britain, bought his dish last spring and put it on the roof of his house. With a converter box, a couple of videocassette recorders and lots of cable, he began running wires into his neighbor's houses, down the block, and eventually into neighborhoods a mile away. The city government says that no wires can cross public roads, but Mr. Khanna and his competitors across the city are little troubled by this decree.</p>
        <p>"It's not such a hard and fast rule," he said. "We can go under the road, through a culvert. We've taken the cable overhead where the trees are shady."  Customers Are Demanding</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Khanna has 275 subscribers, all paying him 150 rupees a month, about $6 at the official rate of exchange. Because cable operators are free to provide whatever mix of programming they wish, he offers recent Hindi movies and cartoons in addition to the satellite channels."</p>
        <p>"People are very demanding," he said of his customers. "They want the best."</p>
        <p>Like many operators, Mr. Khanna does not have the ability to offer all four satellite channels and videos on his cables. But the clamor of his subscribers is forcing him to replace all his cables with thicker ones capable of carrying more programming. As it is, he spends a lot of time placating subscribers who call him at all hours of the night to switch channels or to change the movie.</p>
        <p>"If we have the sports channel on and someone calls and wants to watch MTV, we'll change it," he said. "Sometimes things go really wrong. The night Rajiv Ghandi died, my receiver went out of business. Imagine that. We couldn't get CNN at all. I was on the phone for seven hours telling people I was trying to fix it."</p>
        <p>Among those cashing in on the new thirst for foreign programs is Rajiv Mehrotra, a founder of Shyam Antenna and Telecommunications Systems, the largest manufacturer of television satellite dishes in India. He began by selling small dishes to villages across India so they could receive state television, but now most of his production is geared for the growing cable industry.</p>
        <p>"People obviously want more than they had," Mr. Mehrotra said. "First there was one channel, then two, now six. People want nine channels now. It's precisely the same as the United States 30 years ago."</p>
        <p>Mr. Mehrotra estimated that 100,000 homes are now wired for cable in the capital. "Bombay is much more," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gujral, comfortably settled in a leather chair before an enormous Sony television recently wired for cable, said: "A new challenge is on us. I am not sure of those who feel that shutting out the world is the way. There's no going back."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
