<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The President Is Right on Israel</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="474340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOVIET JEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND EMIGRATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFUGEES AND EXPATRIATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISRAELI SETTLEMENTS (OCCUPIED TERRITORIES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHAMIR, YITZHAK (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDE113AF934A2575AC0A967958260" item-length="558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The President Is Right on Israel</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush is wisely standing firm in urging Congress to delay action on Israel's request for $10 billion in loan guarantees to resettle Soviet Jews. His request has drawn fierce rhetorical fire from the Israeli Government of Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir and its American supporters, and an Israeli Cabinet minister offensively characterized the President as a liar and an anti-Semite.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush is serving America's best interests, and Israel's too, by making a successful peace conference his top Middle East priority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush is wisely standing firm in urging Congress to delay action on Israel's request for $10 billion in loan guarantees to resettle Soviet Jews. His request has drawn fierce rhetorical fire from the Israeli Government of Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir and its American supporters, and an Israeli Cabinet minister offensively characterized the President as a liar and an anti-Semite.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush is serving America's best interests, and Israel's too, by making a successful peace conference his top Middle East priority.</p>
        <p>Soviet Jews are not really the issue here. The U.S. and Western Europe, which pressed long and hard for the right of these Jews to emigrate, recognize an obligation to help Israel absorb them. The four-month delay Mr. Bush seeks would not jeopardize continued immigration. Its only direct consequence would be higher borrowing cost, and the Administration has hinted it might compensate for that with additional aid.</p>
        <p>The showdown is really about the Shamir Government's policy of rapidly and provocatively expanding Jewish settlement in the occupied West Bank, Gaza Strip and Golan Heights. This policy directly compromises both the atmosphere of the conference and the geographic possibilities for trading land for peace.</p>
        <p>A succession of U.S. Administrations has opposed Israeli settlements in the occupied territories. And a succession of Israeli Governments has built them anyway. But Mr. Shamir's present Government, the most right-wing in Israeli history, has been particularly zealous on the settlements issue. The Bush Administration believes that Israel violated, at least in spirit, past pledges not to use U.S. loan guarantees to finance settlements. And almost every time Secretary of State James Baker travels to Israel, he has been greeted by a new crop of settlers.</p>
        <p>Construction plans already approved by Israel's hard-line Housing Minister, Ariel Sharon, would double the Jewish population of the occupied territories within a year. At that rate, questions like land for peace or Palestinian autonomy could become moot even before a peace conference is concluded.</p>
        <p>The conference, if it proceeds, will be a historic achievement. Thanks to Mr. Bush, Mr. Baker and American success in Desert Storm, Israel has a chance to achieve what it has sought since its creation: direct talks with Arab neighbors on recognition and peace. Israel now has to recognize the need to negotiate with representative Palestinians.</p>
        <p>America's enhanced stature throughout the region, a product of Desert Storm, will be tested repeatedly at the peace conference. The U.S. will need to lean on Arabs and Israelis alike to reach compromises. Further Israeli settlements would prejudice the possibility of such compromises. Financing them with U.S. dollars would prejudice America's peacemaking role.</p>
        <p>Understandably, Israel would like to pre-empt any U.S. pressure by locking up a commitment to five years of loan guarantees before the conference begins. Wisely, Mr. Bush would rather have Israel enter the conference knowing that its posture could affect the Congressional vote.</p>
        <p>Using U.S. financial leverage to nudge along a promising peace process amounts neither to duplicity nor anti-Semitism. The President deserves credit, not abuse, for spending his political capital in the cause of Mideast peace.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
