<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>President of FMC Gets Chairman, Chief Posts</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="474305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS PEOPLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FMC CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERG, ERIC N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURT, ROBERT N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALOTT, ROBERT H</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS PEOPLE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DC143BF934A2575AC0A967958260" item-length="307" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>President of FMC Gets Chairman, Chief Posts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC N. BERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERG, ERIC N</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The FMC Corporation, the big Chicago-based maker of chemicals, machinery and military systems, said yesterday that it had named Robert N. Burt chairman and chief executive, effective Nov. 1. Mr. Burt, 53 years old, who has been president of FMC since March 1990, succeeds Robert H. Malott, who is stepping down as chairman because he is about to reach the company's retirement age of 65.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview yesterday, Mr. Burt said rebuilding FMC's balance sheet would be one of his main goals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The FMC Corporation, the big Chicago-based maker of chemicals, machinery and military systems, said yesterday that it had named Robert N. Burt chairman and chief executive, effective Nov. 1. Mr. Burt, 53 years old, who has been president of FMC since March 1990, succeeds Robert H. Malott, who is stepping down as chairman because he is about to reach the company's retirement age of 65.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview yesterday, Mr. Burt said rebuilding FMC's balance sheet would be one of his main goals.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1980's, FMC added billions of dollars in debt to pay a special dividend to shareholders. Shareholders ended up with cash and stock worth roughly $137 for each share that had been worth $65.</p>
        <p>But the move left FMC with a considerably weaker balance sheet -- its net worth was eliminated -- and it has now fallen to Mr. Burt to pay down that debt. The company recently sold zero-coupon bonds that are helping save on cash and have been used to pay off some old high-interest junk bonds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burt also said he hoped to expand FMC internationally, stationing corporate vice presidents for the first time in Europe and Asia and focusing on selling less sophisticated but more affordable versions of the company's food-processing equipment. For example, he said, a less sophisticated version of the tomato processing machinery that the company sells to California farmers could be marketed to growers in Brazil, Chile and Spain. He also envisions selling packaging equipment to Asian food companies that is less complex than the equipment FMC sells to Nestle of Switzerland.</p>
        <p>A chemical engineering graduate of Princeton and a recipient of a Harvard M.B.A., Mr. Burt joined FMC in 1973. He has held executive positions throughout FMC's main operating groups. He and his family live in Wilmette, Ill., a Chicago suburb.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS PEOPLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
