<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Envoy in Mideast Peace Effort Says Israel Is Keeping Too Tight a Lid on Palestinians in Gaza</title>
    <meta content="25mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/25/international/middleeast/25mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1712273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myre, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfensohn, James D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfensohn, James D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EED9103FF936A15753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Envoy in Mideast Peace Effort Says Israel Is Keeping Too Tight a Lid on Palestinians in Gaza</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Envoy in Mideast Peace Effort Says Israel Is Keeping Too Tight a Lid on Palestinians in Gaza</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG MYRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myre, Greg</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Oct. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James D Wolfensohn, special envoy for nations active in Middle East peacemaking, says Israel has failed to ease restrictions on Palestinian movement in and out of Gaza Strip; says residents currently face greater difficulties in traveling than before Israel's withdrawal; criticism is contained in letter from Wolfensohn addressed to United Nations Secretary General Kofi Annan, and to United States, European Union and Russia; spokesman for Israeli foreign ministry cites need for security; Israeli and Palestinian officials say they hope to resume talks within week on Palestinian movement along Gaza's borders; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>James D. Wolfensohn, the special envoy for nations active in Middle East peacemaking, has criticized Israel for failing to ease restrictions on Palestinian movement into and out of the Gaza Strip, where residents currently face greater difficulties in traveling than before Israel's withdrawal.</p>
        <p>''The government of Israel, with its important security concerns, is loath to relinquish control, almost acting as though there has been no withdrawal,'' Mr. Wolfensohn wrote in a letter dated Oct. 17 and released to news organizations on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The envoy criticized Israel for failing to ease restrictions on Palestinian movement into and out of the Gaza Strip.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>James D. Wolfensohn, the special envoy for nations active in Middle East peacemaking, has criticized Israel for failing to ease restrictions on Palestinian movement into and out of the Gaza Strip, where residents currently face greater difficulties in traveling than before Israel's withdrawal.</p>
        <p>''The government of Israel, with its important security concerns, is loath to relinquish control, almost acting as though there has been no withdrawal,'' Mr. Wolfensohn wrote in a letter dated Oct. 17 and released to news organizations on Monday.</p>
        <p>The letter was addressed to the United Nations secretary general, Kofi Annan, and to the United States, the European Union and Russia.</p>
        <p>In the West Bank, Israeli troops shot dead two wanted Palestinians in a gun battle on Sunday night.</p>
        <p>One was Luay al-Saadi, a senior leader of Islamic Jihad, who Israel said was responsible for two suicide bombings and a shooting earlier this year that killed a total of 11 Israelis.</p>
        <p>The confrontation widened on Monday evening when Islamic Jihad fired several rockets from northern Gaza into southern Israel, calling the action an ''initial response.''</p>
        <p>Later, Israeli aircraft fired missiles and ground forces fired artillery shells at suspected Palestinian rocket-launching sites in northern Gaza. No injuries or damage were reported in those exchanges.</p>
        <p>The developments pointed to the fading of hopes that the Gaza withdrawal, completed on Sept. 12, would improve the atmosphere between the sides.</p>
        <p>In his letter, Mr. Wolfensohn also said the Palestinian Authority was plagued by ''internal fragmentation,'' which was harming its own cause.</p>
        <p>''The current combination of violence and turmoil is undermining the stability needed to induce private investors to bring their capital to the Palestinian economy,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfensohn noted that a few development projects in Gaza had begun, including repairs to the main north-south road inside Gaza, and construction on new housing and classrooms.</p>
        <p>''Time is short, and optimism is a fragile commodity,'' he wrote. If the parties involved ''miss this opportunity for change, we will regret it for the next decade.''</p>
        <p>Israel maintained a web of travel restrictions on Palestinians in Gaza before it withdrew.</p>
        <p>In the six weeks since, it has been even more difficult for Gaza residents to travel in any direction to Israel, to the West Bank or on to Egypt and the wider world.</p>
        <p>''Palestinians were hoping that the withdrawal would lead to improvements in their movements, but things have been deteriorating,'' said Ghassan Khatib, the Palestinian planning minister.</p>
        <p>The Rafah crossing point between southern Gaza and Egypt, the scene of chaos immediately after the Israeli pullout, has been closed for most of the past six weeks.</p>
        <p>Israel has proposed an alternative crossing nearby, which it would control, but it is not yet in operation.</p>
        <p>Before the Israeli withdrawal, about 6,500 Palestinians passed daily through the Erez crossing at the northern end of Gaza into Israel, mostly for work, according to Mr. Wolfensohn. The daily figure is now 100 or fewer, he said.</p>
        <p>There also has been a significant drop in the number of trucks crossing at Karni, where commercial goods enter and leave Gaza on its eastern border.</p>
        <p>Mark Regev, a spokesman for the Foreign Ministry, said Israel ''understands that the Palestinian economy has to grow in Gaza, but this has to be balanced with a need for security.''</p>
        <p>He said progress had been delayed by the turmoil on the Gaza-Egypt border and a recent Palestinian shooting attack in the West Bank that killed three young Israelis.</p>
        <p>''The Palestinians must also do more to help us, and that means they have to act against their extremists,'' Mr. Regev said.</p>
        <p>Both Israeli and Palestinian officials said they hoped to resume talks within a week on Palestinian movement along Gaza's borders.</p>
        <p>The shootout that killed Mr. Saadi, 26, came during a nighttime incursion by Israeli troops into Tulkarm. The Israeli military described him as the top Islamic Jihad leader in the northern West Bank, which has been the launching pad for the group's deadliest attacks in recent months.</p>
        <p>The Israeli military said soldiers approached a house in Tulkarm with the intent of arresting ''senior wanted Islamic Jihad terrorists,'' though the forces were not aware that Mr. Saadi was among them.</p>
        <p>The soldiers came under fire and shot dead one wanted Islamic Jihad member, Majed Askar, the military said.</p>
        <p>The troops then spotted a second gunman fleeing the house and shot him dead. Only afterward did the military learn it was Mr. Saadi, said a senior Israeli military officer, on the customary condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>The Israeli officer said Mr. Saadi had been in Israeli custody but was freed last year.</p>
        <p>The Palestinian leader, Mahmoud Abbas, condemned the Israeli raid, while Khaled al-Batsh, a top Islamic Jihad leader in Gaza, said the group ''will never keep silent, and the response will be harsh and tough.''</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Ariel Sharon said in February that Israel would refrain from incursions in Palestinian areas unless it faced the threat of attack. The military says actual and planned attacks have been on the rise, and it has carried out almost daily raids in the West Bank recently.</p>
        <p>More than 20 Palestinians were detained in the West Bank overnight, the Israeli military and Palestinian officials said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
