<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Misery Loves Company, City Smokers Should Like State's Law</title>
    <meta content="23SMOK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/23/nyregion/23SMOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1506598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industrial and Occupational Hazards</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Von Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFDB143FF930A15754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Misery Loves Company, City Smokers Should Like State's Law</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">If Misery Loves Company, City Smokers Should Like State's Law</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL von ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Von Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Smokers in New York State contemplate what they will do when state's ban on smoking in most bars, restaurants and public places goes into effect on July 24; smokers in New York City, which began its own ban in March, face tougher restrictions on their habit; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tina Kurtzhalts had just finished eating in a small bar and restaurant near Ithaca, N.Y., on Monday when she opened her purse, plucked out a cigarette, fingered her lighter and flicked.</p>
        <p>Sniffing the air, Alan Saikkonen, a patron at the next table, quickly turned to her. ''You can't smoke in here,'' he said curtly. ''There's not a restaurant in New York State you can smoke in anymore.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Wednesday, a tough new state antismoking law will begin, making it difficult to legally light a cigarette inside a bar or restaurant in the state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tina Kurtzhalts had just finished eating in a small bar and restaurant near Ithaca, N.Y., on Monday when she opened her purse, plucked out a cigarette, fingered her lighter and flicked.</p>
        <p>Sniffing the air, Alan Saikkonen, a patron at the next table, quickly turned to her. ''You can't smoke in here,'' he said curtly. ''There's not a restaurant in New York State you can smoke in anymore.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mrs. Kurtzhalts has until 12:01 a.m. tomorrow, when a tough new state antismoking law will begin, after which it will be easier to start a chinchilla farm in downtown Yonkers than to legally light a cigarette inside a bar or restaurant anywhere in New York State.</p>
        <p>To smokers in New York City who already feel abused by the smoking ban that began in the five boroughs in March, this may seem like old news. In fact, it is worse news, because the state law is tougher.</p>
        <p>For instance, the city law allows smoking in ''cigar bars'' where tobacco accounts for at least 10 percent of all revenue; in bars or restaurants that build small, separately ventilated smoking rooms; and in bars that have three or fewer owners and no employees. It also allows 25 percent of a bar or restaurant's outdoor seating to be reserved for smokers.</p>
        <p>Under the state law, tobacco bars and the 25-percent rule remain legal, but ventilated smoking rooms are illegal and owner-operated bars with no employees are out of luck.</p>
        <p>The only type of bar, it seems, where patrons can regularly smoke are ''membership associations'' -- a V.F.W. or American Legion outpost, maybe -- where all workers are volunteers and the bartender ''doesn't even have a tip jar,'' said Russell C. Sciandra, director of the Center for a Tobacco Free New York, which fought for the law.</p>
        <p>Though the antismoking laws will grow marginally tougher in New York City beginning tomorrow, the moods of thousands of smokers who live north of the Bronx seem destined to grow markedly darker. For the last several weeks, in a statewide replay of the emotion that played out among city residents in March, interviews with upstate residents revealed either outrage or gratitude toward Albany's politicians.</p>
        <p>''You know what this country is becoming?'' John Lacher, a construction foreman and regular smoker, asked Monday night from his perch in a bar in Nanuet, Rockland County. ''A communist state,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Joan Shaw, whose husband, Ron, owns Rascal's, a working-man's bar in Cayuga County, said she was furious about the law and predicted that it would hurt their business, if not kill it. ''It's the first time I ever called my assemblyman and my senator,'' she said.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, there was Josh McCormick, 47, an engineer from New City, who eats out about five nights a week. ''Secondary smoke is horrible and dangerous,'' Mr. McCormick said over a plate of spare ribs and a glass of lemonade.</p>
        <p>Some upstate business owners are fighting the new smoking law.</p>
        <p>In May and June, 300 or so upstate bar and restaurant owners turned off the State Lottery Division's Quick Draw machines in protest. The boycott cost the state $265,993 in lost revenue, said a spokeswoman for the lottery, Carolyn Hapeman.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the Empire State Restaurant and Tavern Association filed a federal lawsuit in the Northern District of New York to overturn the law. Scott Wexler, the group's executive director, said the suit argues that the state pre-empts existing federal law protecting workers from secondhand smoke. But in an interview yesterday, Mr. Wexler said he did not expect a court to rule on the matter before tomorrow, when the law takes effect.</p>
        <p>For most New York City residents who smoke, the new state law may feel more like insult than injury. But to a select few -- the owner of a small bar in the East Village, the members of the Iranian-Armenian Society in Queens -- it is a curse.</p>
        <p>At the Fish Bar on East Fifth Street in the East Village, John Ross, a co-owner who bartends for free, wondered what would come of his dark refuge where perhaps two of three patrons were smoking on Monday night. The city Health Department recently denied the Fish Bar an owner-operator exemption to the city's smoking ban.</p>
        <p>''It's just not right,'' Mr. Ross, from North Wales, said of the city and state laws. ''The idea was to save employees from secondhand smoke. Do I have any employees? No.''</p>
        <p>His is one of 13 city businesses, including the Iranian-Armenian Society, that have applied for exemptions to the city law and been denied. But with the state law looming, even the establishments that received exemptions, like the Polish German Club House in Queens, must either quickly jettison any salaried employees or face a smoke-free future.</p>
        <p>James Barrows, a Fish Bar patron who enjoyed chain-smoking over a beer on Monday night, said he had voted for Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg but now felt betrayed by him for launching the crusade toward a smokeless New York. But there is still one way for Mr. Barrows, a 30-year-old writer from Brooklyn, to evade the new law, he said.</p>
        <p>''Hoboken,'' he said, gesturing vaguely toward New Jersey. ''I'll be visiting Hoboken.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
