<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexico's North Is Election Battlefield</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="157843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLOUTHIER, MANUEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALINAS DE GORTARI, CARLOS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROHTER, LARRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D61131F933A05755C0A96E948260" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexico's North Is Election Battlefield</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROHTER, LARRY</byline>
      <dateline>MONTERREY, Mexico, June 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: An adage dating back to the days of the Mexican Revolution says ''change begins in the north.'' As Mexico's presidential campaign draws to a close, both the ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party and the opposition hope that saying again proves to be true.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: An adage dating back to the days of the Mexican Revolution says ''change begins in the north.'' As Mexico's presidential campaign draws to a close, both the ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party and the opposition hope that saying again proves to be true.</p>
        <p>An adage dating back to the days of the Mexican Revolution says ''change begins in the north.'' As Mexico's presidential campaign draws to a close, both the ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party and the opposition hope that saying again proves to be true.</p>
        <p>Since the race began eight months ago, no area outside the capital has been more hotly contested than Mexico's northern states. If the more pluralist and democratic Mexico promised by Carlos Salinas de Gortari, the ruling party's nominee, is to emerge, it will most likely do so first here in the northern tier, a land of wide-open spaces with a tradition of self-reliance.</p>
        <p>''Monterrey is, above all, a reaffirmation of individual creativity and personal enterprise,'' Mr. Salinas said tonight. He was burnishing the north's image of itself at a rally attended by thousands in the main plaza of Monterrey, Mexico's third largest city and capital of the pivotal industrial state of Nuevo Leon.</p>
        <p>''Monterrey is, and will continue to be, the decisive center of the social and economic transformation of our country,'' he said. More Open System Sought</p>
        <p>In some respects, the ''modern politics'' Mr. Salinas has made the centerpiece of his campaign have already begun taking shape across the north in spite of efforts by Mr. Salinas's own party, known as the PRI. Though the right-of-center National Action Party, or PAN, has yet to win statewide office even once, it has become a competitive force and established roots throughout the region.</p>
        <p>The north has always played a special role in the politics of contemporary Mexico and is expected do so again in the July 6 vote.</p>
        <p>Because of their proximity to the United States and its democratic institutions and higher standards of living and education, the six border states and five others that are also regarded as part of the region have been especially outspoken in demanding a more modern and open political and economic system.</p>
        <p>Store owners and farmers in Chihuahua, for example, are even more likely than their counterparts just across the border in Texas to be contemptuous of the meddling of bureaucrats in the capital. Intellectuals and middle-class matrons in Baja California Norte complain ceaselessly about prices, school curriculums and local officials imposed by a central Government they regard as remote and largely indifferent to their concerns.</p>
        <p>In return, many in the rest of Mexico regard northerners as excessively individualistic and overly influenced by and tolerant of the United States. Though many of the leaders of the Mexican Revolution were from the region, no northerner has been elected President in more than 50 years. Capitalizing on the Discontent</p>
        <p>Over the last five years, the PAN, whose leadership is primarily composed of northerners, has capitalized on the middle-class discontent in the region stemming from Mexico's deepening economic crisis and one-party rule. Promising an end to corruption and centralism, it has won mayoral races in several key northern and border cities, overcoming the PRI's 60-year control of the government bureaucracy and budget.</p>
        <p>Since 1985, the PAN has also mounted strong, and in some cases apparently successful, races for governor in the states of Chihuahua, Sonora, Nuevo Leon, Baja California Norte and Sinaloa. Charges of widespread electoral fraud and protests followed each of those elections, leaving a residue of ill feeling against the ruling party that the PAN has hoped will work to its advantage this year.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Salinas, dismissed by his many detractors as a technocrat with unproven political skills, has managed to outflank the opposition on several fronts in the north. He is himself running as an apostle of change, pledging to jettison some of the very policies and traditions his party has fostered since coming to power in 1929.</p>
        <p>In particular, Mr. Salinas, a former Minister of Budget and Planning, has proved adept at wooing the business elite in this metropolis of nearly three million people, which the PAN regards as part of its natural constituency. At closed-door meetings and public lunches, Mr. Salinas has stressed his intention to make the economy more competitive and return state companies to private hands, a sharp break with the PRI's history of corporatist policies. Northern Origins Stressed</p>
        <p>Since beginning his campaign in Monterrey last November, Mr. Salinas has also stressed his own northern origins. Though born and educated in Mexico City, he is from a family that has long been influential here, and he considers Agualeguas, a small town 25 miles south of the Rio Grande, to be his real hometown.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salinas's father, Raul Salinas Lozano, is currently a Senator from Nuevo Leon, and an ancestor on his mother's side fought in the battle of the Alamo. His national campaign manager, Luis Donaldo Colosio, is from the northwestern state of Sonora, and his appointment was taken as a sign of the importance Mr. Salinas attaches to halting the PRI's electoral erosion in the north.</p>
        <p>In his speech here tonight, Mr. Salinas said he was ''moved to be back on my home soil'' among ''my dear paisanos.'' He urged his listeners, many of whom had been ordered to attend the rally by PRI-affiliated unions, to vote for him so that ''for the first time in this century a politician whose origins are in Nuevo Leon will be President of Mexico.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Salinas's main rival here, Manuel Clouthier of the PAN, can claim even deeper roots in the region. A prosperous farmer and businessman from the state of Sinaloa, Mr. Clouthier has headed several regional business groups and speaks with the blunt directness many Mexicans regard as typical of northerners.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Salinas, Mr. Clouthier is closing his campaign by focusing on the north. He is in the midst of a sweep through his home state and nearby Sonora and Chihuahua and on Friday will hold a mass rally here, where a poll by the newspaper El Norte shows him trailing Mr. Salinas slightly. Two-Man Race in the North</p>
        <p>The battle in the north is widely considered a two-man race, but Cuauhtemoc Cardenas of the leftist National Democratic Front appears to have some pockets of support, such as Tijuana. In perhaps the most widely commented incident of the entire campaign, peasant supporters of his in the state of Coahuila in February pelted Mr. Salinas with sticks and water.</p>
        <p>But over all Mr. Cardenas has devoted less time and money to the north than his rivals. ''He's calling for a larger state role in the economy and a return to the Mexican Revolution's old way of doing things, and positions like that don't go down very well up here,'' a prominent local businessman said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
