<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Smoky Saigon Bars To Stateside Concerts</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="647822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIETNAM WAR</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">IN COUNTRY REVUE (MUSIC GROUP)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GONZALEZ, DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D71038F934A35752C1A965958260" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Smoky Saigon Bars To Stateside Concerts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GONZALEZ, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the folk singers who perform in the In Country Revue talk about unfriendly theaters, take their word for it. They mean downright deadly.</p>
        <p>Theirs was the theater of war in Southeast Asia; their songs were the lyrical log of days spent slogging through rice paddies, nighttime bombing runs through fierce flak and longing for home the rest of the time. They are the ultimate 60's survivors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the folk singers who perform in the In Country Revue talk about unfriendly theaters, take their word for it. They mean downright deadly.</p>
        <p>Theirs was the theater of war in Southeast Asia; their songs were the lyrical log of days spent slogging through rice paddies, nighttime bombing runs through fierce flak and longing for home the rest of the time. They are the ultimate 60's survivors.</p>
        <p>"This is the last undiscovered music of the 60's," said Chuck Rosenberg, a member of the revue who served in the Special Forces, although an injury prevented him from being sent into combat. (The revue is a collection of veterans who perform together on occasion.) "You think we pretty much drained every ounce of nostalgia from the 60's, but here is this untold folk music made by Americans. By the time the war ended, it was so unpopular and a source of discord that the phenomenon of the cultural expression of G.I.'s was the last thing anybody wanted to hear about."</p>
        <p>Unlike the electric rock or brassy soul music often associated with the war, this style featured simple voices accompanied by acoustic guitars and harmonicas that could change from playful to achingly haunting. The songs that were once belted out in smoky Saigon bars and well-protected firebases have begun to reach a wider stateside audience in recent years through the efforts of the revue and Lydia Fish, a folklorist at Buffalo State College. Ms. Fish was doing research on the Vietnam Veterans Memorial in 1983 when she was told about a cache of recorded folk songs in the Library of Congress. They had been donated by Major General Edward Lansdale, an Air Force officer who ran the Senior Liaison Office of the United States Mission in Saigon. He had collected the songs in the mid-60's, thinking they could give American policymakers an insight into the war.</p>
        <p>"It was amazing quality and obviously an extraordinarily vital tradition," said Ms. Fish, who began to root out other songs and their singers through the Vietnam Veterans Oral History and Folklore Project, which she directs. "I'm interested in Vietnam veterans, and this showed them as the incredibly creative and sensitive people they are, very much against the stereotype of what veterans are like."</p>
        <p>She helped put together a collection titled "In Country: Folk Songs of Americans in the Vietnam War" that was released two years ago on the Flying Fish label. The revue performed in New York a few weeks ago and is playing a series of West Coast dates this month.</p>
        <p>While most people would not associate folk songs with fighters, Ms. Fish said the tradition of military songs dated back centuries, with even foot soldiers under Julius Caesar singing complaints about their leaders. She added that the folk explosion of the 1950's and 60's influenced many of the men (and some women) who went overseas.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fish noted that some of the strongest music in the folk tradition came from highly educated people who probably had heard it while in college -- a group that included C.I.A. agents, some of whom formed the Cosmos Tabernacle Choir, named after a Saigon bar near the American Embassy. In other cases, fighter pilots had long used music to forge bonds among themselves with songs that ranged from boasts of prowess to elegies for fallen comrades.</p>
        <p>"This was something that fighter pilots did in fighter squadrons," said Chip Dockery, a member of the revue who flew hundreds of missions during two tours of duty. "What I wanted more than anything was to fly. If that's what they did, that's what I'd do."</p>
        <p>In time, Mr. Dockery took it one step further, composing a series of songs from the perspective of the Viet Cong truck drivers he and his comrades bombed along the Ho Chi Minh Trail. The songs were sung to the melodies of popular songs like "King of the Road" and "(Sittin' on) The Dock of the Bay."</p>
        <p>Toby Hughes, another revue member who was a pilot known as the "Balladeer of the Air War," described his music as a diversion and a way of dealing with the pressures of a job that few at home knew anything about. "You're 10,000 miles from home, and missing all the things that are back there," he said. "You're doing a job that's more different than anybody you know. You have no idea what a pilot in a war theater does."</p>
        <p>The music also allowed the singers to express fear or sadness in acceptable ways. "Will There Be a Tomorrow?" lays out the pilot's fear of dying in a strange land when he sings: "Will the dawn still arrive, will I still be alive/ Or will I sleep alone here forever?"</p>
        <p>Some songs probed a psychic territory as dark as the skies the pilots zoomed through, with exaggerated aggression that would make civilians blanch and titles like "Strafe the Town and Kill Them All" or "Napalm Sticks to Kids."</p>
        <p>"We'd say words in songs about things you wouldn't necessarily go out and do," explained Mr. Dockery, who is now a commercial airline pilot. "It was part of being in an organization where you were highly trained to go out and perform a mission that could result in somebody's destruction or your death. So we'd sing about killing everything that gets in our way and dying in a heroic pile of metal on the side of a mountain."</p>
        <p>In other cases, the songs mocked the paper-pushers among the officer corps who sat at headquarters and sent others into combat. Ms. Fish said a main function of some of the songs was to question authority. "There's a lot of negotiation of power between the powerful and the powerless," she said. "You get a licensed grumbling that takes place in song."</p>
        <p>ONE OF THE BEST examples of that style can be found in "Tchepone," which was written by Mr. Hughes. The song was named for a Laotian town that was a major staging area at the intersection of two roads along the Ho Chi Minh Trail. It tells how a commander tricks a pilot into thinking a flight over the city would be "an old-time milk run," only to find it more like a journey through hell.</p>
        <p>The song ends with the pilot returning with his plane damaged and the commanding officer nowhere to be found.</p>
        <p>Before the concert, Mr. Dockery praised the song as "the definitive air war song." Mr. Hughes simply joked that he's sung it "more times than Judy Garland sang 'Over the Rainbow.' "</p>
        <p>Although the circumstances that created this music were painful, the range of songs from melancholy and serious to humorous and mocking makes the concerts accessible to an audience beyond those who fought in the war. Mr. Dockery added that the music could be a form of therapy for the veterans who sing along in the audience, seeing themselves in the lyrics.</p>
        <p>"It's about the triumph of the human spirit," said Mr. Rosenberg of the music he and his comrades made. "You find people creating art under amazingly adverse conditions. I'm sure in Bosnia today there are people doing watercolors. Sometimes people need to create meaning and keep their center." PILOT ERROR</p>
        <p>One of the Vietnam folk songs, "Tchepone," describes a bombing mission over heavily defended Laotion city named in the title. It was written by Toby Hughes. a former pilot. Here are portions of the lyrics.</p>
        <p>A black puff in front and then two off the right</p>
        <p>Then six or eight more and I suck it up tight</p>
        <p>There's small arms and tracers and heavy ack-ack</p>
        <p>It's scattered-to-broken with all kinds of flak</p>
        <p>I jink hard to left and head out for the blue</p>
        <p>My wingman says "Lead! They're shooting at you!"</p>
        <p>"No bull!" I cry as I point it toward home</p>
        <p>Still comes the fire from the town of Tchepone</p>
        <p>(Dirty, deadly Tchepone)</p>
        <p>I make it back home with six holes in my bird</p>
        <p>With the colonel who sent me I'd sure like a word</p>
        <p>But he's nowhere around, though I look near and far</p>
        <p>He's gone back to Saigon, to help run the war</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
