<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Time to Hesitate on Haiti</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="648217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFUGEES AND EXPATRIATES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF1230F934A35752C1A965958260" item-length="522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Time to Hesitate on Haiti</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lieut. Gen. Raoul Cedras and his military cronies are feeling pretty bold these days, having wrecked the Governors Island agreement that would have returned President Jean-Bertrand Aristide to Haiti on Oct. 30.</p>
        <p>So what if they are isolated internationally and domestically, abandoned even by some of the local economic oligarchs who welcomed them to power? Haiti's rulers now feel free to intimidate their domestic opponents with impunity. And they contemptuously boycott U.N. peace talks, having reasonably concluded that the outside world isn't prepared to apply maximum diplomatic and economic pressure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lieut. Gen. Raoul Cedras and his military cronies are feeling pretty bold these days, having wrecked the Governors Island agreement that would have returned President Jean-Bertrand Aristide to Haiti on Oct. 30.</p>
        <p>So what if they are isolated internationally and domestically, abandoned even by some of the local economic oligarchs who welcomed them to power? Haiti's rulers now feel free to intimidate their domestic opponents with impunity. And they contemptuously boycott U.N. peace talks, having reasonably concluded that the outside world isn't prepared to apply maximum diplomatic and economic pressure.</p>
        <p>What else are they to think after seeing the Clinton Administration rebuff, at least for now, a French proposal to broaden the reach of international economic sanctions? Instead, Washington proposes to target penalties narrowly on individual military leaders. Individual penalties make sense, but they should be a supplement to broader sanctions, not a substitute for them.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration explains its opposition to broadened sanctions as humanitarian, saying it doesn't want to impose additional suffering on Haiti's impoverished millions. This is a bit hard to take from an Administration that is willing to use U.S. warships to turn back boatloads of desperate Haitians.</p>
        <p>Then as now, the real motivation for the Clinton Administration's policy seems to be a fear of domestic reaction to a massive influx of poor, black Haitian refugees. Once again, that fear seems to have overwhelmed Washington's commitment to Haitian democracy or a humanitarian refugee policy. Once again, the Administration invites suspicion that its backing of President Aristide is less than wholehearted.</p>
        <p>The panic over refugees is probably exaggerated. After all, that warship barrier is still in place. And the numbers of potential new departures bandied about in Washington represent worst-case estimates.</p>
        <p>In any case, the issues of restraining refugees and restoring democracy can't be neatly walled off from each other. Ten months ago, at Washington's request, President Aristide broadcast an appeal to Haitians not to leave because serious efforts to restore democracy were under way. Haitians seemed to listen; fewer took to the seas after that.</p>
        <p>But if the world now seems to back off, departures are likely to surge anew, no matter if sanctions are total, partial or nonexistent. Haiti has always been poor. The biggest variable in refugee departures in recent years has been the presence or absence of political hope. In the long run, there is only one way to solve the refugee problem: by insuring that democracy can survive in Haiti.</p>
        <p>Surely Washington should understand by now that Haiti's present rulers are cruel and desperate men who respond only to extreme, unrelenting pressure. Holding tougher penalties in abeyance won't move them. Pressing for total sanctions plus individual penalties just might.</p>
        <p>The cost of hesitating now may be a future choice reduced to two stark and more damaging alternatives: sending in some kind of international military force or ignominiously walking away.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
