<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rare Miscalculation by Honda</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="484739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HONDA MOTOR CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DA1439F937A35752C1A967958260" item-length="1239" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rare Miscalculation by Honda</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DORON P. LEVIN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVIN, DORON P</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Nov. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among automotive cognoscenti, the Honda Motor Company sits on a tall pedestal for its almost uncanny ability to aim at a market niche and fill it with a wildly popular car. But after Honda's introduction of its Accord station wagon, that pedestal is not quite so high.</p>
        <p>Nearly a year after Honda showed off its first Accord wagons at its Marysville, Ohio, assembly plant, American sales are running at about 2,000 cars a month, well short of the 3,000 cars Honda had hoped for.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among automotive cognoscenti, the Honda Motor Company sits on a tall pedestal for its almost uncanny ability to aim at a market niche and fill it with a wildly popular car. But after Honda's introduction of its Accord station wagon, that pedestal is not quite so high.</p>
        <p>Nearly a year after Honda showed off its first Accord wagons at its Marysville, Ohio, assembly plant, American sales are running at about 2,000 cars a month, well short of the 3,000 cars Honda had hoped for.</p>
        <p>True, a recession in the United States has severely hurt car sales and promises to give Detroit its worst financial beating ever. And true, the station wagon market has been shrinking, badly hurt by the growing popularity of mini-vans.</p>
        <p>But Honda's wagon is also off to a slow start because of its lofty price, its comparatively modest amount of space and a missing feature or two.  Problems of Price and Space</p>
        <p>Honda, for its part, says it is not disappointed with station wagon sales. They will improve, company executives insist, as the model becomes better known and the economy improves. In any event, they say, the plant where the car is built is operating at close to full capacity, partly because Honda is exporting the station wagon to Europe and Japan.</p>
        <p>Honda's first mistake, several Honda dealers said, was in pricing the compact wagon considerably higher than the Honda Accord sedan -- initially more than $2,000 higher. Shoppers quickly noted that the wagon was not all that much bigger than the sedan and concluded that it was not worth the added cost.</p>
        <p>Given what Honda initially wanted for its wagon, ranging from $17,300 to $19,800, many buyers chose roomier competitors like the Subaru Legacy or the Volvo 240 wagon, which costs only slightly more than a fully-equipped Honda wagon. Others just chose the Accord sedan.</p>
        <p>"In the climate we're in, purchase price is a major factor," said Larry Brueshaber, a Honda dealer in Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>Because Honda's wagon is generally less roomy than many other wagons, as well as comparably priced mini-vans and utility vehicles, it is also less useful. With 64.6 cubic feet of cargo room with the second seat folded down, the Accord compares poorly with the midsized Ford Taurus and Mercury Sable wagons (81.1 cubic feet), and import wagons like the Subaru Legacy (71 cubic feet) or the Volvo 240 (76 cubic feet).</p>
        <p>"Honda may have overestimated the potential for a sporty-type wagon without that much space in the back," said Craig Scott, who owns Scott Honda in West Chester, Pa. "And I think Honda has to address the fact that a station wagon is perceived to hold more than four people."</p>
        <p>Although a third adult could squeeze into the back seat, enabling the car to carry five adults, Honda engineers lacked room for a foldaway third seat in the rear similar to the third-seat option offered by Ford on its Taurus and Sable wagons and on the Chevrolet Caprice, Volvo and others. Honda executives have said they are considering adding a third seat, but not until the car is redesigned in 1995 or 1996.  Swayed by a Radio Ad</p>
        <p>Debbie Luciano of Lincroft, N.J., had been planning to buy a 1992 Honda station wagon, and she even put $2,000 on one. Then she heard a radio advertisement that compared its size with that of a Volvo. "I started thinking about these high school kids I drive around," she said. "They are big."</p>
        <p>After comparing the $20,020 price for the well-equipped Honda with the $21,500 cost of the Volvo, she and her husband decided that the extra space was worth the extra money.</p>
        <p>With the 1991 introductory price of $17,300, the basic Accord wagon cost $2,205 more than a comparably equipped Accord sedan. The most expensive wagon had a $19,800 price tag, $2,255 more than the most luxurious Accord sedan. By contrast, prices for a Ford Taurus station wagon start at less than $15,000.</p>
        <p>Honda has since made some pricing changes. For the 1992 model year, it narrowed the price difference between the wagon and the sedan, not by cutting prices but by raising the price of the sedan more than the wagon. Now, the least expensive Honda wagon costs $17,450, compared with $15,825 for the least-expensive sedan, a $1,625 difference. The most expensive wagon costs $20,650, only $655 more than the costliest sedan.</p>
        <p>A Honda spokesman said the value of the station wagon was enhanced this year by the addition of a driver's side air bag as standard equipment. The sedan has featured an air bag since last year.</p>
        <p>Executives of Detroit's Big Three, who have watched glumfaced as Honda's Civic, Accord and Acura models have inexorably devoured their sales since 1973, can barely conceal their glee now that Honda may finally have hit something short of a home run.</p>
        <p>"It surely hasn't measured up to vaunted expectations," said Joel Pitcoff, a research analyst for the Ford Motor Company. "If their strategy was to woo away Taurus and Sable owners, that's going to be a tough struggle."</p>
        <p>The Honda wagon is also struggling in a shrinking market. Throughout the 1980's, mini-vans steadily gained ground as the multipurpose vehicle of choice, while station wagon sales steadily declined. Since 1985, station wagon registrations have plummeted 57 percent, to 390,770 cars in 1990, while mini-van registrations have more than doubled in the same period, to 829,126 units.  Resisting the Mini-Van Trend</p>
        <p>Ford, for example, discontinued its full-sized wagons this year after annual sales had dwindled to less than 15,000 cars. It continues to make the Taurus and Sable wagons.</p>
        <p>But Honda has resisted the mini-van trend, preferring to invest in other projects like its Acura luxury models. The Acura Legend was the first Japanese luxury car to be sold in the United States and quickly captured a niche because it was priced slightly below European luxury brands like Mercedes-Benz and BMW and won more praise from reviewers than American luxury models like Lincoln and Cadillac.</p>
        <p>Since most shoppers consider domestic or foreign brands exclusively, Honda probably did not hope to attract much crossover business from Ford. Still, Honda has to wonder whether the Accord wagon possesses the attributes for its target audience: import buyers who like a sporty vehicle but need a roomier car than a sedan.</p>
        <p>Honda dealers say more changes in the pricing stategy could go a long way toward increasing sales. Generally, Honda cars have been so popular that the company has not offered rebates. But Honda will sometimes subsidize leases or pay incentives to dealers, which can indirectly lower a customer's price.  A Comparison With Subaru</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott, the Pennsylvania Honda dealer, said the Honda wagon "drives and handles like the sedan and has more space, but it still could cost almost $2,000 more," taking into consideration options and incentives.</p>
        <p>"At that price," he said, "people start comparing with the Subaru wagon, which is $3,000 less, or they discover they can get something much bigger for about the same money."</p>
        <p>Last fall, a few months before the Accord wagon was available, John Lewis and Judith Bell-Lewis, his wife, of Lynchburg, Va., were hunting for a station wagon. They bought a four-wheel-drive Subaru Legacy wagon for $15,500. The Honda dealer had told him a comparably equipped wagon might cost $18,000.</p>
        <p>"The Subaru was a great value," Mr. Lewis said. "My wife owned a Honda Accord sedan and loved it, but we have no regrets."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
