<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tobacco War's New Front: Lawyers Fight for Big Fees</title>
    <meta content="09LAWY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1023313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meier, Barry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abramson, Jill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDE153AF93AA35755C0A96E958260" item-length="1852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tobacco War's New Front: Lawyers Fight for Big Fees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY MEIER and JILL ABRAMSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abramson, Jill; Meier, Barry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawyers who sued tobacco industry are fighting for share of spoils from successful suits against industry; debate over fees has moved from states that have settled suits to Congress, which weighs bill to resolve many suits; prospect of paying billions of dollars to small group of trial lawyers has caused outcries, particularly from conservative Republicans who have long sought to rein in fees of trial lawyers; laywers who led cases defend fees, noting they invested heavily in suing tobacco industry at time when may believed industry was invulnerable; table; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawyers who fought the tobacco industry have found a new focus for their energies: fighting for their share of the spoils from lawsuits against the industry.</p>
        <p>In recent months, the issue of the lawyers' fees has been the focus of intense controversy in states that have settled lawsuits against cigarette makers. But now the debate has also erupted in Washington, where Congress is considering Federal legislation that will resolve many tobacco lawsuits and allow the Government to regulate nicotine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawyers who fought the tobacco industry have found a new focus for their energies: fighting for their share of the spoils from lawsuits against the industry.</p>
        <p>In recent months, the issue of the lawyers' fees has been the focus of intense controversy in states that have settled lawsuits against cigarette makers. But now the debate has also erupted in Washington, where Congress is considering Federal legislation that will resolve many tobacco lawsuits and allow the Government to regulate nicotine.</p>
        <p>At stake is the richest pot of legal fees ever to be awarded: billions of dollars scheduled to be paid to a small group of trial lawyers who were either hired by state attorneys general to sue cigarette makers on the states' behalf or who brought class-action claims on behalf of smokers.</p>
        <p>In Texas and Florida, which have already settled with the industry, a battle has broken out over fees to lawyers that could exceed $3.4 billion in those two states. And if lawyers, who were to be paid for their cases as part of last June's proposed $368.5 billion settlement between the industry and 41 other states, were awarded fees of just 5 percent of that, the earnings of some 160 law firms nationwide could reach $18 billion.</p>
        <p>The prospect of such huge awards has caused outcries, particularly from conservative Republicans who have long sought to rein in the fees of trial lawyers, who have traditionally made big donations to Democrats. But the lawyers, who include some of the best-known and most politically well connnected in the country -- like Stanley M. Chesley of Cincinnati, who recently held a fund-raiser for the Democratic Party attended by President Clinton and Hugh Rodham Jr., the President's brother-in-law, and Russ M. Herman of New Orleans -- have begun fighting back.</p>
        <p>The proposed June deal has since collapsed, and the question of whether the lawyers can easily collect their fees is in doubt because Federal tobacco legislation bogged down for weeks in Senate debate. But should such a bill be adopted by Congress it would generate billions in fees because it would settle several types of tobacco lawsuits.</p>
        <p>Even some like Senator John McCain, the Arizona Republican who is the sponsor of a $516 billion tobacco bill before Congress, have begun to argue for controls on fees.</p>
        <p>''There is a large body of opinion that the present scenario is skewed too much in favor of the trial lawyers,'' said Mr. McCain. He said he had recently asked Senator Slade Gorton, Republican of Washington, to propose limits on lawyers' fees resulting from Federal legislation.</p>
        <p>Lawyers who led cases against cigarette makers say they deserve to be richly rewarded. They point out that they took big risks by taking cases on contingency, spending millions of dollars of their own money suing the tobacco industry at a time when many experts believed it was invulnerable.</p>
        <p>The lawyers -- who are also struggling with one another over the fees in some cases -- include Richard F. Scruggs, the brother-in-law of Senator Trent Lott, the majority leader. Many are already multimillionaires as the result of lawsuits brought against asbestos producers. Others, like John P. Coale, a class-action lawyer from Washington, built their reputations on more controversial ventures. Mr. Coale, for example, raced to Bhopal, India, in the mid-1980's to sign up clients who were victims of the explosion of a Union Carbide chemical plant there.</p>
        <p>Those class-action cases, which were filed in some 25 states, do not seek monetary damages for smokers but rather demand that the industry pay for programs like smoking-cessation courses. However, many tobacco proposals before Congress would finance such programs and so effectively pre-empt the lawsuits and the lawyers' chance to collect fees.</p>
        <p>Cigarette makers had agreed to settle the class-action lawsuits as part of last June's agreement, and the lawyers have succeeded in persuading Senator McCain and other lawmakers to settle the lawsuits, a step that would qualify them to collect fees, as part of their tobacco bills. Mr. Herman said that he believed that he and his colleagues deserved to be paid because they had invested millions of dollars in the lawsuits and persuaded the industry last June to finance programs like the smoking-cessation courses.</p>
        <p>But since the June plan, some class-action lawsuits have faced setbacks in court, and some lawmakers, like Representative Martin T. Meehan, Democrat of Massachusetts, have declined to include the cases in their bills, saying that special consideration for trial lawyers could damage a bill's bipartisan appeal.</p>
        <p>Still, even if the class-action lawsuits are not covered, Federal tobacco legislation, if passed, could generate billions in fees because such a law would settle the remaining state lawsuits against the tobacco companies that seek to recover the cost of treating smoking-related illnesses. To handle those cases, state attorneys general, beginning in 1994, hired outside law firms and signed contracts which, depending on the state, guaranteed the lawyers 3 percent to 33 percent of any recovery.</p>
        <p>In a typical contingency fee case, it is not unusual for lawyers to receive 33 percent of an award. However, the settlement amounts in the tobacco cases are so large that many legal experts believe that the fees generated by such contracts are excessive.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, about 100 law firms were retained, although just a handful of lawyers dominated the cases. For example, the law firm headed by Mr. Scruggs represented Mississippi, the first state to sue, and was later hired by 29 other states. Ness, Motley, Loadholt &amp; Richardson, a law firm in Charleston, S.C., was retained by many of the same states.</p>
        <p>But as Congress debates a tobacco bill, lawyers in some states that have already settled their cases are battling each other over fees with the same fervor they once reserved for cigarette makers.</p>
        <p>For example, a battle has been under way in Texas for months over the $2.3 billion in fees sought by a group of prominent trial lawyers who negotiated the state's $15.3 billion settlement with the tobacco industry in January. The lawyers say they were promised 15 percent of the Texas award when they agreed in 1996 to represent State Attorney General Dan Morales.</p>
        <p>But Gov. George W. Bush of Texas opposes the award, calling it outrageous and unjustified. A legal expert hired by Mr. Bush estimated that the fees sought by the lawyers equal an hourly billing rate of $92,000.</p>
        <p>The fight recently took a bizarre turn when Joseph P. Jamail, one of the country's richest trial lawyers, said that Mr. Morales had demanded a $1 million payment from him in a 1996 meeting to discuss the possibility of Mr. Morales hiring Mr. Jamail to head the state's legal team. Mr. Jamail was not hired.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morales has denied the claim calling it a sideshow concocted by his political enemies to divert attention from the ''improper conduct'' of state officials like Governor Bush, who are trying to change the settlement terms. He has also asked a Federal judge for millions of dollars in sanctions against Mr. Bush and other state lawmakers.</p>
        <p>Some lawyers fear that the Texas spectacle and a similar fight over legal fees in Florida only feed the anti-lawyer sentiment in Congress. ''Some of these tobacco lawyers are becoming the poster children for tort reform,'' said Mr. Scruggs of Pascagoula, Miss. ''The biggest problem is that some of these lawyers don't give a damn about their colleagues. They just want their money.''</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the fee issue has split lawmakers along partisan lines. Many of the lawyers involved in lawsuits against the tobacco industry are well-known in Washington because of their large contributions to the Democratic Party. Since 1995, lawyers from 13 firms with tobacco cases have made nearly $3 million in political contributions, the vast majority going to Democratic Party committees or candidates, public records show.</p>
        <p>Trial lawyers have been battling tort reform legislation championed by business interests and Republicans. They have been among the Democratic Party's most generous contributors over the last decade. The 1997 tobacco pact has deeply divided the Association of Trial Lawyers of America, because it would have curbed the future ability of lawyers to sue the tobacco industry. However, some of the association's most prominent members are the ones who sued the tobacco industry and would gain from national legislation.</p>
        <p>And since last June, many of those lawyers have also spent heavily on lobbying on behalf of tobacco legislation. Mr. Scruggs, for example, estimated that his firm paid some $2 million over the past year to three lobbying firms. He said that virtually all of that lobbying has been in support of tobacco legislation, rather than on the issue of fees.</p>
        <p>Under most pending Federal tobacco bills, an arbitration panel would be established to weigh lawyers' claims for fees and to award up to $500 million annually. That method is also being backed by tobacco companies and by many trial lawyers like Mr. Scruggs, who under his contracts with Mississippi, Texas and Florida already stands to share in more than $4.5 billion in fees.</p>
        <p>Some legal experts say that resolving fee disputes through arbitration may defuse partisan bickering. ''We need to get one step removed from the politics of attorneys' fee awards,'' said Robert L. Rabin, a Stanford University law professor who follows tobacco litigation.</p>
        <p>But other experts argue that because Congress is being asked to settle lawsuits, lawmakers should set the fees. And some politicians fear that even arbitration will result in too much money going to lawyers. As a result, some lawmakers contend that fees in tobacco cases should be limited to an hourly rate.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Senate narrowly defeated a proposal to cap the hourly rate for plaintiffs' lawyers in tobacco cases at $250 an hour. And there are even more stringent bills to cap fees in the House, with one proposal calling for a $150-an-hour rate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
