<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="09PUBX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980612T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1023309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio City Music Hall (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minato Mirai Hall (Yokohama, Japan)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Donnell, Rosie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Naruhito (Crown Prince)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kampel, Stewart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DE153AF93AA35755C0A96E958260" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON with Glenn Collins and Stewart Kampel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kampel, Stewart; Barron, James; Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column on Tony Awards host Rosie O'Donnell notes that she made some controversial ad-lib remarks during television commercials that were heard only by audience at Radio City Music Hall; also notes that Crown Prince Naruhito of Japan, after New York Philharmonic concert opening Minato Mirai 21 hall in Yokohama, made overtures about playing his viola with orchestra; O'Donnell and Naruhito photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>M.C.'s Impudence Is No 'Cabaret' Act</p>
        <p>The people in the audience for the Tony Awards at Radio City Music Hall must have wondered if they had wandered onto ''The Jerry Springer Show.'' ROSIE O'DONNELL, the talk show diva and Springer competitor who was the M.C. for the awards show, ad-libbed  shoot-from-the-lip patter that the folks in television land did not see because she delivered it only during the commercials.</p>
        <p>First Ms. O'Donnell referred to FRAN and BARRY WEISSLER, producers of the hit musical ''Chicago'' and the 1994 Broadway revival of ''Grease'' (in which Ms. O'Donnell starred as the salty-mouthed Betty Rizzo), as ''the cheapest people in the free world.'' She also mimicked Mrs. Weissler's  distinctive pronunciation of ''darling.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>M.C.'s Impudence Is No 'Cabaret' Act</p>
        <p>The people in the audience for the Tony Awards at Radio City Music Hall must have wondered if they had wandered onto ''The Jerry Springer Show.'' ROSIE O'DONNELL, the talk show diva and Springer competitor who was the M.C. for the awards show, ad-libbed  shoot-from-the-lip patter that the folks in television land did not see because she delivered it only during the commercials.</p>
        <p>First Ms. O'Donnell referred to FRAN and BARRY WEISSLER, producers of the hit musical ''Chicago'' and the 1994 Broadway revival of ''Grease'' (in which Ms. O'Donnell starred as the salty-mouthed Betty Rizzo), as ''the cheapest people in the free world.'' She also mimicked Mrs. Weissler's  distinctive pronunciation of ''darling.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weissler leapt from his seat, but not to object. He took a bow. He waved. Then the commercial ended, the cameras came back on and Ms. O'Donnell returned to the script.</p>
        <p>''We don't take ourselves seriously,'' Mrs. Weissler said yesterday. ''We thought it was hilarious. Everyone is talking about the Tonys and about us, so what's the problem?''</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Donnell said she had intended her comments to be affectionate. Of Mrs. Weissler, she said, ''She's like a mother figure to me, and I will tease her forever about the fact that they're cheap.''</p>
        <p>During later commercials, Ms. O'Donnell sometimes lapsed into language not printable in a newspaper. She had unkind words for everyone from CHARLTON HESTON, the new president of the National Rifle Association (she suggested that he star in a musical called ''Everybody Get Your Gun''), to NANCY REAGAN (''looks like a human Pez dispenser'').</p>
        <p>Royal Overture</p>
        <p>CROWN PRINCE NARUHITO of Japan so liked what he heard at a New York Philharmonic concert (which opened the Minato Mirai 21 hall in Yokohama, Japan) that he made overtures about playing with the orchestra. Apparently, the Crown Prince, who attended the concert with CROWN PRINCESS MASAKO, is serious about his viola.</p>
        <p>In a backstage huddle after the performance, he and the Philharmonic's music director, KURT MASUR, talked repertoire. They zeroed in on the Brandenburg Concerto No. 6 by Bach and the Octet in E flat (Op. 20) by Mendelssohn.</p>
        <p>But there was a catch. ''Your Highness must still audition,'' Mr. Masur said.</p>
        <p>Put it this way: The Crown Prince has not given up his day job.</p>
        <p>No-Wait Workout</p>
        <p>BILLY CRYSTAL wanted barbells. In his hotel room.</p>
        <p>He got them, but not from room service. Mr. Crystal, the actor and comedian who is in New York to appear in the film ''Analyze This'' with ROBERT DeNIRO, went shopping with a trainer.</p>
        <p>''Typical New York, everything right immediately,'' said RICHARD MILLER, an owner of the Gym Source, a workout equipment store on East 52d Street where Mr. Crystal rented not only barbells but also a bench. ''Took the stuff right off the floor. We said, 'We'll deliver it tomorrow.' They said, 'No, no, we're working out in five minutes.' They put it in the back of a big Suburban he was in, and went over to the hotel.''</p>
        <p>Seen and Heard In the Hamptons</p>
        <p>MICHAEL GELMAN, executive producer of the midmorning talk show ''Live With Regis and Kathie Lee,'' was seen surveying the ocean at Atlantica, a restaurant in Westhampton Beach, N.Y.  ''We had heard that 'Good Morning America' was interested in doing some shows from there,'' said a man who works for the restaurant, ''and now, all of a sudden, Gelman is here.'' . . . BRYAN BANTRY, the fashion agent and producer, had a showing of the new GEORGE CLOONEY-JENNIFER LOPEZ film ''Out of Control'' in the thick-carpeted screening room in his home in Wainscott, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Among those who settled into Mr. Bantry's comfortable seats (and then went to supper at Alison by the Beach, a nearby restaurant) were STEVE KROFT of the CBS newsmagazine ''60 Minutes''; NINA GRISCOM, a former host on the Food Network who has summered in the Hamptons since she was a child, and BILL BEUTEL, an anchor on WABC-TV who has a home in Westhampton.</p>
        <p>Asked how he had liked the film, Mr. Beutel was diplomatic.</p>
        <p>''It's a nice party, isn't it?'' he said.</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON with Glenn Collins and Stewart Kampel</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 12, 1998, Friday  A brief report in the Public Lives column on Tuesday about a party last week in Wainscott, N.Y., misstated the name of the film that was screened. It is ''Out of Sight,'' not ''Out of Control.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 12, 1998, Friday</p>
        <p>A brief report in the Public Lives column on Tuesday about a party last week in Wainscott, N.Y., misstated the name of the film that was screened. It is ''Out of Sight,'' not ''Out of Control.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
