<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business; Trying to Make Fuel Prices Less of a Wartime Gamble</title>
    <meta content="23HEDG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/23/business/yourmoney/23HEDG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1474579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iraq-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fuel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Southwest Airlines Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFDB1E31F930A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business; Trying to Make Fuel Prices Less of a Wartime Gamble</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trying to Make Fuel Prices Less of a Wartime Gamble</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Businesses in several industries face complex task of guarding against oil price spike while staying open to benefits of falling oil prices in wake of start of war in Iraq; some are actively hedging, others are managing fuel inventories or passing costs along to consumers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOW that the war in Iraq has begun, oil prices could go $10 a barrel higher -- or lower -- by this time next month. How can a company that uses a lot of oil or its byproducts protect itself?</p>
        <p>Because the risks run in both directions, businesses in several industries face a complex task: guarding against a price spike while staying open to the benefits of falling prices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that the war in Iraq has begun, oil prices could go $10 a barrel higher  or lower  by this time next month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOW that the war in Iraq has begun, oil prices could go $10 a barrel higher -- or lower -- by this time next month. How can a company that uses a lot of oil or its byproducts protect itself?</p>
        <p>Because the risks run in both directions, businesses in several industries face a complex task: guarding against a price spike while staying open to the benefits of falling prices.</p>
        <p>The companies' methods run the gamut. Some have been actively hedging, using complex financial instruments, while others have preferred to manage fuel inventories or pass along costs to consumers.</p>
        <p>Last September, Southwest Airlines decided to prepare for the possibility of war in the Persian Gulf. The company bought financial derivatives to ensure that it would never pay much more than 70 cents a gallon for jet fuel -- the equivalent of a bit more than $23 for a barrel of crude oil, compared with the price of $28.80 today -- for its fuel supply this quarter. More than 75 percent of its fuel needs for the remainder of 2003 and all of 2004 are similarly protected, and some of its hedges extend all the way to 2008.</p>
        <p>Southwest's hedges mostly take the form of common but sophisticated derivatives called collars and swaps, said Gary C. Kelly, the airline's chief financial officer. In the near term, about two-thirds of the derivatives are based on prices for heating oil, which follow rates for jet fuel more closely than those for crude oil.</p>
        <p>The cost of price protection amounts to about 1 or 2 cents for each gallon of jet fuel, Mr. Kelly said. With jet fuel being traded for more than $1 a gallon lately, he added, ''it's obviously a very substantial saving.''</p>
        <p>Southwest, though, may be the exception rather than the rule.</p>
        <p>''It varies tremendously from firm to firm,'' said Edward N. Krapels, an expert on risk management at Energy Security Analysis, a research firm in Wakefield, Mass. ''In the airline industry, you'll find some who are quite aggressive hedgers, and others who are not.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Krapels said some companies might have become wary of hedging after buying derivatives to protect themselves, only to find that oil prices would fall. In the Persian Gulf war of 1991, for example, the sudden drop in prices that accompanied the build-up of coalition forces and their early victories took many companies by surprise.</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Krapels explained, ''most large consumers are underhedged, with some very significant exceptions.'' He added, ''The impact of an oil price increase on these guys will be very significant.''</p>
        <p>Companies that routinely engage in hedging tend to be in the middle of the petroleum supply chain, said Neal L. Wolkoff, the chief operating officer of the New York Mercantile Exchange, where energy derivatives are traded. ''The greatest participation tends not to be from the ultimate consumer,'' he said. ''It's more either merchants and refiners or integrated oil companies.''</p>
        <p>The Valero Energy Corporation, a top refiner, contracts in advance for cargoes of oil from China, Russia and other countries. The company uses simple mechanisms to guarantee oil prices into the near future. Because of the uncertainty about oil prices in the next few months, Valero has tried to insure itself in case market rates fall below those in its long-term contracts.</p>
        <p>''We are concerned that prices are going to fall off after this whole Iraqi thing is resolved, so any extra barrels we have, we hedge them,'' said Gene Edwards, Valero's senior vice president for supply and trading.</p>
        <p>RATHER than buying options to sell oil at fixed prices, as protection against prices falling, Valero sells future contracts for oil. For example, it might buy oil at $35 a barrel today and promise to sell oil at $32 a barrel next month. If the price of oil next month falls below $32, then Valero can buy oil from the market and sell it at a profit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards said that investment banks often approach Valero with more complicated derivatives, but that the futures generally offer a less expensive solution.</p>
        <p>In addition to buying and selling futures, Valero has been engaging in a more tangible form of hedging -- limiting its own stocks of oil so it can take advantage of prices if they fall. ''You try to keep inventories low, because you don't want to be sitting on extra barrels,'' Mr. Edwards said.</p>
        <p>That kind of activity has kept volume on the New York Mercantile Exchange near normal levels, Mr. Wolkoff said. ''A lot of companies are, in effect, hedging through their physical business,'' he said. ''That means there appears to be a reticence to hold inventory. That's one way of hedging, simply by reducing your exposure.''</p>
        <p>Some companies that use a lot of fuel have an even simpler way of dealing with high and low prices. The Roadway Corporation, the trucking-line operator, passes along the high cost of fuel to customers through a surcharge. Each week, the company updates the surcharge automatically, using the Energy Department's diesel price index.</p>
        <p>''It makes fuel a pass-through for us,'' said John M. Hyre, a spokesman for Roadway. ''We don't benefit by it, and we're not negatively impacted by it. We do have concern for the impact that rising fuel costs have on our customers, though.''</p>
        <p>The company can benefit, however, when fuel prices drop steeply. ''If we encounter good pricing, we will work on getting long-term contracts under that good pricing,'' Mr. Hyre said.</p>
        <p>If the war in Iraq does not go as the Pentagon has planned, any sudden spike in oil prices could have the harshest effects on some people who have little use for petroleum products, except on the drive to work. Hedge-fund managers and other speculators who sell financial protection to companies like Valero could be at risk, Mr. Krapels said.</p>
        <p>''If the war goes badly, and the oil price goes significantly higher than it is today, how well can the people who took the short side of that bet withstand it?'' he asked. ''There could be some very big credit exposures.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
