<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You're Thinking of Living In/Murray Hill, Queens; The Name's the Same, the Pace is Slower</title>
    <meta content="23LIVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/23/realestate/23LIVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1474522"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="If You're Thinking of Living In | Murray Hill, Queens"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Murray Hill (Queens)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Joyce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Queens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFD71231F930A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You're Thinking of Living In/Murray Hill, Queens; The Name's the Same, the Pace is Slower</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Name's the Same, the Pace Is Slower</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>If You're Thinking of Living In column on Murray Hill, Queens; table of geographic data; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE familiar Murray Hill is the one in Manhattan, a part of East Midtown dense with high-rises. Its little-known Queens cousin -- the neighborhoods were named for the same family -- is a part of Flushing, beyond the end of the No. 7 subway line, where midrise brick apartment buildings give way to close-set houses, and a crowded urban feeling yields to a calmer suburban one.</p>
        <p>''People aren't familiar with this Murray Hill,'' said Careen Halton, who spent her childhood in the neighborhood, then returned six years ago to attend graduate school while living in the house her parents still owned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Queens enclave where midrise brick apartment buildings give way to close-set houses, and a crowded urban feeling yields to a calmer suburban one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE familiar Murray Hill is the one in Manhattan, a part of East Midtown dense with high-rises. Its little-known Queens cousin -- the neighborhoods were named for the same family -- is a part of Flushing, beyond the end of the No. 7 subway line, where midrise brick apartment buildings give way to close-set houses, and a crowded urban feeling yields to a calmer suburban one.</p>
        <p>''People aren't familiar with this Murray Hill,'' said Careen Halton, who spent her childhood in the neighborhood, then returned six years ago to attend graduate school while living in the house her parents still owned.</p>
        <p>''When I moved back here, I would say I live in Murray Hill in Queens, and people never seemed to know what that meant,'' said Ms. Halton, who now teaches in Manhattan at a public school in Chinatown. ''Then I started saying I live in Flushing.''</p>
        <p>Even as Murray Hill remains a sleepy, low-key spot -- once home to families of Irish and Italian immigrants, and now an increasingly Korean enclave -- it's ''in transition,'' said the area's councilman, John C. Liu, who lived in Murray Hill as a child and still lives nearby.</p>
        <p>''The people moving in are mostly immigrants and have brought commercial vitality to the area,'' he said. But it suffers from the problem of illegally crowded houses, as does much of Queens. ''Where there used to be very stable owner-occupied homes, you will see many more renters,'' he said. ''Unfortunately, we do have our share of illegal conversion problems.''</p>
        <p>In the last eight years, the influx has included so many Koreans that ''the area looks like Koreatown,'' said John Hong, owner of Han Mi Realty in Flushing, who himself immigrated from Korea 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>His Murray Hill buyers tend to be young Korean families with small children. ''Our immigrants are newcomers from Korea,'' he said. ''They come to Flushing and rent. After 5 to 10 years of settlement, they save money and buy a house.''</p>
        <p>Though the buyers are ''middle-income people,'' prices have soared, rising about 80 percent in five years, Mr. Hong said. A one- or two-family house now starts in the $325,000 to $450,000 range, and a three-family house starts around $700,000, he said.</p>
        <p>''There's high competition in that area,'' said Leo Chiger of Century 21 Benjamin Bayside. ''Buyers don't even negotiate.'' It's not unusual for a home to sell within 30 days, he said, and tear-downs are common. ''Developers are demolishing one-family houses -- they are not even worth restoring -- and building at least two-family homes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>RENTAL units -- either in private homes or in apartment buildings -- hover around $900 to $1,100 for a one-bedroom and $1,100 to $1,400 for a two-bedroom.</p>
        <p>Some of the area's brick apartment buildings are now co-ops. In one six-story brick building, Birchwood, three one-bedrooms are currently on the market, asking $95,000, $119,000 and $139,000, with monthly maintenance of about $460 or $470.</p>
        <p>Murray Hill is about a mile east of a main commercial hub, Main Street in Flushing, with easy bus access. There is also the Long Island Rail Road, whose Murray Hill Station is little more than a forlorn plaza with a pay phone and a bus stop. No parking is available for commuters except on the street.</p>
        <p>A small commercial area surrounds the station, which is scheduled for renovation, to include new paving, stairways, benches, signs and lighting. Construction should start in early 2004 and be finished in the spring or summer of 2005.</p>
        <p>Transportation is so good that ''I never learned to drive,'' said Rita South, who has lived in Murray Hill since she married and moved from the Upper East Side more than 50 years ago.</p>
        <p>Her husband knew and liked the area. ''My husband had gone to the Merchant Marine Academy in King's Point and had dated a girl who lived in Flushing,'' she said. ''I thought this was the most horrendous place to go to, this wilderness.''</p>
        <p>The Souths bought a three-story Victorian house for $15,000 -- a low price, even then, because the house needed repair. Some Victorians remain in Murray Hill, but most have been razed and replaced by multifamily housing.</p>
        <p>The neighborhood was once so bucolic that ''if you walked down Sanford or Barclay Avenues, huge trees on both sides would form an archway,'' Mrs. South said. ''You could walk all the way down to Main Street and be cool and shady in the summer. It was lovely, like Paris.''</p>
        <p>''The neighborhood is more utilitarian now,'' she said. ''I regret the loss of the old houses and trees, but I think the neighborhood has revitalized itself with the coming of the Asians.''</p>
        <p>The area has also grown so dense that on-street parking is scarce. ''At night, I see people searching,'' Mrs. South said. ''They go around and around, looking.'' She allows one of her neighbors, who lives in an apartment building two doors down, to park in her driveway.</p>
        <p>One of Murray Hill's most historic houses is now the headquarters of the Queens Historical Society. The Dutch-English colonial-style house was built around 1785 by a Quaker farmer named Charles Doughty, said James Driscoll, vice president for history at the Queens Historical Society.</p>
        <p>In 1799, Doughty's daughter Mary married a sea captain, Joseph King. He bought the house and called it Kingsland. Their daughter Mary married Lindley Murray; the Murray family had four children and operated one of several large tree nurseries in Queens.</p>
        <p>Those local nurseries left another legacy, Mr. Driscoll said -- the horticultural street names, like Ash, Beech, Cherry and so on, near Parsons Boulevard.</p>
        <p>Development flourished after the railroad station opened in 1889. ''We think the name Murray Hill was coined by real-estate developers,'' said Mr. Driscoll, who noted there is no hill in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>As for the Kingsland Homestead, it gained landmark status in 1965, and, three years later, was moved a few miles up the road to Weeping Beech Park. ''They moved it down Northern Boulevard with a lot of fanfare,'' Mrs. South said. ''It was a Sunday morning, and everyone watched.''</p>
        <p>Murray Hill Plaza, a small shopping hub with a big parking lot, sits near the homestead's original location, on Northern Boulevard near 155th Street. Northern Boulevard itself, a busy artery, holds a mix of Korean restaurants, carwashes and bridal boutiques. There is also Seoul Plaza, a high-end mini shopping mall with valet parking.</p>
        <p>Murray Hill Plaza includes Duane Reade, McDonald's, a bank, a shoe store, a pizza place, a Chinese restaurant and a supermarket, which has changed hands several times. It is currently the Han Ah Reum Asian Mart, brimming with fresh produce and Korean food, with just a few aisles of Western staples.</p>
        <p>THE lack of Western food has drawn complaints, especially from those without cars to get them to farther-away supermarkets.</p>
        <p>The market offers food samples every weekend. Yuna Choi, a high-school student with a weekend job at the market, was recently frying dumplings and fish cakes, and her samples were going as soon as she set them out. The non-Koreans ''say it's good, but they don't purchase it because it's too spicy,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Next to the shopping plaza is the McGoldrick branch of the Queens Borough Public Library, a squat building circa 1974, and one of the system's busiest. The branch, originally called Broadway-Flushing, was renamed in 1930 for the Rev. Edward F. McGoldrick, a library trustee. It has collections in Korean, Chinese and Spanish, as well as large-print books. Beyond the shopping plaza, where Murray Hill merges into Broadway-Flushing, is St. Andrew Avellino Roman Catholic School, along with the parish church.</p>
        <p>Two decades ago, Leemay Wu, whose parents immigrated from China, was one of two Asian pupils at the school. Now, her two young sons attend.</p>
        <p>''I like it that everyone is colorblind,'' in both school and neighborhood, she said. ''I think it is well-rounded.''</p>
        <p>St. Andrew Avellino has just over 400 children in prekindergarten through eighth grade. Tuition is $2,750 for the first child in a family from the parish and $3,450 for the first child from an out-of-parish family.</p>
        <p>Public School 22, the Thomas Jefferson School, has around 800 children in Grades 1 to 6. Next year, the school, which is at Sanford Avenue near 153rd Street, will probably have a kindergarten too, said the principal, Fran Levy.</p>
        <p>P.S. 22 belongs to the well-regarded School District 25 and is one of the 209 city schools exempt from the chancellor's new standardized curriculum. It has strong programs in music, dancing and visual arts, said Dr. Levy. Of the 800 students, 54 percent are Asian, 31 percent Hispanic, 11 percent white and 4 percent black. One-quarter of the students are recent immigrants, defined as having arrived within three years.</p>
        <p>Many continue to the nearby Junior High School 189, at Sanford Avenue and 147th Street, which enrolls nearly 1,300 students in Grades 7 through 9. Most of its graduates later attend Flushing, Francis Lewis or John Bowne High Schools.</p>
        <p>Murray Hill playground, adjacent to the elementary school, is all concrete and often occupied by men playing soccer. Bowne Park is on the other side of Northern Boulevard, which makes for a distinct geographic divide.</p>
        <p>More and closer park space is all that is missing, said Mary Ann Watch, whose three children attend St. Andrew Avellino. ''There's no place for the kids to go to really play,'' she said. Kissena Park is just far enough to require a car trip. ''I can't say, 'Let's just go there for lunch.' ''</p>
        <p>If You're Thinking of Living In | Murray Hill, Queens</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
