<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Snip Their Way to an Unusual Lineup</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL FOOTBALL LEAGUE (NFL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LITSKY, FRANK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D81030F934A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Snip Their Way to an Unusual Lineup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LITSKY, FRANK</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Aug. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giants got down to the 47-man player limit today by waiving 13 players, including Dave Duerson, Mike Perez and Bob Mrosko. When the Giants were done, they were left with a strange team.</p>
        <p>They kept seven rookies, high for a Super Bowl champion. They kept more players on defense (24) than offense (21), reversing normal numbers. They kept 10 linebackers, two above normal, and 9 defensive backs, one or two above normal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Giants got down to the 47-man player limit today by waiving 13 players, including Dave Duerson, Mike Perez and Bob Mrosko. When the Giants were done, they were left with a strange team.</p>
        <p>They kept seven rookies, high for a Super Bowl champion. They kept more players on defense (24) than offense (21), reversing normal numbers. They kept 10 linebackers, two above normal, and 9 defensive backs, one or two above normal.</p>
        <p>The Giants kept only five defensive linemen, two of whom are injured. They have only seven offensive linemen and only two tight ends. More Change to Come</p>
        <p>But by Monday night, when they face the San Francisco 49ers at Giants Stadium in their season opener, the roster is sure to be different. The three unsigned Giants (William Roberts, Mark Ingram and Dave Meggett) play on offense, and when they sign, two defensive players will probably be dropped.</p>
        <p>One person close to the team said Roberts would report very soon. Another said Ingram might miss the first game. Tony Agnone, Meggett's agent, said he and the Giants had agreed on an incentive package for Meggett, but not on his salary.</p>
        <p>The shortage on the defensive line is compounded by injuries to Eric Dorsey, a starting end, and Erik Howard, the starting nose tackle. Coach Ray Handley said the Giants would look for help.</p>
        <p>Dorsey underwent a test today on his sprained right knee. Handley said Howard's back spasms had quieted, perhaps letting him return to practice Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Rodney Hampton, who may replace Ottis Anderson this year as the featured running back, has a sprained right shoulder. He underwent a precautionary medical examination today and might return to practice Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Of the 13 players waived, the best-known were Duerson, a 30-year-old, ninth-year safety; Perez, a quarterback drafted and waived by the Giants in 1988, and Mrosko, a tight end who played for the Giants last year.</p>
        <p>The only other veterans dropped were Tom Rehder, an offensive tackle on the Giants last year, and Richard Ashe, a free-agent tight end.</p>
        <p>The rookies who were dropped were fullback Duane Kinnon, wide receivers Jerry Bouldin and Joey Smith, offensive guard Sean Love, defensive ends Dennis Tripp and Chris Gale, nose tackle Chad Rolen and cornerback Ben Washington. Some of those rookies may be signed as early as Tuesday to the Giants' three-to-five-man practice squad.</p>
        <p>Duerson has Super Bowl rings from the Chicago Bears and the Giants. When the Bears waived him last year, the Giants signed him as a free agent. He is a smart player who has lost speed.</p>
        <p>In his place the Giants kept Lamar McGriggs, a raw rookie safety and also a hard hitter. Duerson was philosophical.</p>
        <p>"I did well in training camp," he said. "Age worked against me. I've enjoyed myself here. I have no regrets. You prepare yourself for days like this." Losing the Battle</p>
        <p>Perez, 26 years old, lost out in his battle to be the No. 3 quarterback to 34-year-old Matt Cavanaugh. Although Perez completed 8 of 9 passes in Saturday's 24-3 preseason loss to the New England Patriots, his fumble led to a Patriots' field goal. But Handley said that Cavanaugh won the job on his own.</p>
        <p>"I like Cavanaugh's experience," the coach said. "I'm real confident if he had to go in a game for any reason, the offense wouldn't miss a beat."</p>
        <p>With Mrosko gone, the Giants' only tight ends are Howard Cross and Zeke Mowatt. That means that the fullback -- Maurice Carthon or Jarrod Bunch -- will sometimes line up as a tight end or an H back.</p>
        <p>The roster now has nine new players. One is James Milling, a Plan B free-agent wide receiver who may be waived when Ingram returns. Another is Mowatt, a former Giant signed six weeks ago as a free agent.</p>
        <p>The seven rookies were all picked up in the draft. They are Bunch (first round), outside linebacker Kanavis McGhee (second), wide receiver Ed McCaffrey (third), offensive tackle Clarence Jones (fourth), outside linebacker Anthony Moss (fifth), inside linebacker Corey Miller (sixth) and McGriggs (eighth).</p>
        <p>There are more rookies than might have been expected because jobs were available. The Giants lost Lee Rouson, David Whitmore and Troy Kyles to Plan B free agency. Mark Bavaro (knee) failed his physical examination before training camp and Stacy Robinson retired.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>WILLIAM SIMMS, the father of PHIL SIMMS, the Giants' quarterback, died Monday in Louisville of a heart attack. He was 63 years old. Simms's wife, DIANA, picked him up at Giants Stadium an hour before practice, and they left immediately for Louisville.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
