<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="TRANS11B" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="994685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DA143CF932A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS -- Agreed to terms with LHP Allen Watson on a one-year contract. Named Tim Mead vice president of communications, Ken Forsch assistant general manager, Jeff Parker director of player development, Larry Babcock manager of baseball information, and Nancy Mazmanian manager of media services.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS -- Designated RHP Ken Robinson for assignment.</p>
        <p>National League  ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS -- Traded INF Mike Bell to the New York Mets for RHP Joe Lisio.  ATLANTA BRAVES -- Agreed to terms with OF Gerald Williams on a one-year contract.  CHICAGO CUBS -- Agreed to terms with 3B Jose Hernandez on a one-year contract.  CINCINNATI REDS -- Agreed to terms with INF Damian Jackson on a one-year contract.  COLORADO ROCKIES -- Agreed to terms with LHP Robbie Beckett on a minor-league contract.  MONTREAL EXPOS -- Agreed to terms with LHP Carlos Perez on a one-year contract.  METS -- Designated INF Mike Bell for assignment.  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES -- Agreed to terms with 1B Rico Brogna on a one-year contract.  SAN DIEGO PADRES -- Sold the contract of RHP Ryan Hancock to Fukuoka of Japan's Pacific League.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS -- Agreed to terms with LHP Allen Watson on a one-year contract. Named Tim Mead vice president of communications, Ken Forsch assistant general manager, Jeff Parker director of player development, Larry Babcock manager of baseball information, and Nancy Mazmanian manager of media services.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS -- Designated RHP Ken Robinson for assignment.</p>
        <p>National League  ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS -- Traded INF Mike Bell to the New York Mets for RHP Joe Lisio.  ATLANTA BRAVES -- Agreed to terms with OF Gerald Williams on a one-year contract.  CHICAGO CUBS -- Agreed to terms with 3B Jose Hernandez on a one-year contract.  CINCINNATI REDS -- Agreed to terms with INF Damian Jackson on a one-year contract.  COLORADO ROCKIES -- Agreed to terms with LHP Robbie Beckett on a minor-league contract.  MONTREAL EXPOS -- Agreed to terms with LHP Carlos Perez on a one-year contract.  METS -- Designated INF Mike Bell for assignment.  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES -- Agreed to terms with 1B Rico Brogna on a one-year contract.  SAN DIEGO PADRES -- Sold the contract of RHP Ryan Hancock to Fukuoka of Japan's Pacific League.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  NBA -- Fined Cleveland Cavaliers coach Mike Fratello $5,000 for remarks about the referees following a Feb. 5 game.  GOLDEN STATE WARRIORS -- Placed G Brian Shaw on the injured list.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  ATLANTA FALCONS -- Signed K Morten Andersen to a three-year contract.  INDIANAPOLIS COLTS -- Named Jay Norvell receivers coach and Steve Champlin director of player development.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  CALGARY FLAMES -- Assigned D Kevin Dahl to Chicago of the IHL.  PITTSBURGH PENGUINS -- Announced the resignation of Donn Patton, president.</p>
        <p>International Hockey League  CHICAGO WOLVES -- Released LW Chad Remackel, D Jason Hehr and D Shawn Reid.  SAN ANTONIO DRAGONS -- Signed LW Dan Lupo.</p>
        <p>LACROSSE</p>
        <p>National Lacrosse League  NEW YORK SAINTS -- Announced Vinny Pfeifer will relinquish coaching duties and remain as general manager. Named Norm Engelke and John Phillips co-coaches.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>National Professional Soccer League  MONTREAL IMPACT -- Fired John Aarnio, coach. Named Paul Kitson interim coach.</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
        <p>WESTERN ATHLETIC CONFERENCE -- Suspended Don Haskins, Texas-El Paso men's basketball coach, one game for publicly criticizing league officials.  GEORGIA TECH -- Announced that John Anselmo, defensive secondary coach, resigned to become head coach at Nassau Community College. Named Bill O'Brien running backs coach.  NORTH CAROLINA -- Named Darrell Moody wide receivers coach.  NORTH DAKOTA STATE -- Announced that Gordon Henderson, women's soccer coach, resigned to accept the same position at Idaho State.  RUTGERS -- Named Jacqueline Atoria assistant athletic trainer.  ST. FRANCIS, IND. -- Named football coach Kevin Donley director of athletic development, Warren Maloney defensive coordinator and Nate Shreffler offensive line coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
