<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cancer Victim to Walk in Fund-Raising Race</title>
    <meta content="LYMPH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1015860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waldenstrom's Macroglobulinemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">White Plains (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mann, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slater, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7D61431F933A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cancer Victim to Walk in Fund-Raising Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slater, Chuck</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT KISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Anne Mann, cancer victim who plans to walk in Human Race in White Plains, NY, to raise funds to combat Waldenstrom's macroglobulinemia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHE has become a familiar figure to the early risers of this town. A petite woman in her 60's starting at the train station and walking briskly through Mount Kisco. Arms pumping, her short, dark hair matting as she proceeds, she walks with purpose, with determination, as if on a mission.</p>
        <p>Anne Mann is walking for her life. Next Saturday, in the Human Race in White Plains, she will be walking 5 kilometers, or 3.1 miles, to raise money to research and combat Waldenstrom's macroglobulinemia, a rare and deceptive cancer with which she is afflicted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHE has become a familiar figure to the early risers of this town. A petite woman in her 60's starting at the train station and walking briskly through Mount Kisco. Arms pumping, her short, dark hair matting as she proceeds, she walks with purpose, with determination, as if on a mission.</p>
        <p>Anne Mann is walking for her life. Next Saturday, in the Human Race in White Plains, she will be walking 5 kilometers, or 3.1 miles, to raise money to research and combat Waldenstrom's macroglobulinemia, a rare and deceptive cancer with which she is afflicted.</p>
        <p>Her story has so many upbeat elements. She is a native of Long Island now living in Mount Kisco. She postponed her college degree to marry and raise three daughters with her husband, Dick Mann. Two years ago, at 61, while working full time, she got the degree, summa cum laude, from Marymount College.</p>
        <p>Then on Oct. 1, 1996 -- ''A day I know well,'' she said -- she learned that routine blood tests indicated that she had Waldenstrom's macroglobulinemia. ''Anne doesn't do things halfway,'' Mr. Mann said.  ''She set out to learn everything she could about Waldenstrom's and what she learned was that there wasn't much to learn.''</p>
        <p>The disease was considered so rare, and so much less aggressive than its cousin, multiple myeloma, that no research had been devoted to it.</p>
        <p>So Mrs. Mann entered last year's Human Race to raise money for Waldenstrom's research. With her daughters, Melinda Mann and Susan Whitten, and her 7-year-old grandson, Francis Whitten, walking with her, she raised $10,000, the most of any walkathon participant.</p>
        <p>''This year,'' she said proudly, ''we have nine walkers and more than $11,000 in pledges not counting any corporate volunteers.''</p>
        <p>It does not promise a happy ending to her story, however. Of the disease, she said, ''Living with it is like living with a time bomb.''</p>
        <p>Waldenstrom's macroglobulinemia, according to the source paper by Dr. Thaddeus M. Rauschi, presented to the Waldenstrom's national support group a year ago, ''is a form of cancer, a hematologic malignancy,'' meaning it affects the blood. It is considered a rare and chronic disease and is treatable but incurable and ''is most closely related to multiple myeloma, with similarities to lymphocytic lymphoma and lymphocytic leukemia.''</p>
        <p>It strikes 1 in 4.4 million people a year, according to the paper. The average onset is 63.8 years, and weakness, fatigue and a tendency to bleed are common symptoms.</p>
        <p>It also weakens the immune system, and the mean survival rate is five years, although secondary, opportunistic illnesses may be the actual cause of death.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mann does not have to be reminded of those facts. ''My red blood count has been dropping over nine months, and I'm awaiting further tests,'' she said. ''The next step is chemotherapy.''</p>
        <p>Still, she walks on -- around Mount Kisco. Keeping in shape is the best defense against the disease, and she has a walkathon to take part in.</p>
        <p>''It is becoming more frustrating, taking me longer to walk my course,'' she conceded. ''I used to do a mile in 12 1/2 minutes. I'm almost down to 15 now. Plus I suffer from nose bleeds, frequently get very tired and don't do much around the house.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mann added, ''She bruises very easily.'' She does, however, still work full time.</p>
        <p>Among the unknowns concerning this cancer is the seemingly high incidence of it in Westchester County. With a population of less than a million, the county should, in a five-year-period, have perhaps one or two Waldenstrom's cases. Yet the Manns can document nearly 20 county residents with the disease in the last few years. ''Statistically,'' Mr. Mann said, ''it makes you wonder.''</p>
        <p>No case causes more wonder than that of 72-year-old Rita Barnett of Bronxville, whose disease was diagnosed three years ago. She sold her house in Yonkers, then recently learned its current occupant has also come down with Waldenstrom's. ''I really have no explanation,'' she said, ''but the odds suggest it's not coincidence.''</p>
        <p>Estelle Siegel, 82, a 20-year survivor of the disease, agreed. ''I know of an astonishing number of cases,'' she said, ''considering the rarity of the disease.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Beverly Deren of the Mount Kisco Medical Group, Mrs. Mann's doctor and a hematologist, is skeptical. ''I haven't seen it in my own practice,'' she said of the supposed clustering. ''We're getting more sophisticated, with better diagnostic techniques, and there's no question people are growing older. There is no obvious toxin in Westchester that I am aware of.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert Kyle of the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minn., who is perhaps the world's leading authority on Waldenstrom's, agreed. ''It's very difficult to know,'' he said. ''There have been clusters with multiple myeloma, but when one checks, it has been a matter of chance. I think the incidence of Waldenstrom's is a little higher, closer to five per million. But the bottom line is, It's still a rare disease. You will find more of it in an area where good medical care is available to the older population. I don't think it's increasing.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Victor M. Sternberg, a periodontist, screens patients for lymph cancers since aggressive care is needed with them. He sees a possible pattern.</p>
        <p>''I have two patients with Waldenstrom's,'' he said. ''The chances of two are very rare for a little practice in Briarcliff Manor. But I can't give you anything statistically significant, anything that's not anecdotal.''</p>
        <p>The questions remain. Research awaits. And so, Mrs. Mann walks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
