<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Family Gives a Bronx Boy A Summer on the Beach</title>
    <meta content="10FRES$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1016123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE FRESH AIR FUND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fresh Air Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Matthew J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EFDE1E31F933A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Family Gives a Bronx Boy A Summer on the Beach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW J. ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenberg, Matthew J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund appeal; focuses on Friendly Town program, nonprofit organization that has been giving urban children summer vacations in the country (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As natives of Northport, N.Y., J. R. and Laurie Morrissey spent their childhood summers rising at dawn and watching the fishing boats head out. They spent their days on the beach, went to barbecues in the evening with family and friends and camped in the Montauk Hills.</p>
        <p>Even after they had married and moved to New York City, the Morrisseys would rent a house in their Long Island hometown each summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As natives of Northport, N.Y., J. R. and Laurie Morrissey spent their childhood summers rising at dawn and watching the fishing boats head out. They spent their days on the beach, went to barbecues in the evening with family and friends and camped in the Montauk Hills.</p>
        <p>Even after they had married and moved to New York City, the Morrisseys would rent a house in their Long Island hometown each summer.</p>
        <p>But something was missing. When they were young, both of their families had invited poor children from New York City into their homes in the summer through the Friendly Town program of the Fresh Air Fund, a nonprofit organization that has been giving urban children brighter summers for more than a century.</p>
        <p>Last year, as their own family was beginning to grow, the Morrisseys decided to play host to a child as their parents had done.</p>
        <p>Many people might wonder why a young couple with a 1-year-old son and a baby daughter on the way would add a 9-year-old boy to their family for two weeks, as they did last summer. And plan to entertain the same boy again this summer, for three weeks.</p>
        <p>For the Morrisseys, who own a women's sportswear company, it is the continuation of a family tradition. ''After Laurie and I talked about it,'' Mr. Morrissey said, ''I mentioned it to my brothers and all the memories came back; the names of kids I'd forgotten and the fun we'd had with them.''</p>
        <p>It was an experience that he wanted to give his own children. Mrs. Morrissey concurred, adding, ''We wanted to give something back the way our parents had.''</p>
        <p>Northport, a village on the North Shore, provided the perfect setting. And Jesse Garcia, who spent two weeks with the Morrisseys last summer, became a part of the family.</p>
        <p>At the Morrisseys' apartment in Stuyvesant Town, it was obvious that Jesse had become a full-fledged member of the family. Jack, the Morrisseys' son, now 2, showed his feelings about Jesse in the way only a toddler can. Pointing at a picture of Jesse, Jack smiled, stamped his feet, jumped up and down and yelled, ''Jesse, Jesse, Jesse.''</p>
        <p>''He became like a big brother to Jack; he'd play ball with him and help him up the stairs while he was learning to walk,'' Mrs. Morrissey said.</p>
        <p>Danny, one of the Morrisseys' 15 nieces and nephews who live in and around Northport, became instant pals with Jesse. ''They're the same age and love baseball, basketball and soccer,'' Mrs. Morrissey said. ''They've got so much in common that you'd think they had grown up in the same town and known each other forever.''</p>
        <p>Jesse also gave the Morrisseys a new perspective on a place they had known their whole lives, and by their own admission, taken for granted. When he first encountered the beach, he dived head first into the sand and did cartwheels. He loved the feeling of the sand against his feet and the cushioning it provided when he fell. In the South Bronx, where he lives in the John Purroy Mitchell Houses with his mother, stepfather and three brothers, the only sand he had known was in a sandbox.</p>
        <p>''I like boogie-boarding,'' said Jesse, when asked what he liked to do at the beach. ''It is so much fun, even when I fall and get scraped on the sand.''</p>
        <p>Like many of the children in the Friendly Town program, Jesse extends his time with the Morrisseys after the summer.</p>
        <p>During his Christmas vacation, Jesse spent four days in Northport with the Morrisseys. He attended the christening of the Morrisseys' daughter, Joie, and this weekend, Jesse is in Northport to celebrate Danny's first communion.</p>
        <p>Besides her role as a host parent, Mrs. Morrissey is also the Fresh Air Fund representative for Suffolk County. There are six ''friendly towns'' under her supervision. She helps recruit families and coordinates transportation for visiting children.</p>
        <p>Last year about 6,200 children stayed with host families. As of Friday, about 2,700 families had signed up for the Friendly Town Program for this summer. Families who want to be hosts may call (800) 367-0003. The Fresh Air Fund also sends children to programs at summer camps. Anyone interested in making a tax-deductible contribution to the fund should send it to the Fresh Air Fund, 1040 Avenue of the Americas, New York, N.Y. 10018.</p>
        <p>THE FRESH AIR FUND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
