<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teacher Unions, Long Far Apart, Discuss a Merger</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="617154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL EDUCATION ASSN (NEA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN FEDERATION OF TEACHERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CELIS, WILLIAM 3D</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EDUCATION PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DA153CF930A15755C0A965958260" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teacher Unions, Long Far Apart, Discuss a Merger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM CELIS 3d</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CELIS, WILLIAM 3D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After decades of hostilities, the nation's two main teachers' unions are talking about merging.</p>
        <p>The issue will be on the table at the annual meeting of the 2.1-million-member National Education Association in San Francisco next week. The other union, the 820,000-member American Federation of Teachers, has long been open to such a merger. And although people from both unions say that significant differences remain and that an actual merger is a long way off, they also say merging makes sense now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After decades of hostilities, the nation's two main teachers' unions are talking about merging.</p>
        <p>The issue will be on the table at the annual meeting of the 2.1-million-member National Education Association in San Francisco next week. The other union, the 820,000-member American Federation of Teachers, has long been open to such a merger. And although people from both unions say that significant differences remain and that an actual merger is a long way off, they also say merging makes sense now.</p>
        <p>Once fiercely competitive, the two unions are now more closely aligned on education issues, officials from both unions say. At a time when organized labor is perceived to be losing influence, a combined union would give teachers more muscle to push for education improvements, an effort now somewhat splintered between the two organizations.</p>
        <p>"It would be the largest union merger in history," said Victor Gotbaum, former executive director of District Council 37 of the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees in New York and a senior research fellow at the City University Graduate Center. "For the labor movement, it would be magnificent. I just hope it happens." Opposition in State Groups</p>
        <p>Union officials said a merger would eliminate the costly and contentious competition for the right to represent teachers in contract talks with local school systems.</p>
        <p>But the idea faces stiff challenges from several state affiliates of the education association, including those in New York and New Jersey. There is still considerable sentiment that the N.E.A. is as much a professional association as it is a labor union, and there is suspicion of the A.F.T.'s affiliation with the A.F.L.-C.I.O.</p>
        <p>"My organization has severe reservations," said Betty Kraemer, president of the New Jersey Education Association, the second largest N.E.A. state affiliate after California, with 142,000 members. "Although we support and believe in the labor movement, we now have an independent organization solely focused on education. We want our N.E.A. free and independent."</p>
        <p>The current movement was initiated by N.E.A. affiliates in Rosemount, Minn., and San Francisco. Although similar merger talks failed in the mid-1970's, N.E.A. officials said they expected that the 8,500 delegates attending the July 2-5 convention in San Francisco would approve a measure authorizing them to begin talks with the A.F.T. and its parent, the A.F.L.-C.I.O. Costly Union-Union Battles</p>
        <p>"The local affiliates were just tired of spending tons of money fighting each other," said Keith Geiger, president of the N.E.A. "They came to the conclusion that spending all that time and money isn't improving education and isn't improving the plight of their members."</p>
        <p>Albert Shanker, president of the A.F.T., which has long been open to the idea of combining the two groups, said he welcomed the dialogue.</p>
        <p>"There has been a realization that we really are in harmony on the major educational issues, that we shouldn't be spending valuable resources, time and money fighting each other," Mr. Shanker said. "It's not worthwhile. We can be more effective."</p>
        <p>A merger in the short run is possible, but not very likely, said officials of both organizations. Mr. Shanker said: "What is more likely is local and state affiliates that want to get together could do so. We'll probably see a step-by-step approach." Success in Minnesota</p>
        <p>The overtures between the two teacher groups, which are two of the nation's largest unions, have grown warmer in recent years as they have become more alike. The N.E.A. has increasingly assumed the role of a union to protect teachers from salary concessions in recessionary times.</p>
        <p>Officials from both groups said that combining them would give teachers a united voice to prop up flagging public support for teachers. Across the nation, teachers have incurred public wrath when they protested small or no pay increases by refusing to perform duties not specified in their contracts. The tactic, called "work to the rule," resulted in teachers refusing to help students before or after school or to sponsor extracurricular events.</p>
        <p>The benefits of mergers have been played out in Rosemount, Minn., a small community south of St. Paul. Last October, the Rosemount Federation of Teachers and the Rosemount Education Association merged into a single unit called the Dakota County United Educators.</p>
        <p>The two unions, each with about 700 members, had fought bitterly over the years for membership and for the right to represent all the district's teachers in contract talks. With neither side able to recruit a majority of members, the campaign to be recognized as the teachers' collective bargaining agent consumed an inordinate amount of time.</p>
        <p>"Members in the last election said 'enough is enough,' " said Renee Scholen, staff representative for the merged union. "They said, 'We want to belong to the same organization.' We are all fighting for the same thing."</p>
        <p>After the merger, Ms. Scholen said, the new union was able to elect its slate of school board candidates, something the two unions had never been able to do. "We have a singular purpose now," she said. "We aren't doing scattershot types of things."</p>
        <p>For all the similarities the two groups profess to share, Mr. Geiger and Mr. Shanker warned that significant obstacles remained before the unions could merge, and they added that a merger was not a foregone conclusion. Not the least of the hurdles are two very different organizational cultures.</p>
        <p>The N.E.A. was founded in 1857 as a professional society for educators and only slowly evolved into a collective bargaining agent for teachers. The A.F.T., founded in 1917, was a union from the outset, drawing heavily from the cities and admitting women and members of minorities into its ranks much sooner than the N.E.A, whose members are mostly from suburban and rural school systems. 'Not Insurmountable Issues'</p>
        <p>The two groups also differ in structure. The N.E.A., for instance, uses a secret ballot, while the A.F.T. conducts roll-call balloting. It is a small point but one that was partly responsible for unhinging the merger talks in 1973 and 1974. Another issue that derailed talks 20 years ago and is expected to be a source of contention again is the N.E.A.'s affiliation with organized labor.</p>
        <p>Meshing the two cultures is not expected to be easy, but Mr. Shanker of the A.F.T. said: "These are not insurmountable issues. These are not lines in the sand."</p>
        <p>Still, he and the N.E.A. leadership face a hard sell to some influential state N.E.A. affiliates, who are vehement in preserving the N.E.A.'s 136-year history of independence. Mr. Geiger said that distinction was expected to be vigorously debated next week at the N.E.A. convention.</p>
        <p>"We can share common goals and share common ends, but that doesn't mean organizationally that we operate the same way," said Greg Nash, vice president of the National Education Association of New York State, with 35,000 members. Its delegates are expected to vote against opening merger talks with the A.F.T.</p>
        <p>"We stand in opposition," Mr. Nash said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
