<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Thompson, Trouble on Slide but Titles in Pool</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="706452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="SWIMMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SWIMMING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LITSKY, FRANK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E0DB1030F936A2575BC0A962958260" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Thompson, Trouble on Slide but Titles in Pool</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LITSKY, FRANK</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, Aug. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On May 31, Jenny Thompson broke her left forearm so badly that she needed a titanium plate and seven screws to keep it in place. Tonight, she completed a storybook comeback by qualifying for the United States team for the world swimming championships three weeks from now in Rome.</p>
        <p>Thompson is a 21-year-old Stanford University senior from Dover, N.H. As a world-class swimmer since 14, she has achieved almost everything possible in the sport. She holds the world record of 54.48 seconds for the 100-meter freestyle. She has won two Olympic gold medals and 11 previous national titles. She was the 1993 United States swimmer of the year. And much more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On May 31, Jenny Thompson broke her left forearm so badly that she needed a titanium plate and seven screws to keep it in place. Tonight, she completed a storybook comeback by qualifying for the United States team for the world swimming championships three weeks from now in Rome.</p>
        <p>Thompson is a 21-year-old Stanford University senior from Dover, N.H. As a world-class swimmer since 14, she has achieved almost everything possible in the sport. She holds the world record of 54.48 seconds for the 100-meter freestyle. She has won two Olympic gold medals and 11 previous national titles. She was the 1993 United States swimmer of the year. And much more.</p>
        <p>On this, the first of seven days of the Phillips 66 national championships and world championship trials, she accomplished something new. In the first final of the meet, she won the women's 100-meter freestyle tonight by 2 feet in 55.50 seconds.</p>
        <p>The first two in most events will make the United States team. Behind Thompson, there was a second-place tie between Angel Martino of Tuscaloosa, Ala., and Nicole Haislett of St. Petersburg, Fla., each in 55.84 seconds. They will swim off at a time to be determined to decide which swimmer competes in the 100 in Rome, although both will be on the team for relays. A Friend Fell on Her</p>
        <p>Thompson is a free spirit, which is one reason she was hurt. She and a friend were on a water slide when they decided to flip over on their backs. The friend lost his balance and fell on her arm.</p>
        <p>"It was real sore," she said, "but I didn't think it was broken. I made a sling out of T-shirts. I slept fine that night. I was in total denial. I told myself, 'Well, I can move my arm, so it can't be broken. I must have hurt soft tissue.'</p>
        <p>"The next day, I went to a hospital emergency room to make sure it wasn't broken. They took X-rays. It was broken, all right. My first reaction was panic. They told me I could swim next year. I said, 'No, I need to swim this year.' "</p>
        <p>Thompson got back in the pool, but all she could do was kick. She kicked so much that she got blisters on her feet. On June 13, only 10 days after surgery, the stitches came out and she could use her arms again in the pool. The left arm hurt and still does when she swims, partly because the muscle tone is not fully back.</p>
        <p>Five weeks after the surgery, Thompson wanted to swim in a meet.</p>
        <p>"Not yet," said Richard Quick, her coach at Stanford.</p>
        <p>They argued.</p>
        <p>"I'm going to cry if I don't swim," Thompson said.</p>
        <p>"So cry," Quick said.</p>
        <p>She cried. But she did not race. Two weeks later, in the Janet Evans Invitational in Los Angeles, Quick let her swim -- 11 races in three days.</p>
        <p>"I was scared," she said. "I didn't know what would happen. But I was grateful just to be racing again." '90 Percent Back'</p>
        <p>Quick was encouraged then, even more now. Before this morning's trial heats, he said, "My guess is that she's 90 percent back."</p>
        <p>Thompson was not sure. But in the trials, her time of 56.32 seconds was second fastest to Martino's 55.22. She felt better.</p>
        <p>In the final, she felt wonderful. At 50 meters, Martino led in 26.74 seconds, a world-record pace. Thompson was second, 2 1/2 feet behind and unhurried. She caught up at 75 meters, and she said later she remembered that any time she was even at 75 meters, she usually won. And she did.</p>
        <p>Quick was proud.</p>
        <p>"That's the best-managed race I've ever seen you swim," the coach told Thompson.</p>
        <p>Thompson smiled at that.</p>
        <p>"The arm gets sore and tight around the fracture," she said later. "I tried not to doubt myself. But I had a more lighthearted approach tonight because I didn't want to put pressure on myself to win. I didn't expect to win. So this means more to me than my world record. I was real proud of myself."</p>
        <p>As for the plate in her arm, she treats it almost as a joke.</p>
        <p>"It has little holes for the screws," she said. "It looks like the inside of a Twix cookie bar."</p>
        <p>SPLASHES</p>
        <p>SETH VAN NEERDEN of Fort Lauderdale, Fla., won the men's 100-meter breast-stroke by 3 feet in 1:01.40, equaling NELSON DIEBEL's 1992 American record. Second-place ERIC WUNDERLICH (1:01.95) also made the world championship team. So did 17-year-old ALLISON WAGNER of Gainesville, Fla. (4:40.27, the fastest in the world this year) and KRISTINE QUANCE of Northridge, Calif. (4:43.53) in the women's 400-meter individual medley and CHAD CARVIN of Laguna Hills, Calif. (1:49.19) and JOHN PIERSMA of Huntsville, Ala. (1:49.79) in the men's 200-meter freestyle. . . . The meet is being swum over a 50-meter long course in the Indiana University Natatorium.  SWIMMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
