<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Partner Testifies That Tax Shelter Of Hedge Fund Was Legitimate</title>
    <meta content="Y09HED$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/09/business/09HEDG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1503187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Shelters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Partnerships</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long-Term Capital Management Lp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Internal Revenue Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scholes, Myron S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Partnerships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Long-Term Capital Management</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Capital Holdings</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Scholes, Myron S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DB123DF93AA35754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Partner Testifies That Tax Shelter Of Hedge Fund Was Legitimate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Partner Testifies That Tax Shelter of Hedge Fund Was Legitimate</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David Cay</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN, July 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nobel Prize-winning economist Myron S Scholes who was partner in Long-Term Capital Management, hedge fund whose 1998 collapse threatened global financial panic, testifies in trial that will determine whether he and his partners must pay $56 million in taxes and penalties; trial is important test of government's resolve in its battle against tax shelters; Scholes testifies that tax shelter of hedge fund was legitimate; shelter involved acquiring stock in four major companies owned by three people in London who participated in separate computer-leasing tax shelter; stock had value of $375 million for tax purposes but just $4 million in open market; Long-Term partners used $106 million of tax value in 1997 to wipe out equal amount of gains from partnerships' investments; Internal Revenue Service audit declared deal elaborate and clever scam; is seeking $40 million in taxes, plus another $16 million in penalties; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Nobel Prize-winning economist who was a partner in Long-Term Capital Management, the hedge fund whose 1998 collapse threatened a global financial panic, testified today in a trial that will determine whether he and his partners must pay $56 million in taxes and penalties.</p>
        <p>The trial, which is in its third week and is expected to last several weeks more, is an important test of the government's resolve in its battle against tax shelters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The trial in the Long-Term Capital Management case is an important test of how serious the government is in its battle against tax shelters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Nobel Prize-winning economist who was a partner in Long-Term Capital Management, the hedge fund whose 1998 collapse threatened a global financial panic, testified today in a trial that will determine whether he and his partners must pay $56 million in taxes and penalties.</p>
        <p>The trial, which is in its third week and is expected to last several weeks more, is an important test of the government's resolve in its battle against tax shelters.</p>
        <p>The economist, Myron S. Scholes, who developed a technique to value stock options that is now a standard, repeatedly invoked two words -- risk and profit -- in response to questions from his lawyer, David J. Curtin of McKee Nelson in Washington. The questioning was intended to show that the partnership, Long-Term Capital Holdings, used a legitimate tax shelter, one that Dr. Scholes worked hard to imbue with ''economic substance,'' making sure everyone involved had a real risk of losses and potential for profits.</p>
        <p>The shelter involved acquiring stock in four major companies owned by three people in London who participated in a separate computer-leasing tax shelter. The stock had a value of $375 million for tax purposes but just $4 million in the open market. The Long-Term partners used $106 million of the tax value in 1997 to wipe out an equal amount of gains from the partnership's investments.</p>
        <p>The I.R.S., in an audit, declared the deal an elaborate and clever sham. The agency is seeking $40 million in taxes, plus another $16 million in penalties, because, it says, the partners were tax sophisticates who knew better. Dr. Scholes, for example, is the author of a book on business tax planning.</p>
        <p>At first, answering his lawyer's questions, Dr. Scholes gave a little cough, his right shoulder twitched and his voice was unsure. His answers were self-deprecating, as when he said he did not hold himself out as an expert on taxes.</p>
        <p>But over the next three hours his demeanor slowly transformed until he was the confident professor, giving detailed answers in a firm voice that demonstrated a command of intricate financial concepts and arcane tax rules.</p>
        <p>Regarding the shelter, Dr. Scholes testified that he knew that ''we had to have a profit, or expect to profit, from it apart from the tax transaction'' if the deal was to pass muster with the I.R.S.</p>
        <p>Dr. Scholes said he ordered analysis, went to dinners and meetings, and even flew to London to meet the owners of the tax-favored stock to learn just how the shares had acquired their valuable tax attributes.</p>
        <p>The stock had a tax value more than 90 times its market price because it was used in computer leasing deals that were themselves tax shelters for the Advanta Corporation, Electronic Data Systems, the Interpublic Group of Companies, Rhône-Poulenc Rohrer and the computer leasing arm of General Electric.</p>
        <p>Those shelters gave tax breaks to the American companies and gave the three London residents stock with an artificially inflated tax price, or basis.</p>
        <p>''To go forward, we had to have parallel tracks to understand the underlying economics as well as the tax matters,'' Dr. Scholes testified.</p>
        <p>''The only way I could see this working potentially was as an investment,'' he said, adding moments later that ''we were not going to buy the tax benefits.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Scholes calculated potential profits and losses, including the price of an option the three Londoners bought that guaranteed they could not lose money by investing in Long-Term Capital.</p>
        <p>He also figured out how to loan them millions of dollars, though he said he arranged to do so at the lowest possible interest rates, rather than the more common banking practice of charging as much as possible.</p>
        <p>The shelter owners in London were let into the Long-Term Capital fund even though it had been closed to other investors. They contributed their stock with the high tax value, got back shares in the partnership at the stock's market price and then withdrew 14 months later with what the fund calculated was a profit of 22 percent for their brief involvement in the long-term fund.</p>
        <p>Dr. Scholes is expected to face cross-examination by Charles P. Hurley of the Justice Department when the trial resumes Wednesday. His testimony contrasted with that of an earlier witness, John M. Sykes III, a tax partner at Shearman &amp; Sterling in New York who wrote legal opinions on the computer-leasing tax shelters. Under questioning by Mr. Hurley, Mr. Sykes acknowledged that he never checked out the economic and other assumptions of the deals he gave opinions on. Mr. Sykes said he did not write down many significant points of his analysis, and that even when one of the computer deals was completely reversed after it was completed, it did not prompt him to reconsider his opinion on the validity of the tax shelters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sykes's answers prompted Judge Janet Bond Arterton of the United States District Court here to question him closely about the reasons that Shearman &amp; Sterling gave a weak opinion on one tax shelter, saying it was ''more likely than not'' to survive an audit, and later issued a much stronger opinion that a virtually identical deal ''should'' survive. Mr. Sykes said he only signed one of the opinions.</p>
        <p>The judge also pressed Mr. Sykes to explain why he never checked the assumptions passed on to him by the three parties to the deal, all of whom used the same investment banker, Babcock &amp; Brown in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Judge Arterton asked: ''How, in the business of writing opinions, can you rely on the representations of strangers?''</p>
        <p>''That's a good question,'' Mr. Sykes said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
