<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alexander Gives Iowa a Big Try but Still Lags</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="828411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS: IN THE PACK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IOWA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IOWA, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALEXANDER, LAMAR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NAGOURNEY, ADAM ROBERT DOLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDREW LAMAR 'LAMAR'ALEXANDER JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALCOLM S 'STEVE' FORBES JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EFD81439F934A35751C0A960958260" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alexander Gives Iowa a Big Try but Still Lags</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NAGOURNEY, ADAM ROBERT DOLE;</byline>
      <dateline>SIOUX CITY, Iowa, Feb. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to the Iowa Republican Presidential caucuses, Steve Forbes may  have spent the most money, and Bob Dole may have corralled the most elected officials. But no one has paid a more sustained tribute to Iowa than Lamar Alexander.</p>
        <p>Since he first set foot here as an unannounced Presidential candidate -- at a college commencement speech southeast of Des Moines on May 8, 1993 -- the former Governor of Tennessee has dwarfed his Republican rivals in the number of days spent in this state (75, as of today).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When it comes to the Iowa Republican Presidential caucuses, Steve Forbes may  have spent the most money, and Bob Dole may have corralled the most elected officials. But no one has paid a more sustained tribute to Iowa than Lamar Alexander.</p>
        <p>Since he first set foot here as an unannounced Presidential candidate -- at a college commencement speech southeast of Des Moines on May 8, 1993 -- the former Governor of Tennessee has dwarfed his Republican rivals in the number of days spent in this state (75, as of today).</p>
        <p>He broadcast his first television commercials last June, before most voters  had heard of Steve Forbes. Mr. Alexander has marketed himself with Madison Avenue efficiency, linking his candidacy to a black-and-red plaid shirt, which is affixed to his posters, his commercials, his banners, his supporters and to the candidate himself.</p>
        <p>As he moves from motel meeting room to college campus across Iowa in this final week, Mr. Alexander employs well-rehearsed gambits, trying to influence undecided voters: He decries the wave of negative television commercials, a line which invariably wins applause. He presents himself as the only candidate capable of defeating Mr. Clinton, sowing doubts about Senator Dole and Mr. Forbes in the process.</p>
        <p>"I think one reason that so many people are undecided in Iowa is they believe that what Senator Dole and Steve Forbes are saying about each other is substantially true," he said, at a campaign stop in Waverly on Monday.</p>
        <p>He has even taken to criticizing Republicans in Congress as he tries to find  a place for himself on the field.</p>
        <p>"We Republicans have a bad habit of getting to Washington and start talking like we spend all our life in a think tank or in a Congressional subcommittee,"  he said in another campaign speech.</p>
        <p>But with the caucuses only days away, even his own polls of likely caucusgoers show Mr. Alexander battling for third place and prepared to settle for fourth. After three years of effort here, and notwithstanding his considerable skills as a campaigner, Mr. Alexander has reached a point where he  will measure his success next Monday by the failures of Mr. Forbes and Senator Dole.</p>
        <p>Settled in a brown leather armchair on his 13-seat campaign jet and picking at a bowl of fruit salad, Mr. Alexander acknowledged today that the most he is expecting here is the kind of "very muddled outcome" that would give him passage to New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander's advisers say he will stay in the race no matter the outcome here. They are counting on Mr. Forbes's candidacy to crumble, and assert that their own polling shows Mr. Forbes's support is dropping in the face of what they believe to be a backlash to his negative television advertisements.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander tried to feed that resentment today, referring to Mr. Forbes as a "zillionaire," and arguing that the Iowa caucuses and New Hampshire primaries  "run the risk of being relegated to oblivion by this wave of television ads."</p>
        <p>And Mr. Alexander said he was not concerned that he had been eclipsed. "What  I've always assumed is, since I've started from zero and wasn't in the world of  Washington where all the news was going on, that this was going to be very step  by step," Mr. Alexander said.</p>
        <p>"What I eventually have to do is get out front enough so that I have a chance to present myself," he said. "I have to get on stage." But after all this time in Iowa, Mr. Alexander is still looking for a way to get on stage.</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Alexander's recent difficulties are beyond his control. He has, as much as any of the other Republicans, attempted to present himself as a candidate from outside Washington. Mr. Forbes was able to wrestle that distinction from him, leaving Mr. Alexander searching for a way to distinguish himself.</p>
        <p>In Iowa, Mr. Alexander has attracted respectable crowds, but they are not particularly effusive. At some stops, he has not attracted a single television camera. With the exception of Mr. Forbes, he is rarely mentioned by his opponents, an accurate measure of the threat they consider him.</p>
        <p>Usually only a handful of people in his crowds wear the red-and-black plaid shirts handed out at the welcoming desk. While some county chairmen report support for an Alexander candidacy, they say he has not matched the organizational support of either Mr. Dole or Senator Phil Gramm of Texas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander's difficulties in making an impression are beginning to frustrate his supporters, who are worried about how he might fare here. "I want  to say, 'Lamar, please, on behalf of everyone in this room, we need you to get higher on the radar screen,' " said Mark Green, 44, a professor of management at Simpson College in Indianola after listening to Mr. Alexander speak for an hour  at the school. "Crystallize for us in this room -- tell us exactly what you are  going to do."</p>
        <p>In fairness, it is not that Mr. Alexander is not saying anything. Indeed, Mr. Alexander is pushing what his own advisers term a series of radical proposals. It is just that they are sometimes lost in the plaid shirts and the piano playing of his scripted days of campaigning.</p>
        <p>What's more, they are the kind of ideas that are unusual enough -- and, Mr. Alexander acknowledges, undeveloped enough -- that they might cause him some difficulties if his wish is granted after New Hampshire and he finds himself pressured to more fully explain his ideas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander would cancel all Federal welfare programs, and take money now allocated to Aid to Families with Dependent Children, to Women, Infants and Children, and the food stamps program, and return it to communities, leaving it  to nonprofit community charity funds to administer the programs.</p>
        <p>The Federal Government would require communities to use the money for those same social services for a five-year transition program. Mr. Alexander said he was confident that communities would not cut back their spending, and that it would not produce a shift of income out of poor neighborhoods to wealthy ones. "If I'm wrong about that in five years, we can take it back," he said.</p>
        <p>POLITICS: IN THE PACK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
