<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Write-Offs Result in a Loss At Dow Jones in 4th Quarter</title>
    <meta content="Y10DOW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980211T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="994328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY REPORTS: THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dow Jones &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabrikant, Geraldine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEEDA1F3DF933A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Write-Offs Result in a Loss At Dow Jones in 4th Quarter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabrikant, Geraldine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dow Jones &amp; Co reports fourth-quarter net loss of $889.3 million compared with profit of $59.6 million in 1996 fourth quarter; excluding one-time items, profits fell 24 percent, to $38.7 million; revenues rose 2.7 percent, to $689.5 million; chart (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dow Jones &amp; Company reported a big net loss yesterday for the fourth quarter, mostly because of a write-off connected to the reorganization of its financial information business.</p>
        <p>The company, which also owns The Wall Street Journal and other publications, had a net loss of $889.3 million, or $9.22 a diluted share, compared with a 1996 fourth-quarter profit of $59.6 million, or 62 cents a share. The loss this year included a charge of $922.5 million for the financial data business, Dow Jones Markets, which was formerly known as Telerate and which the company has put up for sale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dow Jones &amp; Company reported a big net loss yesterday for the fourth quarter, mostly because of a write-off connected to the reorganization of its financial information business.</p>
        <p>The company, which also owns The Wall Street Journal and other publications, had a net loss of $889.3 million, or $9.22 a diluted share, compared with a 1996 fourth-quarter profit of $59.6 million, or 62 cents a share. The loss this year included a charge of $922.5 million for the financial data business, Dow Jones Markets, which was formerly known as Telerate and which the company has put up for sale.</p>
        <p>Excluding one-time items, Dow Jones profits fell 24 percent, to $38.7 million, or 40 cents a share.</p>
        <p>Investors barely reacted to the report, sending the stock up 37.5 cents, to $51.</p>
        <p>Peter Appert, a media analyst at BT Alex. Brown, said that the earnings were in line with expectations but that the write-off was larger than expected. Still, he said, ''they are letting go of Telerate and going forward, so they are much better off.''</p>
        <p>Dow Jones had indicated that it would have a loss in the quarter, figures for which are generally released during the last week of January. This year, however, the company said it was pushing back release of the earnings report because the write-offs were complex and took more time to prepare. Several analysts who follow the company said, however, that they believed that Dow Jones had been waiting to evaluate the range of bids for potential buyers of the financial information business.</p>
        <p>According to one person involved in the discussions, the company has received an offer of $500 million for Dow Jones Markets from Bridge News, which is owned by the investment company Welsh Carson, Anderson &amp; Stowe. Other offers, from Cantor, Fitzgerald Securities; ILX Systems, a unit of the Thomson Corporation, and the Primark Corporation,  are said to be lower.</p>
        <p>However, the bidding is not yet officially over. Bids could be raised -- or dropped -- in subsequent rounds, and a final decision is not expected for several weeks.</p>
        <p>Dow Jones acquired Telerate in a series of transactions for a total of $1.6 billion between 1985 and 1989. It had already written off $200 million and is carrying the business on its books at $1.4 billion.</p>
        <p>Several of the younger members of the Bancroft family, which controls Dow Jones, have been pushing for a sale of the unit, but the decision to put it on the block has apparently not assuaged their dissatisfaction. Two cousins -- William C. Cox 3d and Elisabeth Goth -- are still said to be unhappy with the overall performance of the company, according to a person close to the family.</p>
        <p>In addition, this person said that  Mr. Cox and Ms. Goth had learned that the chairman of Dow Jones, Peter R. Kann, had been attributing the stock's increase in recent months to his management team in talks with some investment groups; Mr. Cox and Ms. Goth are said to be upset because they believe the increase in the stock price is attributable to pressure from them and outside investors to improve the operations of the company. In the last year, the stock has risen roughly 25 percent, from less than $40 a share. A Dow Jones spokesman said yesterday that stock prices were always the result of a large number of factors.</p>
        <p>Still, the Bancroft family is hardly unified in its approach, because older family members have generally been more supportive of the management. Indeed, at a regularly scheduled family meeting in Boston several weeks ago with Roy Hammer, the influential lawyer who is a trustee of many family trusts that own Dow Jones stock, the older family members still appeared quite supportive of the management, according to a person who attended the meeting.</p>
        <p>As for the most recent quarter's results, there were other one-time items, in addition to the cost of the Dow Jones Markets restructuring. The company also took charges to restructure its television operations and IDD Enterprises L.P., a financial publishing subsidiary; it also  recorded a gain on the sale of a newsprint mill and related timberlands.</p>
        <p>The company said that revenues in the fourth quarter rose 2.7 percent, to $689.5 million.</p>
        <p>Though the company said The Wall Street Journal had a strong year, The Journal is part of its business publishing segment, which also includes some TV businesses and the interactive publishing group. Because of write-offs in those businesses, the business publishing unit reported fourth-quarter operating income of $52.6 million, down from $66.6 million in the period a year earlier.</p>
        <p>The company said that advertising linage at The Wall Street Journal rose 8.6 percent for the quarter.</p>
        <p>The financial information services segment includes the results of Dow Jones Markets, Dow Jones Newswires and the Dow Jones Indexes group. For the quarter, those businesses had a loss of $1 billion, compared with income last year of $36.9 million.  COMPANY REPORTS: THE MEDIA BUSINESS  Correction:  February 11, 1998, Wednesday  Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day yesterday about the fourth-quarter results of Dow Jones &amp; Company misstated the name of a possible suitor for its financial information business, and described that company's ownership incorrectly. It is Bridge Information Systems, not Bridge News, and it is owned in part, not entirely, by Welsh Carson, Anderson &amp; Stowe.</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 11, 1998, Wednesday  Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day yesterday about the fourth-quarter results of Dow Jones &amp; Company misstated the name of a possible suitor for its financial information business, and described that company's ownership incorrectly. It is Bridge Information Systems, not Bridge News, and it is owned in part, not entirely, by Welsh Carson, Anderson &amp; Stowe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 11, 1998, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day yesterday about the fourth-quarter results of Dow Jones &amp; Company misstated the name of a possible suitor for its financial information business, and described that company's ownership incorrectly. It is Bridge Information Systems, not Bridge News, and it is owned in part, not entirely, by Welsh Carson, Anderson &amp; Stowe.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: February 11, 1998, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day yesterday about the fourth-quarter results of Dow Jones &amp; Company misstated the name of a possible suitor for its financial information business, and described that company's ownership incorrectly. It is Bridge Information Systems, not Bridge News, and it is owned in part, not entirely, by Welsh Carson, Anderson &amp; Stowe.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
