<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Soldier's Story</title>
    <meta content="WLN085141" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/21/magazine/21QUESTIONS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1696137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 8-21-05: QUESTIONS FOR KAYLA WILLIAMS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE4DC113CF932A1575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Soldier's Story</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Soldier's Story</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deborah Solomon</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: Your new book,''Love My Rifle More Than You,'' brings a chick-lit sensibility to your stories about life in Iraq and essentially characterizes our male soldiers as so many frat boys groping women.</p>
        <p>I just couldn't believe that guys would hit on me when I was the dirtiest that I ever was in life, with dirt caked into my hair. We only had enough water to bathe once a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The former Army sergeant and memoirist talks about sex in the military, Abu Ghraib, equipment shortages and how troops in Iraq spend their downtime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: Your new book,''Love My Rifle More Than You,'' brings a chick-lit sensibility to your stories about life in Iraq and essentially characterizes our male soldiers as so many frat boys groping women.</p>
        <p>I just couldn't believe that guys would hit on me when I was the dirtiest that I ever was in life, with dirt caked into my hair. We only had enough water to bathe once a week.</p>
        <p>Your book describes an appalling game played by the soldiers, in which they toss rocks at you and aim for your breasts.</p>
        <p>They would also throw rocks at each other's penises for fun. It was very strange to see.</p>
        <p>But in a way it was natural. When you're in Iraq, you search for just about anything to ease the mind-numbing tedium of having nowhere to go and nothing to do.</p>
        <p>As a college-educated American who originally enlisted to study Arabic and national security, couldn't you think of any other way to spend your free time? Why not read a book or play baseball?</p>
        <p>I read a book a day. And we played fake baseball using a stick and rocks.</p>
        <p>What is the Army policy on sex between soldiers?</p>
        <p>It isn't covered in General Order No. 1A, which is the main order for soldiers deployed in Iraq, which says you can't drink alcohol or have porn or keep pets, which everyone does anyhow. My personal chain of command said if you are married, don't do it, and if you're not married, just don't get caught. A lot of girls got sent home pregnant.</p>
        <p>Are you concerned that your book might be taken as evidence of the drawbacks of enlisting women, who are generally believed to lack the physical prowess of men?</p>
        <p>Not really. It's becoming tougher to deal with all new recruits, as Americans as a whole become lazier and fatter. It used to be that guys would come into the Army after playing football in high school, and have some physical training. Now, a lot of guys who come into the Army have been playing video games for years and can't run, can't do a push-up.</p>
        <p>Your book makes it sound as if even your own family doesn't take female soldiers too seriously.</p>
        <p>My mother asked me if I had been to the Pyramids. I think she thought I was on a student-exchange program.</p>
        <p>The most disturbing part of your book recounts your own mistreatment of an Iraqi prisoner in Mosul, whom you were instructed to humiliate after he was brought before you stark naked.</p>
        <p>I said a couple of things along the lines of ''You think you can please a woman with that thing?'' I felt horrible about it.</p>
        <p>Were you surprised when you first heard about the abuses at Abu Ghraib?</p>
        <p>I was not shocked that detainee abuse had happened. But everyone I knew was stunned that it would come out publicly. You have to be really stupid to photograph yourself breaking the law.</p>
        <p>Do you feel that the Army, which is having so much trouble enlisting new recruits, is generally supportive of the men and women who serve?</p>
        <p>In terms of equipment, no. I didn't have plates for my flak vest, and we didn't have armor for our vehicles.</p>
        <p>Did you consider buying the bulletproof plates for your vest with your own money?</p>
        <p>They're very expensive. I think they are $250 apiece, and I didn't have that kind of money. When I left the Army after five years, I was earning about $30,000 a year.</p>
        <p>I hear you are marrying a soldier who suffered a serious head wound in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Yes, Brian has a traumatic brain injury, and some small pieces of shrapnel are still in his brain. I've been doing all the paperwork involved with trying to get him V.A. benefits. It's ridiculous. They actually said to us at a meeting, ''We lost your paperwork.''</p>
        <p>Although you are trained in intelligence, do you think the government would ever hire you again to work in that field?</p>
        <p>I think there is a definite chance that this book may close certain doors for me.</p>
        <p>Deborah Solomon</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 8-21-05: QUESTIONS FOR KAYLA WILLIAMS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
