<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Cantonese Menu of Seafood Delicacies</title>
    <meta content="21ctdine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/21/travel/21ctdine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1696475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="DINING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hong Kong</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EED6103EF932A1575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Cantonese Menu of Seafood Delicacies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Cantonese Menu of Seafood Delicacies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE LYNESS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is a fish tank just inside the front door at Golden Restaurant on Whalley Avenue in New Haven. Some good-size fish are paddling around.</p>
        <p>Jimmy Chan, the manager of the restaurant, is a young and very likable guy. He patiently explains -- probably not for the first time that day -- that the sea bass we had for dinner did not come from the tank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>I didn't love everything I ate at Golden Restaurant, but I do love that it is authentic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is a fish tank just inside the front door at Golden Restaurant on Whalley Avenue in New Haven. Some good-size fish are paddling around.</p>
        <p>Jimmy Chan, the manager of the restaurant, is a young and very likable guy. He patiently explains -- probably not for the first time that day -- that the sea bass we had for dinner did not come from the tank.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chan moved to the United States from Hong Kong in 1997. The restaurant's chef, Wing Wong, is also from Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>The restaurant, which opened in November 2002, specializes in seafood, and is authentic Hong Kong. The multipage menu is predominantly Cantonese, padded with some Sichuan and Hunan offerings.</p>
        <p>The clientele is more Chinese than not, and the back pages of the menu, written in Chinese, appear to list a few set menus that can be ordered for a specific number of people. The menu is full of Chinese seafood delicacies that you will have trouble finding elsewhere, like jellyfish, frogs' legs, sea cucumber and fish maws.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chan, who is never absent from the dining room for long, is nonintrusive but gracious about answering questions and advising. One night he recommended the crispy roast duck over the eight precious duck; the skin might have been a bit crisper on the roast duck, but otherwise it was a fine choice. He also recommends special dishes if you are interested.</p>
        <p>The dishes the restaurant does best are those made without sauce, or with very little, like the roast duck, or pillowy squares of deep-fried tofu -- which also come stuffed with shrimp -- served with a dipping sauce.</p>
        <p>But seafood is the thing to have here. Salt-baked squid is difficult to stop eating; it is not, in fact, baked but rather deep-fried in a light, puffy coating, with lots of browned slivered garlic, salt and fresh and dried chilies thrown over the top. The same goes for salt-baked scallops that, given the same treatment, were hot, sweet and perfectly cooked.</p>
        <p>A special of steamed Dungeness crab is made with lots and lots of garlic that sweetens with cooking. Walnut shrimp is an unusual dish of crisp deep-fried shrimp served with mayonnaise, candied walnuts and steamed broccoli. Whole steamed sea bass could have been fresher the first time I ate it here, but the restaurant made up for it the next time. The waiters will fillet the fish.</p>
        <p>Sliced jellyfish, seasoned with sesame and vinegar and served on a bed of pickled daikon, is delicious. The restaurant makes a particularly delicate black bean sauce for clams. Frogs' legs are better deep-fried than sautéed.</p>
        <p>Saucy dishes tend to be heavy and uninteresting. Sesame shrimp are overpowered by the thick, tart, spicy sauce. Garlic sauce with shrimp is thick, sweet and vinegary. Mixed sautéed vegetables are blanketed by a vinegary brown sauce. Crisp bites of orange chicken, however, are juicy inside, not too sweet and unusually good.</p>
        <p>In terms of presentation, the restaurant does two smart things: a big lazy Susan sits in the center of large tables so that dishes can be shared easily among members of large parties; and hot towels are served at least once at the beginning of the meal, more often if you've ordered foods that are messy to eat. On a night that we ate crab, we were offered fresh towels and plates several times. (These are real cloth towels, not paper, rolled up individually in sealed plastic bags.)</p>
        <p>Beer, a house cabernet, merlot and chardonnay are available by the glass, or you can bring your own wine, at no charge.</p>
        <p>I didn't love everything I ate at Golden Restaurant, but I do love that it is authentic.</p>
        <p>Golden Restaurant  1307 Whalley Avenue, New Haven  (203)389-6889</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Basic Chinatown-style restaurant.  NOISE LEVEL -- Moderate.  SERVICE -- Quick, helpful.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Fried squid, sliced jellyfish, chicken wings, crispy bean curd (plain and with shrimp), steamed whole Dungeness crab with garlic, lobster with ginger and scallion, clams with black bean sauce, whole steamed fish, salt-baked squid, salt-baked scallops, walnut jumbo shrimp, crispy frogs' legs, crispy roast duck, duck with black mushrooms, orange chicken.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers, $1.25 to $14.95 for a platter for two. Entrees: $7.95 to $24.95.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards.  HOURS -- Sunday to Thursday, 11 a.m. to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday to 11 p.m.  RESERVATIONS -- I've never needed one.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Not accessible.  REVIEWED BY THE TIMES -- Aug. 21, 2005.  RATINGS -- Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Fair, Poor. Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
