<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE NATION: Health Of Nations; If You've Got a Pulse, You're Sick</title>
    <meta content="21kolata" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/21/weekinreview/21kolata.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1763432"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Health of Nations"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kolata, Gina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Medical Assn</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EEDA133EF932A15756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1168" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE NATION: Health Of Nations; If You've Got a Pulse, You're Sick</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">If You've Got a Pulse, You're Sick</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINA KOLATA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kolata, Gina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recent study showing that Britons are much healthier than Americans despite spending half as much on health care may well reflect fact that Americans are more 'medicalized' than Britons, that is, they are subjected to more intensive screening for disease; some experts call it disease-mongering; cartoon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR a nation that spends more than any other on health, the United States certainly doesn't seem very healthy.</p>
        <p>Many cancers are on the rise -- prostate, breast, skin, thyroid. We're fatter than ever. As for diabetes, the number of people who say they have it has doubled in the last 10 years. Now a report says that the British -- those smoking, candy-eating, fish-and-chips lovers -- are actually healthier than Americans. And they spend half as much on health care.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a nation that spends more than any other on health, the United States certainly doesn't seem very healthy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR a nation that spends more than any other on health, the United States certainly doesn't seem very healthy.</p>
        <p>Many cancers are on the rise -- prostate, breast, skin, thyroid. We're fatter than ever. As for diabetes, the number of people who say they have it has doubled in the last 10 years. Now a report says that the British -- those smoking, candy-eating, fish-and-chips lovers -- are actually healthier than Americans. And they spend half as much on health care.</p>
        <p>The American-British comparison, published this month in The Journal of the American Medical Association, analyzed data from people's own reports of their health and also used some objective measures: a blood test for diabetes, using hemoglobin A1c, and blood tests for proteins associated with heart disease risk, fibrinogen and C-reactive.</p>
        <p>Their blunt conclusion?</p>
        <p>''Americans are much sicker than the English,'' wrote the investigators, led by Dr. Michael Marmot of University College Medical School in London.</p>
        <p>People tried to find reasons. Maybe, many said, the problem is that Americans are under too much stress.</p>
        <p>But, as often happens when it comes to statistics, what this all means may depend on who is doing the interpreting.</p>
        <p>It's hard to make cross-cultural comparisons -- the populations may not be representative. But it can be even worse when the question involves health. Sometimes, the data that are needed just can't be found because what one country measures, another guesses.</p>
        <p>Take obesity, for example. Dr. Jeffrey M. Friedman, an obesity researcher at Rockefeller University, once wondered how much thinner Europeans actually were. So he looked for nationally representative data that included actual measures of weight, not just what some groups of people said they weighed. The United States has such data, but not Europe, with the exception of England.</p>
        <p>''You can't get those data,'' Dr. Friedman said. ''They don't exist.''</p>
        <p>There is, however, one statistic that scientists say is fairly solid: life expectancy at birth. And in comparing the figures for the United States and Britain, it turns out they are almost identical: 77.6 years in Britain; 77.1 in the United States.</p>
        <p>''What do you mean by saying we're not healthy?'' asks Dr. Nortin M. Hadler, professor of medicine at the University of North Carolina. ''How do you define health?''</p>
        <p>The question of which country is healthier, Dr. Hadler and others say, turns out to be a perfect illustration of an issue that has plagued American medicine: the more health problems you look for, the more you find. And Americans, medical researchers say, are avid about looking.</p>
        <p>The British, doctors say, are different.</p>
        <p>''The U.K. has a tradition of independent and perhaps more skeptical primary-care practitioners who are probably slower to label and diagnose people and more reluctant to follow guidelines than their U.S. counterparts,'' says Dr. Iona Heath, a general practitioner in London. ''I have heard it argued that the U.S. believes more in the perfectibility of humanity and the role of science than the Europeans.''</p>
        <p>Some people call it disease-mongering, says Dr. Lisa Schwartz of Dartmouth Medical School. She once calculated that if everyone had the recommended tests for blood cholesterol, blood sugar, body mass index and diabetes, 75 percent of adults in the United States would be labeled as diseased. And new diseases arise by the minute, she says, her favorite example being ''restless legs.''</p>
        <p>Even cancer rates can be hard to compare from one country to another, noted Dr. H. Gilbert Welch, also of Dartmouth, and, with Dr. Schwartz, a researcher with the V.A. Outcomes Group in White River Junction, Vt.</p>
        <p>Here, men over 50 routinely get a blood test for prostate cancer, the P.S.A. test, when they have medical exams. It is so accepted that some doctors do not even tell the men they are doing the test. Here, free skin-screening clinics pop up every year and doctors advise people to have their skin examined regularly for cancer. Here, women get mammograms starting at age 40, and they get them every year thereafter. Here, even thyroid cancer screening is on the rise.</p>
        <p>And while screening picks up cancers that would become deadly if left unnoticed, in many cases it also picks up tiny cancers that might have gone nowhere -- people would have died with them, not of them. Autopsies have repeatedly found that people often have such cancers, but had they been found through screening and treated, people would have thought they'd been ''cured.'' That phenomenon, overdiagnosis, is a recognized consequence of increased screening, medical researchers say. A telltale sign is a cancer whose incidence rises but whose death rate does not budge.</p>
        <p>The most recent example was with thyroid cancer. This month, in a paper in JAMA, Dr. Welch reported that the incidence of thyroid cancer in the United States had increased by 250 percent over the last two decades. But the death rate from it remained the same.</p>
        <p>Screening is much less common in Britain, Dr. Heath says. For example, she said, ''we don't do P.S.A. screening for nonsymptomatic men, and we don't do skin screening.''</p>
        <p>So, she and others say, perhaps it should be no surprise that even though smoking is much more common in Britain, and it is the leading cause of cancer, nearly twice as many Americans as Britons -- 9.5 percent -- said they had had cancer. And the more educated Americans reported the highest rates -- 10.5 percent.</p>
        <p>As for heart disease, 50 percent more Americans than Britons say they have it, and more say they have high blood pressure and high cholesterol. But when Dr. Marmot and his colleagues looked at actual measurements of blood pressure in British and American populations ages 40 to 70, there was no difference. And Americans had lower cholesterol than the British. The paper did not include actual outcomes from heart disease, like heart attacks. The one area where the Americans stand out is with a blood marker for diabetes. The paper reports that 6.4 percent of Americans had elevated levels of hemoglobin A1c, compared with 3.8 percent of Britons.</p>
        <p>But the lesson for Americans is clear. These days, and especially in the United States, with its screening and testing, ''we are labeled,'' said Dr. Hadler of North Carolina.</p>
        <p>''I call that medicalized,'' he added. ''And one of my creeds is that you don't medicalize people unless it is to their advantage. When you medicalize people, they think they're sick, and in our culture it's, 'Do something, Doc. Don't just stand there.' ''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hadler has written a book about the problems of medicalization, calling it ''The Last Well Person: How to Stay Well Despite the Health Care System'' (McGill-Queen's University Press, 2004). The title refers to a story told by Dr. Clifton K. Meador, director of the Meharry-Vanderbilt Alliance, a cooperative program between the medical schools in Nashville.</p>
        <p>One day, as Dr. Meador tells it, a doctor-in-training was asked by his professor to define a well person. The resident thought for a moment. A well person, he said, is ''someone who has not been completely worked up.''</p>
        <p>Health of Nations</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
