<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clintons' Investment Loss Is Disputed</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="674693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHITEWATER CASE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WHITEWATER DEVELOPMENT CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOSTER, VINCENT W JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, HILLARY RODHAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whitewater Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1DA113DF935A25750C0A962958260" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clintons' Investment Loss Is Disputed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN ENGELBERG,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When questions first arose in early 1992 about Bill and Hillary Clinton's Ozark real estate venture, the Clinton Presidential campaign hired a Denver accounting firm that concluded that the couple had lost $68,000 on their investment.</p>
        <p>The firm's report put questions about the Whitewater Development Company to rest during the campaign. And it has been the cornerstone of the Clintons' defense against allegations stemming from the investment. How could they be criticized, they argue, for a deal in which they had heavy losses?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When questions first arose in early 1992 about Bill and Hillary Clinton's Ozark real estate venture, the Clinton Presidential campaign hired a Denver accounting firm that concluded that the couple had lost $68,000 on their investment.</p>
        <p>The firm's report put questions about the Whitewater Development Company to rest during the campaign. And it has been the cornerstone of the Clintons' defense against allegations stemming from the investment. How could they be criticized, they argue, for a deal in which they had heavy losses?</p>
        <p>But a tax return prepared for Whitewater last year at the direction of Vincent W. Foster Jr., the deputy White House counsel who committed suicide last July, suggests that the enterprise was closer to breaking even than the 1992 report asserted.</p>
        <p>The discrepancy is not evidence of wrongdoing or that the Clintons are mistaken in calling the venture a losing proposition. But just how much money the venture lost -- and how much of that loss was borne by the Clintons -- are central questions in evaluating Republican charges that Whitewater was a sweetheart deal. Back Income Tax Returns</p>
        <p>The 1990 tax return was prepared last June. Mr. Foster, a longtime friend of the Clintons, was overseeing the preparation of back income tax returns that the company had failed to file and which the Clintons agreed to clear up when they sold their share in Whitewater shortly after Mr. Clinton was elected President.</p>
        <p>Douglas R. Carmichael, a professor of accounting at Baruch College in Manhattan who is a former vice president of the American Institute of Certified Public Accountants, said the disparity between the report released by the Clintons and the Whitewater tax filing could not be attributed to differences in accounting methods.</p>
        <p>"They just don't seem to be looking at the same project, the same entity," Mr. Carmichael said. "It's difficult to understand how they could possibly have been based on the same facts."</p>
        <p>The Clintons regularly allude to the 1992 report, which was put together in three weeks by a Denver firm then known as Patten, McCarthy &amp; Associates Inc.</p>
        <p>[ On Monday, Hillary Rodham Clinton told reporters, "When this is all over, it's going to be the same story we've been telling for two years: we made a bad investment, we lost money and there's really not much more to add to it."</p>
        <p>[ But while Mrs. Clinton referred in December to the $68,000 loss as "provable by the accountants," on Monday she said the White House "was trying to get an exact figure" for the venture, indicating that the Clintons may be moving away from their steadfast adherence to the report. ]</p>
        <p>Still, the White House has declined to answer questions about it, referring questions to James M. Lyons, a Denver lawyer and a friend of the Clintons who commissioned the report. In interviews over the last month Mr. Lyons generally defended the report's accuracy, but declined to make public its underlying documents. Incomplete Records Mentioned</p>
        <p>In the report, the firm said incomplete records had hampered its work and, where necessary, it filled gaps with judgments based on "experience" in similar projects.</p>
        <p>Billed as a reconstruction of Whitewater's finances, the report is centered on a two-page balance sheet and income statement that says the Whitewater partners lost a total of $157,000 -- $68,300 by the Clintons and the rest by the their partners, James B. McDougal and his wife, Susan.</p>
        <p>The special prosecutor in the Whitewater matter, Robert B. Fiske Jr., is examining charges that Mr. McDougal bore a disproportionate share of its risk at a time when his savings institution, the Madison Guaranty Savings and Loan Association, sought favorable rulings from state regulators appointed by Mr. Clinton, who was then Governor of Arkansas, or whether Mr. McDougal improperly used Madison to prop up the venture.</p>
        <p>Mr. McDougal has said that he paid for most of the losses, and that the Clintons lost no more than $13,500. Before his campaign issued the report, Mr. Clinton contended that he had lost $25,000.</p>
        <p>Whitewater had its roots in a 1978 investment by the two couples. They purchased land along the White River in the Ozarks of northern Arkansas, hoping to ride a boom in vacation and retirement homes. But while other investors who bought similar land at the same time made quick profits or broke even, Whitewater was left with most of its lots unsold when the real estate market soured in the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>The Clintons finally ended their involvement in Whitewater in December 1992, selling their stake to Mr. McDougal for $1,000.</p>
        <p>As part of the sale, the Clintons agreed to file tax returns that the company had neglected in previous years. Mr. Foster, who had been a partner of Mrs. Clinton's at the Rose Law Firm in Little Rock, Ark., took on the work and brought it with him when he moved to Washington.</p>
        <p>Accountants generally give great weight to tax documents because the filing of a knowingly false return is a crime under Federal law.</p>
        <p>The Patten report paints Whitewater as an indisputably failed investment. It puts the company's cumulative losses as of May 31, 1991, at $118,000. On the tax return, cumulative losses -- listed as an entry for retained profits or losses -- as of the same date are reported at $58,000. At Odds Over Land Holdings</p>
        <p>Laurence Goldfein, head of litigation services at Richard A. Eisner &amp; Company, a forensic accounting firm based in New York City, said that judging by the tax return, it appears that if the company was able to collect the money it was owed -- its receivables -- and sell its remaining land, the cumulative loss on the Whitewater deal falls to only $15,000.</p>
        <p>The two documents are even at odds over the company's land holdings. On the tax return, the company owns $27,000 worth of land as of May 31, 1991. On the 1992 Patten report, it had none as of the same date. It is not clear what land could be referred to in the tax filing but, while Whitewater purchased no new lots, it had in previous years repossessed land whose buyers had defaulted.</p>
        <p>Whitewater did not file tax returns for several years. Returns for 1990-1992 were drawn up last June by a Little Rock accounting firm hired by Mr. Foster; the 1991 return is dated June 21, 1993.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldfein said a complete set of Whitewater records might yet explain the disparities between the return and the Patten report. Financial statements and tax returns can differ, he said, but should agree on basic data, such as how much land is owned.</p>
        <p>"They don't reconcile in any fashion whatsoever," said Daniel Beneish, professor of accounting at Duke University. "I don't see the link."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
