<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BackTalk; Individual Stars Also Become Dynasties Unto Themselves</title>
    <meta content="Y28LIP$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/28/sports/othersports/28LIPS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1411751"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Backtalk"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipsyte, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, Lance</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tour de France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Armstrong, Lance</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schumacher, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1DA163BF93BA15754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1037" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BackTalk; Individual Stars Also Become Dynasties Unto Themselves</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Individual Stars Becoming Dynasties</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipsyte, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Lipsyte BackTalk column argues that Tiger Woods's seeming disinterest in social causes and his loyalty to corporate sponsors make him less inspiring role model than cyclist Lance Armstrong; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unless a big brown United Parcel Service truck rolls over the United States Postal Service cycling team today, Lance Armstrong should win his fourth straight Tour de France, a tour de force of athletic dominance that is simultaneously thrilling and disheartening.</p>
        <p>It's the old schoolyard equivalent of watching the bully thrash the other kids. We feel ambivalence. There is the vicarious thrill at such an exercise in super power. And then, our own feelings of impotence evoked, we are sickened. We will be thrashed next.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>We are used to dominance in team sports, but nothing quite like the dominance of Lance Armstrong, Michael Schumacher and Tiger Woods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unless a big brown United Parcel Service truck rolls over the United States Postal Service cycling team today, Lance Armstrong should win his fourth straight Tour de France, a tour de force of athletic dominance that is simultaneously thrilling and disheartening.</p>
        <p>It's the old schoolyard equivalent of watching the bully thrash the other kids. We feel ambivalence. There is the vicarious thrill at such an exercise in super power. And then, our own feelings of impotence evoked, we are sickened. We will be thrashed next.</p>
        <p>We had tastes of that ambivalence twice last weekend. Michael Schumacher won the French Grand Prix to clinch his third straight world Formula One drivers' championship and fifth in nine years, tying the great Juan Manuel Fangio's 45-year-old record. No one had ever won the title so early in the season; there are six races to go.</p>
        <p>A day earlier, Tiger Woods, after melting like a sugar cube in the Scottish mist, fell too far behind to win the British Open. The golf prodigy seemed on his way to winning his third straight major tournament of the season in quest of the Grand Slam, all four majors in the same calendar year. He is still the man to beat in every tournament.</p>
        <p>We are more used to dominance in team sports, where the word ''dynasty'' crops up every generation or so to celebrate a happy combination of great players and deep-pocket owners. Most recently, the Chicago Bulls were replaced by the Los Angeles Lakers. The Yankees just barely missed their fourth straight World Series victory last year, renewing an interest in baseball that labor troubles seem determined to squander.</p>
        <p>But nothing has been quite like the dominance of Armstrong, Schumacher and Woods, three men linked by the rarity of their gifts and their willingness to give over their lives to honing them.</p>
        <p>As is well known, I have a Lance Armstrong problem that borders on fandom; as a bike rider, cancer survivor and appreciator of emotional honesty, I claim him as the only role model I have ever had in sports. As are all virtuosi, he is a genetic freak. And then he works harder than his competition.</p>
        <p>As he makes breathtakingly vivid in his wonderful autobiography, written with Sally Jenkins, ''It's Not About the Bike,'' Armstrong's early success as a triathlete, swimmer and then bike racer emerged from his need to create physical pain that would smother his emotional pain. While he seems personally gritty and grown up, I sometimes wonder what pain he will need when he finally climbs off the bike.</p>
        <p>I don't wonder much about Schumacher, who is barely on my radar. His raw quotes always seem humbler and more humane than his cold and arrogant media image, and I can't begin to understand any racing car that doesn't have a restrictor plate. Like Armstrong, Schumacher gets help from his teammates, although supposedly not as officially. Last May, in the final meters of a race in Austria, the Ferrari bosses ordered Rubens Barrichello to let Schumacher pass him to win and get more championship points. There were fines for the blatant tanking, but no points were lost. Barrichello had convenient motor trouble and did not start last Sunday's race in France.</p>
        <p>My Tiger Woods problem borders on distaste, although I can't be sure how much of it is about him (whoever ''him'' may be) and how much about his crafted image as a Nike supermodel. In any case, it lights up thelipsite@aol.com with charges that I am hostile to his race (which one?), his youth, his success, his beauty, his celebrity.</p>
        <p>I'm neurotic enough to take the charges seriously. Who ever knows? Actually, I admire his focus, dedication and professionalism. I assume that Woods, like Michael Jordan, learned to toady to authority figures from a powerful, driven father. Like Jordan, Woods has been known to bully his sport, but not his sponsors.</p>
        <p>People who appreciate Woods as a golfer tell me how off the mark I am in seeing him variously as a child, a cyborg, a weasel. They say that watching him practice as hard as Armstrong and Schumacher is a tribute to the human spirit, that watching him make impossible shots is an inspiration of what an athlete can do. That's not enough for a nongolfer like me.</p>
        <p>Now, I don't think Woods needs to be a social/political role model using his platform for the public good. We shouldn't allow entertainers to be that important. What if Woods's imagined successor, Lion Irons, turned out to have a skinhead agenda? But I do cringe at what might be Woods's immaturity, his lack of responsibility, or perhaps merely his corporate harlotry.</p>
        <p>In Scotland, when asked about the policy of discriminating against women at the Masters (and by extension at Muirfield, the host of the British Open), this 26-going-on-15-year-old said: ''They're entitled to set up their own rules the way they want them. It would be nice to see everyone have an equal chance to participate if they wanted to, but there is nothing you can do about it.''</p>
        <p>This is a fair measure of his character and an insight into why there are people who find the troubled, passionate Allen Iverson a more authentic person. Neither, of course, is the model authentic American or even African-American. But Woods is not even ready to help people toward the equal chance that he is getting. Woods is just another corporado out for himself.</p>
        <p>At first I was glad he fell apart in Scotland. I didn't want to suffer a media newsweek of Tigertoons. But then I thought that his sponsors would find gold in the human vulnerability of his meltdown. Maybe it was scripted so that he could come back for a richer Grand Slam next year when corporations are back in fashion.</p>
        <p>Backtalk</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
