<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thin Is In</title>
    <meta content="28DINE$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1411602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">De Lorenzo's Tomato Pies (Trenton, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Karla</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1DE1138F93BA15754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thin Is In</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARLA COOK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cook, Karla</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karla Cook reviews De Lorenzo's Tomato Pies restaurant in Trenton, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS an old beau of mine was fond of saying, there are two types of people: those who divide people into groups and those who don't. For the former, there are beguiling subsets for categorizing -- coffee drinkers and tea drinkers, meat eaters and vegetarians, sushi eaters and shudderers at the thought.</p>
        <p>There are also two types of pizza eaters: Those who like their pizzas with a thick, bready base to sop up the sauce and the grease and don't mind folding it to protect themselves from those juices. Then there are those who want a fine, crisp crust from the edge to the point, where judiciously appointed toppings can be borne from platter to mouth with structural integrity intact.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS an old beau of mine was fond of saying, there are two types of people: those who divide people into groups and those who don't. For the former, there are beguiling subsets for categorizing -- coffee drinkers and tea drinkers, meat eaters and vegetarians, sushi eaters and shudderers at the thought.</p>
        <p>There are also two types of pizza eaters: Those who like their pizzas with a thick, bready base to sop up the sauce and the grease and don't mind folding it to protect themselves from those juices. Then there are those who want a fine, crisp crust from the edge to the point, where judiciously appointed toppings can be borne from platter to mouth with structural integrity intact.</p>
        <p>For you who like your pizzas fat, I'm still looking. But you who want the crackerlike crunch of a crust against the hot and soft sweet tomato against a melted-to-almost-crusty mozzarella, with crust bubbles tinged to deepest brown, even black, and Gary Amico, the chief pizza man, catching your eye and asking you, Izzitok?, then De Lorenzo's Tomato Pies is where you'll want to stand in line and eventually eat.</p>
        <p>De Lorenzo's is so no-frills that pizza is the only thing you can order, except for birch beer, Coke and a couple of other sugary drinks. It's a bring-your-own-beer place, a bring-your-own-milk place. There are no menus, but you can bring a piece of paper and a pencil to make your own. Plates are plastic and dessert-size, napkins are paper and forks and knives are cafeteria quality. The tables hold little vials of salt, pepper and hot pepper flakes -- and none of that shaker cheese. And there's one other thing the place lacks: a bathroom. Oh, and it takes no cards and no checks; cash only. And another thing: the air-conditioning is wickedly efficient, and when the wait after ordering can stretch close to an hour (two pizza ovens, 54 seats and another 25 percent of the business is takeout), the combination of the chill and hunger is enough to challenge nearly any parent's ability to entertain.</p>
        <p>But once you know the setup and remember to pack snacks and sweaters, you can relax. Since 1948, De Lorenzo's has occupied the same spot below Chick and Sophie De Lorenzo's apartment in a block of row houses on Hudson Street, deep in Trenton's Chambersburg neighborhood. Years ago, the ownership expanded from the De Lorenzo couple to their daughter, Eileen Amico and her husband, Gary, but many things about the restaurant remain original.</p>
        <p>The line starts at the bench outside the restaurant's door, extends along the edge of a brick planter that holds a few bright red geraniums, past the steps of a De Lorenzo brother's camera shop on the corner and sometimes turns the corner onto the less prosperous Swan Street. Waiters take no names, but as tables empty, the diners closest to the door go in, and would-be customers haul themselves and their coolers up, then sit down one spot closer.</p>
        <p>Inside, if you're lucky, you'll land a warm spot opposite the pie-making center, which offers traditional edible theater: dough stretching and pie slicing. Mr. Amico's elegant pie assembly reflects his 35 years in the same corner.</p>
        <p>Walls are decorated with photographs of the famous and not-so-famous, those who have eaten De Lorenzo's tomato pies and those who write on their photographs that they want to. Maybe they haven't had a chance because they wanted takeout and the phone was busy. There's a rumor that the restaurant takes the phone off the hook. Confirmed: ''We take the phone off a lot of nights,'' Mr. Amico said. ''This isn't a volume kind of thing, and there comes a point, we can't handle it,'' he said. ''It's not right for the customers. It's a mom-and-pop thing that got out of hand.''</p>
        <p>If you want to fit in as if you know the mom and pop, here's the unwritten menu: Pizzas come in small (8 slices) and large (10 slices). Toppings include pepperoni, sausage, clams, anchovies, onions, garlic, mushrooms, black olives, hot peppers, sweet peppers, roasted red peppers and broccoli. You can order a white pizza, which means no house-made tomato sauce. You can order a no-mozzarell' pizza. You can order a pie medium or well-done. A large cheese and tomato pie will feed two adults and two hungry children; a small clam pie is an adequate appetizer for four adults. The real secret, though, is to order more than one pie, and take the waiter's advice: Stagger the pies, so you can eat your slices hot and crisp; the tables are too small for two pizzas, anyway.</p>
        <p>I have yet to try a bad combination, but some are more appealing than others. Mr. Amico's current favorite is tomatoes, anchovies, garlic and olive oil. The clam pie, which was very good with a backdrop of plain cheese and tomato sparked with fresh parsley, dried oregano and garlic, might be excellent with the garlic and without tomato. The canned whole baby clams were tender and succulent, slightly briny and sweet. The pepperoni and mushroom is a classic, but that pepperoni would be welcome on any pizza. The same goes for the Trenton-made sweet pork sausage, browned in hazelnut-size mounds remarkably free of gristle. I also liked the caramelized onions and the roasted red peppers, though the generously sized pieces of both tended to emphasize their slipperiness.</p>
        <p>There's another De Lorenzo's Tomato Pies on Hamilton, owned by another brother of Mr. De Lorenzo. It's a bigger restaurant, with more ovens, and, I hope, a few more comforts. But before we try it, we'll pack sweaters and snacks and make a bathroom stop, just in case.</p>
        <p>De Lorenzo's Tomato Pies  530 Hudson Street, Trenton  (609) 695-9534</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE: Busy, cramped and sometimes chilly.  SERVICE: Affable waiters but the wait can be long.  SMOKING: No smoking allowed.  WINE LIST: Bring your own.  RECOMMENDED DISHES: Any pizza.  PRICE RANGE: Small pizza, $7.50, large pizza, $11. Additional toppings, 25 cents to $1. Small clam pizza, $10; large clam, $16. Soda, 75 cents.  HOURS 3:30. to 10 p.m., Tuesdays through Sundays; also open 11:30 a.m. to 1 p.m. on Fridays.  CREDIT CARDS: Cash only.  RESERVATIONS: None taken.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Difficult, with no restrooms, handicapped or otherwise.</p>
        <p>RATINGS: Poor, Fair Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
