<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil Prices Don't Get This Economy Down</title>
    <meta content="29five" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/29/business/29five.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1757853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="FIVE DAYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Confidence (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Durable Goods (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Conference Board</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Knight-Ridder Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Newsmedia Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ca Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sun Microsystems Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Enron Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Contra Costa Times</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Herald, the (Newspaper) (Monterey County, Calif)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pioneer Press (St Paul, Minn)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Jose Mercury News</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stein, Mark A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kumar, Sanjay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richards, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcnealy, Scott G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lay, Kenneth L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Durable Goods (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DA103FF93AA15757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil Prices Don't Get This Economy Down</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Oil Prices Don't Get This Economy Down</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mark A. Stein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stein, Mark A</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark A Stein Five Days column; Conference Board reported consumer confidence index rose sharply, to 109.6 in April, highest level in almost four years; at same time, consumer spending rose, home sales increased and orders for durable goods shot up 6.1 percent from same period last year; crude oil prices fell while price-per-gallon rose in large cities to more than $3; McClatchy Co, having bought Knight-Ridder last month, sold four newspapers to NewsMedia Group for $1 billion; CA Inc's former chief executive Sanjay Kumar and former top salesman Stephen Richards pleaded guilty to securities fraud and obstruction of justice; Scott McNealy stepped down as chief executive at Sun Microsystems and was succeeded by president Jonathan Schwartz; Enron's former chief executive Kenneth Lay lost his cool on witness stand in his criminal fraud trial in Houston; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GRIM news about energy prices collided with great news about the economy this week, but it was no contest. Optimism triumphed; oil prices stalled and then retreated slightly. Stocks rallied.</p>
        <p>Worried that stubbornly high gasoline prices might erode consumers' optimism and buying power, President Bush suspended some air pollution rules and stopped adding to the country's strategic oil reserves. Congress, meanwhile, proposed sending each taxpayer $100, to arrive just about when midterm elections are under way.</p>
        <p>FULL STEAM AHEAD -- A widely anticipated barometer of consumer confidence rose sharply, to its highest level in almost four years. The Conference Board said its index rose to 109.6 in April from 107.5 in March; analysts had forecast a slight decline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>GRIM news about energy prices collided with great news about the economy this week, but it was no contest. Optimism triumphed; oil prices stalled and then retreated slightly. Stocks rallied.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GRIM news about energy prices collided with great news about the economy this week, but it was no contest. Optimism triumphed; oil prices stalled and then retreated slightly. Stocks rallied.</p>
        <p>Worried that stubbornly high gasoline prices might erode consumers' optimism and buying power, President Bush suspended some air pollution rules and stopped adding to the country's strategic oil reserves. Congress, meanwhile, proposed sending each taxpayer $100, to arrive just about when midterm elections are under way.</p>
        <p>FULL STEAM AHEAD -- A widely anticipated barometer of consumer confidence rose sharply, to its highest level in almost four years. The Conference Board said its index rose to 109.6 in April from 107.5 in March; analysts had forecast a slight decline.</p>
        <p>At the same time, consumer spending rose, home sales increased and orders for durable goods -- those that last three years or more -- shot up 6.1 percent from the same month last year, more than three times the rate Wall Street economists had forecast.</p>
        <p>There were some worrying signs. While home sales rose, the median price of new homes fell more than 6 percent. A slump in the property market and continued high oil prices could turn consumer sentiment around, economists said. For that reason, the chairman of the Federal Reserve, Ben S. Bernanke, told a Congressional committee that the Fed might take a break from raising interest rates to control inflation.</p>
        <p>The government is scheduled to release further signs of the economy's health next week, with personal income on Monday, and employment and payrolls on Friday.</p>
        <p>CRUDE OIL SEESAW -- After peaking above $75 a barrel -- a nominal record, though still well below the record of the early 1980's when adjusted for inflation -- crude oil prices fell for four consecutive days as people appeared to cut back on driving.</p>
        <p>Still, economists and politicians said it was only a matter of time before energy prices began to drag on the economy. In large cities, for example, gasoline cost more than $3 a gallon, and there were reasons to worry that prices could stay high. Gasoline demand continued to rise, although at a slower pace than expected. And inventories of both gasoline and crude oil fell 5.6 percent last week.</p>
        <p>High prices are inflating oil company profits, leading federal officials to reconsider $2 billion in tax breaks that Congress approved in August. And prominent Democrats pushed for repealing oil and gas tax breaks worth more than $10 billion over the next five years.</p>
        <p>The Federal Trade Commission is completing an investigation into whether businesses used Hurricane Katrina to manipulate gasoline supply and prices last fall. It is scheduled to deliver its report to Congress by May 19.</p>
        <p>PAPER TRANSACTION -- The McClatchy Company, which bought the 32-newspaper Knight Ridder chain last month, turned around and sold 4 of the papers to the MediaNews Group for $1 billion. McClatchy will use the cash to pay down the $4.5 billion cost of acquiring Knight Ridder.</p>
        <p>MediaNews bought two of the newspapers, The San Jose Mercury News and The Contra Costa Times, directly. It acquired the other two, The Pioneer Press in St. Paul and The Herald in Monterey County in California, in cooperation with the Hearst Corporation. In exchange, Hearst will acquire an interest in the 40 papers that MediaNews owns outside of the Bay Area.</p>
        <p>McClatchy is still negotiating to sell eight other former Knight Ridder papers, analysts say. The Inquirer and The Daily News in Philadelphia are likely to be sold next.</p>
        <p>EXECUTIVE PLEAS --Two former executives of Computer Associates, the software company now known as CA Inc., pleaded guilty to eight counts each of securities fraud and obstruction of justice in Federal District Court in Brooklyn. The pleas came just weeks before the men -- Sanjay Kumar, the former chief executive, and Stephen Richards, its former top salesman -- were to go on trial.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kumar and Mr. Richards admitted to a wide-ranging conspiracy to inflate the company's sales in 1999 and 2000 and to interfere with a federal inquiry into the fraud by lying to their lawyers and to federal investigators. Mr. Kumar even authorized paying $3.7 million to buy the silence of a potential witness, according to the indictment.</p>
        <p>Judge I. Leo Glasser is scheduled to sentence the men on Sept. 12. Obstruction of justice carries a maximum sentence of 20 years, while each fraud charge carries a sentence of up to 10 years.</p>
        <p>A PIONEER RESIGNS -- After helping to start Sun Microsystems and then running it for 22 years, Scott G. McNealy stepped down as chief executive of the company, a Silicon Valley fixture that has recently fallen on hard times.</p>
        <p>Mr. McNealy chose Jonathan Schwartz, 40, the company's president and a former software entrepreneur as his successor. Mr. Schwartz joined Sun in 1996. Mr. McNealy's record of recognizing talent is well known. Among the leaders who worked under him are Edward J. Zander, now the chief executive at Motorola; Carol Bartz, chairwoman of Autodesk, the engineering software firm; and Eric E. Schmidt, chief executive of Google.</p>
        <p>In an effort to reverse sliding sales of its workstations and servers, Sun is using microprocessors made by Advanced Micro Devices in addition to its custom Sparc processors. It is also selling hardware that can run either Linux or Windows software easily.</p>
        <p>COURTROOM DRAMA -- Enron's founder and former chief executive, Kenneth L. Lay, lost his cool on the witness stand in his criminal fraud trial in Houston. Under cross-examination by a prosecutor, John C. Hueston, Mr. Lay accused a cabal of former Enron executives, investors and journalists of precipitating the company's collapse in late 2001.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lay acknowledged that he had violated Enron's code of ethics by investing in Photofête, a company run by a woman who was then the girlfriend of his co-defendant, Jeffrey K. Skilling. He also acknowledged that he had tried to meet with some of the witnesses against him, an effort Mr. Hueston characterized as attempted witness tampering.</p>
        <p>The cross-examination of Mr. Lay will continue on Monday.</p>
        <p>MOST POPULAR -- Following are the most-viewed business news articles on nytimes.com from April 22 through April 28:</p>
        <p>1. One Day, That Economy Ticket May Buy You a Place to Stand  2. For MySpace, Making Friends Was Easy. Big Profit Is Tougher  3. The Wallaby That Roared Across the Wine Industry  4. David Pogue: New Tricks of a Browser Look Familiar  5. Second Thoughts in Congress on Oil Tax Breaks</p>
        <p>Links are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>FIVE DAYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
