<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'I Shall Presently Be Extinguished'</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="627050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KERMODE, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILSON, EDMUND</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SIXTIES, THE: THE LAST JOURNAL, 1960-1972 (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D61339F93BA3575BC0A965958260" item-length="1286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'I Shall Presently Be Extinguished'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Kermode;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KERMODE, FRANK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE SIXTIES  The Last Journal, 1960-1972. By Edmund Wilson. Edited by Lewis M. Dabney. Illustrated. 968 pp. New York: Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE SIXTIES  The Last Journal, 1960-1972. By Edmund Wilson. Edited by Lewis M. Dabney. Illustrated. 968 pp. New York: Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $35.</p>
        <p>THIS, the fifth and final volume of Edmund Wilson's journals, dwells more than the others on mortality, yet "The Sixties" remains observant and vigorous. Wilson never ceased to heed the advice of Henry James, to be one of those on whom nothing is lost. To read him on anything -- scenery, animals, dreams, men and women -- is enough to make most readers understand that much is lost on them.</p>
        <p>Wilson wrote in pretty well every known form -- novels, poems, plays and those bold books on literature and ideas for which he is best known: "Axel's Castle" (1931), on modernism; "The Wound and the Bow" (1941), on the psychopathology of art; "To the Finland Station" (1940), on the history of the ideas that led to the Russian Revolution. Then there were "The Scrolls From the Dead Sea" (1955), a truly remarkable venture into problems that might have been thought the province of experts only; "Apologies to the Iroquois" (1960), on the rights of American Indians; and "Patriotic Gore" (1962), on the literature of the Civil War. And there are many more.</p>
        <p>The journals are an informal supplement to all this writing. They deal with books, travel, money, health, sex, the people he met, the meals he ate and the houses he lived in; they record jokes and jeux d'esprit -- anything that caught his interest he wrote about. Wilson, who knew so much about many things, knew very little about writer's block. Even in infirm old age he chastises himself for laziness while doing what some healthy young writers would consider a highly satisfactory day's work. He particularly admired authors who produced on the grand scale. Yet he was not a bookworm, and never lost his appetite for pleasure.</p>
        <p>It is hard to avoid epithets like "voracious." Wilson swallowed languages; competent in French and Russian, Greek and Latin, with some German and Italian, he later acquired some Hebrew, and in his last years studied Hungarian, "a tight crowded hemmed-in little language -- unlike Russian, which has the looseness of a large country." When a young woman from Skopje aroused his interest in the Macedonian language, he bought a grammar "and found the language perfectly simple."</p>
        <p>His reading was equally acquisitive; he rather despised most literature professors because they were by his standards not only pedantic but ill read, incapable of that steady assimilation of books that was to him as natural as breathing. So too with his passion for women, somewhat tamed by age but still, in principle, voracious.</p>
        <p>He had vast numbers of friends, some illustrious, some obscure, some bookish, some not, and in old age he went on making new ones. In this volume there are sketches of new friends and acquaintances of very various provenance: Mike Nichols, the English Jesuit Martin D'Arcy, the Yugoslav dissident politician Vladimir Dedijer, the Italian savant Mario Praz, the novelist Ignazio Silone. Older friends, like W. H. Auden, Robert Lowell and the Oxford philosopher Isaiah Berlin, remain, though often subjected to affectionate criticism.</p>
        <p>I have known some of Edmund Wilson's friends, and usually find his appraisals of them both generous and shrewd. Unaffectedly cosmopolitan, he was quite at home in most European capitals and had many friends in them; but he never quite conquered a certain suspicion of foreigners, especially the French and the English. There is a passage about Marcus Cunliffe, a good friend of mine who died in 1990, in which he commends Cunliffe's way of speaking English without Oxford affectation, the way English English should be spoken. In fact, Cunliffe had what is called a mid-Atlantic accent; his long sojourns in the United States (his specialty was American history), his having an American wife, gave his accent a very agreeable ambiguity. The tinge of American, though unrecognized, was presumably what commended it to Wilson.</p>
        <p>Books of this kind are bound to have many pages of rather ephemeral interest, yet Lewis M. Dabney, the editor of "The Sixties," has done a skillful job, and we can perceive some powerful recurring themes. One is the author's continuing lament over what he regarded as the decadence of his own country. He equated the dispossession of the Iroquois with the Soviet action against Hungary; he believed that Americans and Russians were equally subject to "the exactions and absurdities of the tyrannous bureaucracies of the centralized state." He held that President John F. Kennedy fell victim "to what would once have been called the dregs but what now constitute large elements of American society -- gangsters, delinquents, the baboons of the South." He found little new writing that excited him as the work of the 20's had done. Altogether, he might well have echoed Yeats's complaint: "Conduct and work grow coarse, and coarse the soul."</p>
        <p>He regarded himself as a man of the 20's, now, in the 60's, entering what he called in a poem "the dark defile of age." He scrupulously registers his decline, noting for instance his diminished sexual potency, as well as other problems in his marriage to Elena Thornton. Once he threw a volume of the Cambridge journal Scrutiny at his wife -- a use of that severe publication that the stern F. R. Leavis, its editor, would not have condoned. She, for her part, could surprise him by occasional flashes of aristocratic hauteur, and disappoint him by a resolute disinclination to spend time in northern New York State. Mostly, however, they got on well, she willing to defer to him in a quite old-fashioned way.</p>
        <p>Angina, gout, lameness, urinary mishaps and other discomforts were constant reminders of "the flimsiness of human life." He could hardly avoid "the thought that I shall presently be extinguished." He notes derogatory French names for old people, and on his 74th birthday admits that "my not being able to make love, not being able to swim or take much exercise and now, with my lower teeth gone, not being able to eat anything but the softest food is getting me down." But then he read some Macaulay "and somewhat regained my equanimity and my inspiration to live." And there was the daily consolation of solitaire; but a sense of humiliation dominates.</p>
        <p>He had courage: objecting to some loutish trespassers, he says, "I advanced on them with my stick, slowly and flat-footed and inexorably like the Teutonic knights in 'Alexander Nevsky,' and they retreated before me." He declined to have a pacemaker fitted, preferring to fight death without such undignified aids. He read Balzac in the sleepless hours of the night, and noted with approval that Macaulay, another nocturnal companion, had worked on his history while he was dying, describing as "fortifying" this example of "high morality and thoroughness." In "To the Finland Station," Wilson wrote of Marx that he "had gotten up from his bed, and gone to his study and sat down at his work table," and died. He followed this precedent exactly, dying at his desk in 1972.</p>
        <p>He asked that the last chapter of Ecclesiastes be read at his funeral: "The grasshopper shall be a burden, and desire shall fail," says one verse; and another, "Of making many books there is no end; and much study is a weariness of the flesh." But he never quite behaved as if these propositions were true. Certainly desire came close to failing, but there was no loss of interest in books -- though he did find certain novels, Conrad's "Nostromo" in particular, a weariness of the flesh. All in all he is as good a model as Macaulay or Marx for other writers, when their turn comes to enter that dark defile.</p>
        <p>Frank Kermode is the author, most recently, of "The Uses of Error."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Frank Kermode is the author, most recently, of "The Uses of Error."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
