<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On and Off Field, Butler Beats Coleman in Almost Every Category</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="627112"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREE AGENTS (SPORTS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUTLER, BRETT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLEMAN, VINCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED9163BF93BA3575BC0A965958260" item-length="1531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On and Off Field, Butler Beats Coleman in Almost Every Category</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Mets decided to let Darryl Strawberry leave as a free agent after the 1990 season -- maybe that was the first mistake -- they initiated the Vince Coleman era. That was definitely a mistake, first or second.</p>
        <p>The Mets would have been better off then and they would certainly be better off now if they had decided to make Brett Butler, not Coleman, the symbol and the catalyst of their new offense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Mets decided to let Darryl Strawberry leave as a free agent after the 1990 season -- maybe that was the first mistake -- they initiated the Vince Coleman era. That was definitely a mistake, first or second.</p>
        <p>The Mets would have been better off then and they would certainly be better off now if they had decided to make Brett Butler, not Coleman, the symbol and the catalyst of their new offense.</p>
        <p>Replacing power with speed seldom, if ever, works. The Yankees, the most noted collector of power hitters in baseball history, tried it in 1982 after Reggie Jackson departed and discovered what a poorly conceived plan it was. The Mets haven't fared too well with that strategy either.</p>
        <p>But having decided that was the way they wanted to go, they had more than one possibility. Coleman, who in his six seasons with St. Louis had led the National League in stolen bases, was a free agent that winter. Butler, too, was a free agent, although not quite as early in the signing season. A New-Look Free Agent</p>
        <p>Butler was one of the players involved in the three collusion cases the Players Association brought against the clubs in the late 1980's. The center fielder had been a free agent after the 1987 season and signed with the San Francisco Giants, but he became a second-look, or free-look, free agent as the result of the arbitrator's collusion ruling.</p>
        <p>Butler was declared free as of Dec. 7, 1990, two days after the Mets signed Coleman. The Mets, however, knew the collusion players would be free imminently. More specifically, Frank Cashen, then the general manager, knew from a third party of Butler's interest in speaking with the Mets, among other teams.</p>
        <p>Cashen's concentration, though, was clearly focused on Coleman, and he didn't bother waiting until he could officially speak with Butler. The Mets gave Coleman $11.95 million for four years, and they have been paying dearly ever since.</p>
        <p>In the past two and a half seasons, Butler has continued to be one of the most consistent and indefatigable players in the major leagues while Coleman has been one of the most erratic and injured players.</p>
        <p>Consider some statistics:</p>
        <p>Games played: Butler (through Friday) 424, Coleman 235.</p>
        <p>Batting average: Butler .303, Coleman .270.</p>
        <p>On-base percentage: Butler .402, Coleman .336.</p>
        <p>Runs scored: Butler 250, Coleman 146.</p>
        <p>Stolen bases: Butler 103, Coleman 99.</p>
        <p>Butler also has a large lead on Coleman in behavior. Since the two players were free agents, Butler hasn't had angry confrontations with a coach or a manager, hasn't thrown an explosive and hasn't been charged with a felony. 'They Should Have Tried'</p>
        <p>The Mets signed Coleman because they were enamored of his stolen bases. But for a leadoff batter, Coleman has never walked enough, and his on-base percentage has always lagged well behind Butler's.</p>
        <p>"I don't know if they could have signed him, but they should have tried," Richard Moss, Butler's agent, said.</p>
        <p>Butler preferred playing in California, but players have been known to change their minds or have their minds changed for them by contract offers. As Moss said, the Mets should at least have tried.</p>
        <p>The Dodgers have received considerably more value for their $10 million for three years (or $13 million for four if they exercise their option) than the Mets have for their nearly $12 million for four. The Fun Begins for McGriff</p>
        <p>The season began badly for Fred McGriff and went downhill from there. "I hit about a buck 80 in April," he said. "I put myself in a pretty good hole." The San Diego Padres took it from there.</p>
        <p>"This year hasn't been a lot of fun for me," McGriff said. "San Diego was rough on me, knowing you're going to get traded but you don't know when. The last month or so having to go to the ball park every day not knowing if that's going to be the last day in that uniform. But now I'm getting hits and it's getting a lot funner."</p>
        <p>The fun began three weeks ago when the Padres, in their payroll purge, traded the first baseman to the Atlanta Braves. At the time McGriff was hitting .275 and had hit 18 home runs and driven in 46 runs in 83 games. With the Braves, entering last night's game, he has hit .400 with 7 home runs and 15 r.b.i. in 17 games.</p>
        <p>"When the rumors started about being traded, it was tough playing," the veteran said. "I said just keep me in the National League and let me play every day and work on my swing. I felt when I got traded I wanted to be ready to help the club I was going to. I have high expectations for myself, and my numbers were down from past years. So I constantly worked on my swing and my mechanics." 'It Was a Big Circus'</p>
        <p>When the trade finally came, McGriff said, his basic feeling was "more or less just relief."</p>
        <p>"Usually when you're traded," he added, "you hear a couple rumors, but the front office might deny it and keep it undercover," he added. "With me, it was a big circus. Everybody in the world knew I was going to get traded so it wasn't a surprise when I was traded. It was, it's over, get your bag, hop on the plane and go somewhere else and play."</p>
        <p>Taking his improved mechanics to Atlanta, McGriff helped put the Braves in gear. Before McGriff moved into their lineup, the Braves compiled a 53-41 record and scored an average of four runs a game. With the left-handed slugger inspiring the offense, the Braves have compiled a 12-6 record and have scored nearly seven runs a game.</p>
        <p>Yet McGriff hasn't been able to defuse the San Francisco Giants while igniting the Braves. The Giants have matched the Braves' performance and entered yesterday leading by nine and a half games, half a game better than when McGriff began his task.</p>
        <p>"It's tough to threepeat," McGriff said of the two-time champion Braves. "These guys had a lot of pressure coming into the year. They've been performing well, but the Giants have been playing great ball. People haven't given the Giants a lot of credit for the year they're having." Steady On for Gywnn</p>
        <p>With the departure of McGriff, Gary Sheffield, Greg Harris and Bruce Hurst in the space of several weeks, Tony Gwynn has found himself home alone in San Diego.</p>
        <p>"Tony is all right," McGriff said. "He's a 10-and-5 guy so they can't trade him. Tony is happy. He went to college there. He has a home there. He has the perfect situation out in San Diego. Spring training is in Arizona so he just drives over there. Conditions are perfect for him so he's happy."</p>
        <p>The steady stream of departing players the past year hasn't affected Gwynn. A .327 career hitter, the 33-year-old outfielder had six hits in a 12-inning game against San Francisco the other night, topping the trio of five-hit games he has had this season along with a baker's dozen of three-hit performances. He reached the career 2,000-hit mark Friday night and finished the doubleheader with a .348 average, second in the league to Orlando Merced's .352. The Overlooked Incaviglia</p>
        <p>John Kruk, Lenny Dykstra and Darren Daulton are the hitters who are mentioned when reasons for the Philadelphia Phillies' National League East lead are given. But Pete Incaviglia can no longer be omitted.</p>
        <p>Incaviglia has been a platooned left fielder this season, but his ratios of home runs and runs batted in per number of at-bats are the most impressive on the team.</p>
        <p>Incaviglia, entering last night's game, had hit one home run every 14.3 at-bats and had driven in a run every 3.9 at-bats. Among the league leaders in those ratios, only Barry Bonds of San Francisco has a better home run ratio (11.2) and none has an r.b.i. ratio as low as 4.0.</p>
        <p>In a recent four-game stretch, Incaviglia hit 5 home runs and drove in 12 runs in 17 at-bats.</p>
        <p>Despite many impressive power and production numbers in his first five years with the Texas Rangers, Incaviglia has not had much respect the past few years. He has moved from the Rangers to Detroit to Houston to Philadelphia and has had to scramble for the jobs he has had.</p>
        <p>The Astros, for example, signed him to a minor league contract a month before spring training last year, then let him leave at the end of the season rather than exercise the option for a $1.75 million salary. The Phillies signed him in December to a two-year, $2.3 million contract that also has an option year. The Park Avenue Shuttle</p>
        <p>If central baseball's offices are moved to Chicago, as some people have discussed (perhaps to get closer to the real seat of power, the one in which Jerry Reinsdorf of the White Sox sits), will that reduce the visits of Yankees officials to the American League office?</p>
        <p>Last week, George Steinbrenner sent General Manager Gene Michael to Park Avenue in Manhattan to show the league president, Bobby Brown, a videotape of Toronto Manager Cito Gaston standing in the runway after he had been ejected from the game. As if managers, including those who have worked for Steinbrenner, had never done such a thing.</p>
        <p>Brown declined to discuss his view of the videotape, but he apparently planned no action against Gaston.</p>
        <p>"The umpires run the ball game on the field," Brown said. "It's within their jurisdiction. They have the power to do it. I leave it up to them to run their affairs on the field."  NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
