<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burger King Picks a Food Fight With Wendy's</title>
    <meta content="24njweekNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1792354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fast Food Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saddle Brook (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wendy's International Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Burger King Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donohue, Richard J (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strunsky, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fast Food Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED91131F937A1575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="553" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burger King Picks a Food Fight With Wendy's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE STRUNSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strunsky, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Appellate Division panel overturns ruling by Superior Court Judge Richard Donohue upholding Saddle Brook Board of Adjustment's approval of zoning variance that would prevent Wendy's restaurant from being built near Burger King; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It took all of four minutes to drive in, order and drive out of the Burger King on Market Street in Saddle Brook, juggling a Triple Whopper with cheese, medium fries and a Diet Coke. Fast food indeed.</p>
        <p>So it may seem hard to swallow that the owner of that very franchise on Saddle Brook's main drag fought successfully to uphold a local ban on fast-food restaurants after township zoning officials voted to make an exception to it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It took all of four minutes to drive in, order and drive out of the Burger King on Market Street in Saddle Brook, juggling a Triple Whopper with cheese, medium fries and a Diet Coke. Fast food indeed.</p>
        <p>So it may seem hard to swallow that the owner of that very franchise on Saddle Brook's main drag fought successfully to uphold a local ban on fast-food restaurants after township zoning officials voted to make an exception to it.</p>
        <p>But that is exactly what happened. The Burger King's owner, Saddle Brook Realty L. L .C., sued the Saddle Brook Board of Adjustment, seeking to overturn the board's approval of a use variance for a Wendy's near the Home of the Whopper.</p>
        <p>''That's that legal principle known as 'No Competition,' '' said Deborah Kole, a staff lawyer for the New Jersey State League of Municipalities, which was not involved in the lawsuit. ''Just kidding. But, yeah, it is ironic.''</p>
        <p>The case dates to 2004, when the board granted a local corporation, Grillco Two, a variance to build a Wendy's in a strip mall on Market Street, partly because the proposed Wendy's fit in with the surroundings.</p>
        <p>The site is just a vacant lot east of the Burger King. There is a KFC a few blocks away and a McDonald's on Route 46, plus several pizza parlors and Chinese restaurants, but Burger King has cornered the Market Street commercial district as the sole purveyor of drive-through burgers and fries since the 1970's, predating and therefore exempt from a township ban on fast-food restaurants imposed under the 1985 master plan. That law was the basis for Saddle Brook Realty's lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Judge Richard J. Donohue of State Superior Court in Hackensack rejected the Burger King owner's suit, upholding the board's approval in 2005. But Saddle Brook Realty appealed, and two weeks ago a three-judge panel of the Appellate Division unanimously overturned Judge Donohue's ruling, and with it, Wendy's approval, which it found was unjustified.</p>
        <p>Francis DeVito, a lawyer for the Burger King franchisee, said he had been confident all along the Wendy's approval would be overturned.</p>
        <p>Saddle Brook's mayor, Louis V. D'Arminio, said that although the appellate ruling was technically a defeat for the township, he welcomed it and would recommend to the Township Council that it not be appealed to the State Supreme Court. Traffic on Market already moves at a standstill during rush periods, he said, and would only get slower with more fast-food restaurants.</p>
        <p>Antimo A. Del Vecchio, a lawyer for Grillco Two, which was also a defendant in the suit, said his client had not decided whether to appeal.</p>
        <p>Another option, Mr. Del Vecchio said, would be a suit to overturn the ban, which would challenge Saddle Brook's official definition of a fast-food place -- ''an establishment or business, which is essentially designed to dispense a limited variety of food and beverages, which are so prepared, packaged in paper, or in other types of disposable wrappers and containers in a form for quick or ready consumption'' -- as too vague.</p>
        <p>Mayor D'Arminio said a township commission was reviewing Saddle Brook's master plan and would soon release recommendations that could include allowing fast food in some areas away from Market Street.</p>
        <p>''I love the McDonald's French fries, to be honest with you,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THE WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
