<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Through The Quarterback's Eyes</title>
    <meta content="05sbwatch----063--064------90--91--" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="90" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/05/magazine/05sbwatch__063_064___90_91_.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1737182"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="The Fine Points"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curtis, Bryan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simms, Phil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EED61E3FF936A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Through The Quarterback's Eyes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Through the Quarterback's Eyes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bryan Curtis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curtis, Bryan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bryan Curtis The Fine Points column discusses subtleties of Super Bowl plays as examined by analyst Phil Simms; diagrams (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many National Football League fans share a secret shame. They can fake their way through a Super Bowl party, making intelligent-sounding noises about the major players, but in private moments they admit to themselves that they don't really understand the game's complexities. Trap blocks? Defensive audibles? Zone defense, cover 2, end around -- say what? Phil Simms, the Super Bowl-winning quarterback for the New York Giants who is now a CBS analyst, feels everyone's pain. For about two hours each day, Simms pores over game film at his home in Franklin Lakes, N.J., deciding which subtleties can be conveyed on a telecast. One morning during the playoffs, Simms invited Play to join him at a film-study session and offered a few hints on four plays you might see in the big game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What Phil Simms knows and you don't. Or how to watch the Super Bowl like a pro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Many National Football League fans share a secret shame. They can fake their way through a Super Bowl party, making intelligent-sounding noises about the major players, but in private moments they admit to themselves that they don't really understand the game's complexities. Trap blocks? Defensive audibles? Zone defense, cover 2, end around -- say what? Phil Simms, the Super Bowl-winning quarterback for the New York Giants who is now a CBS analyst, feels everyone's pain. For about two hours each day, Simms pores over game film at his home in Franklin Lakes, N.J., deciding which subtleties can be conveyed on a telecast. One morning during the playoffs, Simms invited Play to join him at a film-study session and offered a few hints on four plays you might see in the big game.</p>
        <p>First Down First-and-10, ball on the offense's 20-yard line.</p>
        <p>On about one of every three plays in the N.F.L., Simms says, the offense can't block everybody. ''So they just tell the runner, 'You've got to make somebody miss.''' In this case, with the play designed to go right (the offense here is shown in blue), the blockers ignore the safety (1) edging toward the line of scrimmage on the left. And that, Simms says, is where the viewer's eyes should focus before the play starts: if you can see a safety creeping into your TV rectangle, then it often means the defense is anticipating the run -- and that the other safety (2, not visible on TV) is cheating toward the middle of the field to guard against the pass. (One of the subtler arts of quarterbacking is the ability to notice gradations in a safety's depth, even if the change is just a yard.) l On this play, let's say the defensive line gets a strong push on its left (here, the bottom of the frame), and the running back (3) is forced to reverse direction, where he meets the safety. Watch how the safety approaches the back in the open field. ''If he knows it's a really good [back], he'll be conservative in his approach,'' Simms says. ''He's willing to give up a few yards if it's open space. If he doesn't have high regard for the back, he'll go flying in there and try to tackle him for no gain or a loss.''</p>
        <p>SECOND Down: Second-and-5, ball on the offense's 45.</p>
        <p>Simms says passing plays almost always unfold as they're drawn up: running backs may improvise to some extent, but receivers go where they're told. And no matter how many receivers are whizzing around, the quarterback often looks at only three options: a primary target, a secondary target and a dump-off pass. In the lingo, it's known as ''one, two, dump'' -- and the quarterback will typically rule out the receivers in that order. ''The elimination process happens as the ball is snapped, and sometimes before,'' Simms says. ''Most of the time it's going to be completed before the quarterback [1] finishes dropping back.'' l In this diagram, a play-action fake to the running back (4) is designed to distract the defenders. The primary target is the slot receiver on the near left (2), the secondary target is the receiver on the far left (3), and the running back (4) is the ''dump.'' If the safety (5) drifts toward the slot receiver, the quarterback is likely to eliminate him and look outside. (''When you see a safety making a play on a receiver in the middle, there likely was a pretty big hole somewhere on the outside that the quarterback didn't see,'' Simms says.) If the second option is covered, the quarterback will dump the ball to the back. Of course, pressure from the defensive line can ruin everything. Simms's Yogi Berra-esque take on the pass rush: ''Pressure makes quarterbacks not near as intelligent as they are.''</p>
        <p>THIRD Down: Third-and-10, ball on the defense's 25.</p>
        <p>Safeties and linebackers are crowding the line of scrimmage, threatening a blitz, and the offense uses some mild trickery. It lines up in a standard formation -- two backs, two wide receivers and one tight end -- when suddenly the running back (1) goes in motion to the right. ''Why do you want to shift and go in motion?'' Simms says. ''Because you want to try to get a defense to react to what you're doing. If you just sit there, they will attack you.'' Motion can wreak havoc on man-to-man coverage: it can rearrange the defense, putting slower backs on faster receivers, and force defenders to follow players all the way across the field. It can negate a defense's speed; Simms compares it to a 100-meter dash in which one of the sprinters is held back for a second at the starting line. l How can the TV viewer spot defensive chaos? Simms says to pay attention to the defenders' hands. Linebackers might make hand movements (like stacking their fists on top of each other), a common way to indicate a defensive audible. (An audible may signal any number of changes, from a blitz to a new cover scheme.) In extreme cases, you might see defenders throw both arms up in the air. ''When they throw them up in the air,'' Simms says, ''that means 'Surrender -- everybody drop back, spread out and play a zone,' because they've been tricked by the formation.''</p>
        <p>FOURTH Down Fourth-and-goal, ball on the 1-foot line.</p>
        <p>On three previous plays, the running back has been flattened at the line. The fans are getting edgy, and the offensive coordinator turns to one of the N.F.L.'s most reliable standbys: the play-action fake to the back, followed by the soft lob into the end zone. With goal-line fakes, Simms says, the viewer should watch how long the play takes to develop. ''Generally, when you see these goal-line play-action passes, the longer it goes, the less chance it's going to work. Because if you fool them, they're wide open immediately. If you don't fool them, everybody is running with the receiver.'' Translation: N.F.L. defenders have too much speed, and the receivers have too little room to stretch the defense out. l On this play, the key is the linebacker (1) who has coverage responsibility for the right-side wide receiver (2). As the receiver goes in motion toward the center, the linebacker fears the receiver might be blocking him for a running play, and must make a choice in a split second. Does he cover the receiver (and risk ignoring a handoff), or does he remain in his spot (and risk letting the receiver blow past him)? In this case, we'll say the linebacker correctly follows the receiver and prevents the would-be touchdown. Simms ascribes this success to luck or an extra hour of film study. ''Most of the time when these plays don't work, it's because the defense knows it's coming,'' he says. The defender, like Simms, has been doing his homework.</p>
        <p>The Fine Points</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
