<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Dust Settles in House, Speaker Emerges Standing</title>
    <meta content="05hastert" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/05/politics/05hastert.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1737436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirkpatrick, David D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hastert, J Dennis (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delay, Tom (Rep)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hastert, J Dennis</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DF173EF936A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Dust Settles in House, Speaker Emerges Standing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Dust Settles, the Speaker of the House Emerges, Still Standing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>House Speaker J Dennis Hastert has survived shakeup in Republican leadership following downfall of Rep Tom DeLay; has escaped Republican calls for new blood in leadership in large part because of understated personality and close political ties in caucus; Hastert's easygoing style did little to check DeLay's power, but has helped him escape blame left in DeLay's wake (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the competition to succeed Representative Tom DeLay as the leader of their caucus, House Republicans have railed for weeks against the images of autocracy and corruption that have come to surround their party's control of the chamber.</p>
        <p>But when the party leadership gathered on Friday to present its new face to the public, a familiar figure was still hunched over the center of the table: Speaker J. Dennis Hastert of Illinois, one of the longest-serving House speakers in history and the Republican who has had the ultimate responsibility of managing the caucus and the chamber for the last eight years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even after the House G.O.P. presented its new leadership to the public, a familiar figure remained: Speaker J. Dennis Hastert of Illinois.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the competition to succeed Representative Tom DeLay as the leader of their caucus, House Republicans have railed for weeks against the images of autocracy and corruption that have come to surround their party's control of the chamber.</p>
        <p>But when the party leadership gathered on Friday to present its new face to the public, a familiar figure was still hunched over the center of the table: Speaker J. Dennis Hastert of Illinois, one of the longest-serving House speakers in history and the Republican who has had the ultimate responsibility of managing the caucus and the chamber for the last eight years.</p>
        <p>''This is certainly a brand-new day for House leadership,'' Mr. Hastert said, introducing Representative John A. Boehner of Ohio, the new majority leader and second in command.</p>
        <p>''Thanks, boss,'' replied Mr. Boehner, who was elected on a pledge to turn around the House Republicans' image after Mr. DeLay's indictment on corruption charges.</p>
        <p>First picked for the speaker's job by Mr. DeLay and often described as his sidekick, Mr. Hastert has nonetheless escaped the House Republicans' calls for new blood in their leadership, in large part because of his understated personality and close personal ties in the caucus. If Mr. Hastert's easygoing style did little to check Mr. DeLay's power, Republicans say, the same traits are now helping him escape the blame left in Mr. DeLay's wake.</p>
        <p>''Hastert's approach is sort of the coach as opposed to the dominator, if you will, or the dictator,'' said Representative Sherwood Boehlert, Republican of New York, alluding to Mr. Hastert's previous career as a high school wrestling coach.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hastert bears no more responsibility for ''what DeLay did'' than ''any one of us, me included,'' Mr. Boehlert said.</p>
        <p>Still, under the rules of the House, Mr. Hastert's authority was indispensable to many elements of Mr. DeLay's leadership that are now under attack from others in his party.</p>
        <p>When Mr. DeLay faced scrutiny by the House ethics committee, Mr. Hastert sought rule changes that could have impeded the investigation, provoking a yearlong standoff with the Democrats.</p>
        <p>He also collaborated with Mr. DeLay in his forceful approach to handling legislation, another subject of Republican criticism in the campaign to succeed him. Mr. Hastert often allowed Mr. DeLay to manipulate the House schedule to hold votes open until he had cajoled enough members to turn the result his way. Once, he held the vote on the Medicare drug plan open for nearly three hours; normally, roll-call votes rarely exceed 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hastert also cooperated with Mr. DeLay to block politically awkward amendments or to present revised legislation to the floor without time for study or debate.</p>
        <p>Democrats say Mr. Hastert's role as speaker now undercuts the new Republican talk of reform. ''He was a total enabler,'' said Representative Barney Frank, Democrat of Massachusetts. ''DeLay could not have done any of that without Hastert's full support of his whole operation.''</p>
        <p>Ron Bonjean, a spokesman for Mr. Hastert, said that the Democratic attacks were a sign of desperation and that the speaker was serving the caucus, not Mr. DeLay. ''The speaker believes in following the will of his House Republican colleagues and has always been honored to serve them,'' Mr. Bonjean said.</p>
        <p>Asked whether Mr. Hastert's role in Mr. DeLay's leadership undermined the image change, Mr. Boehner said no, then added: ''The speaker and I have been friends for a long time. We have worked together closely, and we are going to work together closely.''</p>
        <p>Heavy and stooped, with ill-fitting wire-rim glasses that often slide down his nose, Mr. Hastert has always preferred to operate behind the scenes instead of in front of cameras.</p>
        <p>Several Republicans said he was never as strong a speaker as Newt Gingrich, who engineered the Republican takeover of the House in 1994. Among the reasons for the difference, they said, was Mr. Hastert's history with Mr. DeLay. When Republicans took control in 1994, Mr. Hastert helped organize Mr. DeLay's campaign for majority whip and then became his chief deputy.</p>
        <p>About four years later, Mr. Hastert came in fourth in a race for party leader, with just 18 votes. But a few weeks after that, Representative Bob Livingston of Louisiana, who was set to succeed Mr. Gingrich as speaker, confessed to adultery and bowed out of the job, so Mr. DeLay tapped Mr. Hastert, and he was quickly elected to the post.</p>
        <p>Dick Armey, the former majority leader who worked under Mr. Gingrich and Mr. Hastert, faulted Mr. DeLay as running the House for political goals, rather than to make sound policy. ''Obviously the speaker does share some of that,'' Mr. Armey said in an interview.</p>
        <p>But he argued that Mr. Hastert had set aside his own preference for a less political focus because of his strong personal relationship with Mr. DeLay. ''The thing about Denny is, once he makes a delegation of responsibility, he lets that delegation stand,'' Mr. Armey said. ''He doesn't trump it. You can argue maybe he should.''</p>
        <p>Representative Ray LaHood, an Illinois Republican who is a close friend of Mr. Hastert's, said that over the last month, Mr. Hastert worked behind the scenes to help move the party past the corruption charges against Mr. DeLay, the Republican lobbyist Jack Abramoff and another Republican, Representative Bob Ney of Ohio.</p>
        <p>''I think the speaker played a role in Tom's decision not to run for election as majority leader,'' Mr. LaHood said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Frank, the Massachusetts Democrat, said it was Mr. Hastert's low profile that would protect him from the Republicans' recent travails. ''Nobody knows who he is,'' Mr. Frank said. ''People may have underestimated the political advantages of being boring.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
