<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>There Once Was a Wizard in the Wonderful Land of Calvin</title>
    <meta content="12DRES$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/12/fashion/12DRES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1439949"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Klein, Calvin, Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horyn, Cathy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, Zack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Calvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Carr, Zack</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Klein, Calvin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD1031F931A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1369" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>There Once Was a Wizard in the Wonderful Land of Calvin</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">There Once Was a Wizard in the Wonderful Land of Calvin</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Commer</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No better parable exists to describe the enchanted phoniness of the fashion world than L. Frank Baum's ''Wizard of Oz.'' Skipping down glamour's yellow brick road are straw editors and tin men, believing what they believe, while lurking behind the big curtains of Paris and Seventh Avenue, surrounded by vigilant monkey publicists, are gods waiting to be condemned as mere mortals.</p>
        <p>The recent publication of a book about Zack Carr, the late creative director of Calvin Klein, reminds me again that the fashion world is not all it appears, at least (or least of all?) to outsiders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The recent publication of a book about Zack Carr, the late creative director of Calvin Klein, reminds one that the fashion world is not all it appears, at least to outsiders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No better parable exists to describe the enchanted phoniness of the fashion world than L. Frank Baum's ''Wizard of Oz.'' Skipping down glamour's yellow brick road are straw editors and tin men, believing what they believe, while lurking behind the big curtains of Paris and Seventh Avenue, surrounded by vigilant monkey publicists, are gods waiting to be condemned as mere mortals.</p>
        <p>The recent publication of a book about Zack Carr, the late creative director of Calvin Klein, reminds me again that the fashion world is not all it appears, at least (or least of all?) to outsiders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carr, who died two years ago at age 55 of a rare form of cancer that slowly crippled him, was much admired within the industry for his talent and his Southern charms. He was a product of Kerrville, Tex., in the Hill Country, where he was known as Chuckie or as just one of the Carr boys. There were two other brothers, and one of them, George, put together the coffee-table homage, ''Zack Carr,'' with Sam Shahid, an art director in the fashion business, and PowerHouse Books.</p>
        <p>What makes this $75 book noteworthy among the pre-Christmas editions is that by limelighting the talent of a behind-the-scenes player, which Mr. Carr was for the 25 years he spent at Calvin Klein, it raises some Oz-like questions. Who actually was the designer at Calvin Klein all those years, Mr. Klein or his acolyte? And does it matter in the new gilded age of brands, when many designer collections are not designed by the designer at all, whether the public knows?</p>
        <p>George Carr and Mr. Shahid said they wanted to do a book that dwelt only on the acolyte, not the star. To that end, they included original sketches, photos of Mr. Carr with friends and examples from the collections he designed briefly in the 1980's under his own label. But there are few images of clothes he designed for Calvin Klein. ''It was a decision that I personally made,'' said Mr. Shahid, who has worked on many of Mr. Klein's advertising campaigns. ''Let's do a book on Zack.'' Mr. Carr agreed. ''It's all Zack for Zack.'' He added: ''Nobody has to put Calvin Klein down to get Zack's story out. The proof is in his sketches.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein, who was not among the 600 people who attended the book party on Thursday at the Parsons School of Design (he was feeling under the weather), praised Mr. Shahid's ''fantastic art direction'' but said he didn't think the book was about Mr. Carr or him.</p>
        <p>''I think the book is about George Carr,'' Mr. Klein said. ''This is about a brother and his feelings for Zack. To me, that's what the book is about -- this love and admiration.''</p>
        <p>It may be, as the photographer Bruce Weber suggested, that the only purpose of this elegant book is to keep alive the memory of an unsung design hero, a phrase used by Patrick McCarthy, the editorial director of Fairchild Publications, in the book's wistful series of remembrances.</p>
        <p>But what a pity. By wanting to be noble and to give credit where it was due, the collaborators missed -- or perhaps tiptoed around -- the most compelling drama of all: the complex relationship between Mr. Klein and Mr. Carr.</p>
        <p>Of the two men, it was Mr. Carr who possessed the artistic temperament, or rather displayed it freely in moody silences that often ended with a spree of treats from the Comme des Garçons shop for his adoring assistants. As Grace Coddington, a friend and the creative director of Vogue, said, ''He could be up or down, over the moon or insecure.''</p>
        <p>Narciso Rodriguez recalled that when he was at Calvin Klein, he showed Mr. Carr some sketches he and another assistant had made, but Mr. Carr turned away coldly and wouldn't speak to them for days. ''Then one morning he came in and said: 'Y'all' -- he still spoke in a Texas accent -- 'Y'all, I just want to say, I hate you. I'm so jealous. I cannot believe the power I see in your sketches. I hate you both.' '' Mr. Rodriguez laughed. ''Then he'd drag us off to Raoul's for dinner. There was no one like Zack. Creative, generous, vulnerable. He knew everything that was fashion history, and everything that would be fashion history.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weber, who first met Mr. Carr in the late 1970's, remembered a car trip back from Long Island when Mr. Carr brought up Elizabeth Taylor. ''He could name every movie she had been in -- who had done the hair, makeup, clothes,'' Mr. Weber said. ''We had a great talk of fantasy about her.'' Later, after meeting the actress, he started sending her gifts. ''I don't think she ever realized who sent them,'' Mr. Weber said. ''A cashmere stole. Ten silk scarves from Calvin Klein.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''Zack was a mentor to a lot of us. He was aware of Georgia O'Keeffe long before anyone else in this small group. He was like the crazy professor, and Calvin was part of the class.''</p>
        <p>But to anyone connected with that group, the relationship between Mr. Carr and Mr. Klein was a marriage. ''Zack loved Calvin, and he hated him,'' said a former design assistant, speaking, as others did, on condition of anonymity. ''He could talk about Calvin for hours. Zack was a master at that relationship.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weber recalled going on a trip to Greece with them when they broke into a huge fight. As marriages go, he said, ''it wasn't so different from Liz's and Richard Burton's,'' a parallel that others drew as well.</p>
        <p>To say where the creative lines were drawn between them is much harder, however, because it raises touchy questions of loyalty and betrayal in a business where there is little candor. ''It's difficult,'' Ms. Coddington said, ''because I love Calvin.'' She thought for a moment and said, ''Zack was always in the shadows, but, really, he was Calvin Klein.'' Others made similar comments, saying in one instance that Mr. Carr's designs were ''more Calvin than Calvin.''</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Carr did not have what it takes to be the frontman in the business, and when his own company closed at the end of the 80's, he returned to Calvin Klein, where he remained until he became ill -- looked after by family, friends like Ms. Coddington, and Mr. Klein.</p>
        <p>So perhaps the key word is ''difficult.'' It is difficult to know what makes a marriage. And as Ms. Coddington said, with some wisdom, ''There's so much more to being a designer than designing clothes.''</p>
        <p>No one knows that better than Mr. Klein. He does not know what strain in Mr. Carr's big personality allowed him to occupy the shadows of another's fame. ''I can't explain it,'' he said yesterday. ''I think Zack had a great time when he worked here.'' But neither, Mr. Klein said, does he resent anyone else for trying to explain it, or saying that Mr. Carr was Calvin Klein.</p>
        <p>''I take it as a great compliment,'' he said. ''I've been able to set up a company where many people think that way.'' He added: ''You can't do this job alone. It's a collaborative effort by many people. And you have to be around a long time to have that kind of thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
