<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 6 Months, Her Feet Are Back on the Ground</title>
    <meta content="27SHUT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="879730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Astronautics and Aeronautics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atlantis (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Shannon W. Lucid</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lucid, Shannon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Navarro, Mireya</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E7DE153CF934A1575AC0A960958260" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 6 Months, Her Feet Are Back on the Ground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIREYA NAVARRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Navarro, Mireya</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shannon W . Lucid walks out of space shuttle Atlantis today, with some assistance as she feels pull of gravity for first time in more than six months; photo; 53-year-old biochemist is greeted by family, jokes with usual good nature, takes call from Pres Clinton and begins extensive testing to see how her body coped with 188 days in space; doctors say she could experience lethargy, loss of calcium from bones and loss of muscle strength (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shannon W. Lucid walked out of the space shuttle Atlantis today, propped up by helpers but on her own power after feeling the pull of gravity for the first time in more than six months, NASA officials said.</p>
        <p>The shuttle touched down under scattered clouds at the Kennedy Space Center here at 8:13 A.M., after a 10-day mission to exchange cargo with the Russian space station Mir and retrieve Dr. Lucid, 53, a biochemist whose 188 days in space broke the record for an American astronaut and for a woman. In her place the Atlantis left behind another American, John E. Blaha, a 54-year-old retired Air Force colonel, to begin a four-month tour aboard the Mir.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shannon W. Lucid walked out of the space shuttle Atlantis today, propped up by helpers but on her own power after feeling the pull of gravity for the first time in more than six months, NASA officials said.</p>
        <p>The shuttle touched down under scattered clouds at the Kennedy Space Center here at 8:13 A.M., after a 10-day mission to exchange cargo with the Russian space station Mir and retrieve Dr. Lucid, 53, a biochemist whose 188 days in space broke the record for an American astronaut and for a woman. In her place the Atlantis left behind another American, John E. Blaha, a 54-year-old retired Air Force colonel, to begin a four-month tour aboard the Mir.</p>
        <p>In a taped appearance from the astronaut quarters, Dr. Lucid looked relaxed and cheerful as she sat on a reclining chair with legs crossed, laughing and showing the good nature that kept her smiling even after her return was delayed by hurricanes and shuttle problems on Earth. Surrounded by her husband, Michael, two daughters, a son and a son-in-law, all of whom flew in from Texas to welcome her, she joked,</p>
        <p>''Look like we're all together and that you're happy that I'm home.''</p>
        <p>They did.</p>
        <p>In the afternoon she also took a call from President Clinton, who called her ''a terrific inspiration for young women around the country and all around the world.'' Mr. Clinton said he would meet her on Friday in Houston, where she is to arrive at the Johnson Space Center.</p>
        <p>David Leestma, director of flight crew operations and a former astronaut, said fire rescue personnel were getting ready to carry Dr. Lucid from the shuttle after the landing but she said, ''No, I can stand up.''</p>
        <p>She did, as they held her for support, and, although ''wobbly and woozy,'' Mr. Leestma said, she managed to walk 25 to 30 feet to a transport vehicle.</p>
        <p>''She's in great shape,'' Daniel Goldin, the NASA Administrator, said after spending a few minutes with her. ''She came out standing up, on her own power.''</p>
        <p>Despite the first good impressions, Dr. Lucid immediately began undergoing blood-pressure tests and other evaluations to determine how her body had coped with the long stay in weightlessness and how it was readapting to gravity. Doctors said she would have a few days of rest followed by two to three weeks of physical therapy, water exercises and other rehabilitation.</p>
        <p>Doctors said she could experience lethargy, loss of calcium from her bones and as much as a 25 percent loss in muscle strength, as have previous astronauts, who have apparently recovered in weeks or months.</p>
        <p>On her first day back she was given tests to she if her muscle, bone or even blood had been reduced and to examine her body fluids. Despite her initial steps, Dr. Lucid spent her first few hours back lying down or sitting, even when taking her first shower in half a year.</p>
        <p>From the Johnson Space Center, Frank Culbertson, manager of the shuttle-Mir program, said doctors had found her ''in really good health.''</p>
        <p>It remained to be determined, however, whether she is fit to go home, NASA officials said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lucid spent seven more weeks in space than had been planned because of technical problems and launching delays caused by hurricanes. She orbited Earth with two Russians, Yuri Onufrienko and Yuri Usachev.</p>
        <p>In her conversation with the President, Dr. Lucid had only praise for the Russian astronauts.</p>
        <p>''It couldn't have been a better experience,'' she said. ''I really enjoyed working with the cosmonauts.''</p>
        <p>The American who had previously spent the longest stay in space was Dr. Norman E. Thagard, who left Mir after 115 days last year. A Russian astronaut, Elena Kondakova, set the previous record for a woman by spending 169 days on the Mir in 1994 and 1995. The longest space stay ever was by Valery Polyakov, a Russian who was on the Mir for 439 day in 1994 and 1995.</p>
        <p>Today, Tommy Holloway, shuttle program manager, said a nozzle at the bottom of one of the booster rockets that help launch the shuttle will be inspected because it had grooves, some half an inch deep, around its circumference. The grooves indicate an erosion in the layer of insulation inside the nozzle that keeps hot gas from burning through the side of the booster. But Mr. Holloway said it was too early to tell whether this represented a safety concern.</p>
        <p>Throughout her extended stay, Dr. Lucid kept her good humor but left no doubt she was ready to come home. Her plans include camping and canoeing with her son and in-line skating with her daughters. Her return also means the end of sponge baths and dehydrated food.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton sent her greetings and a large box of M &amp; M's, Mr. Goldin said, to help satisfy her expressed craving for those sweets, potato chips and other junk food.</p>
        <p>At a news conference the Atlantis's five other crew members gamely answered questions about Dr. Lucid, who upstaged them despite her absence at the microphones. Lieut. Col. Carl E. Walz of the Air Force, 41, a mission specialist, recalled that when the shuttle touched down ''she just had a tremendous smile on her face and we shook hands.''</p>
        <p>Capt. William F. Readdy of the Navy Reserve, the mission's 44-year-old commander, said Dr. Lucid filled the orbiter with laughter and ''made our burden lighter.''</p>
        <p>The shuttle missions to the Mir are stepping stones to building a larger international space station, set to begin next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
