<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Joyce Typescript Moves to Texas</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="361424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">RANSOM HUMANITIES RESEARCH CENTER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOYCE, JAMES (1882-1941)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STALEY, THOMAS F (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITGANG, HERBERT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FINNEGAN'S WAKE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D7163EF935A25755C0A966958260" item-length="1459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Joyce Typescript Moves to Texas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MITGANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MITGANG, HERBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A typescript of the opening chapter of James Joyce's ''Finnegans Wake,'' with the author's additions written in by hand, has turned up in Texas after being discovered in a private collection last year in Paris.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A typescript of the opening chapter of James Joyce's ''Finnegans Wake,'' with the author's additions written in by hand, has turned up in Texas after being discovered in a private collection last year in Paris.</p>
        <p>A typescript of the opening chapter of James Joyce's ''Finnegans Wake,'' with the author's additions written in by hand, has turned up in Texas after being discovered in a private collection last year in Paris.</p>
        <p>''It's a major literary find,'' said Dr. Thomas F. Staley, director of the Ransom Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin, who is the author or editor of seven books on Joyce.</p>
        <p>The center acquired the typescript and related Joyce papers after Dr. Staley received a tip from a friend in Paris that they existed. The typescript, along with other literary papers, was owned by the 90-year-old widow of Stuart Gilbert, a friend and research assistant of Joyce's who died in 1969.</p>
        <p>''The typescript is part of the only known privately held archive kept by a member of the Joyce circle in France,'' Dr. Staley said in a recent interview.</p>
        <p>Dr. Staley said the changes Joyce wrote on the typescript, which Gilbert apparently retrieved from the printer, ''include additions and emendations,'' all of which appear in the standard Viking Penquin edition of the novel. For example, at one point Joyce inserted a sentence reading, ''Of Burymeleg and Bindmerollingeyes and all the deed in the woe.''</p>
        <p>Price Not Disclosed</p>
        <p>The typescript and other papers were bought for an undisclosed amount. An indication of its possible price can be surmised from the fact that another copy of the typescript, without Joyce's handwritten changes, was sold to a private buyer last November at Sotheby's for approximately $100,000.</p>
        <p>The critic Edmund Wilson said the brilliant, puzzling ''Finnegans Wake'' was written in Jabberwocky, but it actually includes words and phrases from dozens of different languages.</p>
        <p>In ''Ulysses,'' Joyce follows Leopold Bloom, an advertising salesman, around Dublin through the course of one day in 1904 - June 16, a date that is now annually celebrated by Joyce scholars and admirers as ''Bloomsday.'' In ''Finnegans Wake,'' Joyce was supposedly recording the night thoughts on that same day of a dreaming mind through the vision of an Irish publican, H. C. Earwicker, whose initials stand for Here Comes Everybody. Samuel Beckett, a close friend and onetime secretary to Joyce, once said that the only way to understand ''Finnegans Wake'' is to read it aloud.</p>
        <p>''The material in the archive includes documents that help to explain Joyce's working methods and provides clues to how he invented and reinvented language,'' Dr. Staley said. ''The centerpiece of the collection is Gilbert's unpublished diary. It presents a picture of Joyce, his family and friends during the crucial time after 'Ulysses' was published and he had become the doyen of the literary world.''</p>
        <p>A Letter From Eliot</p>
        <p>Among the papers in the collection is a letter written in 1935 by T. S. Eliot to Mr. Gilbert, an Englishman who lived in Paris with his French wife, Moune. In his role as an editor at Faber &amp; Faber in London, Eliot was trying to obtain the manuscript of ''Finnegans Wake.'' Eliot wrote:</p>
        <p>''Is he doing any work at present, and have you any idea how near the book may be to completion? Of course one never can tell with Joyce because he is always revising and rewriting indefinitely, but it would be something to know that he had got within measurable distance of finishing the first draft.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Staley commented: ''Joyce never seemed to cut out words when he revised his manuscripts. He always added new phrases and sentences. 'Ulysses' is about 25 percent longer because of his additions.''</p>
        <p>After 17 years of writing, ''Finnegans Wake,'' which was known as ''Work in Progress'' when it appeared in part in the avant-garde magazine Transition, was finally published in 1939 by Faber &amp; Faber in England and by Viking Press in the United States.</p>
        <p>Journals, Lists and Notes</p>
        <p>In addition to the typescript, the papers also include Gilbert's journals, drafts of critical word lists, workbooks, notes taken at meetings with Joyce and a library of 1,000 volumes. In it are books given to him by Beckett, Albert Camus, Andre Malraux, Jean-Paul Sartre, Eliot and other writers Gilbert knew or translated.</p>
        <p>How did Joyce research all the names, places and foreign-language phrases and minutiae that went into ''Finnegans Wake'' - and then turn them inside out and upside-down in linked words that have driven literary bloodhounds crazy for the last 50 years?</p>
        <p>In a 1926 letter, Joyce defended what he was undertaking: ''One great part of every human existence is passed in a state which cannot be rendered sensible by the use of wideawake language, cutanddry grammar and goahead plot.''</p>
        <p>Gilbert's diary entries expand on Joyce's own explanation and disclose some of the methods behind his mannerisms. In a diary entry made on Jan. 31, 1930, that offers clues to Joyce's derivative research and roundabout creativity on ''Work in Progress,'' or W. in P., Gilbert writes:</p>
        <p>''At last J. J. has recommenced work on W. in P. Five volumes of the Encyclopedia Brit. on his sofa. He has made a list of 30 towns. New York, Vienna, Budapest, etc. Whenever I come to a name (of a street, suburb, park, etc.), I pause. J. thinks. If he can Anglicise the word, i.e., make a pun of it, the name or its deformations are recorded in a notebook. Thus 'Slotspark' (I think) at Christiana becomes Sluts' park. He collects all queer names, in this way and will soon have a notebook full of them.</p>
        <p>''The system seems bad for (1) there is little hope of the reader knowing these names - most seem new even to J. himself, and certainly are to me. And supposing the reader, knowing the fragment dealt with towns, took the trouble to look up the Encyclopedia, would he hit on the 30 J. has selected. (2) The insertion of these puns is bound to lead him away from the basic text, to create divagations - and the work is hard enough anyhow!''</p>
        <p>Advice for Joyce</p>
        <p>In one diary entry, Gilbert offers his opinion about how Joyce should have written ''Finnegans Wake'' and criticizes the Irish author's provinciality. ''The good method would be to write out a page of plain English and then rejuvenate dull words by injection of new (and appropriate) meaning,'' Gilbert wrote in his diary. ''What he is doing is too easy to do, and too hard to understand (for the reader). I think I shall try my hand at the simple method myself. Too much sound and fury makes unsound and furtive . . . or fudgy. He is curled on his sofa, while I struggle with Danish or Romanian names, pondering puns. With foreign words it's too easy. The provincial Dubliner. Foreign is funny.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gilbert's diary entries also show that sometimes the half-blind Joyce made research entries into his little black book himself, but when he called upon his friends to read them back to him, they found them illegible.</p>
        <p>Personal Touches</p>
        <p>A number of Gilbert's diary entries recall social engagements involving the Joyces. On New Year's Eve in 1930, the Joyces gave a party for a group of friends in Paris. At 2:30 A.M., Joyce began to dance an Irish jig to the tune of ''Auld Lang Syne,'' and Nora Joyce became indignant and ordered all the guests to leave because her husband was ''making a fool of himself.'' Gilbert adds in his diary: ''But I disagree; he is a nimble dancer. If J. had not been a writer he'd a been a meistersinger; if not a singer, a ballerino.''</p>
        <p>In other entries from the 1930's, Gilbert confided his view that the lives of Paris's literary lions, including Joyce's, are empty. He writes that they do not attach themselves to anything except ephemeral things and soon get bored. They are ''too self-centered.'' Gilbert said Joyce could not settle down ''to continuous work or make friends for friendship's sake,'' and he still had ''the naive enthusiasm for self-proclaimed rebels and the naive belief that people who have morals are hypocrites.''</p>
        <p>Appraising the Diarist</p>
        <p>Commenting on the rather harsh appraisal of Joyce by Gilbert in the diary, Dr. Staley said: ''Although Gilbert attempts to stand back and watch with cynicism the dynamics of the various people surrounding Joyce, he reveals his own concern for his place in the circle. He knows he is of immense value to Joyce, but he is also unhappily aware that he is not as close or involved in the Joyce orbit as others of whom he writes. For this he is both grateful and at the same time slightly resentful. That he admires Joyce and his achievements is evident. His cynicism, however, is more clearly revealed when he writes of those who surround the master.''</p>
        <p>Selections from Gilbert's diary will appear in the summer 1990 issue of Joyce Studies Annual. An annotated edition of the diary is planned by the University of Texas Press, but the timing has not been determined.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
