<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Repair Hurdles, a Clock Tower Is Saved</title>
    <meta content="29liclockWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1800583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRESERVATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Watches and Clocks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEEDA143FF93AA15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Repair Hurdles, a Clock Tower Is Saved</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RUTHIE ACKERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ackerman, Ruthie</byline>
      <dateline>Roslyn, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH its obelisk shape and mix of Gothic, Romanesque and Egyptian Revival styles, the clock tower in the Village of Roslyn is one of the most recognizable landmarks on Long Island. So when the restoration of the tower was finally finished in September after 11 years of setbacks, residents and officials celebrated.</p>
        <p>''The funny thing is, I actually live by the clock's time,'' said Julie A. Klein, who lives across Main Street from the clock tower and can see it from her living room window, bedroom window and front porch. Ms. Klein said that when the clock tower's 2,500-pound bronze bell rings on the hour, it can be heard throughout the village's historic district.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH its obelisk shape and mix of Gothic, Romanesque and Egyptian Revival styles, the clock tower in the Village of Roslyn is one of the most recognizable landmarks on Long Island. So when the restoration of the tower was finally finished in September after 11 years of setbacks, residents and officials celebrated.</p>
        <p>''The funny thing is, I actually live by the clock's time,'' said Julie A. Klein, who lives across Main Street from the clock tower and can see it from her living room window, bedroom window and front porch. Ms. Klein said that when the clock tower's 2,500-pound bronze bell rings on the hour, it can be heard throughout the village's historic district.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the clock is off by a minute or two, Mayor John Durkin admitted with a smile, so he sends village maintenance workers to adjust the pendulum. But a 111-year-old clock can be forgiven for being a little slow.</p>
        <p>The 55-foot-tall tower was originally built as a memorial to a longtime Roslyn resident, Ellen E. Ward, by her children and given to the Town of North Hempstead before the Village of Roslyn was incorporated. In 1995, the tower's centennial, the Town of North Hempstead sold it to Roslyn for $1.</p>
        <p>The restoration was a birthday present for the centennial, but its completion was delayed because of difficulties getting matching grants from the state, especially after 9/11, said John Collins, the former director of the Roslyn Landmark Society and the project's manager.</p>
        <p>But the first phase was completed in 1997 anyway with $40,000 in private funds raised by the Landmark Society. It included replacing the old mortar on two sides and stabilizing the brownstone to stop further deterioration.</p>
        <p>Phase two started in 2004 with a $34,000 state grant and included finishing the other two sides and restoring the windows, which were falling apart. It also included some electrical work and adding a bronze plaque and a time capsule, which contained Roslyn-specific items like a village pen, a parking meter and a menu from Trattoria Diane.</p>
        <p>But once work on phase two began, it became obvious that there was not enough money to complete it. ''One window cost $6,000,'' said George C. Soos, the village administrator. ''We had 10 windows. With a grant of $34,000, it was hardly enough to do the job.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Durkin said that it was difficult to raise money for monuments.</p>
        <p>''There are so many other causes -- medical causes, health issues, poverty,'' he said. ''To get people to say we're going to rebuild a monument wasn't a high priority. But because of who we are and where we are, people were pretty generous.''</p>
        <p>By the time the group received the state grant, the costs had gone up. Phase two cost $105,000, including state and private funds.</p>
        <p>The total cost of both phases of the restoration came to $145,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Collins said paint samples were sent to experts to determine the color of the original paint -- a blackish-brown -- and to ensure that the restoration was true to the original.</p>
        <p>''The idea of the restoration wasn't to make the clock tower look brand new,'' he said. ''We wanted it to look like a 100-year-old tower.''</p>
        <p>PRESERVATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
