<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trachsel, Piazza and Ordóñez Give Mets a Lift</title>
    <meta content="28METS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/28/sports/baseball/28METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1312792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Piazza, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2DC133DF93BA15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trachsel, Piazza and Ordóñez Give Mets a Lift</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trachsel, Piazza and Ordóñez Lift Mets Over Phillies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Philadelphia Phillies, 6-1; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets played a terrific game last night. They got outstanding pitching from a renewed Steve Trachsel, two home runs from Mike Piazza and a splendid night of hitting and fielding from Rey Ordóñez.</p>
        <p>After the game, they acquired two minor league pitchers from the team they beat, the Philadelphia Phillies, in exchange for the veteran relievers Dennis Cook and Turk Wendell. So even a well-played 6-1 victory at Shea Stadium came with a somber reminder of how insignificant the rest of this season would be. Cook and Wendell now pitch for a National League East rival.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets got outstanding pitching from Steve Trachsel, two home runs from Mike Piazza and a splendid all-around night from Rey Ordóñez in a win over Philadelphia</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets played a terrific game last night. They got outstanding pitching from a renewed Steve Trachsel, two home runs from Mike Piazza and a splendid night of hitting and fielding from Rey Ordóñez.</p>
        <p>After the game, they acquired two minor league pitchers from the team they beat, the Philadelphia Phillies, in exchange for the veteran relievers Dennis Cook and Turk Wendell. So even a well-played 6-1 victory at Shea Stadium came with a somber reminder of how insignificant the rest of this season would be. Cook and Wendell now pitch for a National League East rival.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of mind-boggling,'' said John Franco, the Mets' captain. ''But you've got to do what you've got to do. This is our division. But I guess you have to start somewhere.''</p>
        <p>Four gloomy months have made the Mets (47-57) sellers on the trade market as Tuesday's deadline approaches. Dealing Cook and Wendell for Bruce Chen and Adam Walker may lead to more deals that can boost the major league roster, but mostly it symbolizes how the Mets have squandered the season. They have depleted their bullpen, which at one time had depth that was essential to their success.</p>
        <p>The face of the bullpen will change. Rick White will probably assume Wendell's late-inning setup position, and Chen, Jerrod Riggan and Grant Roberts will play larger roles.</p>
        <p>''Maybe we'll score a whole bunch of runs the next two months,'' Manager Bobby Valentine said, citing the Mets' biggest problem, ''and not even worry about the bullpen.''</p>
        <p>Because of Trachsel, the Mets needed only one inning from their bullpen last night. Trachsel lasted eight innings, allowing an unearned run on six hits and no walks and winning his third start in a row.</p>
        <p>Trachsel is 4-4 with a 3.53 earned run average in nine starts since returning from Class AAA Norfolk on June 8. He got six runs of support for the second start in a row; Ordóñez drove in two runs and Piazza three. Piazza homered to left field in the third inning, a blast that went an estimated 472 feet and gave the Mets a 3-1 lead, and he homered to right in the seventh.</p>
        <p>It was Trachsel's third consecutive strong outing since the All-Star Game break. He improved to 5-10, the same record as Kevin Appier, the other off-season addition to the Mets' rotation. Appier has pitched better than Trachsel, with a 3.99 E.R.A. and a run of bad luck. But Trachsel has been a different pitcher lately, with victories in four of his last five decisions and the confidence to work through misfortune.</p>
        <p>Trachsel survived an ugly -- and unlucky -- first inning that began when second baseman Edgardo Alfonzo booted Doug Glanville's grounder. First baseman Todd Zeile then botched a double-play grounder, bobbling it and getting only the sure out at first. Bobby Abreu singled home Glanville, then stole second and reached third on Piazza's throwing error. But Trachsel struck out Travis Lee to escape further harm and continued to work out of trouble.</p>
        <p>''That's the 'positivity' thing right there,'' Trachsel said. ''Just stay focused and don't let it affect the way you're pitching.''</p>
        <p>Trachsel kept his focus, as well as his assortment of sharp pitches. The Phillies put a runner in scoring position in the third, fourth, sixth and seventh, but could not score again.</p>
        <p>The fourth inning ended with a flourish from Ordóñez, who on Thursday night could not handle a single by Jimmy Rollins that brought in the Phillies' winning run.</p>
        <p>Last night, with one out and runners at first and second in the fourth, Kevin Jordan grounded sharply up the middle. Ordóñez ranged far to his left and caught the ball on a dive. He then flipped it from his glove to Alfonzo, who fielded the low feed and fired to first to complete the double play.</p>
        <p>The luck was turning for Trachsel, whose father, Roy, flew in from California to see the game. Trachsel said he was glad this game went better than the one his sister saw in May. That night, he noted, he was bombed by San Diego, then sent to Norfolk.</p>
        <p>After that game, on May 17, the Mets were 15-25 and their chances to contend were effectively snuffed out. The Mets buried themselves early, and their .500 pace since then was not enough to persuade club officials to stick with this mix.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we're really doing it for right now; that's obvious,'' third baseman Robin Ventura said of the trade. ''Compared to when you're adding guys, it's obviously a different feel. We feel like we've got solid guys like them, and when you get rid of them, it doesn't make you feel that much better. Obviously, you're going to miss those two.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Manager BOBBY VALENTINE said closer ARMANDO BENITEZ had stiffness in his right forearm that ''comes and goes.'' Benitez has pitched only in save situations in his last 10 appearances, and he is 24 for 24 in save opportunities this year.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
