<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haitian Refugee Interviews Begin Aboard U.S. Navy Ship</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="693935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASYLUM (POLITICAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KIFNER, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE0D8173DF934A25755C0A962958260" item-length="1218" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haitian Refugee Interviews Begin Aboard U.S. Navy Ship</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KIFNER, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>KINGSTON, Jamaica, June 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first shipboard processing of Haitians' applications for asylum under the Administration's new policy began today aboard a Navy hospital ship moored here.</p>
        <p>At 9 A.M. 35 Haitians picked up from leaky wooden sailboats were put on board the white-painted Comfort, the red crosses on its hull gleaming in the tropical sun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first shipboard processing of Haitians' applications for asylum under the Administration's new policy began today aboard a Navy hospital ship moored here.</p>
        <p>At 9 A.M. 35 Haitians picked up from leaky wooden sailboats were put on board the white-painted Comfort, the red crosses on its hull gleaming in the tropical sun.</p>
        <p>In keeping with the plan to handle the requests for asylum on ships or on land outside the United States, the 1,000-bed ship carried an array of interpreters and hastily trained immigration officials ready to weigh the stories of the Haitians and decide whether they would be sent back or granted refugee status and allowed to enter the United States or other countries.</p>
        <p>More than 1,800 Haitians have been returned without hearings since the policy was announced last month.  Rights Advocates Watching</p>
        <p>Human rights advocates, who had fought the policy of returning the Haitians picked up at sea, were watching the new procedures with grave concern, waiting to see if they would simply prove to be a more elaborate mechanism for sending the Haitians back.</p>
        <p>Of particular concern were how much time the sun-parched refugees would have to rest and rehydrate after being picked up from the tossing seas, and what access they would have to interpreters and counselors.</p>
        <p>By keeping the interviewing off American soil, the Administration is in effect denying the Haitians access to a number of legal options they would be guaranteed as soon as they set foot in the United States.</p>
        <p>"Only time will tell whether this is a sincere effort by the Administration," said Arthur Helton, director of migration programs for the Open Society Institute in New York. "The Haitian boat people are in a virtual legal netherworld and one in which lawlessness can go unchecked. They are at the mercy of the sensitivity and beneficence of those who staff this operation. The procedural safeguards are meager."</p>
        <p>In addition, the new procedures call for refugees to meet a standard, in the eyes of immigration officials, of a "well-founded fear" of persecution should they be sent home. This is a tougher standard than the "credible fear" that had been used when refugees were being interned at the United States Naval Station at Guantanamo Bay, Cuba.  'Discrimination' Seen</p>
        <p>Lucas Guttentag, an immigration expert at the American Civil Liberties Union in New York, said, "The Administration should not continue to discriminate against Haitian refugees by applying a higher standard for Haitians than for nationals of the former Soviet Union and designated Southeast Asian countries."</p>
        <p>Kofi Asomani, special envoy to Haiti for the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, said tonight: "This is an exceptional situation. It has a number of logistical and other difficulties, but it is something that is workable."</p>
        <p>After visiting the hospital ship this afternoon, he said, "I came away feeling it is possible."</p>
        <p>But when pressed on whether the procedure would be fair in protecting the rights of the refugees, Mr. Asomani replied: "I don't think we can answer that it is fair. Those who have a claim will have a chance to tell their stories. It's as close to what we would say would be a fair procedure as possible."</p>
        <p>The refugees were picked up in three different groups by the United States Coast Guard cutters Escape, Durable and Dependable. Interviewing Begins</p>
        <p>The interviewing of the refugees aboard the ship began around 2 P.M., said Ron Tonalis, a Justice Department spokesman attached to the inter-agency organization running the refugee operation here.</p>
        <p>Shortly after boarding the ships, each of the 34 adults and one child were issued electronically coded plastic identification bracelets, similar to those hospital patients wear. In military terminology, they are called Dmpits, for Deployed Mass Population Identification Tracking System.</p>
        <p>They were also given an explanation of the refugee procedures by representatives of the United Nations refugee organization, who will remain aboard the ship as observers.</p>
        <p>The questioning, Mr. Tonalis said, would be carried out by about 60 immigration inspectors who have been given a week of special training in San Antonio. The refugees were to have access, he said, to a group of about 86 Creole-speaking translators who are contract employees of the State Department, working for the International Office of Migration.</p>
        <p>The immigration inspectors, he said, would have access to a computerized system listing incidents that are known to have occurred in Haiti that might help an asylum-seeker make a case. For example, if a Haitian cites the death of a realtive at the hands of the military government, the computer could confirm the record of the killing.  Final Say by Six Officers</p>
        <p>The initial recommendations of the inspectors on whether individuals are to be granted refugee status would then be reviewed by one of six "quality assurance" officers who would have the final say.</p>
        <p>Those who are deemed legitimate refugees are to be brought to the Guantanamo Bay for medical tests and eventual assignment to sponsors. Those who test positive for exposure to H.I.V. or any of several other diseases could be disqualified, Mr. Tonalis said, although this could be appealed.</p>
        <p>Those who failto gain refugee status are to be put aboard a Coast Guard cutter and transported back to the Haitian capital, Port-au-Prince.</p>
        <p>The essential criterion, Mr. Tonalis said is the "well-founded fear" of persecution based on five categories: race, nationality, religion, membership in a social group, or holding a political opinion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tonalis declined to give any examples of what might or might not be ruled valid.</p>
        <p>In the past Administration officials have said they believed that only about five percent of the Haitians trying to flee were eligible political refugees, an estimate that has infuriated human rights groups. Twists in Clinton Policy</p>
        <p>The shipboard questioning aboard the Comfort and at a processing center being set up on the Turks and Caicos Islands are the latest twists in President Clinton's Haitian policy.</p>
        <p>During his campaign, Mr. Clinton vigorously condemned the Bush Administration's policy of returning Haitians found at sea as "immoral" and "cruel" and called for asylum for those fleeing the military Government that ousted the elected President, Jean-Bertrand Aristide.</p>
        <p>But once elected and faced with a potential flood of unwelcome Haitians, the President reverted to sending Haitians back, even though they were presumed to face additional hostility for having tried to escape.</p>
        <p>But particularly after attention shifted from South Africa this spring, Mr. Clinton found himself under mounting pressure from human rights organizations, including a hunger strike by Randall Robinson, president of TransAfrica Forum, a research and lobbying group.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Clinton has named William Gray 3d, president of the United Negro College Fund, as his special envoy for Haiti and has stepped up the embargo against its military rulers in an effort to unseat them. The United States has also and instituted bans on financial transaction and commercial air traffic between Haiti and the United States to put pressure on Haiti's elite, who generally support the military government.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
