<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Move With Care In the Simpson Case</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="693931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMPSON, O J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMPSON, NICOLE BROWN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDMAN, RONALD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYDANS, SETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D8173DF934A25755C0A962958260" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Move With Care In the Simpson Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYDANS, SETH</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Los Angeles city police and the office of the county's District Attorney have every reason to move cautiously as they marshal evidence in the fatal stabbing of O. J. Simpson's former wife and a friend of hers last Sunday night.</p>
        <p>The authorities here have failed to win convictions in some sensational cases in recent years, among them the McMartin Preschool child-molestation trial, the first trial of police officers who beat Rodney G. King and the murder trial of the Menendez brothers. Indeed, the current District Attorney, Gil Garcetti, won office two years ago in part because of the prosecutorial failures of his predecessor, Ira Reiner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Los Angeles city police and the office of the county's District Attorney have every reason to move cautiously as they marshal evidence in the fatal stabbing of O. J. Simpson's former wife and a friend of hers last Sunday night.</p>
        <p>The authorities here have failed to win convictions in some sensational cases in recent years, among them the McMartin Preschool child-molestation trial, the first trial of police officers who beat Rodney G. King and the murder trial of the Menendez brothers. Indeed, the current District Attorney, Gil Garcetti, won office two years ago in part because of the prosecutorial failures of his predecessor, Ira Reiner.</p>
        <p>Now investigators are circling carefully around a high-profile subject of the current inquiry: Mr. Simpson, a popular onetime football star in the hands of a top-flight lawyer, Robert L. Shapiro, who is bringing in his own forensic experts from New York and Connecticut to examine every step the police take.  No Dearth of Questions</p>
        <p>The police have said little about their efforts, and many questions await answers:</p>
        <p>*What weapon was used to kill Nicole Brown Simpson and her friend, Robert L. Goldman, at the gate of her home in the Brentwood section here? And where is that weapon?</p>
        <p>*Was there more than one attacker? Why were no screams or other sounds of struggle heard on the quiet street? Were the two victims killed simultaneously, or did some time pass between the slayings?</p>
        <p>*Since blood at the scene flowed down a walkway from just inside Mrs. Simpson's gate, which was usually locked, had she not allowed her killer onto the property?</p>
        <p>*Did the Simpsons' two children, later found inside Mrs. Simpson's home, hear nothing? Were they alone when the attack occurred? A Search in Chicago</p>
        <p>As these questions lingered today, police officers carrying metal detectors searched a rocky, weedy lot adjacent to the O'Hare Plaza Hotel in Chicago, where Mr. Simpson had arrived early Monday morning for a promotional appearance after an overnight flight from Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Detective Bert Luper, one of two Los Angeles police officers who are in Chicago to pursue evidence there, would not say what the searchers were looking for. But he did say he had a possible witness: a customer at a nearby gasoline station who recalled having seen a man fitting Mr. Simpson's description in the lot on Monday.</p>
        <p>The officers scouring the block-long lot apparently found nothing there today, but Detective Luper suggested that the search would resume on Friday. Few Confirmed Details</p>
        <p>Detective Luper's remarks were among very few that have been offered by the police, who have not termed anyone a suspect.</p>
        <p>What is known beyond doubt about the case, from confirmation by Mr. Simpson's lawyers and eyewitness verification by reporters, is that the authorities questioned him for three hours on Monday and that they searched his house here, about two miles from Mrs. Simpson's home, as well as the limousine that carried him to the airport late Sunday night for the flight to Chicago, where the authorities later searched his hotel room.</p>
        <p>But, in addition, news reports here, quoting investigators not identified by name, have described findings that, if true, would point toward his being implicated.</p>
        <p>For instance, local news organizations have quoted investigators as saying a bloody glove was found at his home after the killings. Howard L. Weitzman, who was succeeded by Mr. Shapiro as Mr. Simpson's lawyer on Wednesday, said there had been no such discovery.</p>
        <p>The most plentiful source of potential evidence is blood. The simplest test can match blood types in an effort to determine whether Mr. Simpson's type can be found at the scene, or those of the victims at his home, assuming that his type is different from theirs. But since each blood type is carried by many people, this test would be far from conclusive.</p>
        <p>More sophisticated tests can match the DNA in blood at the scene -- if in fact the killer spilled any of his own blood there -- with that of an individual, providing identification with a high degree of probability. But this test can take up to two months to complete.  Simpson Attends Funeral</p>
        <p>As the investigation continued, both victims were buried today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simpson, wearing a dark suit and dark glasses, attended the funeral for Mrs. Simpson this morning. As he left St. Martin of Tours Roman Catholic Church after the service, he held hands with the couple's 9-year-old daughter, Sydney, and 6-year-old son, Justin. The coffin was carried from the church to a white hearse, and the funeral procession left for Ascension Cemetery in the town of Lake Forest, 50 miles to the south.</p>
        <p>Mourners said Mr. Simpson had not been among the eulogists at the funeral. They also said his relations with Mrs. Simpson's family were good. His lawyer, Mr. Shapiro, who attended the funeral, said Mrs. Simpson's mother, Louise Brown, had embraced him and said: "Do everything you can for O. J. The children need their father."</p>
        <p>Mr. Shapiro said he had hired Henry Lee, director of the Forensic Science Laboratory in Connecticut, to examine evidence collected in the police investigation. Mr. Lee helped lawyers for William K. Smith win his acquittal in a celebrated Florida rape trial and, in a widely followed Connecticut case, helped convict a man who had killed his wife and disposed of her body by running it through a wood chipper.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shapiro said he had also hired Dr. Michael Baden, former chief pathologist for New York City, who now works for the state police in Albany, to "request permission from the Los Angeles County Coroner to review their findings."</p>
        <p>"We are focusing on doing as thorough an investigation as is humanly possible with the best experts in the world," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simpson's friends are rallying around him, expressing belief that he could not have been the killer.</p>
        <p>Howard Bingham, a photographer and longtime friend of Mr. Simpson, was quoted by The Boston Globe today as saying that they had traveled together by chance on the overnight flight to Chicago and that Mr. Simpson had shown no emotions out of the ordinary.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
