<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rodriguez Will Play For U.S. in Tournament</title>
    <meta content="18classic" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/18/sports/baseball/18classic.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1732983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Baseball Classic</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Baseball Classic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6DB153FF93BA25752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rodriguez Will Play For U.S. in Tournament</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rodriguez Will Play for U.S. in Tournament</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After Alex Rodriguez wondered and wavered and wondered a little more about whether he should play in the World Baseball Classic, he eventually changed his mind last night and decided to compete for the United States.</p>
        <p>Yesterday afternoon, Rodriguez telephoned Gene Orza, the chief operating officer of the players union, to say that he would not participate. Orza said Rodriguez, the third baseman for the Yankees, sounded definitive after agonizing over playing for the United States or the Dominican Republic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yankees third baseman Alex Rodriguez changed his mind Tuesday night and decided to compete for the United States in the World Baseball Classic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After Alex Rodriguez wondered and wavered and wondered a little more about whether he should play in the World Baseball Classic, he eventually changed his mind last night and decided to compete for the United States.</p>
        <p>Yesterday afternoon, Rodriguez telephoned Gene Orza, the chief operating officer of the players union, to say that he would not participate. Orza said Rodriguez, the third baseman for the Yankees, sounded definitive after agonizing over playing for the United States or the Dominican Republic.</p>
        <p>But a few hours later, Orza, who had spent several weeks trying to persuade Rodriguez to commit to playing for either nation, found out that Rodriguez was questioning his decision. As a roster deadline of midnight approached, Scott Boras, Rodriguez's agent, said that Rodriguez would play.</p>
        <p>''Alex has made the decision to participate in the World Baseball Classic for the United States,'' Boras said. ''He decided that he should honor the country where he's a citizen.''</p>
        <p>In a statement on Arod.com, Rodriguez's Web site, Rodriguez mentioned how he made his decision after discussions with his family, Boras, Commissioner Bud Selig, the players union and players from both teams. Once Rodriguez said last month that he would not participate, Boras said, Rodriguez was inundated with calls trying to persuade him to reverse his decision.</p>
        <p>''The World Baseball Classic offers baseball and its fans an exciting new forum and I look forward, if selected, to representing the United States in what will be baseball's greatest international competition,'' Rodriguez said.</p>
        <p>There was some international intrigue surrounding Rodriguez because his participation in the 16-team tournament developed into a tug of war between the United States and the Dominican Republic. Both nations wanted Rodriguez and included him on their provisional rosters. Boras said that Rodriguez, perhaps the premier player in baseball, felt obligated to play.</p>
        <p>''With all of the talks he had with American and Dominican players, he got a feel for this and made the right decision,'' Boras said. ''I think he understood the importance of a player of his stature competing in this event.''</p>
        <p>When teams voted on staging the World Baseball Classic, the Yankees were the only team that voted against it. Now Rodriguez, Derek Jeter, Johnny Damon, Robinson Cano and Bernie Williams are scheduled to participate, leaving a void in spring training that will irritate George Steinbrenner, the team's principal owner. The tournament runs from March 3 to 20.</p>
        <p>Because Rodriguez did not want to offend either country and is maniacal about maintaining a precise spring training schedule, he announced last month that he would bypass the event. He had originally said he would probably play for the Dominican Republic, where his parents were born. Rodriguez's statement about not playing could have ended his association with the event, but it did not.</p>
        <p>Orza continued lobbying Rodriguez because of the importance of having him in the inaugural tournament. Rodriguez listened to the recruiting pitches until the day rosters were due. After deciding he would stick to his plan and not compete, Rodriguez hedged, then surprised many by saying he wanted to play.</p>
        <p>''If someone who is one of the best players on the planet isn't playing in the tournament, then there's something wrong with the tournament,'' Orza said. ''I think it's the right conclusion.''</p>
        <p>The Dominicans wanted Rodriguez so badly that they included him on their provisional roster, even though they had no guarantee he would participate. The United States originally did not put Rodriguez on its provisional roster, but team officials quickly added him.</p>
        <p>''What we're going to do is save a roster spot for him,'' Bob Watson, the general manager of the United States team, said before Rodriguez agreed to play. ''He can't make up his mind.''</p>
        <p>After Rodriguez's decision became official, Watson was hesitant to get too excited about the addition.</p>
        <p>''If he decides he's going to play, I'd love to have him,'' Watson said. ''Every 10 minutes, something else comes out. When we toe it up in March, if he wants to play, he'll be on our squad.''</p>
        <p>When Rodriguez initially said he was sitting out the event, Orza alerted Buck Martinez, the United States manager. Martinez said that he was disappointed about Rodriguez, but that the United States had other options at third.</p>
        <p>''We'll play someone at third,'' Martinez said at the time. ''It won't be Alex Rodriguez, but it'll still be a very good player.''</p>
        <p>Martinez said that third baseman Eric Chavez of the Oakland Athletics was among 10 players being added to the roster last night, increasing the total to 52 players.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
