<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>American Airlines Refusing To Take Routes Temporarily</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="492081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARGENTINA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN AIRLINES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORTATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALPUKAS, AGIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DA1030F934A35751C1A967958260" item-length="338" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>American Airlines Refusing To Take Routes Temporarily</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SALPUKAS, AGIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American Airlines refused yesterday to add flights on routes to Brazil and Argentina in an effort to win permanent rights to do so.</p>
        <p>American has said the Department of Transportation should award the additional flights permanently because of the high cost of adding service for what might be only a short time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American Airlines refused yesterday to add flights on routes to Brazil and Argentina in an effort to win permanent rights to do so.</p>
        <p>American has said the Department of Transportation should award the additional flights permanently because of the high cost of adding service for what might be only a short time.</p>
        <p>"We cannot economically reallocate assets and people to serve these routes for only a very brief period because we are already heavily booked throughout the holiday period," said P. Jackson Bell, a senior vice president at American. "We can justify the loss of revenue, disruption to our system and our customers, and the added cost of major, unplanned service change only if were granted the authority to continue operations on a long-term basis."</p>
        <p>American, which could quickly add more flights to help passengers stranded by the demise of Pan American World Airways, is trying to wrest concessions from the Department of Transportation.</p>
        <p>The department is eager to help stranded passengers but balked at American's demand.</p>
        <p>The department also awarded United Airlines the right to fly to Brazil and Argentina. Unlike American, which already has a vast route network in Latin America, United is a newcomer and will not be able to begin service until Jan. 15.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey N. Shane, an Assistant Secretary of Transportation, said the awards had been made in such a way "as to secure replacement service quickly and as close to the service pattern operated as possible to insure the least disruption possible to the traveling public."</p>
        <p>Mr. Shane gave authority for American to operate 21 additional weekly flights to Brazil until Jan. 15, when United would begin its service. American's extra flights would then be cut to seven temporary flights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shane made a similar determination for Argentina. American was given seven more weekly fights until Jan. 15, when United Airlines would begin its service. On the New York to Mexico routes the department chose Delta Air Lines to serve the route daily.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
