<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Carrying Sticks and Hugging Trees</title>
    <meta content="09BROOKHT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/09/books/review/09BROOKHT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1349549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brookhiser, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Edmund</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roosevelt, Theodore (1858-1919)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Theodore Rex (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Roosevelt, Theodore</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Morris, Edmund</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEEDA143DF93AA35751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Carrying Sticks and Hugging Trees</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Edmund Morris's 'Theodore Rex': Carrying Sticks and Hugging Trees</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Brookhiser</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brookhiser, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Brookhiser reviews book Theodore Rex by Edmund Morris; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEODORE REX</p>
        <p>By Edmund Morris.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 772 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the second installment of his megabiography of Theodore Roosevelt, Edmund Morris writes with a breezy verve that perfectly suits his subject.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEODORE REX</p>
        <p>By Edmund Morris.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 772 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $35.</p>
        <p>Among the many things that Sept. 11 will change is our view of the past. Even as the New York Stock Exchange and the Nasdaq have been jolted, so has the market in the reputations of dead presidents. It seems safe to say that the John Adams boom, so carefully nurtured by David McCullough and Joseph J. Ellis, is over. The lovable and passionate crank who couldn't administer a bridge game is simply not the man for this hour. The great Virginians of the first Republican Party -- Thomas Jefferson and James Madison -- so sublime in their principles, so incompetent in their diplomacy and warmaking, will also be trading at a discount.</p>
        <p>Who looks more interesting? All the general-presidents, from Washington to Eisenhower; Franklin D. Roosevelt, who was president during the original day of infamy; and Franklin's brave and bumptious older cousin Theodore. Two books that were planned to appear after the centennial of Theodore Roosevelt's first inauguration, in September 1901, acquire a grave relevance.</p>
        <p>''Theodore Roosevelt'' (Times Books/ Holt, $20, to be published next month), Louis Auchincloss's contribution to the American Presidents series, surveys Roosevelt's not-long life -- he died at the age of 60 -- in under 200 pages. Better, however, to take a deep breath and dive into ''Theodore Rex,'' Edmund Morris's sequel to his 1979 masterpiece, ''The Rise of Theodore Roosevelt.'' Morris's new book begins at the moment when an assassin's bullet elevates Vice President Roosevelt to the White House and ends, seven and a half years later, when he leaves office. Another volume will be needed to cover his last, eventful decade, which included a failed attempt to regain the presidency and World War I. In the fashion of modern megabiography, Morris devotes several hundred pages to a relatively brief period of time. But unlike many of his peers, he writes with a breezy verve that makes the pages fly, and that perfectly suits his subject.</p>
        <p>Roosevelt was six weeks shy of his 43rd birthday when he became president, following the death of William McKinley, thus making him the youngest man ever to occupy the White House (John F. Kennedy, who was 43 years and 5 months old on Election Day in 1960, was the youngest man ever to be elected). The air of youth clung to him throughout his administration. Morris quotes the famous judgment of the British diplomat Cecil Spring Rice: ''You must always remember that the president is about 6.'' Equally telling is the 1904 birthday greeting to Roosevelt from Secretary of War Elihu Root: ''You have made a very good start in life and your friends have great hopes for you when you grow up.''</p>
        <p>Roosevelt had a boy's egotism and brutality; the ''bully pulpit'' (his phrase) was often the bully's pulpit. But he was also curious, eager, outgoing, energetic. ''Isn't it a fine thing to be alive when so many great things are happening?'' one lunch guest recorded him saying. Add to the mix his nimble intelligence -- one breathless interlocutor called him ''a perfect flying squirrel'' in conversation -- and it is no mystery that so many people found him so winning. He was like Rudy Giuliani with charm, Bill Clinton with principles.</p>
        <p>Roosevelt made his most constructive contribution in the realm of foreign policy. Together with McKinley, he ushered America into the ranks of the world's great powers. As McKinley's assistant secretary of the Navy, he had pushed for a program of shipbuilding, which he continued as president. At the end of his administration, he sent the expanded Navy, painted white, on a cruise around the world. To facilitate the Navy's movements between oceans, he encouraged a revolution in the Colombian province of Panama. Morris's chapter on the Panamanian adventure skillfully uses a favorite device of his -- short, intercut minisections -- to suggest the fog of ignorance and chance in which high-stakes power plays of this kind always occur. After Roosevelt had won, Philander Knox, his attorney general, told him that ''it would be better to keep your action free from any taint of legality.'' Many Americans condemned Roosevelt's assertions of national strength. But he understood that there had never been a moment of Arcadian apartness in our history. America had been an imperial venture from colonial times. He wished to continue the process in the modern world, and he hoped it would work to the nation's, and the world's, benefit.</p>
        <p>But Roosevelt's foreign policy showed finesse as well as muscle. In 1904 a Greek-American named Ioannis Perdicaris was kidnapped from his Moroccan villa by Ahmed el-Raisuli, a bandit chief, and held for ransom. A phrase from a telegram drafted by Secretary of State John Hay -- Perdicaris alive or Raisuli dead'' -- electrified the Republican convention that was nominating Roosevelt for president. What has dropped from our collective memory of that threat is that it was addressed not to Raisuli but to the sultan of Morocco, whom Roosevelt was urging to treat with the kidnapper (Perdicaris walked as soon as the sultan met Raisuli's terms). Roosevelt could cut deals as well as hurl thunderbolts.</p>
        <p>Sometimes he acted silently. In 1902 he warned Germany against forcibly collecting debts owed it by Venezuela, and he backed up his warning with a naval exercise off Puerto Rico. He conveyed his message discreetly, however, so that Germany would lose no face by backing down. So discreet was he that many historians have doubted that Roosevelt brought any pressure to bear. Morris argues that he did (here, as elsewhere, his footnotes are worth reading). Roosevelt adopted and popularized a West African proverb, ''Speak softly and carry a big stick.'' Cartoonists naturally focused on the stick, but soft speaking was an equally important tool. ''We are too big a people,'' Roosevelt wrote, ''to be able to be careless in what we say.''</p>
        <p>When it comes to Roosevelt's domestic policy, Morris has to try to make sense of that vague and earnest force, the Progressive movement. Roosevelt's most original contribution to its agenda was to push for conservation of natural resources. He offered the arguments of good stewardship, but his was the sensibility of a hunter and an outdoorsman who had seen firsthand two decades' toll on the American West. His record on race was mixed, which makes it better than that of the gross racist Woodrow Wilson. In 1903 a black man accused of rape and murder was seized from prison and burned alive -- not in the Deep South, but in Wilmington, Del. Roosevelt condemned the outrage: ''There are certain hideous sights which when once seen can never be wholly erased from the mental retina. The mere fact of having seen them implies degradation.'' Still, in his second term, he let the soldiers of a black Army unit be railroaded on trumped-up charges of rioting in Brownsville, Tex., and he nearly got into a shouting match at a Gridiron dinner with a Republican senator who vainly tried to defend them.</p>
        <p>Roosevelt made the most noise, however, by picking a fight with the nouveau riche industrialists. Roosevelt himself was a brownstone Knickerbocker, whose caste marks included Groton, Harvard and the Porcellian club. He turned against his class, Morris suggests, in part because he found rich men boring. ''You expect a man of millions,'' Roosevelt said, ''to be a man worth hearing; but as a rule they don't know anything outside their own businesses.'' But his chief motive in taking on the great début de siècle industrial combinations was a growing conviction that they were taking unfair advantage of their competitors and customers. ''I am not deeply interested in'' economic issues, he admitted as his administration wound down; ''my problems are moral problems, and my teaching has been plain morality.'' Roosevelt's friend Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes Jr. warned that ''no part of the conduct of life'' would be safe from government interference on such vague principles. But Roosevelt and his fellow Progressives were off to the races.</p>
        <p>Roosevelt's perfervid self-confidence would bear fruit in 1912, outside the scope of ''Theodore Rex,'' when the ex-president split the Republican Party and ran on the Bull Moose ticket. The aftershocks of that campaign would include the New Deal -- for if Wilson established all the administrative precedents for Franklin Roosevelt, cousin Theodore anticipated the moral fervor. Morris is not as enamored of flags, war and big government as Roosevelt was, but he too feels the tug. A combination of diffidence and enthusiasm allows him to write of our past -- which looks like our future -- with energy and clarity.</p>
        <p>Richard Brookhiser is the author of the forthcoming ''America's First Dynasty: The Adamses, 1735-1918.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Richard Brookhiser is the author of the forthcoming ''America's First Dynasty: The Adamses, 1735-1918.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
