<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Steel Curtain Is Rising To Challenge the Jets' Offense</title>
    <meta content="09JETS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/09/sports/football/09JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1350029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh Steelers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Pittsburgh Steelers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Pittsburgh Steelers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Testaverde, Vinny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E7DF1F3CF93AA35751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1309" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Steel Curtain Is Rising To Challenge the Jets' Offense</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Steel Curtain Rising for Jets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets prepare for game against Pittsburgh Steelers; with playoff berths up for grabs, game is important for both teams; photo; chart shows team stats (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pressure came in waves for Vinny Testaverde last week, the questions about his moribund offense and the Jets' play-calling and his own inability to make a critical fourth-down pass last Sunday buffeting him like so many sacks. He bobbed and weaved and escaped, a game smile on his face, a 7-4 record his greatest defense, explaining that in his 15-year career he has learned how to deal with adversity and that sometimes it takes a few weeks to recover.</p>
        <p>Testaverde will have only a few seconds to recover from each barrage today. The Pittsburgh Steelers (9-2) have the best defense in the National Football League, a scheme that emphasizes the blitz, and the best record in the American Football Conference. The Jets (7-4) have an offense that struggled to score against the worst defense in the league, the Carolina Panthers'; an offense that has scored just six touchdowns in the last five games and a desperate need to win this game to keep alive their chances for a division title.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Steelers, like Pittsburgh's teams of the mid-1970's, have a smothering defense that is the best in the N.F.L. and will put the Jet's struggling offense to the test on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The pressure came in waves for Vinny Testaverde last week, the questions about his moribund offense and the Jets' play-calling and his own inability to make a critical fourth-down pass last Sunday buffeting him like so many sacks. He bobbed and weaved and escaped, a game smile on his face, a 7-4 record his greatest defense, explaining that in his 15-year career he has learned how to deal with adversity and that sometimes it takes a few weeks to recover.</p>
        <p>Testaverde will have only a few seconds to recover from each barrage today. The Pittsburgh Steelers (9-2) have the best defense in the National Football League, a scheme that emphasizes the blitz, and the best record in the American Football Conference. The Jets (7-4) have an offense that struggled to score against the worst defense in the league, the Carolina Panthers'; an offense that has scored just six touchdowns in the last five games and a desperate need to win this game to keep alive their chances for a division title.</p>
        <p>It is a matchup straight from Jack Lambert's dreams.</p>
        <p>''Can we score against them?'' Jets right tackle Ryan Young said. ''We'd like to think we can.''</p>
        <p>The Jets have faced physical defenses before -- they won the muscle match against New Orleans earlier this season -- but they face this one at a particularly pivotal moment. With nine victories, the Steelers know they need only win one more game to assure a playoff spot. The Jets, though, probably need to win at least three of their final five to make the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Earlier last week, Testaverde said it would be tough to score on the Steelers even with a great offense, which the Jets most certainly do not have right now. The offense has come to rely on the turnovers the defense has produced this season to give them repeated tries at the end zone and the occasional bonus touchdown.</p>
        <p>The Steelers will be the floundering offense's greatest test. They play a 3-4 defense that blitzes on nearly every play from all directions and then plays a zone defense behind it. The result: the Steelers, like Pittsburgh's teams of the mid-1970's, have a smothering defense.</p>
        <p>They lead the league in total defense, allowing only 258 yards a game; rushing defense, allowing 72 yards; sacks with 41, 3.7 a game; and fewest points allowed, a remarkable 12.5 a game. In eight games, their opponents did not get 75 yards rushing, including last week when Minnesota had 45. Their outside linebackers have 15 sacks and the rookie linebacker Kendrell Bell has 7.</p>
        <p>Coach Bill Cowher has stuck with his scheme for his 10 years at Pittsburgh, restocking through the years with effective drafting.</p>
        <p>''We like to think we're a tough football team,'' Cowher said. ''We're built around running the ball and stopping the run. It's a blue-collar approach that I think is reflective of this city and of the people of this city. They can relate to the hard work, the grind-it-out fashion. You have to win football games to have people embrace that. We've been fortunate this year to win some close games.''</p>
        <p>The Steelers are so effective with their blitz because it comes from so many different directions and usually with five men at a time. At times, the Steelers may bring blitzers through the gaps on either side of the center. Other times, they might try to bring one up the middle and another around the outside. Sometimes both come from outside. They come from right and left, both on the right, both on the left.</p>
        <p>They may also blitz from the linebackers -- a group that Cowher said is probably as good as he has had in his 10 years there -- or the secondary. The focus of the Jets will be to alleviate pressure up the middle so that Testaverde can step up. But if the Steelers are able to blitz up the gaps on either side of the center and between the guards and tackles, they can take away the running game.</p>
        <p>But, as center Kevin Mawae said last week, teams that live by the blitz, die by it. They inevitably give up protection somewhere to blitz.  Tennessee lost to the Steelers by 34-24 two weeks ago, but hit a 68-yard touchdown pass play on their first play from scrimmage against the blitz. Minnesota, in a 21-16 loss last week, hit pass plays of 80 and 74 yards. In those games, the Steelers yielded 324 yards passing and 340 yards passing. The Titans' and Vikings' secret: shorter drops to thwart the blitz.</p>
        <p>The question remains whether the Jets can hit those big plays, considering they have not done it much this season. Testaverde's longest pass was 39 yards to Laveranues Coles for a touchdown against Miami on Oct. 14, and the passing game is averaging only 152 yards a game (29th in the league), in large part because of a heavy reliance on Curtis Martin, the league's leading rusher. ''Anytime you have opportunities to hit big plays, you want to hit it because it allows you to gain confidence,'' Testaverde said. ''But there are very few of those opportunities. They're physical and they can rattle an offense.</p>
        <p>''It's tough to get a big play on them. When you talk about your conventional blitzing team, they give up some coverage to get to the quarterback and you're able to make some big plays. But it's not that way with the Steelers. They bring five guys, sometimes six, but they're playing zone behind it.''</p>
        <p>Much of the onus for the Jets will be on the offensive line, which will be charged with picking up and warding off the blitz. The line, which had been having a superb season, suffered a bit last week against the Patriots. Randy Thomas, who was making his first start after missing three games, ''was on the ground a little bit,'' Jets Coach Herman Edwards said. He added that Thomas, with a bad ankle, is probably still not completely healthy. Mawae gave up a sack and a half to the rookie Richard Seymour.</p>
        <p>Some offensive players protested that the team got too conservative in the second half against New England, when the Jets went more to the run after a wide-open attack in the first half. But against the Pittsburgh defense, the Jets  will be even more adamant in using Martin to minimize errors even though they expect that he will be thrown for negative yards on some runs.</p>
        <p>''People get frustrated early,'' Edwards said. ''They don't continue to run. A lot in football happens when you perceive yourself to be a running team, à la maybe the Jets. You don't give up when you get a negative play. You don't get nervous and say we can't run the ball. When you start giving up, you fall into the trap.''</p>
        <p>''If they hit us on some negative runs, which they will because they'll blitz us, we can't abandon what we're doing and say 'Uh, it's over.' You have an opportunity to make possible plays if you know what they're doing. You don't go into a game saying we can't do this, we can't do that.''</p>
        <p>Testaverde agreed.</p>
        <p>''We have to continue to keep to our game plan,'' he said, ''no matter what happens during the game.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
