<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cox Empire Seeks Growth (on Its Own Terms)</title>
    <meta content="14COXX$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/14/business/yourmoney/14COXX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1384041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cox Enterprises Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabrikant, Geraldine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cox Communications Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3DC153CF937A25757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="2835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cox Empire Seeks Growth (on Its Own Terms)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cox Empire Seeks Growth (on Its Own Terms)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabrikant, Geraldine</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Focus on growth challenges facing Cox Enterprises Inc, one of nation's largest private media companies which reported $8.7 billion in revenue in 2001; photos; charts (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME years ago, James Cox Kennedy, the chairman of Cox Enterprises, was flying to Hawaii with his mother and some friends. Unhappy that she was smoking, Mr. Kennedy admonished her to stop. When she paid no heed, he tried leverage. ''It's a company plane,'' he warned.</p>
        <p>''It's my company,'' Barbara Cox Anthony, now 79, shot back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cox Enterprises, which has been run by family members since its founding in 1898, may be finding it harder to retain its iron-grip control  if, that is, it wants to grow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME years ago, James Cox Kennedy, the chairman of Cox Enterprises, was flying to Hawaii with his mother and some friends. Unhappy that she was smoking, Mr. Kennedy admonished her to stop. When she paid no heed, he tried leverage. ''It's a company plane,'' he warned.</p>
        <p>''It's my company,'' Barbara Cox Anthony, now 79, shot back.</p>
        <p>True enough. Cox Enterprises, which had $8.7 billion in revenue last year, drawn from newspapers, cable, television, radio and an auto auction business, is controlled by trusts set up for Mrs. Anthony and her 82-year-old sister, Anne Cox Chambers. It ranks as one of the nation's largest private media companies, along with Advance Publications, Hearst and Hallmark. The two Cox sisters are each worth $11.3 billion, according to Forbes, and are tied for 11th in the magazine's ranking of the richest Americans.</p>
        <p>But these days, Cox Enterprises, which has been run by family members since its founding in 1898 by James Middleton Cox, who would become the governor of Ohio and a presidential candidate, may be finding it harder to retain its iron-grip control -- if, that is, it wants to grow.</p>
        <p>All around it, media companies are acquiring one another, expanding their portfolios of media properties and otherwise combining forces. In the wake of a recent Federal Communications Commission ruling that allows companies to own both television stations and cable systems in the same market, further consolidation is inevitable.</p>
        <p>Cox, led by Mr. Kennedy since 1988, has already tried to do a deal, but had it go sour. Last December, Cox Communications, a subsidiary that is 65.5 percent owned by the family and 34.5 percent public, lost a bid for AT&amp;T Broadband, the cable business of AT&amp;T, to the Comcast Corporation.</p>
        <p>Although Cox has never disclosed the exact terms of its offer, the company initially appeared willing to reduce its equity stake in the combination to 35 percent.</p>
        <p>''I was surprised that they were willing to become minority shareholders in a larger company,'' recalled Karim Zia, an analyst at Deutsche Bank. ''The family has always been reluctant to give up control.''</p>
        <p>But Cox was not changing its stripes, according to a Wall Street executive familiar with the bid. Cox's offer was said to be only slightly lower than Comcast's, but it sought control of the merged company's board. ''They had no intention of remaining passive investors,'' this person said. ''That is in part why they lost.''</p>
        <p>Comcast's $47 billion winning bid gave it 33 percent of the new company.</p>
        <p>In March, there were rumors that Cox might try to merge its cable operations with those of AOL Time Warner, a deal that would have reduced the gap between AOL, No. 2 in the industry, and AT&amp;T, the leader. The talk proved false.</p>
        <p>But it is only a matter of time, many analysts believe, before Cox makes another attempt at buying growth -- and bulk.</p>
        <p>Under James Cox Kennedy, the company's revenue has increased 14 percent annually, on average, over 10 years. Though Mr. Kennedy keeps a low profile, he is well regarded by investors for bringing in strong managers and giving them free rein.</p>
        <p>During a lengthy interview at his offices at Cox's headquarters here, Mr. Kennedy, 54, dressed in khakis, a sports shirt and a pullover, said the company was indeed eager to expand its cable operations. ''We want to get bigger,'' he said. ''Size would reduce our costs for programming and equipment. With those savings, the growth will be faster.'' But company officials say they feel no pressure to make acquisitions.</p>
        <p>MR. KENNEDY is keenly aware that as other cable operators consolidate, economies of scale will reduce their costs and increase their profit margins, and Cox -- No. 5 in terms of subscribers -- has not been able to move up.</p>
        <p>But a large-scale acquisition would require Cox to issue stock, which could dilute the family's holdings, or take on more debt, which could hurt its credit rating.</p>
        <p>For 2001, Cox Communications -- the cable business -- had cash flow of $1.6 billion, and analysts say its debt-to-cash-flow ratio is about 4. That's not highly leveraged for a cable company; still, a large acquisition would likely saddle Cox with enough debt to reduce its debt rating from triple-B, the lowest investment grade.</p>
        <p>Last year, as the economy weakened and Cox's newspapers and TV and radio stations were hurt by the drop in advertising spending, Cox Enterprises, the private parent company, sold 13.5 million shares of Cox Communications, or 2.3 percent of it, raising $500 million to pay down debt.</p>
        <p>Several people close to the company say Mr. Kennedy is weighing a move to combine either all or some of the public and private businesses if Cox Communications or its parent decide to pursue more acquisitions.</p>
        <p>But a deal may not be in cable. ''We would not rule out doing something with TV, but it is not something we are likely to do either,'' Mr. Kennedy said. ''We will do what makes the most sense. When the next growth opportunity comes along to take a big bite, we have all those different options.''</p>
        <p>While the cable industry is under a cloud because of its heavy debt and because few cable operators generate profits, Richard A. Bilotti, a media analyst at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, bets that Cox's future growth is likely to be in cable because it is the company's core business and because management likes it.</p>
        <p>But the family remains determined to hold on to its diversified media conglomerate, which has always been run by a family member. From its origins as a newspaper company, Cox Enterprises has expanded and owns 17 daily newspapers, including The Atlanta Journal-Constitution, 30 weeklies, 15 TV stations and a car auction business, Manheim Auctions. It has an interest in professional women's soccer.</p>
        <p>In 1996, after the radio industry was deregulated, Cox Enterprises spun off 28 percent of its radio business to the public as Cox Radio, expressly to use its stock to buy radio stations. That division owns, operates or provides marketing services for 81 stations. It has a market capitalization of $2.97 billion and had $395.3 million in revenue last year.</p>
        <p>But the most visible and fastest-growing entity is Cox Communications, of which at least 25 percent has been publicly held since 1995, when Mr. Kennedy spun it off to ease the purchase of Times Mirror's cable systems. Today the unit, which had 2001 pro forma revenue of $4.06 billion, up 14 percent from 2000, has a market capitalization of $21.02 billion and 6.2 million subscribers. Its stock closed on Friday at $34.99, well below the peak of $58.375 reached during trading on Jan. 24, 2000.</p>
        <p>''Cox has generally had the highest multiple of the cable operators because of its early entry into telephony and high-speed Internet access,'' said Dennis H. Leibowitz, who manages Act II, a hedge fund specializing in media companies. ''And Wall Street has always had high regard for its management.''</p>
        <p>But as deals become bigger, Mr. Kennedy may want to combine some of Cox Enterprises' private assets with its public assets, to strengthen the cable company and give it more firepower for deals.</p>
        <p>MR. KENNEDY can ponder his options, but he must also consult his mother and his aunt.</p>
        <p>The two women, who between them have five children and six grandchildren, have strikingly different lifestyles. They are not particularly close. There has never been a reunion of the entire clan.</p>
        <p>Yet the sisters are of a single mind about Cox's future. Both are extremely private and rarely give interviews, but in a recent telephone conversation from her home in Hawaii, Mrs. Anthony said, ''We have always tried to keep as much of the company private as we could, and we will do that as long as we can.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Chambers concurs. ''We really prefer to keep it a private company,'' she said in a telephone interview. ''I think like most sisters we were very different. We are close the way siblings are: loving one another and hating one another. But even though we are very different, she and I have always had the same goals and pride in the company. We have never disagreed about how and where the company should go.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Chambers is the more cosmopolitan of the pair. She has an elegant Regency-style home in Atlanta, a duplex apartment in Manhattan and a home in Provence in southern France. She was a major fund-raiser for former President Jimmy Carter.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Anthony maintains that she is far more interested in the business of Cox Enterprises than is her older sister. She lives in Honolulu but also spends time at her two ranches in Australia. She is an accomplished horsewoman and breeds cattle, but wherever she is, she talks to her son ''about four times a week,'' she said -- ''mostly about business.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Anthony recalls a close relationship with her father that fostered her interest in business, which for the family's empire began with the purchase of a newspaper in Dayton, Ohio, still owned by Cox and now called The Dayton Daily News.</p>
        <p>''One time in Dayton, I overheard a whole conversation and it was about buying The Atlanta Journal,'' she recalled. ''I told the wife of someone who worked for us and she told my father and he gave me hell.''</p>
        <p>But she did not push her only son (or her daughter, Blair, who lives in Australia) toward business.</p>
        <p>During his childhood in Honolulu, ''Jimmy worked at a surplus store and then in construction,'' Mrs. Anthony recalled. ''After college, he raced motorcycles for a while.'' He did not show much interest in Cox. ''I told him: 'You should go to the company for a year, just to learn it. You should because you own it.' ''</p>
        <p>So, in 1972, after graduating from the University of Denver, James Cox Kennedy, then 24, joined the family business, starting in production at the Atlanta papers. By 1979, he became president of the Grand Junction Newspapers division of Cox in Colorado and was soon publisher of The Grand Junction Daily Sentinel. In 1985, he transferred back to Atlanta as vice president of Cox Newspapers. Three years later, after moving to Cox Enterprises as executive vice president, he was named chairman and chief executive.</p>
        <p>In his early days at Cox, he was the object of quiet ridicule from employees who thought that he was more interested in trapping pigeons on the Cox building's roof than in working. He said he trapped pigeons once.</p>
        <p>Over time, he has won the respect of the family and public shareholders, although he acknowledges that in the beginning, he was ''absolutely terrified'' that he would not succeed. He began to feel some confidence that he could master the corporate world in 1990, when, under his leadership, Cox's car auction business beat back competition from a start-up, General Electric Capital Auto Retail Services, owned by GE Capital and Ford Motor Credit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy is particularly proud of his bet on cable. When he took over, some advisers thought that Cox should sell its cable systems and cash in, but he thought differently. ''I felt close to cable,'' he said. ''I believed in it.'' He also decided to make a heavy bet on telephone services.</p>
        <p>Cox Communications has offered phone service since 1997, and 14 percent of its cable subscribers have signed up. ''Cox has enjoyed solid, impressive low-double-digit cable cash flow growth,'' said Jessica Reif Cohen, a media analyst at Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>The reputation of the company's flagship newspaper, The Atlanta Journal-Constitution, has receded somewhat in recent years, though it remains the voice of its region. During the 1950's and 1960's, Ralph McGill and Eugene Patterson won Pulitzer Prizes as editors at what was then The Atlanta Constitution and were leading white voices of moderation in race relations. Then its stature declined.</p>
        <p>In 1986, Garner Anthony tried to bring it back. Mr. Anthony, then chief executive of Cox, and Charles Glover, who headed the newspaper division, hired Bill Kovach, a former Washington editor for The New York Times, ''to create the world's next great newspaper,'' Mr. Kovach recalled in a phone interview.</p>
        <p>Two years later, ''they cut the budget, killed the Sunday magazine and cut the newsroom staff,'' said Mr. Kovach, who resigned. He is now chairman of the Committee of Concerned Journalists, which is financed by the Pew Charitable Trusts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy said Mr. Kovach ''was editing for outside constituencies.''</p>
        <p>''I only care how the papers are viewed in Atlanta,'' he added. ''I am proud of the paper. I don't care what people in New York or Chicago think about it.'' Mr. Kovach said his Pulitzer entries in his last year were for local coverage.</p>
        <p>TODAY, other businesses within Cox dwarf the newspaper holdings. Indeed, the privately held auto auction business, with $2.26 billion in revenue last year, is the company's second-largest operation, after cable. Its revenue is nearly twice as high as the $1.35 billion of the newspaper unit. Cox Television posted $617 million in sales, while the radio unit had $395 million.</p>
        <p>Within Cox, in fact, it is widely accepted that should anything happen to Mr. Kennedy, ''either Dennis or Jim Robbins would take over,'' Mrs. Chambers said, referring to Dennis Berry, the president and chief operating officer of Cox Enterprises, and James O. Robbins, the chairman of Cox Communications. Mr. Berry, who has run the newspaper division, received the nod to leadership at Cox in part because he had helped the auto business more than triple its revenue over six years.</p>
        <p>Beyond those succession plans, there are family members who may one day take over.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Chambers' grandson, Alex Taylor, who is 27, is a reporter at The Austin American-Statesman, a Cox paper in Texas. ''I am very pleased that he wanted to go into the business,'' she said. Mr. Kennedy, who has two sons, James and Clay, and a daughter, Barbara, hopes family members will join the company.</p>
        <p>During the interview, he pointed to a small papier-mâché statue of a man carrying a briefcase on his bookshelf. Beside it is a framed letter written by one of his sons, then 10, in 1992. ''When I grow up, I want to do what my Dad does,'' it says. ''He is the boss of a company. I look up to my Dad. I want to be like him.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
