<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public &amp; Private; Wanted: A Definition</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="679345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABORTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUINDLEN, ANNA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PATAKI, GEORGE E (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DF153EF93AA35757C0A962958260" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public &amp; Private; Wanted: A Definition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA QUINDLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">QUINDLEN, ANNA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State Senator George Pataki says he is pro-choice. Abortion rights activists say he's not. The dispute is important. Mr. Pataki is running for governor of New York, a state that has one of the pre-eminent histories of abortion rights in America. And he is doing so as the reproductive rights battlefield shifts from the U.S. Supreme Court to the Statehouse.</p>
        <p>Even the Right to Life Committee in his home county notes that though he "claims to be pro-choice," the Senator actually has "a pro-life voting record." Senator Pataki opposed Medicaid funding and a clinic-access bill and supports parental notification. He has earned a perfect 100 percent on the legislative scorecard of the conservative Christian Coalition and the enmity of groups like New York State NARAL, NOW, Planned Parenthood and the Westchester Coalition for Legal Abortion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State Senator George Pataki says he is pro-choice. Abortion rights activists say he's not. The dispute is important. Mr. Pataki is running for governor of New York, a state that has one of the pre-eminent histories of abortion rights in America. And he is doing so as the reproductive rights battlefield shifts from the U.S. Supreme Court to the Statehouse.</p>
        <p>Even the Right to Life Committee in his home county notes that though he "claims to be pro-choice," the Senator actually has "a pro-life voting record." Senator Pataki opposed Medicaid funding and a clinic-access bill and supports parental notification. He has earned a perfect 100 percent on the legislative scorecard of the conservative Christian Coalition and the enmity of groups like New York State NARAL, NOW, Planned Parenthood and the Westchester Coalition for Legal Abortion.</p>
        <p>The announcement this week by the venerable Harry Blackmun that he would step down as a Justice of the Supreme Court led inevitably to a look back at the changing judicial philosophy of this Nixon appointee, who was expected when nominated to be something between a conservative and a moderate. Exhibit A was the opinion that Justice Blackmun wrote in the nation's best-known Supreme Court decision, Roe v. Wade.</p>
        <p>But Justice Blackmun himself likes to remind people that that opinion was 7 to 2, a convincing majority. And we should remind ourselves that it came early on in his tenure on the high court, and that it seems unlikely he had shifted radically in his view of the Constitution.</p>
        <p>The truth is, the notion that the individual is tacitly guaranteed privacy in intimate matters is not in the least a radical reading of the Constitution. The right, as Justice Brandeis wrote, "to be let alone" by government is more commonly the hallmark of the conservative than the liberal.</p>
        <p>It would be soothing, as Justice Blackmun steps down, to believe that that recognition accounts for the marked shift in the attitude within the Republican Party toward abortion rights. But it would be naive, too.  Republicans have divined not that a harsh anti-abortion stand is dissonant with their philosophy, but that it will not win voters. When the subject of who would challenge Mario Cuomo was bruited about last year, it was agreed that a pro-choice candidate was a must.</p>
        <p>The Republican political consultant Jay Severin was quoted in the political newsletter PulseLine as saying Senator Pataki "is pro-choice enough to be pro-choice for our purpose." But Mr. Severin's definition of what pro-choice means is peculiar, to say the least. Describing abortion rights activists with the kind of language Madonna used on David Letterman's show -- "Lesbian Communists" is the closest I can come to a presentable characterization -- Mr. Severin added: "Anyone who's for a woman's right to have caps or get a nose job or get tits or have an abortion, it's all the same thing. It's elective surgery."</p>
        <p>With the essential right to an abortion apparently safe in the high court for some years to come, the debate moves to various restrictions by state legislatures -- waiting periods, parental notification and consent, clinic access measures, Medicaid funding. Gubernatorial races become increasingly important. And pro-choice as an all-purpose label is simply not enough. Not when even those who equate abortion with cosmetic surgery take refuge in the rubric.</p>
        <p>It would be interesting to know whether Senator Pataki studied the soaring birth rates in the poorest areas of Detroit after Medicaid funding was repealed in Michigan before he voted on the issue in New York. It would be interesting to know how many teen-agers he talked to about parental notification, or whether he has discussed with clinic staff the harassment and vandalism that have made clinic-access measures necessary. But his staff either could not or would not make him available for an interview.</p>
        <p>This week Senator Alfonse D'Amato announced that, if permissible, he would shift $400,000 from his own campaign chest to Mr. Pataki's. That makes Mr. Pataki a serious candidate, albeit one whose strings are showing big-time in what, for the Republicans, threatens to become a political puppet show. But Senator D'Amato's patronage can't insulate Mr. Pataki from questions about whether his commitment to legal abortion is a principle or a political ploy, questions that will become the bedrock of state races in the years to come.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
