<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Separating Out the Puff In Mutual Fund Reports</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Your Money Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="685672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="CAVEAT EMPTOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUTUAL FUNDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAHONEY, SARAH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EEDF1439F934A35756C0A962958260" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Separating Out the Puff In Mutual Fund Reports</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sarah Mahoney</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MAHONEY, SARAH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WEDGED in the mailbox this time of year between the Victoria's Secret and the Harry &amp; David catalogues are annual reports from mutual funds. Most often, investors toss the dense documents aside, preferring to linger over the latest lingerie or the new choices for the "Fruit of the Month."</p>
        <p>It makes sense, though, to give the annual report a closer look. Some fund managers let the numbers speak for themselves. Others produce lyrical, heart-warming documents that make you proud to have put your money in such good hands. And then there are the funds with wretched performance that fill their reports with euphemism in an attempt to put the best face on a bad year.</p>
        <p>The reader's task is to cut to the heart of the matter. If a fund did much worse than others with a similar investing style and objective, it may be time to sell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WEDGED in the mailbox this time of year between the Victoria's Secret and the Harry &amp; David catalogues are annual reports from mutual funds. Most often, investors toss the dense documents aside, preferring to linger over the latest lingerie or the new choices for the "Fruit of the Month."</p>
        <p>It makes sense, though, to give the annual report a closer look. Some fund managers let the numbers speak for themselves. Others produce lyrical, heart-warming documents that make you proud to have put your money in such good hands. And then there are the funds with wretched performance that fill their reports with euphemism in an attempt to put the best face on a bad year.</p>
        <p>The reader's task is to cut to the heart of the matter. If a fund did much worse than others with a similar investing style and objective, it may be time to sell.</p>
        <p>Consider the Monitrend Summation Fund, ranked by Morningstar Inc. as one of the worst performers in 1993. "As the market advanced, the Summation Fund underperformed the market because it employed hedging strategies to protect against steep declines," the annual report said, describing a defensive strategy. "With market valuations at stratospheric levels, the Summation Fund hedged downside risk in advance of an anticipated market downturn."</p>
        <p>The fund did act as a buffer when stock prices fell this year. Through April, it had a loss of 1.17 percent, smaller than average for stock funds.</p>
        <p>But the obligatory graph in its pages is worth a thousand words: A $10,000 investment in the Summation Fund on Feb. 3, 1988, would have been worth $9,611 at the end of its fiscal year in November; the same investment in the S.&amp; P. 100, $19,937.</p>
        <p>Some other spins and techniques that funds use to disguise weakness:</p>
        <p>Confessing up front. The president of the Pasadena Growth Fund begins his letter to shareholders by describing the stellar performance he was able to report two years ago. "Today I have a more humbling assignment," he wrote. The fund's performance, relative to other growth funds, is "lackluster," he said. No fooling. The fund's value fell nearly 6 percent last year, while the average growth stock fund gained 11.6 percent.</p>
        <p>Sporting fun. Flag Investors Quality Growth Fund acknowledged some trying times in its report for the year ended Oct. 31, but opened with a light-hearted golf analogy. In a particularly confusing passage, it equates its performance with par golf, which is not mediocre but high-quality play. Its report for the quarter ended Jan. 31 trots out the tortoise and hare fable of steady progress winning the day. Still, it's not just the sprinters that have left this fund in the dust. It lost 5.61 percent during a year when mediocre performers had tidy gains.</p>
        <p>Blaming Mr. Market. Issued at the end of November, Jensen's six-month report introduces a villainous character called Mr. Market. The fund's strategy, it maintains, is absolutely correct. It's Mr. Market that has the attitude problem. But Mr. Market doesn't look so bad. The S.&amp; P. 500 gained 4.01 percent for the six months ended in November, while Jensen had a loss of 2.07 percent.</p>
        <p>Enduring optimism. "Even though the fund suffered short-term pain earlier in the year as the market prices of several great businesses we own fell to very low levels, we clearly now see the beginning of long-term gains," wrote Donald A. Yacktman in the Yacktman Fund's report. "With the wind now at our backs, we are looking forward to a very positive 1994."  CAVEAT EMPTOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
