<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mother and Boyfriend Held In Disappearance of Girl, 4</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="685610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILD ABUSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSING PERSONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">QUEENS (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERNANDEZ, RAYMOND</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ORTIZ, MARIA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORALES, RICHARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ORTIZ, RAYCHELLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E3D81739F934A35756C0A962958260" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mother and Boyfriend Held In Disappearance of Girl, 4</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERNANDEZ, RAYMOND</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The mother of a missing 4-year-old Queens girl and the mother's boyfriend were arrested yesterday, after the boyfriend told investigators that the mother killed the girl and that he disposed of the body, the police said.</p>
        <p>The two suspects, Richard Morales and Maria Ortiz, were charged with endangering the welfare of a minor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The mother of a missing 4-year-old Queens girl and the mother's boyfriend were arrested yesterday, after the boyfriend told investigators that the mother killed the girl and that he disposed of the body, the police said.</p>
        <p>The two suspects, Richard Morales and Maria Ortiz, were charged with endangering the welfare of a minor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morales was also charged with tampering with evidence because of his claim that he disposed of the girl's body by stuffing it into a laundry bag and tossing it into the East River from the Queensboro Bridge.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ortiz denied that she killed the girl, the police said, and investigators noted that Mr. Morales had provided several conflicting accounts of the girl's disappearance. The girl had not been found by late last night.</p>
        <p>Divers searched the East River near the Queensboro Bridge and several other waterfront locations in Brooklyn where Mr. Morales also claimed he had dumped the body.</p>
        <p>"We have searched various locations in order to substantiate his allegations," said Sgt. Tina Mohrmann, a police spokeswoman. A Search in Brooklyn</p>
        <p>The search for the girl, Raychelle Ortiz, began on Tuesday after Mr. Morales reported she had disappeared during an outing in Brooklyn that day. He told the police that the two of them went to Brooklyn, where he took some heroin and then took the girl window-shopping on Fulton Street. He said that he left her outside a pizza parlor while he went inside to buy a slice about 4:30 P.M. and that she was gone when he came out.</p>
        <p>"The boyfriend alleges that the mother killed the child and that he then disposed of the body," said Sergeant Mohrmann. "The mother denies this."</p>
        <p>Noting that there have been numerous inconsistencies in the accounts that Mr. Morales has provided to investigators so far, the sergeant added, "Maybe this is another one; maybe it isn't."</p>
        <p>The girl's mother was placed under arrest at Elmhurst Hospital Center, where she was admitted on Tuesday evening for a drug overdose. She had met Mr. Morales in a drug-treatment program, the police said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morales, who was being held at the 108th Precinct station house, told the police that Raychelle died after the mother became annoyed with the child and threw her, Sergeant Mohrmann said. She did not elaborate. Reports of Neglect</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the police said, people remembered seeing Mr. Morales at the pizza parlor but not a little girl.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ortiz has been reported to New York City's child-welfare authorities several times for neglect, according to court sources familiar with the family's case records. Last year, the mother regained custody of her children, who had been in foster care.</p>
        <p>Raychelle's three siblings, an 8-year-old sister and two brothers, ages 7 and 2, have been placed with Ms. Ortiz's sister, Juanita Echevarria. She and her husband have looked after the children before, police and court sources said. A History of Problems</p>
        <p>Although city child-welfare officials routinely refuse to comment on individual cases, citing confidentiality rules, sources indicate that the earliest report for child neglect was in 1986 and involved the oldest girl.</p>
        <p>Ms. Echevarria said earlier this week that the family has been racked for years by Ms. Ortiz's intravenous drug use, the succession of men she has lived with, and by neglect of the children.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Echevarria said her sister began using intravenous drugs as a teen-ager after meeting her first husband, who later died of AIDS. She said Ms. Ortiz was married again, to another drug user who also died of AIDS. She said Ms. Ortiz herself has the disease.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
