<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Race for Ohio Governor, All Sides Agree on a Need for Change</title>
    <meta content="21ohio" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/21/us/21ohio.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1755920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ohio</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Urbina, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strickland, Ted (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blackwell, J Kenneth (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Ohio</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Strickland, Ted</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Blackwell, J Kenneth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1D6143FF932A15757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Race for Ohio Governor, All Sides Agree on a Need for Change</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Race for Ohio Governor, All Sides Agree on a Need for Change</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN URBINA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Urbina, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>COLUMBUS, Ohio, April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ted Strickland, six-term Democratic congressman from Ohio, and J Kenneth Blackwell, Republican who serves as Ohio's secretary of state, are front-runners in primaries for governor; each presents himself as candidate for reform; all sides agree on need for change; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a state where the governor has been caught up in a corruption scandal and where the only thing leaving faster than manufacturing jobs is young people, candidates for governor are jockeying for the mantle of reform.</p>
        <p>''The zeitgeist is clear,'' said the likely Democratic nominee, Ted Strickland, a six-term congressman, before a packed room of donors the other day at a bar in downtown Columbus. ''People in this state want change. They're tired of scandal. They want to turn things around, and that's just what we are going to do.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>"The zeitgeist is clear," said the likely Democratic nominee, Ted Strickland. "People in this state want change." The Republican front-runner sounded a similar note.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a state where the governor has been caught up in a corruption scandal and where the only thing leaving faster than manufacturing jobs is young people, candidates for governor are jockeying for the mantle of reform.</p>
        <p>''The zeitgeist is clear,'' said the likely Democratic nominee, Ted Strickland, a six-term congressman, before a packed room of donors the other day at a bar in downtown Columbus. ''People in this state want change. They're tired of scandal. They want to turn things around, and that's just what we are going to do.''</p>
        <p>The next day, at a breakfast gathering of young professionals, the front-runner in the Republican primary, Secretary of State J. Kenneth Blackwell, sounded a similar note.</p>
        <p>''We rank 47 in job creation,'' he said. ''Venture capital has increased around the country by about 10 percent but dropped in Ohio by the same amount. We've fallen on real bad times, and I want to change that.''</p>
        <p>Ohio is widely viewed as a bellwether for the 2008 presidential contest. No Republican has ever won the presidency without carrying the state, and many Democrats say the first step to larger ambitions is to break the 16-year Republican hold on the governor's mansion. Primaries for governor will be held on May 2.</p>
        <p>Polls give Mr. Strickland a slight edge over either Mr. Blackwell or the other Republican candidate, State Attorney General Jim Petro. But pundits are keeping a particularly close eye on Mr. Blackwell, who, in an effort to unify fiscal and religious conservatives, is melding his strong opposition to abortion and same-sex marriage with an aggressive plan to control state spending. An African-American, he also hopes to win black votes that usually go to Democrats.</p>
        <p>For their part, the Democrats hope to cash in on growing frustration with Republican scandals in Columbus and Washington.</p>
        <p>''The governor's race is going to be the Democrats' first real test of their 'culture of corruption' argument, which they're using in races throughout the country,'' said John C. Green, director of the Ray C. Bliss Institute of Applied Politics at the University of Akron. ''It may not work everywhere, but if it's going to work anywhere, it's going to be Ohio.''</p>
        <p>Term limits forbid Gov. Bob Taft's re-election, though the chances he would have run otherwise are uncertain at best: Mr. Taft, son of a United States senator, grandson of another and great-grandson of President William Howard Taft, pleaded no contest in August to charges of failing to report thousands in gifts to him.</p>
        <p>The charges stemmed from an investigation of Mr. Taft's friend Thomas Noe, a coin dealer and prodigious Republican fund-raiser who in the past has contributed to both Mr. Blackwell and Mr. Petro. In February, Mr. Noe was charged with stealing at least $1 million from a coin investment that he managed for the Ohio Bureau of Workers' Compensation, and his trial, which promises to keep the scandal on voters' minds, is scheduled for August.</p>
        <p>''We've had an inept, incompetent, corrupt and sometimes criminal political leadership,'' Mr. Strickland said at the recent fund-raiser, ''and in '06, with your help, we will give Ohio back to the people of Ohio.''</p>
        <p>Another issue is demographics and the economy. State officials estimate that Ohio has lost more than 175,000 manufacturing jobs in the last 10 years and that an average of 65 people ages 25 to 39 leave the state every day. Mr. Strickland says he wants to make Ohio more competitive through investments in broadband networks, and has proposed using unspent federal welfare money for a $50-million-a-year expansion of state-financed preschool.</p>
        <p>The congressman, an ordained Methodist minister, also says his experience representing a conservative district makes him equipped to move Ohio into the blue column.</p>
        <p>His Democratic opponent, former State Representative Bryan E. Flannery, is trailing him by more than 40 points in the polls. But so far Mr. Strickland's biggest asset has been the acrimonious battle unfolding between the Republican candidates, whose war chests are nearly as full as his. [On April 20, the secretary of state's Web site said Mr. Strickland had raised $4.1 million since January of last year, Mr. Blackwell $3.8 million, Mr. Petro $3.4 million, and Mr. Flannery $146,000.]</p>
        <p>A former college football player, Mr. Blackwell is an imposing figure who seasons his speeches with references to his up-from-poverty past. (''And who would have imagined that the kid whose job it was to say 'peanuts here, get your fresh roasted peanuts' in front of the stadium would one day become a partial owner of the Cincinnati Reds?'')</p>
        <p>Mr. Blackwell leads Mr. Petro in the polls by about seven points and has been hammering him in speeches and television advertisements, saying that he has failed to offer a plan to control spending and that he only recently became an opponent of abortion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Petro, the state auditor for eight years before becoming attorney general, replied in an interview: ''Ken Blackwell's claims are just goofy. I've always been a reformer, and I've been the one promoting real cost-saving methods while his office was spending far in excess of any other in the state.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Petro has proposed eliminating 11,500 state employees through attrition and early retirement, a step he says would save about $1 billion a year. That money would be used, he says, to reduce in-state tuition at Ohio's public universities, which is about 50 percent higher than at public universities in neighboring states. He has also tried to win over evangelicals in recent weeks by running advertisements in which, holding a Bible, he talks about his faith.</p>
        <p>Further, he has won endorsements from the state's largest newspapers, mostly in reaction to a proposed constitutional amendment, offered by Mr. Blackwell, that would limit annual state and local spending increases to 3.5 percent or the sum of the rates of inflation and population growth, whichever was higher. Critics, including Senators Mike DeWine and George V. Voinovich of Ohio, both Republicans, say this would straitjacket state and local governments' ability to finance needed programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Petro has proposed an alternative amendment, which he says would not affect local governments, to limit state tax revenue to 5.5 percent of Ohioans' personal income.</p>
        <p>Whatever the endorsements, ''Blackwell has a formidable grass-roots and church backing,'' said Dr. Green, the Akron political scientist, who estimates that 25 percent of Ohio voters are Christian conservatives. ''The test will be whether he can get them all to the polls now, and again in November.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
