<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Meter Is Your Metier . . .</title>
    <meta content="23POET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: QUEENS UP CLOSE" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="910888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: QUEENS UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EEDA123EF930A15751C0A961958260" item-length="458" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Meter Is Your Metier . . .</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LeDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Queens County, NYC, announced last November that it was searching for its first poet laureate, to extol virtues of city's fastest-growing and most ethnically disparate borough; to date, only eight applications have been received; this may be because applicants are required to present published or unpublished poems inspired by Queens that they have already written; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fancy yourself a Bayside bard? Does a borough so diverse inspire its residents to verse?</p>
        <p>Apparently not many.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fancy yourself a Bayside bard? Does a borough so diverse inspire its residents to verse?</p>
        <p>Apparently not many.</p>
        <p>Last November, Queens County announced that it was searching for its first poet laureate, a modern-day Whitman to extol the virtues of the city's fastest-growing and most ethnically disparate borough. To date, only eight applications have been received, and the deadline is Saturday.</p>
        <p>The criteria include being a Queens resident for five years or at least having a strong connection to the borough. Applicants should have a significant publication record in English and must present published or unpublished poems inspired by Queens.</p>
        <p>That may be a reason for so few replies. There just isn't that much poetry written about Queens. ''Whenever people call me about the position they say, 'My God, I don't have a poem on Queens,' '' said David Cohen, administrative secretary of the Poet Laureate Project, sponsored by the Friends of the Queens College Library. ''I tell them, 'Well, write one.' ''</p>
        <p>Another problem is that there are not many big-name poets in Queens who can meet the requirements, said Dr. Marie-Lisa Gazaria, a professor of Spanish literature at St. John's University and one of the six judges who will select the poet laureate, to be named in June. ''The problem is that your poet laureate should have a name and should be published in periodicals,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The project was dreamed up by the Friends of the Queens College Library after Brooklyn named its first poet laureate five years ago.  The poet laureate will be expected to write about Queens, groom relations with literary groups and poets throughout Queens and promote activities encouraging the development of poetry and literacy in the borough.</p>
        <p>''People associate Queens with Archie Bunker,'' said Louis Gordon, 84, a retired book dealer who is on the board of the Friends of the Queens College Library and is a member of its poet laureate search committee. ''People don't know that many famous artists have lived and loved in Queens. We want to change that.'' Mr. Gordon cited Walt Whitman, who lived for a time in Astoria, and Jack Kerouac, who lived in South Ozone Park, as among Queens's literary notables.</p>
        <p>One nominee, Steven Stepanchev, professor emeritus of English at Queens College, gave a reading at the campus library last week. He spoke of stasis, and metaphor, and Queens.</p>
        <p>''Metaphor makes reality brilliant,'' he said, quoting Wallace Stevens. ''Queens is a brilliant place to live, and I would like to encourage the love of poetry here.''</p>
        <p>Applications are available at branch libraries in Queens or through Mr. Cohen at (718) 997-3626.</p>
        <p>CHARLIE LeDUFF</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: QUEENS UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
