<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cornwall in the Winter</title>
    <meta content="CORN.$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="910702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cornwall (England)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bodinnick-by-Fowey (Cornwall)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rougny, Paula Boyer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/Cornwall</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DC153FF930A15751C0A961958260" item-length="3132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cornwall in the Winter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAULA BOYER ROUGNY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rougny, Paula Boyer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paula Boyer Rougny article on three-month stay in winter at Penmariam Quay Cottage on Yeate Farm in Bodinnick-gy-Fowey, Cornwall; describes 14th-century converted stone barn, without central heat or telephone, and bracing walks to village in frequent rain and wind; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE were the only people who got off the train at Liskeard. As the conductor helped tumble duffel bags into the January rain, I sensed something odd: no people, no sounds. We were in the bottom of a narrow stone pit. ''Where's the station?'' I called through what proved to be a force 9 gale.</p>
        <p>''Up there!'' shouted the conductor, pointing to a shed. Then his voice was swept away into the Cornish elements.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE were the only people who got off the train at Liskeard. As the conductor helped tumble duffel bags into the January rain, I sensed something odd: no people, no sounds. We were in the bottom of a narrow stone pit. ''Where's the station?'' I called through what proved to be a force 9 gale.</p>
        <p>''Up there!'' shouted the conductor, pointing to a shed. Then his voice was swept away into the Cornish elements.</p>
        <p>My husband, Jean-Pierre, stood sentry as I leaned into a ramp that led 20 feet upward to a footbridge over the tracks. I crossed and climbed 20 more feet to pass under an opening into the shed. There, glistening wet on a rain-splattered floor, was a luggage cart.</p>
        <p>Thus began our three-month residency in England's remote west arm, which we had glimpsed four years earlier when, getting lost several times on a drive between Exeter and Penzance, we discovered the Arthurian appeal of off-season Cornwall. When retirement allowed us more time, we got the British Tourist Authority's free guide, Self-Catering Holiday Homes, and here we were -- in a shed in a gale.</p>
        <p>We had contracted for a 14th-century converted stone barn without central heat or telephone, and we planned to do without a car. The name of our destination was Penmarlam Quay Cottage on Yeate Farm (Yeate to rhyme with gate, which is what it means in Celtic) in Bodinnick-by-Fowey (bah-DIN-ick-by-FOY).</p>
        <p>Armed with the phone numbers of all three Liskeard (liss-KARD) taxi companies, I stepped into the gale at street level to use the red telephone booth. The third answered, cited a price for driving 16 miles with a stop for groceries, and arrived in a smart-looking Peugeot. Five minutes later we were hurrying through a superette like contest winners on a spree. Our winter home called for every provision, and the taxi would be our last fling at convenience.</p>
        <p>As we sped toward Bodinnick, flashes of slate-roofed bluestone houses and barns shot past, and narrow lanes tipped sideways off the main road. Mossy green hills outlined in hedgerows revealed a small fortune in sheep. If the gale had not closed off the sky we would have caught glimpses of the Atlantic Ocean when the taxi crested hills.</p>
        <p>A turn into a 600-year-old stone courtyard brought us to the starkly beautiful Yeate Farm. Angela Oliver, who owns the farm with her husband, David, their children and grandchildren, threw on rain gear and wellingtons and disappeared through an orchard, instructing the driver to advance past a rear gate onto a farm road, turn left and go downhill.</p>
        <p>Until G.I.'s constructed a paved road in the 1940's, Yeate Farm, whose name can be found in the Domesday Survey of 1086, was reached by following a dirt wagon path that led off the then main road to Bodinnick. In back of the farm, downhill, lay the forgotten barn that was now Penmarlam Quay Cottage, the estuary and, beyond it, Mixtow  Farm, the 15th-century home of a pirate family.</p>
        <p>We plunged down a straightaway that ended at the family's boatyard on the Fowey River, beyond which an ocean-going freighter was being nudged by tugs before a dock on the opposite bank. One sheep meadow above the boatyard we made a U-turn into a leafy hidden drive, where Angela waited in the doorway of the cottage.</p>
        <p>The living room was all stone fireplace, flowered slipcovers and deep-set windows that gave onto estuary, river and hills. A staircase spiraled inside a stone half-circle -- a grain bin in the days when sheep slept downstairs and shepherds up -- up to a second floor with three small bedrooms and more deep sills and pastoral views. We came to treasure waking up to the baaings of sheep, the shrilling of wind and the silent arrivals of ships from many lands.</p>
        <p>To reach the market town of Fowey we walked across two pastures, climbed three stiles, walked a quarter-mile down a winding road and caught the ferry that crosses every 10 minutes. The service has been in operation since 1343.</p>
        <p>As a 22-year-old girl in 1930, Daphne du Maurier wrote her first novel in the house called Ferryside adjacent to the Bodinnick slipway. She later moved across the river to the manor she immortalized in the first line of ''Rebecca'': ''Last night I dreamt I went to Manderley again.'' That name was based on Menabilly, a manor house with farms, gatehouse and church, as well as the inn and all cottages in the village of Polkerris. The most recent squire lives in the main house, which the author rented.</p>
        <p>Today's ferry is a six-car slab lashed to a little blunt-ended power boat. Although the lines of cars and pedestrians waiting on both banks in summer are so long that two ferries are pressed into use, in winter it may cross with one or two vehicles, one or two foot passengers, or no one at all.</p>
        <p>We rode daily, crossing with groceries and library books swathed against rain that drills sideways like needles. And we crossed on days imbued with the tropical sunshine that allows palm trees to grow in Cornwall. During the gales, when black sheets of rain move in from the sea, the ferry ties up and drivers must turn around to go 14 miles out of their way. But those on foot are helped into a dinghy with an inboard motor and a wooden tiller. While it rained more often than not, most days included extravagant bursts of everything, even hail. When sunshine appeared it did so with an impulsiveness that blinded eyes more accustomed to cloud cover. On such days we ate deli take-out food on the Fowey town quay or in a nearby old schoolhouse garden. We didn't take food on hikes because we inevitably passed through a village, where we feasted on fish and chips at a pub.</p>
        <p>There are those who say Cornwall is not quite English. It's not just that a major river, the Tamar, splits it top to bottom from the rest of the country, but Cornwall writhes west into the Atlantic with north and south coasts never farther than 30 miles apart and, in the case of Fowey, 15 miles apart.</p>
        <p>Until the mid-18th century, inhabitants spoke Cornish Celtic. Considered to be rough, wild people -- fisherfolk, smugglers, tin miners, pirates and rebels -- yesteryear's Cornish were descended from ancient Phoenicians, wanderers from Ireland and Wales, and survivors of the wreck of the Spanish Armada. In 1457, one aristocratic Fowey woman, Elizabeth Treffry, reputedly defended her home by having molten lead poured over the wall onto the heads of the French, who were attacking in reprisal for raids on their coast by ruffians from Fowey. The Treffry home, called Place, is still standing in town.</p>
        <p>Our cottage was on the chilly side. The bathroom, which backs up to an exterior stone wall, was so moist that not only did towels not get dry, dry ones grew damp. We preheated the room before taking showers by turning on the wall heater, and we warmed the kitchen by turning on the oven. But we didn't do it much. During a cold spell, the electric meter in the kitchen cupboard ate 20 one-pound coins (about $30) a week.</p>
        <p>The upstairs was served by a small space heater that, before our nightly ordeal of jumping into icy sheets, we briefly plugged in. On two occasions when we had overnight guests, we let them take the heater into the guest room while we shivered. Most ''character cottages,'' as ours was called, lack what rental listings refer to as CH: central heat. Because of the proximity of the sea, in addition to steep village streets where sidewalks turn into staircases and ancient buildings veer off-plumb, water seeps through walls and even runs across floors (I saw it in a pub). At their most forceful, gales lift heavy slate shingles off roofs and hurl them into the windows of cars and houses.</p>
        <p>While it is true that the temperature is mild (crocuses and snowdrops in bloom in January; daffodils, tulips, primroses and camelias in February), the humidity turned our cottage into a refrigerator on 40-degree days. Some old houses cannot be updated because of legal restrictions and structural peculiarities that date to the Middle Ages. The Cornish, a cheerful lot, laugh at the omnipresent rawness and, finally, so did we.</p>
        <p>AWARE that during the region's eight warm, balmy, really flowering months it groans under an invasion of tourists, we counted ourselves lucky. (One local town expands tenfold in the summer to a population of 50,000.)  Before we left at the end of March, the Fowey River was patterned in dots by moorings that seemed to bob in anticipation of the arrival of hundreds of pleasure craft.</p>
        <p>Every day or two we tramped four to eight miles -- along the wind-blasted coastal cliff from Lanteglos to Polruan, where we rode another small ferry to Fowey for a lunch of fisherman's pie and beer in front of the fireplace at King of Prussia, or rib-sticking soup with a four-star-quality baguette and cappuccino at Crumbs. We would pick up our copy of The Times of London, and stroll the twisted streets, flattening ourselves against houses if a car came, before catching the ferry for the voyage home to Bodinnick.</p>
        <p>Sometimes we walked to Readymoney Cove and up a flight of hill steps to the remnants of a fort Henry VIII never finished. Onward, through a kissing gate, over stiles, along grassy inclines; past cows and sheep, swans and border collies; past the tiny flowers called winter jasmine that cling to cliffs; past odoriferous barnyards; into rural churchyards where gravestones tilt and the church, which is open, is so Norman that it stuns the imagination; onto headlands being thumped by waves far below, maybe into Polkerris, a scrap of a hamlet dropped between cliffs on a hidden beach, where hikers fall gratefully into the Rashleigh Inn.</p>
        <p>A mini-bus runs through Fowey every 30 minutes and connects with the rail station at Par three miles away. Two bus lines operate on the Bodinnick side of the river and, we were told, anyone who can stand the ruckus may ride a schoolbus. Not all rural bus lines operate daily, but bus drivers wait for the elderly, and drivers (and passengers) lend a hand to mothers with babies and strollers. Like the ferrymen, if they know you're coming, they wait.</p>
        <p>We frequently caught the train to out-of-town hiking adventures, all of which featured irresistible scenery -- a 2000 B.C. stone circle here, an A.D. 100 earth mound there, an ingenious stile, a quoit, a bygone kiln; a ruined engine house over an abandoned mine, nine-foot-high and four-foot-thick stone hedgerows shot through with ferns, ivy, brambles and honeysuckle.</p>
        <p>As for the towns -- East and West Looe, Lostwithiel (lost-WITH-i-el), St. Austell, Truro, Falmouth, Penzance -- all afforded niches for tea, scones and clotted cream. In many of these towns we walked onto sea walls where beaches lapped up to the business district, and in all of them we found stores with used books.</p>
        <p>With just a handful of small food shops in Fowey, the late-afternoon shopper may have to purchase what's left on the shelf, a situation that agreed with us. Life without a car rescued us from a mind-set of must-haves, and the proprietors were attentive and helpful.</p>
        <p>We bought staples at the grocery store, meat at the butcher's, fish at the fish store and fresh produce at a tiny produce shop, where parsley was wrapped in paper with the tender care that a florist would give to long-stemmed roses.</p>
        <p>Though we would try to buy only enough groceries to fill a backpack, the walk home could be a long one.  But the milkman arrived weekly at our cottage door with milk in glass bottles, yogurt, butter, orange juice, mineral water, locally grown root vegetables and bread.</p>
        <p>Eating lunch out alleviated the grocery-lugging situation, and another ploy was to take flashlight in hand and in the black of night head across the two sheep meadows and over the three stiles and down the road to the Old Ferry Inn.</p>
        <p>In the pub at the Old Ferry Inn, with its two resident Old English sheepdogs and four Siamese cats by the fireplace, everybody knows everybody. When we walked in on our second day in Cornwall (the door making a great rasp and all eyes turning toward it), a voice from out of the crowd called, ''Did you come by the farm, or over the stiles?''</p>
        <p>We couldn't eat dinner in Fowey becase in winter the ferry stops running at 5 P.M., a situation that also made us mindful of timing when we ventured far afield.Not that missing the boat would have been calamitous -- we could have taken a taxi upriver and over the little stone bridge or spent the night at one of Fowey's small hotels. But in truth we were always eager to return to our nest, where we would build a fire in the fireplace, prepare dinner in the well-equipped kitchen, watch BBC 1 and read our latest second-hand exclusives.</p>
        <p>Finding your own Camelot in a land of Arthurian legends</p>
        <p>Getting There</p>
        <p>Trains leave Paddington Station in London several times a day for the  three-and-a-half hour trip to Liskeard. Tickets may be bought from Britrail, (212) 575-2667 or (800) 677-8585, or at Paddington, where Great Western Trains Limited, (44-71) 313-1950, a new, privatized rail company, is currently offering a round trip for only about $3.40 more than the one-way fare if the trip is completed within 30 days. For timetable and fares, call (44-345) 484-950. Britrail's one-way coach fare to Liskeard is $81 and round trip is $110.</p>
        <p>Pedestrians on the ferry between Bodinnick and Fowey pay less than $1 a trip. The mini-bus that passes through Fowey terminates in St. Austell, seven miles away, where connecting buses leave from the rail station (including the National Express coach that goes to Heathrow). Trains from Par connect with trains to other Cornish coast areas and elsewhere in Britain.</p>
        <p>The British Tourist Authority publishes two free guides, ''Self-Catering Holiday Homes 1997'' and ''South of England,'' about Cornwall. They are available from the authority at 551 Fifth Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10176; (212) 986-2200.</p>
        <p>The Tourist Information Center at the post office in Fowey is closed Sunday and after 1 P.M. on Wednesday and Saturday. Phone and fax, (44-1726) 833-616.</p>
        <p>From May 9 to 18, Fowey is celebrating Daphne du Maurier's life and work.</p>
        <p>Hiking</p>
        <p>The more challenging sections of the 300-mile Coastal Path, which runs from Morwenstow in north Cornwall to Saltash in south Cornwall may be avoided if one carries an Ordnance Survey map and a local guidebook. The straight-talking guidebooks that sell for $1 to $6 in local shops are also invaluable. Sample directions: ''Over this stile follow the right hedge . . . To avoid the dogs at Roskrow Barton go to D. Cross the field diagonally down, towards modern buildings ahead and around the new barn in the corner of the field onto the farm lane . . . The dogs here can seem threatening -- keep walking.''</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>Brochures for Penmarlam Quay Cottage are available from Angela Oliver, Yeate Farm, Bodinnick-by-Fowey, Cornwall, England PL23 1LZ; (44-1726) 870-256. The cottage sleeps four adults and two children. The bathroom has a shower and, in a shed, a coin-operated laundry. Firewood is provided, but sheets and towels are not. (Some home owners lease bed-and-bath linens, usually for about $10 a person a week.)</p>
        <p>Rates, calculated at 58 cents to a pound: $222 weekly from Oct. 31 to Feb. 28 ($136.80 weekly for a minimum stay of four weeks); Feb. 28 to March 28 and Oct. 3 to 31, $273.60; March 28 to May 23 and Sept. 5 to Oct. 3, $376.20; May 23 to July 4 and Christmas week, $478.80; July 4 to Sept. 5, $632.70; New Year's week, $307.80.</p>
        <p>Other rentals are available through May Whetter &amp; Grose, Estuary House, Fowey, Cornwall, England PL23 1AH; (44-1726) 832-965, fax (44-1726) 832-866. Listings range from $176 in winter to $1,052 in summer.</p>
        <p>Fowey River Estate Agents, 13 Fore Street, Fowey, Cornwall, England PL23 1AH, telephone and fax (44-1726) 833-000, carries listings in the same price range.</p>
        <p>Hill &amp; Son at 3 Fore Street, PL23 1AH, (44-1726) 832-211, specializes in cottages in Polruan, a steep enclave of much charm across the harbor. A ferry for pedestrians operates from Fowey every 10 minutes; drivers use the Bodinnick ferry and drive five miles.</p>
        <p>Hotels include the Fowey, Esplanade, Fowey, Cornwall, England PL23 1HX; (44-1726) 832-551. Its rates are from $170 to $234 for two people, including breakfast and dinner. The restaurant offers a five-course dinner at $34 a person.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Dining in winter is limited. At the King of Prussia, if you can get the table by the window, you'll have the best river view in town. Fisherman's pie costs $7, a pint of local beer $2.50 and a glass of wine $2.</p>
        <p>The Ship Inn and the Globe also serve lunch and dinner, at comparable prices.</p>
        <p>Sam's Deli, Fore Street, (44-1726) 832-322, sells takeout sandwiches, Cornish pasties and muesli bars, and is always crowded and cheerful at midday.</p>
        <p>At the Rashleigh Inn, Polkerris, Par, (44-1726) 813991, a three-mile walk along coastal cliffs or overland, excellent meals can be eaten on the terrace, which gets wet in high tide. For many centuries, the inn and all the houses in Polkerris have been owned by the Rashleigh family. Serves bar meals from $8 from 11 A.M. to 2 P.M. and 6 P.M. to 10 P.M. and the a la carte restaurant is open  6:30 to 9:30 P.M. daily, with prices from $18.50.</p>
        <p>Across the river, the Old Ferry Inn, Bodinnick-by-Fowey, Cornwall, England PL23 1LZ, (44-1726) 870-237, has both a pub and a formal dining room for meals. Rooms range from $32 a person for a single to $56 a person for a double with bath and a view of the river. Prices include full English breakfast, tax and service. The inn serves bar food from noon to 3 P.M. and 6 to 9:30 P.M.; basic dishes cost $4.15 to $11.20. The restaurant is open 6:30 to 9:30 P.M.; a three-course meal ranges from $25 to $30.</p>
        <p>PAULA BOYER ROUGNY lives on the coast of Maine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">PAULA BOYER ROUGNY lives on the coast of Maine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
