<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Owners Ready to Resume Negotiations</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="768423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D61239F931A25755C0A963958260" item-length="495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Owners Ready to Resume Negotiations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ready or not, the owners apparently are finally prepared to resume negotiations with the players for a new collective bargaining agreement. That is the word delivered by people who attended the owners' meetings in Minneapolis last week.</p>
        <p>Although Bud Selig, the acting commissioner, and the chief negotiators haven't said anything about the resumption of talks, one owner said during the weekend that, based on the discussion at the meetings, he expected talks to begin "very soon."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ready or not, the owners apparently are finally prepared to resume negotiations with the players for a new collective bargaining agreement. That is the word delivered by people who attended the owners' meetings in Minneapolis last week.</p>
        <p>Although Bud Selig, the acting commissioner, and the chief negotiators haven't said anything about the resumption of talks, one owner said during the weekend that, based on the discussion at the meetings, he expected talks to begin "very soon."</p>
        <p>Another person made that timetable a little more specific, saying he expected something to happen in the next 10 days to two weeks.</p>
        <p>"We're going to see some prompt action," the second person said. "They'll see what happens with the N.L.R.B. thing, then move on to the next stage. It will be very quick."</p>
        <p>Negotiators for the owners and the players have not met since March 30, the day before a Federal judge issued an injunction that prompted the players to end their strike and return to work. But lawyers for both sides have been meeting in discussions for settlement of the National Labor Relations Board charges against the owners.</p>
        <p>The lawyers will meet again this week. If they reach an agreement or even make progress toward one, they are expected to ask for a postponement of the trial on the N.L.R.B. charges scheduled to begin next Monday before an administrative law judge.</p>
        <p>Talks for a collective bargaining agreement then could resume.</p>
        <p>"We've got to get an agreement," said the owner, who spoke on the condition he wouldn't be identified. "That was stressed. The pressure's on, and it's coming from all directions. Huizenga, Angelos and others spoke, people from different positions. The consensus clearly is let's get it done."</p>
        <p>Wayne Huizenga of the Florida Marlins is considered a hard-liner, Peter Angelos of Baltimore a moderate. From one extreme to the other, the owners and the players believe it is imperative to reach an overall agreement to show the fans it's safe to return to the ball park.</p>
        <p>To be in position to resume talks in even two weeks, the owners' negotiating team will have to work quickly. The owners haven't selected a chief labor lawyer to replace Chuck O'Connor, whom Selig has dismissed, and they don't appear to be certain about their approach to the key economic issue -- how to put some form of restraint on player salaries.</p>
        <p>When they adjourned talks, the owners were trying to get a luxury tax on payrolls, having abandoned their initial strategy of getting a salary cap. Some owners want to return to the cap, but others have said that strategy surely would precipitate another work stoppage.</p>
        <p>John Harrington of Boston, chairman of the negotiating committee, has hinted at a new wrinkle the committee could be developing.</p>
        <p>Some people on the management side are talking about the possibility of the N.L.R.B. settlement discussions producing an impetus that will enable the negotiators to begin resolving issues one by one.  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
