<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="685495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DIWAN GRILL (NYC RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ASIMOV, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0D71639F935A35756C0A962958260" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline/>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ASIMOV, ERIC</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jackson Diner in Jackson Heights, Queens, is renowned as one of the best and cheapest Indian restaurants around, specializing in both the vegetarian dishes of southern India and the more familiar dishes of the north. But elegant? A polite term for the place, with its plastic tablecloths and pink walls, would be modest.</p>
        <p>So what are the owners of Jackson Diner doing with Diwan Grill, a spacious, elegant 150-seat Indian restaurant that opened five months ago in the former quarters of Bukhara in mid-Manhattan? They are doing quite well, thank you, serving northern Indian dishes (but not Jackson Diner's distinctive southern specialties) with all of the vibrancy that continues to draw diners from around the city to Jackson Heights. In fact, the Jackson Diner has turned into a small empire. The original Diwan opened several years ago in Port Washington, L.I.; another Diwan Grill just opened on William Street in the financial district, and further expansion is planned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jackson Diner in Jackson Heights, Queens, is renowned as one of the best and cheapest Indian restaurants around, specializing in both the vegetarian dishes of southern India and the more familiar dishes of the north. But elegant? A polite term for the place, with its plastic tablecloths and pink walls, would be modest.</p>
        <p>So what are the owners of Jackson Diner doing with Diwan Grill, a spacious, elegant 150-seat Indian restaurant that opened five months ago in the former quarters of Bukhara in mid-Manhattan? They are doing quite well, thank you, serving northern Indian dishes (but not Jackson Diner's distinctive southern specialties) with all of the vibrancy that continues to draw diners from around the city to Jackson Heights. In fact, the Jackson Diner has turned into a small empire. The original Diwan opened several years ago in Port Washington, L.I.; another Diwan Grill just opened on William Street in the financial district, and further expansion is planned.</p>
        <p>One thing Diwan has not retained is the no-frills pricing of Jackson Diner. Entrees run as high as $21. But portions are generous enough that entrees can easily be shared. Three entrees should satisfy a party of four, for example, and a party of six might want to order only four.</p>
        <p>The prices also buy style and service. Tables in the dining room are widely spaced, and the room is hushed despite the hard surfaces of the slate floor and the pale yellow pillars. Colorful banquettes line the outside of the room and a series of large round tables undulates through the middle. The typically Indian high-backed chairs lend an air of earnest formality, underscored by the attentive staff, dressed in black pants and white shirts. Food arrives in copper serving bowls, and portions are dished out by waiters with alacrity.</p>
        <p>First to arrive is a platter of pappadams, paper-thin peppery lentil wafers that are marvelous dipped into the accompanying small dishes of sweet-and-sour tamarind sauce and spicy coriander-mint sauce. Many of the appetizers are familiar, but the flavors and textures of these dishes is a revelation to people dulled by the tired fare at most Indian restaurants. Shrimp ki tikki ($7.95), minced shrimp combined with sesame seeds, flour and spices and fried, are delicious. Pakoras ($3.95), wedges of zucchini, cauliflower florets and other sliced vegetables coated with chickpea flour and fried, are greaseless and crisp. Samosas ($3.95) are fine, as is chat papri ($3.95), potatoes and chickpeas in a yogurt and tamarind sauce. A more unusual dish, karare quails, marinated in yogurt and cooked in the clay oven ($6.50), are deep and smoky and inspire prolonged gnawing.</p>
        <p>Many entrees are also familiar but deserve a new look. Rogan josh ($14.95), tender chunks of lamb in a complex spicy sauce, sends waves of flavor passing through the mouth. Seekh kabab ($14.95), minced lamb rolled into cylinders and grilled, is wonderfully spicy, and fish tikka, chunks of salmon cooked in the clay oven, is pricey at $20.95 but is sublime, the fish moist and gently but skillfully spiced. Malai kofta lajwab ($10.95), croquettes made of lentils and soft cheese, are first rate, served in a multi-dimensional creamy sauce. Pasandas ($14.95) are not on the menu, but you can ask for this unusual dish of lamb chunks marinated in yogurt and served in a sauce of ground almonds and cashews, and it is worth the 15-minute wait.</p>
        <p>Another way to save money at Diwan: skip dessert. Neither the soapy rice pudding ($4.95) nor the overly sweet fried cheese balls ($4.95) will alter the drab stereotype of Indian restaurant desserts. They do come in elegant dishes, though.</p>
        <p>Diwan Grill</p>
        <p>148 East 48th Street, Manhattan, (212) 593-5425.</p>
        <p>Best dishes: Shrimp ki tikki, pakoras, samosas, chat papri, karare quails, rogan josh, seekh kabab, fish tikka, malai kofta lajwab, pasandas.</p>
        <p>Price range: $15 to $32 (excluding tax, tip and beverages).</p>
        <p>Credit cards: All major cards.</p>
        <p>Hours: 11:30 A.M. to 2:30 P.M. and 5:30 t0 10:30 P.M. daily.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair access: Three steps down from entrance to dining room; restroom is on same level.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
