<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strangling Is Suspected In S.I. Death</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="685556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E3DF1438F935A35756C0A962958260" item-length="585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strangling Is Suspected In S.I. Death</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG WOLFF</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A lawyer for the family of a Staten Island man who died in police custody last week said yesterday that a doctor hired by the family to perform an autopsy suspects, based on preliminary findings, that the man was strangled.</p>
        <p>The lawyer, John Murphy Jr., cautioned that the findings by Dr. Mark Taff, a forensic pathologist, were not final and that he still needed to review the results of tests by the city's Medical Examiner's office before reaching any definitive conclusions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A lawyer for the family of a Staten Island man who died in police custody last week said yesterday that a doctor hired by the family to perform an autopsy suspects, based on preliminary findings, that the man was strangled.</p>
        <p>The lawyer, John Murphy Jr., cautioned that the findings by Dr. Mark Taff, a forensic pathologist, were not final and that he still needed to review the results of tests by the city's Medical Examiner's office before reaching any definitive conclusions.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Murphy said Dr. Taff found no traces of drugs in the blood and saw evidence of "pinpoint bleeding" in both eyes and over the heart surface. In combination, those findings suggest that the man, Ernest Sayon, 22, did not die of a drug overdose or a heart attack but of strangulation, Mr. Murphy quoted Dr. Taff as saying.</p>
        <p>Dr. Taff could not be reached for comment yesterday, and messages for him left at his office and with Mr. Murphy were not answered.  A Number of Bruises</p>
        <p>Mr. Murphy said he was present at the autopsy, conducted yesterday at the Kings County Hospital Center in Brooklyn, as were doctors from the Medical Examiner's office. Ellen Borakove, a spokeswoman for the Medical Examiner's office, said results of the city's autopsy would not be released until next week. She has said Mr. Sayon suffered a number of bruises over his head and body but no internal injuries.</p>
        <p>Witnesses have told investigators from the Police Department and the Staten Island District Attorney's office that Mr. Sayon died after a clash with police officers conducting an anti-drug sweep through the Park Hill housing complex.</p>
        <p>Some witnesses have said Mr. Sayon was knocked unconscious by a single blow to the head with a gun by one officer, Donald Brown, and that other officers put him in a chokehold.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sayon's death provoked outrage from scores of residents in Clifton, S.I., who say police encounters like the one with Mr. Sayon are becoming more frequent. Since the attack, there have been demonstrations against the police outside the 120th Precinct station house and at the Gracie Mansion gates as well as further allegations of police misconduct. Trip Time at Issue</p>
        <p>Yesterday, a senior police official dismissed news accounts and an assertion by Mr. Murphy suggesting that it took officers up to 17 minutes to take Mr. Sayon to Bayley Seton Hospital, a trip of a few city blocks, and that the officers stopped along the way. The official, speaking on condition of anonymity, said police radio transmissions indicate the officers stopped only briefly to check on Mr. Sayon's condition. The trip took just four minutes, the official said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murphy said Dr. Taff, a former associate clinical professor of pathology at Mount Sinai School of Medicine, found no drugs in Mr. Sayon's blood, though he saw traces of drugs in his bile, secreted by the liver. Mr. Murphy said this suggests that Mr. Sayon used drugs in the past but was not "high" when he died and could not have died of an overdose.</p>
        <p>He said Dr. Taff found bleeding in the muscles surrounding the esophagus, which theoretically could have been caused when emergency technicians inserted breathing tubes for Mr. Sayon. But Mr. Murphy said that according to Dr. Taff, the bleeding in the eyes and on the heart's surface are signs of burst capillaries, suggesting that Mr. Sayon was strangled.</p>
        <p>There was also a hematoma on the neck behind the left ear, further evidence, Mr. Murphy said, that Mr. Sayon had been held in a chokehold.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
