<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>December</title>
    <meta content="02DECE$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/02/movies/02DECE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1531822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="HOLIDAY MOVIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Anita</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3D91638F931A35752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="5949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>December</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">December</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANITA GATES; Compiled with the assistance of Suzanne O'Connor</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gates, Anita</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anita Gates lists and briefly describes movies scheduled for release in December; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dec. 5</p>
        <p>FIVE SIDES OF A COIN -- A documentary about the power and culture of hip-hop, with Run DMC, Afrika Bambaataa, Grandmaster Flash, De La Soul and at least three dozen other artists. Paul Kell directed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>December.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dec. 5</p>
        <p>FIVE SIDES OF A COIN -- A documentary about the power and culture of hip-hop, with Run DMC, Afrika Bambaataa, Grandmaster Flash, De La Soul and at least three dozen other artists. Paul Kell directed.</p>
        <p>FORGET BAGHDAD -- A documentary about Jewish and Arab stereotypes, especially as seen in 100 years of film. Examples include Hollywood features, Israeli boureka comedies and Egyptian musical comedies. The film also focuses on the experience of Sephardic Jews, who may feel like foreigners in their own country. Directed by the Iraqi-born video artist Samir, whose family moved to Switzerland when he was a child.</p>
        <p>FROM HERE TO ETERNITY -- The love scene on the beach (Deborah Kerr and Burt Lancaster clinched and drenched) is well known. Frank Sinatra's performance, as the scrappy Private Maggio, revived his stalled career and won him the Oscar for best supporting actor (one of eight Oscars the film received, including best picture). Montgomery Clift is Private Prewitt, the reluctant boxer, and Donna Reed is the ladylike hooker he falls for. The film, based on James Jones's novel about a military base in Hawaii just before Pearl Harbor, is exactly 50 years old. Fred Zinnemann, who did ''High Noon'' and went on to do ''A Man for All Seasons,'' directed.</p>
        <p>HONEY -- Jessica Alba (who made her name in the futuristic Fox series ''Dark Angel'') stars as an inner-city dancer who makes it big as a choreographer of music videos. Then she encounters sexual harassment. The cast also includes Lil' Romeo and Mekhi Phifer. Directed by Bille Woodruff.</p>
        <p>THE LAST SAMURAI -- It's been a long time since Tom Cruise appeared on screen in period costume (and that was as a vampire). In this 19th-century epic, he's Nathan Algren, an alcoholic Civil War veteran who's been called to Japan to teach its army all about modern warfare. Which will mean the end of the samurai, and Algren becomes unsure that that's a good thing. Edward Zwick (whose film credits include ''Glory'') directed, and he wrote the screenplay with his former ''thirtysomething'' partner, Marshall Herskovitz, and John Logan. Tony Goldwyn, Billy Connolly and Ken Watanabe are Mr. Cruise's co-stars. A related article is on Page 6.</p>
        <p>MONSIEUR IBRAHIM -- Omar Sharif plays a Muslim grocer who becomes good friends with an emotionally needy Jewish boy (Pierre Boulanger) in 1960's Paris. Mr. Sharif shared the best-actor audience award (with Benicio Del Toro for ''21 Grams'') for this role at the Venice International Film Festival. François Dupeyron directed.</p>
        <p>PRISONER OF PARADISE -- In 1944, the Nazis decided to make a propaganda film about Theresienstadt, painting it as a utopian community rather than the death camp it was. To make the film, they chose Kurt Gerron, a German Jew who had been arrested in Amsterdam. Gerron was not just another prisoner. He had starred in ''The Blue Angel'' with Marlene Dietrich and had introduced the song ''Mack the Knife'' in the original Berlin production of ''The Threepenny Opera.'' When the film, ''The Führer Gives a City to the Jews,'' was completed, Gerron was sent to Auschwitz and gassed. Malcolm Clarke (who did the Oscar-nominated short documentary ''You Don't Have to Die'') and Stuart Sender directed this film, which was nominated for best documentary feature of 2002 and is now being released commercially.</p>
        <p>WHAT ALICE FOUND -- A drama about truck-stop prostitution. Emily Grace plays a young woman driving south to Florida. Bill Raymond and Judith Ivey are the seemingly nice couple who stop to help her when she has car trouble. They have some career ideas for her. A. Dean Bell wrote and directed.</p>
        <p>Dec. 10</p>
        <p>BIG FISH -- Tim Burton goes for heart-warming in this adventure drama about a dying father (Albert Finney) and his not-that-close son (Billy Crudup), who wants to know whether the tall tales that Dad told all those years were true. Really, where does a traveling salesman run into giants and witches? Jessica Lange is the dying man's wife, and Ewan McGregor and Alison Lohman play the couple's younger selves. The screenplay is by John August, who wrote ''Go'' (which everyone loved) and ''Charlie's Angels: Full Throttle'' (which they didn't).</p>
        <p>POWER TRIP -- During the Soviet years, a lot of people in Georgia didn't pay their electricity bills and nothing happened. But when AES, an American company, bought the power plant in the capital city, Tblisi, and bills weren't being paid, the company did things the American way: they turned off the power. Paul Devlin's documentary is about the fiasco.</p>
        <p>Dec. 12</p>
        <p>GIRL WITH A PEARL EARRING -- Dad is suddenly unemployed after an accident at work. His 16-year-old daughter goes to work to help out the family. Then she falls in love with her married boss. In Peter Webber's film, this timeless story takes place in 17th-century Holland and the girl's employer is Johannes Vermeer, whose most famous paintings include a portrait of an unknown young woman, ''Girl With a Pearl Earring.'' Colin Firth plays Vermeer and Scarlett Johansson, currently having her star-making moment in ''Lost in Translation,'' plays Griet, the teenager turned housemaid. Based on the best-selling novel by Tracy Chevalier.</p>
        <p>LOVE DON'T COST A THING -- We're remaking 1987 movies already? Sixteen years ago, ''Can't Buy Me Love'' starred Patrick Dempsey as a high school nerd who pays the prettiest girl in school to go out with him so people will think he's cool. This teenage romantic comedy stars Nick Cannon (''Drumline'') as a high school nerd who pays the prettiest girl in school (Christina Milian) to date him for the same reason. Steve Harvey plays Mr. Cannon's father. Directed by Troy Beyer, who wrote and starred in ''BAPS.''</p>
        <p>SOMETHING'S GOTTA GIVE -- We haven't seen Jack Nicholson and Diane Keaton together since his Eugene O'Neill seduced her Louise Bryant in ''Reds.'' This time his middle-aged character is dating her character's daughter (sexy Amanda Peet), but after he has a heart attack he realizes it's the older woman he really loves. But a young doctor (Keanu Reeves) feels the same way about her. Nancy Meyers, who wrote and directed, also wrote ''Private Benjamin'' and ''Baby Boom'' (starring Ms. Keaton) and directed ''What Women Want.''</p>
        <p>THE STATEMENT -- For a man who turned 70 this year, Michael Caine is awfully busy. In this political thriller from Norman Jewison (whose last feature film was ''The Hurricane''), Mr. Caine plays a former Nazi executioner who has led an undisturbed postwar life in France until he is suddenly on everyone's hit list. The cast also includes Tilda Swinton, Charlotte Rampling, Alan Bates, Jeremy Northam and Ciaran Hinds.</p>
        <p>STUCK ON YOU -- The Farrelly brothers, Bobby and Peter, have given moviegoers comedy about multiple personalities, morbid obesity, dogs in body casts and wayward ejaculate. Now they turn to the world of conjoined twins. Bob (Greg Kinnear) and Walt (Matt Damon) share a liver, get along beautifully and make a great hockey player in their hometown. But now Bob wants to go to California to pursue his dream of becoming an actor, and Walt says he won't hold him back. In their new life, they come into contact with Cher, Meryl Streep, Jack Nicholson, Jay Leno and Luke Wilson, who play themselves.</p>
        <p>Dec. 17</p>
        <p>THE LORD OF THE RINGS: THE RETURN OF THE KING -- The end has come for Peter Jackson's film trilogy, based on J. R. R. Tolkien's fantasy novels. Since all three films were shot at the same time, this one is likely to be as spectacular as the first two. When last we saw Tolkien's characters, Frodo (Elijah Wood) was getting a much-needed pep talk, Aragorn (Viggo Mortensen) was looking kingly and Gandalf the Gray (Ian McKellen) was looking grand on a white horse. Now the battle for Middle Earth begins, and someone has got to get that ring to Mount Doom and throw it into the fires. Other returning cast members include Sean Astin, Orlando Bloom, Cate Blanchett, Ian Holm, Liv Tyler, Hugo Weaving and Christopher Lee. Gollum (Andy Serkis, plus computer generation), who won best virtual performance at the MTV Movie Awards, is back, too. A related article is on Page 6.</p>
        <p>Dec. 19</p>
        <p>THE BUTTERFLY -- An 8-year-old girl bonds with the elderly entomologist next door. A family drama starring Michel Serrault and Claire Bouanich. Directed by Philippe Muyl.</p>
        <p>CALENDAR GIRLS -- In Britain, apparently, if you are desperate for funds, the thing to do is take off your clothes. It worked for the unemployed men in ''The Full Monty.'' And it worked for the ladies of the Rylstone Women's Institute in Yorkshire. To raise money for leukemia research, they decided to pose for the group's annual calendar wearing pretty much nothing but pearls. The models were all in their 40's, 50's and 60's. Helen Mirren and Julie Walters star in the film version of this true story. Nigel Cole, who did ''Saving Grace,'' directed.</p>
        <p>THE FOG OF WAR -- ''This is a movie filled with existential dread,'' says Errol Morris, the director. ''There's this surreal sense that nothing has changed.'' The documentary in question is about Robert S. McNamara, secretary of defense during the Kennedy and Johnson administrations. The film focuses on McNamara's involvement in the Vietnam War, the Cuban missile crisis and the World War II fire-bombing of Japan. When it was shown at the New York Film Festival last month, Stephen Holden, writing in The New York Times, called the film a ''sober, beautifully edited documentary portrait.''</p>
        <p>THE HEBREW HAMMER -- Finally, a Jewish action hero. Jonathan Kesselman, the young writer and director of this satire, enjoys playing with stereotypes. The title character, whose real name is Mordechai Jefferson Carver (Adam Goldberg), is a Brooklyn private eye who, in his spare time, saves the world of Jewish culture and tradition. But, as the filmmakers point out, his mother still wishes he'd done more with his life. The Hammer is battling Santa Claus's son Damian (Andy Dick), who is out to eliminate Hanukkah. Mario Van Peebles plays the head of the Kwanzaa Liberation Front. Peter Coyote plays Bloomenbergansteinthal, head of the Jewish Justice League, which includes members of the Worldwide Jewish Media Conspiracy.</p>
        <p>MONA LISA SMILE -- Here's Julia Roberts, barely 36 and already playing the older woman. In this drama from Mike Newell, whose films include ''Enchanted April,'' ''Four Weddings and a Funeral'' and ''Donnie Brasco,'' Ms. Roberts plays an open-minded Berkeley graduate who takes a job teaching art history at Wellesley in 1953. She has wonderful students but is horrified to realize that they have no interest in using their minds beyond whatever it takes to land a husband. And so she questions their values and tries to shake things up. Kirsten Dunst, Julia Stiles and Maggie Gyllenhaal play students.</p>
        <p>Dec. 24</p>
        <p>CHILDREN OF LOVE -- (''Les Enfants de l'Amour'') From Belgium, one weekend in the life of a family separated by divorce, focusing on the three children. Geoffrey Enthoven, the writer and director, began doing research for a documentary but turned it into a docudrama instead. The cast includes Nathalie Stas, Winnie Vigilante, Michael Philpot and Olivier Ythier.</p>
        <p>MONSTER -- Newspapers called Aileen Wuornos the first female serial killer. She was a highway prostitute and drifter who killed at least six men and was executed last year in Florida. Wuornos has been the subject of a television movie, a feature documentary, an opera and an Off Off Broadway play. In the latest film version, written and directed by Patty Jenkins, Charlize Theron takes the role, playing way against type, and Christina Ricci portrays her young lover.</p>
        <p>Dec. 25</p>
        <p>CHEAPER BY THE DOZEN -- Steve Martin and Bonnie Hunt seem made for each other as a pair of busy professionals with 12 children. This isn't exactly a remake of the 1950 film starring Clifton Webb as an efficiency expert who liked to test his theories on his own huge family: Mr. Martin plays a football coach who gets a new, time-consuming city job and Ms. Hunt is an author on a book tour, and both could use some time-management guidance. Their children include Piper Perabo, Tom Welling (the young Clark Kent on ''Smallville'') and Hilary Duff. Ashton Kutcher plays a boyfriend that Dad doesn't like. Mr. Martin has plenty of opportunities for physical comedy, including swinging from a chandelier. Shawn Levy (''Big Fat Liar'') directed.</p>
        <p>COLD MOUNTAIN -- Anthony Minghella's last two films, ''The English Patient'' and ''The Talented Mr. Ripley,'' were major winners. Now he's written and directed this Civil War drama, based on Charles Frazier's novel of the same name. Jude Law plays a badly wounded Confederate soldier who leaves the hospital and begins a long walk home to North Carolina and the woman he loves (Nicole Kidman). She, meanwhile, is trying to manage her dead father's farm. Luckily a helpful drifter (Renée Zellweger -- an American!) turns up and stays. North Carolina's film industry may be thriving, but this film was shot in South Carolina, Virginia and Romania. A related article is on Page 1.</p>
        <p>THE COMPANY -- It's going to be hard for Robert Altman to top his last film, ''Gosford Park,'' but he's giving it a go with this backstage story of the ballet world. He says he hopes to capture ''the work itself in all its demanding beauty.'' Barbara Turner (a co-writer of ''Petulia,'' Richard Chamberlain's best movie, and the glorious ''Pollock'') did the screenplay, based on a story she wrote with Neve Campbell. Ms. Campbell (''Party of Five'') is the central character, a young ballerina on the brink. The cast also includes James Franco, who gave an uncanny performance in TNT's ''James Dean''; Malcolm McDowell; and members of the Joffrey Ballet.</p>
        <p>PAYCHECK -- Michael Jennings (Ben Affleck), a computer engineer, has two big problems in this sci-fi thriller: his $4.4 billion paycheck has been canceled and his memories of the last two years have been erased. (That's the way he manages to work on top-secret projects without confidentiality dangers.) In trying to figure out what happened, he's aided by the woman he both works with and loves (Uma Thurman). Aaron Eckhart is back in bad-guy mode as Jennings's boss. John Woo directed, and Dean Georgaris wrote the screenplay, based on a short story by Philip K. Dick, whose stories and novels have been turned into films including ''Blade Runner,'' ''Total Recall'' and ''Minority Report.'' Related articles are on Pages 9 and 28.</p>
        <p>PETER PAN -- After Mary Martin, Sandy Duncan, Cathy Rigby and Mia Farrow comes a Peter Pan actually played by a 14-year-old boy (Jeremy Sumpter). P. J. Hogan, who did ''My Best Friend's Wedding,'' directed, and Michael Goldenberg (''Contact'') wrote the screenplay, based on J. M. Barrie's classic, and frequently filmed, British play. The cast also includes Jason Isaacs (Lucius Malfoy in the second Harry Potter movie) as Captain Hook, Rachel Hurd-Wood as Wendy and Ludivine Sagnier (the sexy teenager in ''Swimming Pool'') as Tinker Bell.</p>
        <p>YOUNG BLACK STALLION -- A prequel to the 1979 film ''The Black Stallion,'' based on the Walter Farley novel. Seems that before the mysterious Arabian horse met  his best human friend at sea and bonded with him during a shipwreck, he had a significant emotional relationship with a little girl who had been separated from her father. The cast includes Biana Tamimi, Richard Romanus and Patrick Elyas. Simon Wincer (''Free Willy'' but also ''Crocodile Dundee in Los Angeles'') directed. Jeanne Rosenberg, who was one of three co-writers on the first ''Black Stallion'' movie (which was directed by Carroll Ballard), did the screenplay. This is Disney's first dramatic feature made for Imax and other large-screen formats.</p>
        <p>Dec. 26</p>
        <p>HOUSE OF SAND AND FOG -- Sometimes the American dream doesn't come easy. Ben Kingsley plays an Iranian immigrant, a former member of the Shah's inner circle now reduced to doing menial jobs. He jumps at the chance to buy a house for back taxes, but it turns out that the house was seized erroneously and the evicted owner (Jennifer Connelly) has troubles of her own. Ron Eldard, who impressed New York theatergoers in ''Death of a Salesman'' and ''Bash,'' is a deputy sheriff who gets far more involved than he should. Vadim Perelman, a Russian-born newcomer, wrote and directed. Based on the 1999 novel by Andre Dubus III.</p>
        <p>MODERN TIMES -- Charlie Chaplin's last silent film and one of his comic masterpieces. Chaplin, who wrote and directed, stars as a factory employee -- his classic character the Little Tramp -- who has a nervous breakdown shortly after a test of an automated ''feeding machine'' (created so workers won't have to take breaks while eating lunch). He ends up in jail (he loves it there), goes back to a factory (where some large wheels eat his tool box and a co-worker), gets a job as a department store night watchman, becomes a hero while under the accidental influence of cocaine and ends up as a singing-dancing waiter with Paulette Goddard, his favorite waif. The film was originally released in 1936.</p>
        <p>Dec. 31</p>
        <p>JAPANESE STORY -- Which, of course, takes place in Australia. Toni Collette stars as a geologist stuck with baby-sitting a prospective client (Gotaro Tsunashima) who won't be satisfied with the usual city tour. She dislikes him on sight and he doesn't seem to care for her either, but at his request she takes him into the outback, where they eventually face a life or death situation. It's a love story, an adventure, a culture clash and an odd-couple comedy all in one, directed by Sue Brooks and written by Alison Tilson. This is Ms. Collette's return to her home country's film industry after appearing in a number of American and British movies (''The Sixth Sense,'' ''About a Boy,'' ''Far From Heaven'').</p>
        <p>HOLIDAY MOVIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
