<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SAN FRANCISCO FOR LESS GOLD</title>
    <meta content="SANFRAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/02/travel/02sanfran.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1531956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="3 Cities, 3 Days, 3 Budgets | $500"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Francisco (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harlan, Megan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">San Francisco (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E5D61630F931A35752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="2347" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SAN FRANCISCO FOR LESS GOLD</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">San Francisco for Less Gold</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEGAN HARLAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harlan, Megan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Megan Harlan travel article on inexpensive cultural weekend in San Francisco, with budget of $500; photos; chart; list (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO may have swooned, for a while, over the $1,000 tasting menus and college-dropout millionaires of the dot-com boom. But since the economic and tourism slumps, the city not only offers deals to travelers, but its arts scene -- as if awakened from a nap -- seems refreshed and ready for work. Call it the creative upside of the downturn.</p>
        <p>My assignment -- or challenge, as I thought of it -- was to spend an inexpensive cultural weekend in San Francisco. A $500 budget was to cover a marathon run of the city's arts scene for myself and my husband, Matthew, and food and a hotel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An art aficionado gets her fill (and eats well too) and still comes in just under a tight budget.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO may have swooned, for a while, over the $1,000 tasting menus and college-dropout millionaires of the dot-com boom. But since the economic and tourism slumps, the city not only offers deals to travelers, but its arts scene -- as if awakened from a nap -- seems refreshed and ready for work. Call it the creative upside of the downturn.</p>
        <p>My assignment -- or challenge, as I thought of it -- was to spend an inexpensive cultural weekend in San Francisco. A $500 budget was to cover a marathon run of the city's arts scene for myself and my husband, Matthew, and food and a hotel.</p>
        <p>I wanted to see a play, hear live music, and view as much art as I could process in a weekend. For events, I relied on Citysearch.com and SFArts.org (the latter, sponsored by San Francisco Arts Monthly, is a boon for budget travelers, allowing searches for free events by date).</p>
        <p>But we did much more: besides seeing a play, we logged five music performances, a poetry festival, dance recital, walking tour and dinner at a trendy new restaurant. I visited more than a half-dozen museums and galleries. We kept stumbling across artistic happenings; short of hiding in a Gap dressing room, it seemed we couldn't avoid them.</p>
        <p>None of this would have been feasible without an affordable hotel -- and as San Francisco residents, we knew the challenge this could pose. So my very first task was to scour listings on sites like Expedia and Orbitz, where I found bargains in the $120 range. Still, I felt I needed to go cheaper, and settled on the Andrews Hotel, two blocks west of Union Square, with $99 rooms for the warm, late-September weekend we checked in.</p>
        <p>Built in 1905 as a Turkish bathhouse and now affiliated with the stylish local hotel management company Joie de Vivre, the 48-room Andrews doesn't scream hip. But the reservation for our clean, cozy, queen-bed room decorated in floral prints, with full bath, came directly through the Andrews, so I avoided fees from discount travel Web sites. Another plus was that the Andrews offers a disappearing luxury at downtown San Francisco budget hotels: Continental breakfast is included. This proved crucial to staying within our means.</p>
        <p>With tax, two nights came to $225.72. That left $274.28 to eat, drink and make merry. Friday evening, we kicked things off on a thrifty note with free glasses of wine -- one per guest per night from 5:30 to 7 p.m. -- offered by the Andrews at Fino, a restaurant off the lobby (tip: $2).</p>
        <p>Just around the corner, we enjoyed a quick pretheater dinner at Akiko Sushi Bar. The mint-green space is tiny, the sushi fat and fresh. Two chef's specials, one with a large beer, cost $25.16.</p>
        <p>For theater choices, I'd considered ''Les Liaisons Dangereuses'' by the wonderful American Conservatory Theater at the Geary Theater, a block from the Andrews. That afternoon, I visited the TIX Pavilion, Union Square's discount ticket counter, which had $70 orchestra seats at half price (still too much), with second-balcony seats running $19. I chose instead $16 tickets for the West Coast premiere of David Lindsay-Abaire's postmodern comedy, ''Wonder of the World,'' playing at the Eureka Theater, a 200-seat classic black space a 10-minute walk away. After the funny, frisky production, we nibbled brie at the cast party, and decided that this experience beat the worst seats in a fancier house.</p>
        <p>The balmy evening inspired us to continue. Back on Market, we caught a refurbished vintage Chicago streetcar, the Green Hornet (free, because of a broken meter), down to Café du Nord, a crimson, candlelight music club and former speakeasy. For a $10 cover, we heard a local psychedelic pop band, Oranger -- a fresh shade of the city's musical past. Two drinks at the gleaming redwood bar were $10 with tip. After a hook-filled set, a streetcar back down Market was $1.25 each.</p>
        <p>Day's total: $204.52.</p>
        <p>Saturday, Matthew and I woke early to raid the Continental breakfast -- fresh pastries, fruit, juice and coffee, handily laid out on each floor. Then we headed off to the 10 a.m. tour meeting outside SS. Peter and Paul Church in North Beach.</p>
        <p>I am not a tour person. But I'm glad I kept an open mind for this eclectic -- and free -- walking tour of North Beach, one of several dozen by San Francisco City Guides (supported by the San Francisco Public Library). The personable guide, Gail Todd, pointed out wild parrots in Washington Square Park and the gentrification of Grant Avenue, amid stops at former Beat haunts like the Coffee Gallery (now the bar Lost and Found), where she confessed to having seen Allen Ginsberg read poetry back in the day. Tip: $5.</p>
        <p>After two hours of passing the neighborhood's fragrant Italian bakeries and restaurants, we were famished, and stopped for lunch at a local landmark, the Molinari Delicatessen. Two subs -- huge, delicious and a steal at $4.75 -- eaten in the small sidewalk seating area, sustained us until dinner. Total: $14.90.</p>
        <p>We caught a bus ($2.50 total) to the wooden bayside warehouses of Fort Mason Center, a vibrant association of theaters, museums and galleries in the Marina District. The Mexican Museum ($3 apiece) had only two rooms, but was worth it just for Alfonso Soteno's marvelous, towering ceramic ''Tree of Life,'' lavishly petaled with flowers, people, angels and animals.</p>
        <p>Three warehouses down, the Museum of Craft and Folk Art ($4 for me, since my husband passed) displayed work by artists using everyday materials. Exquisite metal suitcases by Mariko Kusumoto, filled with little numbered doors opening, like Advent calendars, onto such objects as Buddhas and treasure chests struck me as metaphors for travel and discovery.</p>
        <p>And they set the mood for the Asian Art Museum ($10), in a serene, Beaux-Arts building at the Civic Center (bus ride free with transfer). Inside, we took in a mesmerizing Indonesian dance recital in the Samsung Hall, host to performances each afternoon. Then, after coffee and a piece of candy ($3.91 total) in the cafe, we lost ourselves in the tranquil galleries. I lingered in the jade room, with its milky rainbow of vases, and before the Tibetan thangkas, or sacred wall-hangings, with powdered pigments symbolizing aspects of wisdom, and depicting the Buddha on mountains threaded with rivers.</p>
        <p>Feeling rather meditative, we strolled to the day's final art stop, the unassuming office building at 49 Geary. On the fourth floor, the renowned Fraenkel Gallery is celebrating a quarter-century of showing photography with ''The Eye Club'' through Nov. 29, featuring haunting portraits by artists like Berenice Abbott and Paul Strand. We wandered through the floor's several other galleries, including Lizabeth Oliveria's, showing playful, cartoon-style thangka paintings by the local artist Stella Lai.</p>
        <p>After a quick rest at the hotel, we took the train ($2.50 total) to the Mission District, where we had reservations that turned out to be essential at the recently opened Last Supper Club. The open-kitchen atmosphere attracts a young, easygoing crowd. Homey cheese ravioli and a grilled half-chicken (both $12), mashed potatoes ($4.25) and a beer came to $43.35, with tip.</p>
        <p>Walking four blocks, we arrived at Bruno's, a dark jazz club, at 8:50 p.m. -- thereby avoiding the $7 cover charged after 9:30 p.m. Refurbished to its early-60's lounge splendor, Bruno's boasts huge, semicircular white vinyl booths. We nursed our $7 martini-glass cocktails ($17 total) until Dapp Theory came on. The five-man jazz-funk ensemble unleashed dizzyingly layered rhythms, with the John Coltrane of harmonica players and a spoken-word vocalist. We said: Cool, daddy-o. And the thing is, it really was.</p>
        <p>Saturday's total, with $2.50 for a bus back to the hotel: $234.52.</p>
        <p>A COUPLE we had met at the club raved about the gospel ensemble at Glide Memorial United Methodist Church. On Sunday, we walked three blocks to the packed 9 a.m. service, in which the charismatic Rev. Douglass Fitch welcomed all faiths and quoted the Dalai Lama. But it was the diverse, 140-strong choir that moved churchgoers to tears belting out gorgeous powerhouse gospel. Donation: $5.</p>
        <p>Ready for more inspiration, we proceeded to the soaring, striped-granite turret of the Museum of Modern Art in SoMa (South of Market). I'd bought two $15 tickets online, which included a $5 charge for the Marc Chagall exhibition -- five rooms of his dreamily narrative visions of artists, lovers and animals on view until Nov. 4. A starker humanism was found at the exhibit from the museum's excellent photography collection, ''Picturing Modernity,'' with unsentimental highlights like Robert Frank's ''Iowa,'' capturing a dance hall.</p>
        <p>We revived at the museum's light, bright Caffè Museo, with lunch treats like smoked salmon salad ($10.30) and chicken focaccia sandwich ($8.50) -- worthy of a foodie town. Total with latte: $20.70</p>
        <p>Across the street glistened the waterfalls, esplanades, gardens and galleries of Yerba Buena Center for the Arts -- a two-block contemporary-art complex in Yerba Buena Gardens. And outside the center, we happened upon one of a series of free events, showcasing Italian art, organized by the Yerba Buena Gardens Festival. The classical guitarist Peppino D'Agostino played supple flamenco, and San Francisco Lyric Opera stars sung popular arias. We roused ourselves from an excerpt from ''La Bohème'' to catch a bus ($2.50) to the International Poetry Festival.</p>
        <p>We climbed Russian Hill to the graceful Italian-inspired buildings of the San Francisco Art Institute. We were late, so we missed all but the last, very moving reader, Peter Streckfus, who won this year's Yale Series of Younger Poets competition. The school's top terrace had views of the Bay, and on our way out, we visited the Diego Rivera Gallery, devoted to student art and Rivera's mural, ''The Making of a Fresco Showing the Building of a City,'' full of invention and motion.</p>
        <p>For a weekend exploring urban creativity, it provided a fitting final image. And the gallery was free, bringing the weekend's grand total to $497.24.</p>
        <p>$500  Lodging: $225.72  Food and drinks: 137.02  Transit: 12.50  Entertainment: 122.00  Total: $497.24</p>
        <p>Proving you don't have to suffer for your art</p>
        <p>Activities</p>
        <p>Café du Nord, 2170 Market Street, (415) 861-5016; www.cafedunord.com, open 6 p.m. to 2 a.m. Thursday to Saturday, 6 p.m. Sunday to Wednesday. Weekend cover, $8 to $10.</p>
        <p>Bruno's, 2389 Mission Street, (415) 648-7701, www.brunoslive.com, open Tuesday to Sunday, 6 p.m. to 2 a.m. for food and music; music only on Monday. No cover weekends before 9:30 p.m.; after that, $7.</p>
        <p>Glide Memorial United Methodist Church, 330 Ellis Street, (415) 674-6000, www.glide.org, has Sunday services from 9 to 10:15 a.m. and 11 a.m. to 12:15 p.m. The Rev. Cecil Williams alternates Sundays with the Rev. Douglass Fitch.</p>
        <p>The Mexican Museum, Fort Mason Center, Building D, (415) 202-9700 or see www.mexicanmuseum.org; Wednesday to Saturday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission, $3.</p>
        <p>Museum of Craft and Folk Art, Fort Mason Center, Building A, (415) 775-0991, www.mocfa.org, is open Tuesday to Friday and on Sunday 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., and on Saturday 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; $4.</p>
        <p>Asian Art Museum, 200 Larkin Street, (415) 581-3500, www.asianart.org, is open Tuesday to Sunday 10 a.m. to 5 p.m., and until 9 p.m. Thursday; $10.</p>
        <p>Fraenkel Gallery, 49 Geary Street, Fourth Floor, (415) 981-2661, Web site www.fraenkelgallery.com, is open 10:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Tuesday to Friday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Saturday.</p>
        <p>Lizabeth Oliveria Gallery, 49 Geary Street, No. 411, (415) 229-1138, Web site www.lizabetholiveria.com; Tuesday to Friday 11 a.m. to 5:30 p.m., Saturday to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 151 Third Street, (415) 357-4000, www.sfmoma.org, is open Thursday to Tuesday, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m., and to 8:45 p.m. Thursday; $10.</p>
        <p>Yerba Buena Center for the Arts, 701 Mission Street, (415) 978-2787, Web site www.yerbabuenaarts.org, and the Yerba Buena Gardens Festival, (415) 543-1718, www.ybgf.org, which organizes free arts events, are in Yerba Buena Gardens.</p>
        <p>The Diego Rivera Gallery at the San Francisco Art Institute, 800 Chestnut Street, (415) 771-7020, www.sfai.edu, is open daily 8 a.m. to 8 p.m. Admission free.</p>
        <p>The TIX Pavilion, (415) 433-7827, www.theatrebayarea.org/tix/tix.shtml, the discount theater ticket counter, is in Union Square. Hours for purchasing half-price tickets (cash only): Tuesday to Thursday 11 a.m. to 6 p.m., Friday to Saturday 11 a.m. to 7 p.m., Sunday 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Eureka Theater, 215 Jackson Street, (415) 788-7469, www.eurekatheatre.org, stages innovative plays by local repertory companies.</p>
        <p>San Francisco City Guides, (415) 557-4266, www.sfcityguides.org, offers 30 free walking tours.</p>
        <p>Lodging and Restaurants</p>
        <p>The Andrews Hotel, 624 Post Street, (800) 926-3739, fax (415) 928-6919, www.andrewshotel.com. Rates run from $89 to $155, with Continental breakfast.</p>
        <p>Akiko Sushi Bar, 542 Mason Street, (415) 989-8218, is open Monday to Saturday, 11 a.m. to 10 p.m. Chef's specials average $9.</p>
        <p>Caffè Museo at MoMA, 151 Third Street, (415) 357-4500, is open 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. daily except Wednesday, until 9 p.m. Thursday; soups, salads, sandwiches (averaging $9), drinks and desserts.</p>
        <p>The Last Supper Club, 1199 Valencia Street, (415) 695-1199, is open daily for lunch and dinner. Pasta entrees, $8 to $12; bottles of wine, $25.</p>
        <p>Molinari Delicatessen, 373 Columbus Avenue, (415) 421-2337, is open 8 a.m. to 6 p.m. Monday to Friday, 7:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Saturday. Sandwiches average $5.</p>
        <p>3 Cities, 3 Days, 3 Budgets | $500 MEGAN HARLAN is a writer and poet who lives in San Francisco.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">MEGAN HARLAN is a writer and poet who lives in San Francisco.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
