<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TOP CONGRESSMAN SEEKS DEEPER CUTS IN MILITARY BUDGET</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="509324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHIPS AND SHIPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAVIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WARSHIPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRCRAFT CARRIERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ASPIN, LES (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYLER, PATRICK E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aircraft Carriers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DB1E3DF930A15751C0A964958260" item-length="1515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TOP CONGRESSMAN SEEKS DEEPER CUTS IN MILITARY BUDGET</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TYLER, PATRICK E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the first detailed Congressional response to the Bush Administration's military plans for the rest of the decade, the chairman of the House Armed Services Committee is proposing to cut $48 billion to $121 billion more than the White House by 1997, reductions he says would still leave the United States a superpower.</p>
        <p>Representative Les Aspin, the Wisconsin Democrat who is chairman of the House military panel, said in an interview that within two years he might be willing to consider cutting the Navy's force of 12 aircraft carriers to 8, cutting the Air Force's 15 tactical air wings roughly in half and slashing the Navy fleet from its current level of 450 ships to 290.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the first detailed Congressional response to the Bush Administration's military plans for the rest of the decade, the chairman of the House Armed Services Committee is proposing to cut $48 billion to $121 billion more than the White House by 1997, reductions he says would still leave the United States a superpower.</p>
        <p>Representative Les Aspin, the Wisconsin Democrat who is chairman of the House military panel, said in an interview that within two years he might be willing to consider cutting the Navy's force of 12 aircraft carriers to 8, cutting the Air Force's 15 tactical air wings roughly in half and slashing the Navy fleet from its current level of 450 ships to 290.</p>
        <p>As chairman of the House committee with jurisdiction over the military, Mr. Aspin carries substantial weight in the Democratic House leadership. But ultimately his views will be leavened by negotiations with the Senate, which has usually been willing to support a higher level of military spending. 4 Visions of Strength</p>
        <p>Mr. Aspin said he would lay out to Democratic leaders and the House Budget Committee four financing options for the post-cold-war period based on four levels of war-fighting ability.</p>
        <p>His aides said he had been seeking support among Democrats for an option that would roughly double President Bush's proposed $50 billion cut in military spending in the next five years. Under this option, greater reductions could follow as international stability improved and the military threat of the former Soviet Union continued to recede.</p>
        <p>The Army would lose three more active-duty divisions, the Air Force would lose five more active-duty air wings and the Navy about 90 ships, including half the attack submarine force. Instead of ending the five-year period with 1.6 million people in the military, as the Bush Administration has proposed in its "base force" plan, the military would drop to 1.4 million troops. Imposing Order on Democrats</p>
        <p>Three of the four Aspin options would cut much deeper than the President's proposed $50 billion reduction over the next five years. Mr. Aspin's aides said that in consultations he had told Senator George J. Mitchell, the majority leader, and Senator Sam Nunn, the Armed Services Committee chairman, "Look, we can take $100 billion or $125 billion over five years out of this budget, no problem, and we might be able to do better than that."</p>
        <p>Mr. Aspin said he met with Senator Nunn to brief him on the options and seek his support for a doubling of the Bush Administration military cut. Senator Nunn said he would study the options, but made no commitment, Mr. Aspin said.</p>
        <p>Representative Aspin's remarks and his presentation this week represent the first comprehensive reaction from a Congressional Democratic leader to the Bush Administration's military plan presented in January. Mr. Aspin's motive for unveiling detailed options for future military spending appears to be an attempt to bring some order to the proliferation of "peace dividend" plans proffered by Democrats in Congress and by Democratic Presidential candidates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aspin said he chose this week to unveil his plan because of the publication of classified war scenarios prepared by the Pentagon to guide military leaders in preparing their budgets through 1999. Wide Support Expected</p>
        <p>Among Democrats, Mr. Aspin appears to be pursuing a centrist proposal for additional military reductions, and as such, his plan is likely to attract substantial support. At the end of 1997, Mr. Aspin's preferred course would still have the United States spending between $210 billion to $235 billion a year on the military, whereas other military experts have recommended going down to an annual spending level of $160 billion to $180 billion by the end of the decade.</p>
        <p>In an interview Friday, Mr. Aspin said that he has supported his financing options with a detailed review of various crises and readiness levels developed by his staff over the past several months. Scenarios combining those factors indicate that even with much deeper cuts in military spending, United States forces could fight three simultaneous regional conflicts and maintain its pre-eminent military position in the world.</p>
        <p>The military crises his staff studied were a repeat of the Persian Gulf war against Iraq; a deployment of United States air power to support South Korean ground forces repelling an invasion from North Korea; a major humanitarian relief action like the one conducted in Kurdistan last year, and an airborne assault like the one on Panama in 1989. Of the four scenarios developed using these crises, the two Mr. Aspin has used in figuring likely cuts would save $48 billion to $121 billion in the military budget in the next five fiscal years.</p>
        <p>In some respects, Mr. Aspin's scenarios are not as demanding as those considered by the Pentagon, which placed greater emphasis on intervention by United States ground forces against North Korea along with the Air Force. The Pentagon's seven scenarios, which were detailed in a New York Times article last week, also said the military should be prepared for potential conflict in Europe, using as an example a hypothetical attack by Russia on Lithuania.</p>
        <p>The importance of Mr. Aspin's war scenario exercise is that it represents a significant challenge to the work done by Pentagon planners. Mr. Aspin said he would soon begin a series of hearings to invite senior military leaders to examine financing options and the war scenarios they are based on.</p>
        <p>"What we have right now is an open debate about how you plan your forces in light of no Soviet threat, which has been the driving thing for planning forces for four or five decades now," Mr. Aspin said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aspin said he met last week with Brent Scowcroft, Mr. Bush's national security adviser, and Gen. Colin L. Powell, Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, to try to engage the Bush Administration in a major new review of military requirements for the rest of the decade. Mr. Aspin said the Administration had failed to establish a credible foundation for the military spending it proposes.</p>
        <p>"If you're going to sell a defense budget," he said, "you've got to have a tale that is convincing to the taxpayers, because people just don't buy defense for the hell of it.</p>
        <p>"They're buying it for dealing with certain potential contingencies or threats, and they don't want to spend more than what is necessary."</p>
        <p>Mr. Aspin said he would not criticize the Pentagon scenarios because he had not reviewed the classified study examining them. The Pentagon, he said, has been unwilling to share the study with Congress.</p>
        <p>It is too soon to tell where this year's struggle over post-cold-war military spending will end. In January Mr. Bush and Defense Secretary Dick Cheney laid out a plan for relatively modest cuts. The House and Senate armed services committees will draft military spending bills this spring that will progress through Congress at the height of the Presidential election season before emergence of a final Pentagon budget for the fiscal year 1993, which begins Oct. 1. Impact of Current Choices</p>
        <p>The potential impact of spending choices, Mr. Aspin said, could force the cancellation of a new aircraft carrier. The choices being made this year could also substantially reduce the proposed 600-plane fleet of F-22 Stealth fighters and the proposed 20-plane force of B-2 Stealth bombers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aspin predicted that the F-22 could end up as a "silver-bullet" weapon, meaning that relatively few might be produced yet would play a critical role as did the F-117 Stealth fighters played in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Also, Mr. Aspin said that while it was important to preserve crucial elements of the military industrial base, like the capacity to produce tanks and aircraft, other production lines that he declined to specify face closing in this decade.</p>
        <p>It may prove politically difficult to cut too deeply into the armed forces and weapons programs in an election year, Mr. Aspin acknowledged. Congress has already shown great interest in cushioning the impact of military cuts in areas of the country that heavily depend on related industries.</p>
        <p>"As in all defense planning, there will be no set of numbers that will satisfy all observers," Mr. Aspin said in remarks prepared for the release of his study. "But it is important that the choices be made through a bottom-up method that relates force structure choices and the different capabilities they buy to the sorts of threats America may face in the new era."</p>
        <p>Mr. Aspin's proposals appear at a time when Pentagon officials are said to be considering fallback positions from the proposal they presented in the summer of 1990. That proposal supported a 1.6-million-member military and also called for the procurement of a new generation of high-technology weapons, whose financing could cause military budgets to begin increasing again after mid-decade.</p>
        <p>Pentagon critics asserted last week that Mr. Cheney and General Powell formed the broad menu of war scenarios to help justify holding the line at their "base force."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
