<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Renovation of the Plaza Hotel Clears a Hurdle</title>
    <meta content="13PLAZ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/13/nyregion/13plaza.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1686895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Plaza Hotel</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Landmarks Preservation Commission</org>
        <org class="online_producer">City Planning Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E7DF103DF930A25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Renovation of the Plaza Hotel Clears a Hurdle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Renovation of the Plaza Hotel Clears a Hurdle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN SHULMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Renovations at the Plaza Hotel will restore it to its original grandeur, city landmarks officials said yesterday after they cleared the way for vast changes, including converting hotel rooms to condominiums and adding an underground complex of luxury stores.</p>
        <p>The Landmarks Preservation Commission recommended the approval of a landmarks waiver that would allow for 39,000 square feet of commercial space. It gave permission to make changes to the exterior of the building -- which already had landmark status -- including adding a new entrance for the stores. The commission also bestowed landmark status on eight of the hotel's famous public rooms and adjacent corridors and vestibules, including murals, chandeliers and decorative metalwork.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Renovations at the Plaza Hotel will restore the grandeur of the 1920's, city landmarks officials said Tuesday after they cleared the way for vast changes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Renovations at the Plaza Hotel will restore it to its original grandeur, city landmarks officials said yesterday after they cleared the way for vast changes, including converting hotel rooms to condominiums and adding an underground complex of luxury stores.</p>
        <p>The Landmarks Preservation Commission recommended the approval of a landmarks waiver that would allow for 39,000 square feet of commercial space. It gave permission to make changes to the exterior of the building -- which already had landmark status -- including adding a new entrance for the stores. The commission also bestowed landmark status on eight of the hotel's famous public rooms and adjacent corridors and vestibules, including murals, chandeliers and decorative metalwork.</p>
        <p>The rooms include the Palm Court, the setting for a scene from the movie ''The Great Gatsby;'' the Terrace Room, where Marilyn Monroe's dress strap once slipped off her shoulder while she was being interviewed by reporters; and the Oak Bar, where Cary Grant's character was kidnapped in ''North by Northwest.''</p>
        <p>Before the decision, the owner, Elad Properties, announced a plan to recreate a 1907 domed glass ceiling in the Palm Court, a move that the landmarks commissioners suggested at a hearing several weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Even so, a preservation group said the changes would destroy the character of one of the grandest grand hotels in the city, and pledged to fight the next step of the approval process, at the City Planning Commission.</p>
        <p>''It isn't a part-store, part-hotel, part-condo -- it's a hotel,'' said Elizabeth Ashby, president of the Historic Neighborhood Enhancement Alliance. ''It is the Plaza, known worldwide for what it is.''</p>
        <p>And the businessman Ronald S. Lauder, who has lobbied to restrict the Plaza to hotel use and went so far as to fly to Israel to negotiate with Elad executives, said in a statement that he would continue his efforts to save the Plaza ''from being transformed into another gaudy bazaar.''</p>
        <p>Eight members of the commission voted to recommend allowing more commercial use, and one abstained. The commissioner who abstained, Roberta Brandes Gratz, said that none of the developer's proposals had shown any concern for preservation until the glass ceiling in the Palm Court was proposed.</p>
        <p>Walter B. Melvin, an architect for Elad, said he had spent the past two weeks planning a recreation of the original Palm Court ''laylight,'' the glass ceiling with patterned lead canes that once formed the decorative interior of a 40-foot skylight.</p>
        <p>A 1921 addition to the hotel blocked the natural light, and the skylight itself was removed around World War II, according to Elad representatives, to prevent it from being a beacon during air raids. The new plan calls for artificial lights above the glass ceiling to create the impression of sunlight.</p>
        <p>''The laylight was a crucial factor,'' said Robert B. Tierney, the chairman of the commission. ''What triggered that was our assessment that the preservation plan was significant,'' he said, adding that the plans would return the hotel to its 1920's sumptuousness.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's decisions marked the latest chapter in a contentious process. Elad Properties had originally planned to convert the entire building to stores and apartments, but last winter, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg helped broker a compromise that would keep nearly half the hotel rooms and preserve the jobs of about 350 of the Plaza's 900 workers.</p>
        <p>The renovation will turn the 800-room hotel into a 350-room one with 180 condominiums, apartments and shopping space. The renovation is expected to cost more than $350 million, and Elad hopes to finish it by late 2006, in time for the Plaza's 100th anniversary.</p>
        <p>''For me personally this is a once in a lifetime opportunity to do something unique,'' said Miki Naftali, the president and chief executive of Elad.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
