<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Story Hours for Grown-Ups; Introducing Urbanites to the Lure of a Well-Told Tale</title>
    <meta content="10TALE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/10/arts/10TALE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010714T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1308155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Storytelling</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Moth (Storytelling Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bohlen, Celestine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Xanders, Joey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Solomon, Andrew</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D61038F933A25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1426" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Story Hours for Grown-Ups; Introducing Urbanites to the Lure of a Well-Told Tale</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Introducing Urbanites to the Lure of a Well-Told Tale</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bohlen, Celestine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Moth, nonprofit group formed by novelist George Green and Joey Xanders, offers storytelling events for adults around New York City and occasionally in other cities; participants in recent story night at Greenwich Village bar comment; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Storytelling as an urban art form has come a long way since 1997. That was the year that George Green, a novelist, first invited friends to his Manhattan apartment for an evening of swapping stories, in hopes of replicating the moth-infested, Jack Daniels-soaked yarns of his youth in Georgia.</p>
        <p>It took one night -- presumably a long one -- before Mr. Green realized that even the most inspired of storytellers require a little discipline and in some cases a lot of help.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A loosely organized company has held regular storytelling evenings for sold-out crowds in bars, restaurants and even planetariums, mostly in New York</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Storytelling as an urban art form has come a long way since 1997. That was the year that George Green, a novelist, first invited friends to his Manhattan apartment for an evening of swapping stories, in hopes of replicating the moth-infested, Jack Daniels-soaked yarns of his youth in Georgia.</p>
        <p>It took one night -- presumably a long one -- before Mr. Green realized that even the most inspired of storytellers require a little discipline and in some cases a lot of help.</p>
        <p>''It was an idea,'' said Mr. Green, who summoned his friend Joey Xanders from San Francisco to solve the problem. ''But we had no idea what we were doing. We thought there would be a lot of natural storytellers and that all we needed was to find a place. But there was more to it than that.''</p>
        <p>Such was the birth of the Moth, a loosely organized company that has since held regular storytelling evenings for sold-out crowds in bars, restaurants and even planetariums, mostly in New York but occasionally in Los Angeles or San Francisco. The name invokes those Georgia nights of storytelling, the teller serving as a sort of porch light, drawing the listeners.</p>
        <p>The goal was to resuscitate a distinctly adult tradition that Mr. Green feared had been lost amid the buzz of New York social chatter and the loneliness of high-tech communication.</p>
        <p>''It seemed to me people were getting further and further apart,'' said Mr. Green, who remains fascinated by the way good storytelling -- whether on Southern porches, in Irish pubs or at Manhattan saloons -- can create a sense of instant community.</p>
        <p>Like the stories, the Moth's format is both fluid and highly structured: half a dozen people are asked to tell stories onstage before an audience on a given theme: ''War Stories,'' for example, or ''the Seven Deadly Sins'' or ''Border Patrol: An Evening of Journeys Through Customs.'' After a run-through the night before, the storytellers have exactly 12 minutes each to tell their tales, until a live musician strikes up a tune that is to the Moth what the hook was to vaudeville.</p>
        <p>At a recent show at Nell's Bar in Greenwich Village the storytellers included a therapist, a former drug addict, an author who has written about Prozac, a reporter who told of investigating a suicide and Andrew Solomon, author of an encyclopedic book on depression.</p>
        <p>The theme, appropriately, was ''Melancholy,'' but the atmosphere was more hilarious than gloomy. The listeners, many of them sharing tables and nursing drinks, laughed at the punch lines that punctuated tales of death and sorrow, suffering and despair. To have it any other way, Ms. Xanders said, would be unbearable.</p>
        <p>''You can't hold an audience without humor,'' said Ms. Xanders, who has a theatrical flair for drawing stories out of people. ''We are always striking a balance. This is not stand-up comedy, but it is not about being too serious either.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Solomon, who appeared with the Moth for the first time that night, said he found the experience exhilarating. ''It is exciting because it is scary,'' he said. ''You feel very naked up there because it is just you, telling your story, with nothing else to mediate between you and the other people.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Solomon said the story he told, about a Cambodian woman who had survived the traumas of the Pol Pot regime, was fully revealed to him in the telling. ''There was a mystical feeling of the rhythms of the story,'' he said. ''I could sense its ebb and flow. You have to have an internal clock.''</p>
        <p>It is Ms. Xanders's job to find the ''curators'' of the shows, who come up with the themes. It is also her job to find the storytellers, which often takes some doing. Not all writers are good storytellers or even have good stories to tell, she said. The same goes for actors or other professional performers who have been known to overestimate their ability to wing it onstage.</p>
        <p>''There is always one dud, and we wouldn't want it to be any other way,'' Mr. Green said.</p>
        <p>For a night of stories based on the theme ''Going Home,'' Ms. Xanders went looking for a wide range of homecomers, from Frank McCourt, the Irish-born writer, to a former prisoner of war to Capt. Frederick H. Hauck, an astronaut. ''It took me a year and a half to find an astronaut,'' recalled Ms. Xanders, who said putting on Moth performances was like ''staging a Broadway show every three weeks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Green's idea from the very beginning was to use stories as a way to create a community, and in the years since the Moth was established that community has continued to grow. Running on an annual budget of $150,000 and the work of two paid employees, the nonprofit organization gets help from a far-flung network of volunteers, alumni and fans, some of whom have been officially recruited onto a board and an advisory council.</p>
        <p>Tickets, which go for $15, sell out quickly, and yet the Moth has never solicited an audience or even advertised. ''It is all word of mouth,'' Mr. Green said, ''but the response has been amazing. People like stories, and they like gathering to hear stories.''</p>
        <p>And the Moths are multiplying. Besides the regular shows, which are now on a summer break, there are story slams, modeled loosely on poetry slams like the ones organized by Bob Holman at the Nuyorican Poets Cafe in the East Village.</p>
        <p>The story slams, which are held once a month at the Nuyorican (admission is $5), are a competition among 10 volunteer storytellers whose five-minute tales are judged by a panel of audience members. The judges are instructed to see if the storytellers stay on time and on topic and, most important, if they have something compelling to say. The response to the slams has been snowballing, said Jenifer Hixson, producer of the events.</p>
        <p>''Before, I used to have to talk people into telling stories,'' she said. ''Now I am getting 20 names in the hat.''</p>
        <p>Four months ago Pem McNerney, 41, of Madison, Conn., won the slam with a story about the end of her marriage, the death of her dog and ''the nature of true love.'' She surprised herself by getting onstage with a story that was so intimate, she said, but found the effect therapeutic.</p>
        <p>''In telling a story, in re-examining it and saying it out loud, it is almost as if you can rewrite your past and create your future,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Moth also runs an outreach program that organizes mini-Moths at schools, a shelter for the homeless, a youth program, an AIDS counseling center and other social institutions, drawing on a pool of about 100 volunteers who are willing to run weekly workshops that culminate in a performance by the students or clients before their peers.</p>
        <p>''First of all you get good stories, and then you help people tell good stories, which helps them to think about things in general,'' said Doug Mennella, 31, a computer programmer who runs the mini-Moths at Project Renewal, a shelter for the homeless on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. ''We are not trying to cure them of any ills. We are trying to get them to be creative.''</p>
        <p>For the staff members and volunteers, there's a payoff.</p>
        <p>''We hear the funniest, most hilarious stories,'' said Lea Thau, the Moth staff member who is responsible for the outreach program. ''I am always amazed at the level of the stories. We get as much out of it as they do.''</p>
        <p>All this goes to prove Mr. Green's original point: that people connect better through storytelling.</p>
        <p>''I feel profoundly that stories should occupy a central place in our lives,'' he said. ''Four years ago there was this idea that the whole world was suffering from short attention span, that the old-fashioned story was dead. But the Moth proves that it is still very much in demand.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 14, 2001, Saturday  An article on Tuesday about the Moth, a loosely organized company that holds storytelling shows at bars and cafes, misstated the birthplace of the writer Frank McCourt, who participated in a show on the theme ''Going Home.'' He was born in Brooklyn, not Ireland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 14, 2001, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about the Moth, a loosely organized company that holds storytelling shows at bars and cafes, misstated the birthplace of the writer Frank McCourt, who participated in a show on the theme ''Going Home.'' He was born in Brooklyn, not Ireland.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
