<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Country Weekend, With Style</title>
    <meta content="15CTTHEA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1497120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westport Country Playhouse</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coward, Noel (1899-1973)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tresnjak, Darko</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hay Fever (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD81438F936A25755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="586" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Country Weekend, With Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews Westport Country Playhouse production of Noel Coward's 1925 play, Hay Fever, directed by Darko Tresnjak; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IMAGINE saying whatever is on your mind whenever and to whomever you want to say it. And saying it wittily, stylishly, fabulously -- and truthfully. It's a perfectly futile fantasy, of course, but vicarious fulfillment is yours at the Westport Country Playhouse, where Noël Coward's 1925 ''Hay Fever,'' a comedy of bad manners, as it has been famously called, has opened the summer season smashingly.</p>
        <p>In its day, ''Hay Fever'' was widely dismissed as a superficial, plotless observation of silly people not worth observing. ''Vicious and unwholesome'' was one critic's judgment of its characters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IMAGINE saying whatever is on your mind whenever and to whomever you want to say it. And saying it wittily, stylishly, fabulously -- and truthfully. It's a perfectly futile fantasy, of course, but vicarious fulfillment is yours at the Westport Country Playhouse, where Noël Coward's 1925 ''Hay Fever,'' a comedy of bad manners, as it has been famously called, has opened the summer season smashingly.</p>
        <p>In its day, ''Hay Fever'' was widely dismissed as a superficial, plotless observation of silly people not worth observing. ''Vicious and unwholesome'' was one critic's judgment of its characters.</p>
        <p>Those characters comprise the Bliss family during a disastrous weekend in their country home. Judith, an almost retired stage star who could have invented divadom, says matter-of-factly, ''I'm much more dignified onstage than in the country.'' But being offstage is no reason for her to stop acting or acting out. Amy Van Nostrand navigates Judith's quicksilver excesses with finesse.</p>
        <p>David, her husband, perfectly played by Jack Gilpin, has a simple philosophy of life. ''I love to see things as they are first, and then pretend they're what they're not,'' David says.</p>
        <p>Their son and daughter, Simon and Sorel, both of ingénue age, display temperaments much like their mother's. ''I sometimes wish we were more normal,'' Sorel says, without having the slightest intention of trying to be normal. ''It's not our fault, it's the way we've been brought up,'' is the reassuring thought Simon offers his sister.</p>
        <p>Each of the four Blisses is constantly sparring with one or all of the others, but just let outsiders -- four weekend guests -- compete, and they rally to each other's defense with a vengeance only a truly united family can muster.</p>
        <p>''You musn't mind if Simon and Sorel insult you a little,'' Judith warns one of the guests.</p>
        <p>What sets the Blisses apart from others is their honesty about who they are; since their lives have been devoted to artistic pursuits, they never bothered to learn social restraint.</p>
        <p>''You always say the right thing,'' Sorel comments, in awe, of Richard, a dull diplomat, played deftly by Robert Stanton, ''and no one knows a bit what you're really thinking.''</p>
        <p>For the Blisses, tact is synonymous with repression. They may be uncivil, but they are not uncivilized.</p>
        <p>Without stylistic flair and precise timing, Coward's characters can prove insufferable. It is lovely to report that the director of this production, Darko Tresnjak, has mastered the inflections, nuances and subtext of the play.</p>
        <p>In what could be a throwaway tea-serving scene at the end of the first act, Mr. Tresnjak's impeccable staging scales hilarious heights. He orchestrates the scene from pandemonium to dead silence when the curtain falls.</p>
        <p>The second act begins even more uproariously, with tirades over a game requiring the acting of adverbs. In a third act of utter lunacy, the guests escape after a horrid breakfast; Mr. Tresnjak creates laughs here that may never have been there in the first place.</p>
        <p>An invigorating breeze of summer wafts through this classy production.</p>
        <p>''Hay Fever'' is at the Westport Country Playhouse, 25 Powers Court, through June 21. Information: (203)227-4177 or www.westportplayhouse.org.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
