<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SUNY's Tuition Is Rising, but How Much?</title>
    <meta content="15SUNY$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/15/nyregion/15SUNY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1497102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">State University of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">State University of New York</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1DA1438F936A25755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SUNY's Tuition Is Rising, but How Much?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">SUNY Tuition Will Rise, but How Much?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trustees of State University of New York are scheduled to meet, but spokesman says that tuition is not on board's agenda; major obstacle is sharp differences between SUNY and State Legislature over size of tuition increase; they agree that tuition must rise since budget problems have forced lawmakers to cut state's contribution to SUNY's $1.9 billion operating budget by $184 million; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The trustees of the State University of New York are scheduled to meet on Tuesday, but students should not expect to find out how much tuition will rise at SUNY's four-year colleges beginning this fall.</p>
        <p>Tuition is not on the board's agenda, a university spokesman, David Henahan, said Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The trustees of the State University of New York are scheduled to meet, but students should not expect to find out how much tuition will rise this fall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The trustees of the State University of New York are scheduled to meet on Tuesday, but students should not expect to find out how much tuition will rise at SUNY's four-year colleges beginning this fall.</p>
        <p>Tuition is not on the board's agenda, a university spokesman, David Henahan, said Friday.</p>
        <p>He said that the trustees hoped to decide soon ''so that students and families have the ability to plan for their college costs this fall,'' but that there is no timetable for that decision.</p>
        <p>The major obstacle is sharp differences between SUNY and the State Legislature over the size of a tuition increase. They agree that tuition must rise since budget problems have forced lawmakers to cut the state's contribution to SUNY's $1.9 billion operating budget by $184 million.</p>
        <p>Tuition, the university's other main source of operating revenue, is currently $3,400 for New York residents and $8,300 for out-of-state students. The university has not raised tuition since 1995, although many of its 64 campuses have raised fees sharply since then and fees on some campuses now exceed $1,000. (Community college tuition, which is lower, is set separately, and varies by campus.)</p>
        <p>The Legislature has set $950 as the maximum increase for undergraduate tuition for New York residents, and called on SUNY to raise tuition for out-of-state students by about $52 million, an amount that works out to nearly $5,000 per student. Several university officials said that a greater increase for New York residents, of $1,100, would meet their needs, and that the increase for out-of-state students should be cut by at least half because a tuition increase of about $5,000 would scare away out-of-state students and widen SUNY's budget gap rather than narrowing it.</p>
        <p>''The $5,000 increase is unrealistic in what it will produce,'' said one high-level university official who spoke on the condition that he not be named. SUNY officials said in-state residents could afford to pay $4,500 in tuition because the neediest students would be covered by the state's Tuition Assistance Program.</p>
        <p>SUNY's chancellor, Robert L. King, led a delegation that included several SUNY presidents and the president of the university's faculty union to lobby legislative leaders on tuition last week. But by late Friday, there was no agreement, both sides said. The main question is whether the trustees will be willing to offend the Legislature and try to raise tuition above the levels set by lawmakers. Although trustees set tuition, the Legislature controls appropriations and SUNY's ability to spend what it brings in. The trustees, except for the student representative, are appointed by the governor, and SUNY officials have close ties to him.</p>
        <p>Last January, trustees proposed a $1,400 increase for in-state residents, a 41 percent jump. Gov. George E. Pataki lowered the figure to $1,200 in his executive budget. But legislators said even that was too high for many students, and set $950 as the limit. They directed SUNY to make up the revenue difference by raising tuition for out-of-state undergraduates to about $13,000.</p>
        <p>''Our position is that if tuition has to go up, we'd rather protect the New Yorkers than the out-of-staters,'' said Assemblyman Ronald J. Canestrari, a Democrat from the Albany and Troy area and chairman of the Assembly's higher education committee. ''We still think the out-of-state tuition would be competitive with other schools in the Northeast.''</p>
        <p>He said SUNY would do even better if it followed the lead of the City University of New York, which recently announced that it had identified administrative savings that would allow it to hold its tuition increase for state residents to $800 -- $150 lower than the Legislature had suggested. (CUNY currently charges state residents $3,200 a year.)</p>
        <p>''We thought that was a fine move on CUNY's part,'' Mr. Canestrari said on Friday.</p>
        <p>But of the 155,206 undergraduates at SUNY's four-year campuses, only 8,834 -- or fewer than 6 percent -- are from out of state, and university officials argue that a $5,000 tuition increase would halve that number. ''That's what our campuses are telling us,'' said a SUNY official who also spoke on the condition that he not be identified.</p>
        <p>According to SUNY's calculations, such a reduction would cost the university $100 million in tuition, room and board, not counting the revenue SUNY would collect from any in-state students who replaced them.</p>
        <p>One university official conceded that it was unlikely that SUNY would have any empty chairs. In recent years, enrollments have risen, to a record 403,000 students last fall, and SUNY projects further increases based on demographics.</p>
        <p>In-state students would pay less tuition than out-of-state students, but they pay the same the room and board fees. The estimated loss of $100 million does not take any of those sums into account.</p>
        <p>SUNY said that the campuses that would be hardest hit by large increases in out-of-state tuition would be its four university centers at Albany, Binghamton, Buffalo and Stony Brook, along with its Potsdam, New Paltz, Plattsburgh and Purchase campuses.</p>
        <p>Legislative leaders said they had re-examined their figures in light of SUNY's complaints, and were convinced that the tuition increases they proposed would allow the university to maintain the $1.9 billion budget it had this year.</p>
        <p>''It has always been our intention to give SUNY the revenue they needed to operate the system,'' said State Senator Kenneth P. LaValle, a Republican from eastern Long Island who is chairman of the Senate's higher education committee.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
