<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prices for Treasuries Slip, Falling Late in the Session</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="865024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D61E39F935A25754C0A960958260" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prices for Treasuries Slip, Falling Late in the Session</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bloomberg Business News</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Treasury prices fell yesterday for the first time in more than a week.</p>
        <p>Some traders expected a slumping stock market to add weight to a perception that the economy is running out of steam. Bonds fell late in the day when a rout in stocks temporarily abated, traders said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Treasury prices fell yesterday for the first time in more than a week.</p>
        <p>Some traders expected a slumping stock market to add weight to a perception that the economy is running out of steam. Bonds fell late in the day when a rout in stocks temporarily abated, traders said.</p>
        <p>If you were in the bond market because stocks were weak, stocks weren't weakening much further and it wasn't benefitting bonds much," said Tony Crescenzi, head of fixed-income trading at the Miller, Tabak, Hirsch &amp; Company "You had less reason to hang on."</p>
        <p>The price of the 30-year Treasury bond fell 14/32, to 86 21/32. The bond's yield, which moves in the opposite direction from its price, rose to 7.07 percent, from 7.03 percent on Friday.</p>
        <p>Concern that the chairman of the Federal Reserve, Alan Greenspan, will hint in Congressional testimony this week that there is reason to raise interest rates may have encouraged some bond investors to sell, Todd Speiser, a trader at Aubrey G. Lanston &amp; Company in New York, said.</p>
        <p>"Stocks have fallen appreciably in the last week or so, and supposedly some decent-sized investors bought bonds and sold stocks," Mr. Speiser said. "They may not want to ride it through" Mr. Greenspan's remarks, which could suggest the central bank is about to raise interest rates.</p>
        <p>Even so, some investors and analysts say a worse threat for bonds would be an indecisive Fed that holds off raising rates to keep stocks from falling further.</p>
        <p>"With economic reports continuing to come out on the strong side, they run the risk of being viewed by the markets as doing too little too late," said Anthony Karydakis, chief financial economist at First Chicago Capital Markets.</p>
        <p>Traders and investors will gain more insight into the pace of inflation from  the Labor Department's report today on June consumer prices. A survey of analysts said that the index probably climbed two-tenths of 1 percent, or three-tenths of 1 percent excluding the volatile food and energy sectors.</p>
        <p>In yesterday's regular weekly auction, the Treasury sold $14.2 billion in new three-month bills and $14 billion in new six-month bills.</p>
        <p>The average discount rate on the three-month bill was 5.19 percent, down from 5.21 percent last week, while the rate on the six-month bill was 5.36 percent, down from 5.41 percent.</p>
        <p>In the corporate bond market, Lucent Technologies Inc. plans to sell $750 million each of 5- and 10-year notes this week to help pay off short-term debt it inherited when it separated from the AT&amp;T Corporation earlier this year. The notes will be rated A2 by Moody's Investors Service and A by the Standard &amp;  Poor's Corporation.</p>
        <p>In the municipal bond market, New York postponed the sale of $76 million in bonds after lawmakers ratified the state's $66 billion budget, more than three months beyond its April 1 deadline.</p>
        <p>Wall Street's credit-rating companies said the budget process, along with a dependence on about $500 million in one-time revenue measures could hurt New York's rating. Standard &amp; Poor's may revise its outlook on the state's debt to stable from positive, reflecting the delay.</p>
        <p>Following are yesterday's results of the Treasury's regular weekly auction of three-month and six-month bills:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>3-Mo. Bills</p>
        <p>6-Mo. Bills Average Price</p>
        <p>98.688</p>
        <p>97.290 Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>5.19%</p>
        <p>5.36% Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>5.33%</p>
        <p>5.59% High Price</p>
        <p>98.693</p>
        <p>97.295 Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>5.17%</p>
        <p>5.35% Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>5.31%</p>
        <p>5.58% Low Price</p>
        <p>98.686</p>
        <p>97.285 Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>5.20%</p>
        <p>5.37% Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>5.34%</p>
        <p>5.60% Accepted at low price</p>
        <p>6%</p>
        <p>5% Total applied for</p>
        <p>$54,876,271</p>
        <p>$51,711,078 Accepted</p>
        <p>$14,169,071</p>
        <p>$14,030,028 Noncompetitive</p>
        <p>$1,468,064</p>
        <p>$1,540,364</p>
        <p>Both issues are dated July 18, 1996. The three-month bills mature on Oct. 17, 1996, and the six-month bills mature on Jan. 16, 1997.</p>
        <p>CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
