<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Microsoft and NBC's TV-Internet Service Trips in Debut</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="865042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNET AND WORLD WIDE WEB</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABLE TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MICROSOFT CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MSNBC (TV CHANNEL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LANDLER, MARK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NEUPERT, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1D61E39F935A25754C0A960958260" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Microsoft and NBC's TV-Internet Service Trips in Debut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LANDLER, MARK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even as executives from NBC News and Microsoft were holding an elaborate news conference yesterday to kick off their MSNBC cable-television and Internet service, which they said heralded a new world of news delivery, MSNBC fell victim to some old-world glitches.</p>
        <p>Computer users were not able to sign on to the Internet component of the service for at least an hour after the network was switched on yesterday at 9 A.M. As a result, MSNBC's anchors on the cable channel found themselves promoting on-line features that no one could see.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even as executives from NBC News and Microsoft were holding an elaborate news conference yesterday to kick off their MSNBC cable-television and Internet service, which they said heralded a new world of news delivery, MSNBC fell victim to some old-world glitches.</p>
        <p>Computer users were not able to sign on to the Internet component of the service for at least an hour after the network was switched on yesterday at 9 A.M. As a result, MSNBC's anchors on the cable channel found themselves promoting on-line features that no one could see.</p>
        <p>Peter Neupert, the Microsoft Corporation executive who oversees the Internet component of MSNBC, said that Microsoft and NBC, which is owned by the General Electric Company of Fairfield, Conn., had loaded too much material on the service at once, which caused it to crash when computer users began trying to visit the MSNBC site on the World Wide Web (http://www.msnbc.com). Mr. Neupert added that the service was functioning normally within an hour.</p>
        <p>But some computer users reported problems signing on to MSNBC's Web site for  the rest of the day. That is not unusual for the first day of an eagerly awaited Internet service.</p>
        <p>For Microsoft, which has a history of delaying product introductions to eliminate the biggest bugs, yesterday's introduction to the mass media underscored the tyranny of the entertainment-business adage, "the show must go on."</p>
        <p>MSNBC's technical problem was one of two sour notes in an otherwise well-orchestrated news conference that featured live appearances via satellite by Tom Brokaw, the NBC anchor, from the lawn of the White House, and William H.  Gates, the chairman and chief executive of Microsoft, from the company's headquarters in Redmond, Wash.</p>
        <p>The other sour note: so far the new cable service is available in only slightly more than one-third of the nation's 63.1 million cable households. While not a bad percentage compared with most other new cable networks, it puts  MSNBC at a disadvantage with its main competitor, CNN, which reaches all cable homes.</p>
        <p>The distribution problem for MSNBC stems from the fact that it fills the cable slot formerly occupied by the America's Talking cable channel of NBC. And  while many local cable systems have agreed to add MSNBC to their schedules, so far the nation's two biggest cable companies, Tele-Communications Inc. and Time  Warner Inc., have not.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Robert C. Wright, the president and chief executive of NBC, questioned the motivation of Time Warner and Tele-Communications. He speculated  that the two companies were about to team up to support a rival 24-hour news channel being started by the Fox Broadcasting Company, which is owned by the News Corporation.</p>
        <p>"This is an interesting proposition because between them right now they have  five news services," Mr. Wright said.</p>
        <p>Time Warner and Tele-Communications both own significant equity stakes in the Turner Broadcasting System, which operates CNN and four CNN spinoffs. Time Warner is currently negotiating with the Federal Trade Commission for approval to acquire Turner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wright said that Time Warner would have trouble with the F.T.C. if it appeared to favor one news channel over another.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Time Warner Cable declined to comment. But one executive close to the company said that Time Warner and NBC had simply failed to come to  terms on a deal to expand the distribution of MSNBC. This person, who declined to be identified, said Mr. Wright was invoking the F.T.C. negotiations as a way  to "bully" Time Warner in future negotiations.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Fox news channel, Brian Lewis, confirmed that Fox was in  talks with Time Warner about gaining distribution for its news channel but said  no announcement was imminent. Fox already has a deal with T.C.I., giving it distribution to 10 million cable households.</p>
        <p>Despite the stir caused by Internet woes, and Mr. Wright's harsh comments, the cable channel was able to make some news in its own right yesterday.</p>
        <p>MSNBC broke the news -- ahead of CNN -- that Michael Irvin, a star wide receiver for the Dallas Cowboys, had entered a plea of no contest to a drug-possession charge in Texas. And MSNBC had a second trophy: Mr. Brokaw's interviewed President Clinton yesterday evening.</p>
        <p>In the interview, which broke no new ground, the President answered questions from Mr. Brokaw and from computer users who submitted them on the Internet.</p>
        <p>The President also shrugged off a poll by the new network, which showed that  many Americans did not believe he and Mrs. Clinton have been telling the truth about Whitewater.</p>
        <p>"Every reading of the evidence as opposed to another round of questions, fails to demonstrate any wrongdoing," Mr. Clinton said.</p>
        <p>The highlight of the network's day turned out to be its scoop in Texas.</p>
        <p>Ed Turner, the executive vice president of CNN, said, "we raised hell" with the CNN news staff about losing the Michael Irvin story to MSNBC. And overall, Mr. Turner said he generally thought the network "had a respectable start."</p>
        <p>He noted, however, that MSNBC tended to focus on one or two stories at great  length, like the recent wave of unrest in North Ireland. Because CNN tends to function as more of a video wire service, Mr. Turner said that MSNBC did not look like it would pose much of a direct threat.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
