<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Debut With Mets, Hernández Keeps Marlins Off Balance</title>
    <meta content="29mets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/29/sports/baseball/29mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1765275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida Marlins</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shpigel, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Florida Marlins</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hernandez, Orlando</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E7DD1F3EF93AA15756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Debut With Mets, Hernández Keeps Marlins Off Balance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Debut With Mets, Hernández Keeps Marlins Off Balance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, May 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Florida Marlins, 7-3; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When watching Orlando Hernández pitch these days, it is convenient to block out his losing record, his high earned run average and his time spent on the disabled list, which can be measured in years, not days. The memories that endure are his hiked-up socks, his funky motion and his postseason excellence.</p>
        <p>On the surface, Hernández's first start as a Met, which entailed five ordinary innings in a 7-3 victory against the Florida Marlins, will not instill a new set of fond moments in the memory banks of the sparse crowd here or the curious viewers in the tristate area. His pitch count soared to 101, and his breaking balls often darted too much.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Orlando Hernandez allowed three runs and five hits in five innings to earn the victory in his first start as a Met.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When watching Orlando Hernández pitch these days, it is convenient to block out his losing record, his high earned run average and his time spent on the disabled list, which can be measured in years, not days. The memories that endure are his hiked-up socks, his funky motion and his postseason excellence.</p>
        <p>On the surface, Hernández's first start as a Met, which entailed five ordinary innings in a 7-3 victory against the Florida Marlins, will not instill a new set of fond moments in the memory banks of the sparse crowd here or the curious viewers in the tristate area. His pitch count soared to 101, and his breaking balls often darted too much.</p>
        <p>Rick Peterson, the Mets' pitching coach, praised Hernández afterward but graded his command as a C-minus. Hernández is now 3-4 with a 6.04 E.R.A. this season.</p>
        <p>But in battling stifling heat, a steeper-than-expected mound and a range of emotions, Hernández struck out seven, made good pitches at pivotal times and gave the Mets hope that, if he stays healthy, he could be an imposing presence in the back of the rotation.</p>
        <p>''You never see the ball too well against him,'' catcher Paul Lo Duca said. ''You just have to try to outguess him.''</p>
        <p>It did not hurt that Hernández's first at-bat as a Met came before his first pitch. The Mets batted around in the first inning, scoring four runs while preying on the Marlins' sloppy defense and inexperience; Florida committed one physical error and three or four mental ones.</p>
        <p>Carlos Beltrán let loose his range of skills. He beat out a bunt single with two runners on base and no outs to help ignite the Mets in the first inning. And he hit a two-run homer in the fourth that completed the Mets' scoring.</p>
        <p>In September, Beltrán also bunted with two runners on and no outs in a game; at the time, Manager Willie Randolph told him that he preferred he did not do that. But after Beltrán did it Sunday, Randolph praised him for his quick thinking.</p>
        <p>Beltrán said, ''We can't wait for doubles and home runs.''</p>
        <p>José Reyes added three hits and José Valentín, playing second base in place of Kazuo Matsui, went 1 for 3 with two runs batted in.</p>
        <p>Matsui, whose 4-for-39 streak over the past 12 games has dropped his batting average 52 points to .213, will platoon with Valentín or Chris Woodward until Randolph decides he has discovered his swing. Since May 16, Matsui, who is not a patient hitter to begin with, has been swinging too early in the count and from his heels.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to say it's a strict platoon,'' Randolph said. ''I'm going to find a way to match up guys that I think is best for the team. When I look at the lineup and who's pitching, I'm going to make a decision daily on what I want to do.''</p>
        <p>Matsui said through an interpreter, ''Willie did talk to me and said that when I get hot, I'll be back in the lineup.''</p>
        <p>It is unclear how Matsui will get hot if he does not play as much, but at least he will have a chance to gauge his competition every day. Randolph said he was not considering bringing up Anderson Hernández or Jeff Keppinger from Class AAA Norfolk, because Valentín and Woodward are competent fill-ins.</p>
        <p>Woodward is the better defender, although Valentín has played well in limited duty. On Sunday, he was the anti-Matsui, converting his two chances with runners in scoring position.</p>
        <p>Orlando Hernández's status is far more certain. Bothered by a back strain earlier this season, Hernández said Sunday that he felt great; the only problems he encountered were caused by external forces.</p>
        <p>He said the temperature, 89 degrees with 55 percent humidity when the game began at 1:06 p.m., was worse than what he dealt with in Arizona and sapped his energy.</p>
        <p>The mound at Dolphin Stadium is higher than the one in the bullpen and other mounds around the major leagues, so Hernández's left foot -- his plant foot -- landed later than it normally would. As a result, his breaking balls pulled wide of the strike zone. Pressure and nerves left Hernández excited and anxious before his debut.</p>
        <p>''There were a lot of fans, Mets fans and Cubans in the stadium,'' Hernández said. ''I was a little emotional.''</p>
        <p>About 12 friends, including a fellow Cuban and the former Met Rey Ordóñez, were in attendance. They watched Hernández plow through a 1-2-3 first inning. But he walked two of the first three hitters in the second, then allowed a three-run homer to Jeremy Hermida.</p>
        <p>Hernández then went 3-0 on the next hitter, Miguel Olivo, before striking him out, with Olivo waving at his signature sweeping slider. Hernández threw 39 pitches that inning.</p>
        <p>In the third, he allowed two base runners but benefited when Hanley Ramírez was caught trying to steal third. In the fourth, he allowed three singles, but picked Josh Willingham off first base. A perfect fifth, punctuated by an inning-ending strikeout of Mike Jacobs on a 91-mile-an-hour fastball, ended Hernández's afternoon and left him, his teammates and countless others eager to see what will come next.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
