<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Showdown Is Set on Bank Guarantees in Japan</title>
    <meta content="31YEN.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/31/business/worldbusiness/31YEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1412342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belson, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koizumi, Junichiro (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Koizumi, Junichiro</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6D81138F932A05754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Showdown Is Set on Bank Guarantees in Japan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Showdown Is Set on Bank Guarantees in Japan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN BELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belson, Ken</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, July 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japan's lawmakers, about to break for summer vacation, have already laid groundwork for their return in September: a battle with Prime Min Junichiro Koizumi over his pledge to remove public guarantee on large savings accounts; confrontation has potential to tie government in knots, delaying overhaul of tax code and national medical plan, as well as 2003 budget; protracted battle over Koizumi's campaign for bank reform could unnerve already jittery investors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About to break for a summer vacation, lawmakers in Japan have already laid the groundwork for their return in September: a battle with Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi over his pledge to remove the public guarantee on large savings accounts.</p>
        <p>The confrontation has the potential to tie the government in knots, delaying an overhaul of the tax code and national medical plan, as well as the 2003 budget. A protracted battle over this important plank of Mr. Koizumi's campaign for bank reform could also unnerve investors already jittery about the financial industry. That may push down stock prices, creating even more problems for the banks, which hold large equity portfolios.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawmakers in Japan are gearing up for a battle with Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi over his pledge to remove the public guarantee on large savings accounts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About to break for a summer vacation, lawmakers in Japan have already laid the groundwork for their return in September: a battle with Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi over his pledge to remove the public guarantee on large savings accounts.</p>
        <p>The confrontation has the potential to tie the government in knots, delaying an overhaul of the tax code and national medical plan, as well as the 2003 budget. A protracted battle over this important plank of Mr. Koizumi's campaign for bank reform could also unnerve investors already jittery about the financial industry. That may push down stock prices, creating even more problems for the banks, which hold large equity portfolios.</p>
        <p>The looming fight is characteristic of other battles Mr. Koizumi has faced during his 15-month tenure. Hard-liners from within his own Liberal Democratic Party have opposed nearly every one of his moves to overhaul the economy. These conservatives are eager to protect small businesses, construction companies and regional banks, all groups that form the core of the party's power base.</p>
        <p>At issue this time is Mr. Koizumi's plan to remove the blanket guarantee on ordinary savings accounts starting April 1, 2003. Afterward, the government would guarantee only savings of as much as 10 million yen ($83,500) for every account if a bank fails. The step was delayed two years ago because lawmakers feared it would lead to bank runs and financial chaos.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koizumi and financial regulators have vowed to follow through with the plan, which they say will make the banking industry more market oriented. Right on cue, however, several conservative Liberal Democratic legislators have moved to oppose him. On Monday, a group led by Hiroyuki Aizawa, chairman of the antideflation panel for the party, said that it would ask Mr. Koizumi to delay the removal of the guarantee.</p>
        <p>Backers of Mr. Aizawa argue that removing the full guarantee will push savers to shift their money from banks they perceive as weak to larger, more stable institutions. This in fact happened earlier this year when the government limited the guarantee on fixed-term accounts. In the period before that change in April, trillions of yen were moved from small banks to the nation's biggest banks, the post office or in cash. The changes helped destroy more than four dozen credit unions and at least one regional bank.</p>
        <p>Eager to streamline Japan's crowded financial industry, Mr. Koizumi and his top bank regulator, Hakuo Yanagisawa, have stood by as the small banks failed. To realign the industry further, they have proposed a series of tax breaks and other incentives including the possible use of tax revenues to encourage small banks to merge. Mr. Koizumi hopes these steps reassure investors without triggering a crisis.</p>
        <p>Brian Waterhouse, a bank analyst with HSBC Securities in Tokyo, said, ''The last thing the authorities want is a panic rush of deposit withdrawals from the weakest banks, which would trigger the very Japanese banking crisis the authorities have insisted all along doesn't exist.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Koizumi has done a delicate dance with investors, trying to persuade them the banking system is sound despite growing numbers of defaulted loans and shrinking profits. If he were to retreat and extend the full guarantee on savings, investors might assume the government knew that the banks were too weak to stand on their own, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Still, the prime minister may be forced to bargain with his rivals. His support remains wobbly and he faces pressure to reshuffle his cabinet in September.</p>
        <p>Today, he survived a vote of no confidence in the parliament, which adjourns on Wednesday until September.</p>
        <p>As a compromise, the two sides may consider several alternatives. Some suggest doubling the government guarantee to 20 million yen ($167,000) or keeping the full guarantee in place for small companies and other businesses that maintain large balances. Reaching an agreement, though, may consume large amounts of Mr. Koizumi's political capital and take months.</p>
        <p>By then, investors may once again have lost faith in the government and doubt the health of the financial industry. That could send bank shares spiraling downward as the deadline approaches in April and push Mr. Koizumi into a corner.</p>
        <p>''If there is a crisis in February or March, the government will be forced to delay removing the guarantee,'' said Nobuyuki Harada, an economist with the Japan Center for Economic Research. ''That would make the small banks happy, but after one or two years, the same problems might surface again.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
