<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Rock; Sound and Fury Aside, Dancing Is the Point</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="501041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCERTS AND RECITALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COP SHOOT COP (BAND)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNSANE (BAND)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOETUS INC (BAND)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARELES, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D61138F93BA25752C0A964958260" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Rock; Sound and Fury Aside, Dancing Is the Point</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PARELES, JON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new format has been turning up at dance clubs in the early 1990's. Disk jockeys combine industrial rock (brutal mechanical rhythms and agonized vocals), techno (crisp electronic rhythm tracks, largely instrumental) and some alternative rock (edgy guitars and synthesizers behind ambiguous lyrics). It's a post-punk, suburban reaction to the urban dance rhythms of house music and hip-hop.</p>
        <p>The Palladium, the Macy's of New York clubs, inaugurated its new weekly Hype Alternative Radical Dance, or Hard, nights on Wednesday, reflecting the popularity of similar nights at Limelight, the Building and other clubs. Like the Limelight, the Palladium will present live bands along with recorded music. Its first Wednesday featured three bands: Cop Shoot Cop, the Unsane and Foetus Inc. With free admission before 11 P.M., the club was well attended but not packed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new format has been turning up at dance clubs in the early 1990's. Disk jockeys combine industrial rock (brutal mechanical rhythms and agonized vocals), techno (crisp electronic rhythm tracks, largely instrumental) and some alternative rock (edgy guitars and synthesizers behind ambiguous lyrics). It's a post-punk, suburban reaction to the urban dance rhythms of house music and hip-hop.</p>
        <p>The Palladium, the Macy's of New York clubs, inaugurated its new weekly Hype Alternative Radical Dance, or Hard, nights on Wednesday, reflecting the popularity of similar nights at Limelight, the Building and other clubs. Like the Limelight, the Palladium will present live bands along with recorded music. Its first Wednesday featured three bands: Cop Shoot Cop, the Unsane and Foetus Inc. With free admission before 11 P.M., the club was well attended but not packed.</p>
        <p>The three bands used live rather than canned rhythms, placing them in the alternative category. But all three showed the influence of machine-driven dance music; rhythm and texture were at the center of the songs.</p>
        <p>Cop Shoot Cop makes something new out of alternative rock's most caustic ingredients. As in much industrial rock, its lyrics, usually delivered in a growl, attack conformity and defy a consumer culture in which rebellion is redirected into a sales pitch; Tod A., its singer and main songwriter, urges listeners to "burn your bridges."</p>
        <p>The music is an exactly calibrated clatter that, unlike industrial rock, sounds handmade. Phil Puleo, on percussion, stands behind drums and a rack of metal sheets, tapping out pinpoint rhythms behind the band's driving, corrosive guitar and keyboard riffs.</p>
        <p>Cop Shoot Cop's dissonant clangor doesn't settle into formula. Songs shift into odd meters, hint at power chords or slip into an old-fashioned skiffle beat. And for one song, "Empires Collapse," the beat became a waltz and a woman joined the band to sing in a classical-style mezzo-soprano. There's no wasted motion in Cop Shoot Cop; every note has a place and a point. Cop Shoot Cop's message is an angry one, and the band's utter precision makes it seem doubly ferocious.</p>
        <p>Foetus Inc. is led by J. G. Thirlwell, who has had a decadelong career on the noisy edges of alternative rock. While leading his own groups, he has produced other bands and collaborated widely (with Lydia Lunch and Cop Shoot Cop, among others). His current group includes three former members of the Swans, a New York band known for its ominous drones. But while Mr. Thirlwell has made brutally effective recordings, on stage he was merely pretentious and rather old-fashioned. Amid smoke-machine smoke and strobe lights, he growled and ranted above the band's hard-rock riffs and predictable crescendos. In a salute to the roots of industrial rock, Foetus opened its set with a recording of Steve Reich's tape-loop piece "It's Gonna Rain," occasionally adding salvos of drums.</p>
        <p>The Unsane are propelled by the drumming of Charlie Ondras, who pounds out fast, intricate, unswerving patterns behind Chris Spencer's wash of guitar chords and Pete Shore's basslines. The singing, mostly by Mr. Spencer, is a welter of distorted exhortations, adding to the sound and fury, but the band's momentum is more memorable than its songs. Its set at the Palladium ended with an interloper taking over the microphone, hurling imprecations and starting an anarchistic rant. But the audience had come to dance, not to rebel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
