<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports Injuries to the Young Are Up Sharply, Doctors Say</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="566205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPORTS MEDICINE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, ELISABETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D8103DF93BA15753C1A964958260" item-length="1534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports Injuries to the Young Are Up Sharply, Doctors Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, ELISABETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ADULTS recall childhood as an endless blur of running and jumping, full of little cuts and bruises, but blissfully free of those nagging injuries that follow exercise later in life -- tendinitis, bursitis and stress fractures.</p>
        <p>Now, however, orthopedists and pediatricians say these injuries are cropping up with alarming frequency in children: from stress fractures of the lower spine in young gymnasts to shoulder tendinitis in swimmers to shin splints in aspiring marathoners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ADULTS recall childhood as an endless blur of running and jumping, full of little cuts and bruises, but blissfully free of those nagging injuries that follow exercise later in life -- tendinitis, bursitis and stress fractures.</p>
        <p>Now, however, orthopedists and pediatricians say these injuries are cropping up with alarming frequency in children: from stress fractures of the lower spine in young gymnasts to shoulder tendinitis in swimmers to shin splints in aspiring marathoners.</p>
        <p>"People are suddenly recognizing that it's a problem," said Dr. Carl L. Stanitski, chief of orthopedic surgery at the Children's Hospital of Michigan in Detroit. "We are seeing more and more stress fractures in children and more and more injuries cause by repetitive use."</p>
        <p>They attribute the rise in such so-called overuse injuries to intensive sports training programs for young children, longer playing seasons and specialty sports camps in which children may spend hours lobbing balls on a tennis court or throwing hundreds of pitches each day. Improved Diagnoses</p>
        <p>In addition, doctors say they are now identifying injuries that in the past might have been ignored.</p>
        <p>"In my practice overuse injuries are much more common than acute injuries, like lacerations and broken bones," said Dr. Gregory L. Landry, a staff pediatrician at the University of Wisconsin Sports Medicine Clinic. "Part of that may be we're getting better at diagnosing these things in kids. In the past, pediatricians did not expect these syndromes in children, so they overlooked the diagnosis or called them growing pains."</p>
        <p>Although overuse injuries generally respond well to rest, if ignored they can cause major problems. "If you stop early in the evolution of these injuries, they just heal," said Dr. Barry Goldberg, director of Sports Medicine at Yale University Health Services. "On the other hand, if kids are caught in an environment where there is pressure to throw through the pain or tough it out, these injuries tend to progress to chronic injury, sometimes lifelong disability, which is really a crime."</p>
        <p>Experts say children are particularly prone to injury from intensive sports. The quality of their equipment and coaching is often not on par with the athletic demands. And children's immature bones have soft areas that are common sites of injury.</p>
        <p>"The most ill-equipped athlete in America is a third-string middle-school football player, who's running his heart out on an adult-size field, wearing a hand-me-down helmet and shoulder pads," Dr. Stanitski said. To prevent overuse injuries, he and others have advocated that young children should play on smaller fields, using smaller, lighter balls that are proportioned to their size.</p>
        <p>Dr. Landry said that at the start of the school soccer season each fall he sees an epidemic of heel pain caused by tendinitis. He said poorly designed shoes were partly to blame.</p>
        <p>"Soccer shoes for children have not caught up with the rest of the sports shoe industry," said Dr. David Bernhardt, a sports medicine fellow at the University of Wisconsin. "They don't provide enough support."</p>
        <p>All too often children's coaches, who are often volunteers and rarely have formal training, drill children the way "some troglodyte coached them in high school or college," Dr. Stanitski said. They also do not teach proper techniques, which puts excess stresses on young bodies.</p>
        <p>"In Little League the coach takes the biggest, strongest kid and says, 'You're the pitcher,' " Dr. Stanitski said. "And he throws with his arm, not using his leg or his body as real pitchers do. Until someone shows that kid how to pitch, he's a setup for overuse problems." Young baseball players may suffer from tendinitis of the shoulder and elbow, he said, as well as bursitis, an inflammation of a fluid-filled cushion in the shoulder. In severe cases, these injuries can lead to severe arthritis by the late teen-age years and the end of a career before it has truly started.</p>
        <p>Some overuse injuries in pre-adolescents are peculiar to children, occurring at the attachment of tendon to bone, a particularly weak junction in the young. Before puberty, the bone beneath these sites is soft, more like a gristle, and vulnerable to microscopic fractures and inflammation.</p>
        <p>The heel pain that afflicts children in running sports like soccer, called Sever's disease, is caused by irritation where the Achilles' tendon from the calf attaches to a bone in the foot. Osgood Schlatter disease, a type of knee pain that plagues children in sports like basketball, is from inflammation at a similar junction in the knee.</p>
        <p>But many injuries are identical to those seen in adults. Nicole Clausen, a 15-year-old cross-country runner from Detroit, has a stress fracture of her shinbone, or tibia, a common running injury sometimes called shin splints.</p>
        <p>In children, overuse injuries occur most often at the start of the season, when bodies are out of shape, or at its peak, when they are bearing the maximum forces they can tolerate.</p>
        <p>Regular exercise causes microscopic trauma to tissue, which generally heals during the hours or days of rest in between. As long as the body is given adequate time to repair itself, the person builds up muscle and becomes better conditioned. But when a child exceeds the body's ability to heal the damage, doing too much, too fast, the tissue starts to break down and overuse injury occurs.</p>
        <p>Experts say that sports camps can breed such problems. "Children go from a relatively low activity state to very intense athletic experience," Dr. Landry said. "I see a fair number of children in my practice who develop overuse syndromes because they did not adequately prepare for the intensity of the camp."</p>
        <p>For other children who turn up in doctors' offices with overuse injuries, the problem is that the season never ends. Traditionally, athletic children played a variety of sports, moving from soccer to basketball to baseball as the seasons changed. Today there are more children who focus on one sport all year round, stressing the same bones, tendons and joints over and over again, Dr. Bernhardt said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stanitski told of one young man who played hockey in the winter, roller blade hockey in the warmer months, and ended up with a tendon injury in his heel after attending hockey camp in the fall.</p>
        <p>Doctors advise that athletic children be evaluated for an overuse injury if they complain of continuing localized pain that is worse with motion and severe enough to limit general activity or full participation their sport.</p>
        <p>Acknowledging that few young athletes are content to sit on the sidelines, doctors treat childhood stress injuries by having children reduce the intensity of their activity, a concept they call relative rest.</p>
        <p>"If you tell a 10-year-old he can't play, he'll say 'yea, right,' so instead of practicing seven days a week tell him to do three," Dr. Stanitski said. "Or instead of crouching behind home plate, have him play second base or, God forbid, right field."</p>
        <p>During the period of rest, exercise is prescribed to strengthen the muscles in the vulnerable limb. A biomechanical evaluation may show that a shoe is not providing support or a pitching arm is being used awkwardly. Once the pain subsides, children undertake progressively more activity until they are going full steam.</p>
        <p>To prevent overuse injuries doctors, say that children should use properly sized equipment and be coached with a tender hand. A 9-year-old who complains of pain should be listened to, not berated for being a sissy and sent back into the game.</p>
        <p>"We are trying to get coaches to understand what injury from overuse is," Dr. Stanitski said. "They can understand a broken bone going in nine different directions, but not a kid who hasn't fallen coming to the sidelines and saying, 'my shoulder hurts.' " Training for Coaches</p>
        <p>The American Academy of Pediatrics in Elk Grove Village, Ill., recommends that children's coaches complete a certification program that covers basic sports skills, teaching techniques, fitness and first aid.</p>
        <p>Some children's sports organizations have rules intended to curb the abuses that lead to overuse injuries. Little League Baseball now limits pitchers to six innings a week.</p>
        <p>Sports medicine specialists are reluctant to fix an absolute minimum age for participation in any sport, but caution against very structured or competitive programs. In this weekend's New York City Marathon there will certainly be a few young runners, a practice that sports medicine specialists do not condone but will not condemn, either.</p>
        <p>"I don't have any big problems with children doing long-distance running as long as they are allowed to quit when they want to quit," Dr. Landry said. "Most children do not get hurt in any sport until there are external forces to continue."</p>
        <p>And, though he is seeing more overuse injuries in children, he tries to keep the problem in perspective.</p>
        <p>"There are many people who are concerned that we have a small group of children who exercise too much and are pushing their bodies over the limit," he said. "But we also have a very large group of children who are not getting enough physical activity."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
