<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="689808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3D8173BF934A15756C0A962958260" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>President Clinton renewed China's favored trade status and said he would no longer use trade to force China to improve human rights.  [ Page A1. ]  With the decision, economic interests won over America's self-image as the world's human rights advocate.  [ A1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>President Clinton renewed China's favored trade status and said he would no longer use trade to force China to improve human rights.  [ Page A1. ]  With the decision, economic interests won over America's self-image as the world's human rights advocate.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>American companies say they are relieved that President Clinton has decided to keep China in the family of America's most favored trading nations. China, it seems, has become the fastest-growing market for some companies.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The Justice Department settled an antitrust suit with a British glassmaker, preventing it from blocking American companies from doing business overseas. Japan, regarded as a possible target of similar suits, vigorously denounced the tactic.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>A senior Japanese cabinet official acknowledged that companies throughout the country had denied job opportunities to women during that country's four-year economic downturn.  [ A9. ]</p>
        <p>A deal has been completed to rescue the company that operates the tunnel between England and France.  [ D4. ] Companies</p>
        <p>Carter Hawley Hale has the potential to stage a remarkable turnaround, or it could fall back into bankruptcy.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>CBS Broadcast Group's president said the network would replace the stations that defected to Fox Broadcasting.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Digital Equipment's chief financial officer resigned and will be replaced by the company's controller.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Representative Jack Brooks said he would introduce a bill to modify the law that exempts insurers from antitrust rules.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>The software maker Computer Associates stunned Wall Street by posting higher than expected sales and earnings for its fiscal year and fourth quarter.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>The parent of Western Union Financial Services has spurned a $430 million offer by the First Data Corporation.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Shares of Boeing Company rose $2.50, to $47, after a published report said the company was about to receive a $5 billion order for more than 50 jetliners from China.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>A battery-powered Geo Metro has driven 214 miles without a recharge. The car runs on nickel metal hydride batteries, which are more often found in laptop computers.  [ D4. ] Markets</p>
        <p>Mutual fund investors seem less alarmed about interest rates, and withdrawals from bond funds have slowed. But there are only limited indications that they are willing to risk more cash.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities were mixed, with the long bond bouncing up and down before ending lower.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>Stocks barely moved as traders headed into the Memorial Day weekend, but a few market leaders, like Philip Morris and Boeing, showed sharp swings. The Dow fell 1.84 points, to 3,753.46.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar finished mostly higher in global foreign exchange trading, aided by a technical rally that reversed a downward slide early in the day.  [ D16. ]</p>
        <p>Coffee prices continued to slide, and an index of 21 commodities retreated for the third consecutive day after reaching a three-and-a-half-year high on Monday.  [ D16. ] The Economy</p>
        <p>A bill was introduced in the House of Representatives to tighten the supervision of the derivatives activities of banks.  [ D5. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>A group of investors is betting that Stone &amp; Webster, the engineering company that builds nuclear power plants, is poised for a turnaround. Market Place.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>Three longtime creative executives are forming a new advertising agency that they said would promulgate what they call "black and blue advertising." Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D17. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
