<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Here's the Hook: Gifts For Online Bill Payers</title>
    <meta content="28BILLS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="SundayBusiness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1630562"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY MONEY: SPENDING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Identity Fraud</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">alsever, jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identity Fraud</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4D9123EF93BA15752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Here's the Hook: Gifts For Online Bill Payers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER ALSEVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">alsever, jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on growing popularity of electronic payments, in form of automatic charges to credit card, debits from checking account or direct payments online, for every manner of goods and services; many businesses offer incentives to encourage customers to use automated payments; company can save billions of dollars by not having to send out and then process bills; it can also better control how and when it is paid; for many consumers, fear of identity theft keeps them from signing up for automatic payments; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PSST. Interested in 10 free music downloads online? Or how about a Target gift card or a discount on your cable television bill?</p>
        <p>They might all be yours if you quit writing checks and choose to have your bills paid automatically from your checking or credit card accounts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PSST. Interested in 10 free music downloads online? Or how about a Target gift card or a discount on your cable television bill?</p>
        <p>They might all be yours if you quit writing checks and choose to have your bills paid automatically from your checking or credit card accounts.</p>
        <p>More businesses -- from cellphone services to newspapers to mortgage lenders -- are realizing the financial benefits of electronic payments. Now they are out to convert those die-hard check writers to electronic billing by offering perks, lower interest rates or discounted prices.</p>
        <p>The stakes for businesses are huge. ''Depending on the company, there's a potential to shave millions of dollars off of their current processes,'' said Rene Tidwell, bill-pay manager at the J.P. Morgan Chase division that processes credit cards.</p>
        <p>Electronic payments, in the form of automatic charges to a credit card, debits from a checking account or direct payments online, are growing in popularity for services from lawn service to milk delivery. In 2003, consumers paid an estimated three billion bills through automatic bank-account debits alone. And the National Automated Clearinghouse Association, a nonprofit rulemaking group for electronic payments, expects that number to rise 12 percent this year.</p>
        <p>Check writers, of course, still prevail. Consumers paid 8 billion to 10 billion bills using paper checks last year, the association said.</p>
        <p>''People are using their credit cards and debit cards for point-of-sale purchases, but when it comes to signing up for automatic payments, there's a little bit of hesitancy,'' Ms. Tidwell said. Many people fear identity theft or fraud -- or that they will lose track of their finances.</p>
        <p>So out go the lures, with the hope that consumers bite hard. The San Francisco Chronicle recently ran an advertisement promising users of its automatic bill pay program 10 free music downloads from iTunes.com. The Chicago Tribune's latest giveaway was a $5 gift card to Target.</p>
        <p>People who sign up for electronic payments for health care coverage from AARP get discounted rates. Cox Communications, the cable television provider, offers various incentives, depending on the region: movies that are otherwise pay-per-view, as well as discounted monthly rates, American Express gift certificates and a chance to win a high-definition television.</p>
        <p>If it weren't for such incentives, some consumers would never sign up.</p>
        <p>''I don't like to give my bank account information out, and I don't give it much thought until someone says I can save a buck or two,'' said Lisa Taraschi, 36. Ms. Taraschi, a Denver real estate agent, prefers paper checks, and she worries that by using electronic payments she will lose track of her finances or be a victim of fraud.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taraschi agreed to automatic payments when Washington Mutual gave her a better interest rate on her mortgage because she signed up for bill pay service. She also lets Brink's Home Security take its payment monthly from her account, because she receives $1 off each $27 bill. ''There has to be an incentive for me,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The same goes for Becca Kornfeld. Ms. Kornfeld, 30, a public relations manager in New York, was reluctant to let anyone withdraw payments from her account. But when the federal Education Department offered a better interest rate on her student loan -- 3.92 percent instead of 4.17 percent -- she agreed to use automatic payments.</p>
        <p>Some consumers, however, have horror stories about automatic debit gone awry.</p>
        <p>''I get a lot of complaints from consumers who say, 'I authorized them to take out one payment, but they're taking it out every month,''' said Mark Budnitz, a law professor who teaches courses on electronic payment systems at Georgia State University's College of Law. ''Or they say, 'I told them to stop, and they're not stopping.' Or, 'they're taking out more than they're supposed to, and I can't get them to stop.'''</p>
        <p>Professor Budnitz said that there were ''a lot of benefits to society when it's all electronic'' but that there were also costs. ''People are going to have to pay when things go wrong,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Yet the electronic future is inevitable, he said. A federal law that went into effect in October lets banks process more checks electronically, avoiding a need to deliver paper checks to one another. In addition, a growing number of businesses, like Netflix, the movie rental company, and Vonage, the broadband phone provider, now require customers to use automatic bill pay.</p>
        <p>Businesses have good reason for heading in that direction. Some companies can cut their billing costs by more than half if they do not have to process and mail bills and collect paper payments, according to research by Gartner Inc., the research firm in Stamford, Conn. Last year, Gartner surveyed 140 companies that send out 1.92 million bills a month, on average, and found that they could save $15 million a year by billing electronically. Companies prefer debiting of checking accounts to credit card accounts because the transaction fees on bank accounts are lower -- 50 cents a transaction, on average, versus 2 percent of the amount of the payment for credit cards.</p>
        <p>By using automated payments, a company can better control how and when it is paid. It can guarantee that customers will pay on time, and it can more accurately predict the flow of cash and liquidity.</p>
        <p>The biggest challenge to getting that cash flow may be gaining the trust of people like Karen Garvey, a journalist from Denver. She said she had several bad experiences with automatic payments. While living in Texas several years ago, two automatic monthly debits kept going long after she requested in writing that they stop. And in Colorado, she said, her gym started taking membership dues from her account every month, though she never authorized it. She said the gym apologized.</p>
        <p>Today, she avoids automatic payment options. ''Never again,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Dawn Cabral, a public relations executive in Stamford, Conn., had a similar experience with a gym membership. ''The amount that they debit is different than the amount they originally told me, so I am nervous every month that they're going to take out more than they should,'' she said in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>Stopping an automatic debit often requires visiting a bank and filling out paperwork. Consumers should check bank statements regularly and report errors to the bank immediately. If a consumer complains that a company took out too much money, took out money too often or is taking funds without authorization, the bank must investigate, by law. If the bank cannot figure out within 10 days who is in the wrong, it must restore the money to the account until the matter is settled.</p>
        <p>FEAR of fraud and identity theft also keep some people from the electronic frontier, said Michael Herd, a spokesman for the clearinghouse association. ''We have to overcome those perceptions'' that electronic debit is dangerous, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Herd said checks dropped into a mailbox put a person at more risk than electronic payments. Those checks, marked with a person's name, address, phone number and account number, can be stolen or handled by more people than an electronic payment, he said. He asserts that electronic payments are safe and accurate.</p>
        <p>Richard Hunter disagrees. A research director at Gartner Inc. and author of the book ''World Without Secrets,'' Mr. Hunter said consumers should be cautious when signing up for automatic debit.</p>
        <p>''It's very true that ID theft is carried out through the mail,'' he said, but he added that personal information is also vulnerable if it is sitting in a computer database or, perhaps, on a printed spreadsheet on a desk in an office. As more information is collected and put into databases, he said, the data is more at risk of being stolen or abused. He said government reports show that company insiders commit as many as 70 percent of cybercrimes that involve financial loss.</p>
        <p>A small business may not have much experience in handling personal information stored on a computer or in protecting databases from hackers or crooked employees. Consumers are advised to research any company before giving out private banking information.</p>
        <p>''The first question people should consider is, 'Do I trust this company?''' Mr. Hunter said. ''Don't give just anyone your information just because they ask for it.''</p>
        <p>QUICK READ  You can almost scrap your checkbook when paying bills these days. But here is what financial experts say you should consider before signing up for automatic payments:</p>
        <p>CHECK OUT the company before giving it access to your account information. Make sure the company is easy to reach if something goes wrong.</p>
        <p>KEEP careful track of expenses to avoid overdraft fees and expensive line-of-credit charges. Payments billed to credit cards can add up quickly if you don't pay off balances each month.</p>
        <p>CHECK statements for errors, and report any to the bank immediately. By law, a bank must investigate any dispute. If it cannot figure out within 10 days who is in the wrong, it must restore the money until the dispute is resolved.</p>
        <p>MARK your calendar to make sure that payments were withdrawn on schedule. Check your credit report, too, to ensure that any payments not withdrawn were not reported as delinquent.</p>
        <p>ADJUST bill payment dates if your employer changes its payday or if you change jobs, so that there is always enough money in your account to cover withdrawals.</p>
        <p>ASK FOR a ''switch kit'' if you change banks. Often, banks will handle the paperwork to switch automatic payments to your new account.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MONEY: SPENDING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
