<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is the Junk Bond Market Ready to Catch Its Breath?</title>
    <meta content="28PORT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="SundayBusiness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/28/business/yourmoney/28port.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1630564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="PORTFOLIOS, ETC."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Portfolios Etc</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Reserve System</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4D9123EF93BA15752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is the Junk Bond Market Ready to Catch Its Breath?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Is the Junk Bond Market Ready to Catch Its Breath?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Portfolios, etc, column on current exuberance of new-issue market for junk bonds and disturbing signs that sector may be in for correction in next several months; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is time to take a break from the junk bond market, which is overheating as companies rush to lock in surprisingly low interest rates before the Federal Reserve pushes them any higher.</p>
        <p>Institutional and individual investors, through mutual funds, have been snapping up billions of dollars of new issues recently. But their big appetites are likely to result in bouts of indigestion in the months ahead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is time to take a break from the junk bond market, which is overheating as companies rush to lock in surprisingly low interest rates before the Federal Reserve pushes them any higher.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is time to take a break from the junk bond market, which is overheating as companies rush to lock in surprisingly low interest rates before the Federal Reserve pushes them any higher.</p>
        <p>Institutional and individual investors, through mutual funds, have been snapping up billions of dollars of new issues recently. But their big appetites are likely to result in bouts of indigestion in the months ahead.</p>
        <p>Since June, individual investors have poured $4.6 billion into junk bond mutual funds, also known as high-yield funds, after pulling out $10.8 billion from February through May, according to AMG Data Services. And institutional investors have been running even faster after the securities, analysts said. At the current pace, the junk bond market should set an annual record for new issuance, topping the $128.1 billion of last year.</p>
        <p>But the prices that investors have paid are high and the yields they have been offered are relatively low, according to Kingman D. Penniman, president of KDP Investment Advisors, a high-yield bond research firm in Montpelier, Vt.</p>
        <p>The new offering last Monday from Wynn Las Vegas, a resort and casino scheduled to open in the spring, offers an example of the deals that investors are accepting in the hothouse atmosphere of junk bonds, Mr. Penniman said.</p>
        <p>In an analysis the Thursday before the sale, KDP said it would be ''comfortable buying this issue'' if the yield was in the range of 7 to 8.5 percent. Mr. Penniman said he would put the credit rating on the Wynn Las Vegas bonds at B or B-, although Standard &amp; Poor's rated them B+.</p>
        <p>By the time the deal was done, the $1.3 billion issue, up from a scheduled $1.1 billion, was priced to yield 6.625 percent, below the low end of KDP's comfort range.</p>
        <p>''That is an indication of how frothy the new-issue market is,'' Mr. Penniman said. ''Some time down the road people will be unhappy that they bought this,'' he said of the new Wynn Las Vegas bonds and other overpriced new issues with relatively low yields he has seen recently. But, he added, there is just too much money demanding junk bond returns.</p>
        <p>Froth in the new-issue market, however, does not mean that investors should abandon high-yield bonds. It means that investors just need to be cautious right now. Junk bonds are still likely to be a place to be next year for those who want to keep money in the bond market. When interest rates are rising, the higher yields provided by junk bonds can offset the concurrent decline in bond prices. Through Friday, the total 2004 return for the junk bond market was 9.4 percent, according to Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Penniman predicts that junk bonds will return a ''solid single digit'' next year. He is assuming that the yield on the Treasury's 10-year note will rise somewhere between 0.75 to 1.5 percentage points. That increase would reduce bond prices. But with an average yield of about 8 percent on junk bonds, the total return could still be around 5 percent.</p>
        <p>The current exuberance of the new-issue market, however, suggests that the junk bond sector may be in for a correction in the next several months. Another disturbing signal is that the spread, or difference, between the average yield on KDP's junk bond index and the yield on the Treasury's 10-year note is now at its narrowest point since the KDP index began in 1990.</p>
        <p>This spread, which had been shrinking all month, slipped to 2.20 percentage points on Friday. Before this month, the weekly low was 2.49 points, in the week ended Jan. 23 this year.</p>
        <p>The high-yield market began a selloff at that point, resulting in a loss of 2.8 percent by the end of May. Most of that loss came in May, as interest rates soared after the surprisingly strong employment reports for March and April. So an especially tight spread can be a warning sign, and right now that means investors who have not been chasing junk bonds should stay on the sidelines, while those who have been in the market should pause. ''You should be sitting on your hands,'' he said.</p>
        <p>CONSIDER two big junk bond rallies that produced years of double-digit returns -- the first from 1990 through 1993, and the second from 1995 through 1997. In each run, historically low spreads in the third year seemed to signal (in hindsight, of course) that the end was near. Junk bonds lost 1 percent in the year after the first rally and eked out a return of just 2.6 percent in the entire five years after the second rally, according to Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>As of Friday, junk bonds appeared to be on track to a double-digit return this year, meaning that 2005 could be the third year in a row for such gains.</p>
        <p>But, as Mr. Penniman said, ''I would not be chasing the market on the basis of a 10 percent return this year and expecting to get that next year.''</p>
        <p>PORTFOLIOS, ETC.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
