<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Make Jordan Wait After Not Signing Guillen</title>
    <meta content="17METS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/17/sports/baseball/17METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1543844"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anaheim Angels</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jordan, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guillen, Jose</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jordan, Brian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEEDE1F3CF934A25751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Make Jordan Wait After Not Signing Guillen</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets Make Jordan Wait After Not Signing Guillen</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets postpone meeting with outfielder Brian Jordan after failing to sign outfielder Jose Guillen, who just signed with Anaheim Angels; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jose Guillen will be playing right field for a new team, but it will not be the Mets. Brian Jordan would like to find a new team, but the Mets are keeping him in limbo.</p>
        <p>The Mets postponed a meeting yesterday with Jordan, the free-agent outfielder, when they became optimistic about their chances to sign Guillen. But later in the day, Guillen, who hit a combined .311 with 31 home runs for the Reds and the A's last season, announced from the Dominican Republic that he had agreed to a deal with the Anaheim Angels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jose Guillen will be playing for a new team, but it will not be the Mets. Brian Jordan would like to find a new team, but the Mets are keeping him in limbo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jose Guillen will be playing right field for a new team, but it will not be the Mets. Brian Jordan would like to find a new team, but the Mets are keeping him in limbo.</p>
        <p>The Mets postponed a meeting yesterday with Jordan, the free-agent outfielder, when they became optimistic about their chances to sign Guillen. But later in the day, Guillen, who hit a combined .311 with 31 home runs for the Reds and the A's last season, announced from the Dominican Republic that he had agreed to a deal with the Anaheim Angels.</p>
        <p>''I'm very happy,'' Guillen told The Associated Press. ''I wanted a contract guaranteeing several years with one team, and that's the most important thing. I'm thrilled to be part of the Angels, a team that won the World Series just a year ago.''</p>
        <p>Guillen agreed to a two-year contract that will pay him about $6.7 million and includes a team option for a third season, two people involved in the negotiations said. The Mets added a vesting option to their one-year, $3 million offer that could have paid Guillen up to $6.5 million, but they were unwilling to guarantee the second year.</p>
        <p>Apparent changes in Guillen's representation had complicated negotiations, with Adam Katz negotiating the deal with Anaheim but Gregg Clifton having spoken to the Mets on Guillen's behalf.</p>
        <p>Katz, who is still listed with the players' union as Guillen's official representative, said he had no evidence that Guillen had switched agents and said he spoke with Guillen yesterday morning as part of negotiations. Katz completed negotiations with Anaheim. The Star-Ledger of Newark first reported the complications involving two agents yesterday.</p>
        <p>Guillen's decision may rekindle the Mets' interest in Jordan, who has feasted on their pitching, especially when he was with the Braves. But the Mets had not contacted his agent, Jim Turner, as of late yesterday. One person familiar with the discussions said the Mets were not close to finding a right fielder.</p>
        <p>Weeks ago, Jordan had Turner convey his interest to the Mets, who courted him aggressively after the 1998 season, when he played for the St. Louis Cardinals. Jordan went on to play three years for the Braves, then joined the Dodgers, but missed the second half of last season after having knee surgery. He rescheduled a medical examination from Monday to tomorrow so he could meet the Mets in New York, Turner said. But the Mets had not made an offer to him.</p>
        <p>The Mets still have Roger Cede単o, but they do not plan on his being more than an extra outfielder next season. They discussed trading Cede単o with the Mariners, the Padres and the White Sox at baseball's annual winter meetings, which concluded Monday.</p>
        <p>The Mets have signed two premier free agents, the Japanese shortstop Kazuo Matsui and the Gold Glove center fielder Mike Cameron, but have been unable to shed Cede単o's contract, which pays him $5 million each of the next two seasons.</p>
        <p>The Mariners have similarly been trying to trade Jeff Cirillo, who will earn $15 million over the next two years, and discussed a swap of bloated salaries with the Mets, who would use Cirillo as a utility infielder.</p>
        <p>The Mets have considered the possibility of acquiring closer Billy Koch from the White Sox, who asked for David Weathers earlier this off-season.</p>
        <p>Trading Cede単o to the Padres would fill two voids. It could bring back the former Mets prospect Terrence Long to play right field and the right-hander Kevin Jarvis for the fifth spot in the rotation. But Long and Jarvis are guaranteed a combined $12.85 million over the next two years.</p>
        <p>The Mets have also spoken with the Red Sox about closer Scott Williamson and with the Mariners about pitcher Freddy Garcia.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
