<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taiwan Passes 2 Resolutions Asking China to Remove Missiles</title>
    <meta content="Y17TAI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1543832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Taiwan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lu, Annette (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen Shui-Bian (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EEDF1F3CF934A25751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taiwan Passes 2 Resolutions Asking China to Remove Missiles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>HONG KONG, Wednesday, Dec. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Taiwan's legislature approves two separate resolutions calling on China to remove nearly 500 missiles pointed at island; Vice Pres Annette Lu calls missiles 'state-sponsored terrorism;' China responds, holding it must make necessary preparations to crush any move toward independence; many Taiwanese politicians are unwilling to back away from confrontation as presidential elections near; party of Pres Chen Shui-bian tends to do better at polls when tensions with China are highest (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Taiwan's national legislature approved two separate resolutions on Tuesday that call on China to remove nearly 500 missiles pointed at the island, as Taiwan's vice president described the missiles as ''state-sponsored terrorism.''</p>
        <p>The resolutions and the comments by Vice President Annette Lu drew a quick response from Beijing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Taiwan's national legislature approved two separate resolutions on Tuesday that call on China to remove nearly 500 missiles pointed at the island, as Taiwan's vice president described the missiles as ''state-sponsored terrorism.''</p>
        <p>The resolutions and the comments by Vice President Annette Lu drew a quick response from Beijing.</p>
        <p>China ''must make necessary preparations'' to crush any attempt toward independence, Li Weiyi, a spokesman for the cabinet's office of Taiwan affairs, told reporters, according to Reuters.</p>
        <p>With closely fought presidential elections set for March, many Taiwanese politicians are unwilling to back away from confronting China.</p>
        <p>When Prime Minister Wen Jiabao of China visited Washington last week, President Bush called for President Chen Shui-bian of Taiwan to stop raising tensions in the Taiwan Strait. But Mr. Chen has been defiant, insisting at campaign rallies and in interviews that he will go ahead with plans to hold a national referendum on Election Day that will demand China's removal of the missiles and a Chinese renunciation of the use of force against the island.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chen's Democratic Progressive Party has long leaned toward more formal independence for Taiwan from the mainland, and it has tended to do better at the polls when tensions with the mainland are highest. The opposition Nationalist Party favors eventual political reunification with the mainland and usually fares badly when people in Taiwan are especially upset with Beijing.</p>
        <p>In an interview with Reuters on Tuesday, Ms. Lu said that China's ''deployment of missiles is a kind of state-sponsored terrorism.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry responded at a routine briefing, saying the comments were ''unreasonable'' and that ''China's using armed force to protect national sovereignty and territorial integrity is totally different.'' The stronger official comments came later.</p>
        <p>The Nationalist Party introduced the first of the two resolutions on Tuesday. It called for China not to deploy any more missiles and to gradually remove the current ones.</p>
        <p>The party's chairman and presidential candidate, Lien Chan, said on Dec. 5 in an interview that the resolution represented an alternative to President Chen's plans to hold a national referendum to seek the removal of the missiles. Mr. Lien said that since China had been building up its missile batteries across the Taiwan Strait for years, those missiles did not pose a ''clear and present danger'' that would justify holding the referendum.</p>
        <p>The Democratic Progressive Party responded in the legislature with a resolution calling on China to remove the missiles immediately.</p>
        <p>With the parties unable to compromise on the wording, both passed.</p>
        <p>The chief spokesman for President Chen, James Huang, said Wednesday that the passage of the resolutions was not enough, unless the votes prompted China to comply, an action that experts agree is very unlikely.</p>
        <p>On Dec. 5, when President Chen announced plans for the referendum, he said that he would proceed with the voting unless China removed the missiles and renounced the use of force before March 20, and that remains his position, Mr. Huang said.</p>
        <p>Referring to the mainland by its legal name, the People's Republic of China, Mr. Huang said, ''The key point is the reaction of the P.R.C. in terms of the missile deployment and the arms buildup against Taiwan.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
