<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's County vs. Mayor</title>
    <meta content="04NJHOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1571497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="GOVERNMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bergen County (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hackensack (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6DF1239F937A35757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1449" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's County vs. Mayor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <dateline>HACKENSACK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bergen County, NJ, lawmakers have decided to build permanent homeless shelter in Hackensack on county property, financing $3 million cost by issuing county bonds if they cannot win city cooperation needed to get federal and state funds; have approved $66,000 feasibility study for building for 100 people to replace trailer-like facility erected 20 years ago as temporary shelter that can house 38 people; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BERGEN COUNTY's Democratic lawmakers have decided to build a permanent homeless shelter here, whether city officials like it or not.</p>
        <p>Over the years, aborted plans and arguments have characterized discussions between Hackensack and the county on how best to deal with the growing homeless population. The cooperation of city officials has always been necessary for the construction of a homeless shelter to get federal and state funds. But county officials now say that such construction at an estimated cost of $3 million could be financed by issuing county bonds, and they are willing to go it alone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BERGEN COUNTY's Democratic lawmakers have decided to build a permanent homeless shelter here, whether city officials like it or not.</p>
        <p>Over the years, aborted plans and arguments have characterized discussions between Hackensack and the county on how best to deal with the growing homeless population. The cooperation of city officials has always been necessary for the construction of a homeless shelter to get federal and state funds. But county officials now say that such construction at an estimated cost of $3 million could be financed by issuing county bonds, and they are willing to go it alone.</p>
        <p>An estimated 3,000 people go through the county's shelter system each year, but the city has withheld approval of a permanent shelter for a range of reasons, including a sentiment by many residents that they bear the burden of a countywide problem.</p>
        <p>Dennis McNerney, the Bergen County executive, however, is tired of waiting for Hackensack. ''I refuse to wait another day as our homeless people line our streets on freezing winter nights because some people can't decide who'll pick up the bill for a new facility,'' he said in his state of the county address last month.</p>
        <p>Mr. McNerney took office last year and is the first Democrat to hold the post. Efforts to build a shelter eluded his Republican predecessor, William P. Schuber, who suggested building one in 1998. Talks broke down after 18 months with each side blaming the other.</p>
        <p>Neither Hackensack, a city of 42,600 whose main street has struggled to compete with nearby shopping centers in Paramus even as the homeless have become a fixture, nor Bergen County, one of the most affluent counties in a state where affordable housing is scarce and housing costs high, is alone when it comes to resisting homeless shelters.</p>
        <p>As the number of homeless have increased in fast-growing Ocean County, for example, advocates for the homeless there have been trying for four years to build a full-scale homeless shelter but have gotten little support from municipal and county officials. And as property values rose in the Ironbound section of Newark, residents started petition drives against an American Rescue Workers homeless shelter, in existence on Magazine Street since the 1930's, and helped force its closing last month.</p>
        <p>Despite general opposition, the Bergen Board of Freeholders, which has a 4-3 Democratic majority, approved a $66,000 feasibility study last month for a two-story building for 100 people to replace a weathered trailer-like facility that was erected 20 years ago as a temporary shelter and now can house 38 people. Because the site on East Kansas Street and River Street near the new county administration building is county property, no city approvals would be needed, county officials said.</p>
        <p>If cost estimates bear out and the freeholders give final approval by the end of this year, as expected, the shelter could start being built in spring 2005 and in use by January 2006. The facility would also be a one-stop center for medical and mental health services, and also offer job training and treatment for alcohol and drug addiction.</p>
        <p>''There are obstacles to this proposal,'' Mr. McNerney said. ''But it should be done, because it's the right thing to do.''</p>
        <p>But Hackensack's mayor, John Zisa said he is not sure it is the right thing to do and that no county official had called to explain the plan in detail.</p>
        <p>''I hope they would consider making us part of the process,'' Mr. Zisa said, ''and bring our personnel, our human resources and police people, into their meetings so that we could have a dialogue that would be helpful and address some of the concerns we have.''</p>
        <p>In past discussions, Mr. Zisa sought to limit any new facility to 25 beds and urged that more county property be returned to the tax rolls. In a recent interview, he also suggested that the city have a role in running the facility and that it be a one-stop center that provided services as well as beds.</p>
        <p>Even though Bergen County was one of the first New Jersey counties to build a homeless shelter some 20 years ago, Mr. McNerney, in his speech said the homeless have had to ''make due with fragmented and often inadequate services while politicians debated the need for a new shelter.''</p>
        <p>Some 3,000 homeless people are housed in the system each year, said Robert F. Halsch Jr. director of the Community Action Program, a nonprofit agency that operates the Kansas Street shelter for the county and a drop-in center in a former fitness center at 67 Orchard Street, about two miles away, where the homeless can get a meal, a shower and counseling, but not a bed.</p>
        <p>Last November, the Hackensack Board of Adjustment barred C.A.P. from expanding the Orchard Street facility to 24-hour operation, but a Superior Court judge issued a restraining order that allows for a full-time operation. This past winter, the homeless were allowed to stay overnight as long as they sat up in chairs to sleep.</p>
        <p>Under the new plan, Orchard Street would close and its services be transferred to the new shelter. County and C.A.P. social workers would have offices at the shelter. Seventy-five beds would be dedicated to longer-term residents who agree to a treatment plan and look for work; the remaining 25 beds would be for emergencies.</p>
        <p>Some 100 people find emergency shelter in the winter, either at Kansas Street; Peter's Place, a private shelter open from October to April with 25 beds at Christ Episcopal Church on State Street near City Hall; or at 40 churches countywide that provide beds on a rotating basis as members of the 250-church Interreligious Fellowship for the Homeless of Bergen County.</p>
        <p>''If you add homeless families on top of that, people living in special needs transitional housing who have come out of the shelters,'' Mr. Halsch said, ''we've got just shy of 330 people on any given night.''</p>
        <p>C.A.P. also manages two rooming houses on State Street, near Christ Church: Chadwick House, a transitional shelter for six homeless young, from 16 to 21, and Warner House, a longer-term home for 23 people who have multiple impairments. And it runs a county-owned apartment at 40 Passaic Street for 27 families, usually single parents with children, who are on welfare, as well as two rooming houses in neighboring Englewood, one for 13 women and the other for 8 men.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zisa, a Republican who has been mayor for 15 years, believes a permanent shelter would be better housed on the grounds of the Bergen Regional Medical Center in Paramus, a county-owned, privately managed hospital, because medical, psychiatric, counseling and drug and alcohol treatment services are all available there.</p>
        <p>Jerome Lombardo, a real estate broker and chairman of a special improvement district on Main Street agrees, saying that business owners are not indifferent to the homeless but are wary of a new shelter. He thinks other communities should help.</p>
        <p>''They have to deal with people asleep in their doorways who want to come in and get out of the cold,'' Mr. Lombardo said. ''Many are hesitant to ask them to leave, and they end up scaring away customers. I think Hackensack has done its fair share.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Zisa also thinks homelessness is not just a city problem. ''We believe there are no more than 4 percent of the homeless on the streets of Hackensack who actually are from Hackensack or started their homeless plight in Hackensack,'' Mr. Zisa said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Halsch, after checking C.A.P. records, disagreed. He said that of those who sought emergency shelter at Kansas Street, Peter's Place and Fellowship churches, 39.4 percent came from Hackensack. The next highest percentage, 10.5 percent, came from Englewood with the rest coming from a ''mix of communities,'' including Teaneck, with 4 percent. Of those staying overnight at Orchard Street center, 66 percent came from Hackensack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halsch said Hackensack is ideal for a shelter because the homeless move in and out of rooming houses, and Hackensack has more than any other town in the county. Hackensack is also a transportation hub and the center of most county services.</p>
        <p>''So this is where people come for services,'' he said. ''Not because the homeless shelter is here. The homeless shelters were a response to the homeless being here.''</p>
        <p>GOVERNMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
