<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ABOUT BOOKS</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="684149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HORNER, SHIRLEY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WATKINS, PAUL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">STAND BEFORE YOUR GOD (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5DC1430F932A35756C0A962958260" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ABOUT BOOKS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Shirley Horner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HORNER, SHIRLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boarding School Life</p>
        <p>THERE'S something about a childhood at an English boarding school for boys that makes for great memoirs.  Be it George Orwell, A. N. Wilson or Evelyn Waugh, who wrote afterward that the experience put one "at home in prison," the traumas recalled are often so brutal that perhaps only through expert writing does an adult transcend them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Boarding School Life</p>
        <p>THERE'S something about a childhood at an English boarding school for boys that makes for great memoirs.  Be it George Orwell, A. N. Wilson or Evelyn Waugh, who wrote afterward that the experience put one "at home in prison," the traumas recalled are often so brutal that perhaps only through expert writing does an adult transcend them.</p>
        <p>"Stand Before Your God: A Boarding School Memoir," by Paul Watkins, legitimately enters that category of the emotionally bruised. Mr. Watkins, a resident of Hightstown, attended not one but two English boarding schools -- Dragon at age 7 and Eton from 12 to 19. His highly praised and captivating book, published by Random House ($22), recalls almost every detail of his shock at being enrolled in the very class-conscious Dragon and his defensive strategy.</p>
        <p>At night at first, feeling abandoned, he cried with his face pressed into his teddy bear so none would know. Even then his imagination was in active gear. He writes that he began to beg "the great forces of magic, good or bad -- whichever would listen -- to send me back across the water," and adds, "I offered up toys and money, then teeth and hair and fingers."</p>
        <p>Why was he, an American, sent to these schools? In the book's second half, he explains that his Welsh-born father believed he had been denied advantages that almost automatically felt into the laps of graduates of Eton and the schools that prepared for Eton.</p>
        <p>What makes the author of particular interest is the fact that at present he teaches writing at two independent boarding and day schools -- as writer in residence at the 130-year-old Peddie School in Hightstown and as visiting scholar at the Lawrenceville School in Lawrenceville, founded in 1810. It seems, though, that his awareness of sadism, snobbery and sexual abuse at the English institutions would drive him far away from a role in a boarding school.</p>
        <p>At Dragon, for example, he remembered the vulnerability of the youngest students and the taunts -- "you could be born with a name that you thought sounded fine," but then someone would change it and Codrington became Cuddlybum "until the end of time." There were beatings, hair pulling and rapping of knuckles for missed homework.</p>
        <p>A vast gulf, he said in an interview, separates the "elitist" English boarding schools and the two "elite" coeducational schools where he teaches.  The English schools only "open up a narrow corridor of opportunity and leave those who do not make it out in the cold." While there, he writes, "you had to stand before your God and commit yourself," but only later would you learn whether you had been helped or hurt by your schooling.</p>
        <p>The ritualized, formal training of his youth left him ill adjusted for his return to the United States, he said.  "And it wasn't easy getting used to being with girls after these male schools."</p>
        <p>If the snobbery exists here too ("I don't see it"), the corporal punishment is against the law ("had I known in England that it didn't go on everywhere, I would have run away"), and he sees no sexual abuse by teacher against student ("the friendlier atmosphere creates a healthier environment").</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins's wife, Cathy, a sculptor, teaches art at Peddie, and should Mr. Watkins ever have a son, he said in the interview, he would send him to a boarding school in the United States because "there is nothing like separation from the family at an early age -- no matter how nurturing -- to develop a youngster's individuality." History of Surgery</p>
        <p>"Surgery: An Illustrated History," an enlightening survey of the development of surgery from the beginnings of history, is not the first book Dr. Ira M. Rutkow has written about the field for both a general audience and a medical one. Two earlier volumes by Dr. Rutkow on surgery in the United States precede "Surgery," an oversize 550-page tome published by C. V. Mosby that sells for $99.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rutkow writes, according to his preface, to place current learning within the context of past and present -- an interest that dates back 15 years when he began collecting data about the practice of surgery in the 19th century. Although he admits to being cautioned by colleagues that "it may be too early to quit my day job," there is no question that Dr. Rutkow, who practices hernia surgery in Freehold, finds himself drawn more and more to the profession of writing.</p>
        <p>"I schedule my surgical practice around the hours that I write," he said in an interview. In fact, he writes four hours a day, he said. His next work will be a history of surgery in the United States.</p>
        <p>"Surgery" opens with a chapter on primitive surgery and lists the earliest example as trephination, boring open the skull -- "and the patient survived."</p>
        <p>The work, rich in colored reproductions of related artwork, traverses ancient civilizations, the classical world, the Far East and the Middle Ages. Its main focus for modern times -- since the Renaissance -- is outside the United States because here surgery did not establish the landmarks it accomplished in Europe until the early years of the 20th century.</p>
        <p>"New Jersey lagged far behind other states until recently," Dr. Rutkow said in the interview, because "we did not have a medical school until the 1950's." Thus, he added, the best New Jersey students went to schools out of state.</p>
        <p>Still, his book points out the presence of two noted 19th-century surgeons: Dr. Joseph Pancoast of Burlington County, distinguished for surgery on the bladder (1859) and the nerves (1872), and Dr. Beriah Watson of Jersey City, instrumental in founding St. Francis and Christ Hospitals in that city.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rutkow's prognosis for surgery? With an awareness of "socioeconomic pressures" -- he holds a doctorate in health care economics -- he writes that surgeons, while remaining humanitarian, must realize they can practice in a "businesslike manner," a strong requirement now facing them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
