<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kendall Slides to Center In Latest Tectonic Shift</title>
    <meta content="20Jets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1711084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D9123FF933A15753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kendall Slides to Center In Latest Tectonic Shift</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Oct. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jets looked like a perfect team for Pete Kendall as a free agent before last season. They would pay him as much as $9 million in his first three years, they were a playoff-caliber team and they were anchored at center by his former Seattle teammate, Kevin Mawae, a perennial Pro Bowl selection.</p>
        <p>''And I'd be playing right alongside him,'' Kendall, whose career has been defined as a guard, said Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Jets looked like a perfect team for Pete Kendall as a free agent before last season. They would pay him as much as $9 million in his first three years, they were a playoff-caliber team and they were anchored at center by his former Seattle teammate, Kevin Mawae, a perennial Pro Bowl selection.</p>
        <p>''And I'd be playing right alongside him,'' Kendall, whose career has been defined as a guard, said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>But Thursday, Kendall, 32, will be practicing at center because Mawae's season was ended by a torn triceps last Sunday.</p>
        <p>Except for a few snaps on the sideline during the 27-17 loss at Buffalo, Kendall has not centered for Vinny Testaverde. The Jets hope Testaverde's experience will help smooth Kendall's transition.</p>
        <p>''Some quarterbacks might see someone on the defense move, and they might hesitate in their count,'' said Doug Marrone, the offensive line coach. ''But Vinny's cadence is consistent.''</p>
        <p>Still, Kendall's move creates one more upheaval for the Jets' offensive line, an embattled unit struggling to open lanes for running back Curtis Martin and to protect Testaverde, 41, the Jets' third starting quarterback this season.</p>
        <p>When the Jets take their first snap Monday night in the noisy indoor home of the Atlanta Falcons, four of their five linemen will be playing positions different from the ones they had in the first game of the season.</p>
        <p>Kendall was the starting center in 2003 for Arizona. But besides a one-game emergency start in 1998, when was Kendall's previous stint as a center?</p>
        <p>''It was 1981, Weymouth Pop Warner Tigerhawks, the Black and Orange,'' said Kendall, who was born in Weymouth, Mass.</p>
        <p>The exchange from center was an adventure for Testaverde on Sunday, when Jonathan Goodwin, a backup guard, replaced Mawae. Two snaps were botched, one recovered by the Bills.</p>
        <p>''It's the responsibility of the quarterback to get adjusted to the center, and my responsibility to put it in the same spot,'' Kendall said.</p>
        <p>Testaverde agreed. ''I've got to know where he puts the ball,'' he said, ''and any adjustment I have is to where the ball is. The problem with some new centers is the ball might be coming left or it might be coming right. If a center can't snap the ball, he's playing guard.''</p>
        <p>The center's job is also to make the line calls, shouting out where the middle linebacker is positioned or what the defense is showing. And the other key for a center is his blocking ability, something Mawae excelled in.</p>
        <p>A position switch is not an exciting challenge for Kendall, who is in his 10th season.</p>
        <p>''I had resigned myself to finishing my career as a guard,'' he said. ''Let's be honest, I'm on my back nine.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The Jets have not scored in the opening quarter in their three road games this season -- all losses. They have lost five straight regular-season road games. Coach Herman Edwards said the Jets' poor first-quarter performance helped stir up the home crowd.  When Vinny Testaverde joined the Jets in 1998 as a 34-year-old quarterback, Coach Bill Parcells told him not to try to force the ball because that led to interceptions. Parcells promised to help him by providing complementary offensive talents. Testaverde wound up with his best season, with 29 touchdowns and 7 interceptions. After two games this season, Testaverde has three interceptions and no touchdowns. Edwards said: ''He needs guys to help him. He's not a 28-year-old guy anymore.''  Middle linebacker Jonathan Vilma leads the N.F.L. with 74 tackles, including 54 unassisted, also the top figure. The Dolphins' Zach Thomas, who has played one game fewer, has 69 tackles.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
