<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flexible N.F.L. Schedule Should Suit NBC</title>
    <meta content="01sandomir" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/01/sports/football/01sandomir.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1780060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ebersol, Dick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Madden, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Michaels, Al</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Costas, Bob</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Collinsworth, Cris</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bettis, Jerome</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE4DE103FF932A3575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flexible N.F.L. Schedule Should Suit NBC</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Flexible N.F.L. Schedule Should Suit NBC</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You cannot examine NBC's Sunday night National Football League schedule without sensing that after being away from the sport since the 1998 Super Bowl (you can't really count the XFL and the arena league), it sought special aid to acquire the best slate of prime-time games in years.</p>
        <p>Anyone who has watched Dick Ebersol, the chairman of NBC Universal Sports, maneuver through the Olympic, baseball, football and basketball rights landscape for the past 17 years would not be surprised if he had learned a spell or two from watching reruns of the witches on ''Charmed.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>From Weeks 10 to 15, and on Week 17, NBC will be able to swap the game perched tentatively on its schedule for one now on CBSs or Foxs menus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You cannot examine NBC's Sunday night National Football League schedule without sensing that after being away from the sport since the 1998 Super Bowl (you can't really count the XFL and the arena league), it sought special aid to acquire the best slate of prime-time games in years.</p>
        <p>Anyone who has watched Dick Ebersol, the chairman of NBC Universal Sports, maneuver through the Olympic, baseball, football and basketball rights landscape for the past 17 years would not be surprised if he had learned a spell or two from watching reruns of the witches on ''Charmed.''</p>
        <p>NBC's schedule is unlike any other ever given to a network, because from Weeks 10 to 15, and on Week 17, NBC will be able to swap the game perched tentatively on its schedule for one now on CBS's or Fox's menus. The league will make the final choice 12 days before any game switch.</p>
        <p>The flexibility was part of what NBC acquired when the league moved what had been ABC's ''Monday Night Football'' package to Sundays, and let ESPN take its cable games from Sunday nights to Mondays in prime time.</p>
        <p>The league, by one kind of analysis, gave NBC the welcoming gift of a schedule that is considerably better than what it provided ABC the past three seasons. Let's analyze each season's Thursday night opener through the ninth week, by looking at the previous season's combined won-loss record of the teams playing in those games.</p>
        <p>Using that methodology, the teams playing for NBC through Week 9 had a 192-96 record last year. The teams on ABC's 2004 and 2005 schedules posted identical 181-107 records in the preceding seasons.</p>
        <p>ABC's 2003 schedule featured teams that were 159-128-1 in 2002.</p>
        <p>''We want to see NBC get off to a strong start, and we believe this schedule has accomplished that without jeopardizing the success of our Sunday afternoon partners,'' said Howard Katz, the league's senior vice president for media operations and the scheduling chieftain.</p>
        <p>Ever since acquiring ''Monday Night Football'' rights for a stratospheric $1.1 billion a season, ESPN has insisted that ''Monday Night,'' even on cable, remains ''Monday Night,'' although it is evident that it is really a reconstituted Sunday night.</p>
        <p>Adopting ESPN's view allows further contemplation of NBC's scheduling advantage. The 10 games ESPN will carry through Week 9 feature teams with a combined record of 167-153 last season.</p>
        <p>ESPN's schedule over the first nine weeks includes six games with one team that had a losing record last season. NBC has only one, when Oakland plays Denver in Week 7. Still, ESPN has a better overall schedule than it did last year, when it didn't carry one game in which both teams playing had made the postseason the previous season. This year it will have four such matchups.</p>
        <p>NBC plunged into Sunday nights certain that Sunday is what Monday used to be, and that its pregame program, with its hockey-influenced name, ''Football Night in America,'' will benefit from audiences spilling over from CBS and Fox. Those networks may stay on the air through the conclusion of their games and their studio wrap-up shows until as late as 8 p.m.; NBC's pregame show begins at 7.</p>
        <p>To no one's surprise, Ebersol does not believe that NBC will suffer from viewer fatigue as the third game of the day. ''More weeks than not, in fact, almost every week, it's the game of the day, or at least it appears to be at this point,'' he said during a conference call yesterday.</p>
        <p>But it invariably happens that injuries and other factors wreck what looks like a great schedule; how much help the new flexibility imparts will become a parlor game of sorts, as fans handicap which games NBC will replace its potential duds with. NBC should be planning a weekly ''Flexible Schedule Selection Show'' with a panel guessing at the possibilities faced by NBC and the implications to NBC, Fox or CBS of each potential replacement.</p>
        <p>NBC is starting its N.F.L. schedule Sunday night, with the Eagles-Raiders game from Canton, Ohio, one day after the Pro Football Hall of Fame enshrinement of the network's newest star, John Madden, who is now calling the sport for his fourth network. It is a gift of scheduling, much like the Sept. 10 matchup of Peyton and Eli Manning when the Colts play the Giants.</p>
        <p>NBC is busily hyping its game voices (Madden and Al Michaels, the refugees from ABC) and studio team (Bob Costas, Cris Collinsworth, Jerome Bettis and Sterling Sharpe) on the type of Web site it uses to promote new dramas, comedies and reality programs. In a new advertising campaign, Costas and Collinsworth praise Madden, while Madden gushes that even when he doesn't make much sense, Michaels always does.</p>
        <p>For those in need of an old lineup, Dick Enberg, Phil Simms and Paul Maguire were NBC's lead team when it last carried the N.F.L. In the studio were Greg Gumbel, Ahmad Rashad, Joe Gibbs, Sam Wyche and Collinsworth.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: sportsbiz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
