<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man Is Accused Of Reporting Terrorist Hoax To Hot Line</title>
    <meta content="01false" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/01/nyregion/01false.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1780031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hoaxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alkatri, Rimon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFDF103FF932A3575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man Is Accused Of Reporting Terrorist Hoax To Hot Line</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Man Is Accused of Reporting Terrorist Hoax to Hot Line</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brooklyn, NY, jewelry store owner Rimon Alkatri is arrested and accused of reporting terrorist plot that investigators conclude was hoax; claimed Syrians in jewelry business were planning suicide bombing in subway system on July 4; police say Syrian Jewish refugee Alkatri used false name and claimed to be from Israel; Alkatri set off frenzied investigation in city and Israel, with city investigators discovering that Alkatri-named conspirators were men with whom he had bitter business dispute (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a call to New York City's terrorism hot line in May, the informant described the plot in chilling detail: Syrians working in the jewelry business had hatched a plan to carry out a suicide bombing in the subway system on one of the most symbolic days of the year, Independence Day.</p>
        <p>They had hidden explosives in hollowed-out jewelry, the informant said, and then used their professional know-how to import the jewelry and bring it to a store that one of them owned in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Syrian jeweler falsely named individuals as terrorists because of a grudge stemming from a business deal, according to police.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a call to New York City's terrorism hot line in May, the informant described the plot in chilling detail: Syrians working in the jewelry business had hatched a plan to carry out a suicide bombing in the subway system on one of the most symbolic days of the year, Independence Day.</p>
        <p>They had hidden explosives in hollowed-out jewelry, the informant said, and then used their professional know-how to import the jewelry and bring it to a store that one of them owned in New York.</p>
        <p>To clinch the story, the informant, who identified himself as Jose Rodriguez and said he was from Israel, told the police officer answering the hot line that he had overheard the plotters use the Arab expression ''Allahu Akbar,'' or ''God is great.''</p>
        <p>The post-Sept. 11 antiterrorist law enforcement apparatus sprang into action, with city, federal and even Israeli officers following leads, conducting 24-hour surveillance and searching homes and businesses with bomb-sniffing dogs. A New York detective stationed in Jerusalem tried to track down the man called Jose Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>In the end, the investigators concluded that the call was a hoax, they said yesterday, perpetrated by a Syrian Jewish refugee named Rimon Alkatri, 34, the owner of a jewelry store in Brooklyn. The five conspirators identified by Mr. Alkatri were not Muslims but Christians and Jews, the police and prosecutors said. He had done business with four of the men, officials said, and had named them as terrorists because he had a grudge against them stemming from a business deal that had ended in a bitter disagreement.</p>
        <p>The arrest offered what investigators said was a disturbing account of how law enforcement officers could be manipulated by a malicious prankster, especially in these times, when the specter of a terrorist attack seems possible and almost no threat seems too outlandish to ignore. This caller seemed credible because of the specific names and details that he offered, officials said.</p>
        <p>Officials said they were fairly sure at least 10 to 12 days before the Fourth of July that the account of a conspiracy was a hoax, but felt compelled to continue the investigation until every person had been interviewed and every suspicion allayed. ''Then the investigation turned towards who the hoaxer was and why,'' said Barbara Thompson, a spokeswoman for Robert M. Morgenthau, the Manhattan district attorney. ''It took tremendous resources and manpower.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Alkatri was arrested yesterday as he was leaving his apartment on East Ninth Street in a Syrian Jewish neighborhood of Brooklyn to work at his jewelry store, El Castillo De Oro, on Knickerbocker Avenue. A grand jury has indicted him on a felony charge falsely reporting an incident in the first degree, and he faces up to seven years in prison if convicted.</p>
        <p>Speaking outside State Supreme Court in Manhattan yesterday after Mr. Alkatri's arraignment had been postponed, his lawyer, Samuel J. Karliner, said his client's only motive was to be a good citizen. Mr. Alkatri called the hot line, Mr. Karliner said, because he truly believed that the five men were conspirators and had apparently made a mistake.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karliner said his client had overheard a worker in his jewelry store named George talking on his cellphone and using the phrase ''Allahu Akbar.'' Mr. Alkatri associated the phrase with the attack on the World Trade Center and beheadings in Iraq and became alarmed, his lawyer said. He gave a false name to the police because he was afraid that the men would find out who he was and hurt him, Mr. Karliner said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karliner said his client came to the United States from Syria as a refugee in 1996, and is married with two children. He said Mr. Alkatri felt wounded that instead of being thanked for his good citizenship, he has been arrested, and predicted that Mr. Alkatri's plight would have a ''chilling effect'' on others.</p>
        <p>The sign that every New Yorker, including his client, has seen in the subway, Mr. Karliner said, urges '' 'If you see something, say something,' not 'If it's not true, we're going to arrest you.' ''</p>
        <p>But investigators announcing Mr. Alkatri's arrest yesterday at a news conference in the office of Mr. Morgenthau, were clearly irritated by the amount of money and resources they had spent following a false trail. The investigation of the threat cost more than $100,000, according to Chief Phil T. Pulaski, commander of the Police Department's Intelligence Division.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alkatri's call came at a tense time, when investigators were quietly pursuing what they said was a bona fide, although nascent, terrorist plot to flood Lower Manhattan by attacking train tunnels under the Hudson River. July 7 was also the anniversary of the 2005 transit bombings in London that killed 52 commuters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
