<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Immigration Agency Spurs Process for Naturalization</title>
    <meta content="T08INS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980810T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1037472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Citizenship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bureaucratic Red Tape</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Immigration and Naturalization Service</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bureaucratic Red Tape</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Citizenship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E1DB113BF93BA3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Immigration Agency Spurs Process for Naturalization</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIRTA OJITO</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Immigration and Naturalization Service, under pressure to reduce unprecedented backlog of citizenship applications, announces measures to speed processing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under pressure to reduce an unprecedented backlog of citizenship applications, the Immigration and Naturalization Service yesterday announced measures that agency officials said would cut in half the time immigrants must wait to become United States citizens.</p>
        <p>The measures range from creating a national customer service office to help improve the agency's performance to asking Congress for $171 million to hire 200 new employees and increase overtime hours.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Under pressure to reduce an unprecedented backlog of citizenship applications, the Immigration and Naturalization Service yesterday announced measures that agency officials said would cut in half the time immigrants must wait to become United States citizens.</p>
        <p>The measures range from creating a national customer service office to help improve the agency's performance to asking Congress for $171 million to hire 200 new employees and increase overtime hours.</p>
        <p>Agency officials also said they would more than double the filing fee for citizenship applications -- to $225 from $95 -- and create a national telephone line, staffed by 500 people, to answer routine questions about immigration services.</p>
        <p>According to the plan, which was detailed by the I.N.S. Commissioner, Doris M. Meissner, much of the money would be used to send teams of experts to work in the five cities that have the highest number of pending citizenship cases. They are Los Angeles (420,000 cases), New York (more than 300,000), San Francisco (220,000), Miami (185,000) and Chicago (100,000).</p>
        <p>Immigration officials said the current backlog of 1.9 million cases nationwide was the result of an inefficient, antiquated system and a soaring number of applications prompted by recent laws that threaten to reduce benefits to noncitizens.</p>
        <p>In some parts of the country, applicants must wait more than two years to become citizens, said an I.N.S. spokesman in Washington, Russell A. Bergeron Jr. Just two years ago, the waiting time was six months. With the new plan, immigration officials expect that a year from now, immigrants will have to wait only 10 months to a year to become citizens.</p>
        <p>Except for the request for money, which would require Congressional approval, the measures would begin to be implemented immediately. The request is likely to be approved because immigration officials said the money was already part of the budget for the Justice Department, which oversees the I.N.S.</p>
        <p>The agency's lawyers and advocates for immigrants reacted to the announcement with caution.</p>
        <p>''Money is not going to help the situation,'' said Jesus Pena, an immigration lawyer in Queens. ''Immigration has already lost sight of its mission, and you can't bring that back by throwing money at an agency.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pena pointed to his most recent experience with the immigration agency as the reason for his lack of optimism. He said he went to the immigration office in Garden City, N.J., yesterday morning to find out why his client, Luz Galindo, had not heard from the agency since she applied for citizenship two years ago. He was told that, inexplicably, her file was in Detroit.</p>
        <p>''How much money, how much sophistication, does it take to bring a file from Detroit to New Jersey?'' Mr. Pena asked.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress have criticized the I.N.S. for rushing to naturalize people without proper background checks, while advocates for immigrants criticize it for taking too long to process applications.</p>
        <p>Leonard Glickman, executive vice president of the Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society in New York, said that he was ''hopeful and optimistic'' about the new measures but that he did not understand why the agency would raise filing fees when the level of service remained poor.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 10, 1998, Monday  Because of an editing error, an article on Saturday about plans by the Immigration and Naturalization Service to reduce the backlog of citizenship cases referred incorrectly to lawyers who reacted to the announcement of the proposals with caution. They were immigration lawyers, not I.N.S. lawyers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 10, 1998, Monday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article on Saturday about plans by the Immigration and Naturalization Service to reduce the backlog of citizenship cases referred incorrectly to lawyers who reacted to the announcement of the proposals with caution. They were immigration lawyers, not I.N.S. lawyers.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
