<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A.T.&amp;T. Is Adding More Translators</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="326853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEPHONES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LANGUAGE AND LANGUAGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN TELEPHONE &amp; TELEGRAPH CO INC (AT&amp;T)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMS, CALVIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Translation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D8113AF936A25751C0A966958260" item-length="495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A.T.&amp;T. Is Adding More Translators</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMS, CALVIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The American Telephone and Telegraph Company said yesterday that it would greatly expand its translation services to provide businesses and consumers with telephone interpreters who can help with 143 languages and dialects, 24 hours a day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The American Telephone and Telegraph Company said yesterday that it would greatly expand its translation services to provide businesses and consumers with telephone interpreters who can help with 143 languages and dialects, 24 hours a day.</p>
        <p>The American Telephone and Telegraph Company said yesterday that it would greatly expand its translation services to provide businesses and consumers with telephone interpreters who can help with 143 languages and dialects, 24 hours a day.</p>
        <p>The service is already available to businesses, which pay a subscription fee of $1,000 to $1,500, monthly fees of $25 to $50, and a per-minute fee of $1.94 to $2.75.</p>
        <p>Later this year, A.T.&amp;T. plans to introduce a non-subscription service that will allow occasional customers to use an interpreter for $3.50 a minute. The calls would be charged to local telephone bills.</p>
        <p>A.T.&amp;T. said the service would allow people who do not speak English to communicate with hospitals, public utilities, police or fire departments and schools or businesses in the United States.</p>
        <p>The service, called A.T.&amp;T. Language Line Service, would also allow a business that needs to get in touch with a non-English-speaking person to have an interpreter translate the communication in a three-way conversation.</p>
        <p>The service would be reached through a toll-free 800 number. An operator would determine the language being spoken, and transfer the call to an appropriate interpreter.</p>
        <p>A.T.&amp;T. said operators would be briefed on common expressions in many widely spoken languages, which would help them say at least ''Hello'' and ''What language are you speaking?'' If the operators needed further help in identifying the language of the caller, they would be able to bring translators onto the line.</p>
        <p>The company said the service would be available in 143 languages and dialects 24 hours a day, 365 days a year. It declined to provide how it would man the translators' positions.</p>
        <p>''The service closes the communications gap between people who speak different languages,'' said Merrill Tutton, vice president of A.T.&amp;T. Consumer Services. ''With the service, no one ever has to be denied the right to life-saving services simply because their language is not understood.''</p>
        <p>Travelers to the United States and other countries that allow international toll-free dialing would have access to the service. For example, someone visiting Azerbaijan who does not speak the language but needs a special allergy medicine could use the A.T.&amp;T. service to communicate with a local doctor.</p>
        <p>A.T.&amp;T. acquired the translation service, which was known as Communication and Language Line Inc., in August. A.T.&amp;T. declined to say how many telephone calls the service receives each year, but company officials said they expect demand for the service to increase rapidly as consumers continue to travel overseas in record numbers and new international business opportunities unfold.</p>
        <p>A.T.&amp;T. said the languages it regarded as frequently used included Spanish, Japanese, Russian, German, French, Italian and Greek. Among the other languages that the company listed are Armenian; Sioux; Azerbaijani; Twi, an African language; Tongan, from the South Pacific, and Punjabi.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
