<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shattered East Beirut Getting Relief Supplies</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="326825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LEBANON</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BEIRUT (LEBANON)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">RED CROSS, INTERNATIONAL (IRC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HIJAZI, IHSAN A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HRAWI, ELIAS (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NADIR, KHALIL ABI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon/Beirut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DA103AF936A25751C0A966958260" item-length="637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shattered East Beirut Getting Relief Supplies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IHSAN A. HIJAZI, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HIJAZI, IHSAN A</byline>
      <dateline>BEIRUT, Lebanon, Feb. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Relief supplies were sent today to East Beirut and tanker trucks began distributing water in the streets of the western part of the capital after two weeks of bitter clashes between Christian factions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Relief supplies were sent today to East Beirut and tanker trucks began distributing water in the streets of the western part of the capital after two weeks of bitter clashes between Christian factions.</p>
        <p>Relief supplies were sent today to East Beirut and tanker trucks began distributing water in the streets of the western part of the capital after two weeks of bitter clashes between Christian factions.</p>
        <p>A convoy of 12 trucks carrying food and medicine crossed the dividing line from predominantly Muslim West Beirut to the Christian side under escort of Red Cross workers. The aid was contributed jointly by international agencies and the Government of President Elias Hrawi, based in West Beirut, after appeals from Khalil Abi Nader, the Maronite Catholic Bishop of Beirut.</p>
        <p>Whole quarters of East Beirut have been devastated by fighting between Army troops loyal to Gen. Michel Aoun and Lebanese Forces militiamen under the leadership of Samir Geagea, who is also a Christian.</p>
        <p>Civilians in East Beirut have been virtual prisoners in damp and dark bomb shelters, afraid to venture out because their half of the city has itself been divided into war zones.</p>
        <p>Hospitals have been unable to cope with the mounting casualties and surgeons have been forced to operate by candlelight or kerosene lamps and to use whisky and arak, the national alcoholic drink, as antiseptics.</p>
        <p>Fierce artillery and rocket duels, which broke out Jan. 30 throughout the 300-square-mile Christian enclave, have wrecked power lines and water mains, leaving all of Beirut and its suburbs without electricity and water.</p>
        <p>Syrian Tankers Haul Water</p>
        <p>At the request of the Hrawi Government, Syrian troops policing the Muslim sector of the capital have provided military tanker trucks to ease the water shortage.</p>
        <p>The trucks, filled in Damour five miles south of here, have been touring West Beirut, distributing water. Men, women and children carrying plastic containers and waiting in line to have them filled are now a familiar sight each day in the city.</p>
        <p>Muslim civilians blame General Aoun for their hardships, recalling similar problems last summer during six months of savage artillery bombardment between Muslim and Christian areas.</p>
        <p>Dr. Geagea and General Aoun are said to live and work in bunkers with electricity, heat and telephone communications provided by powerful generators.</p>
        <p>General Aoun's bunker is two floors beneath the Presidential palace in the suburb of Baabda.</p>
        <p>Dr. Geagea's bunker is three stories under a building that houses the headquarters in Karantina, a seaside district facing Beirut harbor. The presidential palace was badly damaged during bombardment from Syrian and Muslim militia positions during the ''war of liberation'' declared by General Aoun a year ago to evict 40,000 Syrian soldiers from Lebanese territory. Dr. Geagea's headquarters has been damaged in bombardment over the last two weeks. #500 Killed in Latest Fighting Hospital and police records show that 500 people have been killed and 1,750 wounded in the fighting that broke out two weeks ago between forces led by General Aoun and Dr. Geagea.</p>
        <p>A newspaper based in West Beirut, As Safir, said it had learned from military officials that General Aoun expected 1,500 people to be killed in the next round of battles with his Christian adversary. The newspaper quoted him as telling his top aides, ''We can absorb this figure, because we have no alernative but to continue the battle to the very end.''</p>
        <p>Mediators have thus far made no headway in reconciling the two Christian leaders.</p>
        <p>Press reports said today that General Aoun has given mediators 48 more hours before he orders his troops to move against the Lebanese Forces militia. At a news conference on Tuesday, he told Dr. Geagea to surrender or face ''more miserable days ahead.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Geagea called his own news conference today and rejected General Aoun's warning.</p>
        <p>He said he was determined to maintain his 10,000-strong militia independently from General Aoun's 15,000-man army.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
