<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dow Posts 0.22-Point Rise as Volume Dips</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="326764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DD113BF936A25751C0A966958260" item-length="450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dow Posts 0.22-Point Rise as Volume Dips</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILLIP H. WIGGINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Drexel Burnham Lambert's woes did not spill over to the stock market yesterday, as the Dow Jones industrial average edged up by 0.22 point, to 2,624.32.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Drexel Burnham Lambert's woes did not spill over to the stock market yesterday, as the Dow Jones industrial average edged up by 0.22 point, to 2,624.32.</p>
        <p>Drexel Burnham Lambert's woes did not spill over to the stock market yesterday, as the Dow Jones industrial average edged up by 0.22 point, to 2,624.32.</p>
        <p>At the same time, advancing issues on the New York Stock Exchange outpaced declining ones by 749 to 681.</p>
        <p>Volume on the Big Board was relatively stable, at 138.5 million shares, down from the 144.4 million shares that changed hands on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>In the broader market, the Standard &amp; Poor's index of 500 stocks rose by 0.99, to 332.01, while the New York Stock Exchange composite index gained 0.36, to 183.21.</p>
        <p>Programmers in Control</p>
        <p>''Yesterday was another low-volume affair, with investors having little conviction as to what to do in the face of the Drexel situation and the 'junk bond' fiasco,'' said Edward P. Nicoski, the chief technical analyst at Piper, Jaffray Inc. in Minneapolis. ''With liquidity virtually nil, program traders were able to move the market up and down as they pleased. The net result for the day was zero.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicoski said another disconcerting factor had been the upward pressure on oil prices, which affects the outlook for inflation.</p>
        <p>''Ironically, however, should crude oil prices drop sharply, we could then see downward pressure on energy issues, which have represented the market's primarily leadership in recent months,'' the analyst added. Energy stocks ended mixed yesterday after being up early in the day. Exxon slipped by 1/4, to 47; Chevron rose by 1 1/4, to 69 5/8, and Mobil was unchanged at 61 1/2.</p>
        <p>Another analyst indicated that yesterday's performance might be misleading.</p>
        <p>Among individual issues, Great Northern Nekoosa jumped by 2 points, to 64, in active trading. The company has asked its investment bankers to begin discussions with interested parties, hoping to avoid a hostile offer from Georgia-Pacific.</p>
        <p>First Interstate Gains</p>
        <p>First Interstate gained 2, to 34 7/8, also in active trading. The company said a partnership affiliated with Kohlberg, Kravis, Roberts &amp; Company would buy about 3.4 million of the 7.5 million common shares to be offered by First Interstate Bancorp at $33 each.</p>
        <p>The active glamour stocks included Chase Manhattan, up by 1/2, to 27 1/2; I.B.M., up by 1/2, to 103 3/4; Philip Morris, up by 3/8, to 39 1/8, and Citicorp, up by 1/2, to 23 1/2.</p>
        <p>On the American Stock Exchange, the Amex market-value index added 0.33 point, to 358.78, while in over-the-counter trading, the Nasdaq composite index moved up by 0.81, to 426.56.</p>
        <p>In Tokyo, stocks closed marginally higher in what some of the traders there termed a ''wait-and-see'' day. The Nikkei index of 225 issues rose by 48.86 points, to 37,155.89, after dropping by 181.11 points on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
