<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Manning's Playbook, a Lesson on Finishing</title>
    <meta content="02anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/02/sports/football/02anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1794346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Indianapolis Colts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Indianapolis Colts</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mangini, Eric</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EFDE1430F931A35753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Manning's Playbook, a Lesson on Finishing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Manning’s Playbook, a Lesson on Finishing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>East Rutherford, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the Jets' locker room, you could see the pain in their faces, the pain of having watched Peyton Manning and the Indianapolis Colts snatch a game that they thought they might steal.</p>
        <p>Together, the pain reflected growing pains from yesterday's 31-28 loss, the growing pains that all young teams endure before they are capable of stopping such a superior quarterback in a superior offense in the crucible of the last two minutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jets are better than most people thought they would be; maybe even better than they thought they would be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the Jets' locker room, you could see the pain in their faces, the pain of having watched Peyton Manning and the Indianapolis Colts snatch a game that they thought they might steal.</p>
        <p>Together, the pain reflected growing pains from yesterday's 31-28 loss, the growing pains that all young teams endure before they are capable of stopping such a superior quarterback in a superior offense in the crucible of the last two minutes.</p>
        <p>The togetherness of those growing pains also reflected the togetherness this Jets team is developing under its new coach, Eric Mangini.</p>
        <p>Second-guessers will wonder why Mangini, in a fourth-and-goal at the Colts' 2-yard line in the third quarter, bypassed a chip-shot field-goal attempt for a 17-14 lead. Instead, Colts linebacker Rocky Boiman leaped in the end zone to intercept Chad Pennington's pass. But from his years as an assistant to Coach Bill Belichick in New England, Mangini wisely knew that if the Jets were to outscore Manning, they would need touchdowns, not field goals. Good thinking. Bad outcome.</p>
        <p>''The plan was to put the ball in the end zone and score a touchdown,'' Mangini said. ''We've seen Peyton march down the field a lot of times and score a touchdown, and we were looking to match our offensive production with touchdowns.''</p>
        <p>When Justin Miller set a Jets record with a 103-yard kickoff return for a 28-24 lead with 2 minutes 20 seconds remaining, Mangini and all those second-guessers indeed saw what Manning could do: whip his offense 61 yards in 90 seconds, completing five of six passes, notably a rollout on third-and-6 at the Jets' 35 on which he somehow found the All-Pro wide receiver Marvin Harrison near the sideline at the 19.</p>
        <p>''That's why Peyton is who he is, why their offense is the best in the league,'' Pennington said. ''He popped up and found Marvin Harrison.''</p>
        <p>After a second-down dart to wide receiver Reggie Wayne at the 1, Manning barged into the end zone himself for the winning touchdown.</p>
        <p>That's what Peyton Manning does. That's what he has done for most of his nine seasons, after suffering growing pains himself in 1998 as a Colts rookie. And that's why Mangini disdained the field goal; he knew he would need touchdowns to outscore football's purest passer.</p>
        <p>In a way, Miller's kickoff return gave Manning time. Too much time. Ideally, the Jets would have been better off if they had moved upfield slowly and scored a touchdown with only a few seconds to play or kicked a tying field goal and taken their chances in overtime.</p>
        <p>But with that 2:20 still on the clock, the Jets had to depend on their defense, which wasn't up to stopping Manning.</p>
        <p>''Defensively, we didn't do what it took,'' linebacker Jonathan Vilma, clearly annoyed, said. ''Peyton Manning is a great quarterback. We had to be that much sharper physically and mentally. The first three quarters we were fine, but we had to finish.''</p>
        <p>Even with several desperate laterals that resembled a game of tag on their frantic final play, the Jets didn't, or couldn't, finish off what would have been a stunning victory.</p>
        <p>With their usual flair, Manning and the Colts did.</p>
        <p>That's why the Colts, who were 13-0 last season before losing to San Diego, and later losing to the eventual Super Bowl champion Pittsburgh Steelers in the American Football Conference playoffs, are now 4-0.</p>
        <p>And that's why the Jets are 2-2 going to Jacksonville before returning against two of the league's weaker teams, Detroit and Miami.</p>
        <p>Not bad for a team being reconstructed by a rookie general manager, Mike Tannenbaum, and with a 35-year-old rookie coach, Mangini, and two rookies on the offensive line, left tackle D'Brickashaw Ferguson and center Nick Mangold.</p>
        <p>Over all, Ferguson, the first-round draft choice, held his own against Dwight Freeney, the Colts' All-Pro pass rusher, but he'll remember two bad moments.</p>
        <p>On the Jets' opening series, Robert Mathis, instead of Freeney, lined up against Ferguson, barreled past him and strip-sacked Pennington, forcing a fumble that the Colts recovered at the Jets' 26. Manning needed only 94 seconds to send Dominic Rhodes into the end zone from the 6.</p>
        <p>''A better set would have avoided that,'' Ferguson said later.</p>
        <p>On the play before Pennington's fourth-down interception, Freeney spun inside Ferguson to tackle running back Cedric Houston at the 2 for no gain and, more important, no touchdown. Ferguson didn't remember what exactly happened there, but the game films will tell him.</p>
        <p>''Brick is blocking a big-time sack monster,'' Pennington said, alluding to Freeney, ''and he's doing real well.''</p>
        <p>So are the Jets. With a relatively easy schedule and barring another season-ending injury to Pennington, they should win six games, maybe seven, and with a little luck they could produce an 8-8 record.</p>
        <p>Even without several of their Super Bowl stalwarts, the Patriots are still the class of the A.F.C. East, but the Jets are better than most people thought they would be.</p>
        <p>Maybe even better than they thought they would be.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
