<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drama Surrounds Legend of a Kentucky Derby Past</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="602295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GENUINE RISK (RACE HORSE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THOROUGHBRED RACING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DURSO, JOSEPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDD113AF936A25757C0A965958260" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drama Surrounds Legend of a Kentucky Derby Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DURSO, JOSEPH</byline>
      <dateline>MIDWAY, Ky.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two and a half weeks before the 119th Kentucky Derby, racing people in the bluegrass country are keeping a vigil for a 16-year-old mare these spring days.</p>
        <p>She is called "Jenny" around the barns, but she is renowned as Genuine Risk, who made history 13 years ago when she became the second filly in a century to win the Kentucky Derby. Now she stands solemnly in her executive stall at Three Chimneys Farm waiting for the moment when she may make medical history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two and a half weeks before the 119th Kentucky Derby, racing people in the bluegrass country are keeping a vigil for a 16-year-old mare these spring days.</p>
        <p>She is called "Jenny" around the barns, but she is renowned as Genuine Risk, who made history 13 years ago when she became the second filly in a century to win the Kentucky Derby. Now she stands solemnly in her executive stall at Three Chimneys Farm waiting for the moment when she may make medical history.</p>
        <p>After losing foals almost every year for the last dozen years, Genuine Risk has carried her current pregnancy to the very edge of its full term. On a small framed chart attached to the door of the stall, the stark facts are printed: "In foal to Rahy. Due April 20." And while other mares have been bred successfully at her age, no race horse of her stature has endured a series of miscarriages, abortions and stillbirths to finally deliver her first foal at such an advanced age. Still a Puzzle</p>
        <p>"She is in late middle age, by human reckoning," Robert Clay, the master of Three Chimneys, said the other day. "She has been in foal almost every year, but the longest she carried a foal was 10 months of the normal 11. Other times, she'd lose them early. This time, she's gone the farthest."</p>
        <p>The suspense is deepened by mystery. There is no known genetic or physical reason why Genuine Risk should lose foals. The first was positioned badly and died before delivery. The last two were caught in the umbilical cord.</p>
        <p>"Some things are treatable for carrying foals," said Dan Rosenberg, who manages Three Chimneys Farm and directs its breeding operations. "This mare has had several things go wrong over the years.</p>
        <p>"She's very sweet and gentle, and shows good instincts for motherhood. And we're monitoring her carefully. The foal's heartbeat is fine. We check the amniotic fluid. Everything we can monitor is within normal parameters."</p>
        <p>Clay nodded toward the dramatic star of the stable, who stood quietly in her spacious, wood-paneled stall, and said:</p>
        <p>"She looks a little serious today. But about six weeks ago, we began to get emotionally involved over her. By then, she'd gone farther toward full term than at any time since she came here three years ago. We began to get the feeling this might be the year."</p>
        <p>The feeling grew as winter turned to spring and Genuine Risk drew closer to April 20, although mares sometimes deliver as much as a month late.</p>
        <p>The drama of Jenny is unfolding in one of the scrubbed barns at Three Chimneys Farm, 1,100 acres of tranquil elegance down the Old Frankfort Pike below the red brick church marked by a sign that reports: "Mt. Vernon Baptist Church. Organized 1822. Rebuilt 1904."</p>
        <p>As the countdown continues, serenity and star quality prevail in the fields surrounding her barn. In the pasture near the paddock, Seattle Slew reigns at the age of 19. Next door in his private pasture, Slew o' Gold grazes at 13. Across the walkway in another private field, Capote at 9. In the next field, Chief's Crown at 11. And posing in the sunshine, the big chestnut Time for a Change, who is 12 and still regal.</p>
        <p>It is a pantheon of stallions. But the vigil these days centers on the 16-year-old mare Jenny.</p>
        <p>When she was racing, owned by Mrs. Bertram R. Firestone and trained by Leroy Jolley, she made history by outrunning the best colts of her time. She won all four of her races in 1979 at the age of 2. She won four of her eight races in 1980, including the Kentucky Derby, and finished second in the Preakness and the Belmont Stakes. She was the first filly to win the Derby since Regret in 1915. Winning Colors won in 1988, but they are still the only three fillies to capture the Derby. Stellar Racing Record</p>
        <p>When Genuine Risk retired at 4, her record was exceptional: 15 starts, 10 victories and all 15 times in the money. Then she turned to her second career as a mare.</p>
        <p>"She was able to get pregnant rather easily," Jolley recalled the other day at Keeneland Race Course in Lexington. "But she had trouble delivering the foal. The first one was positioned wrong and was dead when the doctors delivered it. Since then, she lost them all, sometimes early, sometimes later."</p>
        <p>Jolley doesn't share the belief that a good racing filly often doesn't make a good broodmare. But Clay said the belief persists in the thoroughbred business.</p>
        <p>"The traits that make a good race horse may not be the best for making a good mare," he said. "You know, maybe it takes some masculinity to be a good race horse, and that very trait may work against a mare when it comes to breeding."</p>
        <p>Clay said that no special medication had been prescribed to help Genuine Risk carry her foal. "Just nature," he said.</p>
        <p>"If it works this time," he said, "she could be bred again, maybe four more times. A 16-year-old mare isn't considered old. Some are bred into their 20's, even 25. But the production level starts to fall off after 20."</p>
        <p>Over the years, Genuine Risk has been bred to a series of stallions, most recently to Cure the Blues, Dixieland Band and for the last two years to Rahy.</p>
        <p>Rahy was a miler of some success in Europe and the United States five years ago, but is also remembered chiefly because the Maktoum brothers of Dubai paid $2 million to buy him as a yearling. It costs the Firestones a stallion fee of $15,000 to breed him to Jenny, but only if a live foal is delivered. Thrilling Prospect</p>
        <p>"I've had things that were thrilling in my professional life," Rosenberg said. "Things that were enormous triumphs. But to call Diana Firestone and tell her she's got a live foal would be the greatest thrill.</p>
        <p>"We don't know the sex of the foal yet, but he's apparently sound, and he's active. We don't want to make any mistakes. But it's really in God's hands now."</p>
        <p>So, the vigil goes on, mostly in the main barns where Genuine Risk stands and waits alongside stalls occupied by mares and their new foals, all legs and ears and nipping around.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, Diana Firestone flies into town from Florida and takes up the vigil in person. She will sit on a chair in the barn or paddock for hours and talk to Genuine Risk, or just sit and watch as her great old race horse plays out the mystery of birth and death one more time.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
