<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreman Defeats A Tough Savarese</title>
    <meta content="27FITE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BOXING" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="925992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Timothy W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Savarese, Lou</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foreman, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7D91431F934A15757C0A961958260" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreman Defeats A Tough Savarese</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Timothy W</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC CITY, April 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Foreman, continuing comeback effort, defeats Lou Savarese in split decision in World Boxing Uion heavyweight bout (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Needing an impressive showing to continue his eternal comeback, George Foreman entered the 12th round of his World Boxing Union heavyweight fight at the Atlantic City Convention Center tonight against Lou Savarese swinging for the fences. He wanted the knockout. But Savarese, who had withstood all of Foreman's heavy artillery through 11 rounds, would not oblige.</p>
        <p>So, when it was over, Savarese's face looked like he had stepped into a roomful of flying knives -- with a cut under his right eye, a cut in his left eyelid and cuts along the bridge of his nose -- and Foreman won a split decision. Judge Al DeVito (114-113) scored the fight for Savarese and judges Barbara Perez (115-112) and Shafeeq Rashada (118-110) scored it for Foreman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Needing an impressive showing to continue his eternal comeback, George Foreman entered the 12th round of his World Boxing Union heavyweight fight at the Atlantic City Convention Center tonight against Lou Savarese swinging for the fences. He wanted the knockout. But Savarese, who had withstood all of Foreman's heavy artillery through 11 rounds, would not oblige.</p>
        <p>So, when it was over, Savarese's face looked like he had stepped into a roomful of flying knives -- with a cut under his right eye, a cut in his left eyelid and cuts along the bridge of his nose -- and Foreman won a split decision. Judge Al DeVito (114-113) scored the fight for Savarese and judges Barbara Perez (115-112) and Shafeeq Rashada (118-110) scored it for Foreman.</p>
        <p>Foreman (76-4) did not have an argument with the split decision, but seemed to marvel at Savarese's ability to withstand his heavy shots.</p>
        <p>''It was a decision for me; that's really all I care about,'' Foreman said. ''I didn't understand how he stayed up with the shots I was giving him. I don't know where he got the strength. In the second half of the fight, I was throwing more punches with a lot of power. He hurt me one time with an overhand right. Tonight I had to box. I don't like to box with these guys. I like the knockout.''</p>
        <p>Savarese (36-1) said he had to stay inside for most of the fight because Foreman opened a cut along his left eyelid in the first round. Savarese's trainer, Tommy Gallagher, said it was a four-inch gash.</p>
        <p>''I fought my best; George is a crafty guy,'' Savarese said. ''He hit me in the first round in the eye and I couldn't see after that. I can take a punch. Whenever he hit me with one punch, I tried to come back with two or three. I've only been down once in my career.''</p>
        <p>It was a very impressive showing for Savarese, who threw 870 punches and landed 336 (39 percent). He threw an average of 72 punches a round. Foreman threw 540 punches and landed 296 (55 percent).</p>
        <p>The fight against Savarese did not do anything to damage Foreman's chances to continue his quest for a match against the winner of the Evander Holyfield-Mike Tyson fight in June. And Savarese did not hurt his chances in the heavyweight division, either.</p>
        <p>Savarese, 31, was supposed to send Foreman into a final retirement, but the music he entered the ring to -- the Bee Gees' ''Stayin' Alive'' -- was ominous. Others were supposed to send Foreman to a rocking chair also -- Holyfield in 1991, Michael Moorer in 1994, Axel Schulz in 1995 and Crawford Grimsley last November.</p>
        <p>Holyfield won a decision against Foreman, and that was the last fight in which Foreman appeared formidable, even though he took a pounding from the younger Holyfield. Moorer was ahead on all cards before he was knocked out in the 10th round, which gave Foreman the World Boxing Association and International Boxing Federation heavyweight championship titles. That was two and a half years ago, and Foreman was stripped of both those titles because he did not take mandatory fights to defend them.</p>
        <p>Foreman, who weighed 253 pounds for tonight's fight, had fought just twice since taking the titles from Moorer. He won a controversial decision against Schulz and then had a lackluster performance against Grimsley in Chiba, Japan, getting the victory in a 12-round decision.</p>
        <p>Savarese, who was a trim 230 pounds for this fight, had been a carefully groomed heavyweight and his 36-0 record was well cultivated. His most prominent opponent was Buster Mathis Jr., whom he knocked out in the seventh round last November. It was also his largest payday to date ($35,000). He earned $500,000 to fight Foreman. So, the fight was a big step up for Savarese.</p>
        <p>Savarese opened the fight with a left hook to Foreman's chin that did not seem to faze him. Foreman later backed Savarese up with a stiff jab and caught him inside with an uppercut.</p>
        <p>Through the first couple of rounds, Foreman was pressing the action and taking Savarese's best shots, mainly his looping left hook. Foreman even showed some ability to slip some of Savarese's punches. In the third round, Foreman opened up a cut along the corner of Savarese's left eyelid, but it did not seem to have that big an impact right away.</p>
        <p>Savarese seemed to pick up his pace in the fourth round and began landing more punches. But he was not putting them together in combination. Foreman seemed to get a little tired in the fifth round, but Savarese did not have enough sting on his punches to take advantage of Foreman's weariness.</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
