<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki Assails Budget Plan Of Legislators</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="853816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAO, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PATAKI, GEORGE E (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2D61139F93BA15756C0A960958260" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki Assails Budget Plan Of Legislators</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DAO, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, May 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rift between Gov. George E. Pataki and the Legislature widened today as the Governor's budget office assailed a bipartisan legislative budget, saying it is $1.2 billion out of balance and filled with irresponsible election-year spending.</p>
        <p>The criticism of the legislative budget, contained in an analysis by Mr. Pataki's top fiscal advisers, was more detailed and markedly sharper than the Governor's initial response to the plan when it was outlined last week -- indicating that the budget impasse, now two months old, could drag on for several weeks longer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The rift between Gov. George E. Pataki and the Legislature widened today as the Governor's budget office assailed a bipartisan legislative budget, saying it is $1.2 billion out of balance and filled with irresponsible election-year spending.</p>
        <p>The criticism of the legislative budget, contained in an analysis by Mr. Pataki's top fiscal advisers, was more detailed and markedly sharper than the Governor's initial response to the plan when it was outlined last week -- indicating that the budget impasse, now two months old, could drag on for several weeks longer.</p>
        <p>The legislative spending plan was the fruit of weeks of negotiations between the Republican majority leader in the State Senate, Joseph L. Bruno, and the Democratic Assembly Speaker, Sheldon Silver. The plan was intended to jump-start molasses-slow budget talks with Mr. Pataki.</p>
        <p>When they released the plan, the leaders said it would spend $1.2 billion more than Mr. Pataki's own plan, mainly by spending more on schools, the state university system and health care programs. But the leaders said their plan would meet two of the Governor's major goals: reducing taxes and keeping spending from state taxes below last year's levels.</p>
        <p>But the analysis released by the State Budget Division today said the legislative plan would actually increase spending by $713 million over last year's levels, compared with Mr. Pataki's plan, which would spend $679 million less.</p>
        <p>The analysis also said the Legislature had at once underestimated the cost of its additional spending and overestimated the value of the revenues it would use to pay for that largess. The result: a budget that would be $1.2 billion in the  red, the analysis said.</p>
        <p>The budget review showed just how far Mr. Pataki and the legislative leaders  remain apart. Though Mr. Pataki said last week that he thought the leaders were  "making progress," his top budget adviser said today that after analyzing the legislative proposal, she now feels that things have not improved at all despite months of negotiations. "What's distressing about this is that there hasn't been much progress since six or eight weeks ago, when the Legislature was talking about being $2 billion higher than us," said Patricia A. Woodworth, the State Budget Director.</p>
        <p>The administration's analysis immediately set off a sharp exchange between Pataki aides and legislative officials. Patricia Lynch, a spokeswoman for Mr. Silver, a Manhattan Democrat, ridiculed the Budget Division for "not having a great deal of credibility to forecast properly."</p>
        <p>John E. McArdle, a spokesman for Mr. Bruno, a Republican from Rensselaer County who had been one of Mr. Pataki's strongest legislative allies, said, "It's not surprising that we get this from a budget director who gave us a budget back in December that was $2 billion out of balance." Mr. McArdle was referring to Mr. Pataki's first budget plan, which assumed significant savings from changes in Federal policies that did not occur.</p>
        <p>Ms. Woodworth responded by saying the legislative plan "fits the pattern that in election years they have to spend more."</p>
        <p>She accused the Legislature of wanting to "have its cake and eat it too" by seeking "to cut taxes and have spending go up at the same time."</p>
        <p>Ms. Woodworth said Mr. Pataki was stunned by the legislative plan when he reviewed it late last week because it would spend so much more than his own plan -- as much as $1.8 billion more, according to his aides. She said he was also shocked that the leaders did not include any of his proposals to change welfare  or toughen sentences for violent criminals in their budget.</p>
        <p>Legislative officials from both major parties have said the Legislature is prepared to pass its own budget and dare Mr. Pataki to use his line-item veto on it if negotiations remain stalled much longer.</p>
        <p>Asked if Mr. Pataki would use his veto power if that happens, Ms. Woodworth said: "If he's sent a budget that is unrealistic, it's something he'd have to consider. But he certainly would prefer to have things worked out."</p>
        <p>In releasing their budget plan last week, the legislative leaders pointed to  several sources of additional revenue to pay for their spending. Those included  higher-than-anticipated income tax revenues and lower-than-expected spending on  Medicaid. They also projected sharply increased revenues from improved tax collection on cigarette sales.</p>
        <p>But the Budget Division said today that Medicaid costs were actually rising slightly and that income tax revenues were not growing as quickly as the Legislature believes.</p>
        <p>Budget officials also said many elements of the legislative proposal cost more than the leaders have projected.</p>
        <p>For instance, the repeal of a tax on real estate transactions worth over $1 million would reduce state revenues by $80 million, the officials said -- not the $20 million projected by the Legislature.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
