<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Indians, Casino Gambling Represents a Self-Help Program</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="452496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAMBLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDIANS, AMERICAN</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL INDIAN GAMING COMMISSION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOPE, ANTHONY J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D6143BF937A25755C0A967958260" item-length="551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Indians, Casino Gambling Represents a Self-Help Program</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>William Safire, in "The Wigwam Casino" (column, May 30), decries the idea that the Pequot tribe of Connecticut is opening a "gambling palace to attract suckers who are addicted to roulette, craps, blackjack and off-track betting." He states, "Also likely to follow are the vices always associated with great accumulations of cash: money laundering of drug wealth, prostitution, mob influence, political corruption." He is against it because "gambling feeds the get-rich-quick illusion that debilitates society; because gambling causes individual ruin, despair and suicide, and corrupts a state that seeks a piece of the action."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>William Safire, in "The Wigwam Casino" (column, May 30), decries the idea that the Pequot tribe of Connecticut is opening a "gambling palace to attract suckers who are addicted to roulette, craps, blackjack and off-track betting." He states, "Also likely to follow are the vices always associated with great accumulations of cash: money laundering of drug wealth, prostitution, mob influence, political corruption." He is against it because "gambling feeds the get-rich-quick illusion that debilitates society; because gambling causes individual ruin, despair and suicide, and corrupts a state that seeks a piece of the action."</p>
        <p>At least we know where he stands. I thought Prohibition had a lot to be said for it. Unfortunately, one of the things that became clear with Prohibition was that restricting the flow of booze to those who couldn't handle it put them at the mercy of the very mob Mr. Safire is afraid of. Worse, it was Government intervention in a business that didn't need it.</p>
        <p>Why is Mr. Safire blaming the Indians? Tribally owned gaming amounts to one-tenth of one percent of gaming in the United States. He thinks that "guilt-ridden paternalism . . . led to a kind of sovereignty that puts reservations on a legal par with states." The tribes have always been sovereign. It is those tribes who have regained recognition of their sovereignty in the last 20 years who are escaping the kind of paternalism that Mr. Safire both decries and practices.</p>
        <p>He doesn't understand why the Senate, the House of Representatives and the Connecticut legislature have come to agreement that the tribes have a right to open their casino, nor does he care. He doesn't know that Gov. Lowell Weicker wrecked his own legislative effort by proposing a ban on the wrong thing and insulting his legislators by going to the press before talking to them. Finally, he doesn't have a clue about the vast amount of taxable revenue that will be generated in Connecticut as a result of this venture, nor does he care.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Safire thinks is that he is "against it because I respect American Indians and do not want to see them isolated and despised." Most of the tribal chiefs I have talked to would rather not be in gaming, but the alternative for them is tribal alcoholism, despair and starvation. Gaming gives them access to pride, money, education, better health, housing and transportation to places where there are jobs. It is their own self-help program, their own bootstrap operation and their only escape from the kind of paternalism most exemplified by Mr. Safire's diatribe.</p>
        <p>I work with the tribes. They understand the need for regulation inside and outside their casinos. Most of them understand the cyclic nature of gambling and that they must treat at least some of the receipts as capital for expansion of tribal businesses, services and infrastructure.</p>
        <p>Can you imagine Mr. Safire saying that women or blacks shouldn't get into profitable gaming because he respects them too much? They would at least hoot him from town or even burn him in effigy. That the tribes don't do this is only a sign of how far they have yet to go to reach equality with those who took their continent away. ANTHONY J. HOPE Chairman National Indian Gaming Commission Washington, May 31, 1991</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
