<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Look Who's Talking' Suit On Plagiarism Is Settled</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="452576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAGIARISM</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRI-STAR PICTURES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOROWITZ, JOY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HECKERLING, AMY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BYRNE, WILLIAM M JR (JUDGE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEYERS, JEANNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STERN, RITA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LOOK WHO'S TALKING (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plagiarism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D8153CF937A25755C0A967958260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Look Who's Talking' Suit On Plagiarism Is Settled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOY HOROWITZ,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOROWITZ, JOY</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A $20 million lawsuit charging that Tri-Star Pictures and the director and writer Amy Heckerling stole the basic premise and large chunks of her 1989 hit, "Look Who's Talking," from a student project given to her three years before the film's release has been quietly settled.</p>
        <p>Under a court order from Judge William Matthew Byrne Jr. of Federal District Court here on May 13, the terms of the settlement between Tri-Star and the independent writers and producers Jeanne Meyers and Rita Stern are confidential. Thus the final chapter of this copyright-infringement case could be titled "Look Who's Not Talking About 'Look Who's Talking.' "</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A $20 million lawsuit charging that Tri-Star Pictures and the director and writer Amy Heckerling stole the basic premise and large chunks of her 1989 hit, "Look Who's Talking," from a student project given to her three years before the film's release has been quietly settled.</p>
        <p>Under a court order from Judge William Matthew Byrne Jr. of Federal District Court here on May 13, the terms of the settlement between Tri-Star and the independent writers and producers Jeanne Meyers and Rita Stern are confidential. Thus the final chapter of this copyright-infringement case could be titled "Look Who's Not Talking About 'Look Who's Talking.' "</p>
        <p>"It was resolved amicably," said Peter Anderson, the lawyer for the plaintiffs. The case was the first major plagiarism battle in Hollywood since the columnist Art Buchwald's victory in 1990 over a breach of contract lawsuit against Paramount Pictures concerning the film "Coming to America."</p>
        <p>The lawyer for Tri-Star, Louis M. Meisinger of Hill, Wynne, Troop &amp; Meisinger, said: "I'm not at liberty to discuss it except to say it was resolved amicably."</p>
        <p>Ms. Meyers said: "Rita and I are really happy, and we're glad it's over.  And we're working on a lot of other things, and that's all I can say."</p>
        <p>Ms. Heckerling did not return telephone calls. But her associate, Twink Caplan, whom the suit charges with acting as a go-between in accepting Ms. Meyers's work for Ms. Heckerling, said: "We're happy girls, me and Amy. But we're not allowed to say one thing." 'Still a Great Victory'</p>
        <p>Ms. Meyers's literary agent, Barbara Markowitz, said: "It's really too bad. I'd love the world to have known it was their movie. But it's still a great victory for writers all over, for the poor writer and producer who work so hard and then get ripped off."</p>
        <p>While plagiarism cases are legion in Hollywood, few plaintiffs make it as far as Ms. Meyers and Ms. Stern, who originally filed suit in January 1990 in Federal District Court in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Court records indicate that a settlement was quickly reached in recent weeks after Judge Byrne issued an order on April 3 turned down to Ms. Heckerling and Tri-Star's efforts to seek a dismissal, saying that the facts of the case not only show "substantial similarity" between the two works but also "suggest copying." Substantial similarity and access to the original work are the two legal thresholds by which a copyright lawsuit can proceed to trial.</p>
        <p>Court documents say that in 1986 Ms. Meyers and Ms. Stern approached Ms. Heckerling, who was directing an episode of the television version of her 1982 hit movie, "Fast Times at Ridgemont High," about adapting a short film that Ms. Meyers had herself adapted from Damon Knight's short story "Special Delivery." Ms. Meyers had done the film for her final student project at the American Film Institute in 1984.</p>
        <p>Ms. Meyers and Ms. Stern charged in the suit that Ms. Heckerling asked to see the film and their treatment for it as a feature-length romantic comedy and that she kept in touch, through Ms. Caplan, for four months before writing to them to say she was not interested in pursuing the project.</p>
        <p>In January 1987, the suit continued, Ms. Meyers and Ms. Stern optioned "Special Delivery" to a production company at Tri-Star Pictures with the understanding that the company would try to develop it as a television movie. A Film's Success</p>
        <p>Ms. Heckerling has denied ever meeting either Ms. Meyers or Ms. Stern. "Look Who's Talking" and its sequel, "Look Who's Talking Too," both starring John Travolta and Kirstie Alley, together have grossed more than $380 million in ticket sales worldwide. In addition, "Look Who's Talking" was No. 1 for six weeks in home-video rentals in the spring of 1990 and broke the top 10 in video sales, according to Billboard magazine. The film also spawned a series on ABC, "Baby Talk."</p>
        <p>Both "Special Delivery" and "Look Who's Talking" depict a woman in her 30's giving birth to her first child, Moses in "Special Delivery" and Mikey in "Look Who's Talking." Both works extend through the first year of the child 's life and conclude with the birth of a girl.</p>
        <p>Though "Special Delivery" focuses on a married couple's adjustment to life with a baby while "Look Who's Talking" follows a mother's search for a suitable father for her son, in both films the babies comment on their surroundings both inside the womb and out.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
