<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Milosevic Stiffens in Talks With U.S. Envoy</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="766460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CONFLICT IN THE BALKANS: IN BELGRADE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SERBIA-INTERNATIONALRELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANCTIONS (ECONOMIC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIPLOMATIC RECOGNITION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KINZER, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILOSEVIC, SLOBODAN (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRASURE, ROBERT (DEPUTYASST SEC)  SLOBODAN MILOSEVIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2DB1639F930A35755C0A963958260" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Milosevic Stiffens in Talks With U.S. Envoy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KINZER, STEPHEN;</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia, June 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The President of Serbia, Slobodan Milosevic, insisted today on new concessions before he will sign an accord committing him to step up pressure on  the Bosnian Serbs.</p>
        <p>An American envoy, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State Robert Frasure, met again today with President Milosevic to offer a deal to lift the crippling United Nations sanctions on Serb-dominated Yugoslavia.  In exchange, Mr. Milosevic would have to recognize the Muslim-led Government of Bosnia and Herzegovina, condemn the hostage-taking by the Bosnian Serbs, and take further steps to seal the border across which the Bosnian Serbs are smuggling supplies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The President of Serbia, Slobodan Milosevic, insisted today on new concessions before he will sign an accord committing him to step up pressure on  the Bosnian Serbs.</p>
        <p>An American envoy, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State Robert Frasure, met again today with President Milosevic to offer a deal to lift the crippling United Nations sanctions on Serb-dominated Yugoslavia.  In exchange, Mr. Milosevic would have to recognize the Muslim-led Government of Bosnia and Herzegovina, condemn the hostage-taking by the Bosnian Serbs, and take further steps to seal the border across which the Bosnian Serbs are smuggling supplies.</p>
        <p>The day's talks took place before the announcement tonight that Mr. Milosevic had served as an intermediary in the release of 120 United Nations peacekeepers held hostage by the Bosnian Serbs.</p>
        <p>One diplomat monitoring the talks said the release of the hostages was likely to stiffen Mr. Milosevic's bargaining stance.</p>
        <p>The release of the hostages "is Milosevic showing his stuff," the diplomat said. "He's saying that he can get something done, that he does have some influence over the Bosnian Serbs. Certainly he would think of that as something  that might strengthen his position in the talks with Frasure.</p>
        <p>"It's a good sign, but the obvious response is that there are still 200 or so hostages still in the hands of the Bosnian Serbs," the diplomat added. "Even if there are just two, it's not an acceptable situation."</p>
        <p>Officials close to the talks are cautious about predicting any deal. They say Mr. Milosevic seems to feel strengthened by the hostage-takings because they add pressure on the outside world to reach an accord. Mr. Milosevic evidently senses the desire among Western nations for a deal, and is trying to extract the best possible bargain.</p>
        <p>According to diplomats in Belgrade, President Milosevic is seeking a permanent lifting of the sanctions rather than the 200-day suspension that Mr. Frasure has offered. He wants the United Nations Secretary General, Boutros Boutros-Ghali, to be responsible for deciding if Yugoslavia is meeting its commitments under any future accord, not the Security Council as Mr. Frasure has proposed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic also wants a commitment that after the sanctions are lifted, Yugoslavia will have access to foreign credit. Mr. Frasure is believed to be offering credits, but only if the European Union agrees on providing them.</p>
        <p>Finally, Mr. Milosevic is said to be insisting that Yugoslavia be allowed to  import as much oil and petroleum as he deems necessary. Western governments are willing to give him access to fuel for factories and civilian vehicles, but  are wary of providing a blank check for fear that some fuel may be used for military purposes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic has been seeking relief from the United Nations sanctions since they were imposed three years ago, and has recently been told by his economic advisers that the sanctions could soon spark another round of hyper-inflation like the one that plagued the country in 1993.</p>
        <p>Some experts here have predicted that an accord may be only hours away. Mr. Milosevic, they note, has often made major policy announcements on weekends in the belief that doing so minimizes the possibility of sudden adverse reactions from the public.</p>
        <p>The government-controlled press, moreover, seems to be preparing people here  for some kind of deal. Whereas in the past it was used to whip up sympathy for the plight of the Serbs in battle zones, the press has in recent weeks largely ignored their ordeals.</p>
        <p>After the recent Serbian defeat in western Slavonia, for example, no pictures of destroyed Serbian homes or sobbing refugees were broadcast here. And when NATO planes bombed Bosnian Serb arms depots last week, the principal television  station led its evening newscasts with a report on murals prepared for the planned Belgrade subway system, and mentioned the raids only briefly.</p>
        <p>In a series of public statements, officials close to President Milosevic have taken an increasingly hard line against the Bosnian Serbs and their leader, Radovan Karadzic. In an interview with a leading German news magazine, Der Spiegel, released in advance of publication Monday, Mr. Milosevic's Foreign Minister, Vladislav Jovanovic, described the hostage-taking by the Bosnian Serbs as "irrational and unacceptable."</p>
        <p>"I tell them that they can be paranoid as individuals or allow their families to be destroyed, but they have no right to destroy an entire people," Mr. Jovanovic said. "We are not going to allow a crazy man to prevent a clever man from arranging his international relations."</p>
        <p>CONFLICT IN THE BALKANS: IN BELGRADE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
