<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Culinary Fantasy Life</title>
    <meta content="29BOOK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19981102T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1057745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="MAKING BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Martin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Making Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3D6113CF93AA15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Culinary Fantasy Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Martin Arnold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Martin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martin Arnold's Making Books column on the popularity of cookbooks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once upon a time, in an empire now long gone, Marcus Gabius Apicius spent his last denarius on a feast. Realizing he had neither the desire nor the discipline to economize in his dining, he committed suicide. But before he did, this epicure of the first century A.D. wrote the oldest known cookbook, ''De Re Coquinaria.'' It was still selling about 900 years later. Which certainly made it a backlist champion. So what Apicius started, no one in book publishing will put asunder. Along with serious religious texts, there's hardly a genre as popular as the cookbook, and a celebrated one sells for years and years and years. In hardcover.</p>
        <p>There is something sensual, almost savory, about a good cookbook, just as there is about good food. Many people who don't cook buy cookbooks simply to read. Harriett Bell, executive editor in charge of cookbooks at Broadway Books, explains that ''a great cookbook takes you somewhere you've never been, like a great novel takes you to a world you never knew about.'' Of course she would see the mystical in the culinary. Her latest, ''Jean-Georges: Cooking at Home With a Four-Star Chef,'' written by Jean-Georges Vongerichten with Mark Bittman (who writes The Minimalist food column for The New York Times), was published last month with a first printing of 45,000 copies and a second of 10,000. The book retails for $40.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Once upon a time, in an empire now long gone, Marcus Gabius Apicius spent his last denarius on a feast. Realizing he had neither the desire nor the discipline to economize in his dining, he committed suicide. But before he did, this epicure of the first century A.D. wrote the oldest known cookbook, ''De Re Coquinaria.'' It was still selling about 900 years later. Which certainly made it a backlist champion. So what Apicius started, no one in book publishing will put asunder. Along with serious religious texts, there's hardly a genre as popular as the cookbook, and a celebrated one sells for years and years and years. In hardcover.</p>
        <p>There is something sensual, almost savory, about a good cookbook, just as there is about good food. Many people who don't cook buy cookbooks simply to read. Harriett Bell, executive editor in charge of cookbooks at Broadway Books, explains that ''a great cookbook takes you somewhere you've never been, like a great novel takes you to a world you never knew about.'' Of course she would see the mystical in the culinary. Her latest, ''Jean-Georges: Cooking at Home With a Four-Star Chef,'' written by Jean-Georges Vongerichten with Mark Bittman (who writes The Minimalist food column for The New York Times), was published last month with a first printing of 45,000 copies and a second of 10,000. The book retails for $40.</p>
        <p>What makes it different from the older famous-chef cookbooks, Ms. Bell says, is that the buyer can actually go home and cook from its recipes. What makes today's cookbooks generally different from many predecessors is that you don't need to be a chemist with a restaurant kitchen to use them. The genre hooks so many people that last year Ms. Bell published Deborah Madison's ''Vegetarian Cooking for Everyone'' at a retail price of $35 and then, when sales took off, had the audacity to increase the price to $40. Try that with a novel, no matter how popular.</p>
        <p>Cookbooks, like fashion, seem to appease wishfulness and the need for fantasy, that ''one-day-I'll-buy-an-Armani'' daydream. Which doesn't mean that all books go unused. But Judith Jones, senior editor at Knopf, who edits both novels and cookbooks, says that ''a huge percentage of people who buy cookbooks don't cook -- they dream that maybe they'll want to do this someday; they want to get a book to know about foods for that day; and the books now have lots of interesting stories about food, as well as recipes.''</p>
        <p>She has been the editor of ''Mastering the Art of French Cooking,'' among other cookbooks, since it was conceived by Simone Beck, Louisette Bertholle and Julia Child in 1961, and has stayed with it through endless printings, now in two volumes. Coming from her next spring is ''A Spoonful of Ginger'' by Nina Simond, which will combine recipes with traditional Chinese medicine, enabling one to cook a tasty dish that will cure a headache.</p>
        <p>Clearly, the potential for food books has not yet been fully explored, but for whatever reason they have become so popular that the larger Barnes &amp; Noble bookstores carry nearly 4,000 food-related titles, according to Lee Stern, the chain's cook and wine book buyer. He attributes a great deal of their popularity to television cooking shows, particularly those on cable. He does believe most buyers actually cook.</p>
        <p>''People go into a cookbook section to buy something they want to eat tonight; the cookbook buyer is very thoughtful,'' he says, adding that the  coffee-table cookbook -- contrived as a mere decoration -- is mostly a thing of the past. The Italian cookbook, he said, is still ''at the top of the pyramid but not the way it was; two or three years ago, the vegetarian seemed played out, but some strong ones are coming again.''</p>
        <p>Jane Dystel, a literary agent who has a number of cookbook writers for clients, also attributes the genre's success largely to the television cooking shows, and to the fact that often the books ''talk more and more about people and the places of food, about the chef's family, as well as about the food and the recipes.''</p>
        <p>Arguably the most fabled of all American cookbooks, although not always the most fashionable, is ''Joy of Cooking,'' first introduced in 1931 by Irma S. Rombauer. It has gone through countless editions, like a dynasty, with Ms. Rombauer being assisted by her daughter, Marion Rombauer Becker. More than 15 million copies have sold, making its backlist a literary oil well. The latest edition  (Scribner), the first since 1975, was a year ago, revised partly by the founder's grandson, Ethan Becker, with the publisher fearlessly shipping more than a million copies in the first six weeks.</p>
        <p>The book's editor, Maria Guarnaschelli , said this edition took three years to produce at a cost of $5 million, including the seven-figure advance, and that the expertise of about 120 food consultants was used to update the work and make it a bit more sophisticated.</p>
        <p>The effort paid off. The book flew out of the publishing house ''performing like a megahit novel,'' Ms. Guarnaschelli said, with joy, adding, ''It's a reference book as well as a recipe book. You can learn about braising and how to bake custards in a water bath.'' Which, of course, is the only way to really manage the heat when cooking a simple custard or a creme brulee.</p>
        <p>Nach Waxman, owner of a Kitchen Arts and Letters, a bookstore in Manhattan specializing in food and wine, said that two-thirds of his customers were food professionals ''buying professional tools. Knives are one tool; books are another.''</p>
        <p>''The general public heats up and cools off about cooking, but it's still becoming a favorite recreational activity,'' he continued. ''In this country we have the luxury to cook as we wish, not for basic nutrition.''</p>
        <p>So, between the professional and the amateur, he sells everything from the latest cookbooks to scholarly works on agriculture to practical books, such as how one can start up an ice-cream factory.</p>
        <p>And for those who want to plunge into deep culinary esoterica, there's ''Tarte a la Creme: Comedy and Gastronomy in Moliere's Theater'' (Ohio State University Press) by Ronald W. Tobin. It only costs $42.50, but it's on back order.</p>
        <p>MAKING BOOKS  Correction:  November 2, 1998, Monday  The ''Making Books'' column on Thursday, about the popularity of cookbooks, misspelled the surname of the author of ''A Spoonful of Ginger,'' a book of recipes applying tenets of traditional Chinese medicine that is to be published in the spring by Knopf. She is Nina Simonds, not Simond.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 2, 1998, Monday</p>
        <p>The ''Making Books'' column on Thursday, about the popularity of cookbooks, misspelled the surname of the author of ''A Spoonful of Ginger,'' a book of recipes applying tenets of traditional Chinese medicine that is to be published in the spring by Knopf. She is Nina Simonds, not Simond.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
