<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Luxury in Recession Land; The Hermes of the World Find New Ways to Prosper In Japan's Weak Economy</title>
    <meta content="Y29GIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1057792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hermes International</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tiffany &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gucci Group Nv</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Louis Vuitton</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6D91E3CF93AA15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Luxury in Recession Land; The Hermes of the World Find New Ways to Prosper In Japan's Weak Economy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Oct. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Luxury goods retailers thrive in Japan even in recession and even as country's overall consumer spending continues to fall; Hermes International plans to open new branch; sales at Tiffany &amp; Co rose 21 percent in first half of year; Gucci Group NV has opened seven stores in Japan since beginning of year and will open flagship store in chic Aoyama neighborhood next spring; Louis Vuitton expects 7 percent to 8 percent increase in sales this year; mainstay of industry are young working women and even high school students, who live at home and have a penchant for expensive brand names; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Perhaps nothing epitomizes the Wonderland-like quality of the Japanese recession like the giant orange Hermes box in the heart of Ginza, Tokyo's most exclusive shopping district.</p>
        <p>For Hermes International, the building-sized box, complete with signature orange packaging and brown ''ribbon,'' is not merely a marketing tool but a reflection of the company's confidence that even in bad times, there will be plenty of Japanese willing to pay hundreds of thousand of yen for one of its handbags. Such confidence is hardly misplaced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Perhaps nothing epitomizes the Wonderland-like quality of the Japanese recession like the giant orange Hermes box in the heart of Ginza, Tokyo's most exclusive shopping district.</p>
        <p>For Hermes International, the building-sized box, complete with signature orange packaging and brown ''ribbon,'' is not merely a marketing tool but a reflection of the company's confidence that even in bad times, there will be plenty of Japanese willing to pay hundreds of thousand of yen for one of its handbags. Such confidence is hardly misplaced.</p>
        <p>Sure, unemployment is at record levels, corporate earnings are sinking, bankruptcies are at a record high, investment is down and the banking system is at the brink of disaster. But luxury goods retailers in Japan are thriving, even as overall consumer spending has continued to fall.</p>
        <p>And while luxury sales in Hong Kong, Singapore and other Asian markets that were once promising engines of growth have stalled -- partly because of their own economic traumas and partly because of a decline in Japanese tourism -- many luxury goods companies continue to post solid gains in Japan.</p>
        <p>''The economy is not so good, but still people want to buy nice things,'' said Hideko Isono, a 30-year-old manicurist who lives with her parents in a suburb north of Tokyo and runs her own business.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it is young working women like Miss Isono, and even high school students, who live at home and have a penchant for expensive brand names, who are chiefly fueling the growth of luxury goods sales here. Sales have also been helped by lower prices, made possible by a slowing economy that has reduced business costs like rent and real estate. And, of course, a lot of the wealthy are immune to hard times.</p>
        <p>Even in recession, Japan continues to be the most important market in Asia for luxury goods companies.</p>
        <p>Just look at sales figures for Tiffany &amp; Company. Sales in Japan rose 21 percent in the first half of the year in yen terms from a year earlier, while sales in the rest of Asia fell 16 percent in local currencies for the same period. And earlier this month, Tiffany said it expected to meet earnings estimates for the third quarter, in large part because robust sales in Japan would offset weak sales in the United States.</p>
        <p>There are other measures of the staying power of luxury goods here. Gucci Group N.V., for instance, has opened seven stores in Japan since the beginning of the year and will open a flagship store in the chic Aoyama neighborhood next spring. ''Japanese consumers are continuing to perceive great value in luxury brands,'' said Domenico De Sole, the president of Gucci.</p>
        <p>Hermes has a three-year backlog of orders in Japan for Kelly bags, made famous by the actress Grace Kelly. The least expensive model sells for 430,000 yen, or about $3,645 at current exchange rates. The Hermes box in Ginza sits on property reportedly bought for $84 million. The company plans to open a flagship store on the site in 2000.</p>
        <p>Louis Vuitton, a unit of LVMH Moet Hennessy Louis Vuitton S.A., expects a 7 percent to 8 percent increase in sales this year.</p>
        <p>Prada, however, is the luxury brand for Miss Isono, whose most recent purchase was a leather wallet. She carries the wallet in a nylon Prada handbag, which she bought at a ''brand store'' in Roppongi, a neighborhood popular with foreign residents and for its night life. ''I like Prada because of its good quality and because it is attractive,'' she said, adding that she found the same characteristics in Gucci and Hermes -- although Hermes was a bit too expensive for her.</p>
        <p>Brand stores specialize in selling luxury goods obtained outside authorized channels of distribution that are sold for prices similar to prices charged in luxury goods boutiques in the United States. That is a bargain here compared with Japanese department stores and the official branches of those same boutiques. The merchandise may not be the latest design, but in handbags, wallets and scarves, that hardly matters. As deregulation has eroded the rigid distribution system here, more and more brand-name goods have found their way to such shops, which are proliferating.</p>
        <p>''Before, everything was really expensive: food, housing, clothes,'' Miss Isono said, providing a firsthand account of a deflationary cycle that many economists, rather than celebrating, actually fear is harming Japan. But consumers seem pleased. ''Now everything is a very good price,'' Miss Isono added, ''so it's easier to buy nice things even if people don't get a bonus or have a lower salary.''</p>
        <p>Because Miss Isono lives at home, she incurs none of the standard living expenses -- rent, food, utilities -- that eat into the incomes of most women like her in Europe or the United States. That is why Gucci's average customer in Japan is between 24 and 35, compared with 35 and 55 in Europe.</p>
        <p>Luxury goods executives estimate that these young women's incomes range from 4 million yen to 6 million yen annually, or $33,900 to $50,800. At the low end of the range, that income would not go far enough to cover a Vuitton bag or Gucci loafers in the United States and pay for rent and groceries, too.</p>
        <p>''The key difference between our business here and in other countries are these young women and the way they live,'' said Kyojiro Hata, the president of Louis Vuitton Japan K.K.</p>
        <p>There are some signs that even those free-spending young women are becoming more cautious, however. A poll of consumers in August by the Nippon Research Institute showed that consumer confidence had wilted most among 20 to 29 year olds, the group that has thus far buoyed overall spending statistics.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Hata sees women in their 20's as fairly impervious to the recession, at least in the short term. ''Restructuring is taking place here, but at higher levels than these women work at,'' he said. ''Current cuts are aimed at higher income, older workers.''</p>
        <p>It is not just young women, though, who are helping luxury goods makers weather the economic fallout here. The cost of business is also declining.</p>
        <p>''Rents are lower and floor space is easier to obtain than ever before,'' said Michiko Shimizu, the president of SAI, a marketing consulting firm. ''Their cost performance is much better, so why not open a few more shops?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hata, of Louis Vuitton, is interested in a parking lot in Aoyama. It is one of the holdings of Japan Leasing, a financing company that recently went bankrupt, and Mr. Hata has visions of a new store on the site.</p>
        <p>He figures the parking lot, which has remained undeveloped despite its prime location because Japan Leasing was seeking an unrealistically high price, will soon come up for sale at a more reasonable price. ''Real estate prices are still high, but they're being forced down,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Lower real estate prices and distribution costs have enabled sellers of luxury goods to push prices lower in their Japanese outlets so that they are more in line with what Japanese shoppers find in Hawaii or Hong Kong. Prices that were once 50 percent higher here than in Hong Kong are now only 20 percent higher and falling.</p>
        <p>As distribution has become more deregulated here, some brand-name merchandise is now showing up in mass merchandising stores like Ito-Yokado and Daiei, as well as the smaller brand stores, where they can sell for 60 percent of department store prices.</p>
        <p>Prices may also be driven lower if a 16 percent import tax on luxury goods is reduced, which is expected as deregulation increases.</p>
        <p>And over the last decade, luxury goods companies have developed strategies for coping with economic downturns, offering expanded product lines that include lower-priced products like key chains, scarves and wallets and the use of cheaper materials like vinyl and fabric instead of leather.</p>
        <p>That does not mean they are ignoring the wealthy, of course. These bedrock customers for luxury goods makers usually are affected far less by an economic downturn than the aspiring upper middle class.</p>
        <p>''We probably benefit less from a boom than some of other luxury companies, but we also don't feel the recession,'' said Mineaki Saito, president of the Hermes Japon Company, which gets less of a boost from younger women because its prices are somewhat higher than those of other luxury goods companies. ''Recession, no recession, our sales have been going up every year since we opened.''</p>
        <p>Junko Kosuge is one of those customers who keeps Hermes' business growing whatever the economic climate. The wife of a doctor, she has a passion for expensive scarves, which she keeps in a glass-fronted antique chest so that she can look at them.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kosuge is awaiting the arrival of a pale pink crocodile skin bag from Italy to add to her collection of Chanel, Gucci and Hermes handbags. She said that she did not expect the bag to cost more than 500,000 yen, or about $4,237 at current exchange rates. (She likes Louis Vuitton bags as well but, she says, ''many, many young women carry them, and at my age, I don't want to bump into them on the train with the same bag.'')</p>
        <p>She insists that she does feel the recession, although she could not really supply an example of its effect on her family. ''People aren't spending money on things they think are wasteful,'' Mrs. Kosuge said. ''I myself feel that way.''</p>
        <p>Isn't a pale pink crocodile bag wasteful? ''No, I don't think so because I was overwhelmed by its attractiveness,'' she said. ''So even if I can only buy one thing like it instead of several, I do because it makes my life fun.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
