<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Church Debate Over Voter Guides</title>
    <meta content="Y29CHR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1057835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1998 CAMPAIGN: RELIGION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christian Coalition</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodstein, Laurie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DF1F3CF93AA15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Church Debate Over Voter Guides</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE GOODSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodstein, Laurie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Christian Coalition, preparing to distribute 45 million voter guides in churches, is meeting increased resistance from liberal advocacy groups and from conservative and moderate ministers who are refusing to distribute guides they say are biased in favor of Republican candidates; coalition holds its guides are nonpartisan, educational materials that compare voting records of candidates, usually on issues central to beliefs of conservative Christians; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Christian Coalition prepares to distribute 45 million voter guides in churches this Sunday -- its most ambitious election-year effort ever -- it is hitting more resistance than ever before from liberal advocacy groups and even from conservative and moderate ministers who contend that the guides are biased in favor of Republican candidates.</p>
        <p>The coalition maintains that its voter guides are nonpartisan, educational materials that compare the voting records of candidates, usually on issues central to the beliefs of conservative Christians, like abortion, homosexuality and vouchers for religious schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Christian Coalition prepares to distribute 45 million voter guides in churches this Sunday -- its most ambitious election-year effort ever -- it is hitting more resistance than ever before from liberal advocacy groups and even from conservative and moderate ministers who contend that the guides are biased in favor of Republican candidates.</p>
        <p>The coalition maintains that its voter guides are nonpartisan, educational materials that compare the voting records of candidates, usually on issues central to the beliefs of conservative Christians, like abortion, homosexuality and vouchers for religious schools.</p>
        <p>Distributing 45 million voter guides means that the Christian Coalition would have to put a guide in the hands of nearly 1 of every 3 Americans registered to vote. To reach its goal, the coalition depends on the cooperation of church pastors, the gatekeepers to the pews.</p>
        <p>But even ministers aligned with the coalition on the issues said in interviews that they were refusing to distribute its voter guides this year.</p>
        <p>Many ministers said the coalition and its guides were tainted by a perceived affiliation with the Republican Party. Some said they did not want to appear partisan before their large and diverse congregations, while others said they did not want to risk jeopardizing their churches' tax-exempt status by handing out partisan campaign materials.</p>
        <p>''I certainly have nothing against the Christian Coalition,'' said the Rev. Rusty Russell, associate minister of Southeast Christian Church, a conservative nondenominational ''megachurch'' with 14,000 members in Louisville, Ky. But a committee at his church decided not to use the coalition's voter guides because, Mr. Russell said, ''we felt like we wanted to stick with something intended to be a little more unbiased.''</p>
        <p>Instead, it will distribute a candidate survey put out by the Family Foundation, a statewide group affiliated with Focus on the Family, a ministry led by James Dobson, the religious broadcaster.</p>
        <p>In September, at the coalition's convention in Washington, several coalition volunteers and church liaisons said in interviews that they had had a difficult time persuading pastors to accept the guides.</p>
        <p>Nelida Kuhlman, a volunteer in New Jersey, said none of the Roman Catholic priests and only half of the Protestant ministers she contacted in Hackensack and Bergenfield agreed to accept them.</p>
        <p>''They're really afraid of losing their tax exemption,'' Ms. Kuhlman said. ''A lot of them don't want to become controversial. The Christian Coalition also has a connotation of being a political lobbying group in Washington.''</p>
        <p>No church has ever lost its tax-exempt status for distributing coalition voter guides.</p>
        <p>The coalition itself, however, has been sued by the Federal Election Commission. The lawsuit contends that in previous elections the coalition coordinated the use of its voter guides, telephone banks and mass mailings to promote Republican candidates, including former President George Bush, Speaker Newt Gingrich, Senator Jesse Helms of North Carolina and Oliver L. North in 1994, when he ran unsuccessfully for a United States Senate seat in Virginia.</p>
        <p>The suit, filed in 1996 and still pending, contends that even if the voter guides do not explicitly favor one candidate, they still violate the law if they are part of a coordinated effort to mobilize specific voters in a contested district.</p>
        <p>Sensing that the lawsuit has made the Christian Coalition vulnerable to accusations of partisanship, two advocacy groups opposed to the coalition have recently sent ''Dear Pastor'' letters to tens of thousands of ministers across the country, warning them away from the coalition's voter guides.</p>
        <p>The Interfaith Alliance, a network of Christian, Jewish and Muslim clergy, most of whom are liberal but some moderate and conservative, has sent 20,000 letters to fellow clergy members in 25 states, accusing the Christian Coalition of ''seeking to transform houses of worship into precinct halls for espousing partisan politics.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Barry W. Lynn, executive director of Americans United for Separation of Church and State, has written letters to 80,000 pastors alerting them to a memorandum written by two Washington tax lawyers warning churches against distributing slanted voters' guides.</p>
        <p>The tax lawyers point to several aspects of the Christian Coalition's guides that potentially violate Federal Election Commission regulations: They list the candidates' stands on only a few, select issues of concern to coalition members (in contrast to the extensive guides issued by the League of Women Voters, for example); they distort the candidates' voting records, saying, for example, that the Democrat supports ''special rights for homosexuals,'' and they distribute most of the guides the Sunday before the election, giving candidates no time to respond to inaccuracies.</p>
        <p>''We have never seen a guide in all of these years that is slanted in such a way as to suggest you vote for a Democrat,'' Mr. Lynn said in an interview. ''They are blatantly partisan appendages of Republican campaign material.''</p>
        <p>The Christian Coalition has responded by directing its field directors and local chapter leaders to give pastors a letter from Randy Tate, executive director of the coalition, calling Mr. Lynn ''the A.C.L.U.'s hand-picked mouthpiece'' and telling pastors not to be ''scared off.''</p>
        <p>''In fact, there is no risk, because Christian Coalition takes great care to see that its voter guides are absolutely correct in accordance with the law,'' Mr. Tate wrote to the pastors.</p>
        <p>He added that Jay Sekulow, head of the American Center for Law and Justice, a group founded by the television evangelist Pat Robertson, had offered ''to defend without charge any church that is sued or threatened because of distributing Christian Coalition voter guides.''</p>
        <p>Of course, many pastors, especially those in conservative evangelical, Pentecostal and Southern Baptist churches, say they are glad to distribute the guides. The coalition says its network is especially strong in Maine, where 900 churches will take the guides, and in Dade County, Fla., where 800 churches have accepted them.</p>
        <p>The Rev. James Merritt, pastor of First Baptist Church in Snellville, Ga., said his church had inserted the coalition's voter guides in its bulletins and would make them available at Sunday services.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of folks out there that don't read, don't keep up, and they really rely on those guides,'' Mr. Merritt said.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, distributing 45 million of anything is an extremely ambitious goal. In previous election years, when, the coalition said, it distributed half that number of voter guides, pastors hostile to the coalition reported receiving boxes with hundreds of voter guides dropped on their church doorsteps the Sunday before the election.</p>
        <p>''That's true,'' Mr. Tate, the coalition's executive director, said in an interview in September. ''In some instances they didn't get into the right hands. In many instances they didn't get distributed.''</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Tate said, the coalition is working to establish 100,000 church liaisons who can calm the fears of the increasing number of pastors who express concern about involvement with the coalition.</p>
        <p>''They have misconceptions,'' Mr. Tate said of the pastors. ''The most common is that somehow it's a violation of church and state to distribute a voter guide, and that anything that talks about candidates is illegal.''</p>
        <p>THE 1998 CAMPAIGN: RELIGION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
