<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witches On Line: Nothing Nearly As Spooky as You Might Imagine</title>
    <meta content="29WICC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1057743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="SCREEN GRAB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Witchcraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ingall, marjorie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Occult Sciences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E5D6113CF93AA15753C1A96E958260" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witches On Line: Nothing Nearly As Spooky as You Might Imagine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARJORIE INGALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ingall, marjorie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>World Wide Web has become a popular medium for witches, who see no contradiction between their earth-based religion and cyberspace; there are an estimated 2,000 witchcraft-related Web sites; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S perfectly reasonable that you'd be able to work magic over the Internet,'' said Kristin Spence, a former editor at Wired magazine. ''It's just another tool. Instead of a cauldron, you're using a keyboard.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Spence is a self-proclaimed witch. She's ''out of the broom closet,'' she said, she's proud, and she's got plenty of company. There are posting and chatting sites for witches (or Wiccans, as the more serious devotees prefer to be known) on Usenet (alt.wicca), Internet relay chat (#wicca) and in on-line conferences (America Online's Pagan Board, the Commons at the Witches' Web, www.witchesweb.com/ commons.html). There's an entire search engine, www.avatarsearch .com, devoted to the occult. The Witches' League of Public Awareness, based in Salem, Mass., of course, even has an area devoted to improving witches' image in the media (www.celticcrow.com).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S perfectly reasonable that you'd be able to work magic over the Internet,'' said Kristin Spence, a former editor at Wired magazine. ''It's just another tool. Instead of a cauldron, you're using a keyboard.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Spence is a self-proclaimed witch. She's ''out of the broom closet,'' she said, she's proud, and she's got plenty of company. There are posting and chatting sites for witches (or Wiccans, as the more serious devotees prefer to be known) on Usenet (alt.wicca), Internet relay chat (#wicca) and in on-line conferences (America Online's Pagan Board, the Commons at the Witches' Web, www.witchesweb.com/ commons.html). There's an entire search engine, www.avatarsearch .com, devoted to the occult. The Witches' League of Public Awareness, based in Salem, Mass., of course, even has an area devoted to improving witches' image in the media (www.celticcrow.com).</p>
        <p>Fritz Jung, Webmaster of the Witches' Voice (www.witchvox .com), a clearinghouse of Wiccan information, estimates that there are 2,000 witchcraft-related Web sites. He says his own site receives, on average, almost 17,000 hits a day. Why does he think there's such a heavy witch presence on line?</p>
        <p>''We realized the medium's communication and networking potential early, and embraced it in a major way,'' Mr. Jung said. ''You could also say that we had a stronger need for the Net. The big religions have long had communication networks in place, but we were very fragmented. The Net was a wonderful opportunity for us to connect.''</p>
        <p>In his nonwitch life (and please, witches disdain the term ''warlock'' -- ''witch'' is sexually nonspecific), Mr. Jung is the management information systems director for a musical instrument retailer in Clearwater, Fla.</p>
        <p>He doesn't see any contradiction in the fact that an earth-based religion thrives in a silicon realm, or that a goddess-focused faith flourishes in a largely male techie preserve. Some witches, in fact, find that witchcraft and computers have a lot in common. ''Programming is like alchemy,'' said Ms. Spence, who signs her E-mail with a smiley emoticon wearing a conical witch hat,</p>
        <p>''It's almost like divination, a magical thing. You have a spell or computer program you want to create, so you find an elegant way to use a main routine and subroutines that refer back to themselves. You construct a system of elements that need to work together in harmony and balance to give the desired outcome.'' Presto.</p>
        <p>Witchcraft, or Wicca (both words are probably derived from the Indo-European root wic, ''to bend''), is a modern take on an ancient pagan belief system.</p>
        <p>Francesca De Grandis, author of  ''Be a Goddess! A Guide to Celtic Spells and Wisdom for Self-Healing, Prosperity and Great Sex'' (Harper San Francisco, 1998), has a site full of rituals and spells. Among them is one ''to free oneself from excessive computer enchantment.'' Her site is www.well.com/user/zthirdrd/WiccanMiscellany. html.</p>
        <p>Carrye De Mers, an editorial assistant at a math publishing company in Emeryville, Calif., has an off-line coven but uses the Web to enhance her spiritual practice. She rattled off the courses she has taken through Pandora's Pagan Web, a site affiliated with a Wiccan bookstore in Miami.</p>
        <p>''Let's see, there's Introductory Tarot, Candle Magick, Urban Pagan and To Stir a Magick Cauldron -- that's the follow-up to Ride a Silver Broomstick.''</p>
        <p>Will Ms. Spence be celebrating Holloween, the most important witches' holiday, in cyberspace?</p>
        <p>''I'm a purist in a lot of ways, so it's hard for me to imagine that those who practice only in cyberspace are getting the full hit,'' she said. ''I'd like to wrench people away from their computers and make them stand on the beach in their bare feet. This is a nature-based religion. But if on line is the catalyst to make people feel safe and not alone in their beliefs, that's great.''</p>
        <p>SCREEN GRAB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
