<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DIARY</title>
    <meta content="12TABL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="964611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE7D9133CF931A25753C1A961958260" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK J. LYONS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MARKETS  Tilting at Exuberance Again  Alan Greenspan, the Federal Reserve chairman, was wearing his Cassandra hat in public again last week. In testimony before Congress, Mr. Greenspan returned to the themes of his famous December ''irrational exuberance'' speech, calling any hopes that the stock market will continue to roar upward at its recent pace unrealistic and warning that inflation remained a looming threat. As usual, he avoided saying definitely whether an interest-rate increase was in the offing, but investors took his remarks to heart and pushed stock and bond prices down.</p>
        <p>MORE IS MORE  Buying the Competition  Federal Express struck a deal to expand into trucking and logistics by agreeing to buy Caliber for $2.7 billion, thereby also acquiring RPS, a big competitor in the business-to-business end of the speedy delivery market. One reason Caliber may have looked especially tempting to the generally acquisition-shy Fedex: Like Fedex (but unlike U.P.S.), Caliber is nonunion. . . . Not long ago, the North Fork Bancorporation had a half-dozen branches and a chairman trying to control costs by telling workers to make do with one pen and one pencil apiece. With a deal last week to buy New York Bancorp for $800 million, its ninth acquisition in as many years, North Fork will become the biggest bank on Long Island, and a serious competitor in the retail backyard of the giant New York City banks -- maybe serious enough to get itself bought in turn.</p>
        <p>LESS IS MORE  Addition by Subtraction  Fed up with trying to persuade the market that its highly profitable finance arm ought to make its stock worth a lot more, the Ford Motor Company decided to hand over its 80.7 percent stake in Associates First Capital to Ford shareholders. The almost $18 billion spinoff accounts for nearly a third of Ford's market value but less than one-twelfth of its second-quarter profits. . . . Champion International also felt the urge to become a purer play, saying it would sell off roughly a quarter of the company to concentrate on coated papers, unbleached paperboard, softwood timberland and distribution. Analysts said Champion could net about $1.1 billion, including the sale of 325,000 acres of timberland, much of it in the environmentally and politically sensitive Adirondack Park in upstate New York.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY STOCKS  Sell on 'Oops,' Buy on Thud  A tale of two losses: On Monday, Silicon Graphics brought investors up short with word that it expected to report a loss for the quarter ended Sept. 30. The market, noting that the company's previous quarter was gangbusters and its competitors in the client-server business are thriving, reacted by hacking a third off its share price. On Tuesday evening, the chip maker Advanced Micro Devices reported an even bigger loss than analysts had been expecting since the company gave warning a month ago. Did the market mind? Not for long. After a rough morning, the stock rallied to close higher and rose again the next day.</p>
        <p>SAFETY  Lock and Unload  The stories are heartbreakers: Children find their parents' handgun in the dresser drawer, they play with it and one winds up maimed or dead. Those stories ought to be growing rarer by the end of next year, when the manufacturers of most handguns made in the United States say they will be shipping all new handguns with a child-safety lock. . . . Chrysler continues to be haunted by allegations of defective rear door latches in the 4.1 million of its mini-vans built before 1996. A Federal jury in Charleston, S.C., awarded $262.5 million to the family of a six-year-old boy thrown from a mini-van in a 1994 traffic accident. Chrysler has a program to replace the latches but has not formally recalled the mini-vans. The company says it will appeal the verdict.</p>
        <p>CURRENCY UNION  The Euro's Bitter Medicine  Getting Europe's economies synchronized for the introduction of the planned common currency in 1999 is proving painful. Germany's central bank felt compelled to head off any hint of inflation with a surprise interest-rate increase, its first tightening in more than five years, despite slow growth and record unemployment rolls. Five neighboring countries swiftly followed suit. In Italy, the center-left coalition Government of Romano Pradi, struggling to trim its too-big-for-the-Euro budget deficit, found itself cutting social welfare spending too deeply for the Communist Party to tolerate. Loss of the Communists' votes in Parliament brought down the Government.</p>
        <p>SOUTHEAST ASIA  Indonesia Calls for Help  Long discredited in geopolitics, the domino theory seems to be reappearing in geofinance. Some of the same pressures that toppled the Thai baht over the summer have since set Indonesia's currency to teetering. Indonesia still has substantial reserves of foreign exchange, but the writing on the wall looked dire enough last week to prompt a request for standby aid from the International Monetary Fund to help stabilize the rupiah. Two more hard-hit currency dominoes, the Malaysian ringgit and Philippine peso, managed gains last week.</p>
        <p>ACCUSATIONS  All the Way to the Top?  The senior F.B.I. agent in the investigation of possible fraud at Columbia/HCA, the nation's biggest hospital chain, called what the Government has uncovered so far a ''systematic corporate scheme'' perpetrated by senior executives -- and not an isolated error or aberration. The chain's billing and accounting practices may not ultimately prove to have been criminally improper, analysts said, but at the least, the company's defenses against pending shareholder lawsuits appear badly undermined by the contents of a 75-page affidavit partly unsealed last week. Neither the company nor its battered stock showed much reaction.</p>
        <p>COINCIDENCES  There's That Word Again  What's hot, black, caffeinated and seemed to figure in every other headline last week? In politics, the long-running Washington donnybrook over campaign finance flared up when videotapes, shot at the famous White House coffees for high-rolling contributors, materialized belatedly. In Silicon Valley, Sun Microsystems sued Microsoft and threatened to yank its license to use Sun's Java programming language on the assertion that Microsoft had twisted Java into another way to seal the hegemony of its Windows operating system. In media, the editor of The Los Angeles Times, Shelby Coffey 3d, resigned, denying that he was driven out by corporate plans to give marketing executives unprecedented sway in the newsroom. Even in the weather report, a hurricane bearing down on Mexico's coffee country made commodity traders jittery at midweek. The storm devastated the coast but largely spared the crop; by Friday the futures pits had calmed down and so had prices, closing up mere pennies from a week earlier and still far below their May peak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MARKETS  Tilting at Exuberance Again  Alan Greenspan, the Federal Reserve chairman, was wearing his Cassandra hat in public again last week. In testimony before Congress, Mr. Greenspan returned to the themes of his famous December ''irrational exuberance'' speech, calling any hopes that the stock market will continue to roar upward at its recent pace unrealistic and warning that inflation remained a looming threat. As usual, he avoided saying definitely whether an interest-rate increase was in the offing, but investors took his remarks to heart and pushed stock and bond prices down.</p>
        <p>MORE IS MORE  Buying the Competition  Federal Express struck a deal to expand into trucking and logistics by agreeing to buy Caliber for $2.7 billion, thereby also acquiring RPS, a big competitor in the business-to-business end of the speedy delivery market. One reason Caliber may have looked especially tempting to the generally acquisition-shy Fedex: Like Fedex (but unlike U.P.S.), Caliber is nonunion. . . . Not long ago, the North Fork Bancorporation had a half-dozen branches and a chairman trying to control costs by telling workers to make do with one pen and one pencil apiece. With a deal last week to buy New York Bancorp for $800 million, its ninth acquisition in as many years, North Fork will become the biggest bank on Long Island, and a serious competitor in the retail backyard of the giant New York City banks -- maybe serious enough to get itself bought in turn.</p>
        <p>LESS IS MORE  Addition by Subtraction  Fed up with trying to persuade the market that its highly profitable finance arm ought to make its stock worth a lot more, the Ford Motor Company decided to hand over its 80.7 percent stake in Associates First Capital to Ford shareholders. The almost $18 billion spinoff accounts for nearly a third of Ford's market value but less than one-twelfth of its second-quarter profits. . . . Champion International also felt the urge to become a purer play, saying it would sell off roughly a quarter of the company to concentrate on coated papers, unbleached paperboard, softwood timberland and distribution. Analysts said Champion could net about $1.1 billion, including the sale of 325,000 acres of timberland, much of it in the environmentally and politically sensitive Adirondack Park in upstate New York.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY STOCKS  Sell on 'Oops,' Buy on Thud  A tale of two losses: On Monday, Silicon Graphics brought investors up short with word that it expected to report a loss for the quarter ended Sept. 30. The market, noting that the company's previous quarter was gangbusters and its competitors in the client-server business are thriving, reacted by hacking a third off its share price. On Tuesday evening, the chip maker Advanced Micro Devices reported an even bigger loss than analysts had been expecting since the company gave warning a month ago. Did the market mind? Not for long. After a rough morning, the stock rallied to close higher and rose again the next day.</p>
        <p>SAFETY  Lock and Unload  The stories are heartbreakers: Children find their parents' handgun in the dresser drawer, they play with it and one winds up maimed or dead. Those stories ought to be growing rarer by the end of next year, when the manufacturers of most handguns made in the United States say they will be shipping all new handguns with a child-safety lock. . . . Chrysler continues to be haunted by allegations of defective rear door latches in the 4.1 million of its mini-vans built before 1996. A Federal jury in Charleston, S.C., awarded $262.5 million to the family of a six-year-old boy thrown from a mini-van in a 1994 traffic accident. Chrysler has a program to replace the latches but has not formally recalled the mini-vans. The company says it will appeal the verdict.</p>
        <p>CURRENCY UNION  The Euro's Bitter Medicine  Getting Europe's economies synchronized for the introduction of the planned common currency in 1999 is proving painful. Germany's central bank felt compelled to head off any hint of inflation with a surprise interest-rate increase, its first tightening in more than five years, despite slow growth and record unemployment rolls. Five neighboring countries swiftly followed suit. In Italy, the center-left coalition Government of Romano Pradi, struggling to trim its too-big-for-the-Euro budget deficit, found itself cutting social welfare spending too deeply for the Communist Party to tolerate. Loss of the Communists' votes in Parliament brought down the Government.</p>
        <p>SOUTHEAST ASIA  Indonesia Calls for Help  Long discredited in geopolitics, the domino theory seems to be reappearing in geofinance. Some of the same pressures that toppled the Thai baht over the summer have since set Indonesia's currency to teetering. Indonesia still has substantial reserves of foreign exchange, but the writing on the wall looked dire enough last week to prompt a request for standby aid from the International Monetary Fund to help stabilize the rupiah. Two more hard-hit currency dominoes, the Malaysian ringgit and Philippine peso, managed gains last week.</p>
        <p>ACCUSATIONS  All the Way to the Top?  The senior F.B.I. agent in the investigation of possible fraud at Columbia/HCA, the nation's biggest hospital chain, called what the Government has uncovered so far a ''systematic corporate scheme'' perpetrated by senior executives -- and not an isolated error or aberration. The chain's billing and accounting practices may not ultimately prove to have been criminally improper, analysts said, but at the least, the company's defenses against pending shareholder lawsuits appear badly undermined by the contents of a 75-page affidavit partly unsealed last week. Neither the company nor its battered stock showed much reaction.</p>
        <p>COINCIDENCES  There's That Word Again  What's hot, black, caffeinated and seemed to figure in every other headline last week? In politics, the long-running Washington donnybrook over campaign finance flared up when videotapes, shot at the famous White House coffees for high-rolling contributors, materialized belatedly. In Silicon Valley, Sun Microsystems sued Microsoft and threatened to yank its license to use Sun's Java programming language on the assertion that Microsoft had twisted Java into another way to seal the hegemony of its Windows operating system. In media, the editor of The Los Angeles Times, Shelby Coffey 3d, resigned, denying that he was driven out by corporate plans to give marketing executives unprecedented sway in the newsroom. Even in the weather report, a hurricane bearing down on Mexico's coffee country made commodity traders jittery at midweek. The storm devastated the coast but largely spared the crop; by Friday the futures pits had calmed down and so had prices, closing up mere pennies from a week earlier and still far below their May peak.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
