<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Film Makers Survive a Skirmish With Revolution Buffs</title>
    <meta content="12FRAU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971019T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="964489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: LOWER MANHATTAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Revolutionary War, American (1775-83)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fraunces Tavern (Nyc)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York American Revolution Round Table (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumer, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramirez, Anthony</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Liberty! The American Revolution (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3D6123CF931A25753C1A961958260" item-length="551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Film Makers Survive a Skirmish With Revolution Buffs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramirez, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Documentary film maker Ronald Blumer shows excerpt from mini-series Liberty! The American Revolution, at recent meeting at Fraunces Tavern of New York American Revolution Round Table; film will be broadcast in November on public television (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At Fraunces Tavern on Pearl Street, where George Washington said farewell to his troops in 1783, there were no tricorner hats, no powdered wigs and, judging by the mostly smiling crowd last week, no wooden teeth. There was, however, not a little nervousness.</p>
        <p>''These people live in the 18th century,'' whispered Ronald Blumer about the 50 or so people who had gathered for the evening. ''Showing what we've worked on to this particular group is just insane.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At Fraunces Tavern on Pearl Street, where George Washington said farewell to his troops in 1783, there were no tricorner hats, no powdered wigs and, judging by the mostly smiling crowd last week, no wooden teeth. There was, however, not a little nervousness.</p>
        <p>''These people live in the 18th century,'' whispered Ronald Blumer about the 50 or so people who had gathered for the evening. ''Showing what we've worked on to this particular group is just insane.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blumer, a documentary film maker, is also a member of this group, the New York American Revolution Round Table, a 39-year-old club of 130 history buffs, including engineers, dentists, securities analysts and lawyers. What Mr. Blumer was showing them last Tuesday night was an excerpt from the six-hour series he has spent the last five years writing, ''Liberty! The American Revolution.'' Scheduled to be broadcast next month on public television, it was produced and directed by Mr. Blumer's wife, Muffie Meyer, and Ellen Hovde.</p>
        <p>This was the first time anyone outside the documentary team, Middlemarch Films, had seen any part of the film. Given the audience, it was no wonder that Mr. Blumer and Ms. Meyer, who was also there, were feeling nervous. The members of the Round Table, who maintain a Web site (http://samson.kean.edu/leew/ arrt/index.html) and meet five times a year at Fraunces Tavern for a dinner of London broil, are fans of the telling detail, such as the wines Thomas Jefferson preferred.</p>
        <p>On this night, the club seems ready to pounce. Thomas Fleming, a member who wrote the book accompanying the series, starts by showing a slide of a 1774 portrait by Johann Zoffany of the monarch who lost the war, King George III. ''It's backward,'' somebody shouts.</p>
        <p>The crowd warms, however, when Mr. Fleming switches slides to a portrait of George Washington.  There are cheers and hearty murmurs of ''our George.'' There are knowing smiles when Mr. Fleming describes Washington as ''the finest horseman of his age, who liked a good Madeira and an off-color joke.''</p>
        <p>By the time the film is shown, the members are in the mood. The 20-minute excerpt, based on diaries and other contemporary sources, focuses on the bleak days near the climax of the war. By December 1780, the British had occupied the South for six months and armed American gangs preyed on Tories, people still loyal to England. Sent by Washington to re-establish order, Gen. Nathanael Greene is shocked by what he finds. ''Like the British invaders, we too have become savages,'' General Greene laments. ''There's not a day goes by that some Tory, deluded as he may be, is not shot to death, just for standing in his doorway.''</p>
        <p>When the lights come up, the club members applaud, and the questions that follow are admiring. Obviously relieved, Mr. Blumer asks, ''How come you didn't find any mistakes?''</p>
        <p>A woman in the crowd shoots back, ''I wouldn't push that if I were you.''</p>
        <p>ANTHONY RAMIREZ</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: LOWER MANHATTAN  Correction:  October 19, 1997, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in the Neighborhood Report last Sunday about the New York American Revolution Round Table misstated the address of the group's Web site. It is http://samson.kean.edu/leew/arrt/index.html.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 19, 1997, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in the Neighborhood Report last Sunday about the New York American Revolution Round Table misstated the address of the group's Web site. It is http://samson.kean.edu/leew/arrt/index.html.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
