<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tests, Too, Have Their Failings</title>
    <meta content="04APPL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Imperfect Measures" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="927602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Imperfect Measures"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (Ethnic, Racial, Religious)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Creole Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Russian Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chinese New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Education Department (NYS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Board of Regents (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, Richard P (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applebome, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guinier, Lani</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ravitch, Diane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lemann, Nicholas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Russian Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFDE1430F937A35756C0A961958260" item-length="1214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tests, Too, Have Their Failings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Importance of standardized tests in determining educational opportunities discussed in light of proposal to offer New York State Regents exams in Spanish, Haitian Creole, Russian and Chinese; photo; Diana Ravitch says tests promote meritocracy in which poor student with good test scores can do better than rich student with low scores; Nicholas Lemann warns that tests tend to reproduce, not negate, family background; Lani Guinier, promoting affirmative action, argues against standardized tests (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW York's Education Commissioner and Governor offered opposing views last week on an issue that goes to the heart of educational quality and opportunity in an increasingly diverse America: should the state offer its college-preparatory Regents examinations in languages other than English?</p>
        <p>The Commissioner, Richard P. Mills, was concerned that English-only Regents exams -- which New York uses to award merit scholarships -- don't fairly test the math or science skills of the state's many immigrants. But the controversy over his proposal to offer test booklets in Spanish, Haitian Creole, Russian and Chinese is only one of many cases questioning the enormous and increasingly contentious role that testing plays in American education.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW York's Education Commissioner and Governor offered opposing views last week on an issue that goes to the heart of educational quality and opportunity in an increasingly diverse America: should the state offer its college-preparatory Regents examinations in languages other than English?</p>
        <p>The Commissioner, Richard P. Mills, was concerned that English-only Regents exams -- which New York uses to award merit scholarships -- don't fairly test the math or science skills of the state's many immigrants. But the controversy over his proposal to offer test booklets in Spanish, Haitian Creole, Russian and Chinese is only one of many cases questioning the enormous and increasingly contentious role that testing plays in American education.</p>
        <p>From S.A.T. college-admission tests to President Clinton's proposed national tests for reading and math, from public schools in New York to public universities in Mississippi, this is the golden age both of testing and of disputes over how schools test, what tests measure and how fair they are.</p>
        <p>At a time when education is seen as the essential route to opportunity, it is not just the details of specific tests that are at issue, but the nature of what the writer Nicholas Lemann calls America's evolving meritocracy, and what the legal scholar Lani Guinier calls America's evolving testocracy: the network of standardized tests that determine access to scholarships and the best schools and colleges.</p>
        <p>''As access to educational quality, who gets a limited number of places in schools and jobs, becomes more competitive, we're seeing many of the big social issues in American life played out on the playing field of tests,'' said Robert Schaeffer, a spokesman for the National Center for Fair and Open Testing, or Fair Test, which is critical of the reliance on standardized tests.</p>
        <p>A Search for Standards</p>
        <p>Across the country, educators increasingly depend on standardized tests even as challenges to their use spread. Current controversies include the following:</p>
        <p>* In New York, supporters of Commissioner Mills's proposal say immigrants should not be penalized since the Regents are used for both high-school graduation and merit scholarships, and students would still have to pass an English Regents test. Critics say testing in other languages would deter students from learning English.</p>
        <p>* In Mississippi, the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit ruled last month that the state's five white public universities continue to discriminate against black students by using ACT college-admission scores to award scholarships. Of almost $6.9 million dispensed in 1992-93, $6.6 million went to whites.</p>
        <p>* Mr. Clinton, in an effort to raise academic standards, has proposed what would be the first national tests, a reading test for fourth graders and a math test for eighth graders. They would not be mandatory.</p>
        <p>* Despite persistent claims that standardized tests are culturally biased in favor of white males, the bans on affirmative action in California and Texas now have the potential to make those states, two of the nation's most diverse, more reliant on standardized tests than ever.</p>
        <p>The role of standardized testing in American life is not a new issue. For decades many experts have argued against overreliance on what Ms. Guinier calls ''one size fits all'' paper and pencil tests. Many critics prefer systems in which students build portfolios of their work, or tests like the revised National Assessment of Education Progress, released last week, which has multiple-choice questions but also asks for written analyses of scientific experiments.</p>
        <p>Why then are traditional multiple-choice tests more influential now than ever before?</p>
        <p>In higher education, when the best colleges and professional schools are deluged with applicants, standardized tests like the S.A.T. are still seen as a cost-effective  and time-effective way to sort applicants. Even if schools wanted to downplay test scores, the near hysteria about rankings like those in U.S. News &amp; World Report's annual college guide, which penalizes colleges for low S.A.T. averages and rewards them for high ones, would argue against it.</p>
        <p>In elementary and secondary education, the sense of urgency about improving educational quality has led lawmakers to insist on ''objective'' measures of performance as a way to gauge how effectively tax dollars are being used.</p>
        <p>And the argument over affirmative action is regularly framed in terms of racial or ethnic preference versus merit -- with merit defined by grades and supposedly objective tests.</p>
        <p>Many political and business interests agree that better measures of performance are needed, and that schools and students won't improve without a way to adequately assess their performance.</p>
        <p>Diane Ravitch, a senior research scholar at New York University, said standardized tests have become increasingly valuable as looser grading standards have made high-school grades less useful.</p>
        <p>''Tests shouldn't be the only thing,'' she said, ''but a real meritocracy replaces inherited privilege with merit, so a poor kid with good test scores can in fact do better than a rich kid with bad test scores.''</p>
        <p>Mirroring Society Too Well</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lemann, who is writing a book on meritocracy in America, said standardized testing like the S.A.T. tended to reproduce, not negate, family background; for as long as there have been such tests, well-to-do children from families with high levels of education have done much better than poorer ones.</p>
        <p>He argues, however, that there are limits to tests' power as arbiters of opportunity. Higher education in America is available to almost everyone, even if Harvard and Yale are not, so low test scores do not rule out a college education as in countries with make-or-break national examinations. And while success in some professions -- law, for example -- is closely linked to attending elite schools, in many other fields -- business and entertainment, for example -- it is not.</p>
        <p>Still, like Ms. Guinier, he argues for a more sophisticated analysis of what tests measure and their fairness.</p>
        <p>Ms. Guinier and a colleague at the University of Pennsylvania Law School, Susan Sturm, argue in a widely circulated paper, ''The Future of Affirmative Action: Reclaiming the Innovative Ideal,'' that the question least addressed in the national debate about affirmative action and merit is what standardized tests measure and how well they do it.</p>
        <p>They maintain that when almost two-thirds of the people entering the work force are projected to be women and members of racial minorities, the tests in use are becoming less and less reliable and fair in apportioning educational opportunity. ''The existing meritocracy creates a modern-day aristocracy that gives further advantages to the already advantaged and creates barriers for those who are not,'' they wrote.</p>
        <p>The issue traverses often hidden fault lines of economic class. If tests like the S.A.T. often serve to a large degree as proxies for class, radically de-emphasizing them could dramatically redefine who gets into Harvard or Berkeley -- to the disadvantage of the largely privileged students who are admitted now.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Lemann says, it's essential to remember that while tests matter, the larger issues of education and equity matter more. ''You can't fix education by fixing testing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Imperfect Measures</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
