<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Restaurants Roll Out the Carpet for Mom</title>
    <meta content="4CART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="DINING OUT" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="927355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mother's Day</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scholem, Richard J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mother's Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E5D81031F937A35756C0A961958260" item-length="1366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Restaurants Roll Out the Carpet for Mom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD J. SCHOLEM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scholem, Richard J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of Long Island restaurant news; restaurants prepare for Mother's Day, their biggest day of year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEXT Sunday, Mother's Day, is the biggest restaurant day of the year. This week, the Island's eating places will be busily trimming and simplifying their menus, bolstering their wait staffs and preparing for the expected onslaught.</p>
        <p>At Veranda, in Glen Cove, diners will receive a complementary plate of hot hors d'oeuvres. An old-fashioned pineapple upside down cake will be the dessert at Estia in Amagansett.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEXT Sunday, Mother's Day, is the biggest restaurant day of the year. This week, the Island's eating places will be busily trimming and simplifying their menus, bolstering their wait staffs and preparing for the expected onslaught.</p>
        <p>At Veranda, in Glen Cove, diners will receive a complementary plate of hot hors d'oeuvres. An old-fashioned pineapple upside down cake will be the dessert at Estia in Amagansett.</p>
        <p>The set menu at Barney's, in Locust Valley, features crab cakes, rack of lamb and ostrich. Shelled lobster with cognac cream is one of the dishes at the Old Inlet Inn in Bellport. At Gurney's, in Montauk, the dessert menu includes Amaretto cheesecake and mocha-whisky pie.  The Mother's Day brunch at 75 Main, in Southampton, includes complementary bloody Mary's or screwdrivers.</p>
        <p>The six restaurants typify the culinary diversity and price range of Mother's Day meals on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Veranda, at 75 Cedar Swamp Road (759-0394), will be offering a special four-course, $25 Mother's Day prix fixe from noon to 2 P.M. The entree course will include choices of veal (piccata, marsala or francaise), chicken (chatelaine, Forestiera or Sorrentino), salmon Dijon or fish du jour with potato crust.</p>
        <p>Estia, 177 Main Street (267-6320), will prepare a $19, three-course dinner. It includes a salad and three entree choices: roasted Cervena venison, Chilean sea bass in a miso broth and Amagansett bouillabaisse.</p>
        <p>Barney's at 315 Buckram Road (671-6300), will be serving dinner on Mother's Day from 1 to 8 P.M. The cost for three courses will be $36.95 with a $10 children's menu also available.</p>
        <p>Barney's has also introduced three spring wine flights culled from its 50 wines by the glass selection.</p>
        <p>At the Old Inlet Inn, at 108 South Country Road(286-2650), the entrees include poached North Atlantic salmon and prime veal with mushrooms and sage.</p>
        <p>Gurney's Inn Resort and Spa, 290 Old Montauk Highway (668-2660), will be offering a special menu and heart-healthy dinners with dishes like a seasoned medley of grilled fresh vegetables and whole-wheat pasta, both served with potato, vegetable, homemade assorted rolls and cornbread. There's also a menu for mother's little helpers with a fruit cup, chicken parmigiana or English-cut prime rib with whipped potato, vegetable and ice cream for $10.95.</p>
        <p>75 Main, (288-7575) will be offering a three-course, prix fixe brunch from 9:30 A.M. to 4 P.M. Diners can choose homemade Belgium waffles with roasted pears and vanilla whipped cream, a three-egg omelet with home fries, toast and a choice of fillings or poached eggs Benedict with home fries and roast-vegetable salad for a main course.</p>
        <p>Openings</p>
        <p>Orlando's, a longtime landmark restaurant at 15 New Street in Huntington, closed many months ago. Since then the guessing about who might purchase its centrally situated site has continued. It ended a couple of weeks ago when workers began construction on Cafe Pello. The new restaurant is owned by Roger Bedoian, along with a group of investors. Mr. Bedoian previously managed Cafe Spasso and Caffe Baci in Westbury. Cafe Pello is expected to be, like them, a casual, modern pasta and pizza cafe. It is scheduled to open in late June.</p>
        <p>Il Farolo has replaced Laurentide as the restaurant at the Montauk Manor Hotel in Montauk (668-4400). Earlier this year, a trio of Huntington restaurateurs changed the French spot into a moderately priced ($11.75 to $21.95 for entrees) Northern Italian restaurant. Gustavo Graziano and Carlos Rojas, the chefs and owners of Il Farolo, and Dean Alonso, its manager, have been associated with the Pasta Tree in Huntington, Maxxa Luna in Commack and Il Subito in Kings Park. Mr. Graziano also was a chef at the Rainbow Room in Manhattan. Il Farolo, the lantern or lighthouse in Italian, has 45 seats and an outdoor patio.</p>
        <p>Sharkey's, a new restaurant and bar, is opening in mid-May where Jolson's was on Montauk Highway in Napeague.</p>
        <p>Six Long Islanders including Peter Honerkamp, the managing partner of the Stephen Talkhouse in Amagansett, own the new spot. Peter Thomas, who cooked at the Three Mile Harbor Inn in East Hampton, will be the chef.</p>
        <p>The menu will emphasize seafood, pastas and steak. The restaurant will serve both lunch and dinner.</p>
        <p>Chili Peppers will soon open where the Harbor Cove Cafe was in Sag Harbor. The new spot will have a Latin slant, featuring dishes like green peppers with seafood and chorizo filling and a Colombian dish of grilled thin steak, chicharon, sweet plantains and avocado served with rice and beans.</p>
        <p>Max's Grille and Tavern will open in June at 13 North Park Avenue in Rockville Centre across from the Fantasy Movie Theater. It will be a classic 1940's American grill and tavern. Nothing on the menu or among the specials will be priced higher than $18. The menu will consist of a combination of traditional and cutting-edge comfort food. Max's Grille and Tavern and George Martin in Rockville Centre, as well as Nick DiAngelo's in Merrick, are all owned by George Korten and his associates.</p>
        <p>Chef's Corner</p>
        <p>Jean Marc Lozach of Ronkonkoma is the new executive chef at Abbott's Steakhouse in Happaugue (435-0505). Mr. Lozach, who apprenticed under his father, Amede, then the executive chef at Le Cote Basque, has since worked as a sous chef and saucier at La Reserve, Tatou and the Stanhope Hotel in the city.</p>
        <p>Jeanine DiMenna, formerly banquet pastry chef and garde manger chef of the Harrison House in Glen Cove, is the new sous chef at Page One in Glen Cove (676-2800).</p>
        <p>Page One is now offering a $25, three-course menu Sunday through Thursday. Entree possibilities include onion-crusted chicken with Minnesota wild rice, spinach and sherry wine demiglace and lobster ravioli with gulf shrimp, asparagus and lobster tarragon sauce.</p>
        <p>The Hallockville Museum Farm and Folk Life Center will be holding an herb day on Saturday from 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. at the Museum Farm and Folk Life Center, 6038 Sound Avenue in Riverhead. Marianne Kay Preston and Jane Wilson Morton, North Shore cookbook authors, will be on hand to sign their cookbook, ''The Fresh Herb Companion,'' and offer tastings of some of their recipes. For information call 298-5292.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday at 1 P.M. raw bar clam shuckers representing the Catalina Seafood Company of Mineola, the Jolly Fisherman of Roslyn, the Crab House of Great Neck, Paddy McGee's of Island Park, Louie's of Port Washington and the River Bay Bar and Grill, will gather at the River Bay in Williston Park to compete for the clam shuckers challenge cup.</p>
        <p>The public is invited to attend. A $12 ticket entitles guests to a ringside seat and unlimited draft beer and clams from 1 to 2 P.M. Proceeds from the $12 ticket will go to the Independent Group Home Living Program, a Long Island nonprofit agency.</p>
        <p>Wine Tastings</p>
        <p>San Marco Restaurant is presenting an evening of fine wines and dining featuring a selection from the Cuvaison, Freemark Abbey, Markham and Quady Vineyards in the Napa Valley along with a five-course, $57.50 dinner. The main course is roasted stuffed suckling pig.</p>
        <p>Potpourri</p>
        <p>Great Restaurants of Long Island, a slick magazine that devotes a full page to each of 88 restaurants whose food is rated 18 or higher by the Zagat Dining Guide, is now being sold at 700 retail locations on the Island and 300 in Manhattan, including bookstores, supermarkets and vineyards and at Lincoln Center, Pennsylvania Station and Grand Central Terminal.</p>
        <p>The first issue, which sells for $2, came out last month. An updated second edition will be distributed in October by Great American Restaurants of Long Island magazine in Plainview (349-5979). Morris Sender, the publisher, is a former advertising agency art director and graphic designer.</p>
        <p>Each of the restaurant listings contains a dining room photograph, a sample menu, a descriptive narrative, hours, the amount of an average check and what constitutes proper attire.</p>
        <p>A map showing the location of each restaurant, as well as articles about local chefs and restaurateurs, are also in the magazine as are columns by Tom Schaudel, a chef and co-founder of the Long Island Food Experience, Peter Carroll, owner of Lenz Winery, and Michael Todd, publisher of Grapezine.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
