<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Viagra Gains Some Advocates As Treatment For Lung Disease</title>
    <meta content="10VIAG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/10/business/10viagra.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1573022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Viagra (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Levitra (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cialis (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impotence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pulmonary Hypertension</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pfizer Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Viagra (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Impotence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Levitra (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Cialis (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Pfizer Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E6DF1038F933A25757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Viagra Gains Some Advocates As Treatment For Lung Disease</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Viagra Gains Some Advocates as Treatment for Lung Disease</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollack, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Viagra, Pfizer drug for erectile dysfunction, is being tested for treatment of pulmonary hypertension, rare but deadly disease, affecting mainly women, in which extremely high pressure in artery that carries blood from heart to lungs can make even routine tasks an ordeal; clinical trial in India, involving only 12 patients, found that Viagra increased ability of patients to exercise by 40 percent; Pfizer expects results of its own much larger and more definitive trial around middle of year; some doctors and insurance companies say they are concerned about use of Viagra to treat pulmonary hypertension, contending it has not been proved effective in rigorous clinical trials; graph shows total prescriptions for Viagra and two other drugs for erectile dysfunction, Levitra anbd Cialis; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Diane Adkins, who has a life-threatening lung disease, used to take a drug that cost more than $100,000 a year and that had to be pumped round the clock into a vein through a hole in her chest. Now she has replaced it with a pill that costs about $10,000 a year.</p>
        <p>But her insurance company will not pay for the cheaper drug, even though it paid for the more expensive one. As the company explained in a letter, ''Your benefit program covers this medication for men over the age of eighteen (18) only.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The blue pill that treats erectile dysfunction may have a new role in treating pulmonary hypertension, a rare but deadly disease that afflicts mainly women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Diane Adkins, who has a life-threatening lung disease, used to take a drug that cost more than $100,000 a year and that had to be pumped round the clock into a vein through a hole in her chest. Now she has replaced it with a pill that costs about $10,000 a year.</p>
        <p>But her insurance company will not pay for the cheaper drug, even though it paid for the more expensive one. As the company explained in a letter, ''Your benefit program covers this medication for men over the age of eighteen (18) only.''</p>
        <p>The drug is Viagra. Wisecracks aside, the blue pill that treats erectile dysfunction, a common but less than fatal male malady, may have a new role in treating pulmonary hypertension, a rare but deadly disease that afflicts mainly women.</p>
        <p>Results of a clinical trial in India, published this week in The Journal of the American College of Cardiology, showed that Viagra increased the ability of patients to exercise by about 40 percent. The authors said that was greater than the effect seen with other drugs in different trials. Although the trial involved only 22 patients, it was the first randomized test to compare Viagra against a placebo for pulmonary hypertension, the journal said.</p>
        <p>Pfizer, the manufacturer of Viagra, said it expected results of its own much larger and more definitive trial around the middle of the year. Investigators expect to present results at the American Heart Association's annual meeting in November.</p>
        <p>But because doctors are allowed to prescribe a drug for any use, once it wins regulatory approval, some are already using Viagra for pulmonary hypertension. The drug is even being given to babies.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was a joke,'' said Drew Walen of Nashville, recalling his reaction when a doctor told him to give the drug daily to his infant son, George, whose lungs did not develop properly because of a congenital problem.</p>
        <p>Pulmonary hypertension is different from hypertension, the common condition of high blood pressure. The pulmonary disease involves extremely high pressure in the artery that carries blood from the heart to the lungs to pick up oxygen. The disease, also called pulmonary arterial hypertension, can make even routine tasks an ordeal.</p>
        <p>''I got to the point where I couldn't change my clothes without getting out of breath,'' said Ms. Adkins, a 48-year old vice president at a floor-covering company who lives in Jensen Beach, Fla.</p>
        <p>For Pfizer, approval of Viagra as a treatment for pulmonary hypertension could ease some of the criticism that drug companies focus too much on so-called lifestyle drugs. In a small way, it could help buttress Viagra sales as new competitors eat into the market for impotence medications. It also might help Pfizer extend the patent protection on the drug.</p>
        <p>Some doctors and insurance companies say they have concerns about this use of Viagra, saying it has not been proved effective in rigorous clinical trials, whereas other drugs have. Patients with pulmonary hypertension use the drug every day and in higher doses than men who use it before sex, potentially raising new risks.</p>
        <p>''I have some ethical issues in using an experimental drug in place of an approved drug,'' said Dr. Richard Channick of the University of California, San Diego, who said Viagra was being overused. Dr. Channick is a consultant to Actelion, a Swiss company with an approved drug for the disease.</p>
        <p>Robert Wanovich, manager of clinical services at Highmark, Ms. Adkins's insurer, said Viagra was not covered because it had not been proved to work for pulmonary hypertension. He conceded, however, that because insurance claims do not specify how a drug is being used, a man using Viagra for the lung disease could be reimbursed ''and we would never know.''</p>
        <p>Though only about 100,000 people in the United States and Europe have pulmonary hypertension, three drugs have already been approved for the condition and several others are on the way. Executives attribute the high degree of competition for treating such a rare disease to two factors. First, the disease has become better understood. And second, if a drug has a high enough price and is taken every day, sales can reach several hundred million dollars a year, even in a small group of patients.</p>
        <p>''A patient population that looks like 100,000 has the equivalent economic value of a million patients or more,'' said Dr. Bruce D. Given, chief executive of Encysive Pharmaceuticals, which is developing a drug for the disease.</p>
        <p>Roland Haefeli, spokesman for Actelion, said the patient population might grow because doctors, who often miss the condition, are looking more carefully now that treatments are available.</p>
        <p>Though far from cures for pulmonary hypertension, the new drugs have helped improve the outlook for patients.</p>
        <p>''In 1999, what I would have said to you is that 50 percent of patients die within two years of diagnosis,'' said Rino Aldrighetti, president of the Pulmonary Hypertension Association, a patient group. ''Now we are looking at five years.''</p>
        <p>Some doctors say they prescribe Viagra because it has worked in small trials, is generally safe and can be cheaper than the approved drugs.</p>
        <p>''We've used it a lot empirically, and it does work,'' said Dr. Robyn J. Barst, an expert on pulmonary hypertension at Columbia University and a lead investigator in the Pfizer trials.</p>
        <p>Pfizer said it would sell a pulmonary hypertension drug under a different name and in a different form from Viagra to prevent prescription errors. Investigators in the clinical trials said the drug was being provided as a round white pill, not a blue diamond-shaped one, and in doses different from those used for erectile dysfunction.</p>
        <p>Joel W. Morris, a Pfizer spokesman, said the company had not decided whether the pulmonary drug would sell for a higher price than Viagra, known generically as sildenafil citrate.</p>
        <p>Pulmonary hypertension is the only new use for which Pfizer is testing the drug. The company recently dropped tests on Viagra for female sexual dysfunction, a potentially huge market, after results were disappointing. Viagra, which had worldwide sales last year of $1.9 billion, faces competition from two new drugs for erectile dysfunction, Cialis and Levitra, which together claim a third of new prescriptions in the United States.</p>
        <p>Given the small patient population, sales of Viagra for pulmonary hypertension are not expected to be that big for Pfizer. Mr. Morris, the Pfizer spokesman, said the company was pursuing the lung disease treatment because there was an unmet medical need and because the company had been urged to do so by doctors, who had begun testing the drug on their own.</p>
        <p>But he conceded that under American law, the company might get a longer respite from generic competition for Viagra because it was testing the drug in children, something that can be done for pulmonary hypertension but not for erectile dysfunction.</p>
        <p>The first drug approved for pulmonary hypertension, in 1995, was Flolan, a version of a natural hormone called prostacyclin, which dilates constricted blood vessels. It is made by GlaxoSmithKline.</p>
        <p>Flolan, which was also the first drug Ms. Adkins took for her condition, disappears from the body so fast that it must be pumped in 24 hours a day. The catheter used poses a risk of infection, and users must carry a small pump and mix a fresh batch of the drug every day.</p>
        <p>The annual cost, roughly $100,000, can also be a hardship. Merle Reeseman of Grove City, Pa., said that when her insurer would not pay for Flolan, she had to separate from her husband of more than 30 years to qualify for Medicaid, which pays for the drug.</p>
        <p>''The only way they would allow it was if I basically became destitute,'' she said. ''This just isn't fair.''</p>
        <p>Another of the new drugs, Remodulin, is a form of prostacyclin infused under the skin rather than through a catheter. That method lowers the infection risk, but many patients complain of pain. The drug was approved in 2002, and sales were $45.1 million last year. The developer, United Therapeutics of Silver Spring, Md., estimated that about 450 Americans were taking Remodulin at the end of 2003, versus about 2,550 taking Flolan.</p>
        <p>CoTherix of South San Francisco, Calif., said it planned to apply to the F.D.A. this year for approval of an inhaled form of prostacyclin already sold in Europe by Schering.</p>
        <p>The first oral drug, approved in 2001, was Tracleer from Actelion; it inhibits endothelin, a hormone that helps constrict blood vessels. Sales in 2003 were 300 million Swiss francs, or about $235 million.</p>
        <p>Though much cheaper than the two other approved drugs, Tracleer still costs about $35,000 a year and can cause liver problems, so users must have their liver enzymes checked every month.</p>
        <p>Encysive, based in Houston, and Myogen, based in Westminster, Colo., are developing pills that they hope will inhibit endothelin more effectively than Tracleer. Encysive's drug, sitaxsentan, is well into the final stage of testing while ambrisentan from Myogen has just entered that stage.</p>
        <p>Viagra works by yet another mechanism, inhibiting an enzyme called phosphodiesterase 5. The drug relaxes blood vessels, allowing blood to flow into the penis -- or, it is hoped, into the lungs.</p>
        <p>Such a use would be a return to Viagra's roots. The drug was originally tested for angina, a cardiovascular condition, and proved disappointing. But some men in the trials reported a side effect: erections.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael McGoon of the Mayo Clinic said the approved drugs typically allow someone who cannot climb even one flight of stairs to climb a flight or more, but ''don't return anybody to what they would perceive as normal health.''</p>
        <p>Results with Viagra are ''extremely variable,'' he said, adding, ''It's not a miracle.''</p>
        <p>Viagra, Dr. McGoon said, may be as effective as other drugs but at a lower cost. Some experts said it was likely that different drugs would be used in combination.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Adkins swears by Viagra. She said she had spent $5,000 on the drug and had hired a lawyer to press her insurer to pay. ''I told them I was going to get a sex change,'' she said. ''They would probably pay for the sex change.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
