<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CD Sings A Car's Praises</title>
    <meta content="29njMOTOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/29/automobiles/29njMOTOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1735555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E5DD113FF93AA15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CD Sings A Car's Praises</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">CD Sings A Car's Praises</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <dateline>EATONTOWN</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LONG before Steve Levin sold cars, he worked at his family's hotel in Lakewood. After he was discharged from the Navy, he found himself at another hotel, only this time in Hawaii.</p>
        <p>There, while working 14-hour days and earning only $300 a month at the Outrigger, Mr. Levin decided there had to be a better way to make a living. He became a car salesman at a dealership in Hawaii, and he was good at it. A job became a career.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not coming to an iPod soon, we hope: new-car shoppers may soon be getting sales pitches on a CD.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LONG before Steve Levin sold cars, he worked at his family's hotel in Lakewood. After he was discharged from the Navy, he found himself at another hotel, only this time in Hawaii.</p>
        <p>There, while working 14-hour days and earning only $300 a month at the Outrigger, Mr. Levin decided there had to be a better way to make a living. He became a car salesman at a dealership in Hawaii, and he was good at it. A job became a career.</p>
        <p>After four years in Hawaii, he moved back to New Jersey in 1972 and has spent the years since then in automobile sales.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levin began to question how cars were sold -- often with a hurried pitch on a test drive around the parking lot. Most cars, he believes, are sold on price, not value.</p>
        <p>So the entrepreneur inside him reasoned: What if a customized compact disc could be played during a test drive that would tout many of the features of a car, not just those the sales representative could remember?</p>
        <p>The result is Motormouth, a set of about 100 CD's that will be introduced at the National Automobile Dealers Association convention next month in Orlando, Fla.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levin has high hopes for his product. ''I want to revolutionize the way we sell cars in this country,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At first, the CD's, recorded by professional announcers, will be sold only to dealers. Mr. Levin would not say how much they cost, but sample tracks can be heard at www.motormouthinfo.com.</p>
        <p>In 2004, Mr. Levin started writing descriptions of Chevrolet models, but has since branched out to other manufacturers. His scripts now number more than 1,000 pages.</p>
        <p>He has already found customers in several states, including the Pine Belt Automotive Group, which owns several dealerships near his home in Eatontown.</p>
        <p>''We're a little bit different in a world where everything is similar,'' said Ernie Marino, the operations manager at Pine Belt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levin, 58, is emphatic that he is not marketing a set of CD's as much as he is marketing a concept --or at least updating it. Because of the high turnover at car dealerships, salesmen and saleswomen often do not get to know their product well enough to sell it better. The national dealers' association says that, on average, nearly half of a dealer's employees leave in a given year. So the training process is constant.</p>
        <p>Paul Taylor, the association's chief economist, said of sales tools like Motormouth: ''It's good for the dealers, and it's good for the customers. It allows the salespeople to use their time in a more qualitative way than just going over the basics.''</p>
        <p>The eight-minute CD's list 80 to 100 features, although customers will probably remember only the few that are important to them.</p>
        <p>Dealers can use the CD set as an instructional aid for new hires. ''It's a good training tool,'' said Mr. Marino of the Pine Belt Group. ''We use it for the novice salespeople. They can take a car out on their own and listen to it. And it's something different for the customer. A salesperson doesn't hit 100 percent of the items.''</p>
        <p>For the dealers, a selling point for the CD's is that they can be used over and over. In contrast, bringing in a sales consultant for a pep talk for the sales staff is a expensive one-time proposition. And once a sales representative leaves the dealership, whatever expertise the consultant imparted goes, too.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levin's wife, Carol, thought up the Motormouth name for the CD series after she and her husband had batted around the idea for a while. ''I did not name the product after my wife.'' Mr. Levin said, laughing. And Mrs. Levin says that she did not name it after him, either.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
