<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Hamlets Explore New Paths in an Old Terrain</title>
    <meta content="08WOLF$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/08/arts/08WOLF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1283912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal National Theater (London)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolf, Matt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russell Beale, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lester, Adrian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brook, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caird, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hamlet (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tragedy of Hamlet, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Royal National Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Phoenix</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota/Minneapolis and St. Paul</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Seattle</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Chicago</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Boston</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Minneapolis</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Tucson</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Phoenix</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris</location>
        <location class="online_producer">London</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Bosnia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">America</location>
        <org class="online_producer">The New York Times Co</org>
        <org class="online_producer">act</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Beale, Simon Russell</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Donnellan, Declan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nichols, Mike</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beale, Russell</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolf, Matt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Holm, Ian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0DA1F3FF93BA35757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Hamlets Explore New Paths in an Old Terrain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from conversation between two leading English actors, Simon Russell Beale and Adrian Lester, who will both be playing Hamlet within weeks of each other at Brooklyn Academy of Music, and Matt Wolf, London theater critic for Variety; Lester will be appearing in Peter Brook's revisionist The Tragedy of Hamlet, while Russell Beale is traveling to New York with Royal National Theater Hamlet directed by John Caird (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HAMLETS proliferate in Britain -- indeed, in Europe -- but it has been a long time since two leading English actors played the same role in New York within such a short period as Adrian Lester and Simon Russell Beale are about to do at the Brooklyn Academy of Music.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lester, 32, arrives first, in Peter Brook's revisionist ''Hamlet'' -- retitled, for the director's purposes, ''The Tragedy of Hamlet.'' The production will be at BAM from April 24 through May 6, the second stop on a three-city American tour beginning in Seattle (now through April 19) and continuing on from New York to Chicago (May 10-June 2).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HAMLETS proliferate in Britain -- indeed, in Europe -- but it has been a long time since two leading English actors played the same role in New York within such a short period as Adrian Lester and Simon Russell Beale are about to do at the Brooklyn Academy of Music.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lester, 32, arrives first, in Peter Brook's revisionist ''Hamlet'' -- retitled, for the director's purposes, ''The Tragedy of Hamlet.'' The production will be at BAM from April 24 through May 6, the second stop on a three-city American tour beginning in Seattle (now through April 19) and continuing on from New York to Chicago (May 10-June 2).</p>
        <p>New York audiences may recall Mr. Lester's previous appearance at BAM in 1994, when he donned a dress to play Rosalind in an all-male ''As You Like It'' directed by Declan Donnellan. He appeared in the Mike Nichols movie ''Primary Colors'' as well.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russell Beale is traveling to New York with a Royal National Theater ''Hamlet'' directed by John Caird. He will arrive at the end of a tour that opens in Boston (Wednesday-April 29) and visits Minneapolis (May 2-13), Tucson (May 16-20) and Phoenix (May 22-27) before reaching BAM (May 30-June 2).</p>
        <p>Last seen at BAM in Sam Mendes's ''Othello'' in 1998, Mr. Russell Beale, 40, won the Evening Standard Drama Award for best actor for his performance of Hamlet in November. In his acceptance speech, he paid tribute to Mr. Lester, who was opening in Paris in Mr. Brook's production the same week.</p>
        <p>With that in mind, The New York Times invited the two actors, who have not yet seen each other's performance, to talk about what is arguably the English-speaking theater's most celebrated role. They spoke over southern Indian food at a restaurant in south London chosen by Mr. Lester, who as a new father wanted to keep close to home. They were joined by Matt Wolf, the London theater critic for Variety. Here are excerpts from the conversation.</p>
        <p>ADRIAN LESTER -- Thank you for coming down here to do this.</p>
        <p>SIMON RUSSELL BEALE -- (Smiles) I should jolly well hope so. (Surveying the Three Monkeys restaurant, which had opened especially for the occasion.) A good choice by the way, even if it is Herne Hill.</p>
        <p>LESTER -- This place is great. I come here all the time.</p>
        <p>WOLF -- Did you two think of yourselves as natural Hamlets?</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- Adrian is.</p>
        <p>LESTER -- I didn't think I was at all.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- If there is such a thing.</p>
        <p>LESTER -- I don't think there is, but then you look around and think: ''Oh, right. What could people say about me doing Hamlet? Well, there's not anybody like me who's ever done it.'' And the same could be said of you, Simon. You look around and you go, ''Aren't I supposed to be pale and slim and young?''</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- People say to me, ''Shouldn't he be tall, blond and slim?'' Or, ''Shouldn't he be tall, black haired and slim?'' That proves there's no such thing as a natural Hamlet. Though I do remember seeing your dreadlocks and thinking, ''That's a good idea.''</p>
        <p>LESTER -- (Laughs) A Hamlet with an Afro? No way. People have this thing about what they want to see. They'll look at me and go: ''Oh, dreadlocks. Oh, no.''</p>
        <p>WOLF -- But don't they forget that after 30 seconds?</p>
        <p>LESTER -- They do, but some people have found what I do more vicious because I've got dreadlocks. Again, it's what you see</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- The aggressive black man?</p>
        <p>LESTER -- Exactly.</p>
        <p>WOLF -- You faced a version of this as well, didn't you, Simon?</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- (Sighs) Tubby or not tubby, which is my dreadlock. Oh, the fat thing. Yes.</p>
        <p>LESTER -- Did you get that?</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- Yes, but I got it incredibly nicely rather than horribly. It was just, they all went, ''Well, he's obviously grotesquely fat, but he can do it.'' Rather than saying, ''He's grotesquely fat and he can't.'' Which is good. I was rather relieved.</p>
        <p>It is strange, this physical thing, because the one thing we know about Shakespeare is that he gives so few physical indications -- Rosalind being one of the few. We don't know what Antony looks like or Cleopatra, except that she's slightly dark.</p>
        <p>WOLF -- Is it accurate to think of yours as sweeter, gentler Hamlets?</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- I think it has to do with Horatio. Both teams have focused on Horatio as a very commanding, encompassing figure in the play, and Horatio is one of the gentlest characters Shakespeare ever wrote. So if you decide to circle the play without Fortinbras but with Horatio -- which I think you, Adrian, do -- then you are focused on the idea that Horatio has this fantastic commission about telling Hamlet's story. That, I think, does produce a sweeter Hamlet -- a man who needs his story to be told, rather than to be king. You don't concentrate on being king, do you?</p>
        <p>LESTER -- No, and of course with Fortinbras as this example of what a true prince should be -- vengeful, taking action without speaking about it -- if you take that away, then you're left to explore what would happen to this poor guy Hamlet.</p>
        <p>WOLF -- Can you wipe the slate clean, as it were, especially in Britain?</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- There has never been a time when there aren't 800 Hamlets. I think you do it anyway. You are aware consciously that there is a history about it. You see this list of Hamlets and you think, ''Oh, my God, no.'' (Laughs) And there's Adrian opening in about five minutes. There's Olivier. There's Gielgud. I remember in 1990 having a bath the morning of the press night of ''Richard III'' -- and I had this pain in my stomach -- suddenly realizing that people were going to be there (and it proved to be so) who had seen every single ''Richard III'' since 1920 and performances that I now realize were great, like that of Ian Holm. But there's an extraordinary shutoff point when the rehearsal room door closes. Gielgud died the morning we started rehearsals for our ''Hamlet,'' and you thought, ''This is really weird.'' But you have to -- as Adrian says -- start from scratch.</p>
        <p>WOLF -- How would you appraise your Hamlets?</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- They are more similar than one imagines, I suspect.</p>
        <p>LESTER -- Mine is much more about Peter's vision of the play. Let us make no mistake: it's not even Shakespeare's ''Hamlet,'' it's Peter Brook's ''Hamlet.'' He will suddenly say things and you think, ''God, I wish I wrote that down.'' Peter is always paring it down and making it pure. He has been talking about the idea of ''Hamlet'' for so long that when we got to the production several decisions had already been made: he pushed scenes around, chose what to cut, shifted speeches.</p>
        <p>In rehearsal, I thought: ''Let me stretch my muscles. Can I just do it badly?'' No! Absolutely no way. Don't even begin to explore it in that way. And very cleverly, every time I made a decision that I knew I was making, Peter took it away from me. So it left me more and more at sea and more and more at the impulse of that particular moment. Unless you know what Peter is doing, it's very troubling. But I began to see a method behind that kind of madness, and it made me begin to feel as if I were improvising. So there's a strong improvisational feel about the performance.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- John Caird is very romantic; he has a vision of humanity as basically good. That's quite unusual in the sense that when you look at these great plays, even ''As You Like It'' and certainly ''Richard III'' and ''Othello'' and ''The Tempest,'' there's a path you can go that is deeply cynical and life-hating. But John has a very life-affirming vision of the way human beings behave. We did much the same as Adrian and Peter did: we cut the play down to the personal politics of the court, but within those personal politics, everyone has the potential to love each other. That's fascinating: even the idea that Hamlet and Claudius could get on. I think John's idea was that the play was about love betrayed.</p>
        <p>LESTER -- Peter sat us all down and said: ''This play has not survived because it's nice. We can't forget what's happening in Bosnia. We can't forget what happened around the Ceausescus. We can't forget it when power is abused.''</p>
        <p>For me, it was odd. Suddenly he had told the whole company that Hamlet's not nice and the play's not nice, and it gave me license in rehearsal to play about with it.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- Exactly the opposite happened to me. I think John allowed me to be nice. What he said to me was: ''This part is limitless, so there's nothing right or wrong about these things. You can be as nice and as charming as you want to be, and that will be fine, rather than being a psychopath.''</p>
        <p>I'm having problems with the relationship with Ophelia at the moment. I find her so unbearably vulnerable and hurt that it's very difficult to be a bastard. In rehearsal, you would have to go and apologize to people afterward and say, ''Sorry about that.'' You have to do some fairly brutal things, especially to the women. Actually, I don't understand Hamlet's misogyny.</p>
        <p>LESTER -- It's a shame that Ophelia and Gertrude are really the only two women on the stage because you'd like to see some other contrast. There were two scenes in the play that left me in tears of frustration because I just couldn't get them right, and it was always the scene with Ophelia and the scene with the mother. In our version, after seeing the Ghost, Hamlet doesn't know whom to trust. It made sense to me that the first thing he did then was go to Ophelia and look at her and hold her at arm's length and stare at her and just think----</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- Are you honest?</p>
        <p>LESTER -- Yes, are you honest?</p>
        <p>WOLF -- What about the issue of madness.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- (To Adrian Lester) You're madder than I, aren't you?</p>
        <p>LESTER -- I think I am. I'm barking, aren't I? I'm completely crazy. (Laughs) It's funny, because I don't think that I'm playing a mad Hamlet. I think he's a normal person under extraordinary circumstances who behaves extraordinarily because of those circumstances.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- Well, I was a coward, Adrian. I knew I wanted to do two things: I knew I didn't want to assault my mother----</p>
        <p>LESTER -- Mmm. Me, too.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- I didn't want to follow the Oedipal line.</p>
        <p>LESTER -- (Delightedly) Me, too. We've had Olivier tell us from Freud that it must be right.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- The other thing is, I was really worried about the madness because I didn't know what to do. I think grief is a type of madness; somebody said it's like being mugged. What do you do if you sit on a piece of information like that -- that your uncle is a murderer? It would drive you crazy. In my version, though, it's a perfectly normal sort of crazy. But, let's face it, Hamlet is not well.</p>
        <p>WOLF -- How does one's own life experience affect the playing of a role that has been said to contain all life within it?</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- As you know, my mom died before rehearsals started, and John Caird's mom died, as well, the same week. I can't say what it's like. It's a profoundly important and distressing experience. I'm fairly ruthless about coping with myself at career moments, but on the press night I had her picture in the wings, and it became a sort of tribute to her. And still is.</p>
        <p>Adrian, are your parents still alive?</p>
        <p>LESTER -- Yes. I haven't lost mine.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- What I didn't realize about grief is that a lot of it is about panic. You come off after a performance and you suddenly think, ''She's not here, she's not going to be here.'' And the reaction would be that you would panic: not that you wanted to phone her; just that she wasn't there. Then you realize that the play, in terms of the detail and the progress of grief, is basically about panic. And I thought, ''Gosh, Shakespeare, good for you, you've got it absolutely right.''</p>
        <p>LESTER -- Everything is in this play; Shakespeare has just put it all down.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- And what about that fifth act: it will be now if it is not to come, if it is not to come, it will be now, the readiness is all. Let be.</p>
        <p>Why is that so profoundly important when you go (he exhales slowly)----</p>
        <p>LESTER -- Let be.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE. -- Let be.</p>
        <p>WOLF -- (To Adrian Lester) In a play largely driven by death, you were preparing for a new life.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- What have you got----</p>
        <p>LESTER -- A little girl called Lila.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- (Smiling) A little girl!</p>
        <p>LESTER -- I didn't truly consider what it would be like having a child. Actually having a baby, oh, it's wonderful. But when you begin to read and listen to the doctors and talk about what could go wrong, suddenly, you're full of anxiety the whole time. I will go back now and give a completely different performance because the baby is well and healthy. But before that, I was just anxious. Lolita [Mr. Lester's wife, Lolita Chakrabarti, an actress] was on tour in America with ''As You Like It'' when she was pregnant. So there was this complete worry in my head. Richard Eyre [the British director] said he always thought ''Hamlet'' was a play about a man who learns to cope with death. Peter thought it was a play about a man who learns how to kill. But to me it is about someone who comes to terms with their little existence.</p>
        <p>WOLF -- How do you bid farewell to a Hamlet?</p>
        <p>LESTER -- I think it's changed and improved me as an actor.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- Me, too.</p>
        <p>LESTER -- I don't think I've ever been as vulnerable as I am with Hamlet. It's taught me something.</p>
        <p>RUSSELL BEALE -- I think it's taught me about -- and this goes back to ''let be'' -- the fact that people are interesting as human beings. There's this rather amazing moment, if you're lucky enough to play Hamlet, when you realize that people have followed you for three hours through this terrible story, and you just say to them: ''Look, this is me. I'm worth watching, and I'm a human being.''</p>
        <p>This is why the part can be played by anybody, of course. It doesn't matter what Adrian or I look like, or what sex we are. It's a human being standing onstage saying, ''Let be.''</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
