<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TECHNOLOGY: Prospectus; Some New York on-line specialists are placing their ads off line on billboards, newspapers, radio and TV.</title>
    <meta content="26PROS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1057113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stites, Janet</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DD153CF935A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TECHNOLOGY: Prospectus; Some New York on-line specialists are placing their ads off line on billboards, newspapers, radio and TV.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Janet Stites</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stites, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on growing number of New York on-line companies that are placing ads on billboards, newspapers, radio and TV; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF Scott Kurnit, the founder and chief executive of the Mining Company, ever finds himself feeling insignificant or questioning his new business endeavor, he can bolster his self-esteem by catching the F train from his offices in midtown Manhattan to SoHo and there gaze upon his company's latest marketing effort: a giant mural on a building on Houston Street near Broadway touting ''miningco.com.''</p>
        <p>Cater-cornered to the famous DKNY ad, the mural is just one piece of evidence that New York companies like his that deal with Internet-related media are beginning to understand the need to promote their on-line brands in the off-line world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF Scott Kurnit, the founder and chief executive of the Mining Company, ever finds himself feeling insignificant or questioning his new business endeavor, he can bolster his self-esteem by catching the F train from his offices in midtown Manhattan to SoHo and there gaze upon his company's latest marketing effort: a giant mural on a building on Houston Street near Broadway touting ''miningco.com.''</p>
        <p>Cater-cornered to the famous DKNY ad, the mural is just one piece of evidence that New York companies like his that deal with Internet-related media are beginning to understand the need to promote their on-line brands in the off-line world.</p>
        <p>The Mining Company, an Internet search engine that offers personal guides to Web sites, joins such other companies as iVillage, N2K, theglobe.com and Connecticut-based priceline.com that have recently undertaken national advertising blitzes -- broadcast, cable TV, outdoor and print -- intended to make their brands household names, the likes of ESPN or (dare they wish) Coca-Cola.</p>
        <p>Not one of these companies existed five years ago. Nor did their industry.</p>
        <p>Now, iVillage advertises its Women's Network on several cable TV channels.</p>
        <p>N2K, which agreed last week to merge with its biggest competitor, CDNow, has its own huge billboards in Times Square and on Sunset Strip in Hollywood for its Web-based retail business, Music Boulevard. It also introduced a broadcast, cable and radio campaign during the Grammy Awards show this year.</p>
        <p>Theglobe.com invested $8 million to plaster its logo on everything from bus stops to cable to the T-shirt of a waiter in SoHo at the trendy Jerry's restaurant, a popular lunch spot for Silicon Alley denizens.</p>
        <p>All these companies have established a presence on the World Wide Web through banner advertising and strategic relationships with other sites. But to build the critical mass they have promised their investors -- and in the case of N2K, its shareholders -- they must have a presence in the nonvirtual world, too. Survival demands that they drive traffic to their Web sites to increase ''viewer impressions,'' the count of how many times the pages on a site are seen.</p>
        <p>For now, the Mining Company, iVillage and theglobe.com are focusing most of their advertising dollars on markets with a ''wired'' population, primarily New York, San Francisco, Boston and Seattle.</p>
        <p>Priceline.com, an airline ticket broker in Stamford, Conn., has taken a more ambitious and focused approach. Eschewing TV and on-line advertising, the six-month-old company has spent $20 million to buy national radio spots featuring William Shatner and full-page ads in The New York Times, The Wall Street Journal and USA Today.</p>
        <p>''We want people to know about us before they get on line,'' said Jay S. Walker, priceline.com's founder and chief executive.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Walker, radio and newspapers are the most efficient media for his particular brand because ''you don't need a lot of pictures or motion to convey'' his company's simple message, that ''as long as you're flexible, you can name your price on an airline ticket, a car or, shortly, a hotel room.''</p>
        <p>James Dettore, chief executive of Brand Institute, a New York consulting firm, says the cost of creating an on-line brand for Internet companies is inherently cheaper than creating a brand for, say, cookies.</p>
        <p>''Generally, companies will spend 8 to 10 percent of their budget on marketing,'' Mr. Dettore said. But he contends that Internet companies have two advantages over others: the medium is global, and it is fast.</p>
        <p>''Historically, it takes 15 to 20 years to establish a megabrand,'' Mr. Dettore said. ''The software industry -- Microsoft, Dell and Gateway -- accelerated this to three to five years. And Internet brands are growing even faster.'' Even so, he says, building a national brand is expensive, costing ''anywhere from $50 million to $100 million.''</p>
        <p>The challenge is finding an efficient way to allocate limited resources. iVillage has raised some $67 million in capital -- an impressive amount but not near enough to cover the cost of building the brand, developing the product and meeting payroll.</p>
        <p>The Mining Company has raised about $20 million, as has theglobe.com, which filed for a public offering in July. Priceline.com has raised $52 million, and N2K has raised more than $160 million through two public offerings and private financing.</p>
        <p>Internet companies often find it hard to accept the vague, imprecise measurements of a campaign's effectiveness in traditional media.</p>
        <p>Debbie Newman, N2K's vice president for marketing, advertising and sales, describes the frustration of assigning a value to a brand's image -- and of conveying that value to her bosses.</p>
        <p>''The Internet has become a response-based, customer acquisition buy,'' she said. ''It's become pretty scientific. We can count how many customers we acquired for every banner we place.''</p>
        <p>In contrast, she said, ''The off-line advertising is more intangible, but it builds confidence and trust in our virtual brand.''</p>
        <p>As of last week, Ms. Newman has larger, equally intangible, problems to worry about.</p>
        <p>With the N2K-CDNow merger, the brand she has worked so hard to create may become obsolete if the management of the newly formed company deems CDNow, or an entirely new name, more valuable than N2K or its Music Boulevard.</p>
        <p>Jon V. Diamond, co-founder of N2K and chairman of the new company, said in a phone interview on Friday: ''We have agreed to a process to work with senior management and consultants to assess our brand equities and a third brand. We'll continue to market our respective services through the holiday season.''</p>
        <p>If all goes as planned, the merger will be complete in January and the new name -- and new branding campaign -- will be announced soon thereafter.</p>
        <p>Back down in SoHo, Mr. Kurnit of the Mining Company has issues of his own. Just days after the paint dried on his mural, the gasoline station in front of the building where it resides sold its air rights to a billboard company. Now, a cigarette ad blocks a part of the Mining Company's mural -- and perhaps its chance to make a fleeting impression amid the noise.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
