<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Czechs and Russians Renew The Rivalry of Another Era</title>
    <meta content="21HOCK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="996860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE XVIII WINTER GAMES: ICE HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1998)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Czech Republic</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4DD1E3FF932A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="1339" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Czechs and Russians Renew The Rivalry of Another Era</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>NAGANO, Japan, Feb. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on historic rivalry between Czech and Russian hockey teams, who will face each other in championship game at Nagano; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several times during this extraordinary performance, Pavel Bure, the captain of the Russian hockey team, raced down the ice with the puck on his stick, leading a speeding stream of nine other skaters to the Finnish goal line. It looked like a game of ''crack the whip'' that children play on skating rinks.</p>
        <p>All game long, Bure held the whip hand and did much of the cracking. On 10 shots against Finland today, Bure scored five goals and almost had a couple more in a 7-4 victory in the second semifinal of the Olympic hockey tournament in Big Hat arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Several times during this extraordinary performance, Pavel Bure, the captain of the Russian hockey team, raced down the ice with the puck on his stick, leading a speeding stream of nine other skaters to the Finnish goal line. It looked like a game of ''crack the whip'' that children play on skating rinks.</p>
        <p>All game long, Bure held the whip hand and did much of the cracking. On 10 shots against Finland today, Bure scored five goals and almost had a couple more in a 7-4 victory in the second semifinal of the Olympic hockey tournament in Big Hat arena.</p>
        <p>So Bure was in a good mood afterward when he was talking about the brilliant goalie, Dominik Hasek of the Czech Republic, which ousted Canada by 2-1 today after a shootout and will face Russia in the gold-medal game on Sunday.</p>
        <p>''Before playing against Hasek, I'm going to read up the other Hasek, the famous Czech writer, who wrote 'The Good Soldier Schweik,' '' Bure said. ''I've already read it once.'' The book, by Jaroslav Hasek, is about a soldier who fought in World War I.</p>
        <p>This may have been one of the rare times when a war reference was appropriate in a sports context, because the Russian-Czech championship game will evoke in some the memories of another war in another era. This rivalry, one of the best in Olympic hockey history, was at its peak during the Cold War, when most members of the Soviet National team also played for Central Red Army. Four times, between 1968 and 1984, the Russian-based team of the Soviet Union and the team representing the nation then known as Czechoslovakia went into their final games in the Olympic tournament with the gold medal at stake, three times playing each other. The Soviets won all four gold medals and the Czechs, who have never won a gold, settled for three silvers and one bronze in this period.</p>
        <p>''It's different now,'' said Aleksei Kasatonov, the former defenseman for the Sovietn national team who is now its general manager. ''I remember the game in 1984. For us, it was like life and death. Now, it's just a sporting competition, not as political as it was right after 1968.''</p>
        <p>Although they were technically allies at this time, the Russian-Czech rivalry also included military force in 1968, after they first jousted for the gold medal. In August, the Soviets sent tanks into Prague, under the authority of the Warsaw Pact, to quell an anti-Communist uprising. Those who think that current players are ignorant of this history, or that it has no relevance to hockey, should take note of the number on the broad back of Jaromir Jagr, the best Czech player who is not a goalie. Jagr wears No. 68. He chose it, he has said in the past, in honor of the politics of that troubled year, some four years before his birth.</p>
        <p>''Yes, I know this,'' Kasatonov said.</p>
        <p>Peter Svoboda, one of the top Czech defensemen, left the game late in the third period with what he said was a re-injury of a sore elbow. Svoboda said he hoped he would feel well enough to play in the championship game. When someone asked Svoboda the secret of his team's success, he replied: ''Hasek and Jagr.''</p>
        <p>Although he didn't score today, Jagr was the best Czech skater in a 2-1 victory over Canada. The game was tied at 1-1 after regulation and a 10-minute overtime. In the shootout rotation, five Canadians shot pucks at Hasek and four Czechs shot pucks at Patrick Roy. They didn't need the last shot because Robert Reichel of the Islanders scored on the first one, ending a moment of high tension and finishing Canada's hopes for gold.</p>
        <p>Hasek called the shootout ''unbelievable pressure, the biggest pressure of my life.'' You make one mistake,'' he said, ''and you lose.''</p>
        <p>Roy said of the shootout: ''It didn't start well, because the first guy hit the post and it went in. I'm not here to find excuses. If we lose, we lose.''</p>
        <p>This tournament, filled for the first time with National Hockey League stars, was supposed to mark the ascendancy of North American hockey, particularly for Canada and the United States, on the world's biggest sports stage. Instead, Canada faces Finland Saturday for the bronze and the United States team is already home, having lost three of four games and having gained a reputation for patronizing bars and vandalism in the athletes' village.</p>
        <p>''In Europe, we have excellent hockey,'' said Vladimir Yurzinov, coach of the Russian team. ''Hopefully, now, no one will look down on us.''</p>
        <p>Everyone looked up with admiration at Hasek, who stopped 24 of 25 shots before the shootout. Bure said of Hasek, ''By now, he is probably the best goalkeeper in the world.''</p>
        <p>It was the second consecutive Olympics in which Canada was defeated in a shootout. In 1994, the gold-medal game between Sweden and Canada was decided when goalie Tommy Salo of Sweden stopped Paul Kariya of Canada while Peter Forsberg of Sweden beat goalie Corey Hirsch of Canada.</p>
        <p>Today's regulation-time goals were scored by Jiri Sleger of the Czech Republic and Trevor Linden of Canada. Linden's goal came just 1 minute 3 seconds before the end of regulation. ''History will say this was a great hockey game,'' said Marc Crawford, coach of Team Canada. ''It will go down as a classic. You just wish you were on the other end of the score.''</p>
        <p>Some questioned Crawford's use of Ray Bourque, a defenseman, in the shootout, instead of centers such as Wayne Gretzky or Steve Yzerman. ''Ray is great on breakaways,'' Crawford said. ''You go with your gut instincts. We did consider using Wayne.''</p>
        <p>Crawford settled on Theoren Fleury, Bourque, Joe Nieuwendyk, Eric Lindros and Brendan Shanahan.</p>
        <p>Yzerman said he had no problem with the selection. ''I would not second-guess or question any of the guys picked,'' Yzerman said. But he did voice objections to the shootout format. Asked if he likes it, Yzerman replied: ''Obviously not. Yes, it is exciting. But I haven't been in favor of it. I'm less so in favor of it now.''</p>
        <p>Slavomir Lener, head coach of the Czech team, said his players routinely practice penalty shots during team workouts. ''It's fun for the players, kind of relaxing,'' Lener said. Crawford said his team practiced penalty shots earlier in the week, before the previous game against Kazakhstan.</p>
        <p>In the second semifinal, Bure scored the first three goals, two on breakaways, taking advantage of turnovers. The Finns came back to tie it at 3-3 and again at 4-4 before Russia pulled away. Bure scored the last two, the final into an empty net when Finland pulled its goalie.</p>
        <p>For Finland, it will probably be the last Olympic appearance for Jari Kurri and Esa Tikkanen, two veterans who began their careers in the 1980's in Edmonton with Gretzky.</p>
        <p>It is most certainly Gretzky's last Olympics as well. He had no goals and three assists going into the bronze-medal game. And when Canada's game ended, and all his teammates took the ice to commisserate, Gretzky remained on the bench for a long minute, taking in the scene.</p>
        <p>''There are no words to describe it, the loss is devastating,'' Gretzky said. ''The truth of the matter is this is probably my last international competition. We were really focused here in trying to re-establish hockey in Canada. The younger guys will get the opportunity again. For me, a gold medal was not in the cards for my career. I love playing hockey and I love representing Canada.''</p>
        <p>THE XVIII WINTER GAMES: ICE HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
