<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Justices Ease Court Controls In School Desegregation Case</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="518207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EQUAL EDUCATIONAL OPPORTUNITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COURTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">DE KALB COUNTY (GA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, ANTHONY M (ASSOC JUSTICE)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Equal Educational Opportunities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DB163FF932A35757C0A964958260" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Justices Ease Court Controls In School Desegregation Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ruling in a major school desegregation case, the Supreme Court today gave hundreds of formerly segregated school districts a potential new legal tool for returning to local control after decades of operating under Federal court supervision.</p>
        <p>The 8-to-0 ruling, in a case from De Kalb County, Ga., in Atlanta's suburbs, allows school districts to win release from court control bit by bit as they achieve racial equality in various facets of their operations. It overturned a Federal appeals court ruling that required school districts to achieve equality in seven aspects of their operations before they could win release from judicial supervision of any. Important Qualifications</p>
        <p>But if the decision provided a road map for the return to local control, it left significant obstacles in the school districts' path. As a result, the practical impact of the ruling is less clear than its significance as legal doctrine.  [ Excerpts from the opinions, page B8. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ruling in a major school desegregation case, the Supreme Court today gave hundreds of formerly segregated school districts a potential new legal tool for returning to local control after decades of operating under Federal court supervision.</p>
        <p>The 8-to-0 ruling, in a case from De Kalb County, Ga., in Atlanta's suburbs, allows school districts to win release from court control bit by bit as they achieve racial equality in various facets of their operations. It overturned a Federal appeals court ruling that required school districts to achieve equality in seven aspects of their operations before they could win release from judicial supervision of any. Important Qualifications</p>
        <p>But if the decision provided a road map for the return to local control, it left significant obstacles in the school districts' path. As a result, the practical impact of the ruling is less clear than its significance as legal doctrine.  [ Excerpts from the opinions, page B8. ]</p>
        <p>Justice Anthony M. Kennedy's majority opinion contained important qualifications, suggesting that even a school district that has erased the vestiges of segregation in its assignment of students to particular schools might have to remain under court supervision because of the "synergistic" relationship between various elements of a school system's operations.</p>
        <p>The lower Federal courts in Georgia will now apply the facts of the case. Lawyers for the De Kalb County school district expressed confidence that it would soon win release from judicial supervision for most aspects of its operations.</p>
        <p>Justices Harry A. Blackmun, John Paul Stevens and Sandra Day O'Connor concurred in the outcome of the case but did not sign Justice Kennedy's opinion on the ground that the Court should have ordered the lower courts to undertake a more searching re-examination of the reasons most black students in De Kalb County still attend schools that have a black majority.</p>
        <p>Justice Clarence Thomas did not vote in the case, which was argued a month before he joined the Court.</p>
        <p>The case gave Justice David H. Souter his first opportunity to vote on a desegregation question. While he joined Justice Kennedy's majority opinion, he did so with a concurring opinion of his own suggesting unease with the speedy removal of Federal court supervision from once-segregated school districts. Because Justice Souter's was a necessary fifth vote, the majority opinion may well have had to adopt a more qualified tone than it otherwise would have.</p>
        <p>The decision was a victory for the De Kalb County school board, which has been under a Federal desegregation decree since 1969. It went back to court in 1986 requesting a declaration that it had satisfied its duty to achieve a "unitary" school system.</p>
        <p>Federal District Judge William C. O'Kelley found that the school system had eliminated segregation in several categories, including student assignment, and announced an end to court supervision of those categories. Seven Aspects Listed</p>
        <p>But the United States Court of Appeals for the 11th Circuit, in Atlanta, disagreed, ruling in 1989 that the district must remain under Federal court control until it had achieved and maintained equality for at least three years in seven aspects of its operations. Those aspects are student assignments, transportation, physical facilities, extracurricular activities, assignments of teachers and administrators, allocation of resources and the "quality of education."</p>
        <p>The Court today overturned the 11th Circuit's ruling, saying a Federal court may relinquish control over a school system "in a gradual way" as aspects of the system achieve the goal of desegregation.</p>
        <p>The De Kalb County schools were never under a busing order. The original desegregation decree called for the closing of some all-black schools and for the drawing of new district lines. These measures achieved integration for a brief period before white flight and black migration from Atlanta changed the racial composition of the district from 95 percent white in 1969 to 47 percent black by 1986.</p>
        <p>Justice Kennedy's majority opinion accepted Judge O'Kelley's conclusion, in his 1988 decision, that the resegregation of the school population was the result not of official action but of private choices and uncontrollable demographic shifts for which the school system had no continuing constitutional responsibility.</p>
        <p>"Racial balance is not to be achieved for its own sake," Justice Kennedy said. "Once the racial imbalance due to the</p>
        <p>de jure</p>
        <p>violation has been remedied, the school district is under no duty to remedy imbalance that is caused by demographic factors."</p>
        <p>Although De Kalb County itself is quite likely to prevail under the standards the Court set today, that is not necessarily the case for other school districts seeking relief from continuing court orders.</p>
        <p>Even a school district that has achieved equality in some areas, Justice Kennedy said, will remain under judicial supervision unless it can demonstrate "its good faith commitment to the entirety of a desegregation plan so that parents, students and the public have assurance against further injuries or stigma."</p>
        <p>In a concurring opinion, Justice Souter made more explicit some of the qualifications in Justice Kennedy's majority opinion. He said that in gradually releasing school district from supervision, Federal judges must be careful that the vestiges of discrimination that remain do not "act as an incubator for resegregation in others." Souter's Views Revealed</p>
        <p>Justice Souter's role in the case, Freeman v. Pitts, No. 89-1290, was particularly interesting because his views on desegregation were unknown when the Court agreed last year to decide the case.</p>
        <p>Besides Chief Justice Rehnquist and Justice Souter, Justices Byron R. White and Antonin Scalia also signed Justice Kennedy's opinion. Justice Scalia also wrote separately, suggesting that in a future case the Court should rewrite the basic standards that it left intact today and make it easier for school districts to escape continued judicial scrutiny.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
