<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="518304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D81F30F932A35757C0A964958260" item-length="507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK CITY  A CHANGING OF THE GUARD</p>
        <p>Each morning as John Gotti swaggers into a packed Brooklyn courtroom wearing his trademark silk tie and sneer, a baby-faced 23-year-old named Chen I. Chung impassively enters a similar, if almost empty, courtroom two floors below. But despite the lack of attention paid to his trial, Mr. Chung and other well Asian-American gang leaders may well represent the future of organized crime, prosecutors say. A1. GOTTI CASE GOES TO THE JURY</p>
        <p>The jury in John Gotti's racketeering-murder trial is to begin deliberations this morning, after the judge excused one juror from the case and then gave the remaining panel members their final instructions. The judge, I. Leo Glasser of Federal District Court in Brooklyn, declined to disclose his reason for dismissing the juror, a woman designated as Juror No. 3. But he said it did not involve any wrongdoing by any of the parties in the trial. B3. 48 HELD IN ARSON-FOR-PROFIT CASE</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK CITY  A CHANGING OF THE GUARD</p>
        <p>Each morning as John Gotti swaggers into a packed Brooklyn courtroom wearing his trademark silk tie and sneer, a baby-faced 23-year-old named Chen I. Chung impassively enters a similar, if almost empty, courtroom two floors below. But despite the lack of attention paid to his trial, Mr. Chung and other well Asian-American gang leaders may well represent the future of organized crime, prosecutors say. A1. GOTTI CASE GOES TO THE JURY</p>
        <p>The jury in John Gotti's racketeering-murder trial is to begin deliberations this morning, after the judge excused one juror from the case and then gave the remaining panel members their final instructions. The judge, I. Leo Glasser of Federal District Court in Brooklyn, declined to disclose his reason for dismissing the juror, a woman designated as Juror No. 3. But he said it did not involve any wrongdoing by any of the parties in the trial. B3. 48 HELD IN ARSON-FOR-PROFIT CASE</p>
        <p>Forty-eight people, including several insurance brokers, claims adjustors and businessmen in the Garment District in Manhattan, were arrested and charged with running what the District Attorney called one of the nation's largest full-service, arson-for-profit rings. B3. REGION  AN AGREEMENT ON THE BUDGET</p>
        <p>Using a time-honored method for closing a budget deal, New York State leaders produced more money for schools and for New York City with an array of last-minute fiscal maneuvers that included the sale of an Aqueduct Race Track parking lot by one quasi-public authority to another. The agreement was a victory for Mayor Dinkins, whose lobbying helped restore $31 million of the $100 million in cuts that the city had protested. He also headed off a plan by suburban and upstate lawmakers to cut an additional $40 million from the city's school budget. A1. Lawmakers do some semantic backpedaling on pledge to pass a budget on time. B4. THE AUTO INSURANCE QUANDARY</p>
        <p>When he was running for Governor, Jim Florio made auto insurance reform one of the major themes of his campaign. Now, despite claims of progress, insuring a car remains as perplexing as ever for millions of New Jersey drivers. B6. FLORIO TO VETO DELAY IN WAGE LAW</p>
        <p>In a move aimed at putting the new Republican Legislature on the spot, Governor Florio said he would veto a Republican bill to delay a new New Jersey minimum wage -- after workers have already begun getting bigger paychecks. B4. HOBOKEN REJECTS WATERFRONT PLAN</p>
        <p>After weeks of fierce debate, voters in Hoboken rejected a waterfront redevelopment that supporters called a financial boon to the city and opponents described as a monstrosity. B6. TAKING ON THE CATHOLIC CHURCH</p>
        <p>The Episcopal Bishop of Newark attacked the Roman Catholic Church's policies regarding women and homosexuals, calling the church repressive, prejudiced, hypocritical and "in danger of losing its soul." B6. Parents lose bid for control of closed parochial school. B6. About New York B3</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
