<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Opera Is a Natural Pastime</title>
    <meta content="01KOZI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/01/arts/01KOZI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1306263"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Glimmerglass Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chabrier, Emmanuel (1841-94)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Handel, George Frederick (1685-1759)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Britten, Benjamin (1913-76)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Etoile (Opera)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Agrippina (Opera)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rape of Lucretia (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Halls of Fame</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Halls of Fame</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E2DE1E30F932A35754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Opera Is a Natural Pastime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <dateline>SPRINGFIELD, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Glimmerglass Opera, founded in 1975 with initial budget of $14,000, now has $6 million annual budget and 900-seat house and reputation for adventurous programming; offerings this year include Chabrier's Etoile, Handel's Agrippina, and Britten's Rape of Lucretia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the gymnasium of a community center in this village just north of Cooperstown, the cast of the Glimmerglass Opera's new production of Mozart's ''Nozze di Figaro'' gathered for the first time. It was a soggy, chilly Monday in June, and most of the singers had driven in over the weekend. Now they convened to meet one another and the production team, and to hear the English director Stephen Lawless explain his concept of the work.</p>
        <p>Some of the singers, like Dean Ely, the Figaro; Joyce Guyer, the Countess; Nicole Heaston, the Susanna; and David Evitts, the Bartolo, come to the production with considerable professional experience; others, like Valerie Komar, the Cherubino, and Alison Trainer, the Barbarina, are participants in Glimmerglass's Young American Artists Program, which offers apprenticeships and recital opportunities for singers starting their careers. These performers would be immersed in ''Figaro'' for three months: in rehearsals until the production opens this Friday as well as in performances continuing through August.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the gymnasium of a community center in this village just north of Cooperstown, the cast of the Glimmerglass Opera's new production of Mozart's ''Nozze di Figaro'' gathered for the first time. It was a soggy, chilly Monday in June, and most of the singers had driven in over the weekend. Now they convened to meet one another and the production team, and to hear the English director Stephen Lawless explain his concept of the work.</p>
        <p>Some of the singers, like Dean Ely, the Figaro; Joyce Guyer, the Countess; Nicole Heaston, the Susanna; and David Evitts, the Bartolo, come to the production with considerable professional experience; others, like Valerie Komar, the Cherubino, and Alison Trainer, the Barbarina, are participants in Glimmerglass's Young American Artists Program, which offers apprenticeships and recital opportunities for singers starting their careers. These performers would be immersed in ''Figaro'' for three months: in rehearsals until the production opens this Friday as well as in performances continuing through August.</p>
        <p>Founded in 1975 by a group of opera enthusiasts in Cooperstown (still regarded as the company's home, although it is technically in Springfield), Glimmerglass presented a modest first season: just a production of ''La Bohème,'' in English, at a high school. Its budget then was $14,000. Now the company has a $6 million annual budget, a 900-seat house surrounded by farmland on the shore of Lake Otsego -- James Fennimore Cooper's Glimmerglass -- and a reputation for adventurous programming and solid casts that has attracted audiences to this operatically out-of-the-way spot, 225 miles northwest of New York.</p>
        <p>Operatic rarities are its main draw, and the offerings this year include Chabrier's ''Étoile'' (which opens on Thursday), Handel's ''Agrippina'' (July 21) and Britten's ''Rape of Lucretia'' (July 28). When it presents a favorite like ''Figaro,'' Glimmerglass tends to offer stagings that are inventive but not off the deep end.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lawless, having staged ''Figaro'' four times before, told the singers who had gathered between the gym's basketball hoops that he saw the opera as a study in sexual and class tensions, exacerbated by assaults on the trust necessary to make a marriage work, all packed into the Classical structure of a single day. As he spoke, using a model of Benoît Dugardyn's set to show how the stage would be transformed during the opera's four acts, the singers passed around drawings of Johann Stegmeir's costumes: undergarments in the first act give way to increasingly flamboyant dress in the second and third, most of which is stripped away for the various rendezvous in the fourth.</p>
        <p>''So you mean,'' one singer asked, ''we begin and end in our underwear?'' Exactly, Mr. Lawless said, leaving it to Mr. Stegmeir's drawings to show that 18th-century underwear was not as skimpy as its modern counterpart.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, Mr. Lawless and his team had spent several hours in the unheated Alice Busch Opera Theater, the company's home since 1987, examining the set. A trapdoor through which the gardener Antonio was to emerge during the second-act finale proved too far upstage to be effective, leading Mr. Lawless to consider having Antonio climb through a window instead. Elsewhere at Glimmerglass, orchestra and chorus rehearsals for ''L'Étoile'' were getting under way.</p>
        <p>''Choosing repertory is very complicated,'' said Paul Kellogg, who has run Glimmerglass since 1979 and who raised the company's profile considerably when he succeeded Christopher Keene as the general and artistic director of the New York City Opera in 1996. ''There is the requirement that we earn a certain amount of box-office income. And there's a need to balance the season, to include repertory that's known and works we feel we can introduce to our audience and expand their experience and, really, their tolerance for new or unusual work in a general way. We go through many variations of a season before we settle on it.''</p>
        <p>That ''we'' is an administrative circle that includes Esther Nelson, the company's general director; Stewart Robertson, its music director; Nicholas Russell, its artistic administrator; and John Conklin, its assistant artistic director. They work in a rabbit warren of offices in a building behind the opera house and alongside a barn, which has been converted into a costume shop. In the winter, they remain in touch by telephone and meet several times, usually in New York, to juggle repertory and casting ideas.</p>
        <p>Repertory decisions are trickier than they used to be, because Mr. Kellogg and his team no longer plan just for Glimmerglass. Like many other companies, Glimmerglass now thinks in terms of co-production, an arrangement in which two or more companies share the costs of sets and costumes, and stage the production by turns. Glimmerglass doesn't have to look far for partners, with Mr. Kellogg at the New York City Opera and Mr. Robertson entering his fourth season as music director of the Florida Grand Opera in Miami. Of the current productions, the Chabrier, Britten and Handel works are headed for the New York State Theater; the Mozart will be seen in Miami in 2003.</p>
        <p>There were fears, at first, that with a dependable flow of productions from Glimmerglass to the New York City Opera, a significant part of the Glimmerglass audience -- operagoers traveling from New York -- might stop attending.</p>
        <p>''It seems not to have happened, or if it has, those people have been replaced by people from other places,'' Mr. Kellogg said. ''I think one reason people come here is for the whole experience: the intimacy of the house, the countryside, the immersion in opera during a weekend. It's very different from seeing the productions in New York. And one of the most important characteristics for me is the company's informality. Very early on, we decided that there would be no dress code. It's rural upstate New York. People feel free to come in shorts and T-shirts. One of the things opera has needed to fight is a perception of inaccessibility.''</p>
        <p>All told, some 40,000 opera fans visit Glimmerglass every year, accounting for box-office sales of about 90 percent. Most of that audience is not local; Cooperstown's population is only 5,000. But about 40 percent of the audience comes from within two hours of Glimmerglass, an area that is bounded by Albany and Syracuse, and includes several university towns. Still, the diversity of the audience and its expectations is another element the administration wrestles with in planning its seasons.</p>
        <p>''There is a continual back and forth,'' said Ms. Nelson, who came to the company from the Nevada Opera in 1996 to take on the administrative duties Mr. Kellogg needed to shed when adding the City Opera position. ''It's a good thing, because out of teamwork comes an infusion of ideas. Everyone involved here is out there working with singers, directors and designers during the season, and they each bring something to the table.</p>
        <p>''But it can be tough. We cannot do the majority of the season with 'Traviata.' That would be against our mission. On the other hand, because my colleagues work in seasonal houses where the emphasis is on bread-and-butter productions, when they come here, they say, 'Finally I can do this obscure work that no one has ever heard of but that I personally love.' And my role is sometimes to say, 'It's a terrific idea, but guess what: even here, I might not be able to sell that.' ''</p>
        <p>Determining what will sell is partly instinctive, although Ms. Nelson analyzes past box-office performance to minimize the guesswork. Asked how she can predict that one rarity will draw an audience and another won't, she reached for a black binder filled with spreadsheets showing ticket sales, broken down by date and seat location, for the last several years as well as an up-to-the-minute accounting of sales this year.</p>
        <p>In her view, which was seconded by Mr. Robertson, the music director, the company is taking a chance this year by offering only one standard repertory production, ''Figaro,'' instead of its usual mix of one staple, a work from just outside the core repertory and two rarities or modern works. By early June, most of the ''Figaro'' performances were sold out, as were two performances of ''L'Étoile'' and two of ''Agrippina.'' The Britten lagged behind.</p>
        <p>''Generally, it's the Baroque work that drags,'' Ms. Nelson said. ''Baroque opera has a loyal following, but small. It's the same with the Britten, which is going to require some special promotion. People think that it's nonmelodic, and frankly, there are people who hear the title and who say: 'Oh, my God, a rape. I'm not going to that.' You do have to fight that, even at Glimmerglass.</p>
        <p>''With 'Étoile,' you know it's not going to sell as well as 'Figaro,' so when we schedule it, it has fewer performances. But because it's an operetta, it will attract people who don't really like serious opera, particularly once there is some word of mouth.''</p>
        <p>GLIMMERGLASS has its limitations. The size of its stage and pit rule out the grander 19th-century German and Russian operas. Moreover, neither Mr. Kellogg nor Ms. Nelson sees the season extending beyond four productions, largely because of the brevity of the summer in central New York State, where it is often too cool to present opera in an unheated house before July or after August. And having fostered a small bed-and-breakfast industry in the surrounding towns, the company is now encountering housing shortages, both for its staff -- about 300, from stagehands to singers -- and for its audience with the proliferation of baseball camps near Cooperstown's main draw, the Baseball Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>Then there are the more immediate, everyday problems of running an opera company. In early spring this year, a disagreement about the length of pauses between scenes -- one that had ramifications for the musicians' union (and thus for cost) -- led John Cox and his production team to withdraw from ''Agrippina'' just before the sets were to be built. After a flurry of anxious phone calls, Lillian Groag agreed to direct the work, with new sets by Mr. Conklin and costumes by Jess Goldstein.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robertson has to sort out more mundane problems as well. ''Oh, somebody might be singing a role for the first time, and it might not lie in their voice quite where they thought it would,'' he said in an easygoing Scottish brogue. ''Or a director may feel he's been shortchanged on staging time. We'll move some chorus rehearsals to give him an extra hour of staging, at which point the chorus mistress will call me, all bent out of shape because she isn't able to give the choral parts the final touch that she wanted. You know, that sort of thing is always going on.</p>
        <p>''I'm a kind of hands-on music director. I get my sleeves rolled up, and I get right in there. Otherwise, a lot of the decision-making and musical control seeps sideways, to artistic administration, stage management or somewhere else. I'd rather have it all in one place.''</p>
        <p>Be that as it may, performers, directors and designers who work at Glimmerglass don't seem to find the administration dictatorial.</p>
        <p>''What I like about Glimmerglass,'' said Mr. Stegmeir, the costume designer for ''Figaro'' and, last year, Strauss's ''Salome,'' ''is that we discuss ideas here more than in many other companies, where they mainly want to do what's been done before. Opera is a strange thing. Companies and audiences want that Broadway sense of spectacle, but unlike Broadway, we don't have the long rehearsal period and the previews that make it possible to try things out and see what works. Here we do a lot of rehearsing on the stage, sometimes in costume, sometimes not, and we make changes as we go along.''</p>
        <p>''Until now,'' he said on the first day of rehearsals, ''everything we've done is hypothesis. Now we can come to terms with the singers and what they have in mind. We get to see how it all fits into this canopy that we've created.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
