<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fortuneteller in New Jersey Accused of Bilking Woman of $50,000 Life Savings in a Scam</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="719108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS AND SWINDLING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HACKENSACK (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANLEY, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, MARYANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE5DF113CF93AA25753C1A962958260" item-length="470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fortuneteller in New Jersey Accused of Bilking Woman of $50,000 Life Savings in a Scam</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HANLEY, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>HACKENSACK, N.J., Oct. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fortuneteller's flimflam started with a simple $35 tarot-card reading in the summer of 1993, and by the time it crashed today with her arrest she had bilked her victim of at least $50,000, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The scam involved a slick-talking 22-year-old woman who promoted herself as "Mrs. Lisa" and prayed over bars of Dove soap, candles and leaves in her little storefront parlor, and a forlorn and gullible 33-year-old businesswoman from Bergenfield who became convinced that money was evil and ultimately lost her life savings, said John J. Fahy, the Bergen County Prosecutor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The fortuneteller's flimflam started with a simple $35 tarot-card reading in the summer of 1993, and by the time it crashed today with her arrest she had bilked her victim of at least $50,000, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The scam involved a slick-talking 22-year-old woman who promoted herself as "Mrs. Lisa" and prayed over bars of Dove soap, candles and leaves in her little storefront parlor, and a forlorn and gullible 33-year-old businesswoman from Bergenfield who became convinced that money was evil and ultimately lost her life savings, said John J. Fahy, the Bergen County Prosecutor.</p>
        <p>"This lady created a mind-set where she controlled her," Mr. Fahy said. "She took advantage of her vulnerability."</p>
        <p>The fortuneteller, Maryanne Miller, was arrested by Mr. Fahy's detectives today on charges of theft by deception after an undercover detective went to her parlor in Palisades Park with a tale of a fancy inheritance and a sad romantic life like the one the businesswoman told in July 1993, Mr. Fahy said.</p>
        <p>For $10,000, the detective was told, all evil spirits embroiling her life would vanish, Mr. Fahy said. The detective gave Ms. Miller $1,000, he said, and she soon found herself charged with bilking the detective and the woman, and ordered held on $10,000 bond.</p>
        <p>After the victim went for the tarot-card reading last year, Ms. Miller convinced her that her life was clouded by a "bad aura" and her bad luck and unhappiness with a boyfriend were rooted in money, Mr. Fahy said. "Basically, she said that money is bad," Mr. Fahy said.</p>
        <p>Early in their 13 months of meetings, the victim was told to bring water in a sterilized mayonnaise jar and to place it between her knees during prayer, Mr. Fahy said. When the victim was told to look upward, Ms. Miller slipped a dark substance into the jar, turning the water black, and told her victim the color signified bad omens, he said.</p>
        <p>"She said she would heal her negativity and create a better relationship with her boyfriend and get her life back on track," said David Nathanson, chief of the fraud division in Mr. Fahy's office.</p>
        <p>Early in the scam, Mr. Nathanson said, the businesswoman turned over thousands of dollars in cash from her savings and then, when that was depleted, she started paying with checks made out to cash. In the end, the woman surrendered her credit cards, which Mr. Fahy said Ms. Miller used to pay for a wide-screen television set, clothing from Victoria's Secret and a $2,500 trip to Florida with her live-in boyfriend.</p>
        <p>The charge against Ms. Miller, theft by deception, was based on unreasonable promises that she would lift the evil in the woman's life and improve her relationships for money, Mr. Fahy said. "The idea money is bad and relations can be corrected by disposing of money is absurd on its face," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
