<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loss Leaves Schundler In Search of Political Role</title>
    <meta content="10SCHU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/10/nyregion/10SCHU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1341573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schundler, Bret D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Newark</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Schundler, Bret D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2D91438F933A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loss Leaves Schundler In Search of Political Role</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Loss Leaves Schundler in Search of Political Role</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, NOV. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bret Schundler's concession speech, in which he delivers rambling call to arms, draws mixed reviews; it causes concern among nervous Republicans who see Schundler's brand of conservative Republicanism as recipe for permanent disaster for party; Republican leaders are vague about what role Schundler and his supporters have in party; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a race full of difficult moments, Bret D.  Schundler left his party pondering one final awkward note after he was trounced by James E. McGreevey on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Rather than simply concede defeat and thank his supporters, he delivered a rambling call to arms. He recalled the political differences with fellow Republicans that he suggested had helped sink his campaign, and warned Mr. McGreevey, a Democrat, that Mr. Schundler's supporters would be watching him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEWARK, NOV. 9  In a race full of difficult moments, Bret D. Schundler left his party pondering one final awkward note after he was trounced by James E. McGreevey on Tuesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a race full of difficult moments, Bret D.  Schundler left his party pondering one final awkward note after he was trounced by James E. McGreevey on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Rather than simply concede defeat and thank his supporters, he delivered a rambling call to arms. He recalled the political differences with fellow Republicans that he suggested had helped sink his campaign, and warned Mr. McGreevey, a Democrat, that Mr. Schundler's supporters would be watching him.</p>
        <p>It was an odd performance for a candidate who had just lost his bid for governor by 14 percentage points. And if it excited some of his  supporters, it is still being dissected by other nervous Republicans who see Mr. Schundler's brand of conservative Republicanism as a recipe for permanent disaster for the party.</p>
        <p>Republican leaders like Joseph M. Kyrillos Jr., state senator and chairman of the state party, say publicly that Mr. Schundler and the conservatives who backed him have a role in the party's future.  But they are vague about what exactly that role will be.</p>
        <p>Others were still trying to make sense of Mr. Schundler's election-night farewell.</p>
        <p>''His whole concession speech went on for too long, and I just didn't stay for it,'' said John O. Bennett, the newly chosen Republican leader in the State Senate, which is now evenly split between the two parties. ''I think there is a position in the party for him, but I leave it to others to decide if he will be a candidate in the future.''</p>
        <p>Ronald Posyton, a Union County Republican who broke ranks to support Mr. McGreevey, said that the election-night performance simply reinforced his view that ''for a smart man Mr. Schundler does some stupid things.''</p>
        <p>''I thought he was running all over again with that speech,'' he said.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's political history suggests that a candidate has to run at least once and lose in order to build the support base and name recognition to eventually succeed.  That was the case with Christie Whitman, the Republican who came close to defeating Bill Bradley in the 1990 Senate race before returning a year later in a successful run for governor. The same held true for Mr. McGreevey, who came surprisingly close to defeating Mrs. Whitman in 1997 as a prelude to his election this time.</p>
        <p>But even Mr. Schundler's partisans, like Assemblyman John E. Rooney, Republican of Northvale,  question whether he will replicate that pattern. Indeed, some Republicans said that he could instead go down in history with James Courter and Peter Shapiro, a Republican and Democrat respectively, who lost their gubernatorial races by large margins and slipped from political view.</p>
        <p>''All those others like Whitman and McGreevey came close, and when you lose by the margins that Bret did, people don't forget,'' said Mr. Rooney, who noted that even in largely Republican Bergen County,  Mr. Schundler lost by 11 percentage points. ''The numbers are the numbers and if you can't come close as the statewide candidate you shouldn't be the candidate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rooney and David Rebovich, a political scientist at Rider University, both said that Mr. Schundler would perhaps be of more help to his party in a post in the Bush administration rather than in the state, where his uncompromising conservatism has limited appeal.</p>
        <p>Such a move would be welcomed by some Republican candidates in New Jersey who found themselves spending money on advertisements and mailings intended to differentiate their positions on abortion and gun control from Mr. Schundler's after Democrats had lumped them all together.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schundler, for his part, spent the days after the election talking privately with supporters. He has refused to grant interviews to analyze the voting or to speculate on his future. But William Pascoe, his campaign manager, said that the former Jersey City mayor had no plans at this point to seek a job in Washington and intended to assert his leadership as the party's standard bearer.</p>
        <p>''I think that what you are likely to see from Bret is political activity behind an agenda that unites New Jerseyans,'' Mr. Pascoe said. ''He will be taking on issues, not in a partisan way. You shouldn't look for him to be rallying the troops in Trenton.''</p>
        <p>Jim Florio, Democrat and former governor, predicted that it was just that kind of role that would bedevil Republican legislative and party leaders in their efforts to heal wounds and regroup after this week's losses.</p>
        <p>''What was most troubling to me the other night was Mayor Schundler and his sort of campaign harangue in his concession speech, and he was sending out signals that 'as soon as you start to do anything I'm going to be on you,' '' Mr. Florio said.</p>
        <p>''The problem is not going to be McGreevey's, it's going to be the Republican Party's, and they're going to have to figure out what to do with him,'' he said of Mr. Schundler.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
