<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Texas Town Holds Fast to Its Ties to a Classic</title>
    <meta content="Y09MAR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/09/national/09MARF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1495564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Marfa (Tex)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dean, James (1931-55)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hudson, Rock (D1985)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hopper, Dennis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Giant (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Marfa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Texas</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4D91539F93AA35755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1244" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Texas Town Holds Fast to Its Ties to a Classic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Texas Town Holds Fast to Its Ties to a Classic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <dateline>MARFA, Tex., June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More than 150 people gather in Marfa, Texas, to watch first public screening of movie Giant since director George Stevens brought James Dean, Elizabeth Taylor, Rock Hudson and Dennis Hopper there in 1955 to film what was then most expensive movie ever made; Giant captured transformation of Texas from artistocratic ranching economy into state dominated by roughhewn oilmen; screening concides with scheduled release of digital version of movie; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All that remains of the Victorian mansion's facade are some timbers stretching into the sky above the West Texas plain. The Rolls-Royce parked among the cattle herd has been replaced by a pickup truck with a bumper sticker proclaiming, ''Beef: It's What's For Dinner.''</p>
        <p>Yet the legacy of ''Giant,'' the 1956 film that captured the transformation of Texas from an aristocratic ranching economy into a state dominated by rough-hewn oilmen, persists. Nowhere more, perhaps, than in this town of about 2,300 in the Big Bend region of Texas, where ''Giant'' was filmed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The legacy of "Giant," the 1956 film that captured the transformation of Texas, persists in a town of about 2,300 where the movie was filmed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All that remains of the Victorian mansion's facade are some timbers stretching into the sky above the West Texas plain. The Rolls-Royce parked among the cattle herd has been replaced by a pickup truck with a bumper sticker proclaiming, ''Beef: It's What's For Dinner.''</p>
        <p>Yet the legacy of ''Giant,'' the 1956 film that captured the transformation of Texas from an aristocratic ranching economy into a state dominated by rough-hewn oilmen, persists. Nowhere more, perhaps, than in this town of about 2,300 in the Big Bend region of Texas, where ''Giant'' was filmed.</p>
        <p>More than 150 people gathered on the patio of Hotel El Paisano here on Saturday night to watch the first public screening of ''Giant'' in Marfa since the director George Stevens brought James Dean, Elizabeth Taylor, Rock Hudson and Dennis Hopper here in 1955 to film what was then the most expensive movie ever made. The screening coincided with the scheduled release of the digital version of the movie on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The filming of ''Giant,'' which cost $5 million to make, left an impression among residents here.</p>
        <p>''I'm a little too much of an old lady to say this, but boy did Jimmy Dean have this little sexy giggle,'' Lucy Garcia, a retired baby sitter who was 15 when the film was made, said in an interview. ''We had a 10 p.m. curfew back then, but I'd stay out until 9:59, trying to get me a look at Jimmy.''</p>
        <p>For its time, ''Giant'' was considered forward-looking because it explored the segregation between whites and Mexican-Americans in West Texas. One of the film's defining moments is when Rock Hudson's character, the land baron Jordan (Bick) Benedict, gets into a fistfight over the honor of his grandson, who is half Hispanic. (He loses.)</p>
        <p>But the movie's impact went beyond Marfa. The play ''Come Back to the Five and Dime, Jimmy Dean, Jimmy Dean,'' by Ed Graczyk, describes a group of people in the fictitious small Texas town of McCarthy, which gathers 20 years after the star was killed in a car accident shortly after completing ''Giant.''</p>
        <p>Tino Villanueva wrote a book-length poem, ''Scene From the Movie Giant,'' that explored the racial tension in Texas between Latinos and whites. Some residents said that tension still lingered in Marfa, even as the town has started a transformation from a ranching outpost into an artist colony.</p>
        <p>The Chinati Foundation, built to house large-scale sculpture, has brought in a stream of outsiders. The town's main movie house, the Palace Theater, shut down in the 1970's and now serves as a studio for a private illustrator. Across the street, the Texas Theater, which was frequented mainly by Mexican-Americans, is shuttered.</p>
        <p>''Back then it was pretty damn near impossible for a Mexican boy to go out with an Anglo girl,'' said Mateo Quintana, 67, who owns a barbershop on Highland Street, Marfa's main drag. ''Those months when they were making 'Giant' were kind of a chance to forget about all that.''</p>
        <p>During the filming of the movie, Warner Brothers kept a plane at Marfa's airstrip to carry each day's film to California, where it was processed and returned the following day for editing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stevens, the director, viewed the rough edits at screenings -- which were open to the public -- at the Palace Theater.</p>
        <p>The crew and nearly the entire cast stayed at the Paisano, recalled Marcos Pe単a, who as a teenager worked as a porter at the hotel.</p>
        <p>''I used to serve Elizabeth Taylor breakfast every morning; she liked a fruit plate,'' said Mr. Pe単a, 67, who now works as a serviceman for a gas company. ''She had this silver bowl filled with money that she'd stick her hand into and give me tips of $1, $5, whatever was in there.''</p>
        <p>Leaning on the fence outside his trailer home, Mr. Pe単a said in an interview that James Dean, who played the role of Jett Rink, the ranch hand turned oil tycoon, was the most amicable of the cast, often shooting pool with townspeople in the basement of the hotel. Rock Hudson, Mr. Pe単a said, was ''a little bit more conservative, kind of like a snob.''</p>
        <p>Unlike many other parts of Texas, Marfa -- which was named in 1883 by the wife of a railroad executive after a character in the Dostoyevsky novel ''Brothers Karamazov'' -- remained dependent on ranching even after the Texas oil boom.</p>
        <p>''Giant was considered a highwater mark of a certain view of Texas when it was still thought of with some awe as a super-state,'' said Don B. Graham, a professor of English at the University of Texas and author of ''Cowboys and Cadillacs: How Hollywood Looks at Texas.''</p>
        <p>Nostalgia for the state's ranching ethos permeated the screening of ''Giant'' on Saturday night, which was sponsored by Warner Brothers. Proceeds from the $50-per-ticket event -- organized by Kirby F. Warnock, a part-time rancher and documentary filmmaker -- went to Marfa's library.</p>
        <p>Two actors who appeared in the movie, Jane Withers (Vashti Snythe) and Earl Holliman (Bob Dace), signed autographs.</p>
        <p>'' 'Giant' continues to define Texas,'' said Bill D. Rollins, a San Antonio stockbroker and energy company executive, who attended the fund-raiser wearing cowboy boots with the words ''Giant'' and ''Marfa'' tooled into the leather. ''It's about the power of the land, both above it for the herds and below it for the mineral rights.''</p>
        <p>Clay Evans, on whose family ranch ''Giant'' was filmed, sat quietly for a moment in the cab of his pickup Saturday night after fans of the film made a pilgrimage to the site where the facade of Bick Benedict's mansion has been left to the elements, a few tame antelope and the occasional jack rabbit.</p>
        <p>''My daddy let the Hollywood people on our land and we had some fun,'' Mr. Evans, 67, said.</p>
        <p>While some residents of Marfa reminisce fondly about the filming of ''Giant,'' others say some of the issues raised in the film still persist -- even after the population of 3,600 dwindled by more than a third in the mid-1950's, when the debate over segregation gained momentum in Texas and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>For example, Ms. Garcia, the former baby sitter, said Hispanics and Anglos in Marfa were at odds over space in the town's cemeteries, which remain almost entirely segregated. Whites in Marfa, she said, were hesitant to sell Hispanics the land they need to enlarge their cemetery.</p>
        <p>''A lot of us Mexicans are still pushed around by the gringo like in the time of 'Giant,' '' Ms. Garcia said. ''Some things in Texas take a long time to die.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
