<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Court Ruling in Entrapment Case</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="519662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PORNOGRAPHY AND OBSCENITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENTRAPMENT, LEGAL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACOBSON, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D81E39F934A35757C0A964958260" item-length="1729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Court Ruling in Entrapment Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the Supreme Court's decision today in Jacobson v. United States, holding that the Government entrapped a Nebraska farmer into violating the law against child pornography. Justice Byron R. White wrote the majority opinion, joined by Justices Harry A. Blackmun, John Paul Stevens, David H. Souter and Clarence Thomas. Justice Sandra Day O'Connor's dissenting opinion was joined by Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and by Justices Anthony M. Kennedy and Antonin Scalia. FROM THE DECISION By Justice White</p>
        <p>On Sept. 24, 1987, petitioner Keith Jacobson was indicted for violating a provision of the Child Protection Act of 1984, which criminalizes the knowing receipt through the mails of a "visual depiction (that) involves the use of a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct." Petitioner defended on the ground that the Government entrapped him into committing the crime through a series of communications from undercover agents that spanned the 26 months preceding his arrest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the Supreme Court's decision today in Jacobson v. United States, holding that the Government entrapped a Nebraska farmer into violating the law against child pornography. Justice Byron R. White wrote the majority opinion, joined by Justices Harry A. Blackmun, John Paul Stevens, David H. Souter and Clarence Thomas. Justice Sandra Day O'Connor's dissenting opinion was joined by Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and by Justices Anthony M. Kennedy and Antonin Scalia. FROM THE DECISION By Justice White</p>
        <p>On Sept. 24, 1987, petitioner Keith Jacobson was indicted for violating a provision of the Child Protection Act of 1984, which criminalizes the knowing receipt through the mails of a "visual depiction (that) involves the use of a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct." Petitioner defended on the ground that the Government entrapped him into committing the crime through a series of communications from undercover agents that spanned the 26 months preceding his arrest.</p>
        <p>Petitioner was found guilty after a jury trial. The Court of Appeals affirmed his conviction, holding that the Government had carried its burden of proving beyond reasonable doubt that petitioner was predisposed to break the law and hence was not entrapped.</p>
        <p>Because the Government overstepped the line between setting a trap for the "unwary innocent" and the "unwary criminal,"</p>
        <p>Sherman v. United States,</p>
        <p>and as a matter of law failed to establish that petitioner was independently predisposed to commit the crime for which he was arrested, we reverse the Court of Appeals judgment affirming his conviction.</p>
        <p>In February 1984, petitioner, a 56-year-old veteran-turned-farmer who supported his elderly father in Nebraska, ordered two magazines and a brochure from a California adult bookstore. The magazines, entitled Bare Boys I and Bare Boys II, contained photographs of nude pre-teen and teen-age boys. The contents of the magazines startled petitioner, who testified that he had expected to receive photographs of "young men 18 years or older." . . .</p>
        <p>The young men depicted in the magazines were not engaged in sexual activity, and petitioner's receipt of the magazines was legal under both Federal and Nebraska law. Within three months the law with respect to child pornography changed; Congress passed the act illegalizing the receipt through the mails of sexually explicit depictions of children.</p>
        <p>In the very month that the new provision became law, postal inspectors found petitioner's name on the mailing list of the California bookstore that had mailed him Bare Boys I and II. There followed, over the next two years, repeated efforts by two Government agencies, through five fictitious organizations and a bogus pen pal, to explore petitioner's willingness to break the new law by ordering sexually explicit photographs of children through the mail.</p>
        <p>The Government began its efforts in January 1985 when a postal inspector sent petitioner a letter supposedly from the American Hedonist Society, which in fact was a fictitious organization. The letter included a membership application. . . .</p>
        <p>Petitioner enrolled in the organization and returned a sexual attitude questionnaire that asked him to rank on a scale of one to four his enjoyment of various sexual materials, with one being "really enjoy," two being "enjoy," three being "somewhat enjoy," and four being "do not enjoy." Petitioner ranked the entry " [ p ] re-teen sex" as a two, but indicated he was opposed to pedophilia.</p>
        <p>For a time, the Government left petitioner alone. But then a new "prohibited mail specialist" in the Postal Service found petitioner's name in a file, and in May 1986 petitioner received a solicitation from a second fictitious consumer research company, "Midlands Data Research." . . . Petitioner responded: "Please feel free to send me more information, I am interested in teen-age sexuality. Please keep my name confidential."</p>
        <p>Petitioner then heard from yet another Government creation, "Heartland Institute for a New Tomorrow" (HINT), which proclaimed that it was "an organization founded to protect and promote sexual freedom and freedom of choice. We believe that arbitrarily imposed legislative sanctions restricting your sexual freedom should be rescinded through the legislative process." The letter also enclosed a second survey. Petitioner indicated that his interest in " [ p ] reteen sex-homosexual" material was above average, but not high. . . . Potential 'Pen Pals'</p>
        <p>HINT also provided computer matching of group members with similar survey responses; although petitioner was supplied with a list of potential "pen pals," he did not initiate any correspondence.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the Government's "prohibited mail specialist" began writing to petitioner, using the pseudonym "Carl Long." The letters employed a tactic known as "mirroring," which the inspector described as "reflect(ing) whatever the interests are of the person we are writing to." Petitioner responded at first, indicating that his interest was primarily in "male-male items." . . .</p>
        <p>Petitioner's letters to "Long" made no reference to child pornography. After writing two letters, petitioner discontinued the correspondence.</p>
        <p>By March 1987, 34 months had passed since the Government obtained petitioner's name from the mailing list of the California bookstore, and 26 months had passed since the Postal Service had commenced its mailings to petitioner. Although petitioner had responded to surveys and letters, the Government had no evidence that petitioner had ever intentionally possessed or been exposed to child pornography.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>Petitioner responded. A catalogue was sent and petitioner ordered Boys Who Love Boys, a pornographic magazine depicting young boys engaged in various sexual activities. Petitioner was arrested after a controlled delivery of a photocopy of the magazine. Petitioner's Explanation</p>
        <p>When petitioner was asked at trial why he placed such an order, he explained that the Government had succeeded in piquing his curiosity. . . .</p>
        <p>In petitioner's home, the Government found the Bare Boys magazines and materials that the Government had sent to him in the course of its protracted investigation, but no other materials that would indicate that petitioner collected or was actively interested in child pornography. . . .</p>
        <p>There can be no dispute about the evils of child pornography or the difficulties that laws and law enforcement have encountered in eliminating it. Likewise, there can be no dispute that the Government may use undercover agents to enforce the law. . . .</p>
        <p>In their zeal to enforce the law, however, Government agents may not originate a criminal design, implant in an innocent person's mind the disposition to commit a criminal act, and then induce commission of the crime so that the Government may prosecute. Where the Government has induced an individual to break the law and the defense of entrapment is at issue, as it was in this case, the prosecution must prove beyond reasonable doubt that the defendant was disposed to commit the criminal act prior to first being approached by Government agents.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>When the Government's quest for convictions leads to the apprehension of an otherwise law-abiding citizen who, if left to his own devices, likely would have never run afoul of the law, the courts should intervene.</p>
        <p>Because we conclude that this is such a case and that the prosecution failed, as a matter of law, to adduce evidence to support the jury verdict that petitioner was predisposed, independent of the Government's acts and beyond a reasonable doubt, to violate the law by receiving child pornography through the mails, we reverse the Court of Appeals judgment affirming the conviction of Keith Jacobson. FROM THE DISSENT By Justice O'Connor</p>
        <p>This Court has held previously that a defendant's predisposition is to be assessed as of the time the Government agent first suggested the crime, not when the Government agent first became involved. Until the Government actually makes a suggestion of criminal conduct, it could not be said to have "implant(ed) in the mind of an innocent person the disposition to commit the alleged offense and induce its commission." . . .</p>
        <p>Today the Court holds that Government conduct may be considered to create a predisposition to commit a crime, even before any Government action to induce the commission of the crime. In my view, this holding changes entrapment doctrine.</p>
        <p>Generally, the inquiry is whether a suspect is predisposed before the Government induces the commission of the crime, not before the Government makes initial contact with him. There is no dispute here that the Government's questionnaires and letters were not sufficient to establish inducement; they did not even suggest that Mr. Jacobson should engage in any illegal activity. If all the Government had done was to send these materials, Mr. Jacobson's entrapment defense would fail.</p>
        <p>Yet, the Court holds that the Government must prove not only that a suspect was predisposed to commit the crime before the opportunity to commit it arose, but also before the Government came on the scene.</p>
        <p>The rule that preliminary Government contact can create a predisposition has the potential to be misread by lower courts as well as criminal investigators as requiring that the Government must have sufficient evidence of a defendant's predisposition before it ever seeks to contact him. Surely, the Court cannot intend to impose such a requirement, for it would mean that the Government must have a reasonable suspicion of criminal activity before it begins an investigation, a condition that we have never before imposed.</p>
        <p>The Court denies that its new rule will affect run-of-the-mill sting operations, and one hopes that it means what it says. Nonetheless, after this case, every defendant will claim that something the Government agent did before soliciting the crime "created" a predisposition that was not there before. . . .</p>
        <p>The Court's rule is all the more troubling because it does not distinguish between Government conduct that merely highlights the temptation of the crime itself and Government conduct that threatens, coerces or leads a suspect to commit a crime in order to fulfill some other obligation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
