<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Page Two: Feb. 6-12; What's in a Name? In Politics, a Lot.</title>
    <meta content="13PAGETWO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/13/weekinreview/13pagetwo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1649691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="The Week in the News"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulse, Carl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winston, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2D8143AF930A25751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Page Two: Feb. 6-12; What's in a Name? In Politics, a Lot.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Feb. 6 - 12</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawmakers are choosing their words with care as they lay foundation for major policy fights, aware that way they characterize legislation can decide its fate; biggest current debate is over Social Security; Republicans refer to personal accounts when describing proposal to let workers invest part of their payroll taxes; Democrats call them private accounts, few syllables away from privatization; Republican pollster David Winston says survey he took found that people opposed 'privatization' by 53 percent to 38 percent; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is a war of words on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>Are those proposed new Social Security accounts private or personal? Would a procedural effort to halt Senate filibusters be deploying the nuclear or constitutional option? Was the measure passed by the House last week to make it tougher to get into and remain in the country a border security or immigration bill?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As lawmakers on Capitol Hill lay the foundation for major policy fights, they are choosing their words with care, aware that the way they characterize legislation can decide its fates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is a war of words on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>Are those proposed new Social Security accounts private or personal? Would a procedural effort to halt Senate filibusters be deploying the nuclear or constitutional option? Was the measure passed by the House last week to make it tougher to get into and remain in the country a border security or immigration bill?</p>
        <p>As lawmakers lay the foundation for major policy fights, they are choosing their words with care, aware that the way they characterize legislation can decide its fates.</p>
        <p>''We are learning the importance of language,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, whose party has recently been lagging behind the opposition in legislative phrase-making.</p>
        <p>Politicians have always polished bill titles and come up with catchy slogans. Democrats did it when they controlled Congress -- consider the New Deal and the Great Society. But under Newt Gingrich in the mid-1990's, Republicans made language a focus of their politics, studying polls to find words that worked.</p>
        <p>Their success at turning the staid old estate tax -- a name redolent of Rockefellers and Vanderbilts -- into the diabolical death tax was a triumph. So was labeling a medical procedure partial birth abortion.</p>
        <p>The biggest current debate is over Social Security. The Republicans refer to personal accounts when describing the proposal to let workers invest part of their payroll taxes. The other side calls them private accounts, a few syllables away from privatization.</p>
        <p>Republicans are fighting that word -- which they once embraced -- by saying that it incorrectly implies that their plan takes the program out of government. ''Personal is ownership, private is outside the Social Security system,'' said Representative Paul Ryan, Republican of Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>He acknowledges that polls show the pri-word is a loser. David Winston, a Republican pollster, said that a survey he took in December found that people opposed ''privatization'' by 53 percent to 38 percent. The same people supported ''personal retirement accounts,'' 60 percent to 35 percent. ''The brand of 'privatization' at this point is not necessarily popular,'' Mr. Winston said.</p>
        <p>Democrats and others say the Republicans want to hide the true nature of their plan. ''If it looks like a pig and acts like a pig, it is a pig,'' said Senator Ron Wyden, Democrat of Oregon. ''They can dress it up different ways, but this is code for privatization.''</p>
        <p>PEACE PROSPECT -- Mahmoud Abbas, the Palestinian president, and Ariel Sharon, the prime minister of Israel, declared a truce at a meeting in Egypt. Mr. Abbas said they had ''jointly agreed to cease all acts of violence against Israelis and Palestinians everywhere,'' while Mr. Sharon said they ''agreed that all Palestinians will stop all acts of violence against all Israelis everywhere, and in parallel, Israel will cease all its military activity against all Palestinians everywhere.''</p>
        <p>The radical Palestinian group Hamas said the truce was not binding on it, and Palestinian factions mounted a mortar-and-rocket attack on Jewish settlements in the southern Gaza Strip. Mr. Abbas responded by firing three of his security chiefs in Gaza, which aides said reflected his determination to enforce the cease-fire.</p>
        <p>NUCLEAR REVELATION -- North Korea declared for the first time that it possessed nuclear weapons, and refused to return to disarmament talks. American officials said they were surprised by the timing of the announcement, but that intelligence agencies had assumed for years that the North probably had such weapons.</p>
        <p>CLASS ACTION -- In a victory for President Bush and business groups, the Senate voted to make large class-action lawsuits against companies harder to file by requiring that they be filed in federal courts, which are already bound by restrictive precedents in such cases, rather than state courts. Quick passage is expected in the House.</p>
        <p>ARTHUR MILLER'S LEGACY. One of America's most celebrated playwrights died Thursday night at the age of 89. His best-known play, ''Death of a Salesman,'' was acclaimed a masterpiece, though some criticized it as too sentimental. Few could deny the durability of many lines, including:</p>
        <p>''You can't eat the orange and throw the peel away -- a man is not a piece of fruit.''</p>
        <p>''Attention must be paid.''</p>
        <p>The Week in the News</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
