<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Democracy on These Ballots</title>
    <meta content="13AGENDA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="SundayBusiness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/13/business/yourmoney/13agenda.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1649660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE AGENDA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Exxon Mobil Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4DE143AF930A25751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Democracy on These Ballots</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Democracy on These Ballots</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Emil Rossi believes that corporations should adopt changes that receive more than half of votes at their annual meetings, but companies in which he is shareholder have proved very resistant; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PRESIDENT BUSH has been preaching the benefits of democracy to people throughout the Middle East. But back home, corporate executives and securities regulators are making it clear they do not believe that what is good for Iraqis will be good for General Motors -- or any other public company.</p>
        <p>The notion that the majority of shareholders should rule is still treated as a quaint one, at best, in most American boardrooms. Just ask Emil Rossi, who is so hard-headed that he thinks companies should adopt changes that receive more than half of the votes at annual meetings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>PRESIDENT BUSH has been preaching the benefits of democracy to people throughout the Middle East. But back home, corporate executives and securities regulators are making it clear they do not believe that what is good for Iraqis will be good for General Motors - or any other public company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PRESIDENT BUSH has been preaching the benefits of democracy to people throughout the Middle East. But back home, corporate executives and securities regulators are making it clear they do not believe that what is good for Iraqis will be good for General Motors -- or any other public company.</p>
        <p>The notion that the majority of shareholders should rule is still treated as a quaint one, at best, in most American boardrooms. Just ask Emil Rossi, who is so hard-headed that he thinks companies should adopt changes that receive more than half of the votes at annual meetings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rossi is no dewy-eyed naïf. He knows that companies are not bound by the votes on most shareholder proposals. From the cluttered office in his family's hardware store in Boonville, Calif., he has been trying for three decades to exercise his rights as an investor in dozens of large corporations. Now 80, he says his mission is not getting any easier, despite all the talk of a revolution in corporate governance.</p>
        <p>''They treat us like we have leprosy,'' he said of the executives and lawyers who devise arguments against putting shareholders' proposals to a vote. ''Every one of them will give us an argument to throw them off. It's silly. They're like a bunch of 8-year-old kids.''</p>
        <p>His recent tangle with Exxon Mobil illustrates his point. In September, Mr. Rossi sent the company an informal two-paragraph letter proposing a shareholder vote on the question of whether the majority's will should be done. ''If the shareholder's vote does not count, how does that make the shareholders the owners of the company,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>Most of the proposals that Mr. Rossi and his sons, Nick and Chris, have submitted over the years have dealt with the removal of takeover defenses known as poison pills, which, in their opinion, suppressed the value of their shares. This one grew out of Mr. Rossi's frustration with companies that had ignored proposals that had won as many as 70 percent of votes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rossi made clear that he had standing to make his demand by noting that he owned 9,984 shares of Exxon Mobil's stock, a stake then worth about $470,000.</p>
        <p>The company's executives threw up their first defense in less than two weeks. Henry H. Hubble, a vice president for investor relations at Exxon Mobil's headquarters in Irving, Tex., challenged Mr. Rossi to prove that he met the basic requirement to propose a resolution: having held shares worth at least $2,000 ''for at least one year by the date you submit a proposal.''</p>
        <p>As proof, Mr. Rossi provided a listing from his broker of the holdings in an account at Morgan Stanley. It said he had deposited the shares he claimed on March 7, 2003, more than 18 months before he submitted his proposal.</p>
        <p>That was when Mr. Hubble started splitting hairs. For one thing, he countered, Mr. Rossi had submitted evidence that he owned the shares on Sept. 8, the day he sent the letter, but what mattered was whether he owned them on Sept. 14, the day his letter was received.</p>
        <p>For another, he showed that he owned enough shares on March 7, 2003, and on Sept. 8, 2004, but not all along the way. Mr. Hubble instructed Mr. Rossi that he had to show that he had ''owned the shares continuously for at least the one-year period.''</p>
        <p>Smelling obstruction, Mr. Rossi scribbled off a quick retort to Mr. Hubble saying, ''Your objections are a colossal waste of the shareholder's meeting.'' He had submitted the same proposal to GenCorp, another of his investments, and that company had accepted the same accounting of his holdings as proof.</p>
        <p>But in both instances, the question of ownership was merely a skirmish before the big guns were rolled out. Both companies turned to big law firms for the ammunition they needed to persuade the Securities and Exchange Commission that Mr. Rossi's idea was not only radical but possibly illegal.</p>
        <p>GenCorp's lawyers at Jones Day, a law firm in Cleveland, laid out in 10 pages of detail why Mr. Rossi's proposal would violate Ohio law and could leave directors powerless to exercise their good judgment.</p>
        <p>Exxon Mobil's lawyers at Pitney Hardin in Morristown, N.J., came up with a six-page letter to the company's board explaining how the majority-rule proposal ''directly contravenes New Jersey law and, if implemented, would cause the board to violate its fiduciary duty.'' (Although Exxon Mobil is based in Texas, its predecessor, Standard Oil, was chartered in New Jersey.)</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Exxon Mobil said no shareholder proposal had ever received a majority of votes, but the company's board would reconsider any that did.</p>
        <p>In each case, regulators at the commission said they would not recommend any action against the company if it left Mr. Rossi's proposal off its 2005 proxy. Reached at his store, Mr. Rossi sounded frustrated but unsurprised by the defeats.</p>
        <p>''I've built up a great distrust and it would take an awful lot to change my opinion of them as a rule,'' he said, speaking generally of corporate management. ''It hit me wrong to begin with that things weren't democratically done. All over the world we're telling them to be democratic, and here we turn around and say no.''</p>
        <p>THE AGENDA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
