<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>America Online's new campaign is designed to point consumers in several new directions.</title>
    <meta content="06ADCO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/06/business/media/06adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1616863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">America Online Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFDF163BF935A35753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>America Online's new campaign is designed to point consumers in several new directions.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">America Online Launches a New Ad Campaign</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nat Ives</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMERICA Online will begin a new ad campaign tomorrow with a new logo and a refocused brand promise, posed as a question to consumers: ''Want a better Internet?''</p>
        <p>Executives hope that the answer -- which company research says is ''yes'' -- will prod consumers to take a fresh look at AOL.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>America Online will begin a new ad campaign with a new logo and a refocused brand promise, posed as a question to consumers: "Want a better Internet?"</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMERICA Online will begin a new ad campaign tomorrow with a new logo and a refocused brand promise, posed as a question to consumers: ''Want a better Internet?''</p>
        <p>Executives hope that the answer -- which company research says is ''yes'' -- will prod consumers to take a fresh look at AOL.</p>
        <p>''America Online has gone through a transition, and is continuing to go through a transition,'' said Joe Redling, chief marketing officer at AOL, a unit of Time Warner. ''We needed to transform AOL from a 'one product, one size fits all' dial-up brand into an online services company that's relevant across a number of segments.''</p>
        <p>As the campaign proceeds, America Online hopes to begin selling even nonmembers products that could include antivirus packages, digital photography programs and telephone service over the Internet, using the technology known as voice-over-Internet protocol. AOL has already begun seeking new contacts with nonsubscribers throughIn-Store.com, a comparison shopping site that the company introduced last month.</p>
        <p>But the initial, and familiar, challenge for AOL will be convincing Web surfers that it offers something that other companies do not, said Tom Wolzien, a media analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company. ''That goes to the question of, once you've got a high-speed connection to the Web, why do you need these guys?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Since America Online evolved from Quantum Computer Services, an Internet bulletin board that was incorporated in 1985, it has often been considered an entry-level Internet service. ''Its problem was that it hadn't kept up with the rest of the Web,'' Mr. Wolzien said. Now the company is trying to embrace the most sophisticated applications while retaining its easy-to-use reputation.</p>
        <p>The campaign comes amid improved financial results at AOL. Most recently, its second-quarter advertising revenue totaled $221 million, up 23 percent over the second quarter of last year. (Time Warner will present its third-quarter results on Nov. 3.)</p>
        <p>Although the number of AOL's United States subscribers fell by 668,000 to 23.4 million during the second quarter, the number of broadband subscribers, about 4 million, was almost double from the year-earlier number.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Time Warner said it was reviewing the accounting at AOL Europe before 2002 and that the review could lead to financial restatements. Earlier, Time Warner said that the Securities and Exchange Commission and the Justice Department were examining the way the company handled $400 million in ad revenue that AOL received from Bertelsmann, the German media company.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Wolzien says the company remains the largest Internet services provider by membership and one of the largest cash-flow producers within Time Warner. ''Therefore it's very important to the company that AOL is ultimately successful.''</p>
        <p>The campaign, backed by an estimated $30 million this quarter, begins with two-page ads tomorrow in The Wall Street Journal, The Washington Post and The New York Times.</p>
        <p>''Today,'' the ads will say, ''we're announcing a series of commitments that will drive our employees to one common goal: to make life online better for our members, and in so doing, to improve their lives.''</p>
        <p>They then list eight points or promises, for example: ''AOL will simplify the vast possibilities of the online experience for our members, no matter how complicated the Internet becomes.''</p>
        <p>Point No. 7 (''AOL will continuously innovate for our members'') emphasizes services like fighting spam, an area that the company sought to bolster in July with the purchase of Mailblocks in Los Altos, Calif., a developer of a service intended to block spam, for undisclosed terms.</p>
        <p>The print ads were created by the Martin Agency in Richmond, Va., part of the Interpublic Group of Companies that was added to the AOL roster in August.</p>
        <p>Mike Hughes, president and creative director at Martin, says the ads are meant to speak to the business community without any Madison Avenue bombast. ''We've tried to get out of the way and let the facts tell the story,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Television commercials created by BBDO Worldwide in New York will enter rotation on Monday during the baseball playoffs. The first shows a huge crowd of AOL members assembling at headquarters with ideas on improving the Internet. The second depicts a member who pops into the AOL boardroom with a long list of suggestions. They were filmed on the AOL corporate campus in Dulles, Va.</p>
        <p>Bill Bruce, executive vice president and executive creative director at BBDO New York, part of the Omnicom Group, said the Internet had reached a point where AOL should recommit to its members. ''As the Internet started in its infancy, there was a sense of wonder and awe at people connecting,'' Mr. Bruce said. ''At this point, people are starting to understand there are things online they like or dislike. America Online is their advocate.'' Further commercials are planned.</p>
        <p>All elements of the campaign will feature a new logo designed by the Desgrippes Gobé Group, an image and brand consulting company. The updated logo turns the familiar triangle into a directional pointer and puts it to work zipping down a list of connection options -- broadband, wireless and dial-up -- that the company offers.</p>
        <p>But one element is still up in the air. ''We're still tweaking the final tag line,'' said Mr. Redling, the AOL executive. ''It always comes down to the last week.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
