<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Apple Sending Clone Makers Mixed Signals</title>
    <meta content="11APPL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="949957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Apple Computer Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Laurie J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Fred</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DB113CF932A2575BC0A961958260" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Apple Sending Clone Makers Mixed Signals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Apple Computer executives have not said whether company would continue to license Macintosh operating system to makers of lower-priced Mac clones, an issue of strategic importance to future of troubled company; this has fueled speculation that Apple executives think clones do Apple more harm than good; clone sales now account for one of every five Macintosh computers sold; remarks made by Apple's chief financial officer, Fred Anderson, at MacWorld Expo trade show, indicate that Apple would not prolong its licensing agreements unless clone makers demonstrate commitment to expanding Macintosh market; analysts say this means clone makers would need to concentrate on Apple's weakest markets, like low-end consumer machines and certain geographic areas, and leave higher-margin markets to Apple; clone makers have been angling to increase breadth of their offerings, not narrow them (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With all the momentous announcements at last week's MacWorld Expo trade show, Apple Computer executives were nearly silent on an issue of strategic importance to the future of the troubled company: Whether Apple would continue to license the Macintosh operating system to makers of lower-priced Mac clones.</p>
        <p>The absence of any straight answers is fueling speculation that Apple executives -- starting, apparently, with Steven P. Jobs, the company's co-founder -- seem to think the clones do Apple more harm than good. Clone sales now account for one of every five Macintosh computers sold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With all the momentous announcements at last week's MacWorld Expo trade show, Apple Computer executives were nearly silent on an issue of strategic importance to the future of the troubled company: Whether Apple would continue to license the Macintosh operating system to makers of lower-priced Mac clones.</p>
        <p>The absence of any straight answers is fueling speculation that Apple executives -- starting, apparently, with Steven P. Jobs, the company's co-founder -- seem to think the clones do Apple more harm than good. Clone sales now account for one of every five Macintosh computers sold.</p>
        <p>At the show, Mr. Jobs said nothing about Apple's licensing plans. But at a news conference later in the week, Apple's chief financial officer, Fred Anderson, told reporters that Apple would not prolong its licensing agreements unless clone makers demonstrated a commitment to expanding the Macintosh market.</p>
        <p>In other words, analysts say, the clone makers would need to concentrate on Apple's weakest markets, like low-end consumer machines and certain geographic areas, and leave the higher-margin markets to Apple.</p>
        <p>''This could mean significant trouble,'' said James Staten, an analyst at Dataquest Inc., a market research company in San Jose, Calif. ''We're not getting the signal that Apple is willing to bargain.''</p>
        <p>It is not a message clone makers are eager to hear. To the contrary, they have been angling to increase the breadth of their offerings, not narrow them. Umax, for example, would like to sell clone notebook computers, and all the companies are eager to start selling machines based on the Common Hardware Reference Platform announced nearly three years ago by I.B.M. and Apple. CHRP is significant because it will allow customers to run both  Macintosh software and software written to run on Microsoft Windows on the same machines.</p>
        <p>And nearly every one of them already sells machines that compete with Apple at the high end of the market, where the profits are greatest. At the show, Power Computing, the leading clone maker with nearly a 10 percent share of all Macintosh computers sold, announced one of the highest-performing clone machines yet.</p>
        <p>Apple's unwillingness to endorse extension of the licensing agreements right now can be easily understood in light of sales statistics. The market for Macintosh computers was roughly $900 million in revenues in the first quarter of 1995 -- the last period in which Apple had 100 percent of the Macintosh market.</p>
        <p>Today, that market is worth $796.6 million (as of the second quarter of 1997), with Apple accounting for about 80 percent.</p>
        <p>The licensing debate is occurring in two arenas. At issue in the short term is whether the clone makers' current contracts with Apple include the latest version of the Macintosh operating system, called OS 8, which became available late last month. Industry analysts say Apple is stalling as it scurries to reassemble its own management, and some speculate that the company overstated the advances in OS 8, positioning it as a major revision of the Mac operating system in order to argue that it falls outside current contracts.</p>
        <p>The clone makers, a group that includes Motorola, Umax Computer Systems and a start-up, Power Computing, believe their current contracts with Apple include OS 8.</p>
        <p>The second area open to question is whether Apple will allow the clone makers to sell Rhapsody, Apple's radical overhaul of the Macintosh operating system. Rhapsody is based on software Apple acquired when it bought Mr. Jobs's company, Next Software Inc. Also in question is when Apple is going to supply them with the technology they need to build machines based on CHRP.</p>
        <p>Clearly, the clone makers have cause to worry. ''If Apple is entertaining reversing its policy on licensing, it could be disastrous,'' said Mike Rosenfelt, director of marketing at Power Computing, based in Round Rock, Tex. Hedging its bets, Power Computing recently announced it would sell machines running Microsoft Windows and powered by Intel microprocessors.</p>
        <p>''We have no confirmation from Apple there is any change,'' said Phil Pompa, vice president of marketing for Umax, whose American offices are in San Jose,  Calif. ''But if the rumors turned out to be true, we'd be worried about our ongoing business.''</p>
        <p>Rather than abandoning its licensing practices altogether, however, Apple could adopt a tiered licensing schedule, where it charges more for machines sold in the high end of the market. Still, depending on the fee, that structure could also have dire effects for some cloners, though it may help Apple reach a balancing point it can live with.</p>
        <p>But negotiations are sensitive for another reason: I.B.M., which licenses the Macintosh operating system from Apple to supply to several other clone makers, is only one of two suppliers of the Power PC chip that serves as the engine for all Macintoshes sold today. The other is Motorola. If the current rift is left to fester much longer, I.B.M. could choose to stop selling chips to Apple, analysts say.</p>
        <p>The possibility that Apple will reverse its clone strategy comes at a defining moment in the market, as clone makers start preparing machines based on the CHRP specification. Motorola showed a prototype CHRP machine that it hoped to start selling in September. The machine features a parallel port for connecting PC peripherals, a first for a Mac, and can be configured to run either OS 8 or Microsoft's Windows NT.</p>
        <p>But Apple may already be seeing an upswing in its sales against clones. In the second quarter, clone sales accounted for  20 percent of all Mac hardware sales, down from 30 percent in the first quarter, according to Dataquest. Mr. Staten, the Dataquest analyst, said the surge was a result of Apple's release of new Macs in the second quarter that were more competitive in both price and performance with clones.</p>
        <p>At the consumer end of the market, for example, Apple's Power Mac 6500 now costs only about $100 more than a Power Base 200, which is priced at $1,300.</p>
        <p>For their part, the clone makers said Apple's apprehensions about the impact of clones were misplaced. ''Apple is more competitive because of licensing,'' Mr. Rosenfelt said. ''People want choice.''</p>
        <p>But in the meantime, there appears to be some movement. Just two weeks ago, executives from Umax said that Apple executives had conceded that the current contract between the two companies did indeed permit Umax to sell Mac OS 8, though they said nothing about Rhapsody or CHRP. But other clone makers said Apple was keeping them in the dark about whether they could do the same.</p>
        <p>And Umax executives said the company was still waiting to receive the new software, which Apple was late in delivering.</p>
        <p>''The last 30 days, there has been a vacuum of information,'' Mr. Rosenfelt said. ''We're simply looking for clarity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
