<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Autry's Halo, a Dream</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="341784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL '90"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA ANGELS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">AUTRY, GENE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYDANS, SETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D81538F93BA35757C0A966958260" item-length="1540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Autry's Halo, a Dream</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYDANS, SETH</byline>
      <dateline>PALM SPRINGS, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Gene Autry, the singing cowboy who owns the California Angels, was never quite good enough to become a baseball player, and by his own description was never much of an actor. What he was and still is, he says, is a personality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Gene Autry, the singing cowboy who owns the California Angels, was never quite good enough to become a baseball player, and by his own description was never much of an actor. What he was and still is, he says, is a personality.</p>
        <p>Gene Autry, the singing cowboy who owns the California Angels, was never quite good enough to become a baseball player, and by his own description was never much of an actor. What he was and still is, he says, is a personality.</p>
        <p>There is no mistaking the 82-year-old tycoon in his cowboy boots and Stetson, his gold rings and his diamond-studded bolo string tie as he mingles with his players in the clubhouse at the Angels' spring training complex.</p>
        <p>And although he doesn't press the point, there is no denying that at the end of a long and hugely successful career in entertainment and business, there is one crucial satisfaction that has eluded him: a pennant for the team he has owned for 29 years.</p>
        <p>Maybe, he says cautiously, this will be the year, although Oakland and Kansas City seem to be the teams to beat in the American League West, and Texas is a contender too.</p>
        <p>''I don't think anyone likes to lose, especially when you get so close,'' he said. ''It hurts. But that's the way the little ball bounces.''</p>
        <p>Autry's neediness is almost painful for his players and management, perhaps all the more so because he seems to take defeat so gracefully.</p>
        <p>''Those of us who work for Mr. Autry, we are dying to win for him,'' said Mike Port, the team's general manager. ''You hear it from the players, the desire to win one for the Cowboy.''</p>
        <p>The manager, Doug Rader, sees the same thing as he watches Autry, leaning on a cane and fingering his hearing aid, wander the locker room.</p>
        <p>''People would like to win it for Mr. Autry,'' Rader said. ''I've never seen that before in any club I've been associated with. In the back of everybody's mind is how important it is for him.''</p>
        <p>The team came painfully close in 1979, 1982 and most spectacularly in 1986, when it was one out away from the pennant in a playoff with Boston.</p>
        <p>''In hindsight, it's probably impossible to come any closer to the World Series than we did that year,'' Port said.</p>
        <p>Though he is enthusiastic and involved, Port said Autry is not an intrusive owner, placing his trust in the players, for whom he sometimes pays stunningly large sums of money.</p>
        <p>''I try to telephone him every day just to keep him involved,'' Port said. ''But Mr. Autry usually calls me first. He is just interested in how things are going. He asks me questions from a fan's point of view.''</p>
        <p>''Frustrated ballplayer,'' is the way several people around the club refer to Autry.</p>
        <p>''I submit that some of his happiest times are the times he spends down in the dugout with the players,'' Port said.</p>
        <p>''He once told me that had not the fates put a guitar into his hands, what he was aspiring to be was a major league baseball player.''</p>
        <p>Autry, born north of Dallas, grew up in Oklahoma, where he said he worked on farms and ranches until he was 17 years old.</p>
        <p>''Oh, I fooled around with baseball, but I never really took it serious,'' he said. ''I knew a lot of ballplayers, but I didn't think I was good enough to match up the ballplayers of that era.''</p>
        <p>It was his job as a telegrapher with the St. Louis to San Francisco railroad that set his life on its course away from baseball.</p>
        <p>''I worked a lot of small towns on the midnight to 8 A.M. shift and I used to play the guitar and practice,'' Autry said.</p>
        <p>''One night, the late Will Rogers came in to send his daily column to the syndicate in New York,'' he said. ''I was playing and singing. Naturally, I put the guitar down but he said, 'No, go ahead. I like it.' ''</p>
        <p>It was only later, when he sat down to send the telegram that Autry realized that his admirer was the actor and comedian, who was staying with relatives in Oklahoma.</p>
        <p>It was Rogers's continuing encouragement that inspired Autry to take his chances as a professional singer, and baseball was set aside for years to come.</p>
        <p>He was a phenomenal success, starting with a science fiction serial that was a predecessor to Flash Gordon, and becoming a contemporary of John Wayne in the booming Western genre.</p>
        <p>Autry became one of Holywood's top draws, making 88 movies, 108 television shows, traveling the theater and rodeo circut and cutting millions of records, including the popular ''Rudolph the Red Nose Reindeer.''</p>
        <p>But he has kept his screen success in perspective.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't say that I was an actor,'' he said. ''I never pretended to be. I think I was a personality. I had a very successful recording string from the year 1927 to a few years ago.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Autry was getting rich. He was making up to $1 million a year before he volunteered for the Air Force during World War II, where he still recalls his precise salary: $115 a month. Chastened by this cut in income, Autry got serious about making money. When the war ended, he began buying radio and television stations, real estate and hotels, and finally during the 1961 expansion, his baseball team.</p>
        <p>He said his current wealth has been estimated at between $115 million and $200 million.</p>
        <p>His success in baseball, as in his entertainment career, was a matter of personality.</p>
        <p>''I knew most of the owners in the American League that had to vote on it, so I was awarded the franchise for the American League,'' he said of his successful bid for an expansion team.</p>
        <p>In the years since then, money seems to have been no object in Autry's drive for a pennant, and he has been accused of pushing up salaries with big outlays for free agents.</p>
        <p>In 1976, the first year of free agency, Autry signed three - Joe Rudi, Bobby Grich and Don Baylor. And although their contracts seemed small compared with today's -Rudi, for example, received $2.09 million for five years - Autry had established a free-spending philosophy that would guide his team's pursuit of a pennant through the next 15 years.</p>
        <p>''He has not hesitated, if you will, to be willing to pay the freight,'' Port said, although not all his purchases have worked out. Perhaps the most spectacular disappointments were the free-agent pitchers, Bill Travers and John D'Aquisto, who each received four-year contracts worth $1.5 million in 1980.</p>
        <p>Travers played two years (1981, 1983), didn't win a game and lost four with an earned run average of 7.00 for the Angels in 14 appearances. D'Aquisto played one year for the Angels, pitched only 6 games, had a 0-0 won-lost record and an e.r.a. of 10.89.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Port said, Autry's support for the team has been unflagging as it continued to fall short of the pennant, long after other owners might have given up.</p>
        <p>Most recently, Autry has shown himself a spectacular spender this year, paying $16 million for a five-year contract for Mark Langston, a pitcher.</p>
        <p>Langston was widely courted by other teams as a free agent. And although pitching was already the Angels' strong suit, Autry pursued him with his most persuasive weapon, his personality.</p>
        <p>Accompanied by his wife, Jackie, a 48-year-old banker who is his constant companion, Autry escorted Langston and his wife, Michelle, around the Gene Autry Western Heritage Museum in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>More than the money, Langston later said, it was Autry's charm that brought him to the Angels.</p>
        <p>''I try to treat all of them the same; I try to be a friend to the ballplayers,'' Autry said. ''I treat them like human beings, like I would want to be treated.''</p>
        <p>As for the money, he said this is the cost of a good team these days.</p>
        <p>''Why, gosh, our salaries this year are going to be in the $20 million range,'' he said of the Angels.</p>
        <p>Autry knows that the players have nicknamed him the Cowboy, but are much too young to have been among his fans in the days when he always got the girl.</p>
        <p>Now, he is pleased that some of the players have seen his movies - all of which he still owns - on recent cable television reruns.</p>
        <p>The time may be ripe for a revival of good, old-fashioned Westerns, he said.</p>
        <p>But when asked to sum up his richly varied life in a word of advice for the young ballplayers with whom he loves to mingle, it was not art or sport or even personality that was foremost on his mind, but finance.</p>
        <p>''My advice to the players?'' he said, and paused.</p>
        <p>''My advice to the players is, well, they're making good money,'' he said. ''I would tell them to go find good investments.</p>
        <p>''Try to find someone they can trust to help them invest their money.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, during the labor negotiations this spring, while the players were seeking a better financial deal, Autry feared for something that may be even more important to him than finance: his relationship with his ballplayers.</p>
        <p>''I think the union's are very necessary,'' he said. ''But I always hope that that will not destroy the friendship between the owners and the players. That's the important thing.''</p>
        <p>AUTRY'S CLOSE CALLS</p>
        <p>1978</p>
        <p>87-75, tied for 2d, 5 games back.</p>
        <p>1979</p>
        <p>88-74, first place, 3 games ahead; Angels lose, 3 games to 1, to Baltimore in playoffs.</p>
        <p>1982</p>
        <p>93-69, first, 3 games ahead; Up 2 games to none against Milwaukie, Angels took a 3-2 lead into 7th inning of fifth game only to lose, 4-3.</p>
        <p>1984</p>
        <p>81-81, tied for second, 3 games back.</p>
        <p>1985</p>
        <p>90-72, 2d place, 1 game back.</p>
        <p>1986</p>
        <p>92-70, first, 5 games ahead; In playoffs, Angels are up 3-1 in games and one out away from pennant, only to lose that game and eventually the series.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL '90</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
