<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Acting Adult</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="341636"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE SPRING REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADULT EDUCATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LEARNING ANNEX</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYERS, STEVEN LEE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adult Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DA1539F93BA35757C0A966958260" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Acting Adult</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Steven Lee Myers</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYERS, STEVEN LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: SOBERED by declining enrollment, The Learning Annex, the largest and one of the oldest for-profit education businesses in the nation, is changing its image. Gone are the breezy self-awareness and interpersonal discovery classes that built its reputation, replaced by practical courses on computers, business and careers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: SOBERED by declining enrollment, The Learning Annex, the largest and one of the oldest for-profit education businesses in the nation, is changing its image. Gone are the breezy self-awareness and interpersonal discovery classes that built its reputation, replaced by practical courses on computers, business and careers.</p>
        <p>SOBERED by declining enrollment, The Learning Annex, the largest and one of the oldest for-profit education businesses in the nation, is changing its image. Gone are the breezy self-awareness and interpersonal discovery classes that built its reputation, replaced by practical courses on computers, business and careers.</p>
        <p>Gone, too, are the young, fashionably beautiful women whose faces have adorned Learning Annex catalogues since it opened 10 years ago. The cover for May is as down-to-earth as its content, featuring simple cartoon drawings.</p>
        <p>''Our market has always been the baby-boomers,'' said William Zanker, the founder and president of The Learning Annex. ''They're getting older now. They're getting families. They're getting more serious.'' The Annex's transformation comes when adult education is at its peak. About 15 million Americans took noncredit, nondegree courses last year, a two-thirds rise from 1980, said William Draves, director of Learning Resources Network, trade group representing 1,100 commercial and nonprofit educators. But as the industry has burgeoned, The Annex was forced to retreat amid high operating costs and declining enrollment, especially among singles. Of its 15 national branches, 9 have closed since the end of 1988.</p>
        <p>'Quick, Fun, Inexpensive'</p>
        <p>''We didn't appreciate the shift in interests quickly enough,'' said Mr. Zanker, an effervescent 35-year-old. ''We want to keep the same premise - education that's quick, fun, inexpensive - but we want to be more serious, too, not frivolous and not singles-oriented.''</p>
        <p>That evolution of interests has reverberated industry-wide. ''It doesn't mean macrame is out,'' Mr. Draves said. ''But we're seeing people take more courses in literature and the humanities, more on the environment, more on social issues.''</p>
        <p>The lesson has been painful for The Learning Annex, which built its reputation on the likes of classes in flirting and hot-air ballooning. Begun in New York City in 1980, it blitzed Manhattan with colorful catalogues, quickly becoming popular among singles searching for continuing social life as much as continuing education.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zanker tried to torque his local success into a national chain of education centers. In 1984 the company went public. A year later the first branch opened in Washington, D.C.; four years later there were offices in 15 cities nationwide.</p>
        <p>''We realized that if we were to survive we would have to rise to its level of intensity,'' said Jamie Jaffe, education director of The Boston Center for Adult Education, begun in 1933. ''Suddenly, marketing became the buzzword in adult education.''</p>
        <p>The Annex's mistake, many educators said, was focusing on packaging while going light on education. ''It's all style and no substance,'' said Ted Weisgal, co-director of Leisure Learning Unlimited in Houston, which competed with The Annex's branch for three years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zanker said The Annex was now ''moving back to a quasi-traditional way of teaching.'' Perhaps as a result, enrollment at the six remaining branches - New York, Toronto, Washington, San Francisco, Los Angeles and San Diego - is growing. Some 13,000 people take courses each month, a 10 percent increase from last year, Mr. Zanker said, adding that The Annex, which has never recorded a profit, has ''been profitable every month this year.''</p>
        <p>While he has not abandoned his vision of a national chain, he said the future of adult education lay in audiotapes, videotapes and workbooks, along with mail-order courses and one-day ''fly-in'' seminars. Mr. Zanker said he envisioned a Berlitz-like line of courses, with packaged programs - and the prestige that Berlitz enjoys. ''We're going back to the cities we left,'' he said, ''only this time in a different way.''  THE SPRING REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
