<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LITTLE HOUSE IN THE BIG CITY: SMILING THROUGH</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="World of New York Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="341909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT REALLY MAKES NEW YORK WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD153DF93BA35757C0A966958260" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LITTLE HOUSE IN THE BIG CITY: SMILING THROUGH</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY GARRISON KEILLOR; Garrison Keillor is the host of ''The American Radio Company,'' heard weekly on public radio from Brooklyn.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: I'm from Minnesota, not brought up to be a complainer, so even when I do see something in New York that doesn't work, I try to make the best of it. The tin loudspeakers in subway stations, for example, that make the train announcements sound like somebody sawing a piece of sheet metal. You stand in the dismal dank of the subway, water dripping, rats scurrying across the tracks, and you listen for the distant screech of the C train, and 15 uneventful minutes pass, and a transit employee turns on the P.A.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: I'm from Minnesota, not brought up to be a complainer, so even when I do see something in New York that doesn't work, I try to make the best of it. The tin loudspeakers in subway stations, for example, that make the train announcements sound like somebody sawing a piece of sheet metal. You stand in the dismal dank of the subway, water dripping, rats scurrying across the tracks, and you listen for the distant screech of the C train, and 15 uneventful minutes pass, and a transit employee turns on the P.A.</p>
        <p>I'm from Minnesota, not brought up to be a complainer, so even when I do see something in New York that doesn't work, I try to make the best of it. The tin loudspeakers in subway stations, for example, that make the train announcements sound like somebody sawing a piece of sheet metal. You stand in the dismal dank of the subway, water dripping, rats scurrying across the tracks, and you listen for the distant screech of the C train, and 15 uneventful minutes pass, and a transit employee turns on the P.A. and says something you can't hear because it hurts too much - it does cast a shadow over one's loyalty to mass transit. It would be nice to know if he is advertising cheaper fares or announcing that the train is canceled for three weeks because a water main has burst in the Village, where water is piped through hollowed-out logs dating back to the Dutch. But a Minnesotan doesn't let these things ruin his day. A Minnesotan carries a good book along on the subway and uses the time to improve himself. The IND has been like a college to me, and some authors that never made sense to me when I lived in Minnesota, like Beckett and Kafka and Pynchon - the C train really helps you see what they're driving at.</p>
        <p>No, a Minnesotan living in New York is a happy man, who isn't discouraged by a little noise and filth and squalor and sheer arrogance. In the event of serious illness, there's a dog tag around my neck with an airline ticket to Minneapolis pinned to it, but otherwise, I like it here, and wherever I travel, when people say, ''How can a good man like yourself live in that godforsaken hellhole?'' I always reply, ''It's not that bad.'' I don't badmouth the place where I live, the way New Yorkers who live in Minneapolis do. New Yorkers make lousy Midwesterners, always moaning about the cold, the flatness of the prairie, the oceanlessness, the oysterlessness, the homogeneousness of everything, our provincialism, our Lutheranism, our lousy pastrami, our passivity - after a while, we almost feel like saying something to them, but of course we don't, it's not in our nature to respond to provocation by jerks. No, Midwesterners are gentle, humorous people, and that's why some of us live in New York: because the city needs us to really appreciate it, which we do, no matter what. We view problems as opportunities in disguise: lousy television reception, for example, may be one reason why New Yorkers are able to tell a story. Traffic congestion makes for good hikers. Street crime makes for more home life.</p>
        <p>The warmth and generosity and honest, open-handed approach to life that characterize a Midwesterner make it hard to live in New York. I realize this. My family and I live simple, Shaker-like lives because you can't get anything in New York without screaming and we aren't that sort of people.</p>
        <p>The fact is that, because the streets are jammed with 40-foot limos, delivery trucks can't move, so anytime salespeople promise you something by next Wednesday, they're lying. The stuff you order today is sitting in a container in Yokohama. Next Wednesday they'll be trying to deliver the stuff they sold last November, so if you call them on Thursday to ask where your order is, they'll tell you Monday, and on Tuesday they'll tell you Friday and Saturday it'll be Wednesday. It will arrive in June. All New Yorkers understand this. You can, however, get delivery by early May if you're willing to scream.</p>
        <p>It isn't enough to scream on the phone. Look in any office in New York and you'll see six telephone receivers lying on desks, sounds of weeping and gnashing and ranting and raving coming out of them, and when the sounds stop, someone picks up the phone and says, ''Wednesday.'' No, you need to actually go in and plant your feet in their office and screech and foam until the spit drips off your chin and tear your clothing and drop to your knees and chew the carpet. They will not be upset by this. They'll just look down and smile and say, ''O.K., tomorrow,'' and tomorrow means early May. The only way to possibly get it today is to steal it, but even then you have to wait in line.</p>
        <p>Apartment renovation requires more than screaming. If you hire a New York architect and contractor to do the job, they will give you an estimate of $75,000 and two months, no matter how big or small the job is. The following Groundhog Day, you call a lawyer to threaten them with a million-dollar lawsuit, and they finish the job a year later for a quarter-million - the apartment is a mess, nothing works, your lawyer goes and screams at them until spit drops from his chin and they give you a rebate of $75,000, the original estimate: This is standard New York procedure for apartment renovation. If you try to take a short cut and sneak in non-New Yorkers to do the job for a reasonable price, minus lawyers, the city will eat them like a bonbon.</p>
        <p>In this system, based on the squeaking-wheel principle, a cheerful, positive-thinking Midwesterner doesn't fare so well. At the moment, having gone a quarter-million in debt to fix the bathroom floor where I was piling the Sunday Timeses I hadn't finished reading - it buckled - I now ride the C train every day to Penn Station, where I catch a train to East Hampton, L.I., where Chip, my contractor, lives. I'm slowly paying off my debt to him as an indentured day laborer, hauling concrete in buckets for the big guest houses he's building in his hilltop compound, two of them up by the Big House and two down by the Grecian Pool and Fountain of Hope with its magnificent cluster of Naiads. What with the four-hour commute each way, I leave my apartment at 4 A.M. and come home about 11 at night and am not certain whether I am still married or not, so you can understand why a delay on the subway could be a problem. Once or twice when the P.A. has screeched something, I've walked down the platform to the token booth and thought about asking the token lady what the announcement was, but the token booth is a steel-and-glass bunker whose intercom makes her voice sound like a rasp on a piece of loose plywood so I can't understand her, either. Anyway, she has her own life to think about, just as I have mine.</p>
        <p>Mine is all right. It could be worse. Maybe it'll get worse soon and I'll regret that I moved here - maybe next Wednesday I'll suddenly pitch face-down on West 44th Street and lie in the gutter and the passerby who stoops to read my dog tag (which says: ''I am an American Lutheran. Take me to Swedish Hospital in south Minneapolis. I can pay.'') won't understand English and I'll be shipped to Bellevue and lie in a vast, drafty ward jammed with the Union casualties from Gettysburg - maybe then I'll just wish I'd stayed home. But for now I'm happy to be here. New York is the greatest city in the world, and that's something only a Midwesterner could say.</p>
        <p>WHAT REALLY MAKES NEW YORK WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
