<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No, Doctors Are Not Just Like Auto Mechanics</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="342063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KITE, CHARLES H (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED71130F93BA35757C0A966958260" item-length="269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No, Doctors Are Not Just Like Auto Mechanics</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a physician who has been accused by New York State's David Axelrod of doing unnecessary back and neck surgery, I found Jerry Jasinowski's comments (''Quality Control for Health Care,'' March 11) particularly telling.</p>
        <p>In a field of service where placebos can be a major aid, where trust and faith have significant impact on a patient's cure, I find the president of the National Association of Manufacturers suggestions particularly inept.</p>
        <p>His attempt to suggest that the diagnosis and appropriate medical and surgical intervention of disc disease is on a par with evaluating and fixing a slipping clutch implies to me that either his own logical clutch slipped, or that he has no insight into the vagaries that go into many medical decisions and judgments.</p>
        <p>That entire communities can vary in their use of certain procedures or methods of handling a particular disease as compared with others across the country should not surprise a thoughtful person. Areas of specialization, of differing schools of medical thought and practice will determine statistical variability in medical practice.</p>
        <p>The assumption that people with diseases are like autos with a worn-out clutch and that science has wiped out the art of medicine is far from the truth. Fortunately for Mr. Jasinowski, his back and the rest of us, this is not the case. One thing any reader of the vast sums of medical research knows well is that statistics can be used to prove almost anything. Frankly, his use of such statistical facts should leave your readers with equal disdain.</p>
        <p>DR. CHARLES H. KITE</p>
        <p>Albany, March 14</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
