<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Army of Adjuncts Seeks to Organize on State College Campuses</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19950507T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="759239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ON CAMPUS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODNOUGH, ABBY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DA1331F933A05757C0A963958260" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Army of Adjuncts Seeks to Organize on State College Campuses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODNOUGH, ABBY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They call themselves "gypsy scholars," scurrying from campus to campus, often in a single day. Deprived of office space, they grade papers in parking lots and hold office hours in noisy snack bars. Although many carry full college teaching loads, they seldom earn more than $12,000 a year.</p>
        <p>And now these instructors -- adjuncts, or part-time faculty members, at New Jersey's state colleges -- say they are fed up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They call themselves "gypsy scholars," scurrying from campus to campus, often in a single day. Deprived of office space, they grade papers in parking lots and hold office hours in noisy snack bars. Although many carry full college teaching loads, they seldom earn more than $12,000 a year.</p>
        <p>And now these instructors -- adjuncts, or part-time faculty members, at New Jersey's state colleges -- say they are fed up.</p>
        <p>This spring, an effort was begun to unionize more than 4,000 adjuncts at eight state colleges. The process could prove difficult: because adjuncts have hectic schedules, organizing such a disparate group is itself a challenge. Some fear that fighting for a union will jeopardize their careers, or that college officials could delay the effort with litigation.</p>
        <p>But many adjuncts say it is crucial to lobby for higher pay, health benefits, job security and improved working conditions. They also say their drive for recognition is long overdue.</p>
        <p>Nationally, the ranks of adjuncts have swelled in recent years as colleges have struggled with tighter budgets. In New Jersey, part-time instructors now make up one-third of the faculty members at public four-year colleges, and more at community colleges.</p>
        <p>"As budgets have been cut, there has been a dramatic increase in the use of adjuncts because they are the cheapest option," said Donald Silverman, president of the Council of New Jersey State College Locals, which is leading the unionization effort. The council, which voted in February to help organize adjuncts, already represents full-time faculty members at the eight campuses.</p>
        <p>So far, reaction from college administrations has been muted. Since the state's collective bargaining law allows for the unionization of public employees, they cannot prevent the effort. But as the need to cut costs becomes more pressing, the prospect of paying adjunct professors higher salaries can only be unsettling.</p>
        <p>"Since there are no laws against what they're doing, we really have no response," said Dr. Larry Carter, vice president for academic affairs at Jersey City State College, one of the eight campuses involved. "I have a lot of sympathy for people with terminal degrees who can't find full-time jobs, but their situation is a reflection of our economy."</p>
        <p>At New Jersey's state colleges, most adjuncts do not receive health benefits, pensions or tenure, Dr. Silverman said. They have no job security from one semester to the next, and can be bumped from teaching schedules at the last minute if courses don't fill up. Adjuncts are paid about $450 per credit hour, Dr. Silverman said, and most classes carry three credit hours. If they teach the maximum two courses at one campus, they could earn $2,700. Some earn three times that amount in a semester, but that involves a staggering load of 18 credits.</p>
        <p>For full-time instructors at state colleges, the beginning salary is $27,755, Dr. Silverman said. Tenured professors can make as much as $74,775.</p>
        <p>"The salary is just laughable," said Cherie Kipple, an adjunct professor who teaches composition at Jersey City State. "A lot of us have master's degrees and doctorates, but we have to run our legs off to survive."</p>
        <p>Since February, the council has been compiling lists of adjuncts at the eight colleges. They include Jersey City State, Kean College in Union, Montclair State University, William Paterson College in Wayne. Ramapo College in Mahwah, Rowan College in Glassboro, Richard Stockton College in Pomona and Trenton State College.</p>
        <p>"I have never encountered a campaign with more positive support," said Mel Driban, a representative of the American Federation of Teachers who is supervising the effort. "It's very unusual to have not only the adjuncts, but the full-time faculty recognizing that it's time to end this abuse."</p>
        <p>Although many adjuncts have credentials equal to or better than those of full-time faculty members, there can be drawbacks. Ralph Edelbach, an associate professor of technology who is supervising the union effort at Trenton State College, says full-time faculty members have more time to spend with students.</p>
        <p>"There are situations where adjuncts can bring unique skills into the classroom," he said. "But there's no doubt that for basic classes, full-timers are the best option."</p>
        <p>Mr. Driban said that if there are no obstacles, the state Public Employee Relations Commission could hold an election for a bargaining agent as early as December. But in the past, administrations at other New Jersey colleges have fought the unionization of adjuncts. At Raritan Valley Community College in Branchburg, litigation delayed a unionization effort for six years. And at Rutgers University in New Brunswick, part-time faculty members spent three years establishing a chapter of the American Association of University Professors. It took them another three years to negotiate a contract.</p>
        <p>The potential challenges do not faze people like Ruben Diaz, an adjunct professor of mathematics who teaches at Jersey City State and two other colleges. He works six days a week, often from 7 A.M. to 10 P.M., then spends another two hours grading papers. Constantly on the road, he rarely sees his wife and two children.</p>
        <p>"My life is never easy, and I am tired of running," he said. "If this will bring some change, I will help work for it."</p>
        <p>But even at Rutgers, where the average part-time salary was raised to $650 per credit hour after unionization, there have been few other improvements, said Karen Thompson, vice president of the part-time faculty union.</p>
        <p>"There has been a certain lessening of abuse, but it's still overwhelmingly true that part-timers are the invisible faculty," she said. "To stick with this life, you must be driven by an incredible love of teaching."  ON CAMPUS  Correction:  May 7, 1995, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last week about attempts to unionize part-time college instructors misstated the pay scale at Rutgers University; $650 per credit is the minimum salary, not the average salary. The article also misidentified the president of the New Jersey Council of State College Locals. He is Donald Silberman, not Silverman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 7, 1995, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last week about attempts to unionize part-time college instructors misstated the pay scale at Rutgers University; $650 per credit is the minimum salary, not the average salary. The article also misidentified the president of the New Jersey Council of State College Locals. He is Donald Silberman, not Silverman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
