<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Historical Society's Cost of Living</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="759118"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER WEST SIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOTBAUM, BETSY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLOOM, JENNIFER KINGSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DF163EF933A05757C0A963958260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Historical Society's Cost of Living</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER KINGSON BLOOM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLOOM, JENNIFER KINGSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has come to this: the New-York Historical Society, so starved for cash that its future is in question, has begun renting out its landmark neo-classical building on Central Park West at 77th Street for weddings, at $5,000 a pop.</p>
        <p>The society has also started selling posters at West Side street fairs, pulling in a few hundred dollars a year. And in a move that sparked some criticism, it sold its collection of European Masters, its paperweights and duplicates of some American paintings at auction, garnering $16 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has come to this: the New-York Historical Society, so starved for cash that its future is in question, has begun renting out its landmark neo-classical building on Central Park West at 77th Street for weddings, at $5,000 a pop.</p>
        <p>The society has also started selling posters at West Side street fairs, pulling in a few hundred dollars a year. And in a move that sparked some criticism, it sold its collection of European Masters, its paperweights and duplicates of some American paintings at auction, garnering $16 million.</p>
        <p>But none of that is enough, and with no more government bailouts foreseen, the society says it is left with only one real cure, an option that is likely to enrage the surrounding community: to construct a large building on vacant land and the site of a brownstone it owns on West 76th Street.</p>
        <p>The cause of all the hustling is the financial problems that have dogged the society for decades as its endowment was gradually spent. The problems surfaced two years ago, when the society shut its doors and fell under the receivership of the state Attorney General. The city and state assembled a $10 million package to renovate the 91-year-old organization's headquarters, but the bailout did not include funds for operating expenses.</p>
        <p>"People will say, 'Nothing but brownstones, that's all we will accept,' " predicted Betsy Gotbaum, who took over as executive director of the society in August. "But we have a commitment to the Attorney General to maximize the financial return from this. We are operating under a mandate."</p>
        <p>Last week, as the society prepared to re-open on May 11, officials mailed booklets to more than 25 developers describing its real estate and asking for proposals. But any building large enough to generate profits is unlikely to pass muster with neighbors.</p>
        <p>"I don't want to be in a community where we're hated," Ms. Gotbaum said.</p>
        <p>In 1986, the society proposed building a giant residential tower atop its existing building; Community Board 7 killed the plan in a flash. A model of the design, by Hugh Hardy, the architect, gathers dust on a remote shelf in the society's archives.</p>
        <p>With its lesson learned, the society now hopes to build no higher than the 15-story apartment building on West 77th Street it would abut. Ideally, its new building would have three basement levels to accommodate the society's extensive library.</p>
        <p>But Peter Wright, a member of the society's citizen advisory committee, said it should focus instead on making its collection -- which he called "boring" -- more interesting to children who visit the Museum of Natural History across the street. That way, the society would attract more paid visitors and perhaps wealthy patrons.</p>
        <p>"Zillions of kids don't want to see silver terrines and Audubon prints," Mr. Wright said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gotbaum agreed and said a future exhibit is planned about "icons -- from George Washington through Elvis and Marilyn Monroe." But the exhibit will not open unless it has a corporate sponsor, she said.</p>
        <p>This week, curators are hastily assembling an exhibit scheduled to open in two weeks, "Treasury of the Past," which is sponsored by Chemical Bank. Even Ms. Gotbaum was cleaning plastic display cubes on a recent weekend.</p>
        <p>But because of a smoky fire March 3, sparked by a welder's torch, the society's most popular exhibit -- a trademark collection of Tiffany lamps -- will not be on display. Each lamp must be taken apart and cleaned of soot, an inestimably long process.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gotbaum said she hoped to save money by removing artifacts from a rented storage space ($500,000 a year) and by teaming up with another nonprofit institution, like a school. And she hopes the re-opening will spark new interest -- and donations.</p>
        <p>"I don't know in the very short term what we're going to do about the shortfall," Ms. Gotbaum said. "But the long-term goals are very hopeful and real. This place could be fabulous." JENNIFER KINGSON BLOOM  NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER WEST SIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
