<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Proposed Definition of Poverty May Raise Number of U.S. Poor</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="759298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D81F30F933A05757C0A963958260" item-length="1545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Proposed Definition of Poverty May Raise Number of U.S. Poor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Experts at the National Academy of Sciences will soon recommend to Congress huge changes in the way poverty is defined and measured, and the changes could substantially increase the number of working Americans classified as poor.</p>
        <p>The official definition of poverty used by the Federal Government for three decades is based simply on cash income before taxes. But in a report to be issued on Wednesday, a panel of experts convened by the Academy three years ago at the behest of Congress says the Government should move toward a concept of poverty based on disposable income, the amount left after a family pays taxes and essential expenses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Experts at the National Academy of Sciences will soon recommend to Congress huge changes in the way poverty is defined and measured, and the changes could substantially increase the number of working Americans classified as poor.</p>
        <p>The official definition of poverty used by the Federal Government for three decades is based simply on cash income before taxes. But in a report to be issued on Wednesday, a panel of experts convened by the Academy three years ago at the behest of Congress says the Government should move toward a concept of poverty based on disposable income, the amount left after a family pays taxes and essential expenses.</p>
        <p>Under the proposal, the Government would count not only a family's cash income, but also noncash Government benefits like food stamps, subsidized housing, school lunches and home energy assistance. Those items would increase family income.</p>
        <p>But other recommendations would reduce family income. Specifically, the panel said that taxes, work expenses, child care costs and medical expenses paid by consumers from their own pockets should be deducted from cash income.</p>
        <p>If its recommendations are adopted, the panel said, there will be "higher poverty rates for families with one or more workers and for families that lack health insurance coverage, and lower rates for families that receive public assistance."</p>
        <p>The 12-member committee, the Panel on Poverty and Family Assistance, was convened in 1992, when Congress was controlled by Democrats. But the forthcoming report seems unlikely to be embraced by the Republicans who now control Congress and who could block changes to which they object.</p>
        <p>The recommendations have immense political implications. Voters and politicians use poverty statistics to assess the performance of Presidents and the health of the economy. Eligibility for more than 25 Government programs, including food stamps, Head Start and Medicaid, is linked in some way to the official poverty levels. Poverty is also a factor in the formulas for distributing billions of Federal dollars to state and local governments for education and other purposes.</p>
        <p>In its report, the panel tried to estimate the effects of its proposals on the poverty rate for 1992. In the Census Bureau's original report for that year, 14.5 percent of Americans were officially classified as poor, but under the panel's recommendations, this figure would have been at least 15 percent or 16 percent, and under some of the panel's options for measuring poverty, it could have exceeded 18 percent. Each percentage point represents more than 2.5 million people.</p>
        <p>The panel also recommends that the official poverty threshold, now $15,141 for a family of four, be adjusted for geographical differences in housing costs. The threshold is now the same for all families of a particular size, even though it is well known that housing costs are greater in New York City, for example, than in rural Mississippi.</p>
        <p>In its report, the panel will say, "Our major conclusion is that the current measure needs to be revised: it no longer provides an accurate picture of the differences in the extent of economic poverty among population groups or geographic areas of the country."</p>
        <p>The panel was headed by Prof. Robert T. Michael, a former dean of the Graduate School of Public Policy Studies at the University of Chicago. Members of the panel, including economists, sociologists and other social scientists, said they tried to be nonpartisan and apolitical.</p>
        <p>It was conservatives who first demanded a full-scale re-examination of the way that poverty is measured. Since the early 1980's, they have asserted that the current definition of poverty overstates the problem because it ignores the value of noncash benefits like food stamps and Medicaid.</p>
        <p>But the report contains a stinging dissent from the one conservative Republican on the panel, John F. Cogan, who was deputy director of the Office of Management and Budget under President Ronald Reagan. The panel's major recommendations, he said, "are not based on scientific evidence," but reflect "value judgments made by scientists with a particular point of view."</p>
        <p>The panel does not recommend a specific dollar amount for the new poverty level, saying, "Ultimately, that decision is a matter of judgment." But it does suggest "a reasonable range" for the poverty threshold: $13,700 to $15,900 for a family of four in 1992 dollars. The official poverty level in that year was $14,228, and it would probably rise faster in future years under the panel's recommendations than under current policy.</p>
        <p>The original poverty level, developed by Mollie Orshansky of the Social Security Administration in the early 1960's, was set at three times the cost of a minimal diet, because the Agriculture Department had found that the average family spent about one-third of its income on food.</p>
        <p>But in its report, the Academy said that the poverty level should be set in a different way, to reflect the cost of food, clothing and shelter including utilities, plus a small additional amount to allow for other needs like household supplies and personal care.</p>
        <p>Even under the traditional definition of poverty, the number of poor people has been rising. In its latest report, the Census Bureau said that the number of Americans in poverty rose in 1993 for the fourth straight year, to 39.3 million.</p>
        <p>The current measure of poverty was developed in the early 1960's and has remained essentially unchanged since then. "From the beginning," the panel said, "the poverty measure had weaknesses, and they have become more apparent and consequential because of far-reaching changes in the U.S. society and economy and in Government policies."</p>
        <p>The official poverty levels are adjusted each year for increases in consumer prices, so they "represent the same purchasing power now as they did 30 years ago," the panel said. But, it declared, the poverty thresholds have not kept pace with improvements in the American standard of living. Indeed, it said, simply updating the thresholds for inflation "ignores changes in living standards over time."</p>
        <p>The panel said that the official poverty thresholds should be "updated annually to reflect changes in expenditures on food, clothing and shelter over the previous three years." If President Clinton adopted this recommendation, the official poverty levels would probably rise faster than the current thresholds because consumer spending on these basic goods and services is expected to rise more than prices over the long term.</p>
        <p>The panel said that its proposed yardstick would more accurately measure poverty and "would improve the targeting of benefits to needy families." But it could also increase the number of people who qualify for assistance and the cost of social welfare programs. So, given fiscal constraints, the Government may need to readjust the standards for determining need and eligibility, the panel said.</p>
        <p>In his dissent, Mr. Cogan, an economist at the Hoover Institution of Stanford University, said the panel's recommendations would "fundamentally change the concept of poverty from an absolute standard to a relative standard." As a result, he said, "the poverty line would rise about 8 percent faster per year than under the current method."</p>
        <p>The panel finds many defects in the current measure of poverty:</p>
        <p>*"Because of the increased labor force participation of mothers, there are more working families who must pay for child care, but the current measure does not distinguish between the needs of families in which the parents do or do not work outside the home."</p>
        <p>*"Because of differences in health status and insurance coverage, different population groups face significant variations in medical care costs, but the current measure does not take account of them."</p>
        <p>*The current measure of poverty takes no account of tax laws and social welfare programs that profoundly alter the economic well-being of millions of Americans. For example, Social Security payroll taxes have substantially increased over the last 30 years, reducing workers' disposable income, while the food stamp program has expanded, raising disposable income for beneficiaries.</p>
        <p>As might be expected, the panel had great difficulty deciding how to treat medical care benefits. Ultimately, it decided that the value of Medicare, Medicaid and health benefits provided by employers should not be counted as income. And the proposed poverty thresholds, based on the need for food, clothing and shelter, do not include an allowance for medical care.</p>
        <p>But the panel said that in determining family income, the Government should deduct any amounts that family members actually pay for medical care or health insurance premiums. "Even with insurance," it said, "many people must pay out of pocket to obtain that insurance or to receive care, and such expenses reduce disposable income."</p>
        <p>Likewise, the panel said that income should be redefined to exclude child care costs. "The child care deduction should be capped and apply only to families in which there is no adult at home to provide the care," it said.</p>
        <p>The panel also said, "The definition of 'family' should be broadened for purposes of poverty measurement to include cohabiting couples" who are not married.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
