<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cut Short, a Life Still Resonates</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="656817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="BROWNSVILLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1DE0930E72CA1494CC3BF6F9D" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cut Short, a Life Still Resonates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNETTE HOLLOWAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a city numb with tales of violence, the murder of Jose Duran last August somehow caught the eye: a hard-working immigrant father of 12, returning at midnight from his dishwashing job at an elegant French restaurant in Manhattan, is shot for his wallet. From a window in the Brownsville Houses, two of his sons, in their nightly watch for their father's return, see him clutch his chest and fall to the ground. The family is left without its breadwinner.</p>
        <p>In the months since her husband died, Maria Enedina Duran's days have been filled with miracles as people from around the world reacted to the crime in an outpouring of generosity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a city numb with tales of violence, the murder of Jose Duran last August somehow caught the eye: a hard-working immigrant father of 12, returning at midnight from his dishwashing job at an elegant French restaurant in Manhattan, is shot for his wallet. From a window in the Brownsville Houses, two of his sons, in their nightly watch for their father's return, see him clutch his chest and fall to the ground. The family is left without its breadwinner.</p>
        <p>In the months since her husband died, Maria Enedina Duran's days have been filled with miracles as people from around the world reacted to the crime in an outpouring of generosity.</p>
        <p>"In all my days I've never heard of anything so tragic," a woman wrote to the family in a letter enclosed with $500. "If there's ever anything I can do, please do not hesitate to let me know."</p>
        <p>The family's savings account has grown from a mere $200 to more than $50,000 in donations, and Mrs. Duran plans to buy a small apartment building to house the family and other relatives. Since the incident, she has wanted to be surrounded only by family.</p>
        <p>The children have received everything from pants, shirts, sweaters and gym shoes to free tuition at a nearby private school and free counseling. Assemblyman Vito J. Lopez hired Mrs. Duran's eldest daughter, Josephine, 22, to work as a part-time clerk in his office. Le Perigord, where Mr. Duran had worked, held a fund-raiser for the family, and in September the restaurant gave Esteban, Mr. Duran's 20-year-old son, his father's old job.</p>
        <p>"He was so special," said Mrs. Duran, weeping as her daughter translated. "And what's happened to us since has been special. I never thought that people could be so good."</p>
        <p>Mr. Duran moved his family to New York City in 1984 in search of a better life. Equipped with a high school education and manual labor skills, Mr. Duran found the dishwashing job, working six days a week to support his family. The man with big, soft brown eyes and a silly streak around his children had dreams of buying a house for them and his wife, the girl he met after church as a teen-ager in the countryside of San Jose de Las Matas in the Dominican Republic.</p>
        <p>The Durans moved to the Brownsville Houses from the south side of Williamsburg in February, after spending years on a Housing Authority waiting list. Crime was pervasive in Williamsburg, but Brownsville, one of the most violent areas of New York City, made it seem like paradise. Still, the family was happy to move to Brownsville because it meant more space.</p>
        <p>Within days of the murder, a 17-year-old resident of the Brownsville Houses was charged with the shooting. The Duran family moved back to Williamsburg, to Mrs. Duran's mother's three-bedroom apartment at 357 South Third Street. The children sleep doubled up in the clean apartment. One room is crammed with a bunk bed and a single bed. Even when all the children -- who are between 20 months and 22 years old -- are home, a doleful stillness hangs about the place.</p>
        <p>"We don't ever plan to move back to Brownsville," said Josephine. "My mother cries and screams if she's in a car that goes anywhere near it."</p>
        <p>Josephine recalled: "We rarely got to see my father, so when he did spend time with us, it was always quality time. He loved New Year's Day. He would make all kinds of resolutions. It's really sad that he won't be here to make any this year.</p>
        <p>"I am a religious Catholic, and I ask God all the time, 'Why did this happen?' If he needed my father in heaven, why did he send someone to kill him?" LYNETTE HOLLOWAY CRIME REPORT</p>
        <p>73d Precinct Complaints throught July</p>
        <p>1993</p>
        <p>1992</p>
        <p>Assault</p>
        <p>737</p>
        <p>687</p>
        <p>Burglary</p>
        <p>475</p>
        <p>524</p>
        <p>Grand larceny motor vehicle</p>
        <p>356</p>
        <p>525</p>
        <p>Murder</p>
        <p>36</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>Rape</p>
        <p>50</p>
        <p>49</p>
        <p>Robbery</p>
        <p>1,329</p>
        <p>1330</p>
        <p>BROWNSVILLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
