<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Diary: December 12 - 17</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="656779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED61638F93AA25751C1A965958260" item-length="1646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Diary: December 12 - 17</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Hubert B. Herring</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ECONOMY Believe It or Not, a GATT Agreement (With Some Holes)  When seven years of world trade talks ended last week -- on schedule! -- it was really a bow to the inevitable. For even as political flash fires flare worldwide, the business world is rapidly making borders irrelevant -- a reality negotiators recognized in cutting many tariffs and moving toward ending subsidies. The goal was clear: raise everyone's living standards. And the cheers were equally clear. "The world has chosen openness and cooperation," said Peter Sutherland, GATT's director general. There was also a sense that in the deadline dash, negotiators lopped off anything sticky -- like a late spat over European limits on American movies -- to deal with another day. President Clinton met his "fast track" goal, however -- Congress must vote "yes" or "no," not amend the pact to death. A comment by France's Foreign Minister, Alain Juppe, best captures the mood: "I never want to hear the word GATT again."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ECONOMY Believe It or Not, a GATT Agreement (With Some Holes)  When seven years of world trade talks ended last week -- on schedule! -- it was really a bow to the inevitable. For even as political flash fires flare worldwide, the business world is rapidly making borders irrelevant -- a reality negotiators recognized in cutting many tariffs and moving toward ending subsidies. The goal was clear: raise everyone's living standards. And the cheers were equally clear. "The world has chosen openness and cooperation," said Peter Sutherland, GATT's director general. There was also a sense that in the deadline dash, negotiators lopped off anything sticky -- like a late spat over European limits on American movies -- to deal with another day. President Clinton met his "fast track" goal, however -- Congress must vote "yes" or "no," not amend the pact to death. A comment by France's Foreign Minister, Alain Juppe, best captures the mood: "I never want to hear the word GATT again."</p>
        <p>Wisconsin Takes On Welfare  Wisconsin agrees on one thing: welfare needs an overhaul. What it can't agree on is a solution. Sounds familiar. Wisconsin, though, wants to probe this frontier. Last week, Gov. Tommy G. Thompson signed a law pledging, by 1999, to replace Federal welfare with a state plan. But all is not unity. Mr. Thompson, a Republican, has a time-worn formula: give business hiring incentives. Democrats have their own time-worn formula: create public-service jobs. Not an original idea in sight. But given the sorry state of the current system -- "a jailer of people," one Democrat called it -- Mr. Thompson has a point when he says, "The best thing to do is to start over fresh." A November Spending Spree  People must really think the economy's out of the woods, because even last month, when shopping could easily be put off, they spent up a storm. The Commerce Department said last week that November retail sales rose 0.4 percent, a solid eighth straight rise. Americans spent nearly $180 billion, or about $700 for every woman, man and child. (Did they need that stuff? Don't ask.) And they're looking to the future, too: sales of durable goods provided the power, rising 0.9 percent. ("Durable" goods, by the way, are those meant to last three years.) A Lucite Hyena! How Lovely!  You unwrap the package with trepidation, struggling to keep that joyful smile on your face, and there it is, the gift from hell -- the after-shave (you have a beard), the turtleneck (you loathe turtlenecks), the book you'll never read (but will take up shelf space till the statute of obligations runs out), the demitasse cups (does anyone use these?). What a waste, you sigh, and move glumly to the next gift. But this is an age when even sighs must be counted, so it's no surprise that one economist has put a dollar figure on that waste. In The American Economic Review, Joel Waldfogel, of Yale, estimates that of $40 billion spent annually on gifts, $4 billion, possibly even $10 billion or so, is a "deadweight loss" -- the difference between what the giver spends and the value the recipient puts on the gift. Like all Scrooges, though, he'll get his. Now, as he readily admits, "I'm afraid I may not get as many gifts."  Annenberg 'Bomb' for Schools  "I felt I had to drop a bomb on the situation," Walter Annenberg said. An apt image, for what spurred him to action last week was the growing violence in schools -- "so many youngsters," he lamented, "with knives and revolvers." And Mr. Annenberg, who at 85 has made billions in publishing ventures like TV Guide, can afford one heck of a "bomb." He's giving $500 million to groups involved in school reform, the largest single gift ever to public education. Going Without Health Insurance  Lest anyone dream that the health care crisis will ease on its own, Government data showed last week that it's only getting worse. In 1992, the report said, the number of people without health insurance hit 38.9 million, up 2.3 million from 1991 -- a rise greater than in the two previous years combined. Not surprisingly, half the people making less than $10,000 lack coverage. But the problem is not just at small companies and among the unemployed -- the major trouble spots. Fully 19 percent of the uninsured are in the families of those who work for companies with more than 1,000 workers. No one is safe from this epidemic. COMPANIES A Bit Less Bloody at Toys 'R' Us  Hooded vampires stalk scantily clad sorority girls. If they catch them, they drill into their necks and drain their blood. Only the wide-eyed child at the controls can stop them. Wholesome stuff, right? Some people think so. Tom Zito, head of Digital Pictures, which makes the Sega game called Night Trap, says it's "actually very benign and is designed as a parody of a vampire movie." Yes, one can just hear some scholarly 10-year-old: "Awesome parody, dude!" But if kids aren't scared, retailers are (because, perhaps, the Senate is even now pondering curbs on video game violence?). Last week Toys 'R' Us stopped selling Night Trap, and F.A.O. Schwarz followed suit. "I'm thrilled," said Senator Joseph Lieberman of Connecticut, a crusader against violent games. "This will help parents raise their children and not leave it to the video-game industry." Con Ed Indicted for Blast  After a 1989 steam-pipe explosion in Manhattan, the Government says, Con Edison did not let on for four days that the blast had spewed out 200 pounds of asbestos. Last week Con Ed and two of its retired officials were indicted on charges of concealing that knowledge. Mixed Signals on Shawmut  Washington didn't quite get its signals straight on Shawmut National. Just last month the Federal Reserve, citing lending bias, blocked a planned acquisition by Shawmut, New England's No. 3 banking company. But last week, when the Justice Department settled its bias case against the bank, Attorney General Janet Reno went out of her way to praise the corrective steps Shawmut took months ago. Shawmut, though denying any bias, agreed to pay $10,000 to $15,000 to any black or Hispanic customer who could show possible discrimination. But the Justice Department said the violations were from 1990 to 1992. Was the Fed a latecomer? Lucky Stores Comes a Long Way  Diane Skillsky has been at Lucky Stores in California for 21 years, at one point working at a cash register next to her teen-age son. Her son was offered a shot at a better job; she wasn't. She, and a lot of others, refused to take it anymore. In a decade-long sex-discrimination battle, Lucky insisted that women weren't promoted because they didn't want better jobs. (Just as the homeless like it on the street.) But last week Lucky agreed to pay $75 million in damages to 14,000 women and to invest $20 million in affirmative action, one of the largest sex-bias settlements ever. Said Ms. Skillsky: "This is a great day." And you can bet the rest of the grocery industry was watching very, very closely. At Kodak, No Quick Fixes Wall Street often thinks that one mere mortal can instantly reverse a corporate giant's fortunes. Sometimes it gets a rude reminder of its naivete. In October, when Eastman Kodak named George M. C. Fisher as chairman, replacing Kay R. Whitmore, who'd been criticized for being too timid a cost-cutter, Kodak stock shot up. But last week, Mr. Fisher said, in effect, "Wait a second, folks, it's not that easy." Forget record earnings next year, he said, "it looks more challenging." And, going right to that sacred issue, he added, "Cost-cutting alone is not the long-term answer." That did it. End of honeymoon. The shares plunged to Whitmore levels and below, losing $7.25 in a day, ending the week at $55.25.  United's Unions Try Again  United Airlines' unions made yet another stab at buying control of the airline last week, in a complex deal that includes concessions on wages and work rules. But investors were wary: even though the deal is valued at $173 a share, the stock fell to $143.375 by week's end. INTERNATIONAL At Ford, Trade Pact Means Jobs  Backers of the North American Free Trade Agreement must have applauded. They'd said all along that the accord would mean more American jobs, not fewer, and last week some corroborating evidence bubbled out of the economy's laboratory: Ford said it would build its new compact cars in both Mexico and the United States and greatly increase exports to Mexico. The rejiggering of its operations, it said, will create 550 jobs in the United States and Canada and 300 in Mexico. One swallow does not make the case, though; this week some company may well slash payrolls, pinning the blame on the trade accord. German Engineering Meets U.S. Accounting  Daimler-Benz badly wants to expand its horizons beyond a recession-battered Germany, but it's discovering that each step has a price. Planning to list its shares on the New York Stock Exchange soon, it agreed to report its earnings the American way, stricter than the German method that allows moving funds in and out of reserves. But at the moment of truth, that fine point led to two starkly different numbers. Daimler said last week that in the first nine months of 1993 it lost $105 million -- but that ballooned to $1.19 billion under American accounting. True, Mercedes sales have improved, and it has plans for a new Alabama plant. But with that new number, one wonders if American investors will see the shares as quite so desirable.  Japan's Trade Surplus Slips  It took a while, but it's happening. The pricey yen is finally putting a dent in Japan's trade surplus, which has made Japan highly unpopular the world over. Last week, Tokyo reported that the surplus fell 2.2 percent in November from the year-earlier figure, the first such decline in nearly three years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
