<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Theater; 'Family Secrets': Catskills to California</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="639335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRANTLEY, BEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLASER, SHERRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOWELLS, GREG</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FAMILY SECRETS (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DC163DF934A35753C1A965958260" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Theater; 'Family Secrets': Catskills to California</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRANTLEY, BEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a lively but decrepit Jewish grandmother named Rose, one of five fully fleshed characterizations in the one-woman show "Family Secrets," Sherry Glaser tells the story of the octogenarian's botched suicide attempt, which involved a gas range and half a bottle of aspirin. Her son, Rose recalls, wondered why she didn't just jump out the window, since she lived on the 33d floor. Rose's complacent answer: it was cold outside.</p>
        <p>Now in itself, the story may have the weary resonance of something that has made many rounds on the borscht circuit. But Ms. Glaser doesn't play it as an isolated joke. She charges the anecdote with an energetic empathy that brings into focus both the old woman's truly felt despair and the sharp-edged, absurdist logic that is her best defense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a lively but decrepit Jewish grandmother named Rose, one of five fully fleshed characterizations in the one-woman show "Family Secrets," Sherry Glaser tells the story of the octogenarian's botched suicide attempt, which involved a gas range and half a bottle of aspirin. Her son, Rose recalls, wondered why she didn't just jump out the window, since she lived on the 33d floor. Rose's complacent answer: it was cold outside.</p>
        <p>Now in itself, the story may have the weary resonance of something that has made many rounds on the borscht circuit. But Ms. Glaser doesn't play it as an isolated joke. She charges the anecdote with an energetic empathy that brings into focus both the old woman's truly felt despair and the sharp-edged, absurdist logic that is her best defense.</p>
        <p>Much of the material in "Family Secrets," co-written and directed by Greg Howells, is old as the Catskills. But in this multi-generational family portrait, Ms. Glaser never lets her punch lines hover and wait for laughs.</p>
        <p>She breathes fluid life into a longstanding tradition of Jewish humor by presenting it as an evolved mechanism for dealing with the irrationality of both the world outside and the demons within. In the process, she flirts dangerously with caricature and bathos. But with sophisticated timing and earthy physical detail, Ms. Glaser infuses the evening with an invigorating visceral vitality.</p>
        <p>By rights, we shouldn't expect to be surprised by the five thoroughly familiar stereotypes she portrays, all New Yorkers transplanted to California. In addition to Rose, there is her son, a drily philosophical accountant; his compulsively neat, manic-depressive wife; and their daughters, a loopy New Age mystic and an angst-torn adolescent.</p>
        <p>In each persona, Ms. Glaser convinces us not only of the idiosyncratic, self-contained logic with which her characters frame the world, but of how the bodies they inhabit define them. (Her use of utterly distinct, clear-cut hand gestures is particularly revealing.) Indeed, in her own more mainstream-tailored way, she can be as graphically and aggressively body-conscious as the performance artist Karen Finley.</p>
        <p>Portraying Fern, a ditsy, 20-something spiritualist who takes a religious view of such bodily functions as menstruation, Ms. Glaser explicitly goes through the protracted labor of natural childbirth. The segment's searingly established perspective is that of a woman for whom the central reality is pain. (The only way, Fern says as her labor advances, for her lover to realize what she's going through would be if she bit him on the testicle, "and I'm talking about every three minutes.")</p>
        <p>Ms. Glaser is equally persuasive at enacting the cramped, tortured movements of the geriatric Rose. And as Mort, Rose's son and Fern's father, she exudes a bone-tired, patriarchal weightiness (counterpointed by his habit of intensely engaged nose-picking).</p>
        <p>But Ms. Glaser's most daring and fully realized incarnation is Bev, Mort's wife, who, frustrated by her inability to be the perfect mother, has a nervous breakdown after preparing a very imperfect lasagna. As Bev painstakingly re-creates the phases of her therapy, the nasal laughter that punctuates the monologue becomes the ultimate window on the character. It is variously shaded with delight, apologetic rue, genuine craziness and triumph.</p>
        <p>Only Sandra, a bulemic 16-year-old reminiscent of Laraine Newman's petulant Valley Girl sketches on "Saturday Night Live," slips into staleness. But even here, Ms. Glaser, angrily grabbing her buttocks and breasts to display their inadequacies, achingly conveys the physical frustration of a girl trapped in an ungainly body.</p>
        <p>For obvious reasons, none of the characters in "Family Secrets" ever share the stage. But we are always aware of an implicit, exasperated dialogue among them. If the theatrical shorthand that Ms. Glaser uses to suggest this can seem a little perfunctory, she succeeds in establishing both the vast differences among the family members and the prickly, combative humor that unites them, especially in argument.</p>
        <p>Producers concerned with escalating costs should take heart. With actors like Ms. Glaser around -- along with the many talented solo performers flooding Off Broadway this season -- a cast of one is really all that's required for a satisfying night at the theater. Family Secrets  By Sherry Glaser and Greg Howells; directed by Mr. Howells; set by Rob Odorisio; lighting by Brian MacDevitt; costumes by Lorraine Anderson; production stage manager, Cathy B. Blaser. Presented by David Stone, Irene Pinn and Amy Nederlander-Case, in association with Harriet Newman Leve and Robert J. Linden. At Westside Theater, Downstairs, 407 West 43d Street, Clinton. WITH: Ms. Glaser</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
