<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where There's Fear, There's News</title>
    <meta content="29FRANKET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word &amp; Image" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="940165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Word &amp; Image"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frankel, Max</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1D61631F93AA15755C0A961958260" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where There's Fear, There's News</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Max Frankel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frankel, Max</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Max Frankel column says the decline in the number of Americans who read, watch or listen to the news is due less to a lack of the kind of events and developments that alarm the public than it is to a failure on the part of journalists to discern the public's fears and explore them in stories that make life meaningful and manageable to the public; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A remarkable phenomenon: more reporters and news outlets than ever before, but they complain they can't find enough news.</p>
        <p>As Jack Rosenthal, the editor of this magazine, has often observed: the number of radio and TV correspondents in Washington has exploded in one generation from 200 to 3,000; the amount of time that, say, ABC gives to news in normal waking hours has expanded from 2 hours to 15; where once there were three networks, now NBC alone is three, not counting its Web sites. The political conventions last year attracted more than 5,000 media people, not counting Ted Koppel, who escaped the boredom. When Hong Kong is returned to China this week, the media mob on hand will exceed 7,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A remarkable phenomenon: more reporters and news outlets than ever before, but they complain they can't find enough news.</p>
        <p>As Jack Rosenthal, the editor of this magazine, has often observed: the number of radio and TV correspondents in Washington has exploded in one generation from 200 to 3,000; the amount of time that, say, ABC gives to news in normal waking hours has expanded from 2 hours to 15; where once there were three networks, now NBC alone is three, not counting its Web sites. The political conventions last year attracted more than 5,000 media people, not counting Ted Koppel, who escaped the boredom. When Hong Kong is returned to China this week, the media mob on hand will exceed 7,000.</p>
        <p>Yet the audience for conventional news, on the air and in print, keeps shrinking. And serious journalists blame the absence of ''good stories,'' by which, of course, they mean bad news.</p>
        <p>''Long wars, short wars and pseudowars,'' is how Richard Harwood of The Washington Post remembers the golden age. ''Genocidal madness abroad and domestic inquisition at home, social revolutions and domestic upheavals, assassinations, near assassinations, the Nixon disgrace, trips to the moon, missile silos on the Great Plains, hostages in Iran, chaos in the Middle East, disillusion, disintegration and ideological death in the Soviet empire.''</p>
        <p>Yes, says Reuven Frank, the former president of NBC News. ''We are no longer threatened with annihilation. ... I may be bored, but I am not disturbed.''</p>
        <p>Because people are insufficiently disturbed, the number of viewers who regularly watch network news has declined by a third in the last five years. With the cold war ended, the networks have cut back sharply on foreign and political coverage and search desperately for tantalizing domestic themes, starting with domestic sex.</p>
        <p>Why do we respond so readily to bad news? Because we are in all matters more swiftly motivated by fear than an appreciation of the good. ''This is the way we are made,'' wrote Hans Jonas, the German philosopher, as quoted by Richard Wolin in The New Republic. ''The perception of the malum is infinitely easier to us than the perception of the bonum: it is more direct, more compelling, less given to differences of opinion or taste. ... An evil forces its perception on us by its mere presence, whereas the beneficial can be present unobtrusively and remain unperceived, unless we reflect on it.''</p>
        <p>Reflection, alas, is not a common reflex of our media. Most are still enthralled by the breathless old formulas that rank the ''latest'' news as the most important, ''exclusive'' gossip as more meaningful than digested experience and whatever noisily ''happened'' as more newsworthy than what is quietly happening. A moment's reflection would reveal that all those camera crews parachuting into Hong Kong tomorrow will not teach us as much as the handful of Chinese-speaking reporters who have been tracking the gradual commercial and political accommodations between Hong Kong and Beijing.</p>
        <p>But China has not yet appeared on America's collision radar. So the fears that most of the media have been exploiting are of disease, crime and terrorism. Crime news, of course, lost some of its luster when the Ramseys replaced O. J. and Company. Tales of terrorism, without Atlanta and T.W.A., are now confined to one monstrous blow in Oklahoma. That leaves health, which the media prefer to hype with false hope: they find it easy to promise remarkable breakthroughs, cures and prolongations of life. No wonder we Medicare-eligible listeners are the most faithful consumers of news; we get much the biggest kick from the rejuvenation of every laboratory rat.</p>
        <p>Without war and devastation, what is left to animate the news? Well, why not reflect on wars and devastations? Is Gen. William Odom right to call our aircraft carriers, antimissile cruisers and even Marine Corps ''obsolete''? Could the Pentagon apply its training skills to urban ghettos and transform military bases into lifesaving boarding schools for poor kids? Merely airing ideas like that would net the media a year's worth of contention. And they could reflect on the wars that we're still fighting and losing, against illegal immigration, traffic jams, drugs.</p>
        <p>The fear of death can also inspire better stories about health. Instead of distant cures, why not dramatize the known causes of cancer? Media that once commanded nightly fear of an unseen enemy in Vietnam can surely produce compelling news about the smoke, smog, alcohol and other hidden hazards of modern life. And yes, effective news has to be compelling news. That's why wars, sports and criminal trials grab our attention; like well-plotted fiction, they provide conflict and a narrative line toward climax.</p>
        <p>''Tales are tools,'' says Jerome Bruner, the Harvard psychologist who has been reflecting on America's main political fear of the moment -- the inadequacy of our kids' education. As summarized by Clifford Geertz, the anthropologist, in The New York Review of Books, Bruner's thesis is that we live ''in a sea of stories'' and that learning how to swim in such a sea, how to construct stories, understand stories, classify stories, check out stories, see through stories and use stories to find out how things work or what they come to, is what the school and the whole ''culture of education'' should be about.</p>
        <p>Journalists, like teachers, are society's narrators. The good ones discern our fears, anxieties and curiosities and tell stories that make life meaningful and manageable. They can bark to command our momentary attention or they can reflect and shape our lasting image of re-</p>
        <p>ality. There are plenty of good stories to address our fears. We need better, not just more, storytellers.</p>
        <p>Word &amp; Image</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
