<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Food Notes</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="697805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3DA1F3CF935A35754C0A962958260" item-length="1025" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Food Notes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Florence Fabricant</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Food Network Moves</p>
        <p>The Television Food Network, which is broadcast around the clock in many cities, has had to cut back its hours in Manhattan. The original agreement between the Time Warner Cable Group, which owns Paragon and Manhattan Cable, and the food network was for it to share Channel 50 with a New Jersey public broadcasting station, WNJN.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, however, the food network was able to begin broadcasting around the clock on Channel 54 because that channel was not being used. But on July 4, WNBC started broadcasting "America's Talking," its 24-hour talk-television program, on Channel 54, through an earlier agreement with Time Warner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Food Network Moves</p>
        <p>The Television Food Network, which is broadcast around the clock in many cities, has had to cut back its hours in Manhattan. The original agreement between the Time Warner Cable Group, which owns Paragon and Manhattan Cable, and the food network was for it to share Channel 50 with a New Jersey public broadcasting station, WNJN.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, however, the food network was able to begin broadcasting around the clock on Channel 54 because that channel was not being used. But on July 4, WNBC started broadcasting "America's Talking," its 24-hour talk-television program, on Channel 54, through an earlier agreement with Time Warner.</p>
        <p>As a result, the food network has been moved to Channel 50. WNJN broadcasts on the channel from 3 P.M. to midnight in the summer, and the food network will be on the remaining 15 hours. The network's schedule after Labor Day will depend on the New Jersey channel's programming.</p>
        <p>Reese Schonfeld, the president of the food network, said he had hoped that a recent case before the Supreme Court -- about which channels cable networks must carry -- would make it possible for his network to retain its 24-hour programming. But the Supreme Court ruling did not give cable companies greater discretion in which signals they can carry.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Schonfeld said that his network is expanding.  "We are adding 250,000 homes in Connecticut," he said.  Steaks by Mail</p>
        <p>Prime Access, a wholesale butcher in White Plains, has started selling steaks by mail. Unlike most mail-order steaks, they are shipped fresh, wrapped in Cryovac, to be used within five days or frozen.</p>
        <p>These prime dry-aged steaks are buttery, flavorful and well marbled, with the outside fat trimmed so closely that they tend not to flare up on the grill or under the broiler. Through Sept. 15, the company is featuring two 10-ounce boneless strip steaks for $29.95 plus $6.95 shipping. The steaks are regularly four for $79.95 plus shipping. Overnight and weekend delivery is extra.</p>
        <p>The company also sells T-bone, porterhouse and strip steaks with the bone. To order, call (800) 314-2875.  Free Tastings</p>
        <p>Agata &amp; Valentina, an Italian fancy food store at 1505 First Avenue (79th Street), is adding a sidewalk cafe. To introduce it, on Friday and Saturday the store will offer free tastes of many of the items that are prepared on the premises, like muffins, focaccia, juices, tiramisu, mozzarella and pizza. The tastings start with coffee and muffins from 9 to 11 A.M. Other items will be served from noon to 9 P.M.  Vive la Charite</p>
        <p>To celebrate Bastille Day, the Jericho Project, a nonprofit organization that provides housing and rehabilitation for homeless people, is holding a benefit wine tasting on July 14. All the wines will be French. The tasting, at the Sky Club in the Met Life Building at Park Avenue and 45th Street, will be from 6:30 to 9:30 P.M.Tickets are $40 if purchased in advance, $45 at the door and $25 for people 21 to 25; the can be reserved by calling (212) 316-4700.</p>
        <p>Another fund-raising event with a Bastille Day theme is the annual "Let Them Eat Cake" contest for pastry chefs. It will be held on Monday from 5 to 7 P.M. at Tavern on the Green, 67th Street and Central Park West. More than 20 pastry chefs from around the country will create extravaganzas that suggest the French Revolution. Tickets, $50 in advance or at the door, benefit scholarships at the Culinary Institute of America. For information: (212) 688-5458. Ice Cream Inventions</p>
        <p>Ciao Bella, an ice cream company on Mott Street in Little Italy, has just introduced what might be called cookies-and-cream for sophisticates: hazelnut-biscotti gelato. The company, which started making ice cream for restaurants and now sells retail at Dean &amp; DeLuca and many of the Hot and Crusty shops, is staying on the cutting edge with another new flavor: raspberry iced tea sorbet.</p>
        <p>Perugina has just introduced Baci ice cream on a stick. With its royal-blue foil wrapping, this worthy confection made of hazelnut ice cream enrobed in bittersweet chocolate mimics the famous Baci candies. The ice cream bars are $2.50 each at the Perugina store, 520 Madison Avenue (54th Street). Cookware Sale</p>
        <p>Chip Fisher, the new owner of Charles Lamalle, the venerable French cookware supply house at 36 West 25th Street, 6th floor, is having a sale to make room for new merchandise.</p>
        <p>There are good but old-fashioned carbon-steel Sabatier knives, including a 10-inch chef's knife for $12.50. A sturdy two-pronged stainless steel fork is $28. Tin-lined copperware starts at about $30. A lovely little covered saucepan for melting butter is $38. There is a vast supply of plain and decorated white porcelain casseroles, terrines, souffle dishes, gratin dishes and so forth.</p>
        <p>Peugeot peppermills starting at $20, paella pans for $12.50 to $20, charlotte molds for $4.50 and vast quantities of wooden spoons, spatulas and olive scoops, starting at $1, are some other items being offered.</p>
        <p>It's worth rummaging around for oddities. Jean-Michel Diot, the chef at Park Bistro, bought nearly 400 tiny individual pressure cookers for less than $1 each. He plans to use them to make quick vegetable stews that he will serve in the little pots. (He is also experimenting with foie gras.)</p>
        <p>Buyers must pay with cash; no credit cards are accepted. The sale runs Monday through Friday, from 8 A.M. to 4 P.M., through the end of July; (212) 242-0750.  Alfresco Inspiration</p>
        <p>Anyone who has ever considered renting an Italian palazzo for the summer could be inspired to action by "Picnics of Tuscany" by Craig Pyes (Simon &amp; Schuster, $14), a small volume illustrated with Tuscan landscapes by Corot.</p>
        <p>At the very least, it could make a person want to buy a crusty loaf, some cheese and a bottle of Chianti and head to the countryside. Eight imaginative picnics, with simple but detailed instructions for setting the stage and preparing the food, are laid out in the book. The recipes are for flavorful, forthright dishes like frittatas, roast chicken, bruschetta and salads.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
