<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Berra Will Still Watch The Yanks From Afar</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="380096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERRA, LARRY (YOGI)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINBRENNER, GEORGE M 3D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, CLAIRE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DF1238F93BA1575BC0A966958260" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Berra Will Still Watch The Yanks From Afar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAIRE SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, CLAIRE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: George Steinbrenner signed his resignation a week ago yesterday and tendered it the next day, leaving Yankee Stadium in other hands for the first time since 1972.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: George Steinbrenner signed his resignation a week ago yesterday and tendered it the next day, leaving Yankee Stadium in other hands for the first time since 1972.</p>
        <p>George Steinbrenner signed his resignation a week ago yesterday and tendered it the next day, leaving Yankee Stadium in other hands for the first time since 1972.</p>
        <p>Is the Steinbrenner reign really over, though? Yogi Berra, an expert of sorts when it comes to gauging when things in baseball are, indeed, over, is not yet convinced. And that's important because Berra, who voluntarily became the Yankees' prodigal son, vowing not to return to Yankee Stadium until Steinbrenner packed and left for good, is not about to come back yet.</p>
        <p>''To me, I don't think he's out of it yet, so I don't know when I'll come back,'' Berra said last week by telephone from his home in Montclair, N.J.</p>
        <p>It's not that Berra wouldn't like to return. The Hall of Famer and arguably the greatest catcher ever misses the team that employed him as a player from 1946 through 1963, as a manager in 1964 and again in 1984-85, and as coach from 1976 through 1983. So Berra tracks the Yankees and the Mets, a team for which he briefly played as well as managed and coached.</p>
        <p>Admiration for Maas</p>
        <p>''They got a pretty good-looking kid in Maas,'' said Berra, who watches the Yankees as well as the Mets on television. ''A lot of those kids don't look bad. If they keep playing like that, I think they could be pretty good.''</p>
        <p>As for familiar faces, there aren't that many left to identify. ''I think there's only the two I managed, Don Mattingly and Dave Righetti,'' Berra said. ''I'd like to see them. And I know Stump. I like him. He was my coach, you know. But he got fired.''</p>
        <p>Reminded that Stump Merrill, the Yankees' manager, just got a two-year contract extension, Berra said; ''I'm happy for him. But, you know, it don't mean a thing there. We'll see, I guess.''</p>
        <p>To talk to Berra is to listen to a man more stubborn than bitter, however. And to listen to a man with a long memory. He lived through a season in which he, too, supposedly enjoyed a vote of confidence.</p>
        <p>Dismissal After 16 Games</p>
        <p>In 1985, Steinbrenner said Berra was his manager for the year. Berra was dismissed after 16 games. It was then that Berra told his stunned players, including his son, Dale, to play hard for Billy Martin. It was then that Berra, after receiving an emotional ovation from the team as he was dropped off at O'Hare International in Chicago, walked away and never looked back.</p>
        <p>He and Steinbrenner haven't exchanged a word since. ''I waved at him in a winter meeting, once,'' Berra said. ''But speak? Nope.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees are now playing the Yogi Berra video on their giant screen at the Stadium these days as part of their salute to great Yankee players. The last time the Berra video was shown was in April 1985.</p>
        <p>Berra, who went on to serve as a coach for the Houston Astros until his retirement last year, has received an occasional invitation to Yankee old-timers games. He even was asked to attend a ceremony in his honor as the Yankees did something many agreed was long overdue: put up a plaque with Berra's likeness where the rest of the monuments to Yankee greats stand behind the left-field wall.</p>
        <p>Berra did not attend any of those events, nor did he allow his family to to do so. He also declined to attend a ceremony honoring Phil Rizzuto at this year's Old-Timers Day. Berra's reasons were well-known and accepted by Rizzuto, his friend and former teammate.</p>
        <p>Berra said he really doesn't spend much time thinking about Steinbrenner in this summer of the owner's discontent. He has been too busy attending charity golf tournaments, running the family racquetball club, spending time with his seven grandchildren and occasionally serving as adviser and scout for John McMullen, a friend and the owner of the Astros.</p>
        <p>''This summer's been super,'' Berra said. ''We have a lot of barbecues, believe me. And Carmen hasn't thrown me out of the house, yet. So, it's been all right.''</p>
        <p>One baseball event Berra refused to give up was the Hall of Fame ceremonies. He was one of a record 34 Hall of Famers in attendence this year as Joe Morgan and Jim Palmer were inducted. ''To see Ted Williams and Al Lopez again, that was great,'' Berra said.</p>
        <p>Thinking About Rose</p>
        <p>Did the Hall of Famers discuss another great, Pete Rose? ''Nah, not really,'' Berra said.</p>
        <p>Does Rose belong in the Hall? ''I don't know,'' Berra said. ''He's got time yet. I got to think about that one a little bit.''</p>
        <p>As for Steinbrenner, does Berra feel for a man who had to give up his team because he finally conceded that some of his actions were not in the best interest of baseball?</p>
        <p>Berra paused a moment, then said: ''I can't tell about George, yet. You can never tell about George.''  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
