<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agreement to Preserve Environment Provides Help for Madagascar</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="380079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MADAGASCAR</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONSERVATION INTERNATIONAL</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CENTRAL BANK OF MADAGASCAR</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Madagascar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Madagascar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED61438F93BA1575BC0A966958260" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agreement to Preserve Environment Provides Help for Madagascar</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN the first debt-for-nature swap that cancels both trade debt and bank debt, the Central Bank of Madagascar has agreed to allow a private conservation group to pay $5 million of the Government's international debt in exchange for a commitment to try to save Madagascar's unique and endangered plants and animals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN the first debt-for-nature swap that cancels both trade debt and bank debt, the Central Bank of Madagascar has agreed to allow a private conservation group to pay $5 million of the Government's international debt in exchange for a commitment to try to save Madagascar's unique and endangered plants and animals.</p>
        <p>IN the first debt-for-nature swap that cancels both trade debt and bank debt, the Central Bank of Madagascar has agreed to allow a private conservation group to pay $5 million of the Government's international debt in exchange for a commitment to try to save Madagascar's unique and endangered plants and animals.</p>
        <p>The private group, Conservation International, based in Washington, will pay some corporations and banks money owed them by Madagascar. Under the agreement, the Central Bank of Madagascar and Conservation International will have a role in negotiating a discount price at which the conservation group would buy the debt in secondary markets. The Government of Madagascar, which will gain greater credit worthiness as well as having a portion of its debt paid, will then devote $5 million worth of Malagasy francs to conservation.</p>
        <p>Freeing Money for the Environment</p>
        <p>The money will be used for research to make inventories of endangered plants and animals; to make environmental education available to the Malagasy people; to give parks, preserves and other protected areas technical and financial support; to provide information for policy formation and to teach agricultural techniques that are less harmful and more supportive of development than current slash-and-burn methods.</p>
        <p>Conservation International was the first to negotiate a debt payment agreement with a developing country when it reached an accord with Brazil in 1987. Madagascar has reached earlier agreements, including one last year with the World Wildlife Fund.</p>
        <p>Kurt Low, assistant for the conservation finance program of the World Wildlife Fund, said the latest agreement was notable as the first to include trade debt. ''To date there have been no debt-for-nature swaps involving trade credits in principle or in practice,'' he said.</p>
        <p>This innovative agreement attempts to address economic, conservation and developmental needs simultaneously in Madagascar, an island of 228,880 square miles off the east coast of Africa that harbors plants and animals found nowhere else.</p>
        <p>More than 80 percent of its forests have already been destroyed, and the damage is irreparable, experts say. When forests in southern Madagascar are cut down, ''you're cutting down more ecological diversity than anywhere else in the world,'' explained Roderick Mast, director of the Madagascar program for Conservation International.</p>
        <p>Problem of Farming Methods</p>
        <p>Slash-and-burn agriculture, clearing land for cattle and using charcoal for fuel cause many of the island's environmental problems.</p>
        <p>Conservation International signed an agreement with the Central Bank of Madagascar on May 7 to allow the Government of Madagascar to cancel some debts to American exporters and banks.</p>
        <p>Steve Rubin, director of conservation finance at Conservation International, came up with the idea of simultaneously canceling trade credits and bank credits while doing research for a book on the economics of environmental issues, ''Untying Your Money,'' published in 1989 in Britain by Economist Publications.</p>
        <p>''The original holders of Malagasy debt have no interest in further lending to the country, so they sell it,'' Mr. Rubin said. The lenders choose to sell the debt for a part of its value rather than risk the uncertainty of waiting for full repayment.</p>
        <p>The Bankers Trust New York Corporation holds much of the country's debt to banks; a French subsidiary of the International Business Machines Corporation and Honeywell hold trade credits and are negotiating with Conservation International.</p>
        <p>Jocelyn Rafidinarivo, the Counselor for Financial and Public Affairs of the Democratic Republic of Madagascar, said, ''It is not a large amount of money but it will alleviate some of the debt burden, and the money saved and used for conservation will help farmers develop new techniques to grow their produce.'' The country's external debt exceeds $3 billion.</p>
        <p>Madagascar evolved in isolation from the rest of the world for 150 million to 200 million years. Humans are thought to have arrived on the island as recently as 2,000 years ago. As a result, there are an unparalleled number of species that occur nowhere else in the world.</p>
        <p>Ninety-five percent of the primates on Madagascar live there and nowhere else. That is true of 80 percent of the flowering plants, 98 percent of the palm species and 88 percent of the reptiles. If these species become extinct in Madagascar they are extinct forever.</p>
        <p>Madagascar has several species of lemurs, monkey-like primates that help provide a balance in the ecosystem by dispersing the seeds of the plants and fruits they eat, which enables them to grow at various locations on the island rather than being concentrated in one area. ''If they were to go extinct, whole ecosystems would be adversely affected'' Mr. Mast said. Lemurs also give insight into the the ancestry of all primates, including humans.</p>
        <p>Baobab trees are another example of the danger of diminishing ecological diversity in Madagascar. The island is the home of seven species of baobab tree, while only one species exists in Africa. The trees absorb and retain water. They can provide drinking water for communities and their nectar is eaten by lemurs and birds. The threat to the tree does not lie in the extraction of water but in their removal to clear the land for farming.</p>
        <p>''The Malagasy people, more than anyone else, know the value of their environment,'' Mr. Mast said, but few agricultural alternatives to clearing more land and slash-and-burn techniques are available for poor farmers.</p>
        <p>''Very fundamentalist conservationists just think about birds,'' said Mr. Rafidinarivo. ''We've got to think about people, too.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
