<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Horse Farm Holds Off Eviction</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="776935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EVICTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PRINCE FARMS EQUESTRIAN CENTER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PAQUETTE, CAROLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D6163BF930A15754C0A963958260" item-length="1666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Horse Farm Holds Off Eviction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE PAQUETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PAQUETTE, CAROLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STANDING by the railing of the riding ring at the Prince Farms Equestrian Center in St. James, watching her daughter Erin, 11, learn how to control her horse, Kathy McNeill breathed a sigh of relief.</p>
        <p>Mrs. McNeill had just heard that eviction proceedings against the 200-year-old horse farm had been postponed, at least until the season ends. The camp would operate, and Erin, who had just started lessons, would attend for two weeks in August.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STANDING by the railing of the riding ring at the Prince Farms Equestrian Center in St. James, watching her daughter Erin, 11, learn how to control her horse, Kathy McNeill breathed a sigh of relief.</p>
        <p>Mrs. McNeill had just heard that eviction proceedings against the 200-year-old horse farm had been postponed, at least until the season ends. The camp would operate, and Erin, who had just started lessons, would attend for two weeks in August.</p>
        <p>"It would have broken her heart if she couldn't go," Mrs. McNeill, of Commack, said. "She's just learning. This is the closest riding school to us. We've been looking into summer camps for horseback riding, and most schools don't have it."</p>
        <p>Prince Farms is among many of the 53 horse farms in Nassau and Suffolk Counties that are struggling to stay alive. Increased expenses and rising taxes have caused many smaller farms to be sold to developers. Long Island has 30,000 horses, at tracks, on farms and in backyards, said Dr. Ceyla Allison, president of the Nassau-Suffolk Horseman's Association. "It's an expensive operation," she said, "and people are struggling. There is tremendous pressure for people to give up their open space."</p>
        <p>Dr. Allison pointed to the Little Plains Stables in Greenlawn, which closed recently. "It was a wonderful small stable where kids could ride and afford it," she said. "But they could not keep it up and sold to a developer. Prince Farms is larger, older and a classy place. I hope it can be saved."</p>
        <p>Carol Peterson, who has owned Prince Farms for a year and a half, leases the site from the Dime Savings Bank for $2,500 a month. Shelearned about the eviction on May 1, she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peterson and the parents of the 75 students, along with the boarders of 40 horses, have been looking for a buyer to keep the 17.2-acre property on the northern side of Edgewood Avenue in its traditional uses, 11 acres as a horse farm and 6.2 as a swim and tennis club.</p>
        <p>The site, which is on the market at $850,000, was acquired by the bank in October 1993, when the owner, Joseph DeSimone, declared bankruptcy. In the Village of Head of the Harbor, the area includes a two-story house, a stable, a ring, 14 paddocks, tennis courts and a swimming pool. A developer has opted to buy the property and build houses on eight two-acre lots.</p>
        <p>Thirty students and their parents organized a protest in June at the Dime branch in the Smithaven Mall in Lake Grove, and bank officials agreed to postpone the eviction until Sept. 22 unless a buyer for the property could be found by Aug. 15. The buyer would have to keep the farm and club, or the site would revert to the developer, the chief marketing officer for the bank, David Totaro, said after a meeting in June with Ms. Peterson.</p>
        <p>"We were hoping to get a little more time, but we're happy for the time the bank gave us," Ms. Peterson said.</p>
        <p>The riding camp has other supporters, among them a counselor, Elizabeth Beck, 15, of Centereach, who said, "It's the one place where I can take care of my horse full time, and I trust the care they give, too."</p>
        <p>An instructor, Stephanie Balducci, 23, of St. James, said she had been teaching at the farm for seven years. She grew up at Smithtown Farms on Brown's Road in Nesconset, which was sold after the town refused to allow it to build an indoor arena, Miss Balducci said.</p>
        <p>"A developer came in, but then backed out," she said. "Now it's an empty field of garbage, and the barn burned down. I'd hate to see this happen again when so many little kids depend on us."</p>
        <p>Eight vacant two-acre parcels, part of a housing development are behind the farm, Miss Balducci said, adding: "The land on the other side of the fence is empty. Who's to say this wouldn't be left empty, too?"</p>
        <p>Mr. Totaro said two possible buyers came forward at the protest on June 23 and offered to buy the property. "Their names remain confidential until both have an opportunity to present their materials to our credit review," he said. "One is a group of individuals. The other is an individual. Both voiced interest in buying the entire property."</p>
        <p>Originally a club for the rich and famous, visitors to the center included Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis. In a well-known photograph taken in 1936, a serious-looking Jacqueline Bouvier is shown leading her dejected-looking horse, Buddy, after losing in the lead-line class.</p>
        <p>Gloria Levin, who joined the club 35 years ago and who initiated the campaign to save the farm, said that after Mr. DeSimone became an absentee owner the swim and tennis club became run down and then closed. In October 1993, Mr. DeSimone lost the property to foreclosure, and the Dime bought it back through a foreclosure auction.</p>
        <p>The bank set up a subsidiary, the Prince Farms Development Corporation, to manage the site.</p>
        <p>The Dime, with 26 branches on the Island, lost more than $1 million at Prince Farms when Mr. DeSimone defaulted, Mr. Totaro said.</p>
        <p>He said the site cost $6,000 a month to maintain and paid $35,000 a year in taxes. Ms. Peterson said the taxes were recently reduced, to $25,000, after the bank sold six acres on the southern side of Edgewood Avenue to the Suffolk County Water Authority.</p>
        <p>The bank, which had found a developer to buy the property, notified Ms. Peterson on May 1 that she would be evicted on June 1, she said. After seeing surveyors on the property, Ms. Peterson was told by the bank that its operating corporation planned to build a road from Fifty Acre Road through the swim and tennis club to two paddocks at the horse farm.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Levin said she set out to spearhead the drive for Prince Farms. "I went to the Smithtown Town Board and the Head of the Harbor Village meetings," she said. "I contacted the county, trying to get someone to buy the place. Then the kids got upset, and we got a following. People ask me why are you knocking yourself out, you can play somewhere else. But this ambiance is unique to Long Island. My kids grew up here."</p>
        <p>A main stumbling block seemed to be a one-year moratorium by Head of the Harbor on subdivisions larger than six acres. Ms. Peterson and Mrs. Levin asked the village to lift the moratorium, so they could sell the site as two parcels. Although the moratorium was lifted, the bank said, it planned to sell the property as one parcel.</p>
        <p>Mayor Daniel Shybunko said the moratorium was set up to allow the village to study land use, to see whether zoning has to be changed.  "We had just had a new election and the three trustees who were not re-elected had been for the study," Mr. Shybunko said. "The study was suspended. So there was no longer a valid reason for the moratorium.</p>
        <p>"The village does not allow building for speculation. But the bank owns Prince Farms, which is an approved subdivision. So they could cut a road, put in curbs, lay out plots and then try to sell the property as a package."</p>
        <p>Mr. Shybunko said Mrs. Levin had suggested that the village buy the property and use it, but there was no interest. The 1.8-square-mile community of 400 homes is too small for such a major investment, he said.</p>
        <p>Supervisor Patrick Vecchio of Smithtown said, "My position is the town should not be in the position of saving a horse farm." But, he added, he supports financing the swim and tennis club as a town recreation center with $400,000 from the town's park fund.</p>
        <p>"By using park funds," Mr. Vecchio said, "it wouldn't cost the taxpayers anything, and fees could be charged to cover the cost of purchase and staffing. However, there is no interest on the Town Board for acquiring the property."</p>
        <p>On June 29, Mrs. Levin said, she received a letter from County Legislator Michael D'Andre, Republican of Smithtown, saying that he asked the legal department of the Real Estate Division to explore county financing. The letter also asked whether rents generated from a a recreational center could pay for a purchase by the county.</p>
        <p>One potential buyer, Joseph Malenda of Lake Ronkonkoma, a builder and landlord, offered $500,000 for the farm. Mr. Malenda said that his family had boarded their horse at Prince Farms for four years and that they liked the "good clean, familylike atmosphere." If he bought the property, he said, he would install an indoor arena and attract additional students and boarders. But he said that the prospects were not good.</p>
        <p>"My offer of $500,000 to buy the horse farm still stands," Mr. Malenda said. "But I'm not doing too well. I can't find a second purchaser to satisfy the bank. I need to find a viable bona fide buyer to come up with $350,000 for the swim and tennis club."</p>
        <p>A consortium of five families interested in buying the club, say they may have a deal. "In searching around we found someone who has horses," a member of one of the families, Deborah Graber of Nissequogue, said. "And there is the possibility of him buying the entire parcel and working with us to lease with option to buy the swim and tennis club. Twenty percent was put down, and we're looking to finance through Dime."</p>
        <p>The group would refurbish the club and open it to members.</p>
        <p>"We have over 100 families interested," Mrs. Graber said. "We were members ourselves. It wasn't a stiff, upper-crust club. Just a very necessary, nice environment. We would like to bring that back."</p>
        <p>Another potential buyer, Brian Boshell, owner of Dilly Dally Art and Entertainment in Setauket, said that he was interested in the club for a possible animation and film studio and that he was looking for a partner with a Hollywood company.</p>
        <p>"People who have never heard of this are now coming forth," Mrs. Levin said. "It's very heartening. At this time I think we have stalled. The ax is not going to fall. There are too many potential buyers."</p>
        <p>At the Dime, Mr. Totaro said: "We're very sensitive to this issue, because it's in a community where we have branches. If for some reason we can't make it work we would like to walk away from the table with both sides' saying we tried to make it work."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
