<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Singer Lends Her Name to a Camp</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="777152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THE FRESH AIR FUND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">FRESH AIR FUND</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CAMP MARIAH (FISHKILL, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WADDELL, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAREY, MARIAH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DD103CF930A15754C0A963958260" item-length="680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Singer Lends Her Name to a Camp</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT WADDELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WADDELL, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>FISHKILL, N.Y., July 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a sunlit summer day, near the still waters of Lake Beaver, 30 children sat nervously under a white tent, waiting to perform for the pop singer Mariah Carey. They had chosen Ms. Carey's song "Hero" to sing at the dedication of Camp Mariah, the Fresh Air Fund's career awareness camp that was being named in her honor.</p>
        <p>"I met her before," said Sonseray Cummings, a 13-year-old from the Bronx, "She's a regular person. She's a superstar, but she's down to earth."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a sunlit summer day, near the still waters of Lake Beaver, 30 children sat nervously under a white tent, waiting to perform for the pop singer Mariah Carey. They had chosen Ms. Carey's song "Hero" to sing at the dedication of Camp Mariah, the Fresh Air Fund's career awareness camp that was being named in her honor.</p>
        <p>"I met her before," said Sonseray Cummings, a 13-year-old from the Bronx, "She's a regular person. She's a superstar, but she's down to earth."</p>
        <p>Ms. Carey, who is a Fresh Air Fund director, has pledged $1 million to the fund, all earmarked for Camp Mariah; $650,000 of which she has already raised through benefit concerts. The special mission of the camp is to introduce inner-city youngsters between 12 and 15 to the possibilities of careers in art, drama, journalism, photography and other areas.</p>
        <p>Many people are aware that the Fresh Air Fund pays for city children to go to summer camp or visit host families in rural areas. But the fund is equally committed to helping youngsters shape their futures.</p>
        <p>There are two four-week summer sessions at Camp Mariah, each for more than 140 children. In addition, a related Fresh Air project, the Career Awareness Program, is offered year-round and arranges for youngsters to accompany volunteers to their jobs.</p>
        <p>"This is a unique experience," said Jenny Morgenthau, executive director of the Fresh Air Fund, speaking of the programs at Camp Mariah. "We want to show the connection between getting an education and having a career."</p>
        <p>When Ms. Carey arrived, the tent soon filled with eager youngsters. Camp Mariah was dedicated in a short ceremony, and Ms. Carey was obviously pleased with the children's rendition of her song.</p>
        <p>"They knew all the inflections and just where to raise their voices," she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Carey said that when she was looking for a charity to support, she was struck by the Fresh Air Fund's career awareness projects because they were clearly fun for children as well as educational.</p>
        <p>"If nothing else," she said, "this camp will give these kids hope and be a positive influence on their lives so they won't fall through the cracks."</p>
        <p>"Coming up to this beautiful area, away from the negative influences, changes your perception of the world," she added, echoing a crucial tenet of the Fresh Air Fund.</p>
        <p>The lessons haven't been lost on Aurelius Mayfield, 13. "I thought this was just going to be a camp to play and eat and jump," he said. "This is my second year, and it's been much more than I expected: the camp is about making something out of your life."</p>
        <p>In addition to the usual hiking and swimming, the children attend career classes and get some realistic ideas even about dreamy fields like show business.</p>
        <p>Tanikka Price, a music and voice teacher at Camp Mariah, said: "I want to show the kids that there are other jobs in the music industry besides being a star -- the person who lays down the tracks or the person who writes the contracts. Sometimes being a star is not a viable option."</p>
        <p>Perquida Payne, 11, said that attending Camp Mariah had made her realize she wanted to be a lawyer.  "They treat you with so much respect here," she said. "I want to help people, and I have the attitude and I'm aggressive not to back down."</p>
        <p>Many of the youngsters were unsure what careers they wanted to pursue, but they expressed an understanding of the importance of the decisions that lay ahead of them and what they would have to do to achieve their aims.</p>
        <p>"You have to plan to make your goals come alive," said Yahaira Vargas, 14, who is interested in fields as diverse as acting and police work.</p>
        <p>But despite all the thoughts of future careers and choices, today belonged to Ms. Carey. "This is better than the Grammys," she said. "There, you're stressed out and freaked out. This is more real and touching. This is about people and giving something back."</p>
        <p>The nonprofit Fresh Air Fund depends primarily on private contributions. It costs $912 to send a child to camp. Donations may be sent to the Fresh Air Fund, 1040 Avenue of the Americas, New York, N.Y. 10018.  THE FRESH AIR FUND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
