<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Vichyssoise Of Ice Cream</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="734438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="LIVES WELL LIVED: REUBEN MATTUS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE CREAM</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HAAGEN-DAZS CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REICHL, RUTH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MATTUS, REUBEN (1912-94)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3D6113DF932A35752C0A963958260" item-length="469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Vichyssoise Of Ice Cream</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ruth Reichl</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REICHL, RUTH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>1912-1994 Reuben Mattus, the Polish immigrant who invented Haagen-Dazs, started out as a teen-ager with a horse and wagon, peddling the product that would make his fortune in the Bronx. It only took a foreign-sounding name to turn good old American ice cream into an exotic treat. By Ruth Reichl</p>
        <p>IN 1959, REUBEN MATTUS invented Haagen-Dazs. Most people thought it was ice cream. They were wrong. It was a new way to sell food to a nation convinced that everybody else in the world ate better. Call it the vichyssoise strategy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>1912-1994 Reuben Mattus, the Polish immigrant who invented Haagen-Dazs, started out as a teen-ager with a horse and wagon, peddling the product that would make his fortune in the Bronx. It only took a foreign-sounding name to turn good old American ice cream into an exotic treat. By Ruth Reichl</p>
        <p>IN 1959, REUBEN MATTUS invented Haagen-Dazs. Most people thought it was ice cream. They were wrong. It was a new way to sell food to a nation convinced that everybody else in the world ate better. Call it the vichyssoise strategy.</p>
        <p>Vichyssoise is a native New Yorker. Created at the Ritz-Carlton in 1917, it masqueraded as a French soup and enjoyed enormous success. When Mattus created his richer, more expensive ice cream, he used the same tactic. He had been selling the family ice cream in the Bronx for 30 years, and he was not the first to think that Americans would be willing to pay more for a better product. But he was the first to understand that they would be more likely to do so if they thought it was foreign. So he made up a ridiculous, impossible to pronounce name, printed a map of Scandinavia on the carton and the rest is history.</p>
        <p>The absurdity in this is that in those days America truly was the empire of ice cream. What passed as ice cream in Europe was a sweet, hard, grainy substance that came in crumbling cones best suited for use as packing material. Americans didn't care; they honestly believed that any food from across the ocean had to be better than the home-grown sort. And once they tried the ice cream with the silly name, they were hooked.</p>
        <p>The success of Haagen-Dazs spawned imitations with even sillier names, like Frusen Gladje. But it didn't stop there; before we knew it, all sorts of perfectly wonderful American foods were pretending to be imported. In New York, somebody invented a thicker waffle, dubbed it "Belgian" and watched its popularity soar. Smirnoff vodka, made in Connecticut, enjoyed a sudden vogue. A fish called "Dover sole," which often is neither a sole nor from Dover, became the seafood of choice. Nobody much liked sherbet, but when it changed its name to sorbet it became suddenly chic. Even poor old rocket, a hardy weed, was not taken seriously until somebody thought to call it arugula.</p>
        <p>But things may be changing. Two years ago, Mattus, having sold his high-fat ice cream to the Pillsbury Company, decided to reverse course and market a low-fat ice cream. When the king of butterfat cuts the calories, a new day must be dawning.</p>
        <p>But the medium isn't the message here; the name is. Just look at what Mattus decided to call his new product. He could have given it a silly name like plickenwohl or mincesse. Instead, he gave it a straightforward American moniker -- Mattus' Lowfat Ice Cream -- and ushered in a new era in eating.  LIVES WELL LIVED: REUBEN MATTUS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
