<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Minus 1: New Number For Barry Sanders</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="734584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DETROIT LIONS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GREEN BAY PACKERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, DAVE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANDERS, BARRY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Detroit Lions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Green Bay Packers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1DA1F30F932A35752C0A963958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Minus 1: New Number For Barry Sanders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDERSON, DAVE</byline>
      <dateline>GREEN BAY, Wis.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Barry Sanders was asked recently how he wanted to be viewed, his answer was as succinct as he is.</p>
        <p>"As No. 20 for the Detroit Lions," he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Barry Sanders was asked recently how he wanted to be viewed, his answer was as succinct as he is.</p>
        <p>"As No. 20 for the Detroit Lions," he said.</p>
        <p>Opponents had other numbers in mind. Such as 1,883, his rushing yardage that led the National Football League during the season. Such as 8,672, his career rushing yardage that is already 11th on the career list after only 6 seasons. Such as 5-8 and 203, the height and weight of the N.F.L's offensive player of the year.</p>
        <p>But like it or not, Barry Sanders now has a new number: minus 1.</p>
        <p>In the Packers' 16-12 victory yesterday, their swarming defense turned the Lions' dazzler into a dud. In 13 carries, he finished with minus 1 yard. On six carries, he gained 7, 1, 1, 3, 1 and 2 yards. On six others, he lost 2, 6, 4, 1, 1 and 2 yards. His other carry was for no gain.</p>
        <p>He caught three passes, but for only 4 yards, creating a paltry plus 3 in overall yardage in the opener of the N.F.C. Central intramural championships in the Super Bowl XXIX playoffs. His previous rushing low was 1 yard on 5 carries against the Pittsburgh Steelers in his rookie season of 1989.</p>
        <p>It's not unusual for Sanders to lose yardage occasionally. During the season he lost yardage on 51 rushes. Against the Jets four weeks earlier, he had been stopped for a loss nine times but still netted 127 yards. And even when he lost yardage, other teams feared that with his water bug quickness, sooner or later he would escape for a long gain.</p>
        <p>Of the nine runs of 60 or more yards in the entire N.F.L. this season, Sanders had six of them.</p>
        <p>And yesterday the Lions and 58,125 Packer parishioners kept waiting for him to break that long one, but he never did. Never came close. Usually he makes the first tackler miss and twice he was out near the sideline one-on-one with Wayne Simmons, but twice the Lions' outside linebacker nailed him to the green-painted dirt.</p>
        <p>"He can freeze you," Simmons said. "If you stay there and dance with him, he's going to get you. You've got to go right at him."</p>
        <p>In the process, the Packer defense accomplished what no other team ever had in a post-season game: holding an opponent to minus rushing yardage. Detroit was held to minus 4 yards on a total of 15 carries. The previous low was plus 7 rushing yards, twice: in Super Bowl XX, the Chicago Bears limited the New England Patriots to 7 and in a 1963 divisional playoff in Buffalo, the Boston Patriots limited the Bills to 7.</p>
        <p>"Our plan was to rush the ball," Sanders would say later, "and the good thing was, we always tried, so I can't fault the game plan. When we tried to get outside, they were always there. Thy did a good job of fighting off the blocks and closing up all the gaps on defense."</p>
        <p>Credit the Packer defensive game plan, as devised by Fritz Shurmer, their defensive coordinator who helped put the Los Angeles Rams into the 1989 N.F.C. championship game. He had been the Phoenix Cardinals' defensive coordinator for three seasons until supplanted a year ago by Buddy Ryan, the new head coach and general manager.</p>
        <p>"Our plan was to get up the field and take Sanders's lanes away," Shurmer said. "You don't want him out there on the perimeter. And when we tackled him, we wanted to take our best shot. If you let him juke, he'll break your ankles."</p>
        <p>In their two regular-season games with the Packers, the Lions had lost here, 38-30, when Sanders gained 47 yards and won, 34-31, when Sanders had 188 yards on the Silverdome's artificial turf (where he averaged 136.6 yards this season, to 98 on the road). But Shurmer dismissed the surface factor.</p>
        <p>"That balances out," Shurmer said. "Our tacklers were playing on the same field he was. We just took his angles away from him."</p>
        <p>Defense was more important than usual for the Packers, without their best wide receiver, Sterling Sharpe, his career now jeopardized by a neck injury. And the weather forecast had been for snow and temperatures in the teens, what would have been the first snow of the winter here in this meat-packing and paper-towel city once known as Title Town.</p>
        <p>"The snow," one forecaster said on Thursday, "should arrive during the game."</p>
        <p>Yes, the game. When the Packers are playing, their game is what Green Bay is all about. In the only other New Year's Eve game here, Vince Lombardi's Packers qualified for Super Bowl II with a 21-17 victory over the Dallas Cowboys in the 1967 N.F.L. championship game as quarterback Bart Starr squirmed into the end zone behind guard Jerry Kramer's block.</p>
        <p>Remembering that the temperature that frigid New Year's Eve in 1967 was 16 degrees below zero, Packer parishioners had braced for another bitter-cold picnic at Lambeau Field, an open-air saucer not that much different than it was in 1967 or even in 1957 when it was constructed.</p>
        <p>But in the darkness before dawn yesterday, "the snow went around Green Bay," the official forecaster Tassos Kallas reported. The game-time temperature was 33, with not much wind. For this time of year that's almost tropical weather up here along the Lake Michigan shore.</p>
        <p>"This," said Lee Remmel of the Packer front office, "was probably the warmest playoff game we've ever had here."</p>
        <p>By the time 58,125 Packer parishioners were celebrating, a sunset glowed across blue skies while the losing Lions were bluer than the number on Barry Sanders's silver jersey.</p>
        <p>Instead of 20, that number was now minus 1.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
