<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Dance; Circling A Floor Of Leaves</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="561621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MOVEMENT RESEARCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUSARD, YVES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, CHRISTINA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D81E3BF93AA35753C1A964958260" item-length="371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Dance; Circling A Floor Of Leaves</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yves Musard and Christina Jones, two very different choreographers, were the latest entries in the Movement Research series at Judson Church on Monday night. Open to the public at no charge and providing an unpressured setting that is congenial to works in progress, the series aims more for experiment than finished work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Musard's "Vessel," however, will probably remain as it is. What looks like minimal activity is enacted within a deliberate structure. In this case, it took the form of Mr. Musard's repeated circular trajectories on the floor, usually while inching along in a pushup position. The ground was strewn with dry leaves that Mr. Musard had scattered as he entered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yves Musard and Christina Jones, two very different choreographers, were the latest entries in the Movement Research series at Judson Church on Monday night. Open to the public at no charge and providing an unpressured setting that is congenial to works in progress, the series aims more for experiment than finished work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Musard's "Vessel," however, will probably remain as it is. What looks like minimal activity is enacted within a deliberate structure. In this case, it took the form of Mr. Musard's repeated circular trajectories on the floor, usually while inching along in a pushup position. The ground was strewn with dry leaves that Mr. Musard had scattered as he entered.</p>
        <p>Wearing striped trousers and a black top, he lay prone near a blinking light at the beginning of the piece, and at the end he finished at the opposite side of the room. To say the solo symbolized a life's journey would be to attach meaning where none was solicited. Nonetheless, Mr. Musard, a French-born choreographer who lives in New York, has had an emotional edge to his formal images in the past. Here, advancing insectlike a few inches above the ground amid the occasional crackle of the leaves, he seemed as solitary as the occasional note with which his voice sang out.</p>
        <p>The monotony was broken by the moments when he stood on one leg, tipped forward with arms dangling and looked like a Brancusi sculpture.</p>
        <p>Miss Jones, a former dancer in the Urban Bush Women troupe, and Brandon Ross, playing an electric guitar, performed in "Improvised Duet." Between solos, Miss Jones read from a notebook about bats and ladybugs. Referring to "memories" in her head, hips or shoulders, Miss Jones stressed those body parts in separate passages.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross's rich musical textures and riffs flowed into this stream of free association. Miss Jones moved with a mix of grace and force, and if the movement shifted occasionally from the fierce to the ordinary, there was a resonant point to her recurrent teetering and off-balance images. Unlike Urban Bush Women's dancers, she did not focus explicitly on the black heritage. But that heritage was implicit in her concluding remark: "There are so many layers to get through to be free."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
