<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Many Questions Await Knicks as Camp Opens</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="388360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK KNICKERBOCKERS</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D9153CF931A35753C1A966958260" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Many Questions Await Knicks as Camp Opens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For a team that has made the playoffs for three consecutive seasons, the Knicks have crucial questions to address as they prepare to open training camp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For a team that has made the playoffs for three consecutive seasons, the Knicks have crucial questions to address as they prepare to open training camp.</p>
        <p>For a team that has made the playoffs for three consecutive seasons, the Knicks have crucial questions to address as they prepare to open training camp.</p>
        <p>How will they compensate for the loss of Johnny Newman? Can Mark Jackson recapture his form of two years ago? Can they depend on Kiki Vandeweghe to stay healthy for a full season? Can Al Bianchi, the general manager, find a way to work around the salary cap to make a trade for another proven scorer?</p>
        <p>Those are some of the major challenges facing the Knicks, who begin closed two-a-day practice sessions today at the State University of New York in Purchase, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Roller Coaster Experience</p>
        <p>Having survived a roller coaster first season as head coach, Stu Jackson had several months to reflect on last year's results: a 45-37 regular season, the dramatic first-round playoff victory over Boston, and the second-round playoff loss to Detroit.</p>
        <p>After spending a summer watching videotapes with his staff, Jackson has pinpointed several areas that will be addressed during training camp.</p>
        <p>''There are several things we have to do to reach the next level,'' Jackson said. ''We have to find a way to take some of the scoring load off of Patrick Ewing. And we have to become a better team defensively, particularly our half-court defense.</p>
        <p>''To help Patrick, I think we're going to have to up-tempo our offense a little bit to create more opportunities for other players. Without question, Patrick will still be our main guy. But one of our goals is to become a more versatile offensive team by the time the season begins.''</p>
        <p>Bianchi is still trying to sign Jerrod Mustaf, New York's first-round draft choice and the 17th pick over all. The Knicks' coaches are not sure how much Mustaf, a 6-foot-10-inch forward from Maryland, can contribute this season, but the longer he goes unsigned, the less likely he is to make a significant impact. Perfect Attendance?  According to Bianchi, Mustaf and the Knicks are ''getting closer'' to agreeing, and Mustaf should be in camp at some point.</p>
        <p>All other Knicks are expected to report today. According to what the coaches have heard and seen, the players have kept themselves in excellent condition during the off season, and Vandeweghe's chronic back appears as sound as it has been in two years.</p>
        <p>Players like Ewing, Charles Oakley, Maurice Cheeks, Gerald Wilkins, Kenny Walker, Trent Tucker, and Eddie Lee Wilkins have established roles that may not change much during the next few weeks. But this is an important preseason for Vandeweghe. With Newman gone to the Charlotte Hornets, after the Knicks chose not to match Charlotte's offer sheet to Newman, Vandeweghe will be counted on more heavily. And bench players like Brian Quinnett and Stuart Gray must prove they can contribute on a consistent basis.</p>
        <p>Then there is Jackson, the fourth-year point guard, whose performance mysteriously nose-dived last season. After winning rookie of the year honors, followed by an All-Star season two years ago, Jackson slumped badly last season and eventually lost his starting job to Cheeks. By the playoffs, Jackson was making only cameo appearances whenever Cheeks needed a breather.</p>
        <p>By all accounts, Jackson played basketball regularly this summer and will report to camp in terrific shape. How much he plays will depend on how well he plays.</p>
        <p>''I have to see how he plays in camp to determine what my expectations will be,'' said Jackson, the coach. ''No matter what his role is, we all need to be pulling on the same rope. Our main objective is to help the Knicks win.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks are opening training camp three days before the rest of the National Basketball Association, because they are this season's league representative in the fourth annual McDonald's Open, to be held Oct. 11-13, in Barcelona, Spain.</p>
        <p>Knicks Signings</p>
        <p>The Knicks signed Quinnett, a second-year forward, to a multiyear contract yesterday. . . . The Knicks also signed three free agents yesterday, John Starks, a 6-5 forward from Oklahoma State; Greg Grant, a 5-7 guard from Trenton State, and Tharon Mayes, a 6-3 1/2 guard from Florida State. All three will report when training camp begins today. . . . Earl Cureton, a nine-year N.B.A. veteran who played in Italy last season, also signed with the team.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
