<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Executive Computer; Borland Is Making the Most of Old Technology</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="437404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOFTWARE PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BORLAND INTERNATIONAL INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MICROSOFT CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PETER H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D61F3CF937A25757C0A967958260" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Executive Computer; Borland Is Making the Most of Old Technology</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter H. Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PETER H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For users not yet ready or willing to switch to the Windows operating system from the Microsoft Corporation, Borland International's new Quattro Pro spreadsheet, version 3.0, offers almost the same "what you see is what you get" graphics and commands. Perhaps more than any other recent program, Quattro Pro proves that there is still plenty of life left in the DOS operating system.</p>
        <p>The Quattro Pro graphical interface is the most noticeable improvement in what many people already regarded as the best spreadsheet for personal computers made by the International Business Machines Corporation and compatible models. The true value of a spreadsheet is its ability to manipulate and consolidate numbers, and Quattro Pro does that as well as program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For users not yet ready or willing to switch to the Windows operating system from the Microsoft Corporation, Borland International's new Quattro Pro spreadsheet, version 3.0, offers almost the same "what you see is what you get" graphics and commands. Perhaps more than any other recent program, Quattro Pro proves that there is still plenty of life left in the DOS operating system.</p>
        <p>The Quattro Pro graphical interface is the most noticeable improvement in what many people already regarded as the best spreadsheet for personal computers made by the International Business Machines Corporation and compatible models. The true value of a spreadsheet is its ability to manipulate and consolidate numbers, and Quattro Pro does that as well as program.</p>
        <p>Certainly, Microsoft's Windows is a productive advance, replacing the character-based face of DOS with a mouse-driven system of pull-down menus, symbols and windows. Microsoft, which is based in Redmond, Wash., has sold more than two million copies of Windows, and its Excel 3.0 spreadsheet has become the standard that everyone, including Borland and the Lotus Development Corporation, is scrambling to meet.</p>
        <p>"Let's face it, there are tens of millions of computers out there, and 90-plus percent of them are Intel-based PC's running DOS," said Frank J. Michnoff, director of desktop computer strategies for the Meta Group, a market research and consulting firm in Westport, Conn. He was referring to the many personal computers powered by microprocessors made by the Intel Corporation of Santa Clara, Calif. "Everyone is so focused on Windows and OS/2, they're forgetting that the old technology continues to progress as well," he said. "I see more happening in the DOS market than ever before."</p>
        <p>Unlike Windows in general and Excel in particular, which requires a personal computer using a fast 80286 chip and several megabytes of memory, Quattro Pro will work on a personal computer with the less powerful 8088 chip and only 512 kilobytes of memory (the configuration of the old I.B.M. PC XT). Of course, Quattro Pro, like most spreadsheets, will work better with more processor power and memory. And an EGA or VGA monitor is required to take advantage of Quattro Pro's "what you see is what you get" graphics mode. That feature is popularly known as wysiwyg (pronounced wiz-ZEE-wig).</p>
        <p>Borland, based in Scotts Valley, Calif., is not alone in courting the millions of spreadsheet users in the DOS world. Lotus, whose 1-2-3 spreadsheet, popularized that form of software, is reported to be nearly ready to release an upgraded version of its low-end spreadsheet, to be called Lotus 1-2-3 Release 2.3. (To confuse matters, Lotus is developing a raft of 1-2-3's, including a Windows version and a Macintosh version, and another DOS version called Release 3.1 Plus. It also makes a version for the OS/2 operating system.) Lotus 1-2-3 Release 2.3 is said to have some impressive features of its own, including a built-in viewer function that lets the user actually look into spreadsheet files on a hard disk before loading them into memory, a trick first used in Lotus's Magellan program.</p>
        <p>On the surface, Quattro Pro could pass for a Windows program. Command buttons, which are operated by clicking a mouse, have a sculpted, three-dimensional look just like the ones on Excel. They even depress when they are clicked.</p>
        <p>Quattro Pro 3.0 allows users to see typefaces, sizes, colors and styles the way they will appear when the worksheet is printed -- a great benefit for people who use spreadsheets to create presentations and reports.</p>
        <p>A "zoom" command even lets an executive swoop in to look more closely at a particular table or area of a worksheet, or zoom back out to see the bigger picture.</p>
        <p>Under the hood, however, Quattro Pro lacks such advantages of Windows as advanced memory management or the ability to stay active on screen while the user works in another application. Nor does it have Excel's impressive object-linking and embedding technology, which ties together, for example, a chart within a spreadsheet to its original data source. But for looks, both on screen and on paper, Quattro Pro yields little ground to the fancier Windows programs.</p>
        <p>Other improvements include better printing performance on laser printers and a "print to fit" feature that can condense a spreadsheet to fit onto a single page. For those whose worksheets are too big to fit legibly on one page, Quattro Pro has a banner-printing feature as well, for printing sideways on continuous-form printers.</p>
        <p>Some executives forgo paper and use their spreadsheets for computer-based presentations. For them, Borland has added a number of jazzy features, including sound effects and slide-show transitions, which employ television tricks like fades, wipes, dissolves and spirals. The effects can be quite impressive, although some users may find it gauche to start a presentation with trumpet fanfare and conclude it with the sound of digitized cheering and applause.</p>
        <p>Borland also includes a "Proview Power Pack" that offers guidance on how to use these special effects to best advantage. The Power Pack comes with a selection of clip art that can be used to add emphasis to reports or 35-millimeter slides, a collection of digitized sound effects, special shortcuts called macros and templates that automate the production of many styles of graphs and charts and two Bitstream headline fonts to supplement the 18 fonts included with the spreadsheet itself.</p>
        <p>All these new features augment what was already a superior spreadsheet, and it is somewhat surprising that Borland released version 3.0 so soon after the last major upgrade, version 2.0, which was introduced last fall.</p>
        <p>"It is very, very impressive that they were able to turn this around so quickly," said Louis Giglio, vice president and director of computer software and services research for Bear, Stearns &amp; Company in New York. "Version 2.0 shipped in October, and here it is tax time and they've already shipped a new version with impressive new features."</p>
        <p>Quattro Pro has a list price of $495. Owners of earlier versions of Quattro Pro can upgrade for $49.95 to $99.95, depending on which version they have. And Borland will sell the new version for $129.95 to anyone willing to switch from competing high-end spreadsheets, a tactic that has made significant inroads against Lotus's 1-2-3. The Proview Power Pack is included with the main software; it costs an additional $49.95 for those who are upgrading or switching from a rival.</p>
        <p>"Some of Lotus's problems can be laid directly on Borland's doorstep," said Mr. Giglio. He said he expected the competition to heat up when Lotus, which is based in Cambridge, Mass., brings out its Windows version of 1-2-3 later this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
