<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blame the Bishops, but Not Public Relations</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="349445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABORTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC RELATIONS AND PUBLICITY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LARSON, MARGARET</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Relations and Publicity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D81338F931A35756C0A966958260" item-length="496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blame the Bishops, but Not Public Relations</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In ''Catholic Bishop's Big P.R. Blunder'' (Op-Ed, April 19), Eugene Kennedy is correct to view the recently announced public relations campaign against abortion by America's Roman Catholic bishops as a blunder and to see such an action as compromising their moral authority.</p>
        <p>But he fails to grasp that among Catholics and non-Catholics there is distaste and anxiety at what appears to be political action by the bishops. It is to the credit of previous bishops that Catholic politicians have insisted, whatever their personal faith, that they could not in this democracy act on the law to impose Catholic values on people who do not share them.</p>
        <p>It is the proper function of the church to convince its parishioners and seek converts. It is manifestly improper to insert its beliefs into politics and government. Abortion is an issue on which many people do not agree with the Pope and his bishops.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy taints his argument also by unrestrained and highly colored tirades against public relations. To suggest that public relations is brought in ''when the truth won't do'' and that it is ''the substitute for a genuine moral and ethical sense'' is to utter untruths. Public relations ''boys'' do not lack moral sense. The perpetrators of Watergate, Reagan-omics, Exxon evasions may be so lacking. But cover-up uses of a tool does not make all such tools corrupt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy comes closer to the truth when he calls ''masterly'' the description of pro-abortion as pro-choice. This is what good public relations is about, to identify the real message. For most of us believe ardently in the American idea that individual conscience is the real issue.</p>
        <p>The bishops may believe that what should be the Catholic individual's conscience should be everyone's conscience. That is not our belief. And many Catholics who oppose abortion agree. For the bishops to flout the carefully delineated line between faith and democracy is to set up a barrier against their own communicants.</p>
        <p>In a wildly complex world, public relations is the communications arm of many vital industries and of many social issues, such as clean air and water, environment protection, treatment for acquired immune deficiency syndrome, literacy, brotherhood, better education, care for the aged, all of which the Catholic Church supports.</p>
        <p>To malign the messenger is to miss the point of the message or confuse it with the source.</p>
        <p>The real fallacy of the bishops' foray into public relations is that they are undertaking a campaign beyond the appropriate function of the church. Taking on all American women may be an ideal, but it is inappropriate, particularly before the church has sold its own parishioners.</p>
        <p>A good public relations campaign can blur edges and confuse perceptions. But, an effective one, in the long run, does not misread its proper goals so badly.</p>
        <p>MARGARET LARSON</p>
        <p>New York, April 19, 1990</p>
        <p>The writer heads her own public relations organization.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
