<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Winfield Seeking the Key To Finding His Old Form</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="349564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WINFIELD, DAVE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, CLAIRE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDC163AF931A35756C0A966958260" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Winfield Seeking the Key To Finding His Old Form</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAIRE SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, CLAIRE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Has it come to this? Dave Winfield, role player, out with the coaches and the manager, Bucky Dent, taking advantage of the time allowed in the batting cage for the extra players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Has it come to this? Dave Winfield, role player, out with the coaches and the manager, Bucky Dent, taking advantage of the time allowed in the batting cage for the extra players.</p>
        <p>Has it come to this? Dave Winfield, role player, out with the coaches and the manager, Bucky Dent, taking advantage of the time allowed in the batting cage for the extra players.</p>
        <p>''Nah, early b.p. isn't anything new and unique,'' Winfield said. ''It's important just to get some swings in, to see some breaking balls.''</p>
        <p>Winfield, standing on the top step of the Yankee Stadium dugout, paused, then said quietly, as if speaking to himself: ''You'll see me in practice, knocking the cover off the ball. Other teams will see, too.''</p>
        <p>Winfield spoke before stepping onto the Yankee Stadium field to take early hitting along with Steve Balboni, another right-handed bat not destined to appear in Dent's lineup against the Oakland right-hander Mike Moore last night.</p>
        <p>Platoon With Washington</p>
        <p>It's something new for the 17-year major league veteran, not having the luxury of knowing he's in there every day, no matter what sort of pitcher the other team might use. That all ended for Winfield Monday when Dent, looking at the left fielder's .191 batting average and at the team's struggles against right-handers (3-7), opted to platoon Winfield and the newly acquired Claudell Washington.</p>
        <p>Winfield pinch-hit for Washington in the eighth inning last night against the left-handed Rick Honeycutt, and his fortunes got no better. He struck out.</p>
        <p>Winfield sat out against Bob Welch, a right-hander, on Monday, missing a game in which the Yankees were limited to six hits in a 6-0 loss.</p>
        <p>Should Dent stick to the platoon, Winfield will most likely not start any of the three games against Oakland. The A's are scheduled to start yet another right-hander, Scott Sanderson or Todd Burns, tonight.</p>
        <p>Winfield is obviously not pleased with the latest development, but he chose to tread softly in order to avoid another flareup in the controversies that have marked his nine years with the Yankees. Still, he refuses to accept the reasoning that his low average means that perhaps his career is in jeopardy. Winfield also adamantly rejects any analysis that suggests his age (38) and the season missed because of back surgery have withered his skills.</p>
        <p>''This is just a period of adjustment,'' Winfield said. ''It has nothing to do with physical ability or past injuries. I can play with anybody in the league, in the outfield or anything. Other teams know. I'm sure the opposition is pleased when they don't see me. That's fact. Ask any pitcher.''</p>
        <p>Yet, what sort of testament would pitchers give for a player hitting below .200 and mired in an 0-for-20 slump on the current homestand?</p>
        <p>Winfield insists the average and the hitless skein are misleading.</p>
        <p>''They've caught some line drives, in center, at short, some deep drives,'' Winfield said. ''It's not like these guys are beating up on me. No one's embarrassing me or overpowering me. I had a good week, then a bad week. It happens.''</p>
        <p>It's not allowed to happen that way when a team struggles along with you, when your personal history and that of the team owner make every move by either party subject to careful dissection and repeated analysis.</p>
        <p>George Steinbrenner, in town for Monday's game against Oakland, expressed surprise at the lineup change and insisted that the decision was and is in the hands of his baseball people.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner did express a certain sadness about Winfield's struggles, however, because, he said, ''he's worked hard to come back.''</p>
        <p>''But they have to make baseball judgments,'' he said about Dent and the coaches.</p>
        <p>The irony in Winfield's situation could be that Winfield and Champ Summers, the hitting coach, feel they have found a flaw in Winfield's swing.</p>
        <p>''There was something in my stride,'' Winfield said. ''I was basically lifting my front leg and coming back when I need to come back and then forward in order to swing the way I ordinarily do. Champ and I discovered it during b.p. yesterday, but talk is cheap. That's why we're filming today. Getting it on video means a little more.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
