<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Ballet Closes Ranks And the Shows Go On</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="544975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BATTERED SPOUSES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY BALLET</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNNING, JENNIFER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARTINS, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KISTLER, DARCI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED7163DF937A15754C0A964958260" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Ballet Closes Ranks And the Shows Go On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNNING, JENNIFER</byline>
      <dateline>SARATOGA SPRINGS, N.Y., July 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A curtain parted on the private world of the ballet on Tuesday to reveal that ballet stars, for all their glamour, are merely mortal. The news was out that Peter Martins, balletmaster in chief of the New York City Ballet, had been arrested early Sunday morning by the police in Saratoga Springs, the company's usually relaxed summer home, on charges of beating his wife, the ballerina Darci Kistler.</p>
        <p>The story broke on Wednesday, with lurid front-page headlines in several New York City tabloids. By Thursday afternoon, the curtain had dropped back into place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A curtain parted on the private world of the ballet on Tuesday to reveal that ballet stars, for all their glamour, are merely mortal. The news was out that Peter Martins, balletmaster in chief of the New York City Ballet, had been arrested early Sunday morning by the police in Saratoga Springs, the company's usually relaxed summer home, on charges of beating his wife, the ballerina Darci Kistler.</p>
        <p>The story broke on Wednesday, with lurid front-page headlines in several New York City tabloids. By Thursday afternoon, the curtain had dropped back into place.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kistler, 28 years old, had called the police to the couple's rented apartment, saying that Mr. Martins, 45, had slapped her and thrown her into an adjoining room when she persisted in requests that the two discuss their faltering, seven-month-old marriage. Ms. Kistler has subsequently moved out of the apartment but has been taking classes and performing with the company at the Saratoga Performing Arts Center.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kistler and Mr. Martins appeared in court on Wednesday, when Ms. Kistler dropped charges against Mr. Martins. The third-degree assault charge was withdrawn "with prejudice," said David Gray, the company's press representative, which means the charge cannot be refiled. Mr. Gray later issued a statement saying that the two regretted the escalation of a personal dispute and would seek professional help.</p>
        <p>Gillian Attfield, the president of the City Ballet, denied reports that the board had scheduled an emergency meeting this week. A source close to the board said that the group's immediate concern has been damage control rather than the resignation or dismissal of Mr. Martins.  And the Jokes Begin</p>
        <p>By Thursday evening, a joke was making its way through the town's more blase social circles. There was to be a new addition to the City Ballet repertory, the joke went, a ballet set to music by Smetana and called "The Battered Bride."</p>
        <p>One former City Ballet dancer talked of the dancers' initial shock, depression and feelings of being lost. He said there had been a great deal of conversation about the incident among dancers who had been in abusive relationships. But the habits of work were eventually reinstated.</p>
        <p>Public comments by company personnel were as rare on Thursday as sunbathers in this rainy, chilly resort town. Someone close to the company who did not wish to be identified said that Mr. Martins had steeled himself on Tuesday to go to the Performing Arts Center to teach his customary morning ballet class to the company. Below the nameplate on his office door, someone had written in red ink, "wife-beater," but there was no response from the dancers when he entered the studio. Ms. Kistler took the class, another the source said, appearing slightly bruised but calm.</p>
        <p>By performance time Wednesday night, said a former company member who visited backstage, the dancers "were behaving as well as always, and working as always." "I don't think people recognize how famous they are," the dancer said, referring to Mr. Martins and Ms. Kistler. "I pray the personal doesn't take over the professional."  Extra Applause</p>
        <p>Ms. Kistler was greeted with a standing ovation from a group of dance students when she performed on Tuesday night in Jerome Robbins's "In G Major," and applause greeted her entrances and exits in the ballet. By Thursday afternoon, however, the audience seemed to accept Ms. Kistler simply as one of the company's lead dancers, without special applause at her entrance in Mr. Martins's "Delight of the Muses."</p>
        <p>But the incident was on the mind of some audience members. "I thought it was unfortunate this had to be sensationalized," Kathy O'Malley, of Loudonville, N.Y., said. "Brutality is not right under any circumstances. I hope they get the counseling they need. But I'm going to look at her as the artist, the performer she is. I don't expect this to affect her dancing in the least."</p>
        <p>Tony Yeacael, a local taxi driver, said, "We usually get scandals with the track crowd," referring to the racing season that follows the City Ballet engagement. There was a big crowd gathered at the courthouse on Wednesday to see Mr. Martins and Ms. Kistler, he said, adding, "At least they got them out on time for the show."</p>
        <p>The dancers go on to New York for the filming of "The Nutcracker" before their annual two-week layoff in September. "There is an incredible continuity to the company," a former ballerina said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
