<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NFL Training Camp Report</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="545017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL FOOTBALL LEAGUE (NFL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, ROBERT MCG JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D7123FF937A15754C0A964958260" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NFL Training Camp Report</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT McG. THOMAS Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">THOMAS, ROBERT MCG JR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Buffalo Bills</p>
        <p>The Bills, who had tried to dismiss the continued significance of the mysterious knee infection that kept strong safety Leonard Smith out of the Super Bowl, faced up to reality yesterday. Smith, a mainstay of the Buffalo defense since he arrived from Phoenix in 1988, was released after failing his physical.</p>
        <p>The 31-year-old Smith, whose recovery had been slow despite hard work at rehabilitation, had known he might not be ready for immediate action, but he was surprised by the cut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Buffalo Bills</p>
        <p>The Bills, who had tried to dismiss the continued significance of the mysterious knee infection that kept strong safety Leonard Smith out of the Super Bowl, faced up to reality yesterday. Smith, a mainstay of the Buffalo defense since he arrived from Phoenix in 1988, was released after failing his physical.</p>
        <p>The 31-year-old Smith, whose recovery had been slow despite hard work at rehabilitation, had known he might not be ready for immediate action, but he was surprised by the cut.</p>
        <p>"I felt like I would still be a part of the team and rehab during the year and see what happened later and then continue playing," he said as he left camp.</p>
        <p>In the end it might have been Smith's age as much as his ailing knee that cost him his job. The Bills were simply unable to wait for an uncertain full recovery.</p>
        <p>"We feel that we're better off committing ourselves to the new young prospects," said Coach Marv Levy.  He added that last year's first-round draft choice, Henry Jones, is Smith's most likely replacement and that veteran Dwight Drane is another contender.</p>
        <p>As the Bills opened their training camp in Freedonia, N.Y., Levy had other problems to contend with. Among seven veterans without contracts were four other starters from last year's American Conference champions: Pro Bowl linebacker Cornelius Bennett, tight end Keith McKeller, cornerback Kirby Jackson and defensive end Leon Seals. Chicago Bears</p>
        <p>William (Refrigerator) Perry was among the missing and unmissed as the Bears opened their training camp in Platteville, Wis., yesterday. Perry doesn't have a contract, but he does have an appetite, and to Coach Mike Ditka, that's a far bigger problem.</p>
        <p>"I don't think he'll be with the football team this year," said Ditka, describing himself as fed up with Perry's chronic feeding habits and often-broken promises to stick to a reasonable diet. "He's not coming in until we sign him and we're not signing him until we weigh him," added the coach, who has set a 320-pound limit for the defensive lineman.</p>
        <p>Just how much Perry weighs is anybody's guess, but based on past training camps it is likely to be far more than 320 pounds.</p>
        <p>Ditka, who has lived with Perry's weight problems in the past, said that this year will be different since Perry is no longer an essential part of the Bears' plans. That's because he has two hungry linemen, Chris Zorich and Alonzo Spellman, ready to move into Perry's positon. Cincinnati Bengals</p>
        <p>Defensive end Natu Tuatagaloa will have nonfootball matters on his mind if he shows up on time for the start of training camp today. He was arrested in San Rafael, Calif., Monday night and charged with assaulting his girlfriend. Tuatagaloa, a former University of California star, was released on $7,000 bail on Tuesday, but has a date in Marin Municipal Court on Aug. 3. The police said that the player's girlfriend, Lisa Malnick, told them that Tuatagaloa pushed her to the ground during an argument on the porch of the home they share with their five-year-old daughter. Malnick said she banged her head, scraped her knee and forearm and cut her toe in the fall. Miami Dolphins</p>
        <p>Nose tackle Alfred Oglesby admitted making up a story that he had been kidnapped to escape punishment for breaking curfew on Wednesday night and missing practice yesterday afternoon.</p>
        <p>Oglesby said he missed yesterday's practice after being kidnapped late Wednesday by two armed men who stole the car he was driving. He said that the men abandoned him in the Everglades and that he had to walk most of the way back to the Dolphins' training camp.</p>
        <p>After being interviewed by the police, however, Oglesby admitted making up the tale in hopes of avoiding punishment from Coach Don Shula after missing curfew and then oversleeping and missing yesterday morning's training session.</p>
        <p>"I'm sorry about the first story," Oglesby said. "I was a little afraid. I didn't know what to tell Coach Shula. I really panicked. I didn't want to lose my job."</p>
        <p>Oglesby, 25 years old, said he expected a "stiff fine" from Shula. The coach, who initially said he would take Oglesby at his word, told aides he would decide how to punish Oglesby today.</p>
        <p>Police searched for Oglesby Wednesday night and yesterday after teammate Richmond Webb reported him missing in Webb's car. Officers found the 1990 BMW yesterday morning in a crime-ridden suburb of Miami. Philadelphia Eagles</p>
        <p>In a parting that he said saddened him, Coach Rich Kotite announced that tight end Mickey Shuler, a 14-year National Football League veteran, left camp after failing his physical and is expected to retire. Shuler, who joined the Eagles in 1990, missed most of last season with back problems.</p>
        <p>"I've been with him basically since 1983, and I'm sorry to see him go," said Kotite, who coached Shuler as offensive coordinator with the Jets before becoming head coach of the Eagles.</p>
        <p>"He was a tremendous overachiever. He had a great work ethic."</p>
        <p>Before last season, Shuler was the leading receiver among active tight ends and seventh overall among active players on the receiving career list with 456 catches. He spent 12 years with the Jets after being drafted out of Penn State and made the Pro Bowl twice. San Diego Chargers</p>
        <p>Leslie O'Neal, a Pro Bowl defensive end with a well-known aversion to training camp and a reputation for tough contract negotiations, pulled a stunt that left the Chargers reeling with surprise. He signed a one-year contract in time to join yesterday's first full workouts.</p>
        <p>O'Neal, one of three veterans who signed on Wednesday, along with center Courtney Hall and linebacker Henry Rolling, had a disarming explanation for his surprise appearance.</p>
        <p>"They made me a fair offfer," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
