<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Book Notes</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="526405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AWARDS, DECORATIONS AND HONORS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CAMBRIDGE UNIVERSITY PRESS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HARPERCOLLINS PUBLISHERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FEIN, ESTHER B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADFORD, BARBARA TAYLOR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAWRENCE, D H (1885-1930)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ASHBERY, JOHN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SONS AND LOVERS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LILLY, RUTH, POETRY PRIZE</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DC1330F935A35756C0A964958260" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Book Notes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Esther B. Fein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FEIN, ESTHER B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barbara Taylor Bradford, one of the best-selling commercial fiction authors, has signed a contract with HarperCollins to write three novels for more than $20 million, making her one of the highest paid authors in the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barbara Taylor Bradford, one of the best-selling commercial fiction authors, has signed a contract with HarperCollins to write three novels for more than $20 million, making her one of the highest paid authors in the world.</p>
        <p>The deal, which people in publishing say is one of the biggest ever in the industry, gives HarperCollins worldwide English-language rights for the hard-cover, paperback and audio editions of Mrs. Bradford's books, the first of which is to be published in the fall of 1994.</p>
        <p>HarperCollins in England has published all of Mrs. Bradford's seven novels for markets in Britain and other English-speaking countries outside of Canada and the United States. Doubleday published her first five novels in the United States, including her debut success, "A Woman of Substance." Her two most recent books, including her latest best seller, "Remember," were published here by Random House.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bradford keeps all foreign-language rights and, more significantly in the so-called women's genre, she has the film rights to her books. Five of her previous novels have been made into mini-series or television movies. "To Be the Best" is to be shown on CBS in the summer and "Remember" is being turned into a screenplay under the direction of her husband, Robert Bradford, a television producer.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bradford, who said in an interview that she would celebrate her staggering deal with a good meal and a fine bottle of Champagne, explained that she decided to integrate all of her English language rights under one publisher to simplify and bolster international marketing and sales efforts and that she chose HarperCollins mostly out of loyalty.</p>
        <p>"They made me, in England and the rest of the Commonwealth, one of the biggest authors in the world," said Mrs. Bradford, a former journalist from Leeds, England, who moved to the United States in 1964.</p>
        <p>She said she had been pleased with Random House's treatment of her and still owed that publisher one novel, "Angel," which she said she planned to turn in at the end of the year and to promote aggressively.</p>
        <p>Harold Evans, the publisher of Random House, said he was "surprised and saddened" when he heard of Mrs. Bradford's decision and added that Random House had barely begun to negotiate with her for her next books when he was told that she had signed a contract with HarperCollins.</p>
        <p>"We took her to new levels of success in hard cover with 'Remember' and in paperback at Ballantine with 'The Women in His Life,' " he said. "We had only just started talking, which is why we're so surprised, but I guess this is the business we're in." The Second Son</p>
        <p>Why was D. H. Lawrence's novel called "Sons and Lovers" when there was only one son in the book? The answer is that in Lawrence's original text there was an older brother to Paul Morel, William, who was but one of the parts of the book that were cut by the publisher, Duckworth, for fear that its sexual tone was too provocative for British readers in 1913.</p>
        <p>In an effort to set the literary record straight, Cambridge University Press is planning to publish an uncut version of "Sons and Lovers" in the fall, restoring not only William but many passages that give a fuller, bawdier, more passionate feel to a book that was pretty steamy even in its censored form.</p>
        <p>The original censoring was done by Lawrence's friend and editor, Edward Garnett, who cut 10 percent of the book without consulting the author, said Dr. Helen Baron and Dr. Carl Baron, the editors who have prepared the new Cambridge edition. Lawrence acceded, they said, because he was broke.</p>
        <p>Many of the cuts distort Lawrence's portrait of his characters, depriving readers of both subtle observations and important events that shaped them. In one scene that was truncated, Clara let Paul stay in her bedroom after he missed his train. In the standard version, Paul fell asleep, then woke up and looked silently at the darkened room. In the original, when Paul woke up he noticed a pair of Clara's stockings, and "He got up stealthily, and put them on himself."</p>
        <p>Other changes have the effect of splashing cold water on a heated passage. In one, the cut sentence reads: "He could smell her faint perfume." Pretty harmless. But the original reads: "He could smell her faint natural perfume, and it drove him wild with hunger." Different tone entirely.</p>
        <p>When he did his trimming, the Barons say in their foreword to the new edition, Garnett was looking at length as well, since the book was about 100 pages longer than was standard in those days. But they note that he was often careless in his slicing and in several instances left in later references to scenes he had cut, causing "confusion to generations of readers."</p>
        <p>Cambridge University Press usually publishes expensive scholarly editions of classics, but it will bring out two editions of "Sons and Lovers," a $24.95 commercial edition that is a straightforward publication of the uncut novel and a $95 critical edition that diagrams all the changes. Poet Honored</p>
        <p>John Ashbery, who has received every other major American poetry prize, has won the 1992 Ruth Lilly Poetry Prize, Joseph Parisi, the editor of Poetry magazine and the chairman of the prize selection committee, announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>The $25,000 prize, one of the largest poetry awards in the United States, is administered by the Modern Poetry Association and the American Council for the Arts and was established in 1986 by Ruth Lilly, a philanthropist from Indianapolis, to honor an American poet "whose accomplishments warrant extraordinary recognition."</p>
        <p>Mr. Ashbery, who is 65 years old, said in an interview that being a poet in the United States was an odd occupation since "not that many people in this country like poetry, and in fact, many people hate it."</p>
        <p>Given the American indifference at best, he said, he finds it curious but reassuring that publishing houses here continue to publish poetry at all. "I've never understood why most of the major houses bother," said Mr. Ashbery, whose latest book, "Flow Chart," was published last year by Alfred A. Knopf. "I've been told that it's because poetry doesn't cost that much to publish and when poets are well known, even if they are unread, their names add prestige to a house that helps to attract other writers who might bring income."</p>
        <p>Mr. Ashbery said the prize money was "certainly welcome but hardly enough to quit my job and retire." Every poet he knows, Mr. Ashbery said, lives on income other than from writing, mostly from teaching, as he does at Bard College in Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y..</p>
        <p>Despite his age and distinguished position in the world of American letters, Mr. Ashbery said that winning the Lilly prize was, like winning an Oscar for a veteran film actor, a boost to the ego. "It makes one feel better," he said. "It temporarily allays one's doubts about one's work that you think you've conquered but that eventually come creeping back."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
