<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BASEBALL: National League; Odd Homer Helps Expos Beat Padres</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="526401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DD1230F935A35756C0A964958260" item-length="622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BASEBALL: National League; Odd Homer Helps Expos Beat Padres</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Expos 5, Padres 2</p>
        <p>MONTREAL, May 5 (AP) -- The Expos won their first night game of the season tonight after 12 consecutive losses as Larry Walker hit a ground-rule inside-the-park homer to lead Montreal to a 5-2 victory.</p>
        <p>John Vanderwal, a late substitution in left field, and Walker hit back-to-back bases-empty home runs in the third off Greg Harris (1-2) to support the pitching of Dennis Martinez (2-4). Martinez gave up one run on seven hits in seven innings before Bill Landrum relieved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Expos 5, Padres 2</p>
        <p>MONTREAL, May 5 (AP) -- The Expos won their first night game of the season tonight after 12 consecutive losses as Larry Walker hit a ground-rule inside-the-park homer to lead Montreal to a 5-2 victory.</p>
        <p>John Vanderwal, a late substitution in left field, and Walker hit back-to-back bases-empty home runs in the third off Greg Harris (1-2) to support the pitching of Dennis Martinez (2-4). Martinez gave up one run on seven hits in seven innings before Bill Landrum relieved.</p>
        <p>Walker's shot started out as what appeared to be a high, routine fly ball to the warning track in right field.</p>
        <p>But as right fielder Tony Gwynn ran back to get under the ball, it struck a speaker about 150 feet above the field and dropped to the field about 30 feet from the fence. Terry Tata, the home-plate umpire, ruled it a home run on the basis of ground rules pertaining to such speakers. Cubs 4, Braves 3</p>
        <p>CHICAGO (AP) -- Rey Sanchez hit a sacrifice fly with the bases loaded in the 10th inning for Chicago. Sanchez was given the starting shortstop position for at least two weeks when Shawon Dunston was placed on the 15-day disabled list with a back strain.</p>
        <p>"It's a great feeling to know I'm going to start," Sanchez said. "It's a chance for me. Playing for Shawon, one of the best shortstops around, will be not be easy."</p>
        <p>Andre Dawson and Derrick May singled with one out off Alejandro Pena (0-2), the fifth Atlanta pitcher. Pena intentionally walked Hector Villanueva, and Sanchez, just 1 for 13 since coming up from Class AAA Iowa of the American Association, flied to right, scoring Dawson for Chicago's second victory in eight games. Phillies 6, Dodgers 2</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA (AP) -- Terry Mulholland pitched an eight-hitter for his first victory of the season and Dale Sveum drove in three runs as Philadelphia sent Los Angeles to its fifth consecutive loss. The Dodgers spolied Mulholland's shutout bid in the eighth after a walk to pinch-hitter Stan Javier, who stole second and scored on Mike Sharperson's one-out single. Eric Karros led off the ninth with a homer for the Dodgers' other run off Mulholland (1-3).</p>
        <p>Tom Candiotti (3-1) lost for the first time in the National League. He was trailing when he was forced to leave the game in the third after being hit in the chest by a liner off the bat of John Kruk. The Dodgers said Candiotti had bruises and would be re-examined Wednesday. Pirates 5, Reds 2</p>
        <p>PITTSBURGH (AP) -- Andy Van Slyke had three hits, including a homer and a double, and Pittsburgh rallied in the sixth inning for the second consecutive night to beat Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>Tim Belcher (1-4), who was 7-1 against Pittsburgh entering the season, lost to the Pirates for the second time in a week after carrying a 2-1 lead into the sixth. Belcher was the loser in the Pirates' 4-0 victory in Cincinnati last week.</p>
        <p>Van Slyke is 7 for 9 in the series and has improved his average from .107 on April 17 to .363 with 26 hits in his last 52 times at bat. Cardinals 7, Giants 5</p>
        <p>ST. LOUIS (AP) -- Todd Zeile snapped a sixth-inning tie with a sacrifice fly, his first r.b.i. in 12 games, as St. Louis won after squandering a five-run lead. Ozzie Smith doubled to lead off the sixth and advanced on a groundout before Zeile lined out to right off Dave Burba (1-3).</p>
        <p>Reliever Mike Perez (3-0) allowed two hits in one and two-thirds innings. Todd Worrell got out of a bases-loaded jam in the eighth when pinch-hitter Craig Colbert lined into an inning-ending double play and Lee Smith worked the ninth for his league-leading ninth save in 10 opportunities.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals took a 5-0 lead off Kelly Downs after three innings, but the Giants tied it with four runs in the sixth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
