<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: White House; Bush and Justice Dept. Step Up Response to Riot</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="526272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOOT AND LOOTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARSON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRUTALITY AND HARASSMENT CHARGES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TERWILLIGER, GEORGE J 3D (DEPUTY ATTY GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KING, RODNEY GLEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WINES, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D6123AF935A35756C0A964958260" item-length="1086" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: White House; Bush and Justice Dept. Step Up Response to Riot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WINES, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush accelerated his efforts today to demonstrate concern about last week's riots, moving up a scheduled trip to Los Angeles as the Justice Department dispatched 50 officials there to oversee Federal investigations of riot-related violence.</p>
        <p>The actions raised the Federal resources committed to restoring order in the Los Angeles area to 5,100 people, mostly military troops, and more than $600 million. Since the weekend, the White House has issued a growing stream of announcements about riot-related assistance. Some of Mr. Bush's political critics had asserted at the end of last week that his response to the crisis had been slower and more modest than was demanded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush accelerated his efforts today to demonstrate concern about last week's riots, moving up a scheduled trip to Los Angeles as the Justice Department dispatched 50 officials there to oversee Federal investigations of riot-related violence.</p>
        <p>The actions raised the Federal resources committed to restoring order in the Los Angeles area to 5,100 people, mostly military troops, and more than $600 million. Since the weekend, the White House has issued a growing stream of announcements about riot-related assistance. Some of Mr. Bush's political critics had asserted at the end of last week that his response to the crisis had been slower and more modest than was demanded.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush told Senate Republicans at a meeting on Capitol Hill that he had ordered the Justice Department to arrest any rioters who can be charged under Federal laws in connection with the 58 deaths, destruction and looting that marked the unrest. Those officials also are to work with the local authorities in investigating all riot-related crimes, the White House said. Questions of Jurisdiction</p>
        <p>It remains to be seen which prosecutions will take precedence in cases where both Federal and state laws were broken, Deputy Attorney General George J. Terwilliger 3d said in an interview today. "As in any series of cases, the decision about what jurisdiction to prosecute under will be made based on the evidence and the respective state or Federal interest involved," he said.</p>
        <p>The department's decision today to take an active role in investigating and prosecuting riot-related crimes contrasts with its more passive role in the case of Rodney G. King, the black motorist whose beating by four white Los Angeles police officers was the fuse that led to last week's violence.</p>
        <p>In Mr. King's case, the department deferred an investigation of the officers until state prosecutors had completed their case against the four men. The officers won acquittals on all charges that were decided; one charge against one officer resulted in a mistrial, and prosecutors are deciding whether to retry it. A Federal grand jury is continuing to hear the case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Terwilliger, an architect of the Justice Department's response to the riots, said today that the department's actions in the two cases were not contradictory.</p>
        <p>"I would disagree that we backed away in the King case," he said. "We put any further prosecutive effort on hold because the state wished to go forward," but continued to monitor the trial. That, he said, is routine when state prosecutors express strong interest in a case.</p>
        <p>The decision to send Federal investigators and prosecutors to Los Angeles was made after state and local officials were consulted and agreed with the proposal, he said.</p>
        <p>Senator John Seymour of California, one of 41 Republican lawmakers at the session where Mr. Bush spoke, told reporters that the Justice Department was already reviewing videotapes of the riots to try to track down suspects.</p>
        <p>The White House later said that Mr. Bush would fly to Los Angeles on Wednesday afternoon, a day ahead of schedule, for two days of visits to the riot areas and extensive talks with victims of the violence, community leaders, police officers and National Guard troops.</p>
        <p>In a statement today, Attorney General William P. Barr said the Justice Department was sending 40 Federal agents, 20 from the Federal Bureau of Investigation and 20 from the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms, to help identify and arrest rioters. Ten agents from the Los Angeles office of the Drug Enforcement Administration will join them to work on drug-related violence, Mr. Barr said. Working With Local Officials</p>
        <p>The agents will work with city, county and state law-enforcement officials to investigate "the most aggravated crimes of violence committed during the riot," he said. Five prosecutors from Washington and the United States Attorney's office in Los Angeles were assigned to oversee Federal prosecutions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barr said that the Federal agents have jurisdiction in the riot cases through an array of Federal laws dealing with civil disorders, Federal property damage, firearms violations and other crimes. But a Justice Department official, speaking on condition of anonymity, said later that the bulk of the most serious offenses, from murder to property damage, would probably be governed solely by state laws and therefore not subject to Federal action.</p>
        <p>Many of the applicable Federal laws appear to be tangential to the actual rioting. They include laws prohibiting destruction of Federal property, like mailboxes and post offices; prohibitions against interfering with the police or firefighters during a civil disorder; bans on threatening or injuring people engaged in interstate commerce, and a number of gun laws that make it illegal, for example, to transfer firearms for use in a crime.</p>
        <p>Department officials said it was uncertain whether civil-rights laws would also be applied in the investigations, although some said those laws could apply if it is found that Korean-owned businesses were specifically targeted for destruction by rioters.</p>
        <p>The political thrust of today's moves was to cast Mr. Bush as a strong leader in a crisis and to place his White House firmly in the Republican tradition of responding to civil disturbances with an emphasis on law and order.</p>
        <p>The White House response is especially important to Mr. Bush's political future because California, a Republican linchpin in recent Presidential races, is viewed by Republicans and Democrats alike as a tossup in this election year. Before the riots, Mr. Bush had planned two long trips to the state this month to prepare for the state's Presidential primary on June 2.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's only public comments on the situation today were intended to be soothing. In an afternoon ceremony at the Mexican Cultural Institute marking Cinco de Mayo, a Mexican holiday celebrating the defeat of French invaders under Napoleon III on May 5, 1862, the President called for citizens to "rethink and reaffirm the bonds that knit all nationalities together."</p>
        <p>Administration officials said that Mr. Bush indicated again in a morning meeting with Cabinet secretaries, the second in two days, that he planned few, if any, new Federal initiatives to address urban problems, but would instead press Congress to enact several Republican programs now mired in Capitol Hill committees, including a proposal to extend Federal tax breaks to businesses that invest in the inner cities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
