<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hormone Replacement: Weighing Risks and Benefits</title>
    <meta content="01BREA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1172980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Menopause</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Estrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Progestin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Uterus</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Breast Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Estrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Menopause</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Estrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Menopause</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uterus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2D9163FF932A35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hormone Replacement: Weighing Risks and Benefits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane E Brody article on research suggesting that progestin, which many menopausal and postmenopausal women take in combination with estrogen, may be a more important factor than estrogen in development of breast cancers associated with hormone replacement therapy; notes that progestin was included in hormone regimen specifically to prevent estrogen from inducing endometrial cancer, a cancer of urterine lining; says that until issue is settled by studies now under way, a woman should evaluate potential benefits and risks based on her own family and personal medical history, as well as her comfort level with taking or not taking hormones (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Should I or shouldn't I?'' It's a question millions of women ask themselves these days, as baby boomers near or recently past menopause try to decide whether to take hormone replacement. Joining them are millions of older women, many of whom have been taking estrogen or a combination of estrogen and progestin for years and wonder if it is wise to continue, as well as many others who wonder if it is wise to start.</p>
        <p>At issue is an oft-repeated finding that the use of hormone replacement is associated with an increased risk of developing breast cancer, especially when the hormones are taken for upwards of 10 years or more. Although heart disease ultimately kills six times as many women as breast cancer and the cancers linked to hormone replacement tend to be highly curable, there is an emotional factor to consider: justifiably or not, breast cancer is the disease most feared by American women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Should I or shouldn't I?'' It's a question millions of women ask themselves these days, as baby boomers near or recently past menopause try to decide whether to take hormone replacement. Joining them are millions of older women, many of whom have been taking estrogen or a combination of estrogen and progestin for years and wonder if it is wise to continue, as well as many others who wonder if it is wise to start.</p>
        <p>At issue is an oft-repeated finding that the use of hormone replacement is associated with an increased risk of developing breast cancer, especially when the hormones are taken for upwards of 10 years or more. Although heart disease ultimately kills six times as many women as breast cancer and the cancers linked to hormone replacement tend to be highly curable, there is an emotional factor to consider: justifiably or not, breast cancer is the disease most feared by American women.</p>
        <p>A new study, reported last week in The Journal of the American Medical Association, suggests that, although estrogen has long been considered the main hormonal risk in breast cancer, progestin may be a more important factor. The study, by scientists at the National Cancer Institute conducted among 46,355 postmenopausal women, found that in lean (but not in heavy) women, taking estrogen with progestin was associated with an 8 percent increase in breast cancer risk with each year of use, as opposed to a 1 percent increase when estrogen alone was taken.</p>
        <p>Likewise, a study conducted in Los Angeles County by Dr. Ronald K. Ross and colleagues at the University of Southern California among 1,900 postmenopausal breast cancer patients and 1,600 healthy postmenopausal women found a substantially higher risk of breast cancer when progestin was combined with estrogen for hormone replacement therapy than when estrogen alone was taken. This study is scheduled for publication this month in The Journal of the National Cancer Institute.</p>
        <p>Women may rightly regard these findings, which confirm several previous studies, as a cruel twist of fate, since progestin has been included in the regimen specifically to prevent estrogen from inducing endometrial cancer, a cancer of the uterine lining. Endometrial cancer is much rarer than breast cancer and has a very high cure rate, but the treatment for it can be quite debilitating. When a woman with a uterus takes estrogen without progestin, the risk of endometrial cancer is increased as much as 14-fold.</p>
        <p>The situation is further complicated by the fact that all of these studies have flaws. Many of them rely on women's memories of what hormone treatments they took, and memories can be imprecise. The studies are not controlled clinical trials -- that is, women are not randomly assigned to receive hormones or placebos. A large placebo-controlled clinical trial, sponsored by the National Institutes of Health is under way, but results are not expected until 2006 and even then may not answer all the questions.</p>
        <p>Over all, studies have shown, women who have used hormone replacement therapy tend to live longer than women who do not. But these studies too are flawed, in that hormone use is most common among well-educated, better-off women, who may be more likely to follow healthy diets and exercise regularly.</p>
        <p>As a result of this uncertainty, doctors have long advised women to weigh their individual circumstances -- their own health and their family histories of cancer, osteoporosis, heart disease and so on -- in making the decision on hormone replacement.</p>
        <p>The main reason women start hormone replacement is to counter the symptoms of menopause, primarily hot flashes that disrupt sleep and cause daytime discomfort and, secondarily, vaginal dryness. There is wide agreement that hormone treatment for a few years, until a woman gets past the hot flash stage, is advantageous, as is hormone replacement for a limited time for women who have had their ovaries removed before natural menopause.</p>
        <p>But estrogen is believed to have a host of other benefits that are especially important now that a woman of 50 can expect to live to 85 or beyond. Unfortunately, these benefits accrue only while taking estrogen; once the hormone is stopped, both the risks and the benefits dissipate.</p>
        <p>On the benefit side, estrogen raises protective HDL cholesterol and its use after menopause has been associated with a 50 percent reduction in heart disease and stroke. Estrogen also prevents the loss of bone density that accelerates at menopause and the hormone may actually increase bone mass after menopause, countering osteoporosis and debilitating fractures, some of which are life-threatening.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, preliminary research suggests, among women who have taken estrogen for many years, the risk of developing Alzheimer's disease is cut in half. Estrogen also reduces the accretion of abdominal fat, which is a risk factor for heart disease and a major source of cosmetic distress for many middle-aged women.</p>
        <p>But because it is not known how much of these benefits derive from the hormone replacement, and how much from lifestyle, many women and their doctors are considering other strategies for coping with menopause.</p>
        <p>Hormone replacement is not the only route to a stronger heart and bones. Wholesome living habits -- a good diet that is low in saturated fat and rich in fruits and vegetables and whole grains, regular weight-bearing exercise, avoiding smoking and maintaining a normal body weight -- are the surest and safest ways to achieve a healthy old age.</p>
        <p>In fact, the American Heart Association calls them ''first-line'' therapies for postmenopausal women at risk of cardiovascular disease. If such an approach fails to control cardiac risk factors like high cholesterol or high blood pressure, there are a number of medications that can help and, according to the heart association, they should be tried before hormone replacement.</p>
        <p>In an editorial accompanying the new JAMA study, Dr. Walter C. Willett, Dr. Graham Colditz and Dr. Meir Stampfer, epidemiologists at the Harvard School of Public Health, point out that ''the commonly held belief that aging routinely requires pharmacological management has unfortunately led to neglect of diet and lifestyle as the primary means to achieve healthy aging.''</p>
        <p>There are also two licensed substitutes for estrogen and more in the research pipeline. These drugs, the ''designer estrogens'' tamoxifen and raloxifene, protect the heart and bones without raising the risk of breast cancer. In fact, tamoxifen has been shown to prevent breast cancer, and early findings suggest that raloxifene may have a similar benefit. But neither drug prevents hot flashes. Instead they increase this problem, and tamoxifen (but not raloxifene) also increases the risk of endometrial cancer. And it is not known what, if any, benefit they have on the brain.</p>
        <p>In addition to raloxifene, which was licensed to counter postmenopausal bone loss, there are other bone-building drugs, the biphosphates, that do not cause hot flashes.</p>
        <p>A growing number of women concerned about the risks of hormone replacement (like a woman's own estrogen, estrogen therapy also increases the risk of blood clots) are turning to so-called natural alternatives. These are foods and herbs that are rich in phytoestrogens, plant-based chemicals that act like weak estrogens. The most popular among them are soy, flaxseed and black cohosh.</p>
        <p>Although it has long been assumed that a diet rich in soy is a major reason for the low rate of breast cancer among Japanese women, recent evidence points to a host of other factors, including differences in the amount, type and effects of the estrogens produced by Japanese women.</p>
        <p>Thus, while phytoestrogens may help to counter menopausal symptoms, it is not known whether they decrease, increase or have no effect on the risk of breast cancer, or any other estrogen-related disease, for that matter. The estrogen in the most widely used hormone replacement products is derived from the serum of pregnant mares.</p>
        <p>Are there other ways around the hormone dilemma? Dr. Malcolm C. Pike and Dr. Ross at U.S.C. have proposed two alternatives to current regimens of estrogen and progestin to limit the effects of progestin on the breast. Instead of a monthly oral use of progestin, they said the hormone could be administered vaginally, which would limit the amount to which breast tissue might be exposed.</p>
        <p>Or, instead of taking the two hormones daily or using progestin for a part of each month to protect the uterus, they suggest taking progestin for 10 days at a time only once every three to four months. Other experts have suggested that taking progestin only twice a year may be frequent enough to prevent endometrial cancer.</p>
        <p>Of course, for women without a uterus, there is no need to take progestin at all because they have no chance of developing endometrial cancer. On estrogen alone, apparently the increase in breast cancer risk is very small.</p>
        <p>What is the bottom line? Several studies now under way may help to clarify both the risks and benefits of postmenopausal hormone replacement, although none are likely to provide the definitive answers that most women seek. But answers may not come in time for the current generation of menopausal women because the kinds of studies required to establish them are very costly, difficult to do and would take decades to complete.</p>
        <p>Until then, every woman facing the hormone decision must evaluate the potential benefits and risks based on her own family and personal medical history, as well as her comfort level with taking or not taking hormones. Does she have a strong family history of heart disease or breast cancer or, perhaps, even Alzheimer's disease? Does she have highly cystic breasts? Has she required one or more breast biopsies? Is she willing to modify her living habits to reduce her risk of life-threatening chronic diseases that are influenced by estrogen?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
