<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stories From the Naked City, And Every Picture Tells One</title>
    <meta content="01WEEG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1173079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Phillips (Auction House)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edidin, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weegee (Usher Fellig) (1899-1968)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feldstein, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EED9173FF932A35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stories From the Naked City, And Every Picture Tells One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER EDIDIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Edidin, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phillips auction house in Manhattan holds sale of photographs of Weegee; Henry Feldstein, dealer who specializes in Weegee's photographs, says that 79 lots, or about 118 photos, were sold for total of $256,300; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 1990's were generous to Manhattan, scouring the island with good fortune and better publicity. And while prosperity is something no sane New Yorker will complain of, many feel nostalgic now and then over the rapid disappearance of an older, more raffish city, a place whose lurking shadows and patchwork dereliction were at least distantly related to the movies, detective novels and tabloid images that taught us what a city was.</p>
        <p>Yesterday afternoon, a crowd gathered to look at, and to buy, some images of that bygone city: cigarette smoke curling over a rakishly tilted fedora, a pistol on the pavement and a body in the gutter, a mysterious blonde with a drink in her hand, Bowery bums and gleaming black sedans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 1990's were generous to Manhattan, scouring the island with good fortune and better publicity. And while prosperity is something no sane New Yorker will complain of, many feel nostalgic now and then over the rapid disappearance of an older, more raffish city, a place whose lurking shadows and patchwork dereliction were at least distantly related to the movies, detective novels and tabloid images that taught us what a city was.</p>
        <p>Yesterday afternoon, a crowd gathered to look at, and to buy, some images of that bygone city: cigarette smoke curling over a rakishly tilted fedora, a pistol on the pavement and a body in the gutter, a mysterious blonde with a drink in her hand, Bowery bums and gleaming black sedans.</p>
        <p>In a modest first for a professionally immodest New Yorker, Phillips auction house in Manhattan held a sale devoted solely to the photographs of Weegee, or Weegee the Famous, as he stamped his work. In roughly two hours, the auctioneer briskly sold off 79 lots, about 118 photos in all, for $256,300.</p>
        <p>Henry Feldstein, a dealer who specializes in Weegee's photographs, said the market for his work had been strong for the past 10 years. Up to $25,000 has been paid at auction for a single print, and prints have gone for more than that in the private market. Indeed, the demand for images of New York from the 30's through the 50's is growing, several dealers said. ''New Yorkers love pictures of old New York, more than people in any town I can think of, except maybe Paris,'' said David Winter, a dealer in photography.</p>
        <p>Before he was Weegee, the artist was Arthur Fellig. Born in 1899, Mr. Fellig was a  seventh-grade dropout who supported himself through a series of part-time jobs and often slept in Pennsylvania Station or Bryant Park. At some point, he fell in with a street photographer who kept a pony as a prop, said Miles Barth, the former curator of archives and collections at the International Center for Photography in New York and the author of ''Weegee's World,'' (Bullfinch, 1997).</p>
        <p>Having found his trade, Mr. Fellig never left it. In the 1920's he became a darkroom technician at Acme News Pictures. It was during this period that he became Weegee. Weegee himself claimed the name was a tribute to his uncanny ability to be first to a crime scene (as if he owned an especially effective Ouija board).</p>
        <p>Acme occasionally pressed Weegee into service to cover a story when no one else was available. His work, like that of the staff photographers, was always anonymous. Weegee, however, wanted to be famous, so in 1935, in the middle of the Great Depression and at a time when freelance news photographer was a virtual oxymoron, he went into business for himself.</p>
        <p>Living in a $17-a-month room across the street from the old police headquarters on Centre Street, Weegee spent 10 years working the graveyard shift, 10 p.m. to 5 a.m., covering the city in search of the drama the tabloids needed for their huge audiences.</p>
        <p>There were so many killings that Weegee became known as the official photographer of Murder Inc.</p>
        <p>He became so famous for this work that, according to the photographer Louis Stettner, slumming society folk would follow Weegee's Chevy around town, hoping for a glimpse of the nocturnal savagery he brought to them in the papers every day.</p>
        <p>Some of Weegee's photographs -- ''The Critic,'' for example, in which an impoverished woman looks contemptuously at two grandes dames about to attend the opera, or ''Their First Murder,'' which shows a small knot of people, staring, with expressions ranging from grief to glee, at a murder victim -- are familiar even to those who are not students of photography.</p>
        <p>Whatever he aimed his Speed Graphic flash camera at, he seemed unable to take a boring picture of the city or its people. Weegee's picures ''clear away the darkness of night,'' said James Sanders, co-author of the recent PBS documentary, by Ric Burns, on the history of New York. ''They are darker and stranger than ordinary jounalism.''</p>
        <p>Weegee, who died in 1968, reached the pinnacle of his celebrity in 1945, when he published ''Naked City,'' a book of his photographs that became a best seller. It was a surprising work, if only because half of it contained neither cops nor robbers, but unsentimental, moving pictures of life on the Lower East Side and the Bowery. Afterward, he vowed never again to shoot a corpse. And he kept his word.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
