<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dvorak Helps Rangers Make Rapid Recovery</title>
    <meta content="01RANG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1173118"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nashville Predators</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Nashville Predators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6D7173FF932A35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dvorak Helps Rangers Make Rapid Recovery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers defeat Nashville Predators, 5-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Radek Dvorak is not the only reason for the turnaround in the Rangers season, but he has been a significant factor.</p>
        <p>Last night at Madison Square Garden, Dvorak scored the first hat trick of his career in a 5-1 victory over the Nashville Predators.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Radek Dvorak is not the only reason for the turnaround in the Rangers season, but he has been a significant factor.</p>
        <p>Last night at Madison Square Garden, Dvorak scored the first hat trick of his career in a 5-1 victory over the Nashville Predators.</p>
        <p>When the Rangers obtained him in a three-way trade at the end of December, they were 12-18-6. They lacked a speedy style; their lines lacked identity and overall cohesiveness.</p>
        <p>And the Rangers seemed destined to miss the Stanley Cup playoffs for a third consecutive season.</p>
        <p>Since Dvorak's arrival, the Rangers have gone 10-4-1, have reached .500 again and have moved back into a qualifying spot in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>Dvorak, a speedy right wing, has formed one-third of the Czech line, which has led the team's January surge.</p>
        <p>Jan Hlavac, the left wing of the line, had three assists. Petr Nedved, who centers them, had one assist.</p>
        <p>Also making a major contribution for the Rangers was goalie Mike Richter, who stopped a penalty shot in the first period to preserve a one-goal lead.</p>
        <p>Mike York and Alexandre Daigle also scored for the Rangers, who ended a two-game losing streak and won for the 10th time in their last 13 games. Dvorak scored the first goal of the game in the first period and the last two in the third period.</p>
        <p>For local fans of Czech hockey, the next nine days could be interesting. The Rangers play three of their next four games against the Devils, beginning tomorrow night at the Garden.</p>
        <p>New Jersey has the best record in the National Hockey League, and the Devils' best line is paced by two Czech aces, Petr Sykora and Patrik Elias.</p>
        <p>If all happen to get on the ice at the same time, the games could be entertaining.</p>
        <p>''It would be fun,'' Dvorak said with a smile, when asked about that sort of matchup. ''Lot of offensive plays. Lot of passing and shooting. Making nice passes. That is the most part of Czech hockey.''</p>
        <p>But there is more to it than that. In recent seasons, the best goalie in the N.H.L. has been Dominik Hasek of the Czech Republic; the most valuable player last season was Jaromir Jagr, another countryman.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Czech Republic has done well in international tournaments and won the gold medal in the Nagano Olympics. Nedved was asked why Czech hockey is so good lately.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing to do in the Czech Republic.'' Nedved said. ''Everybody plays hockey.'' Dvorak, who is 22 years old, is the youngest of the three. Nedved is 28 and Hlavac is 23.</p>
        <p>The Rangers led by 2-0 after one period, even though Nashville had better scoring chances. The best moment of the session was Richter's save on Randy Robitaille's penalty shot.</p>
        <p>It came with the Rangers holding a one-goal lead at 14 minutes 20 seconds of the period. Robitaille took the puck from the Rangers' Theo Fleury and raced the other way until Sylvain Lefebvre pulled him down in the slot, drawing the call from referee Dan Marouelli.</p>
        <p>Robitaille skated in from center ice and Richter moved up off his line to cut down his angle of vision. As Richter moved backward, Robitaille took a low backhand shot, hoping to beat Richter between the skates. But Richter stopped the weak shot, the ninth time in 10 chances he has stopped a penalty shot in the regular season.</p>
        <p>One of them was this season, on Nov. 11 at Washington, against Richard Zednik. Richter has also faced two in the playoffs and has stopped both.</p>
        <p>''You get tired of getting scored on,'' Richter said, ''but not of saving any puck.''</p>
        <p>With Nashville pressing through the third period while trailing by 3-1, Dvorak was able to get behind the defense for breakaway goals at 7:28 and 15:01.</p>
        <p>He has 12 goals for the season, five of them with the Rangers, the others with Florida.</p>
        <p>Dvorak was obtained in a three-corner deal that sent Todd Harvey to San Jose and Mike Vernon to Florida. Rangers Coach John Muckler said: ''It's nice to see him have a big game. He's showed great speed. He showed good hands.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>ALEXANDRE DAIGLE's goal broke a scoreless streak of 19 games. . . . MIKE YORK leads all N.H.L. rookies in goals with 16. . . . TIM TAYLOR, checking center of the Rangers, sprained his right knee when his skate got caught in a rut in the ice. The seriousness won't be known until practice Tuesday. . . . MANNY MALHOTRA, playing recently with Hartford of the American Hockey League, will be called up to the Rangers for the Devils game.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
