<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bids Climb In Western Union Sale</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="709873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WESTERN UNION FINANCIAL SERVICES INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FIRST FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORSTMANN LITTLE &amp; CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FIRST DATA CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, ADAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7D61538F930A3575AC0A962958260" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bids Climb In Western Union Sale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM BRYANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRYANT, ADAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The latest round of a bidding war for Western Union Financial Services, the world's largest money-transfer business, ended yesterday with First Financial Management turning in the highest offer, valued at $1.07 billion.</p>
        <p>The trailing bids were submitted by Forstmann Little &amp; Company, which offered $970 million, and by the First Data Corporation, which said it would pay $660 million, plus assume pension liabilities valued at about $265 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The latest round of a bidding war for Western Union Financial Services, the world's largest money-transfer business, ended yesterday with First Financial Management turning in the highest offer, valued at $1.07 billion.</p>
        <p>The trailing bids were submitted by Forstmann Little &amp; Company, which offered $970 million, and by the First Data Corporation, which said it would pay $660 million, plus assume pension liabilities valued at about $265 million.</p>
        <p>The bids filed yesterday marked the next-to-last step in a drawn-out effort by Western Union's parent company, the New Valley Corporation, to sell its Western Union unit. New Valley, based in Paramus, N.J., has been operating under bankruptcy court protection since March 1993.</p>
        <p>In recent months, bidders have raised the stakes to levels that suggest that New Valley's creditors will most likely be paid the money they are owed by the winning bidder. Time to Alter Offers</p>
        <p>Although First Financial submitted the highest bid yesterday, the future of Western Union is by no means clear. The companies can submit final bids on Sept. 16.</p>
        <p>"I expect First Financial to come away the winner," said Robert V. Bolen, an information services company analyst for J. C. Bradford &amp; Company, a brokerage firm based in Nashville.</p>
        <p>First Financial said it would pay $800 million in cash and assume about $265 million of New Valley's unfinanced pension liabilities.</p>
        <p>The bid by Forstmann Little, a buyout firm based in New York, calls for it to pay $970 million in cash, but the company said it would not assume pension liabilities. Details of Bids</p>
        <p>And First Data's bid is made up of $360 million in cash, plus $300 million in stock. First Data, which is based in Hackensack, N.J., also said it would assume Western Union's unfinanced pension liability, raising the value of its bid to approximately $925 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolen said that First Financial was the bidder with the best ability to smoothly merge Western Union into its own operation and produce the highest return on its investment in the company.</p>
        <p>Atlanta-based First Financial, which offers a range of data and information services like credit-card processing, already has a national telecommuncations network into which Western Union could be integrated.</p>
        <p>The combination of the two companies, said Patrick Thomas, First Financial's chairman, offers "numerous possibilities for offering expanded services through this extensive channel of distribution."</p>
        <p>Western Union has 24,000 agents in 75 countries and is expected to generate revenue this year of more than $550 million. In 1993 it completed 40 million transfers of funds totaling more than $7.8 billion. It has 90 percent of the transfer market.</p>
        <p>First Financial's stock dropped $1.875, to $59.875, in trading on the New York Stock Exchange yesterday. Analysts attributed the drop to concerns that the company was facing competitive pressure from First Data in the merchant credit card-processing business.</p>
        <p>One analyst, Richard Bove of Raymond James &amp; Company, cut his rating on First Financial to "hold" from "buy" because of his concern that a bidding war might prove costly to the company. He said that if First Financial was successful, it might dilute its earnings by about 7 percent.</p>
        <p>Shares of First Data, which also trades on the New York Stock Exchange, closed at $47.50, down 37.5 cents.</p>
        <p>The completion of the bidding process for Western Union would close another chapter in that company's long and difficult history. Founded in 1851, Western Union has made some mistakes over the years, including standing by as telephones, fax machines and computer networks overtook its telegram and telex services.</p>
        <p>With financial problems piling up, it turned to Bennett S. LeBow, the leveraged-buyout specialist, who took over Western Union in 1987 with $500 million in junk bunds issued by Drexel Burnham Lambert.</p>
        <p>Unable to pay the high interest on its debt, the company sold its telex systems to AT&amp;T in 1990 for $180 million. The next year, the company renamed itself New Valley, and in 1993, filed for bankruptcy protection in Newark.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
