<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Panel and Administration Divided Over Anti-Crime Measure</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="476225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEARCH AND SEIZURE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">IFILL, GWEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D9163EF936A1575AC0A967958260" item-length="432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Panel and Administration Divided Over Anti-Crime Measure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GWEN IFILL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">IFILL, GWEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The House Judiciary Committee dealt the Bush Administration a preliminary setback on anticrime legislation today, rejecting a provision that would have permitted greater use of improperly seized evidence in Federal criminal cases.</p>
        <p>In rejecting the White House proposal, which would have allowed courts to use such evidence as long as prosecutors could prove officers had "good faith" reasons for conducting a warrantless search, the House conformed with the Senate version of the bill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The House Judiciary Committee dealt the Bush Administration a preliminary setback on anticrime legislation today, rejecting a provision that would have permitted greater use of improperly seized evidence in Federal criminal cases.</p>
        <p>In rejecting the White House proposal, which would have allowed courts to use such evidence as long as prosecutors could prove officers had "good faith" reasons for conducting a warrantless search, the House conformed with the Senate version of the bill.</p>
        <p>"If you open the door here to illegal evidence, what is going to be the next step?" said Representative Don Edwards, the California Democrat who is chairman of the Judiciary Subcommittee on Civil and Constitutional Rights.</p>
        <p>But the committee departed from the Senate approach on other important issues, like restrictions on the number of successive petitions a court can grant to death row inmates seeking relief. Politics of Debate Assailed</p>
        <p>The Senate largely went along with the Administration's approach, which would limit inmates to one claim in the Federal court system. But the House rejected that alternative on Monday, choosing instead a measure that would provide exceptions in cases in which the inmate did not have access to competent counsel.</p>
        <p>As lawmakers debated the House anticrime bill, several railed against the politics of the crime debate, which they said often has little to do with substance. Representative Charles E. Schumer, a Brooklyn Democrat who is chairman of the Judiciary Subcommittee on Crime and Criminal Justice, said the House bill should do more to prevent crime before it happens.</p>
        <p>The anticrime legislation, said Mr. Schumer, would do little to keep "the proverbial little old lady from getting hit on the head."</p>
        <p>The House measure includes provisions that will ban 16 assault weapons, add new crimes to the list of those punishable by the death penalty and provide new support for local police and community-based anticrime organizations. Many members of the House Judiciary Committee appeared intent on resisting efforts to add state crimes to Federal jurisdiction, as the Senate did in several instances.</p>
        <p>Representative Jack Brooks, the Texas Democrat who is chairman of the House Judiciary Committee, called such efforts "grandstanding gestures that would, in a stroke, usurp local authority for criminal justice matters."</p>
        <p>A pair of amendments in the Senate bill sponsored by Alfonse M. D'Amato, Republican of New York, would allow the Federal Government to intervene in prosecution and sentencing if the crimes involved guns or drugs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
