<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Export-Import Bank: Who Is Helping Whom?</title>
    <meta content="LTR012333" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1423983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Export-Import Bank of US</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Robert M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EED61E31F936A2575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Export-Import Bank: Who Is Helping Whom?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California Space Authority chief executive Robert M Davis letter on September 1 article on credit aid given by Export-Import Bank of US holds satellite buyer's wealth and manufacturer's politics are irrelevant</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The article began with an example of a loan guarantee provided by the bank for the sale of a satellite manufactured in the United States to an international telecommunications company. It also discussed the satellite buyer's wealth and the manufacturer's politics, neither of which I believe to be relevant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The article began with an example of a loan guarantee provided by the bank for the sale of a satellite manufactured in the United States to an international telecommunications company. It also discussed the satellite buyer's wealth and the manufacturer's politics, neither of which I believe to be relevant.</p>
        <p>What is relevant is that an international telecommunications company needed to buy a satellite. That company had a choice: it could buy the satellite from an American manufacturer or from a European one.</p>
        <p>Following a basic principle of business, the telecommunications company compared prices, including the cost of financing. At a purchase price of $150 million to $200 million, a small difference in an interest rate can make or break a deal.</p>
        <p>In this case, the company chose an American manufacturer in part because the Export-Import Bank provided a loan guarantee that allowed the company to get a lower interest rate for the loan.</p>
        <p>It is well known that European satellite manufacturers offer government-provided financing options to their customers. To compete effectively with these European rivals, the nation's satellite manufacturing industry must have available government financing options.</p>
        <p>Loan guarantees are not corporate welfare. As the article states, the default rate on these loans is extremely small -- about 2 percent. Instead, the guarantees are a small and necessary national investment in the nation's satellite manufacturing industry.</p>
        <p>The global satellite industry is facing a steep decline in market demand due to a downturn in the telecommunications industry. It is projected that only two or three of the world's five commercial satellite manufacturers will survive current market conditions. Continued assistance from the Export-Import Bank is required to ensure that at least one of the survivors will remain in the United States.</p>
        <p>ROBERT M. DAVIS  Santa Maria, Calif., Sept. 9</p>
        <p>The writer is president and chief executive of the California Space Authority, a group that promotes space projects in the state.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
