<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conservatives Mount Challenge in Sweden</title>
    <meta content="15SWED$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/15/international/europe/15SWED.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1424028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sweden</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Sweden</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Persson, Goran</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0D71F31F936A2575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conservatives Mount Challenge in Sweden</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Conservatives Mount Challenge in Sweden</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>STOCKHOLM, Sept. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Polls indicate dead heat between ruling center-left government in Sweden and four center-right parties seeking as group to oust it from power; Liberals have surged in polls after offering plan to tighten immigration rules; Prime Min Gorana Persson can take heart from poll showing that more than half of Sweden's people feel they are better off than they were four years ago, but poll also reveals that Swedes are unhappy with quality of public services they receive in return for high taxes they pay; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Social Democrats, rulers of Sweden for all but nine years in the past seven decades, are fighting in a national vote on Sunday to survive the conservative advance that has recently swept across European electoral politics.</p>
        <p>Until a month ago, the center-left government led by Prime Minister Goran Persson, 53, seemed a sure bet to win another four-year term from voters who were telling pollsters they were satisfied with Sweden's economic performance and welfare state protections and were willing to go on paying the highest taxes of any country in Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Social Democrats are fighting in a national vote on Sunday to survive the conservative advance that has recently swept across European electoral politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Social Democrats, rulers of Sweden for all but nine years in the past seven decades, are fighting in a national vote on Sunday to survive the conservative advance that has recently swept across European electoral politics.</p>
        <p>Until a month ago, the center-left government led by Prime Minister Goran Persson, 53, seemed a sure bet to win another four-year term from voters who were telling pollsters they were satisfied with Sweden's economic performance and welfare state protections and were willing to go on paying the highest taxes of any country in Europe.</p>
        <p>But a recent surge by the Liberals, one of the four center-right parties seeking as a group to oust the Social Democrats and their allies, the Green and Left Parties, has made the race a dead heat. The Liberals rose from a predicted 3 percent of the vote to 14 percent after offering a plan to tighten immigration rules, a potent issue across Europe.</p>
        <p>Sweden, with one million of its nine million citizens born elsewhere, is known for its tolerance toward immigrants, and the Liberals sought to distance themselves from antiforeigner parties that have had success in neighboring Denmark and Norway. ''Racists who vote for the Liberal Party must be soft in the head,'' said its leader, Lars Leijonborg.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Leijonborg won sudden favor with a proposal that would require immigrants applying for citizenship to pass a Swedish language test. He argued that far from being anti-immigrant, the plan was intended to integrate foreigners into Swedish life more effectively and to improve their chances for getting better jobs than the marginal ones many of them have now.</p>
        <p>Independent commentators agreed that comparing the Liberals' stance with that of anti-immigrant parties elsewhere in Scandinavia and Europe was mistaken.</p>
        <p>''The issue is dormant here, and we are probably not immune from getting one of these unpleasant parties one day, but so far we haven't,'' said Olof Ruin, a political scientist at the University of Stockholm. He said Sweden's history of supporting liberation movements abroad and giving asylum to the politically outcast made this country an unlikely place for xenophobic politics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leijonborg, 52, is a possible candidate for prime minister if the center-right parties win a majority, though the more likely candidate would be Bo Lundgren, 55, of the Moderates, the largest opposition party. The others from the right are Alf Svensson, 64, of the Christian Democrats and Maud Olofsson, 45, of the rural Center Party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Persson, a former finance minister, has by most accounts increased his stature since taking office in 1996 upon the resignation of a fellow Social Democrat, Ingvar Carlsson, and then winning election to the post in 1998. At home he has used a budget surplus to restore economic stability, dropped interest rates and reduced already low unemployment. Abroad he has drawn attention by directing a smooth-running presidency of the European Union, making Sweden a leader on social issues and backing the American-led campaign against terrorism.</p>
        <p>His re-election strategy, however, may end up having been too complacent. ''He basically ran on the general issue of confidence -- 'I fixed the economy, people are better off than they were, trust me,' '' said Toivo Soren of the Sifo research and consulting firm.</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Soren said, Sifo's polls indicate that more than half of Sweden's people feel they are better off than they were four years ago, but the surveys also reveal unhappiness with the quality of the public services they are taxed so highly to sustain.</p>
        <p>Another uncertainty is whether the Greens can get at least 4 percent of the vote, the threshold required for parliamentary representation. The Social Democrats will probably need the Greens' support to form a new government.</p>
        <p>Denmark, France, Italy, the Netherlands, and Portugal have all elected conservative leaders over the past two years, and in Germany, Gerhard Schröder, a Social Democrat, is in a tight race against a Christian Democrat, Edmund Stoiber, in the election next Sunday.</p>
        <p>The extraordinarily high taxes that Swedes pay are not the incendiary issue they would be in most other societies. ''When we ask people what are the main issues for them, high taxes comes in at No. 9 or 10,'' said Mats Lindgren, managing director of the Kairos Future consulting firm. ''I think you would not find that in any other place in the world, but here tax cuts are not something you can win on.''</p>
        <p>In Sweden, public spending is nearly 60 percent of gross national product, and individuals can end up paying up to 53 percent in taxes on incomes as low as $30,000. Mr. Persson's government lowered that figure from 59 percent two years ago, and he has since devoted his campaign promises not to further cuts but to improving the health and education services the taxes go toward.</p>
        <p>In a final televised debate between the seven party leaders on Friday night, he scoffed at opposition suggestions that some services ought to be privatized. ''I don't want to put the nation's health on the stock exchange,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In what is something of a national characteristic, Swedish elections tend to be exercises in confrontation avoidance, with a high premium on order and decorum. ''Someone once said you can never tell when Swedes are having an argument because they never raise their voices,'' said Mr. Lindgren.</p>
        <p>There are no caterwauling sound trucks in the streets and boulevards of Stockholm, and strict rules bar placards from all but a few public spaces. The debate on Friday night was as well-mannered as a classroom presentation.</p>
        <p>Though Swedes may not get emotional about their elections, they do take them seriously. Voting patterns indicate that more than 80 percent of the country's 6.7 million registered voters will cast ballots on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
