<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campbell Reminds Giants: Tight End Is Receiver, Too</title>
    <meta content="17GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/17/sports/football/17GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1343584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Campbell, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Minnesota Vikings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Minnesota Vikings</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Campbell, Dan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EED6153BF934A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campbell Reminds Giants: Tight End Is Receiver, Too</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Campbell's Plea to Giants: Tight End Is a Receiver, Too</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Nov. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants tight end Dan Campbell hopes to get more active role as pass receiver (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dan Campbell has dreamed about having one of those days, the kind when passes rain down in his direction and every one of them sticks to his hands.</p>
        <p>He finally had one this week, but unfortunately for Campbell, it came in a practice rather than in a packed stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giants' Dan Campbell believes his time will come, when his teammates realize that tight ends can contribute to the team's offense too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dan Campbell has dreamed about having one of those days, the kind when passes rain down in his direction and every one of them sticks to his hands.</p>
        <p>He finally had one this week, but unfortunately for Campbell, it came in a practice rather than in a packed stadium.</p>
        <p>Although the numbers may tell you differently -- he has just three catches this season and had eight all of last season -- Campbell still says that he believes his time will come, that the practice Thursday will carry over into the game. And if his breakout game comes on Monday night against the Minnesota Vikings, he will at least have the element of surprise on his side. When the Giants whipped the Vikings, 41-0, in the National Football Conference championship game last season, they completed 29 passes, with 4 touchdowns coming through the air. But not one ball was caught by a tight end.</p>
        <p>''I've told some people I have this feeling I'm going to have a game like that and people are going to say, 'Where did this guy come from?' '' Campbell said. ''I know it's going to happen sometime, and it won't come out of nowhere.</p>
        <p>''If it happens, it's really going to open up our offense. That's what I want to do, to contribute to make this team better.''</p>
        <p>It is a contribution Giants Coach Jim Fassel and the offensive coordinator, Sean Payton, are not opposed to, but the tight ends are still down the chart, behind receivers Amani Toomer, Joe Jurevicius and Ike Hilliard, as well as running backs Tiki Barber and Greg Comella.</p>
        <p>As Fassel said earlier this week: ''Our tight ends should get more involved, and I want them more involved, but if you have 10 plays, I want Tiki's hands on it, Hilliard's hands on it, Toomer's hands on it. The tight ends might be lower down the food chain.''</p>
        <p>Two years ago, when Campbell was a rookie without a catch, he watched Pete Mitchell catch 58 passes for the Giants. Last season Mitchell grabbed 25, and the downward spiral continued for him outside of New York; he was waived by the Detroit Lions this week. But Mitchell's production surpasses by far what the Giants have received from the position this season. Campbell has 3 catches for 34 yards. Howard Cross caught his first pass of the season last week, a 5-yarder, and the rookie Marcellus Rivers caught a 1-yard touchdown pass in the opener and has not caught a pass since.</p>
        <p>That is where Campbell's week of practice comes in. ''We need to get the tight end more involved,'' Fassel said. ''Dan Campbell really had a pretty good week this week, practiced well, caught the ball more than I've seen him in a long time.''</p>
        <p>Campbell saw a sign of this coming last Sunday in a victory against Arizona, although the statistics and the highlight reel might not show it. His most notable play came on a fourth-and-goal from the 1-yard line in the fourth quarter. The play called for a rollout to the right by Kerry Collins with Campbell slipping off the line as the primary target. But Campbell never got off the line and Collins was shoved out of bounds to end the threat.</p>
        <p>''It is frustrating, but to tell you the truth, I didn't let it eat me up,'' Campbell said. ''I think last week was pretty good. I only had one catch, but the one that I caught, Kerry told me, 'Hey, show up for me over the middle.' He checked downfield, nobody was open, and he saw me come across and he threw me the ball. Even as simple as that is, that builds confidence between us.''</p>
        <p>While Campbell dreams about a six-catch game, the occasional attention is all he is really hoping for right now. ''You know, at times it gets frustrating,'' Campbell said. ''I just want to feel like I'm contributing, especially in the passing game.''</p>
        <p>If the ball is not thrown his way Monday night against Minnesota, Campbell can accept that, too. ''One thing Howard taught me is you do what you're told,'' Campbell said, referring to Cross. ''If they tell you to block a 300-pound defensive end and get Tiki around the corner, you do it. If they want you to clear out for Amani or Ike, you do it. You keep your mouth shut and eventually your time will come. Or it won't and you'll stay in the league 13 years like Howard did. It can't be all that bad.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>People magazine released its sexiest men issue and TIKI BARBER was featured along with his twin, RONDE, a defensive back for the Tampa Bay Buccaneers. Asked if his teammates knew about the designation, Barber said no and quickly hid his copy under his playbook.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
