<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kenya Teaches Its Citizens Lawlessness</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="466679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KENYA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DC1E3EF931A2575BC0A967958260" item-length="407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kenya Teaches Its Citizens Lawlessness</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Kenyans Do Some Soul-Searching After the Rape of 71 Schoolgirls" (front page, July 29), on the events in Meru, is very distressing. Never in my days as a student in a boy's boarding school in Kenya could anything so atrocious have been contemplated. Indeed, such nefarious acts have until now been the sole preserve of the police and paramilitary forces, who have raided women's hostels at the universities while "quelling" student disturbances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Kenyans Do Some Soul-Searching After the Rape of 71 Schoolgirls" (front page, July 29), on the events in Meru, is very distressing. Never in my days as a student in a boy's boarding school in Kenya could anything so atrocious have been contemplated. Indeed, such nefarious acts have until now been the sole preserve of the police and paramilitary forces, who have raided women's hostels at the universities while "quelling" student disturbances.</p>
        <p>Government spokesmen attribute the attack to a lack of discipline by male students. You suggest it was because of a general lack of respect for women. However, these reasons are merely symptomatic of the gradual breakdown of civil society and norms due to state-sponsored repression and violence.</p>
        <p>In the last few years, Kenyans and the world have watched as the Government has undone much of what made Kenya the envy of other African countries. The Government has taught by example that might makes right, unleashing coercive forces on anyone who dares question its policies (most of which have led to disastrous consequences). High-ranking officials have profited from corruption and graft.</p>
        <p>The Government has destroyed the educational system by ignoring merit in the selection of staff and students, and by changing the curriculum at the President's whim.</p>
        <p>Cabinet ministers openly cavort with women other than their wives, enticing them with wealth or threats. Any woman who dares challenge the Government (for example, Prof. Wangari Mathaai, the environmentalist who received the 1990 Africa Leadership Prize) faces insults from the President on down.</p>
        <p>The Kenyan Government must learn that the daily rhetorical venom and physical violence it perpetrates will only breed a culture of violence in the citizenry. This may manifest itself in organized armed struggle, increased violent crime or the type of vile attack that has now occurred.</p>
        <p>It is not enough for the Government to condemn the attack. The issue of women's rights and status needs to be addressed. Similarly, the male students should be brought to book. But these problems will recur and continue unless Kenya resorts to accountable and participatory government as envisaged by the framers of its constitution (who include Thurgood Marshall). Above all, the government and the political hierachy must lead by example. MAINA KIAI Research Fellow, TransAfrica Forum Washington, Aug. 1, 1991</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
