<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Slow Ride on the Meggett Merry-Go-Round</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="746928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW ENGLAND PATRIOTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, MIKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEGGETT, DAVE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3D9143FF936A35750C0A963958260" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Slow Ride on the Meggett Merry-Go-Round</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREEMAN, MIKE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The joke going around the Giants late last week was that Bill Parcells was so desperate to get a former New York player he had agreed to terms with Y. A. Title. Humor is sometimes a way to deal with frustration and the Giants are still somewhat rattled about losing running back David Meggett to the New England Patriots.</p>
        <p>It was one of the biggest free-agent losses for the Giants in years and there is no question it will hurt. What makes it even more painful for the team is that it came at the hands of Parcells, who already has the former Giants Bob Kratch and Myron Guyton. It is no secret that Parcells likes to stick it to his old team whenever he can.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The joke going around the Giants late last week was that Bill Parcells was so desperate to get a former New York player he had agreed to terms with Y. A. Title. Humor is sometimes a way to deal with frustration and the Giants are still somewhat rattled about losing running back David Meggett to the New England Patriots.</p>
        <p>It was one of the biggest free-agent losses for the Giants in years and there is no question it will hurt. What makes it even more painful for the team is that it came at the hands of Parcells, who already has the former Giants Bob Kratch and Myron Guyton. It is no secret that Parcells likes to stick it to his old team whenever he can.</p>
        <p>Yet, as with most things in the N.F.L., which is sometimes like the C.I.A., there is always more to the story than what meets the eye. And that is the case with Meggett. Yes, the Giants made some mistakes, but a more complicated portrait of the situation emerges after discussions with several agents and personnel men around the league who asked not to be identified. The story is not as simple as the Giants losing their 5-foot-7-inch star.</p>
        <p>A combination of factors led to Meggett leaving, and the Giants can only be blamed for a few of them. Ten personnel directors interviewed for this story -- some managing teams with legitimate shots at the Super Bowl, some who have no shot -- would have paid the kind of money for Meggett that the Patriots did if they were in the Giants' shoes.</p>
        <p>The only real mistake New York made was at the beginning. Meggett wanted to start negotiating when the season was over in December, months before he hit the market as an unrestricted free agent. Meggett has told people that if the Giants had come to him then, it might have actually been easier to sign him. All along he had said he wanted to stay in New York -- he had actually just built a house in northern New Jersey. The Giants knew this and thought there was no way he would leave, but the damage might have already been done.</p>
        <p>These days teams must actually recruit their own players because other teams make it sound like their situation is paradise. It's like college all over again. And teams that want to keep their own free agents must put on the full-court press as early as possible. Meggett said that a few calls from Coach Dan Reeves might have helped.</p>
        <p>Instead, the season ended, months went by and there were no talks. Then, mere days before free agency opened, Tony Agnone, Meggett's agent, told the Giants that if talks didn't begin within days then Meggett had no obligation to go back to them should he get an offer. When free agency opened, the Giants contacted him immediately and the negotiating began.</p>
        <p>The Giants took the lead by giving Meggett his first offer, and it would be a pattern throughout the negotiations: once free agency opened the Giants weren't slow, quite the opposite. That was partly because of a change in the way the Giants negotiated, according to players' agents.</p>
        <p>Ernie Accorsi, who built the Cleveland teams in the 1980's that made three A.F.C. title appearances, was brought in to ease the daily burden of negotiating on Giants General Manager George Young, and the new system mostly worked.</p>
        <p>With Young watching closely and supervising everything -- he always had the final say -- agents said Accorsi handled the day-to-day interaction with the agents for Meggett, linebacker Corey Miller and others.</p>
        <p>Things moved swiftly. The Giants made some good opening offers and, basically, were bidding against themselves. The Patriots and Browns didn't get involved until late, with only the Patriots ever making an offer for Meggett. Agents say that Young has become more receptive to giving blockbuster signing bonuses (Miller's $1.5 million bonus is the largest the Giants have ever given), something the Giants have been reluctant to do in the past. Agents gave credit to Young for being more open and to Accorsi for helping him to open up.</p>
        <p>In this new market there are going to be times when a team must overpay to keep their player. Meggett got a five-year deal worth $10 million from the Patriots -- $3 million to sign, meaning next season alone he will earn about $5 million. The Giants offered an average of about $1.8 million and $2 million to sign.</p>
        <p>When the Patriots backed up their truck load of cash to Meggett's door, the Giants had a decision to make. Did they pay a very good player, who doesn't start on offense, $5 million in one season? Running back Rodney Hampton is a free agent at the end of next season. If Meggett received $5 million, what do the Giants give their player who carries the ball 30 times a game? Quarterback Dave Brown is also a free agent. If Meggett got $10 million, what is the franchise quarterback worth?</p>
        <p>In the final days and hours it came down to this for the Giants: with two key free agents on the horizon, a big Meggett paycheck would have thrown everything out of whack.</p>
        <p>While the Giants sometimes focus too much on the future, this wasn't one of those times. In the past, the team has been blamed for moving at a snail's pace. The start was slow in the Meggett derby but soon the Giants were step for step with their speedy little running back.</p>
        <p>In the final analysis, although Meggett is an upper echelon player, he is not the man the Giants should have opened the vault for. But that being said, if the Giants had started talks with Meggett earlier, they would have had a better chance to keep him and maybe for a lower price than what New England eventually paid. Indeed, talk might have been cheap.  PRO FOOTBALL: ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
