<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alabama Penalties Eased; Miami Braces for Its News</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="812655"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOWL GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL COLLEGIATEATHLETIC ASSN (NCAA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LONGMAN, JERE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bowl Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7D91139F932A35751C1A963958260" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alabama Penalties Eased; Miami Braces for Its News</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LONGMAN, JERE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though it is still prohibited from playing in a bowl game this season, the University of Alabama had sanctions against its football team modified yesterday in the first significant reduction of penalties ever levied by the National College Athletic Association's infractions committee.</p>
        <p>A third year of probation was dropped, nine football scholarships were restored and a faculty representative was cleared of charges of unethical conduct by the N.C.A.A. infractions appeals committee. After the announcement, the embattled football coach, Gene Stallings, said that he would return next season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Though it is still prohibited from playing in a bowl game this season, the University of Alabama had sanctions against its football team modified yesterday in the first significant reduction of penalties ever levied by the National College Athletic Association's infractions committee.</p>
        <p>A third year of probation was dropped, nine football scholarships were restored and a faculty representative was cleared of charges of unethical conduct by the N.C.A.A. infractions appeals committee. After the announcement, the embattled football coach, Gene Stallings, said that he would return next season.</p>
        <p>The University of Miami said yesterday that it expected to learn today of sanctions against its football program. If a bowl prohibition is to be assessed, Miami officials have said they want to begin serving the punishment immediately  by skipping a bowl appearance this season.</p>
        <p>Miami was expected to face Notre Dame in the Orange Bowl, but the absence of  the Hurricanes would force a shuffling of pairings and would result in the participation by the Big East co-champion Virginia Tech in a major bowl.</p>
        <p>The five-person N.C.A.A. appellate panel that ruled in the Alabama case is composed of college administrators and independent legal experts. It was formed  in 1993 in response to criticism that the N.C.A.A. infractions committee served  as both judge and jury in meting out penalties for rules violations. The appeals committee has heard five previous cases, granting only minor relief in one case, involving the University of Mississippi.</p>
        <p>Last August, the Crimson Tide was banned from post-season play for a year, placed on probation through the 1997 season and sanctioned with the loss of more than 25 scholarships.</p>
        <p>The violations resulted from improper loans totaling $24,000 that the former  running back Gene Jelks received through two boosters and from the improper signing with an agent by the former defensive back Antonio Langham.</p>
        <p>Stallings and the former Alabama athletic director Hootie Ingram were accused by the N.C.A.A. of improperly investigating and failing to report for months that Langham had signed with an agent following Alabama's victory in the 1993 Sugar Bowl. The victory secured a national championship for the Crimson Tide.</p>
        <p>Alabama was forced to forfeit all of the victories that followed during the 1993 season when Langham participated as an ineligible player. And Tom Jones, the university's former faculty athletics representative, was censured for unethical conduct for allegedly providing false and misleading information regarding the Langham case.</p>
        <p>The penalty assessed against Jones was overturned yesterday because the N.C.A.A. infractions committee never informed Jones that he was being charged with unethical conduct before he was reprimanded. Thus, he was given no opportunity to defend himself, the appeals committee said.</p>
        <p>While the N.C.A.A. is not bound by the due process guarantees of the United States Constitution, rules enforcement "must provide protections that are generally necessary for fairness to exist in these proceedings," said Marshall M. Criser, acting chairman of the appeals committee.</p>
        <p>While president of the University of Florida in the 1980's, Criser was a vocal critic of the sanctioning process of the N.C.A.A. infractions committee.</p>
        <p>"There is now a meaningful appellate procedure, I believe," Criser said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The dropping of the charge against Jones, cooperation by the university and the lack of widespread violations led to the lessening of other sanctions against Alabama, the appeals committee said.</p>
        <p>As for Miami's desire to have a possible bowl sanction imposed immediately, "Our intent from the beginning has been to take this situation, put it in our past as soon as possible and begin a new day," Athletic Director Paul Dee said. "Actually, come Saturday we're going to be looking at the future."</p>
        <p>Miami (8-3) won its last seven games to tie with Virginia Tech for the Big East title.</p>
        <p>"If you take the punishment now, it means you're eligible later," Dee said. "Assuming you're competitive later, you might be eligible for the same payday."</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
