<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theatrical Doings for a Blooming Spring in Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="25SEAS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/25/arts/25SEAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1258055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Academy of Music</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E7D61538F936A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theatrical Doings for a Blooming Spring in Brooklyn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brooklyn Academy of Music announces performance schedules for spring (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Theater productions by Peter Brook and Ingmar Bergman, a tribute to the 20th anniversary of the Mark Morris Dance Group and the United States debut of the Glyndebourne Festival Opera are among the highlights of the 2001 spring season at the Brooklyn Academy of Music.</p>
        <p>The season, which runs from Jan. 12 through June 21, begins with the Sydney Theater Company's presentation of ''The White Devil,'' John Webster's 1612 tale of betrayal and intrigue in a 17th-century Italian court. Adapted and staged by the Australian director Gale Edwards, the production was given its premiere during the Sydney 2000 Olympics Arts Festival in August.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Theater productions by Peter Brook and Ingmar Bergman, a tribute to the 20th anniversary of the Mark Morris Dance Group and the United States debut of the Glyndebourne Festival Opera are among the highlights of the 2001 spring season at the Brooklyn Academy of Music.</p>
        <p>The season, which runs from Jan. 12 through June 21, begins with the Sydney Theater Company's presentation of ''The White Devil,'' John Webster's 1612 tale of betrayal and intrigue in a 17th-century Italian court. Adapted and staged by the Australian director Gale Edwards, the production was given its premiere during the Sydney 2000 Olympics Arts Festival in August.</p>
        <p>The Glyndebourne Festival Opera makes its United States debut with Nikolaus Lehnoff's staging of Janacek's ''Makropulos Case.'' The German soprano Anja Silja performs the lead role of Emilia Marty, an alluring diva who has lived for 337 years by drinking a magic elixir. David Atherton conducts the ensemble and the Brooklyn Philharmonic Orchestra in performances, Feb. 11 through 17.</p>
        <p>Beginning on March 6 the Mark Morris Dance Group celebrates its 20th season with five programs totaling 15 works, including the New York premieres of Mr. Morris's setting of the Virgil Thompson opera ''Four Saints in Three Acts'' and ''Sang-Froid,'' a piece for nine dancers set to music by Chopin. The three-week season is bolstered by films, Brooklyn Academy of Music dialogues and an education program for public school students.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Miller's setting of Bach's ''St. Matthew Passion'' recalls its 1997 appearance with performances from April 8 through 14. The stripped-down production, performed in casual dress, features the soprano Heidi Grant Murphy and the New York Collegium Orchestra, led by Paul Goodwin.</p>
        <p>The director Peter Brook acknowledges 30 years as a Brooklyn Academy artist with a new interpretation of ''Hamlet,'' his first Shakespeare production in the United States since ''A Midsummer Night's Dream'' in 1971 and his first exploration of ''Hamlet'' since 1955. Adapted and directed by Mr. Brook, the work will feature Adrian Lester in the title role and Natasha Parry as Gertrude.</p>
        <p>As part of ''France Moves,'' a citywide festival celebrating French contemporary dance, Philippe Decoufle and Decoufle et Complices Associes will make their United States debut in ''Shazam!,'' a spectacle centered on multiple videos that project images of live dancing on stage. The 90-minute piece evolved from a commission for the 50th Cannes International Film Festival and runs from April 25 through 29. The festival will also feature the United States premiere of ''Le Jardin Io Io Ito Ito,'' a multimedia work by the choreographers Jose Montalvo and Dominique Hervieu, May 2 through 5.</p>
        <p>Four years after making its United States debut in Handel's ''Amadigi,'' the Opera Theater Company of Ireland returns with Handel's rarely heard ''Rodelinda.'' First performed in 1725, the opera tells of intrigue and power struggles in late seventh-century Lombardy. The soprano Helen Williams is to sing the title role, accompanied by the New York Collegium Orchestra, under the conductor and harpsichordist Laurence Cummings.</p>
        <p>''DanceAfrica'' returns to the Brooklyn Academy for its 24th season with the United States debut of the Ndere Troupe of Uganda, performing ritual dances and indigenous music. The program also features the New York-based Forces of Nature and Sabar Ak Ru Afriq, the Brooklyn troupe that celebrates urban African diaspora culture through dance. Performances run from May 25 through 27.</p>
        <p>On June 5 through 9, Mikhail Baryshnikov and his White Oak Dance Project will present ''Past Forward,'' a multimedia performance featuring reconstructed and new works by Judson Dance Theater choreographers like Yvonne Rainer, David Gordon and Trisha Brown. Mr. Baryshnikov dances and narrates the work.</p>
        <p>The season closes with Ingmar Bergman, in his ninth Brooklyn Academy appearance, directing the United States premiere production of Strindberg's ''Ghost Sonata.'' Performed by the Royal Dramatic Theater of Sweden, the production -- Mr. Bergman's fourth rendition of this macabre chamber play -- incorporates ideas regarding the work that he has explored throughout his 60-year career. The cast is led by longtime Dramaten actors Erland Josephson, Jan Malmsjo and Elin Klinga. Performances run from June 20 through 24.</p>
        <p>The academy's spring season is sponsored by the Philip Morris Companies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
