<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Spy Who Loved Me</title>
    <meta content="20JAMESSW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/20/books/20JAMESSW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1590934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fielding, Helen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Olivia Joules and the Overactive Imagination (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Fielding, Helen</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Olivia Joules and the Overactive Imagination (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEEDD1430F933A15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Spy Who Loved Me</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Olivia Joules and the Overactive Imagination': The Spy Who Loved Me</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Caryn James</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James reviews book Olivia Joules and the Overactive Imagination by Helen Fielding (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OLIVIA JOULES</p>
        <p>AND THE OVERACTIVE</p>
        <p>IMAGINATION</p>
        <p>By Helen Fielding.</p>
        <p>306 pp. Viking. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Helen Fielding's novel, a Bridget Jones clone (but thinner) falls for a guy who might be a terrorist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OLIVIA JOULES</p>
        <p>AND THE OVERACTIVE</p>
        <p>IMAGINATION</p>
        <p>By Helen Fielding.</p>
        <p>306 pp. Viking. $24.95.</p>
        <p>BRIDGET JONES lived through 9/11 and emerged a changed person: she has morphed into Olivia Joules, a style reporter who stumbles into counterterrorism. Helen Fielding has changed, too. In ''Olivia Joules and the Overactive Imagination,'' she trades in Jane Austen for Austin Powers as a touchstone -- a deal as shaky as it sounds.</p>
        <p>Keeping the essential personality from ''Bridget Jones's Diary,'' Fielding drops the new girl into a more adventurous setting and genre. Like Bridget, Olivia is big on reinvention. Born plain Rachel Pixley in the village of Worksop, she renamed herself, not too subtly, after the unit of kinetic energy, the joule. She has a tendency toward professional disaster (her big story about locusts in Sudan turned out to be about two grasshoppers) and a Bridget-like compulsion to list her Rules for Living -- like ''Don't expect the world to be safe or life to be fair'' and the crucial ''Never change haircut or color before an important event.'' Even her differences from Bridget reflect the same obsessions. Olivia decided years ago to lose weight; she's still amazed at how much nicer people are to her now that she's a slim blonde.</p>
        <p>When Olivia is sent to Miami to cover the debut of a supermodel's face cream, she finds herself attracted to the exotic Pierre Feramo, despite her suspicion that he belongs to Al Qaeda. Pierre sort of resembles Osama bin Laden -- her best friend calls him Osama bin Feramo -- but he's generous with flattery and Cristal, and Olivia simply can't decide. Let's just say he's no Mr. Darcy.</p>
        <p>When a cruise ship explodes in Miami, killing hundreds of passengers, Olivia sets out to discover the truth about Feramo. She follows him to Los Angeles, dines with him in Honduras, has a rendezvous with him in Sudan. She kisses a handsome stranger, finds drugs planted in her hotel room and is confronted by a hooded man while scuba diving -- and the farther she travels from the familiar world of style reporting, the weaker the novel becomes. When Olivia crosses paths with the C.I.A. and M.I.6, the book really falls apart.</p>
        <p>This is the first of Fielding's four novels to abandon the first-person voice, but that distance from Olivia isn't the main reason she seems so lifeless. Using terrorism to drive the plot of a flighty novel isn't the problem either; Jon Stewart and David Letterman have already mastered fun-with-Osama jokes. No, the problem is Fielding's discomfort with the genre she's sending up. She's clearly spoofing the clichés of spydom, and there are some inspired touches (like a Wonderbra with a dagger hidden in the underwire). But while Fielding can be a dazzling social observer -- and she displays enough of her old wit to send readers flying through the first, better, half of ''Olivia Joules'' -- her prose is merely functional. Here the flat tone makes the book leaden where it should be playfully tongue-in-cheek, as if instead of mocking the spy genre's clichés Fielding were simply embracing them.</p>
        <p>Bridget, despite her cartoonish exaggeration, is vivid enough to live beyond the pages of a novel. You know she'd be horrified by that silly little Renée Zellweger, deliberately gaining weight to play her in the movies. Olivia is an all-too-calculated creation.</p>
        <p>Fielding has said she abandoned a multigenerational saga to write the escapist ''Olivia Joules,'' and while we can be grateful to have dodged that epic, success seems to have brought her a new malady: fear of literary ambition. That's quite unnecessary. Her accomplished first novel, ''Cause Celeb,'' skewers celebrity charities and touchingly depicts famine in Africa. Her even better story, ''Luckybitch'' (published in an anthology edited by Nick Hornby, ''Speaking With the Angel''), is written in the voice of an old woman, alone and drinking too much; she's Bridget Jones's nightmare future self. The story is moving, genuine and not a bit boring -- nothing like ''Olivia Joules.''</p>
        <p>Caryn James is a critic for the Arts &amp; Leisure section of The Times and the author of ''Glorie,'' a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Caryn James is a critic for the Arts &amp; Leisure section of The Times and the author of ''Glorie,'' a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
