<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'A Tinkling Piano in the Next Apartment'</title>
    <meta content="20NOIS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/20/nyregion/thecity/20nois.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1590720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK OBSERVED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6DF1439F933A15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1249" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'A Tinkling Piano in the Next Apartment'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'A Tinkling Piano in the Next Apartment'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kevin Baker New York Observed essay reminisces about old sounds of city and describes ones he hears now from his apartment window; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAYOR BLOOMBERG'S campaign to crack down on excessive noise in the city will no doubt meet almost universal acclaim. It is, after all, the rare New Yorker who has not been driven nearly to homicide by one or another completely unnecessary, inconsiderate and brain-rattling noise, usually in the middle of the night.</p>
        <p>In my neighborhood on the Upper West Side, the major culprits include semi-trailers blasting their air horns as they hurtle up Amsterdam Avenue, apparently trying to break the sound barrier (note to the nation's truckers: New York is not a movie set; people actually live here), or that first, dreaded blast of music that heralds what my wife and I have come to call, Three A.M. Salsa Party (pre-empted occasionally by Two A.M. Hip-Hop Jam or Four A.M. Cruisin' to the Oldies).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even in New York, there are the distant, human sounds that drop grace notes into city life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAYOR BLOOMBERG'S campaign to crack down on excessive noise in the city will no doubt meet almost universal acclaim. It is, after all, the rare New Yorker who has not been driven nearly to homicide by one or another completely unnecessary, inconsiderate and brain-rattling noise, usually in the middle of the night.</p>
        <p>In my neighborhood on the Upper West Side, the major culprits include semi-trailers blasting their air horns as they hurtle up Amsterdam Avenue, apparently trying to break the sound barrier (note to the nation's truckers: New York is not a movie set; people actually live here), or that first, dreaded blast of music that heralds what my wife and I have come to call, Three A.M. Salsa Party (pre-empted occasionally by Two A.M. Hip-Hop Jam or Four A.M. Cruisin' to the Oldies).</p>
        <p>Believe it or not, though, New York is actually a much quieter city than it was, say, 100 years ago. Try to imagine tens of thousands of iron-rimmed wagon wheels rattling over cobblestone streets, or a steam engine on that elevated rail just outside the window.</p>
        <p>And what about those noises that we love? They do exist, although I imagine that New Yorkers' taste in sound is as subjective as their taste in everything else.</p>
        <p>One rule of thumb, I suspect, is that when it comes to city noises, distance lends enchantment. Much as I loathe the truck grand prix a few yards from my door, I am always transported by the distant wail of truck brakes, somewhere out in the night. There is something achingly, primordially lonely about that sound. Then there is the faint twang of the subway rails as a train starts to approach the station, still several blocks away. It is a small sound, but the very soul of anticipation -- much better than the actual clamorous arrival of the Broadway local.</p>
        <p>Even better is the rumble of the Metro-North trains as they emerge from under Park Avenue, which, on particularly still nights, we can hear clear across town. This is an atavistic, rural noise, one that feels as if it should have been banished from the city long ago, much like the bells of the beautiful, Romanesque church of St. Michael's, sounding every half-hour, just across the street from my apartment building.</p>
        <p>I feel privileged to be able to hear such sounds still. They make you cognizant of another urban noise that has vanished, although up to a generation ago it was nearly ubiquitous. That is the human voice of the street vendor, hawking his wares. No doubt, New Yorkers of a certain age can still remember the used-clothes collector, singing out his mournful cry, ''I cash clothes!'' as he shambled from neighborhood to neighborhood, laden with used dresses, suits, hats. Not to mention the cries of all the newsies, pushcart peddlers and knife sharpeners, or the fish, greens, sweet-potato, ice and even coal sellers of Harlem, who specialized in setting their own sly lyrics to the popular tunes of the 30's and 40's:</p>
        <p>A tisket, a tasket</p>
        <p>I sell fish by the basket</p>
        <p>And if you folks don't buy some fish</p>
        <p>I'm gonna put you in a casket</p>
        <p>THE songs of the street vendors must have all but defined the tempo of our city throughout most of its history, perhaps especially in the 19th century, when they were everywhere, aggressively peddling oysters, lemonade, cabbages, matches, handy black funeral veils or pears in syrup served in little clay dishes. Then there were the hot-corn girls, pre-Civil War New York's twisted, virgin-whore fantasy. These were teenage girls, always barefoot, wearing trademark calico shawls, and selling ears of fresh-roasted corn -- and sometimes themselves. They sang plucky verses at the passing men who pitied them, and wanted to protect them, or to buy them:</p>
        <p>Hot corn! Hot corn!</p>
        <p>Here's your lily-white corn!</p>
        <p>All you that's got money</p>
        <p>Poor me that's got none</p>
        <p>Come buy my lily-white hot corn</p>
        <p>And let me go home!</p>
        <p>As sad and sordid as the existence of the hot-corn girls was, their cries could evoke a nostalgia that is one of the greatest rewards of living in a large city. In 1854, even so strait-laced a puritan as the Wall Street lawyer George Templeton Strong wrote in his diaries ''of sultry nights in August or early September when one has walked through close, unfragrant air and flooding moonlight and crowds, in Broadway or the Bowery, and heard the cry [of the hot-corn girls] rising at every corner, or has been lulled to sleep by its mournful cadence in the distance as he lay under only a sheet and wondered if tomorrow would be cooler.''</p>
        <p>It is these human noises that ultimately convey the romance of city life. What New Yorker doesn't understand the essentially urban experience inherent in, say, the lyrics of that sublime, Holt Marvel-Jack Strachey-Harry Link standard, ''These Foolish Things'':</p>
        <p>A tinkling piano in the next apartment,</p>
        <p>Those stumbling words that told you what my heart meant</p>
        <p>These foolish things remind me of you</p>
        <p>Somewhere down the alley that runs behind our back apartment, there is a voice teacher who gives lessons in his home, and in the afternoon one might catch a gorgeous line of opera or part of a classic show tune. Every year just before Christmas, the voice teacher has his students over for a party, and my wife and I will sit by the window in the evening, listening to the buzz of party conversation, then the sound of students and teacher singing together around the piano.</p>
        <p>We have no way of knowing just where the music is coming from; there are four or five apartment houses down the alley. Nor would we ever want to be invited, or even to look in on the party. It would only be bound to disappoint. It's much better this way -- evoking at once all of the best holiday parties we have ever been to, or imagined, or seen in the movies, just by ear alone.</p>
        <p>Or take the space where I am writing this. It is a little room, which faces on the fifth floor of the small inner courtyard of my building. It is a good space for a writer. There is not much to see -- only brick walls, a small patch of sky and other windows with the shades perpetually drawn for privacy.</p>
        <p>But in the evening I can hear a whole hive of activity, all around me. People preparing or clearing away dinner, scraping plates or lighting stoves. Calling to children to take their baths, or do their homework. Laughing, and speaking in English, Spanish, Mandarin, Creole French and other tongues. Somewhere a man is ringing small bells while he chants Buddhist prayers.</p>
        <p>This is, I think, the great, redeeming quality of city life, what makes it worthwhile living here, despite all the thoughtless depredations of bikers and truckers, and radio blasters. It is the rare opportunity to both live in the world and yet remain as distant from it as one needs to be at any given moment. The chance to listen, and yet be still.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK OBSERVED Kevin Baker, the author, most recently, of ''Paradise Alley,'' is working on his third historical novel, ''Strivers Row,'' which is set in Harlem in the 1940's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Kevin Baker, the author, most recently, of ''Paradise Alley,'' is working on his third historical novel, ''Strivers Row,'' which is set in Harlem in the 1940's.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
