<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Diplomacy Resumed by U.S. and Iraq</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="411377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="STANDOFF IN THE GULF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYLER, PATRICK E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DA1530F934A15751C1A966958260" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Diplomacy Resumed by U.S. and Iraq</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TYLER, PATRICK E</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq, Dec. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a week of silence, diplomatic contacts have resumed between the senior United States envoy in Baghdad and Iraqi officials, but no progress has been reported toward resolving the Persian Gulf crisis.</p>
        <p>Meeting ith Western reporters, the American envoy, Joseph C. Wilson 4th, the deputy chief of mission, said, "I have not given up hope on the diplomatic process."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a week of silence, diplomatic contacts have resumed between the senior United States envoy in Baghdad and Iraqi officials, but no progress has been reported toward resolving the Persian Gulf crisis.</p>
        <p>Meeting ith Western reporters, the American envoy, Joseph C. Wilson 4th, the deputy chief of mission, said, "I have not given up hope on the diplomatic process."</p>
        <p>Secret consultations continued today in the Iraqi capital involving senior Iraqi officials and 20 to 25 Iraqi Ambassadors who have been summoned from Western and other foreign capitals before the Jan. 15 deadline in the United Nations Security Council resolution demanding that Iraq withdraw its occupation army from Kuwait or face eviction by force.</p>
        <p>Foreign Ministry officials have declined to comment on the consultations and have told foreign journalists that they would not be available for the rest of the week. Western officials said they regarded the gathering as an extraordinary session that could signal a new diplomatic initiative by Iraq, probably after the New Year.  Some 'Room for Diplomacy'</p>
        <p>A United States official here said he could not confirm "at this point" an Israeli newspaper report that American and Iraqi officials had discussed or agreed on a date for Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d to meet in Baghdad with President Saddam Hussein as part of an effort to avert war.</p>
        <p>The official, whose comments on diplomatic progress were generally positive yet also ambiguous, said, "What you should take from this is that so long as there is some sort of diplomacy to be conducted we are going to conduct it."</p>
        <p>"I think and I hope there is some more room for diplomacy," the official said. Later the official said, "Obviously we're not sitting on our hands here."</p>
        <p>The United States and Iraq remain deadlocked over dates for an exchange of high-level visits proposed by President Bush in an attempt to avert war over Iraq's occupation of Kuwait.  Hints of Compromise Dates</p>
        <p>The United States has insisted that it will send Mr. Baker to Baghdad no later than Jan. 3, but Mr. Hussein said he was not available until Jan. 12, three days before the deadline. The White House has said that date is unacceptable because it is too close to the Jan. 15 deadline and thus the Iraqis would be able to say after such a meeting that they had not had enough time to consider any American offer or to pull out of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>Officials in Washington and Baghdad have hinted at compromise dates between Jan. 5-8 for the Baker meeting, but the United States official here discouraged any suggestion that the Bush Administration had relented on its position that the Baker meeting must occur no later than Jan. 3.</p>
        <p>The Israeli newspaper report said a date of Jan. 9 was agreed on as a date for Mr. Baker's visit. But a State Department spokesman in Washington denied the report. Western officials here said a meeting as late as Jan. 9 was plausible, because many Western governments estimate that Iraq could withdraw its forces in the five to six days remaining before the deadline after such a meeting took place.</p>
        <p>Western embassies here said they had noted the strong resurgence of rumors that Mr. Hussein's Arab Baath Socialist Party is making plans to set off national demonstrations about Jan. 10 that would create the impression that the Iraqi people would rather pull out of Kuwait than go to war. Avoiding Look of Stubbornness</p>
        <p>There have been similar suggestions that Mr. Hussein would submit the question of a pullout to his National Assembly, a consultative body that is controlled by Mr. Hussein's one-party apparatus.</p>
        <p>As with all rumors in the Iraqi capital, Western diplomats say it is difficult to determine whether the current rumor has official sanction or reflects popular sentiment.</p>
        <p>The resumption of diplomatic contacts between the United States Embassy and the Iraqi Foreign Ministry might have been compelled by leaders on both sides who wished to avoid any accusations of stubbornness in working out a compromise on the dates.</p>
        <p>As recently as Monday, the United States official had made a point of telling reporters here that there had been no diplomatic contacts between the United States Embassy and the Iraqi Government for a week.  'You Know Our Position'</p>
        <p>In the last meeting between Mr. Wilson and Nizar Hamdoon, an undersecretary of the Iraqi Foreign Ministry, Mr. Wilson read from an aide memoire that recounted the history of the dispute over the dates, but proposed no compromise, while Mr. Hamdoon listened and then said, "You know our position," Western officials said.</p>
        <p>Today, a United States official said he meant to convey a new impression about the resumption of diplomatic contacts. To demonstrate that contacts had resumed, the official picked up the telephone and dialed the Foreign Ministry. It is believed from his comments on the telephone that he spoke to Mr. Hamdoon, who is a former Ambassador to Washington.</p>
        <p>Also today, Mr. Wilson made arrangements to send a bottle of California wine to Iraq's Foreign Minister, Tariq Aziz, as a Christmas gift. Mr. Aziz is a Christian.</p>
        <p>On Christmas Day, Mr. Wilson received a cake in the shape of a Yule log from Mr. Hussein as well as a floral arrangement of purple and lavender zinnias.  Reports on U.S. Readiness</p>
        <p>In an editorial on Tuesday, the state-controlled Baghdad Observer posed the question of whether "time is running out," for diplomacy and then replied, "Who says so?"</p>
        <p>"Peace can always be saved but all it needs is courage," the newspaper said, insisting that Mr. Hussein has the right to chose his own date in January to receive Mr. Baker.</p>
        <p>"This is the idea," the editorial said, "but if the U.S. wants to keep insisting on its own terms, then it will be closing the door to peace."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hussein and other Iraqi officials continued their warnings about the consequences of war in the region, but thus far there has been no official reaction to reports from Washington that the dominant view of the United States military leadership is that American forces in Saudi Arabia might not be prepared for offensive action by mid-January.</p>
        <p>Still, some Iraqi officials have greeted that assessment with skepticism, pointing out that United States and allied air forces in the Persian Gulf have been prepared for some time to carry out offensive operations against Iraq's armed forces.</p>
        <p>"I don't believe this report," said an Iraqi Government official. "They could send 1,000 airplanes tomorrow to bomb us."  STANDOFF IN THE GULF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
