<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Classical Pirates Made New In a Swashbuckling Revival</title>
    <meta content="08KIRO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19970409T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="DANCE REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="921334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E1D81F3DF93BA35757C0A961958260" item-length="1044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Classical Pirates Made New In a Swashbuckling Revival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, April 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews performance by Boston Ballet at Wang Center for the Performing Arts in Boston, in first American production of The Pirate; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Experiment in dance is not necessarily synonymous with the avant-garde, as the Boston Ballet is demonstrating with surprising success at the Wang Center for the Performing Arts here in the first American production of ''The Pirate,'' otherwise known as ''Le Corsaire,'' a 19th-century French-Russian ballet.</p>
        <p>It was a risk to present a distinctly old-fashioned work that even the Kirov Ballet from Leningrad made persuasive in New York in 1989 only through brilliant classical dancing in a few set passages of Marius Petipa's choreography.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Experiment in dance is not necessarily synonymous with the avant-garde, as the Boston Ballet is demonstrating with surprising success at the Wang Center for the Performing Arts here in the first American production of ''The Pirate,'' otherwise known as ''Le Corsaire,'' a 19th-century French-Russian ballet.</p>
        <p>It was a risk to present a distinctly old-fashioned work that even the Kirov Ballet from Leningrad made persuasive in New York in 1989 only through brilliant classical dancing in a few set passages of Marius Petipa's choreography.</p>
        <p>Sensing the need for local relevance, the Boston Ballet linked the work's pirate-and-shipwreck theme last weekend to pre-performance lectures by Barry Clifford and Kenneth Kinkor, two historians involved in the salvaging of the Whydah, a pirate ship that sank off Cape Cod in 1717.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, this three-act ''Corsaire,'' based on the version for the Bolshoi Ballet that Konstantin Sergeyev (a former Kirov director) staged shortly before his death in 1992, works on its own extravagant terms.</p>
        <p>It is true that unlike Petipa's ''Sleeping Beauty'' and even his ''Bayadere,'' the Orientalist fantasy it most resembles, ''Le Corsaire'' has come down over the century with little unity in its tale-telling or overall style. A colorful pantomime ballet with a typical Romantic story about passionate pirates on the bounding main rescuing harem captives has turned into a hodgepodge of music and choreographic interpolations.</p>
        <p>Petipa himself staged five versions of the 1856 original by Joseph Mazilier. By the final 1899 Petipa version, the score had five composers; Russian producers have since modified the story line repeatedly.</p>
        <p>Plot is the least believable aspect of the Boston Ballet version simply because it has become so vestigial. The end result, however, is a credible pretext for classical dancing in a swiftly paced spectacle.</p>
        <p>How impressively the Boston Ballet has raised the standard of technique was clear on Saturday night in a cast led by Larissa Ponomarenko as Medora, a Greek maiden, and by Viktor Plotnikov as Conrad, the pirate who rescues her from a pasha and a slave dealer. Even more crucial was the choreography that Rudolf Nureyev and Margot Fonteyn made their signature piece as the ''Corsaire'' pas de deux. Patrick Armand, the Boston Ballet's top virtuoso, proved true to spectacular form here.</p>
        <p>Alas, thanks to Western ignorance of ballets like ''Le Corsaire,'' few knew until recently that this famous excerpt was not originally a pas de deux but a pas de trois, and that the male choreography was not by Petipa but by Soviet choreographers, chiefly Vakhtang Chabukiani.</p>
        <p>Now, as in the latest Kirov version, it is clear that the Nureyev role is danced not by Medora's lover, the pirate chief, but by Ali, his servant, while Conrad alternates with him in partnering the ballerina.</p>
        <p>But unlike the Kirov staging, based on a 1955 production by Pyotr Gusev, the Boston Ballet version plays down dramatic relationships. In the Kirov, Medora made her class status clear. Ali was obsequious and Medora reached longingly toward Conrad.</p>
        <p>Not so with Mr. Armand's assertive bravura, presented for its showpiece value. The same could be seen with three other pure-dance displays.</p>
        <p>One came from Pollyana Ribeiro as Gulnare, Medora's fellow harem slave, now relegated to Act III, where she led the classical divertissement ''Jardin Anime'' with a radiant combination of classical precision and charm. Other versions would have her dancing in Act I in the duet ''Pas d'Esclave.'' But here it was performed by Jennifer Gelfand, once a prodigy as a virtuoso and now a mature stylish dancer. Her partner was the athletically exuberant Reagan Messer. He kept to classical form, but he was also allowed to keep a high-flying step that he invented.</p>
        <p>The green light came from Natalya Dudinskaya, a former Kirov star and Sergeyev's widow. She has staged the production with Vadim Desnitsky, Sergeyev's assistant; Sergei Berezhnoi, a ballet master with the Boston Ballet, and Anna-Marie Holmes. Now associate director, Ms. Holmes will succeed Bruce Marks as artistic director of the Boston Ballet in July.</p>
        <p>For ''Le Corsaire,'' she has made major decisions about cutting mime scenes and part of Acts I and III. This has left the story, loosely based on Byron's poem ''The Corsair,'' unintelligible to some in the audience,  who saw the ballet as little more than a string of dances. Yet Ms. Holmes has correctly seen the Petipa set pieces as a valuable school for classical dancing.</p>
        <p>Good work in this respect came in Act III from the three odalisques (Christina Elida Salerno, Tatyana Jouravel and Ayuko Hirato) as well as the corps in the garden scene. The tutus here were the most garish of Irina Tibilova's designs, whose sets and costumes, purchased from the Bolshoi, were tastefully muted elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Regrettably, the garden divertissement is no longer a vision scene in which a pasha dreams that his garden has come to life. Instead Medora urges all to dance to distract the pasha from the pirates in disguise, who have come to rescue her.</p>
        <p>Other changes are more convincing. A spectacular shipwreck has been restored to the end, leaving Medora and Conrad embracing on a rock. The Soviet-era choreography is sharply defined, especially a Sergeyev duet in Act II for Ms. Ponomarenko and Mr. Plotnikov. They are elegant dancers who need only more consistency in their classical technique.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ponomarenko was utterly charming in a character solo in Act II, restored here by Ms. Dudinskaya. Arriving at the pirate lair, Medora wears a little sailor's suit and heeled shoes, mimes her love for dance and swaggers like a drum majorette. Birbanto, Conrad's lieutenant, was danced with gusto by Carlos Santos, although he often danced without explanation. What this fine production needs is a little more connective tissue. Jonathan McPhee conducted the patchwork score with the musical equivalent of a straight face.</p>
        <p>''Le Corsaire'' will be performed again tomorrow through Sunday afternoon.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 9, 1997, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption yesterday with a review of the Boston Ballet's performance of ''Le Corsaire'' on Saturday misspelled the surname of one dancer. She is Larissa Ponomarenko, not Ponomarkeno.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 9, 1997, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption yesterday with a review of the Boston Ballet's performance of ''Le Corsaire'' on Saturday misspelled the surname of one dancer. She is Larissa Ponomarenko, not Ponomarkeno.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
