<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economy &amp; Business; Big 3 Automakers Are Likely to Swerve Into the Slow Lane</title>
    <meta content="16AUTO$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Outlook" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/16/business/businessspecial/16AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1449186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">DaimlerChrysler AG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Hyundai Motor Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DB163DF935A25751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economy &amp; Business; Big 3 Automakers Are Likely to Swerve Into the Slow Lane</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Big 3 Automakers Are Likely to Swerve Into the Slow Lane</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Automobile makers brace for slump in 2003 in wake of booming sales of recent years; fear market saturation; foreign automakers continue to push more vehicles into United States; General Motors, Ford Motor and DaimlerChrysler face higher operating expenses in addition to probable fall in sales; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HEADING into this year, a question hung over the Motor City: Could the boom-time sales pace of recent years, fueled by the mighty growth of sport utilities, possibly continue?</p>
        <p>The answer for much of 2002 was a resounding yes. So now analysts are asking the same question about 2003. And this time even auto executives are bracing for a slump.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most agree that the bulk of the expected sales diminishment in 2003 will come largely from the hide of the Big Three.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HEADING into this year, a question hung over the Motor City: Could the boom-time sales pace of recent years, fueled by the mighty growth of sport utilities, possibly continue?</p>
        <p>The answer for much of 2002 was a resounding yes. So now analysts are asking the same question about 2003. And this time even auto executives are bracing for a slump.</p>
        <p>''Consumers are evidently responding to a sluggish economy,'' said Scott Sprinzen, a credit analyst for Standard &amp; Poor's, in a recent report that suggested that a slump evident in recent months would be likely to continue into next year. ''After a string of exceptionally good sales years, the market is evidently saturated.''</p>
        <p>Last year, the terrorist attacks emptied car lots of potential buyers until General Motors refilled them quickly with its ''Keep America Rolling'' advertising and incentive campaign, which included offers of interest-free financing. The Ford Motor Company and the Chrysler Group, a unit of DaimlerChrysler, quickly followed suit, and the ensuing price war made October 2001 the best month in industry history. By the end of last year, analysts worried that buoyant sales could not possibly continue in balky economic conditions and with spending money drained in a bear market.</p>
        <p>But they did.</p>
        <p>For much of the year, the Big Three price war kept people buying, providing a spot of hopefulness in a doleful economy. At least until October, the industry's worst month in more than four years. Though sales recovered somewhat in November, they were still off 13 percent from the robust levels of November 2001.</p>
        <p>Is this a hiccup or a harbinger?</p>
        <p>There is hardly a consensus. On the bullish side is Scott Hill, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, who predicts industry sales of 16.7 million vehicles next year, compared with the 16.5 million to 16.8 million expected for 2002.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hill cites a combination of factors, from an economy that he believes is stabilizing to consumers' desire to swap cars more often because of a glut of new products and new features, coupled with low prices. Demographic trends are also favorable, he says, because two big generations -- baby boomers and their children, Generation Y -- are entering crucial car-buying years.</p>
        <p>''Peak buying is around age 47,'' Mr. Hill said. ''That's the absolute peak of automotive consumption. The percentage of the population moving into that area continues to rocket.''</p>
        <p>Members of Generation Y, he added, are moving into a period of heavy used-car buying and are also probably buying more new vehicles because of cheap offerings from Hyundai and its Kia brand.</p>
        <p>Other analysts, like Ronald A. Tadross of Banc of America Securities, are pessimistic. Mr. Tadross says sales are likely to be no higher than 16 million and possibly as low as 14 million next year, the latter number being something of a doomsday prediction considering that sales peaked in the United States at 17.4 million in 2000 and were 17.1 million in 2001.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tadross predicts that a dropoff in leasing in recent years will mean that 500,000 to a million fewer cars will come off leases next year -- and thus will not need replacing. He also says booming sales of recent years have left many people with young cars that work fine and are not worth trading in because resale values are depressed by a flood of new and used cars.</p>
        <p>''We already are hearing reports from dealers of trade-in-value shock on the part of consumers,'' he wrote in a recent report.</p>
        <p>Whatever the level of sales diminishment, most agree it will come largely from the hide of the Big Three, which have been losing market share to foreign brands for years. Top foreign brands have managed to outsell Detroit despite having far lower incentive offers. In October, for instance, Honda's sales fell 5.6 percent, far better than the industry at large, even though the company's incentive costs, be they rebates or reduced financing, amounted to only $416 a vehicle, according to the Autodata Corporation.</p>
        <p>By comparison, sales fell 32 percent at G.M. and 34 percent at Ford despite incentive spending of $2,575 and $2,392 a vehicle, respectively. These levels could be pushed higher if demand diminishes because competition is only increasing as foreign automakers like Nissan, Toyota and Honda continue to build more plants and push more vehicles in the United States, by far the most lucrative market.</p>
        <p>And these are only the beginning of the Big Three's headaches next year.</p>
        <p>''Pension expenses will be higher,'' said John A. Casesa, an auto analyst at Merrill Lynch, ''some raw-materials costs will be higher, like steel, and we'll probably see an increase in wage and benefit costs,'' because a new contract will be negotiated with the United Auto Workers.</p>
        <p>''Even before the sales outlook, things will be tough,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
