<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art in Review; Elliott Erwitt</title>
    <meta content="09gall-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1824927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DF1E3FF93AA35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art in Review; Elliott Erwitt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kimmelman, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Personal Best''  Edwynn Houk Gallery  745 Fifth Avenue, at 58th Street  Through Feb. 23</p>
        <p>It's always said about Elliott Erwitt that he knows how to tell a joke, which is true of course. He has told so many good ones over the years, choosing among them is tough, but one of my favorites is the 1954 photograph he shot in Las Vegas of a dour grandmother in glasses yanking the gun barrel of a painted plaster gunslinger that is really a slot machine. The tacky setting, in the glare of lights, and the deadpan humor -- the plaster cowboy grimacing, the matron, icy cold, like a portly Clint Eastwood with bobby pins, an arrow and the word ''push'' painted on a glass door in the foreground and directly pointing at her head -- lifts the image from the level of sight gag to something approaching an American paradigm. This is Mr. Erwitt's deeper, sometimes obscured, virtue: to show us our world in a tender way that does not deny its darker side.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Personal Best''  Edwynn Houk Gallery  745 Fifth Avenue, at 58th Street  Through Feb. 23</p>
        <p>It's always said about Elliott Erwitt that he knows how to tell a joke, which is true of course. He has told so many good ones over the years, choosing among them is tough, but one of my favorites is the 1954 photograph he shot in Las Vegas of a dour grandmother in glasses yanking the gun barrel of a painted plaster gunslinger that is really a slot machine. The tacky setting, in the glare of lights, and the deadpan humor -- the plaster cowboy grimacing, the matron, icy cold, like a portly Clint Eastwood with bobby pins, an arrow and the word ''push'' painted on a glass door in the foreground and directly pointing at her head -- lifts the image from the level of sight gag to something approaching an American paradigm. This is Mr. Erwitt's deeper, sometimes obscured, virtue: to show us our world in a tender way that does not deny its darker side.</p>
        <p>This latest survey (the Houk gallery seems to reshuffle the deck of his work every year or so) has as its ostensible excuse the publication of ''Elliott Erwitt: Personal Best,'' a truly gigantic doorstop of a volume, weighing in at nearly a dozen pounds, which I suspect is far more than the weight of the Chihuahua he photographed panting beside the ankles of its mistress and her Great Dane. The show takes pains to include his photojournalism and foresighted, noirish views of America, which anticipated Winogrand and others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Erwitt's book would be almost perfect save for the frustrating lack of page numbers and all the double-page images with their middles obscured by the gutter. Thirty-four images from the book make up the show, including a couple of views of New York with the prints enlarged so that it is possible to stand before the one of the Flatiron Building on an empty, rain-soaked morning, with a splendid view straight down Fifth Avenue, the triangle of the building echoed by the painted white lines on the converging streets, and imagine yourself right there on the spot. It's a magical effect and a glorious picture.</p>
        <p>I also love the shot, again blown up, of the young woman in the bonnet gazing from atop a balcony at the Empire State Building shrouded in fog. And the haunting one of dancers in Finland, caught in silhouette against an open doorway. It puts me in mind of that funny ''60 Minutes'' report, some years back, on how stern Finlanders let loose by learning the tango. They, like Mr. Erwitt, are romantics at heart.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
