<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NBC's Russert Wraps Up Prosecution Case in Libby Trial</title>
    <meta content="09libby" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/09/washington/09libby.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1824852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Classification of Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News Sources, Confidential Status of</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Neil A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Libby, I Lewis Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russert, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Joseph C Iv</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Valerie Plame</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wells, Theodore V Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walton, Reggie B (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Judith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abramson, Jill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News Sources, Confidential Status of</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classification of Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Libby, I Lewis Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Plame, Valerie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5D7113FF93AA35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NBC's Russert Wraps Up Prosecution Case in Libby Trial</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">NBC’s Russert Wraps Up Prosecution Case in Libby Trial</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prosecution finishes presenting its case in perjury trial of I Lewis Libby Jr; defense must now try to undo government's contention that Libby lied under oath during investigation into leak of CIA officer Valerie Plame Wilson's identity; last day of prosecution is seen as battle of wills between Libby's chief defense lawyer Theodore V Wells Jr and Tim Russert of NBC News; Libby's team wins victory when Judge Reggie B Walton rules that defense can call as witness Jill Abramson, managing editor of New York Times; defense wants to question her in effort to discredit one of prosecution's witnesses, Judith Miller, former reporter for The Times; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The prosecution finished presenting its case in the perjury trial of I. Lewis Libby Jr. on Thursday, leaving his defense lawyers to try to undo the government's contention that Mr. Libby lied under oath during an investigation into the leak of a C.I.A. officer's identity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Libby's legal team will begin with a parade of Washington journalists as witnesses for the defense when the proceedings resume Monday. But lawyers for Mr. Libby, the former chief of staff to Vice President Dick Cheney, left it a mystery as to whether they would call the two star attractions on their witness list: Mr. Cheney and Mr. Libby himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>I. Lewis Libby Jr.’s legal team will begin with a parade of Washington journalists as witnesses for the defense when the proceedings resume.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The prosecution finished presenting its case in the perjury trial of I. Lewis Libby Jr. on Thursday, leaving his defense lawyers to try to undo the government's contention that Mr. Libby lied under oath during an investigation into the leak of a C.I.A. officer's identity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Libby's legal team will begin with a parade of Washington journalists as witnesses for the defense when the proceedings resume Monday. But lawyers for Mr. Libby, the former chief of staff to Vice President Dick Cheney, left it a mystery as to whether they would call the two star attractions on their witness list: Mr. Cheney and Mr. Libby himself.</p>
        <p>The last day of the prosecution's case was largely consumed with an intense battle of wills between Mr. Libby's chief defense lawyer, Theodore V. Wells Jr., and the final prosecution witness, Tim Russert of NBC News. Before the jurors left for a long weekend, they were bombarded as they have been each day with a fast-moving and complex torrent of information.</p>
        <p>They seemed to pay close attention as Mr. Wells, known for his cross-examination skills, and Mr. Russert, a successful public communicator, went at each other for a second consecutive day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wells focused on Mr. Russert's behavior when he was first called by an F.B.I. agent and asked about a telephone conversation he had had with Mr. Libby on July 10 or 11, 2003.</p>
        <p>In that call, the agent told Mr. Russert that Mr. Libby had said in an interview that he first learned of the identity of the C.I.A. operative, Valerie Wilson, from Mr. Russert in the July 2003 conversation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russert told the agent that Mr. Libby's assertion was untrue, that the issue of Ms. Wilson never came up in that conversation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wells, using the technique that Mr. Russert is known for as moderator of ''Meet the Press,'' then put up on video screens throughout the courtroom Mr. Russert's words in an affidavit he filed later. In an effort to avoid complying with a subpoena to testify about the same subject before a grand jury, Mr. Russert swore that he could not discuss the conversation because to do so would violate his deeply held journalistic principles.</p>
        <p>''Did you disclose in the affidavit to the court that you had already disclosed the contents of your conversation with Mr. Libby'' to the Federal Bureau of Investigation, Mr. Wells asked.</p>
        <p>''As I've said, sir  ,'' Mr. Russert began.</p>
        <p>''It's a yes or no question,'' Mr. Wells interrupted.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to answer it to the best of my ability,'' Mr. Russert replied.</p>
        <p>''This is a very simple question. Either it's in the affidavit or it's not,'' Mr. Wells said. ''Did you disclose to the court that you had already communicated to the F.B.I. the fact that you had communicated with Mr. Libby?''</p>
        <p>''No,'' Mr. Russert said.</p>
        <p>The July phone conversation between Mr. Libby and Mr. Russert is at the heart of the five-count felony indictment. Mr. Libby swore that he did not learn the identity of Ms. Wilson from fellow administration officials but learned it then from Mr. Russert.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors have asserted that Mr. Libby concocted that testimony to avoid acknowledging that he learned about her from fellow officials.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wilson's identity was first disclosed publicly on July 14, 2003, in a column by Robert Novak, only days after The New York Times published an Op-Ed article by her husband criticizing the Bush White House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russert was notably more subdued during his two days of cross-examination than the ebullient personality he presents on television. He seemed initially taken aback by the pace and ferocity of Mr. Wells's questions. But by Thursday he had regained much of his confidence.</p>
        <p>The Libby defense won a victory of sorts when Judge Reggie B. Walton agreed to exclude part of one of the five felony counts against Mr. Libby. But it remained unclear whether the change, which was not contested by the prosecutors, would matter in jury deliberations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Libby's team won another victory when Judge Walton ruled that the defense could call as a witness Jill Abramson, the managing editor of The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Mr. Libby's lawyers want to question Ms. Abramson in an effort to discredit one of the prosecution witnesses, Judith Miller, a former reporter for The Times. Ms. Miller, who went to jail for 85 days before agreeing to testify before the grand jury, has provided pivotal testimony against Mr. Libby, saying he informed her in detail about Ms. Wilson in several conversations.</p>
        <p>Ms. Miller also testified that after a July 8, 2003, breakfast meeting during which Mr. Libby spoke at length about Ms. Wilson, she recommended to Ms. Abramson, then the Washington bureau chief, that the newspaper assign a reporter to look into Mr. and Mrs. Wilson.</p>
        <p>Ms. Abramson had been quoted in The Times denying such a conversation, and Mr. Libby's lawyers want Ms. Abramson to cast doubt on Ms. Miller's credibility.</p>
        <p>Ms. Abramson will probably testify on Tuesday, and other journalists, like Bob Woodward and Walter Pincus of The Washington Post, will take the stand on Monday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
