<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Colombia Panel Backs President In Campaign Gifts of Drug Cartel</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="816061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COLOMBIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">COLOMBIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CALI CARTEL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAMPER, ERNESTO (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DD1739F936A25751C1A963958260" item-length="455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Colombia Panel Backs President In Campaign Gifts of Drug Cartel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>BOGOTA, Colombia, Dec. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The threat of impeachment for President Ernesto Samper was eased today when a Colombian congressional committee voted against opening a formal investigation into charges that the President personally approved the acceptance of millions of dollars in contributions from the Cali drug cartel to help him win election last year.</p>
        <p>"There are no merits to open a formal investigation," said Jorge Humberto Mantilla, a member of the Colombian House of Representatives, whose committee voted 14 to 1 against the inquiry. "But if definitive proof arises, the investigation will be reopened. This does not mean that he is guilty or innocent."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The threat of impeachment for President Ernesto Samper was eased today when a Colombian congressional committee voted against opening a formal investigation into charges that the President personally approved the acceptance of millions of dollars in contributions from the Cali drug cartel to help him win election last year.</p>
        <p>"There are no merits to open a formal investigation," said Jorge Humberto Mantilla, a member of the Colombian House of Representatives, whose committee voted 14 to 1 against the inquiry. "But if definitive proof arises, the investigation will be reopened. This does not mean that he is guilty or innocent."</p>
        <p>The decision by the committee, which had been expected, is unlikely to put an end to the general climate of uncertainty that has accompanied Colombia's most serious political crisis in decades, since Colombian justice officials are  continuing to gather evidence of wrongdoing in the campaign.</p>
        <p>While the President's role in the acceptance of drug money is unclear, prosecutors say that they have proven beyond doubt that the 1994 campaign did indeed receive millions of dollars from members of the Cali cartel and that their remaining task is to determine how much money there was and who is responsible for the contribution.</p>
        <p>"The political crisis is far from over," said Fernando Cepeda, a former cabinet minister. "If anything, it is just beginning."</p>
        <p>Since April, the chief prosecutor's office and the Supreme Court have been investigating at least a dozen congressmen, politicians close to the President and sports and entertainment figures for their alleged ties to the Cali cartel in what has become the country's first official inquiry into drug-related corruption.</p>
        <p>The investigations reached a new height in August when Defense Minister Fernando Botero, who served as Mr. Samper's campaign manager, resigned after the campaign's treasurer, Santiago Medina, told prosecutors that he had received over $5.8 million from the Cali cartel at the behest of Mr. Botero and of the President. Days later, Mr. Botero was arrested.</p>
        <p>Confronted by increasing calls for his resignation, Mr. Samper announced that he had asked the committee to open a preliminary investigation against him.</p>
        <p>Chief Prosecutor Alfonso Valdivieso has said his office's investigation of Mr. Samper's campaign financing will not be affected by the congressional committee's decision.</p>
        <p>"This decision is bound to produce controversy," said Alfonso Gomez Mendez, a lawyer and expert on constitutional law. "The investigation by the committee was not thorough enough. I do not think the President technically committed a crime, but that is not the point. The issue should be political."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
