<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Breaking the Same Old, Same Old Indian Mold</title>
    <meta content="15UNDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/15/living/15UNDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1247381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mirchi (Manhattan Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3DC1F38F936A25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Breaking the Same Old, Same Old Indian Mold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov, in $25 and Under column, reviews Mirchi, Indian restaurant in Greenwich Village (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of my recurring disappointments has been the dismal state of New York's Indian restaurants. Although it is possible to ferret out food with the spicing, vibrancy and diversity that make Indian one of the world's glorious cuisines, a vast majority of restaurants, especially in Manhattan, settle for a dreary sameness. You would almost believe that the extent of Indian cooking is no more than what fits on a takeout menu.</p>
        <p>For that reason alone, Mirchi, which opened about a month ago in Greenwich Village, deserves a warm welcome. It tries to break the imprisoning mold, and while its kitchen has been bedeviled by inconsistency, it succeeds often enough to for its failures to be forgiven.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of my recurring disappointments has been the dismal state of New York's Indian restaurants. Although it is possible to ferret out food with the spicing, vibrancy and diversity that make Indian one of the world's glorious cuisines, a vast majority of restaurants, especially in Manhattan, settle for a dreary sameness. You would almost believe that the extent of Indian cooking is no more than what fits on a takeout menu.</p>
        <p>For that reason alone, Mirchi, which opened about a month ago in Greenwich Village, deserves a warm welcome. It tries to break the imprisoning mold, and while its kitchen has been bedeviled by inconsistency, it succeeds often enough to for its failures to be forgiven.</p>
        <p>From its clean and simple design,  it is clear that Mirchi is trying to set itself apart. Its casual service and loud Indian-by-way-of-London techno music suggest other youth-oriented restaurants with bar crowds rather than other Indian restaurants. Yet the food is strictly Indian, with not even a hint of fusion.</p>
        <p>The focus is street foods and other small plates, a deceiving concept since many portions are quite large. Mirchi's other point of departure is forceful spicing, with occasionally very high heat (the word mirchi means hot, as in chilies). Sometimes this is done beautifully. Chicken tak-a-tak ($6), shredded chicken essentially stir-fried on the tawa (pronounced tav-AH), an Indian equivalent of a wok, was exceptional, with a peppery bite augmented by garlic, ginger and chili. Another night I had the same dish made with ground lamb, and it was no more than meat with chili heat, dull and one dimensional compared with the chicken.</p>
        <p>Ragda pattice ($6), savory potato cakes topped with white beans, onions and chili, was another good dish, spicy but freshened with mint and cilantro. I loved mung jhinga chat ($7), grilled shrimp in a sweet-and-tangy tamarind sauce with an earthiness added by mung bean sprouts, while slivers of chicken breast tossed with onions, tomatoes and tamarind  murgh chat ($5) was a well-balanced blend of sweet, salty and spicy.</p>
        <p>As much as I liked these dishes, though, I couldn't help wondering if they would always be so good. One evening dhoklas ($4), steamed cakes of chickpea flour flavored with cilantro and chili, were bland and dry.  Another night they were moist and light. Same with sev poori ($5), a  crisp bread shell filled with potatoes, onions, chickpea vermicelli, yogurt and spices. Once it was made correctly and was delightful. Another time, the poori was too hard, and the filling was simply piled on top. Some dishes I won't willingly try again, like Koliwada maachi ($8), cubes of soft, watery salmon in an indistinct sauce.</p>
        <p>Main courses are just as inconsistent. Jaipuri lal maas ($15) is a fabulous and subtle lamb dish, made, the menu says, with 30 red chilies. Yet the chunks of lamb are not fiery but hauntingly spicy, as if the chilies had left a ghostly imprint of their power, capturing the full flavor of the pepper. Hyderabadi baingan ($12), baby eggplant in a creamy coconut and ginger sauce, achieves a perfect eggplant flavor without bitterness, while kicheri ($9), a rice and lentil dish that is to India what chicken soup is to New York, is exactly what I want next time I have a cold.</p>
        <p>I won't dwell on failures like a watered-down version of chicken in a black pepper sauce ($15) or fish in mustard sauce ($17), which was hard to distinguish from the chicken's black pepper sauce.</p>
        <p>One feature you won't find at many moderately priced Indian restaurants is a wine list. It's a great idea, though Mirchi offers too many chardonnays and merlots, which are overwhelmed by spicy food.</p>
        <p>At Mirchi, the ups outweigh the downs, and the potential for improvement is clear. For simply trying to tread a different path, I say thank you.</p>
        <p>Mirchi</p>
        <p>29 Seventh Avenue South near Morton Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 414-0931.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES: Chicken tak-a-tak, potato cakes with white beans, grilled shrimp in tamarind sauce, chicken chat, dhoklas, lamb with 30 chilies, eggplant in coconut and ginger sauce.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE: Appetizers, $4 to $9; main courses, $9 to $19.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.</p>
        <p>HOURS: Lunch, Monday through Friday, noon to 3 p.m. Dinner, Sunday through Thursday, 5:30 to 11 p.m., Friday and Saturday, 5:30 to midnight.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Everything is on one level.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
