<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nanchang Journal; The Bike That Won the East Is Now Heading West</title>
    <meta content="Y15SHA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/15/world/15SHAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1247502"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motorcycles, Motor Bikes and Motorscooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nanchang (China)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang Jiang</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motorcycles, Motor Bikes and Motorscooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEFD6163BF936A25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nanchang Journal; The Bike That Won the East Is Now Heading West</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>NANCHANG, China</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chinese sidecar motorcycles known as Chang Jiang, once the workhorse of Communist world, are not used much by Chinese today, but there is a steady stream of Westerners at the shop in Nanchang where Zhan Xiong builds and sells them; motorcycle is a copy of 1938 R-12 BMW sidecar motorcycle, which Hitler appropriated and adapted for military use and which is familiar to Westerners from newsreels and films; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the gloomy, grease-smudged recesses of a small garage in an industrial Shanghai neighborhood, gray-haired Zhan Xiong tends to a small flock of starry-eyed devotees of his stock in trade: 750-cc sidecar motorcycles that were once the workhorse of the Communist world.</p>
        <p>The Chinese bikes, called Chang Jiang after the Mandarin name for the Yangtze River, are made in a Dickensian red-brick factory on the fringe of a munitions manufacturing complex here in Nanchang, a river town in central China known as the birthplace of the People's Liberation Army.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the gloomy, grease-smudged recesses of a small garage in an industrial Shanghai neighborhood, gray-haired Zhan Xiong tends to a small flock of starry-eyed devotees of his stock in trade: 750-cc sidecar motorcycles that were once the workhorse of the Communist world.</p>
        <p>The Chinese bikes, called Chang Jiang after the Mandarin name for the Yangtze River, are made in a Dickensian red-brick factory on the fringe of a munitions manufacturing complex here in Nanchang, a river town in central China known as the birthplace of the People's Liberation Army.</p>
        <p>The motorcycle's low-slung silhouette and guttural idle are recognizable to any Westerner who has seen black-and-white newsreels of German troops during World War II. That is because it is a copy of a 1938 R-12 BMW sidecar motorcycle, which Hitler appropriated and adapted for military use by his army.</p>
        <p>''Westerners seem to have a particular psychological attachment to this bike because it was used in the war,'' mused the mildly befuddled Mr. Zhan, a mechanic who spent more than 40 years skinning his knuckles on the motorcycle's greasy bolts. He spoke amid the clutter of broken motorbikes that fills his crowded shop.</p>
        <p>He sells the once ubiquitous motorcycles now, though with the country eager to keep up with the rest of the world, few Chinese choose to ride them these days.</p>
        <p>Individual Chinese are not allowed to own sidecar motorcycles in most cities, and it is illegal to separate the motorcycle from the sidecar. The army, which had exclusive use of the bikes, has nearly abandoned them, and the country's various police forces are slowly switching to Yamahas.</p>
        <p>Foreigners are about the only customers Mr. Zhan has left. He would be out of business but for middle-aged expatriate men with romantic, if outdated, visions of China and some younger men pursuing unlikely macho fantasies among the schoolchildren and grandparents who bicycle along the streets here.</p>
        <p>Rev one up and even the paunchiest cubicle dweller feels stirred by the spirit of Steve McQueen making his wild ride in the 1963 film ''The Great Escape.'' He was actually riding a Triumph painted to look like a BMW, though he was chased by stuntmen riding the real three-wheel item.</p>
        <p>While a Chinese riding one draws no attention at all, a foreigner invariably provokes giggles and gawks from local residents, for whom the sight is roughly equivalent to a Chinese tourist strutting in spurs and chaps down a Dallas street.</p>
        <p>Parked curbside, though, the motorcycles attract the attention of almost any Western male within shooting distance of a midlife crisis.</p>
        <p>The people who have made the pilgrimage to Mr. Zhan's Shanghai shop are a diverse crew: a cranky Australian who goes by the name Butch and leads a motley group called the Red Devils Motorcycle Club on weekend trips into the countryside; this reporter, whose Chang Jiang mostly gathers dust in a garage; and Mark DeCocinis, general manager of Shanghai's Ritz Carlton Hotel, who chauffeurs his family to church in one of Mr. Zhan's bikes and even offers guests a package that includes a sidecar tour around town.</p>
        <p>''The first thing they ask is, 'Where's the helmet?' '' said Mr. DeCocinis, whose bike is a glossy black with leather seat covers made for him by a friend, the Italian designer Stefano Ricci. Helmets in China are typically plastic shells that offer little protection, and many riders go without them. Mr. DeCocinis gives passengers a slow ride in any case.</p>
        <p>The Nazis mounted machine guns on the sidecars and issued the bikes to armored units on the Eastern Front. Stalin's generals countered by importing several through Sweden and copying the design. They began having the motorcycle built in Irbit, a town in the Ural Mountains remote enough to be safe from German bombers, and the bike was eventually named after the mountain range.</p>
        <p>In 1957 Soviet engineers gave China a few of the bikes along with drawings of the tooling used to make them. Mr. Zhan, now 63, started working at the factory the next year as the motorcycle went into mass production.</p>
        <p>The motorcycle's unique air-cooled, opposed-cylinder engine is so reliable that BMW says a quarter of the bikes it sold with the engine since 1923 are still on the road. Between the production from China and from the Soviet Union, the rugged bike spread across the Communist world from Cuba to North Korea.</p>
        <p>On the fringe of the Nanchang factory, whose more modern workshops make fighter aircraft and ballistic missiles, a single conveyor belt runs down the middle of a cavernous room and past stacks of olive-drab steel-tube frames, bulbous black gas tanks and army-green fenders. From the white fretwork of steel beams holding up the roof hang huge banners whose red Chinese characters read, ''Safe Production -- Prevent Accidents.''</p>
        <p>Accidents are not much of a threat these days. The production line is idle most of the year. It takes the factory only a matter of weeks to satisfy annual demand of a few thousand motorcycles.</p>
        <p>Only a few hundred of those bikes are built with the vintage body fancied by foreigners. Most are retrofitted with boxy blue-and-white bodies used by the police. And a few of the bikes are fitted with fire extinguishers for China's forest service, though with rubber tires and leaky gas tanks, it is not clear how they help in fighting fires.</p>
        <p>The police in China's former client states like Vietnam and Albania still buy the motorcycles. But the factory cannot sell to its biggest potential market, the United States, because the bike spews too much exhaust to meet American emission standards.</p>
        <p>The Russian makers of the Ural, meanwhile, have upgraded their motorcycle technology, and that bike is enjoying a modest rebirth among vintage motorcycle enthusiasts in America.</p>
        <p>So China's expatriate community is about the only market keeping the Chang Jiang production line from closing completely.</p>
        <p>''The equipment's here, so we'll probably keep making the motorcycles for a few more years,'' said Fan Luxing, the motorcycle factory's chief engineer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zhan is unsentimental about the bike, which he sees as little more than bent sheet metal bolted to steel tubes, an engine and three tires. Bemused as he is by others' fascination with the motorcycle, though, he is also grateful.</p>
        <p>So far this year, he said, he has sold 20 of the bikes to foreigners.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
