<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Acknowledges an Arrest for Drunken Driving in 1976</title>
    <meta content="03DRIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/03/politics/03DRIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1244120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: A DRIVING OFFENSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maine</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fehlau, Erin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0DD1639F930A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Acknowledges an Arrest for Drunken Driving in 1976</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>WEST ALLIS, Wis., Nov. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush confirms reports on two TV stations in Maine that 24 years ago, in Sept 1976, he was arrested for driving while intoxicated, during visit to his family's vacation home in Maine; says he admitted his mistake to police officer who pulled him over, then paid fine; says he stopped drinking in 1986; Bush does not explicitly blame Gore campaign or Democrats for revealing incident, but says 'I've got my suspicions'; Erin Fehlau, television reporter, describes how she tracked down story and says she is confident she was not set up by any campaign operative (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush said tonight that he was arrested for driving while intoxicated 24 years ago while visiting his family's vacation home in Kennebunkport, Me.</p>
        <p>After a boisterous rally here, Mr. Bush hastily arranged his first news conference in about a month to confirm reports by WCSH-TV and WPXT-TV in Portland, Me., about his arrest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush said tonight that he was arrested for driving while intoxicated 24 years ago while visiting his family's vacation home in Kennebunkport, Me.</p>
        <p>After a boisterous rally here, Mr. Bush hastily arranged his first news conference in about a month to confirm reports by WCSH-TV and WPXT-TV in Portland, Me., about his arrest.</p>
        <p>''I'm not proud of that,'' Mr. Bush said, clutching the hand of his wife, Laura, as he faced reporters in a driveway. ''I've oftentimes said that years ago I made some mistakes. I drank too much, and I did on that night.''</p>
        <p>He said that he had been driving, that he had admitted to a police officer who pulled him over that he had been drinking and that he had paid a fine.</p>
        <p>''I regret that it happened,'' he said. ''But it did. I've learned my lesson.''</p>
        <p>He noted that he stopped drinking in 1986 after his 40th birthday and that ''it was the right decision.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said repeatedly that he had suspicions why this report had come out ''somehow four or five days before an election.'' Although he did not explicitly blame the campaign of Vice President Al Gore or the Democrats, he said at one point, ''I've got my suspicions.''</p>
        <p>Erin Fehlau, a reporter for WPXT, said last night on ABC's ''Nightline'' that she had been tipped off to the story by a police officer in a Maine courthouse She said the officer had overheard a lawyer talking about Mr. Bush's arrest. Ms. Fehlau said the lawyer was a delegate to the Democratic convention.</p>
        <p>She then tracked down a copy of  the accident report, as well as the original arresting officer. ''I'm confident I wasn't set up,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ever since he began his presidential campaign, Mr. Bush has been dogged by questions about his past, particularly over whether he had used illegal drugs. And although he has often discussed drinking, he deflected other questions by saying only that he had been ''young and irresponsible.''</p>
        <p>Pressed tonight on why he had not previously acknowledged the arrest, Mr. Bush said he had wanted to serve as a role model to his two daughters and made ''the decision that as a dad I didn't want my daughters doing the kinds of things that I did.''</p>
        <p>When he was asked how he thought he could get away with the lack of disclosure, he said sharply, ''I'm not trying to get away with anything.''</p>
        <p>''I've said I've made mistakes in the past,'' he said. ''People know that. They've thought about that. They're making their minds up now. They've seen me as the governor of the state of Texas. I've upheld the honor and integrity of my office.''</p>
        <p>Chris Lehane, a spokesman for Vice President Al Gore, declined to comment, but insisted that the Gore campaign had ''nothing to do with the emergence of this information.''</p>
        <p>The arrest was first confirmed by Mr. Bush's spokeswoman, Karen P. Hughes, who held a news conference in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hughes said Mr. Bush had been driving with his sister, Dorothy,  and friends, including the Australian tennis star John Newcombe, in September 1976 and was stopped after leaving a bar. She said he had had ''several beers.'' He pleaded guilty to a misdemeanor charge of driving under the influence of alcohol, she said, paid a fine of $150 and ''had his driving privileges rescinded in Maine for a period of time.''</p>
        <p>Calvin Bridges, identified as the arresting officer by the Bush campaign, said in a telephone interview with The Associated Press that he recalled driving home from work after midnight that September night and spotting a car slipping briefly onto the shoulder before getting back on the road.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush failed a road sobriety test and a second test in the police station, registering a 0.10 percent blood-alcohol level, the legal limit at  the time, Mr. Bridges said.</p>
        <p>Asked about Mr. Bush's demeanor, Mr. Bridges, who is retired, said, ''The man was, and I say this without being facetious, a picture of integrity. He gave no resistance. He was very cooperative.''</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Bush spent about 90 minutes in custody.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hughes said this was the only time Mr. Bush had been arrested except for a previously reported arrest for a college prank at Yale, where he stole a Christmas wreath.  Mr. Bush had another run-in with law enforcement authorities while at Yale after he and other students tried to tear down the goal posts after a football game with Princeton.</p>
        <p>The disclosure of the Maine arrest came just five days before Election Day, with Mr. Bush having a slight edge in the polls.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: A DRIVING OFFENSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
