<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Men Can Do</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="746544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHERRILL, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOUGH, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DA1731F930A35750C0A963958260" item-length="479" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Men Can Do</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Sherrill and Paul Tough;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TOUGH, PAUL; SHERRILL, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The battle of the sexes has taken another ugly turn, and once again, science is to blame. Behaviorists at Yale University now claim that they have uncovered definitive evidence that men and women use their brains differently.</p>
        <p>According to reports in this newspaper, not only are men less sensitive than women to emotional cues, women "do better on certain tests, like those measuring verbal speed." Men, one article added dismissively, "do better on other tasks, like imagining what an object would look like if it were rotated."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The battle of the sexes has taken another ugly turn, and once again, science is to blame. Behaviorists at Yale University now claim that they have uncovered definitive evidence that men and women use their brains differently.</p>
        <p>According to reports in this newspaper, not only are men less sensitive than women to emotional cues, women "do better on certain tests, like those measuring verbal speed." Men, one article added dismissively, "do better on other tasks, like imagining what an object would look like if it were rotated."</p>
        <p>Needless to say, these findings have made life almost unbearable for men around the country. Conversations with women now turn inevitably to the topic of verbal speed -- how women have it, how men don't. Suddenly women feel "empowered" to rapidly correct our split infinitives, toss off palindromes and propose party games like "Let's Measure Our Verbal Speed."</p>
        <p>Men have reacted with denial and rage. Bars are full of bitter, sulky men waving crossword puzzles and Jumbles at each other. It's a sad spectacle, and what's more, it's entirely the wrong reaction. Listen, gentlemen, why play defense? We are good at something, too. Something they're not good at. And that something -- let's say it loud -- is imagining what objects would look like if they were rotated.</p>
        <p>Give a woman an object, ask her to imagine what the object would look like if it were rotated. What you'll get is a lot of nervous laughter and verbally quick excuses. Do the same thing with a guy, and bam, he'll tell you what the object would look like if it were rotated. It's science.</p>
        <p>Men have suffered enough this decade. And, yes, as a sex, we've made some mistakes. But it's time for the apologies to stop. It's time for us to celebrate what we do best. Let's imagine what objects would look like if they were rotated, and let's feel good about it.</p>
        <p>Look up from this paper right now, men. Take the first object you see and imagine what it would look like if it were rotated. Doesn't that feel great? Now look out your window at the World Trade Center. Give it, say, a 90-degree turn to the left. Piece of cake, right? And that's a 110-story building you're spinning around like a child's top. Do you have any idea what it would cost to actually rotate the World Trade Center?</p>
        <p>Dr. Sally Shaywitz, the Yale behaviorist who was principal author of the brain study, has been patting the fairer sex on the back for the ability to do verbal things like reading. Reading "is the most complex of human functions," she claimed last week. "Reading is the pinnacle of what humans can do."</p>
        <p>Says you, Sally. Yes, reading is swell. It's right up there on any list of human functions. But some humans can do more -- those humans called men. You want a pinnacle? Try imagining what an object would look like if it were rotated, Dr. Shaywitz. Go ahead. Just try.  Stephen Sherrill is a writer. Paul Tough is an editor at Harper's Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Stephen Sherrill is a writer. Paul Tough is an editor at Harper's Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
