<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Megan's Law' Puts Lawyers In Tough Spot</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="799020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIVACY, RIGHT OF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY BAR ASSN</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANLEY, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D8123FF935A25753C1A963958260" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Megan's Law' Puts Lawyers In Tough Spot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HANLEY, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>HACKENSACK, N.J., Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Megan's Law" has a new problem: angry lawyers who do not want to defend sex offenders free.</p>
        <p>The New Jersey Bar Association is in an uproar over a proposal that lawyers provide free legal service for indigent sex offenders who wish to challenge the new law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"Megan's Law" has a new problem: angry lawyers who do not want to defend sex offenders free.</p>
        <p>The New Jersey Bar Association is in an uproar over a proposal that lawyers provide free legal service for indigent sex offenders who wish to challenge the new law.</p>
        <p>"I guess you could call it a strike," Harold A. Sherman, the bar association president, said about some lawyers' plans to defy judges. "There's a lot of anger out there. I feel a lot of heat."</p>
        <p>The dispute goes back to July, when the State Supreme Court upheld the constitutionality of Megan's Law, the 1994 legislation mandating that residents be notified when a sex offender is released from prison and moves into their community.</p>
        <p>The court ordered that hearings be held to allow offenders to challenge determinations by county prosecutors on how dangerous a particular offender is and how widespread notification should be.</p>
        <p>In its ruling, the court guaranteed court-appointed lawyers for offenders too poor to pay, and suggested that the Legislature make money available for their cases.</p>
        <p>But the Legislature has not acted, and two of the judges assigned to oversee hearings -- Lawrence M. Lawson of Monmouth County and Walter R. Barisonek of Union County -- now say court-appointed lawyers will have to work free.</p>
        <p>Lawyers' anger seems strongest in Gloucester County, in southern New Jersey. Robert Becker, president of the county bar association, said 30 lawyers there had been selected to handle appeals, and "easily half have said they won't accept the assignment."</p>
        <p>The protest represents a rare public display of lawyers' displeasure with the court system and threatens more delays in carrying out the law.</p>
        <p>Enforcement has been delayed since February by court challenges, leading to a backlog of 2,248 cases. Prosecutors are reviewing the cases to determine which offenders are dangerous enough to warrant alerting schools, neighbors and others.</p>
        <p>The lawyers complain about the Legislature's failure to provide money, the lack of information about the length and nature of appeals, and assignments to represent clients that stir moral aversion, including child molesters.</p>
        <p>Some lawyers threaten to sue the court system and defy orders to handle cases. But no one has defied a judge yet, because Gloucester's Prosecutor is not finished reviewing the county's 62 registered offenders, and there is no way of knowing how many will appeal and will qualify for a free lawyer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Becker says pay is not at the heart of the unrest. "They're just not giving us a choice of doing it or not," he said.</p>
        <p>As James A. Crawford, president of the Bergen County Bar Association, explained, "The parents of a young girl might not want to represent someone convicted of molesting children."</p>
        <p>He said lawyers' attitudes might be different if the offenders had not already been convicted. "There's no presumption of innocence here," he said.</p>
        <p>The protest has grown in the last three weeks as prosecutors continue to assess released offenders as low, moderate or high risks of committing more sex crimes. Notification about moderate and high risks can be made to schools, day-care centers, camps and other institutions that care for children, and to shelters and centers that care for women. For those determined to pose a high risk, neighbors are also notified.</p>
        <p>The law was passed quickly last fall, just weeks after 7-year-old Megan Kanka was murdered near her home in Hamilton Township. A neighbor, a convicted sex offender, was arrested and convicted in her death.</p>
        <p>In the July decision upholding the law, Chief Justice Robert N. Wilentz urged the Legislature to provide money for court-appointed lawyers. He also suggested it could set up an agency outside the court system to handle appeals. The Legislature has done neither.</p>
        <p>Another critic of the current system, Frederick L. Blankenhorn, president of the Monmouth County Bar Association, criticized Gov. Christine Todd Whitman and her fellow Republicans, who control the Legislature.</p>
        <p>"Republicans are saying now that everything mandated by government should be funded by government," he said. "Here, they're not doing it."</p>
        <p>Rae Hutton, spokeswoman for the Senate President, Donald T. DiFrancesco, said the Legislature was committed to fulfilling the public-safety promises inherent in the law. But it is premature, she said, to talk about funds for court-appointed lawyers until it is known how many court work will be needed. "No one has ruled out funding," Ms. Hutton said.</p>
        <p>The State Supreme Court has made no final decision about whether to order the state to pay lawyers. "The court obviously is aware of the issue, and if necessary, will decide it," said a court spokesman, Richard Pliskin. He would not comment further.</p>
        <p>Lawyers critical of the possibility of being ordered to do "pro bono" work say it would be too taxing, especially on small firms. They fear appeals could last up to five days, require long preparation and involve appeals to higher courts, and force lawyers to pay for expert witnesses like psychiatrists. Judges, however, say the state court system will pay for such experts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sherman, the bar association president, has called a meeting of all county bar presidents on Tuesday to plan further action, and has invited top court officials to attend.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
