<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cray Is Ready to Introduce Its First Parallel Computer</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="637160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CRAY RESEARCH INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKHOFF, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DA173BF934A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cray Is Ready to Introduce Its First Parallel Computer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF,</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Sept. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seeking to shore up its eroding control of the market for the fastest computers, Cray Research Inc. will introduce its first massively parallel computer on Monday.</p>
        <p>Massively parallel processors are made by chaining together hundreds or thousands of inexpensive commercial microprocessors. They have been making inroads into the supercomputer business that Cray dominated in the 1980's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seeking to shore up its eroding control of the market for the fastest computers, Cray Research Inc. will introduce its first massively parallel computer on Monday.</p>
        <p>Massively parallel processors are made by chaining together hundreds or thousands of inexpensive commercial microprocessors. They have been making inroads into the supercomputer business that Cray dominated in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>Although they require that software be rewritten from the ground up, massively parallel processors, known as M.P.P. systems, have become powerful tools for solving many of the most vexing problems faced by scientists and engineers.  They have also stolen much of the glamour that Cray had long derived from its claim of making the world's fastest computers. The company, based in Eagan, Minn., has continued to sell machines with a limited number of specialized processors, including special hardware for computing long strings of simple mathematical operations at high speed.</p>
        <p>These computers, known as vector processors, have been the workhorses for military research laboratories and they are used by scientists and engineers to solve a wide range of problems from weather prediction to molecular modeling.</p>
        <p>But like I.B.M.'s commercial mainframe computers, Cray's supercomputers have come under assault in recent years from companies that exploit the low cost of microprocessors and write special software that breaks up problems so they can be solved in parallel operations.</p>
        <p>For Cray, competition from more than half a dozen smaller makers of massively parallel systems has been accompanied by declining Government spending on supercomputers. Cray's revenue fell to $797.6 million last year from $862.5 million in 1991, and analysts expect it to be flat this year.</p>
        <p>Cray executives said last week that they were confident the new family of products, known as T3D, would cause the company to grow again.  "I expect we'll have sufficient revenue next year to be No. 1 in the massively parallel market," John F. Carlson, Cray's chief executive, said.</p>
        <p>To do that, Cray will have to leapfrog the two leaders in the $300 million massively parallel computer market: the Thinking Machines Corporation and Intel Supercomputers Systems, a unit of the Intel Corporation, the nation's leading chip maker.</p>
        <p>Cray executives said they thought they could quickly enter the massively parallel market by offering a machine that had both old and new attributes. The T3D machines are intended to establish a middle ground between the vector processors and the massively parallel systems. Each of the T3D systems will connect a massively parallel array of microprocessors made by the Digital Equipment Corporation to a conventional vector processor designed by Cray.</p>
        <p>The company and some computer scientists assert that this kind of "heterogeneous" design makes possible a machine that will offer superior performance on a wide range of scientific and engineering problems.  "They have the sizzle," said Jeffry Canin, a computer industry analyst at Salomon Brothers in San Francisco. He said Cray would be able to appeal to a range of customers, who would be attracted by a machine that is balanced at solving a wide range of problems.</p>
        <p>Indeed, computer scientists who tested the computer while it was under development said that it had impressive performance. One researcher said that a Cray T3D with 64 processors would have a peak performance of more than nine billion mathematical calculations a second and a sustained speed of more than three billion calculations. This would place the power of the new Cray at almost twice the speed of the Delta series, the most powerful massively parallel computer made by Intel.</p>
        <p>A number of computer researchers and industry analysts cautioned, however, that the performance comes at a price. While all of the other makers of massively parallel computers are offering air-cooled machines, Cray elected to water-cool its system, making it possible to package the components more closely together. But water-cooling systems tend to be significantly more costly and their added complexity tends to make them less reliable.</p>
        <p>Moreover, by linking the new systems to an existing line of processors, Cray is making them more attractive to its existing customers than to new purchasers. Other Factors</p>
        <p>"It's basically a way of holding on to their customer base," said Gary Smaby, a computer industry consultant at the Smaby Group in Minneapolis. "It's not being positioned as, or sold as, a stand-alone M.P.P. It's been optimized most effectively in the Cray environment."  Cray's entry into the massively parallel market is also clouded by the fact that three other leading computer companies are poised to begin offering massively parallel systems. I.B.M., Convex Computer and Fujitsu have all demonstrated prototypes to customers in recent months.</p>
        <p>I.B.M., in particular, may be able to take advantage of its newest and most powerful microprocessor, which has a substantial speed advantage over the Digital Equipment Alpha processor that Cray is using.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Cray may find it quite difficult to straddle the old and new supercomputer cultures. "M.P.P. is a religion and parallel vector is another religion," said Ed Macie, the president of Intel Supercomputers and a former Cray salesman. "It's hard to have two religions in one organization."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
