<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Style Points</title>
    <meta content="05STYL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/05/sports/olympics/05style.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1601881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2004)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Uniforms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, William L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece/Athens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uniforms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Athens (Greece)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United States Olympic Committee</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1DA153CF936A3575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Style Points</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Style Points Count in Athens, Too</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM L. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamilton, William L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fashions and team uniforms for Olympic Games have greatly evolved over years, but are still subject of great interest to designers, marketers and advertisers; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It used to be a come as you are affair.</p>
        <p>The athletes competing in the first modern Olympics in Athens in 1896 wore their own sports clothes or private athletic club uniforms in competition. They wore shorts and singlets, with the occasional Beau Brummel like the United States hurdler Alvin Kraenzlein, who was in an Eton collar and cravat in Paris in 1900, or a fashion maverick like the discus thrower Martin Sheridan, who won the gold in London in 1908 wearing garters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Games open in Athens, the athletes' apparel will be anything but happenstance, from the merchandising possibilities to the political implications.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It used to be a come as you are affair.</p>
        <p>The athletes competing in the first modern Olympics in Athens in 1896 wore their own sports clothes or private athletic club uniforms in competition. They wore shorts and singlets, with the occasional Beau Brummel like the United States hurdler Alvin Kraenzlein, who was in an Eton collar and cravat in Paris in 1900, or a fashion maverick like the discus thrower Martin Sheridan, who won the gold in London in 1908 wearing garters.</p>
        <p>But when the Games open in Athens next week, the athletes' apparel will be anything but happenstance, from the merchandising possibilities to the political implications.</p>
        <p>In an acknowledgment of the global opportunity for merchandising, as well as performance and pride, the United States team, like many other teams, will be wearing five different uniforms: one each for the opening and closing ceremonies, a uniform to compete in, a podium uniform for accepting medals and an official village uniform as casual wear.</p>
        <p>Costume changes have become something of an Olympic event.</p>
        <p>The official United States team uniforms for Athens were designed by two companies to broaden sales appeal for retail versions of what the Olympic athletes will wear -- from downtime to competition, something for everyone. And individual United States teams and individual American athletes have allegiances to other companies showcasing their own products and technologies.</p>
        <p>United States officials said that the 2004 designs were not toned down because of the war in Iraq or the sensitive nature of the United States' presence on the world stage. They are more evocative of a country that anyone could be fond of -- Great Gatsby-style golf caps, not the gunslingers' cowboy hats of Sarajevo in the winter of 1984 or the flag-waving patriotism of the star-spangled gymnasts' uniforms in Los Angeles that summer.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for Roots and Adidas said that the designs were developed two to three years ago, involved no deliberation on how to fine-tune or spin the image of the United States, and had not been amended since they were conceived.</p>
        <p>''There was no discussion of making the athletes less conspicuous as Americans,'' said Michael Budman, a co-founder of Roots, who was speaking from Greece, where he is attending the Games with his family.</p>
        <p>Budman, a United States citizen who has lived in Canada for 25 years, added: ''It's a difficult time, but reality is not what perception has been made out to be. I don't think the world is down on the U.S.''</p>
        <p>The U.S.O.C.'s director of marketing, Cheryl Herbert, explained that the move away from iconic uniform designs, like cowboy clothing, was a more general trend, prompted by the athletes.</p>
        <p>''We've stopped looking at it as a uniform, but as providing athletes with athletic fashion,'' she said. ''It's team psychology. If the athletes aren't comfortable wearing cowboy boots and hats, that's going to affect performance. They want everyday apparel. The costumes have dissipated.''</p>
        <p>Roots, a Canadian company that designed uniforms for the United States team for Salt Lake City in 2002, is responsible for the uniforms the athletes will wear for the opening and closing ceremonies.</p>
        <p>They include a loose, vintage-looking basketball shirt and a twill golf cap that can be worn front to back, back to front, or sideways, depending on how street-fashionable the athletes choose to be.</p>
        <p>Roots is strong on casual wear, Herbert said.</p>
        <p>''We wanted it to be fashion relevant, so kids would view the Olympics as cool,'' Chester Wheeler, director of corporate sales and licensing for the Olympic committee, said.</p>
        <p>Roots' beret for the United States in Salt Lake City was a bestseller: More than a million, at $19.95 each, were sold, including one to the musician Sheryl Crow, and a bagful to Katie Couric for her NBC production crew.</p>
        <p>Revenue from the 2002 designs was more than $40 million, which Roots expects to surpass with its Athens line because summer sportswear is generally more popular than winter gear.</p>
        <p>Adidas, which has its headquarters in Germany, has designed the track-suit podium uniforms and the village wear.</p>
        <p>''The Adidas line is more athletic and performance-driven,'' Herbert said. ''You might wear it to work out.''</p>
        <p>Adidas worked with 20 other countries on designs for Athens, distinguishing teams with national colors, not individual silhouettes or elements of traditional dress. Adidas offered two shapes.</p>
        <p>Countries like the United States, Greece and Germany had first pick, Bernd Feldmann, Adidas's corporate public relations director for the Olympics, said. That design was not offered to countries like Romania and Hungary.</p>
        <p>Roots also outfitted Canada, Britain and Barbados, making national distinctions with subtle references. Britain's outfits are a shade of ecru, or off-white, which is associated with Fred Perry, the British tennis player, Budman said.</p>
        <p>The parade of athletes at the opening ceremony on Aug. 13 will have aspects of the international parade television viewers and spectators have become familiar with. National uniforms, however, date to 1906, to an event in Greece that is not recognized officially by the International Olympic Committee.</p>
        <p>''It was the first march of nations, with flag bearers,'' Bill Mallon, president of the International Society of Olympic Historians, said. ''The U.S. uniform was white shirt, white shorts, with a shield, with red, white and blue stripes on the front of the shield.''</p>
        <p>Allen Guttmann, a sports historian and professor at Amherst College, and the author of ''The Olympics: A History of the Modern Games'' (University of Illinois Press, 2002), said that white was the standard of the early Games.</p>
        <p>''Nineteenth-century sportswear was usually white,'' Guttmann said. ''The point was conspicuous consumption. White gets dirty more quickly and you have to have a good deal of money to wash your togs after every play. It was a way to distance players from the working class. Class relationships had a lot more to do with sports in the early 20th century than nationalism.''</p>
        <p>Guttmann explained that the importance of the appearance of nations, as witnessed by the appearance of participating athletes, came to the fore for the first time in Berlin in 1936, when Nazi Germany played host to the Games.</p>
        <p>''People talked about the uniforms,'' he said. ''It was the first Olympics at which you had strongly nationalistic symbolism side by side with Olympic symbolism. Because the Games were so political, countries gave more thought to the uniforms.'' French athletes wore berets. Britons wore straw boaters. Egyptians wore fezzes. Athletes from Japan wore imperial peaked caps.</p>
        <p>Mallon said that national pride displayed through uniforms incorporating traditional dress gave the Games a permanent visual identity as a global village and hit its stride in the 1950's and 60's.</p>
        <p>''Before that, they largely marched in coats and ties,'' he said. ''Then, the Bermudans in Bermuda shorts started.''</p>
        <p>The Olympics have had their fashion moments, good and bad, from Sonja Henie's radically stylish skating costumes -- ermine-trimmed satin-and-white skates -- to Peggy Fleming's home-sewn chartreuse chiffon, which her mother chose at Macy's because the color matched the famous liqueur produced by monks living outside Grenoble, France, where Fleming competed in 1968.</p>
        <p>Abebe Bikila, an Ethopian runner, won a gold medal in bare feet in Rome in 1960. Michael Johnson, an American sprinter, won gold medals in Atlanta in 1996 -- in gold shoes.</p>
        <p>At Lake Placid in 1980, looking like Starsky or Hutch, United States athletes wore fleece-lined suede jackets, blue jeans, and cowboy hats and boots provided by Levi Strauss.</p>
        <p>''It was very stylin','' said Lynn Downey, the historian at the company, who added that the blue velour warm-up suit that Levi Strauss designed has ''become a major collectible on eBay.''</p>
        <p>The Olympics have had their fashion critics, too.</p>
        <p>Katarina Witt cut the ice with controversy in 1984 and 1988 because the cut of her costumes were sensationally scant.</p>
        <p>Witt told Vogue magazine in a 1991 interview that she had the body for it.</p>
        <p>And the Games have had their political fashions. The American sprinters John Carlos and Tommie Smith raised black-gloved fists on the awards podium in Mexico City in 1968, in solidarity with the black power movement.</p>
        <p>In Athens this month, the prevailing fashion will be the look of performance, and the look of performance is the look of technology. It is a phenomenon viewers first saw in Lake Placid in 1980, Mallon said, when the speed skater Eric Heiden won gold medals wearing a gold bodysuit (and matching hood) that looked like speed itself.</p>
        <p>Todd Van Hornek, Olympic creative director for Nike, called it the art of speed, which the company develops in tandem with what he called science of speed in designing athletic apparel. ''It's fantastic to be fast, with engineering, but you have to look fast too,'' said Van Horne, speaking of graphics and shapes that psychologically convey performance, to the wearer and to the viewer.</p>
        <p>Or, as BVD put it in their advertising in 1932, after signing Johnny Weissmuller, the Olympic gold medalist, for $500 a week to help sell swimming suits, ''You swim faster in our suits because the stripes go up and down.''</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
