<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Protest Leader In Indonesia Is Relieved Of Party Role</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="859550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDONESIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDONESIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYDANS, SETH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUKARNOPUTRI, MEGAWATI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SURYADI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DA1539F930A15755C0A960958260" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Protest Leader In Indonesia Is Relieved Of Party Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYDANS, SETH</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, June 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Indonesia's most prominent political opposition figure, Megawati Sukarnoputri, was ousted today from her party's leadership by rival members, leaving her supporters uncertain over their next move.</p>
        <p>With the blessing of the Indonesian Government, the rival members reinstated  Ms. Megawati's predecessor as party chairman at a meeting in the western city of Medan, setting the stage for a possible confrontation with her supporters, who continued to occupy the party headquarters in Jakarta.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Indonesia's most prominent political opposition figure, Megawati Sukarnoputri, was ousted today from her party's leadership by rival members, leaving her supporters uncertain over their next move.</p>
        <p>With the blessing of the Indonesian Government, the rival members reinstated  Ms. Megawati's predecessor as party chairman at a meeting in the western city of Medan, setting the stage for a possible confrontation with her supporters, who continued to occupy the party headquarters in Jakarta.</p>
        <p>Ms. Megawati, the daughter of Indonesia's late President Sukarno, denounced  the rival meeting as unconstitutional and said, "I will continue to fight for democracy and uphold the people's sovereignty."</p>
        <p>But without the position of party leader, Ms. Megawati would not have legal standing to run for President in elections scheduled for 1998, and her supporters said her political options were limited.</p>
        <p>The reinstated party chairman, Suryadi, said he hoped to keep Ms. Megawati in a prominent position in the party, but her supporters said she would not accept  a compromise.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Ms. Megawati, 49, has raised an increasingly vocal challenge to the leadership of President Suharto, who has ruled Indonesia since taking power from Mr. Sukarno in 1966.</p>
        <p>In six presidential elections, he has been the only candidate of all three Government-sanctioned parties, including that of Ms. Megawati, the Indonesia Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>True opposition parties are not allowed in Indonesia, and Mr. Suryadi, who like many Indonesians uses one name, said today that he did not want his party to become "the enemy of the Government."</p>
        <p>Ms. Megawati had been leading the party in that direction, threatening last week to mobilize her supporters and saying that if she chose, she could paralyze the country by bringing millions of people into the streets.</p>
        <p>But on Thursday, when 5,000 of her supporters demonstrated in central Jakarta to protest the rival party meeting, soldiers with batons choked off the demonstration, sending dozens of people to the hospital and sobering their leaders.</p>
        <p>"It was a shock," Laksamana Sukardi, the party's treasurer and a Megawati loyalist, said on Friday. "We need to pause and save some logistics and energy.  We don't have anything. We don't have money. We don't have access to the media.  We don't have tanks. We don't have barbed wire."</p>
        <p>He said Ms. Megawati's choices were now limited. "I think there are two options now: to gracefully withdraw or to face them head on," Mr. Laksamana said.</p>
        <p>He said a head-on confrontation might be quixotic. "The force that we are challenging is too huge," he said. "I don't see a chance to succeed at this time."</p>
        <p>But he said he did not expect Ms. Megawati simply to accept defeat.  "A graceful withdrawal would make a lot of grass-roots supporters disappointed and  they might have to wait for a generation or two for true democracy."</p>
        <p>President Suharto, who is 75, has not said whether he intends to run again, and Ms. Megawati's challenge comes in the context of growing speculation about his plans and about his possible choice of a successor.</p>
        <p>"After 30 years of relatively stable rule, no one is sure that the transition is going to be accomplished with stability," said Jeffrey A. Winters, an associate professor at Northwestern University who is an expert on Indonesia.</p>
        <p>"There is no institutionalization for change, which is what makes investors nervous."</p>
        <p>Though he has brought increasing prosperity to this nation of 190 million people, President Suharto has maintained tight control over its press and political system.</p>
        <p>His monopoly on power has fueled opposition and created an opening for an opposition figure like Ms. Megawati, who has attracted a following primarily because of her family name.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
