<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arts, Culture and Condiments</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="859541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ENDOWMENT FOR THE ARTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALEXANDER, JANE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E5DA1539F930A15755C0A960958260" item-length="575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arts, Culture and Condiments</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year ago, the National Endowment for the Arts and the National Endowment for the Humanities did not seem to have much chance of surviving the budget buzz saw in Congress. With bipartisan support, however, they have hung on. Forced to  cut grants and personnel, they have begun to look for alternative sources of funding from companies and individuals to stay alive in the years ahead. The endowments' efforts deserve support, but they also pose a new kind of danger. Outside fund-raising should not siphon private giving away from other arts programs or compromise the endowments' independent mission.</p>
        <p>Government support for the arts is often criticized as a luxury and an intrusion into a field best supported by private patronage and giving. But private contributions are not growing at a sufficient pace, and the 40 percent budget cut suffered by the arts endowment this year has dealt a blow to many worthwhile arts programs. A recent report sponsored by a Presidential panel on the arts and humanities and subsidized by the Rockefeller Foundation found that  private giving had actually fallen since the late 1980's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year ago, the National Endowment for the Arts and the National Endowment for the Humanities did not seem to have much chance of surviving the budget buzz saw in Congress. With bipartisan support, however, they have hung on. Forced to  cut grants and personnel, they have begun to look for alternative sources of funding from companies and individuals to stay alive in the years ahead. The endowments' efforts deserve support, but they also pose a new kind of danger. Outside fund-raising should not siphon private giving away from other arts programs or compromise the endowments' independent mission.</p>
        <p>Government support for the arts is often criticized as a luxury and an intrusion into a field best supported by private patronage and giving. But private contributions are not growing at a sufficient pace, and the 40 percent budget cut suffered by the arts endowment this year has dealt a blow to many worthwhile arts programs. A recent report sponsored by a Presidential panel on the arts and humanities and subsidized by the Rockefeller Foundation found that  private giving had actually fallen since the late 1980's.</p>
        <p>Corporate giving has gone up, and many national institutions like the Kennedy Center, the Holocaust Museum and the National Gallery have benefited. Increasingly, however, corporate contributions to the arts are tied to marketing strategies by the companies involved. Recently, for example, the arts endowment  announced its biggest corporate gift ever -- $450,000 from the H. J. Heinz Company to support arts education in schools. The announcement of the gift was tied to a separate corporate initiative to promote a contest among schoolchildren to redesign the keystone-shaped label for Heinz ketchup. Three winners will have their designs appear on ketchup bottles next year to celebrate 100 years of "the nation's favorite condiment." A news conference attended by the arts endowment's chairwoman, Jane Alexander, announced both the grant and the ketchup label contest.</p>
        <p>There does not seem to be anything inherently wrong with letting a company promote its ketchup if that is what it takes to generate money for arts programs in schools. Museums, performing arts groups and many other worthy causes would be nowhere without the generosity or benign self-interest of private companies,  which should not be forced to remain anonymous about their giving. Nevertheless, the National Arts Endowment has to be careful about endorsing corporate advertising campaigns.</p>
        <p>For companies, there may be an advantage to giving money to the endowment, forgoing the need to examine the worthiness of arts groups on their own. But some companies may choose to avoid going through an endowment that has had to be politically cautious in order not to offend conservatives in Congress.</p>
        <p>Ms. Alexander, a respected actress, author and producer, has brought energy and creativity to the embattled campaign for government support of the arts. She has forcefully made the case that the United States can do more and has won the  respect of Republicans and Democrats while managing the agency's cutbacks and streamlining the grant-giving operations. Her attempt to tap other sources of funding is commendable. But it would be a shame if, in the process, critics of the endowment use them as an excuse to squeeze it tighter. Support for the arts  is a worthy objective of any government that cares about elevating and educating all its citizens.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
