<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="859604"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFDA1539F930A15755C0A960958260" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 3-12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 3-12</p>
        <p>IRAQ'S STOLEN ANTIQUITIES As Iraqis continue to suffer from stringent economic sanctions, art experts and  archeologists say, precious antiquities from ancient civilizations are pouring into the international market to raise cash. 1</p>
        <p>A NEW COURSE FOR INDIA With the new Prime Minister, India has marked a transition from a leadership of  upper-caste Brahmins to a Government led by a lower-caste son of a farmer. 3</p>
        <p>INDONESIAN LOSES PARTY SUPPORT Indonesia's most prominent opposition figure, Megawati Sukarnoputri, was ousted  from her party's leadership by rival members supported by the Government. 4</p>
        <p>SIERRA LEONE REBEL TALKS PEACE Foday Sankoh, a shadowy guerrilla leader from Sierra Leone, emerged recently from the bush to engage in peace talks. He says he is still roiled by offenses that caused him to start fighting. 6</p>
        <p>ARAB LEADERS MEET IN CAIRO Twenty-one Arab leaders gathered in Cairo to express alarm at the early hard line taken by Israel's new Government. 8</p>
        <p>Japan's manhunt for fugitives in a subway gas attack is in vain. 5</p>
        <p>Chile's Santiago zoo is hostile to man and beast. 6</p>
        <p>Europe protests U.S sanctions aimed at Cuba, Iran and Libya. 12 National 14-26</p>
        <p>RIGHT TO KNOW ABOUT WATER Congress is considering a far-reaching proposal requiring municipal water systems to tell the public what contaminants have been found in local drinking water. 1</p>
        <p>TROUBLE IN FOREIGN ADOPTIONS While most of the recent American adoptions of children from Eastern Europe and  Russia have gone well, a growing number of the parents say their children have serious problems that do not naturally evaporate under the love and care of doting families. 1</p>
        <p>DISCORD IN THE TEXAS G.O.P. At the Texas Republican Party convention, anti-abortion forces denied delegate slots at the party's national convention to several prominent Texans who had been nominated by the Dole campaign, but Senator Kay Bailey Hutchison kept hers. 1</p>
        <p>PARAMILITARY MOVEMENT IN OHIO The case of a paramilitary enthusiast from a well-respected family in Ohio is as complex to judge as the Patriot movement itself. 1</p>
        <p>THE CHURCH FIRE AGONIES While the string of fires at black churches in the South reflects the dynamics peculiar to that region, the burnings are also indicative of the agonies of race and ethnicity throughout the nation. 14</p>
        <p>WARNER VS. WARNER In Virginia, Warner vs. Warner is not a movie sequel or even a divorce case. It  is a big-money Senate race, and each candidate is trying to one-up the other in  the name game. 18</p>
        <p>A BATTLE CONTINUES The superintendent of the Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument is a Mandan Hidatsa Indian who passionately wants to make it a more welcoming place for Indians. But he is finding that for many on both sides of the fight the wounds continue to be tender. 20</p>
        <p>Metropolitan 27-33</p>
        <p>A STRING OF SERIAL ARRESTS In one astonishing week, three men whom the authorities describe as belonging to a macabre fraternity -- those who attack a series of strangers -- were caught in the New York region, in something of an arrest spree. 27</p>
        <p>STUDYING BID TO HOST OLYMPICS A team of New York City officials and business leaders is exploring ways to bring the Summer Olympics to the city in 2008. Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani is convening a task force to study the feasibility and benefits of hosting the lucrative Summer Games. 27</p>
        <p>A CLOISTER UNTOUCHED BY TIME Behind the high stone wall and black iron gates of Our Lady of Mount Carmel Monastery in Crown Heights, Brooklyn, a group of cloistered Carmelite nuns live  in complete isolation, a life that is rooted in the 16th century and mystifies the rest of the neigborhood. 27</p>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund 30</p>
        <p>Obituaries 33-34 Andreas Papandreou, the former Prime Minister of Greece</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
