<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Brits Enjoy a Better Week Than Bumbling Mets</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="617886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TENNIS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WIMBLEDON TENNIS TOURNAMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DE1039F934A15755C0A965958260" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Brits Enjoy a Better Week Than Bumbling Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Homesickness washes over the visting New Yorker. It is not the burgers they insist upon selling, nor is it the corn on the cob and the hot dogs the pubs drag out to celebrate the Fourth of July. What makes the New Yorker miss home so much is the bark of the pack, hot on the whiff of failure.</p>
        <p>There is no Mike and there is no Mad Dog, at least not on my civilized BBC radio band, but they do have their rabid tabloids here, and they are yowling about the failure of the national cricket team and the national soccer team. Two sports they invented, by the way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Homesickness washes over the visting New Yorker. It is not the burgers they insist upon selling, nor is it the corn on the cob and the hot dogs the pubs drag out to celebrate the Fourth of July. What makes the New Yorker miss home so much is the bark of the pack, hot on the whiff of failure.</p>
        <p>There is no Mike and there is no Mad Dog, at least not on my civilized BBC radio band, but they do have their rabid tabloids here, and they are yowling about the failure of the national cricket team and the national soccer team. Two sports they invented, by the way.</p>
        <p>England does not lack for sporting heroes -- I give you Daley Thompson of the decathlon and Nick Faldo of golf -- but the tabs always seem to be yowling about the inadequacies of British tennis, usually accompanied by great dripping downpours.</p>
        <p>This year is slightly different. For one thing, it has not rained one drop during play. For another thing, the Brits have had their moments on the court. Chris Bailey terrorized Goran Ivanisevic into the dusk on Thursday. Andrew Foster (Hero Foz, to the tabs) has actually survived to the second week, to play Pete Sampras in the round of 16.</p>
        <p>And yesterday, Chris Wilkinson, a 23-year-old from Southampton, made it to the place they call Centre Court. He was playing Stefan Edberg, who lives in the Kensington district of London, which did not sway the fans at Center Court.</p>
        <p>"Edberg is not just playing Chris. He is playing the whole of Center Court and the rest of Britain as well," Bailey said after his long match with Ivanisevic. "The crowd gave me such a lift and every time they roared it brought me out in goose bumps."</p>
        <p>The noise at Center Court does not reach the level that Shea Stadium fans used to make when giants like Hernandez and Carter and Strawberry walked the earth. But the British fans did yell "Chris! Chris! Chris!" with such wild abandon that the chair umpire actually had to caution, "Quiet please," and "Thank you," a few times.</p>
        <p>Wilkinson played with the pluck that Britons have always admired in their soccer players, diving to the ground nearly a dozen times in pursuit of the ball. Edberg lost his serve five times in three sets, but he wound up manhandling Wilkinson, 6-4, 7-5, 6-3, all the same.</p>
        <p>Who said England does not have tennis heroes? It was something like Old-Timers' Day in the Royal Box, which was devoid of major royals. After Wilkinson's match, the announcer introduced a few retired footballers and rugby players as well as former Wimbledon champions and former Davis Cup aces. Unfortunately, the latter were all around 85.</p>
        <p>Fred Perry, the hero of the four straight Davis Cup title squads from 1933-36, looked as fit as his statue on the grounds of Wimbledon, and more combative than some of the modern-day lads.</p>
        <p>The prevailing cliche is that the stiff upper lip of any tennis-playing Briton inhibits going for somebody else's jugular. There was a hopeful note this week when Foster accepted a default by the flu-ridden Andrei Olhovskiy without so much as a protest. Was this a sign of new killer instinct in the young Brits?</p>
        <p>Foster wouldn't go that far, but he said, "I don't think you'll find Jim Courier being too sympathetic, really."</p>
        <p>Will England ever be a force in world tennis? Bailey stuck it to his country on Thursday when he noted that Wimbledon generates millions of dollars but that the Lawn Tennis Association had threatened to cut off the funding of his private coach. Tennisgate. The next morning a tennis official named Richard Lewis claimed it was just a "misunderstanding."</p>
        <p>American sporting frenzies tend to be regional or local. If our college basketball players fail to win a gold medal at the Summer Games, we send out Michael Jordan or Charles Barkley the next time. England's traumas are national.</p>
        <p>The English lost to Norway and the United States in soccer a few weeks ago. Manager Graham Taylor must go, the headlines say. The English lost their last cricket test match so badly that the entire Australian batting order skipped its second time around. Captain Graham Gooch must go, the headlines say.</p>
        <p>"Venus may be in the wrong juxtaposition with somewhere else," said Ted Dexter, the chairman of selection for the cricket team.</p>
        <p>This was more novel than the goofy explanations for Bobby Bonilla calling the press box to complain about the official scoring. Old-fashioned New Yorkers would have a soft spot for underdogs like England. Plus, the English didn't trade Lenny Dykstra.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
