<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rural Plateau and Its Earthy Cuisine</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="617897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ITALY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PUGLIA (ITALY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FANT, MAUREEN B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Puglia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DE1E39F934A15755C0A965958260" item-length="2515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rural Plateau and Its Earthy Cuisine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN B. FANT;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FANT, MAUREEN B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I DISCOVERED Puglia about 15 years ago while seeking a route from Rome to Greece. There had to be an alternative to the long, boring train ride to the Brindisi ferry; there had at least to be something to see on the way. The logical place to begin looking was the region to which the port of Brindisi belongs, Puglia.</p>
        <p>As an archeology student, I knew a few things about the area: that the modern region of Puglia corresponds to ancient Apulia plus ancient Calabria, which has nothing to do with modern Calabria; that there were pre-Greek people called Apuli, Peucetii and Messapii; that the museum of Taranto, the Spartan colony of Taras and later Roman Tarentum, was worth any amount of difficulty to see; that in 37 B.C. the Roman poet Horace had had any amount of difficulty getting to Brundisium, terminus of the Via Appia; and that Virgil had died there on his way back from Greece in 19 B.C. The modern version of the trip did not offer hope that the poets' experiences had been exceptional.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I DISCOVERED Puglia about 15 years ago while seeking a route from Rome to Greece. There had to be an alternative to the long, boring train ride to the Brindisi ferry; there had at least to be something to see on the way. The logical place to begin looking was the region to which the port of Brindisi belongs, Puglia.</p>
        <p>As an archeology student, I knew a few things about the area: that the modern region of Puglia corresponds to ancient Apulia plus ancient Calabria, which has nothing to do with modern Calabria; that there were pre-Greek people called Apuli, Peucetii and Messapii; that the museum of Taranto, the Spartan colony of Taras and later Roman Tarentum, was worth any amount of difficulty to see; that in 37 B.C. the Roman poet Horace had had any amount of difficulty getting to Brundisium, terminus of the Via Appia; and that Virgil had died there on his way back from Greece in 19 B.C. The modern version of the trip did not offer hope that the poets' experiences had been exceptional.</p>
        <p>Figuring, however, that there must be more to Puglia than that, I read "A Traveler in Southern Italy" by H. V. Morton (Methuen, London, 1969) and met Frederick II and the Swabians, St. Nicholas, the Normans and Irish saints. I learned of cathedrals, castles, Baroque architecture, bright white towns of Oriental cast and cone-roofed farmhouses called trulli strewn across the countryside. In the end we flew to Bari, sight-saw our way down to Otranto, deep in the heel, took the passenger ferry from there to Corfu, and considered the trip a success.</p>
        <p>I'd been trying to get back to Puglia ever since, and this year, my friend Franco Filippi and I had hoped finally to explore the whole region. But when work pressures turned our planned fortnight into a long weekend, we decided to concentrate on one easily defined area, the Murgia (high ground) dei Trulli and Valle d'Itria. The area, which extends inland from the coast about equidistant from Bari and Brindisi, is easily circumnavigated in a couple of hours and offers a complete change of scene from the rolling green hills of the Latian-Umbrian-Tuscan landscape we're used to. That was one reason for our choice; the other was the reputation of the local cuisine, rooted in the land and sheep raising, and considered by many Puglia's most interesting. We were perfectly satisfied on both fronts, and found more besides.</p>
        <p>We rented a car at Brindisi airport and started westward for Martina Franca, a small city of famous beauty that we'd chosen as our base. About half an hour later, in a countryside of red earth, olive groves and vineyards, we began to see our first trulli and near them multitudinous low dry-stone walls.</p>
        <p>The trulli, unique to Puglia (though structures with affinities can be seen around the Mediterranean), are concentrated in this area; their derivation is unknown, but they are well suited to the local materials and climate. Pasquale Montanaro, a young architect in Locorotondo who wrote his university thesis on the trulli, says that the earliest attested mention of trulli by that name dates from the 14th century, and that the first trulli were probably built as early as the 10th century. Examples of churches and bell towers with conelike domes exist that can be dated back that far; Mr. Montanaro's plausible theory is that the houses were knocked down and rebuilt, whereas the churches were carefully preserved. The oldest surviving domestic trullo is just outside Locorotondo and dates to the 16th century.</p>
        <p>Trulli are circular dry-stone constructions of blocks of local limestone. They can be singles or multi-coned clusters. The characteristic roofs are made of concentric rings of limestone slabs called chiancarelle, which gradually decrease in diameter to form a conical roof, which in turn is topped by a white pinnacle. The lower part of the house and the pinnacle are whitewashed, and the gray limestone of the cone is often painted with large white folk or religious symbols.  The oldest trulli are completely round, while the more recent ones, dating from the late 19th century to the 1940's, have square bottoms and conical tops. Some recently renovated trulli are ghastly hybrids, at their worst displaying the gilded aluminum window and door frames that blight venerable Italian towns. About 10 families of specialized trullari preserve the craft of building and restoring trulli, and young people are keeping the knowledge going.</p>
        <p>ALTHOUGH Puglia is one of the most fertile and productive areas of Italy -- most of the country's wheat for pasta is grown there and the region's dense, strong olive oil is highly respected -- its agriculture is characterized by tiny "handkerchiefs" of land, the result of generations of subdivision, hence all those little walls.</p>
        <p>Such fragmentation lies behind the persistent rural poverty. The other distinguishing feature is that the countryside is inhabited, apparently densely, with farmers living as near as possible to their fields. Clusters of houses, called contradas, grew up, but real towns were the exception. In the hillier country of other parts of Italy, on the other hand, farmers live in towns and commute.</p>
        <p>We followed the trulli to the edge of Martina Franca, and prepared to be impressed by the legendary beauty of its anomalous white Baroque architecture. But the periphery was much like that of any other southern Italian town with the striking exception of the odd trullo engulfed by the urban sprawl.</p>
        <p>Our fears of having come to Martina Franca 30 years too late were soon allayed at our first look at the pedestrians-only centro storico, or old town. It is white and beautiful, as advertised, with wrought-iron balconies and 18th-century the dominant style. Clean and orderly and highly exotic, it looks Spanish or Moorish (the Saracen influence being the common factor) despite the clearly Italianate Baroque architecture. We had what was intended to be a light lunch at the Trattoria ai Portici in the centro, a typical provincial trattoria, complete with television. Our antipasto was a parade of little dishes containing black olives, fresh sheep cheeses, eggplant rolls, capocollo, soppressata (salami) and prosciutto. We followed that with orecchiette (literally little ears) with tomato and basil. These are the best known Pugliese pasta, little rounds sliced off a roll of dough and pressed with the thumb for a concave, or earlike, effect. I buy these dry all the time in Rome, but there is no comparison with the fresh, local version.</p>
        <p>Not satisfied with food and architecture alone, we drove about half an hour to the Grotte di Castellana, on the northern edge of the trulli district, Italy's largest and most spectacular caves. Natural wonders and a tourist attraction of some note, they should be avoided completely in July and August. On a Saturday afternoon in June, however, the crowds were modest and the guided tour to the White Cave (Grotta Bianca), supposedly voted the most beautiful cave in the world by speleologists, took somewhat less than the announced two hours (forget the shorter one-hour tour, which does not reach the White Cave).</p>
        <p>We'd been advised by Pugliese gourmets that we'd find the genuine local cuisine in a rather elegant restaurant, Al Fornello da Ricci, on the outskirts of Ceglie Messapico, 11 miles southeast of Martina Franca. Although it's becoming less and less advisable to accept the Italian restaurateur's casual disregard for written menus, we'd been told that we should just let Mr. Ricci do what he wanted with us, and so we surrendered to an endless antipasto of fried potato croquettes, fried squash blossoms stuffed with ricotta, stuffed artichokes, green beans drenched in oil (which gave me new respect for the vegetable), olives, beets, tiny new potatoes, roasted peppers, pancetta (bacon), soppressata and fresh local sheep cheeses.</p>
        <p>IN place of pasta we had puffed grains of wheat boiled and served with a strong tomato sauce and pecorino cheese, then a puree of fava beans with boiled greens. The main course, for which we had little room, was typical skewer-roasted meat -- lamb, mixed veal and pork sausage, and the local involtino (roll-up), lamb liver wrapped in a piece of lamb intestine. Here and everywhere else, the breadbasket was kept filled with taralli, like small unsalted pretzels and about as habit-forming. Quality and quantity came out with even scores -- both high.</p>
        <p>We saw a rougher version of the same skewer at a town festival in Locorotondo, about four miles north of Martina Franca, on Sunday evening. On Wednesday and Saturday evenings, and on special occasions like this one, the town butchers make up large skewers with sausages, involtini and pieces of lamb and cook them to order. We fell in love with Locorotondo, but not for the skewers. First, the town is beautiful. As the name suggests, it's circular, and sits on high ground, about 1,300 feet above the valley. Its center is white punctuated with flower-laden iron balconies, Baroque carvings and stone gabled roofs (such houses are known as cummerse, and the style is traditional for use in town; the building technique is very different from that used for trulli, which belong to the countryside). Most impressive, it's well kept and orderly, and despite its familiar name, thanks to its famous wine, doesn't rely on tourism to give it a sense of identity. We sat in the public gardens and watched the struscio, the evening promenade, which appropriately was conducted at a brisk pace in a circular pattern rather than back and forth.</p>
        <p>In contrast, Alberobello, about nine miles north of Martina Franca and considered the trulli capital, has sold out to tourism. It is atypical of the area, a sizable town, founded at the end of the 17th century, of more than a thousand trulli, and is, despite a heavy dose of schlock, well worth seeing once in your life. One shop can be recommended, that of Giuseppe Maffei (Via Duca d'Aosta 4/8), a real craftsman who sells his carefully made limestone trulli models in various sizes. Fifteen years ago I saw the town quite unspoiled, with just an occasional naive hand-lettered sign in German offering a view from a roof or some such, so you knew even then they knew how cute they were.</p>
        <p>Another change since my last visit is the addition of a very good, very serious gourmet restaurant, Il Poeta Contadino (the Peasant Poet), which some Pugliese friends of friends invited us to try with them. It calls itself a rustic restaurant, and indeed is installed in a former barn (albeit huge and stone), but the style is more Paris than rural Puglia. The owner, Leonardo Marco (whose father built the barn), offers a highly refined, often creative menu featuring both meat and fish. We chose the "land" (which is to say meat) tasting menu, on grounds that it was more suited to the place, though many of the dishes, despite their use of local ingredients, could not have been conceived outside such a rarefied setting. For example, we started with a sformato di carciofi, a sort of artichoke pudding held together with ricotta and goat cheese; dessert was focaccia di mandorle, an almond cake with a black cherry sauce -- all authentic ingredients in very fancy dress. The ficelle con cime di rape e pomodorini (handmade pasta with greens and small tomatoes) and agnello a cutturidd' (a sort of lamb and chicory stew), both exquisite, clearly showed their peasant roots through all the refinement. Pugliese wines are represented on the wine list, as a small minority, though Locorotondo, from just down the road, is snubbed.</p>
        <p>For our last morning we drove first to the pretty town of Cisternino (five miles) and on to the coast by way of Ostuni (another eight miles), which really looks as though it was airlifted in from an Aegean island -- all steps and whitewash, reapplied several times a year -- with just a few souvenir shops around the edges. Ostuni is on three hills, of which the old town occupies one, but below it on the sea is a typical coastline of small beach houses and modern hotels. June not yet being vacation season, they were still fairly deserted. We drove up the coast 12 miles to the large archeological site of Egnazia (ancient Gnathia), with Messapian and Roman remains (none remaining to any great height, but interesting nonetheless), but didn't find our hoped-for fish lunch. We'd been told that this coast had little in the way of restaurants, the culinary traditions being land-based, and in any case Monday is a bad day for fish anywhere, there being no catch on Sunday.</p>
        <p>So we turned just inland to the countryside outside the town of Fasano where a 17th-century fortified farmhouse complete with tower, called Masseria Salamina (masseria is a generic term for a large farm), has been converted into a rustic hotel and restaurant. The furnishings are a bit modern (cane-seated chairs), but the stone walls and traditional food are genuine, and the atmosphere marvelously peaceful, at least on a Monday. We had puree of favas and chicory, and spaghetti with green beans and grated cacio ricotta cheese, then roast lamb, and -- a nod to the nearby Adriatic -- octopus.</p>
        <p>Masseria Salamina, we decided, was where we should have stayed for our three-day break -- and would be the first place we'd return next time. EXPLORING THE TRULLO COUNTRY OF PUGLIA Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Masseria Salamina, Azienda Agrituristica, 72010 Pezze di Greco, Fasano (Brindisi); (080) 727307. Closed Tuesday. Lunch for two with carafe of wine $40 (no credit cards accepted).</p>
        <p>Trattoria ai Portici, Piazza Immacolata 4/ 6, Martina Franca (Taranto); (080) 701702. Closed Tuesday. Meal for two with wine about $54.</p>
        <p>Il Poeta Contadino, Via Indipendenza 21, Alberobello (Bari); (080) 721917. Closed Sunday evening and Monday. Menu changes with the season. Meal for two with wine about $101 (all major credit cards accepted).</p>
        <p>Trattoria Centro Storico, Via Eroi di Dogali 6, Locorotondo (Bari); (080) 9315473. Closed Wednesday in winter. Meal for two with wine about $40.</p>
        <p>Al Fornello da Ricci, Contrada Montevicoli, Ceglie Messapico (Brindisi); (0831) 977104. Closed Monday evening and all day Tuesday. Meal for two with wine, about $81 (all major credit cards except American Express accepted).  Where to Stay</p>
        <p>The area does not offer a great variety of interesting hotels, though it's not hard simply to drive around and find a decent place to sleep either on the coast or inland.</p>
        <p>Masseria Salamina, Azienda Agrituristica, 72010 Pezze di Greco, Fasano (Brindisi); (080) 727307. Rates vary with season; through Sept. 11, a double is $68.</p>
        <p>Hotel al Casale, Via Gorizia 39/41, 70010 Locorotondo (Bari); (080) 9311377. Double $61 with breakfast; single $34 with breakfast. These rooms are a good deal more modern and spacious than the unprepossessing facade would lead one to believe.</p>
        <p>Park Hotel San Michele, Viale Carella 9, Martina Franca (Taranto); telephone (080) 8807053, fax (080) 8808895. Double $101 with breakfast. The hotel is well equipped but lacking in charm, despite a pretty garden and pool.</p>
        <p>MAUREEN B. FANT is the author of "Eat Like the Romans: The Visitor's Food Guide" (Alphabyte, Rome).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">MAUREEN B. FANT is the author of "Eat Like the Romans: The Visitor's Food Guide" (Alphabyte, Rome).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
