<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Modern-Dress 'Hamlet' Takes an Unusual Spin</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="618168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">STUDIO THEATER (LINDENHURST, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANK, LEAH D</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HAMLET (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D71730F934A15755C0A965958260" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Modern-Dress 'Hamlet' Takes an Unusual Spin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEAH D. FRANK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRANK, LEAH D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is a pleasant surprise to have a prejudice shattered, as one of this writer's was last week by Studio Theater in Lindenhurst.</p>
        <p>The publicity sent out by the theater read: " 'Hamlet' . . . staged in modern dress, with a new score . . . This production . . . is like none that has ever crossed the boards before."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is a pleasant surprise to have a prejudice shattered, as one of this writer's was last week by Studio Theater in Lindenhurst.</p>
        <p>The publicity sent out by the theater read: " 'Hamlet' . . . staged in modern dress, with a new score . . . This production . . . is like none that has ever crossed the boards before."</p>
        <p>Not only is this "Hamlet" being done with a musical score, but it also is being presented with only nine actors and without an intermission. That is the type of publicity that at best signals a "Saturday Night Live" skit or, in all probability, a very dreary evening of semiprofessional theater.</p>
        <p>It is a pleasure to report that this production, give or take a few awkward transitions, is spellbinding.</p>
        <p>First of all, Georgia Mcgill has directed the play in such a manner that although the focus is on the character of Hamlet, the thrust of the production is on the extensive theatricality within Shakespeare's play.</p>
        <p>The ghost of the murdered king, often a problem to stage, is here calm and patient, but insistent that justice be done. Ms. Mcgill double-casts the actor who plays the ghost as the Player King, whose troupe of actors sets the trap to catch the King's murderer.</p>
        <p>When the Player King re-enacts the murder of King Hamlet, the scene, because it is played by the same actor in the same costume, becomes a flashback to that moment in the garden when Claudius pours poison into the King's ear.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mcgill has used the technique of collapsing scenes into one another so that, as an example, when Claudius and Laertes plot Hamlet's death, the discussion occurs as the duel proceeds. And as Gertrude relates the story of Ophelia's drowning to her brother, we watch that tragedy as it happens.</p>
        <p>Queen Gertrude and the newly crowned King Claudius sit, one on each side of the stage, watching the action throughout the play. The audience is treated like members of the Danish court experiencing their kingdom's tragedy firsthand.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mcgill toys with the element of time, and although her intent is to shorten "Hamlet" for television-bred audiences unaccustomed to long multiple-act historical dramas, the effect is to create a fresh approach to a frequently performed classic.</p>
        <p>All of her good work would be for naught, however, were it not for the strong, passionate and intelligent performance turned in by Fred Maliszewski as Hamlet. Here is a young prince who is unsure of himself, depressed by the sudden death of his father and offended by the quick marriage of his mother to his uncle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maliszewski's performance encompasses all of the insecurities of youth with the addition of a moral fervor that can be frightening in its intensity. Yet through all of the manic-depressive moods to which Hamlet is prone, Mr. Maliszewski manages to let traces of a kind, gentle young man shine through. Regardless of his self-doubts, this prince would clearly have become a good and just king had fate taken a different turn.</p>
        <p>Louise M. Millman's Gertrude is a stark woman who eschews makeup and pins her hair back and close to her skull. In this version, the queen's actions make sense as those of a plain woman overwhelmed by the flair and attention of her late husband's brother.</p>
        <p>The other standout in the cast is Eric Pourchot as both the pompous, flighty busybody Polonius and as the pragmatic, jocular Grave Digger.  Michele Cuomo gives a very creditable performance as Ophelia, the young woman who suffers from a terrible teen-age crush on Hamlet.</p>
        <p>Greg Dinunzi has composed music that underscores the entire play. This is not the sound of chirpy tunes but, rather, a relentless soft beat that keeps time to the throbbing, dark passion surging through Elsinore. By the end of the play, the music seems to echo Hamlet's fading heartbeat as he dies.</p>
        <p>The "modern dress" consists of soft, draping jackets, pants and skirts mostly in a variety of shades of basic brown, black and gray, which turns out to be an intelligent artistic choice for a low-budget production. The alternative of cheap brocade and velvet tunics and ill-fitting tights makes modern dress very sensible indeed.</p>
        <p>No credit is given for costume or set design, but like the costumes, the set is simple and extraordinarily effective. The stage is bare, with a black floor and black rear curtain. The only set pieces are tall red chairs whose long narrow rungs stand as silent symbols of the rivers of blood that purged that Denmark from the sins of its royalty.</p>
        <p>"Hamlet" continues at the Studio through next Sunday.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
