<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who's Minding the Baby? It Sounds Like Ali</title>
    <meta content="15INKY$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/15/theater/reviews/15inky.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1657178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Groff, Rinne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greco, Loretta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Campbell, Jessi</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Inky (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Inky (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4DC123CF936A25750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who's Minding the Baby? It Sounds Like Ali</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Who's Minding the Baby? It Sounds Like Ali</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood reviews Rinne Groff play Inky, directed by Loretta Greco and starring Jessi Campbell; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beware the nanny with bruised knuckles. That's the only conclusion to draw from Rinne Groff's ''Inky,'' a peculiar, unfocused comedy about the competitive ethics of the 1980's that opened last night at the Julia Miles Theater.</p>
        <p>The title is the odd nickname for the odd main character, a young woman of vaguely Eastern European background installed as au pair in the chic but cramped apartment of Barbara (Marianne Hagan) and Greg (Jason Pugatch), a young couple determined to scale the peaks of Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beware the nanny with bruised knuckles. That's the only conclusion to draw from Rinne Groff's peculiar, unfocused comedy at the Julie Miles Theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beware the nanny with bruised knuckles. That's the only conclusion to draw from Rinne Groff's ''Inky,'' a peculiar, unfocused comedy about the competitive ethics of the 1980's that opened last night at the Julia Miles Theater.</p>
        <p>The title is the odd nickname for the odd main character, a young woman of vaguely Eastern European background installed as au pair in the chic but cramped apartment of Barbara (Marianne Hagan) and Greg (Jason Pugatch), a young couple determined to scale the peaks of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Actually, it's primarily Barbara, played histrionically by Ms. Hagan as a pouting virago who dreams of swollen status. Foreplay for her is a game in which she strips her husband's clothes away in search of hidden dollar bills.</p>
        <p>Since Barbara displays an almost pathological aversion to her new baby boy and her 9-year-old daughter, Allison, and Greg is slaving night and day to accommodate Barbara's insistent demands for a real estate upgrade, child care falls to Inky.</p>
        <p>This proves problematic, since this innocent-eyed, skinny-limbed young woman, played with an intriguing opacity by Jessi Campbell in a promising New York stage debut, is unnaturally obsessed with Muhammad Ali. The play's short scenes are intercut with segments in which Inky repeats verbatim Ali's famed bursts of braggadocio in her comically garbled accent as she bobs on her toes and spars with an imaginary partner.</p>
        <p>These quirky monologues strike an appealingly surreal note, but Ms. Groff's comic jabs don't always hit their marks. In fact, as the play's brief scenes shuffle by, in Loretta Greco's languid staging, the objects of Ms. Groff's satiric feints grow increasingly unclear, and her perspective on her characters grows ever blurrier.</p>
        <p>Barbara, who falls under the spell of Inky's odd fixation, suddenly begins speaking of a desire to take a good punch, both literally and figuratively. ''Don't you sometimes feel like you want to know something beyond all this privilege?'' she asks Greg late in the play.</p>
        <p>''Now you think we're too privileged?'' he responds with a disbelief probably shared by the audience, given Barbara's previously overstated rapaciousness and the suddenness of this reversal.</p>
        <p>It is hard to tell whether Inky's obsession with Ali is meant to be a symptom of the era's warped ethical values or a healthy route to feminine empowerment. It cannot logically be both. She speaks vaguely to Barbara of being sexually abused, but it's hard not to sympathize with Greg's outrage when he learns Inky has conscripted Allison into a scheme to cheat the Girl Scouts of their cookie dough, so to speak. (Barbara thinks it's a riot.)</p>
        <p>Worse follows, as Inky begins systematically undermining Greg's relationship with his family, ultimately resorting to outright emotional and sexual blackmail. But since Greg, played with an aptly beleaguered air by Mr. Pugatch, is the only reasonably sympathetic -- and consistent -- character in the play, we are naturally repelled by Inky's choice of an aggressive role model.</p>
        <p>And yet at the play's hopeful conclusion, Allison (Elizabeth Schweitzer), who has pointedly been kept offstage throughout the proceedings, parrots Inky's Ali impersonation, to the apparent delight of her parents.</p>
        <p>Ms. Groff threads references to combat throughout the dialogue. In the play's last scene, Barbara, her values apparently entirely transformed, wistfully asks Greg, ''What have you been fighting for?'' But Ms. Groff is too vague in her use of this imagery, and too loose in her observation of character, for such implicit statements about the aridity of the rat race to hit home.</p>
        <p>'Inky'</p>
        <p>By Rinne Groff; directed by Loretta Greco; set by Robert Brill; costumes by Valerie Marcus Ramshur; lighting by Sarah Sidman; original music and sound, Robert Kaplowitz; production stage manager, Brian Westmoreland; production management, Dynamic Productions. Presented by Women's Project, Ms. Greco, producing artistic director; Jane Ann Crum, managing director; vocal consultant, K.C. Ligon; fight choreography by Angel David. At the Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton; (212)239-6200. Through April 3. Running time: 1 hour 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Jessi Campbell (Inky), Marianne Hagan (Barbara), Jason Pugatch (Greg) and Elizabeth Schweitzer (Allison).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
