<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wine Talk</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="706781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WINE TALK (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2DC1E30F934A2575BC0A962958260" item-length="1126" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wine Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REMEMBER your first visit to New York? To Paris? London? You had read everything you could get your hands on about the city and spent months fantasizing about the trip.</p>
        <p>And what was your first impression? Wonderful? Yes. Exciting? Perhaps. But not at all like what you'd imagined. Right?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REMEMBER your first visit to New York? To Paris? London? You had read everything you could get your hands on about the city and spent months fantasizing about the trip.</p>
        <p>And what was your first impression? Wonderful? Yes. Exciting? Perhaps. But not at all like what you'd imagined. Right?</p>
        <p>Wine is like that. Wine descriptions in newspapers and magazines, in advertisements and on bottle labels tend to be overblown or precious or both. Only occasionally do they correspond to what's in the bottle.</p>
        <p>Several years ago, a writer named Tom Maresca laid out a clear and effective plan for understanding and appreciating the subject in a book called, optimistically, Mastering Wine (Grove Press, revised 1992; $12.95).</p>
        <p>Mr. Maresca's method is a model of simplicity: he pairs wines and pretty much lets them speak for themselves. Two cabernet sauvignons, perhaps, or a cabernet and a merlot. A Burgundy and a Bordeaux in one instance; a California chardonnay and a chardonnay from New Zealand in another. Mr. Maresca's pairings become quite sophisticated in the later stages of his program, but the technique is no less sound for that.</p>
        <p>The principle is this: No amount of verbiage can compare with a taste comparison. The late Alexis Lichine put it another way: "There is no substitute for pulling corks."</p>
        <p>Provoking these reflections is thefall issue of Wine and Spirits, a consumer magazine. Most of it is devoted to a "tasting tour" of wines made from five popular grapes: cabernet sauvignon, chardonnay, pinot noir, riesling and sangiovese. Mr. Maresca's book, the magazine acknowledges, provided the inspiration for the issue.</p>
        <p>Six to eight pairs were examined in each category. One cabernet coupling included two relatively inexpensive wines, a 1990 Mouton-Cadet from Bordeaux at about $9 and a 1993 California cabernet under the Vendange label for about $6. The French wine was relatively delicate and subtle while the California selection was deeper-hued and fruiter -- "a little strutting powerhouse of cabernet fruit," the magazine said.</p>
        <p>Under the theme "power and grace," a Fetzer 1991 North Coast Barrel Select cabernet from California, for about $12, had the power, with its "mouth-scouring tannins," while a Santa Rita Maipo Valley Reserva from Chile, which was $8.50 and also from 1991, had the grace, with "an elegant, soft texture."</p>
        <p>In another cabernet pairing a $9 Cousino-Macul 1990 Maipo Valley Antiguas Reservas, from a 57-year-old Chilean vineyard, was compared with a $24 Jordan Vineyard 1990 Alexander Valley, from 20- to 25-year-old California vines. Both had a similar soft, rounded texture, but the Chilean vines produce a wine with an intense, concentrated bouquet that makes it seem much older than its four years, the magazine said.</p>
        <p>One chardonnay pairing included a Meursault from Burgundy, bottled by Louis Jadot and priced at about $24, and a chardonnay from the Stone street winery in Sonoma County, priced at about $20. Meursault, like all fine white Burgundy, is 100 percent chardonnay. The French wine, from a cooler climate, was slightly more acidic, but both proved to be "big and round and full-bodied."</p>
        <p>Another chardonnay grouping compared wines from three vineyards owned by the same winery, Chateau Woltner in the Napa Valley. The differences were subtle.</p>
        <p>A French Champagne made entirely from chardonnay grapes, a Pol Roger 1986 Brut Chardonnay, priced at about $60, showed itself to be more elegant than a Scharffenberger 1989 Mendocino Brut Blanc de Blancs, priced at about $20.</p>
        <p>Wines and Spirits noted a curious juxtaposition of descriptive terms on the labels of the Pol Roger and the Scharffenberger. The French label emphasizes that the wine is made from white chardonnay grapes, while the American label uses the French term for the same thing, blanc de blancs.</p>
        <p>In the pinot noir category, a subtle 1989 Chambolle-Musigny from Burgundy, bottled by Joseph Drouhin and priced at about $30, was almost but not quite overwhelmed by an aggressive $15 1992 pinot noir from Au Bon Climat, a winery from California's Santa Maria Valley.</p>
        <p>A New York State riesling, Glenora 1992, Finger Lakes, about $8, was matched with a Deinhard 1991 Kabinett, from Germany's Mosel region, priced at about $13. Apart from alcohol content -- 8.5 percent for the German wine, 11 percent for the one from New York -- differences here were mostly stylistic.</p>
        <p>In the one comparison between an Italian sangiovese and one from California, the results are not markedly different from those found in the other pairings of Californian and European wines. A 1991 Bolla Sangiovese di Romana, for $6, was "lively and tannic"; a 1992 Atlas Peak Napa Valley Sangiovese, at $16, was "bigger and softer on the tongue, with an abundance of seemingly riper but more generalized, less sharply identified fruit flavors."</p>
        <p>Many of the wines in these 35 groupings were too similar to show any obvious differences in taste or aroma. Writing about them, just like tasting them, becomes an exercise in nuance, which presumably is what interests the readers of wine magazines.</p>
        <p>The tasting technique is particularly valuable to the neophyte. It's a game anyone can play: Take two bottles of red or white wine at about the same price and open simultaneously. It constitutes a miniature wine course. Do they look different? In what way? Do they smell different? Which one smells best? How does one taste, compared with the other? Which is a better buy? Stick with the one you like best or use it as the basis for future pairings. Either way, you've gained confidence. You're no longer a stranger to wine and you're poised to learn -- and enjoy -- much more.</p>
        <p>And if you didn't like either bottle? Try two more. Or stay with lite beer.</p>
        <p>TASTINGS</p>
        <p>Penfolds Organic Chardonnay/Sauvignon Blanc, 1993, Australia. About $10.</p>
        <p>Penfolds, a large wine producer based in the Barossa Valley of South Australia, is best known for its red wines, especially the Grange Hermitage. But the company, which is celebrating its 150th anniversary this year, has recently begun making white wines.</p>
        <p>This blend of two of the best-known white grapes offers some of the best attributes of both wines: the richness of chardonnay and the fruitiness of ripe sauvignon blanc. Seventy percent of the wine was given oak-barrel aging, but the oak flavors are sufficiently subdued so that they blend with the natural qualities of the wine rather than overpower them.</p>
        <p>Penfolds says the wine was made from grapes grown with "the latest organic viticultural techniques." That is, with fewer chemicals in fertilizers and insecticides. Thus, a large Australian producer has joined the ranks of wine makers who are experimenting with organic farming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
