<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="20MOVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="996541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6D8153FF933A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="4313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy movies and film series playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film or series. Ratings and running times are in parentheses. An index of reviews of films opening today appears on page 9.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>* ''THE APOSTLE,'' starring Robert Duvall and Farrah Fawcett. Directed by Mr. Duvall (not rated, 110 minutes). In a gutsy, gripping film that is unmistakably a labor of love, Mr.  Duvall gives the performance of his career.  He plays Sonny, a Southern preacher of vast charm and volcanic energy, as serious in his faith as he is flawed in nature. Driven to violence by trouble with his estranged wife, Sonny assaults her lover and finds himself on the run in the rural South. As he rebuilds his life, Mr. Duvall defines the man's very essence in unhurried, luxuriantly watchful scenes that capture the full flavor of Sonny's spiritual world. Real Southern parishioners contribute immeasurably to the churchgoing scenes in a film that never condescends to its subject or setting (Janet Maslin).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy movies and film series playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film or series. Ratings and running times are in parentheses. An index of reviews of films opening today appears on page 9.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>* ''THE APOSTLE,'' starring Robert Duvall and Farrah Fawcett. Directed by Mr. Duvall (not rated, 110 minutes). In a gutsy, gripping film that is unmistakably a labor of love, Mr.  Duvall gives the performance of his career.  He plays Sonny, a Southern preacher of vast charm and volcanic energy, as serious in his faith as he is flawed in nature. Driven to violence by trouble with his estranged wife, Sonny assaults her lover and finds himself on the run in the rural South. As he rebuilds his life, Mr. Duvall defines the man's very essence in unhurried, luxuriantly watchful scenes that capture the full flavor of Sonny's spiritual world. Real Southern parishioners contribute immeasurably to the churchgoing scenes in a film that never condescends to its subject or setting (Janet Maslin).</p>
        <p>* ''AS GOOD AS IT GETS,'' starring Jack Nicholson, Helen Hunt and Greg Kinnear. Directed by James L. Brooks (PG-13, 133 minutes). Nobody does a better job of backing characters into happiness than Mr. Brooks does, especially when those characters are so high-strung that happiness is almost out of the question. Echoing the quirky appeal of his ''Broadcast News'' in a more conventional sitcom atmosphere, this zinger-filled comedy a trois features high spirits, strong acting and tart writing. Mr. Nicholson, whose other recent performances have been virtually phoned in, is back in fine form playing an obsessive-compulsive misanthrope. His appalling, awfully funny wisecracks account for much of the film's spiky humor, especially after he winds up with the companions he deserves: a gentle gay painter (Mr. Kinnear) and a lovely, long-suffering waitress (Ms. Hunt) who is his own personal Alice Kramden. Complications ensue (Maslin).  ''BLUES BROTHERS 2000,'' starring Dan Aykroyd. Directed by John Landis (PG-13, 105 minutes). In this sequel, Elwood Blues (Mr. Aykroyd), released from prison after 18 years, sets out to reconstitute the Blues Brothers Band. In so doing, he becomes the mentor of an orphan boy and incurs the enmity of a state police commander, the Russian mafia and a white supremacist militia group. Once this film gets past its cumbersome plotting and gets down to its music, ''Blues Brothers 2000'' overrides the temptation to suggest buying the soundtrack and forgetting the rest. Without the film, one would miss the big, colorful, high-energy, helium-humored production numbers featuring performers like Aretha Franklin, B. B. King, James Brown, Sam Moore and a host of other big-name singers, instrumentalists and various other stars in cameo roles (Lawrence Van Gelder).  * ''THE BORROWERS,'' starring John Goodman. Directed by Peter Hewitt (PG, 83 minutes). This charming children's film based on books by Mary Norton combines a quaint, cozy style with skillful technological tricks.  The title characters are believably tiny, and the film enjoys their ingenuity with much more playfulness than similar toy stories like ''The Indian in the Cupboard.'' Borrowers themselves need no introduction: they live in ordinary houses, and they're the reason you can never find household objects that aren't nailed down. With much visual wit, the film enjoys their antics (like climbing refrigerator magnets as if scaling the side of a cliff) and Mr. Goodman's fine, hammy villainy as a lawyer who wants to evict two families: the little Borrowers and the life-sized Lenders. Mr. Goodman does especially well for an actor who played so many special-effects scenes to an empty fist (Maslin).  * ''THE BOXER,'' starring Daniel Day-Lewis and Emily Watson. Directed by Jim Sheridan (R, 107 minutes). This tender, wrenching Belfast drama takes a far more reflective view of Northern Ireland's ''troubles'' than the director's more fiery ''In the Name of the Father'' did. But it has no less passion or grit.  With prison and fighting as strong central metaphors, it casts Mr. Day-Lewis in the title role of a loner who has served a 14-year jail term and now wants the impossible: a peaceful, quiet life. The magical star of ''Breaking the Waves'' plays his estranged ex-sweetheart, now another prisoner's wife and also the daughter of an I.R.A. leader. ''You have to get rid of him, or you're going to find him in a pool of blood,'' he tells his daughter when the boxer returns home and rekindles the romance. Galvanized by such tensions, Mr. Sheridan tells a story of bravery, love and renewal with the stirring conviction that such things are possible even in perpetually embattled places (Maslin).  * ''DECONSTRUCTING HARRY,'' starring Woody Allen and Kirstie Alley. Directed by Mr. Allen (R, 96 minutes). Private life caught up with Woody Allen several years ago, and now, with rancorous brilliance, he returns the favor. This savage, liberating comedy is one of his funniest films, and it also has a detached wisdom that transcends autobiographical trivia. Love, lies and the saving grace of creative imagination are at center stage here, as Mr. Allen weaves a dizzying plot around real events and a writer's self-serving, wickedly fictionalized versions. Jump cuts, frank profanity and an unapologetic taste for vice give the film an invigorating honesty, and Mr. Allen is brazen in making the most of it. To those who would take offense at the nastiness of this, the film offers a ruefully mature answer: tough (Maslin).  * ''THE GINGERBREAD MAN,'' starring Kenneth Branagh and Embeth Davidtz. Directed by Robert Altman (R, 115 minutes).  What is it about John Grisham legal thrillers that puts 70's directorial superstars back on track? Like Francis Ford Coppola with ''The Rainmaker,'' Robert Altman steers a straight course through this noir story, making his best genre film since ''The Long Goodbye.''  Mr. Branagh, while hardly a good old boy, is surprisingly effective as a Savannah lawyer seduced into trouble by a glum, mysterious beauty (Ms. Davidtz) with a wild-eyed crazy father (Robert Duvall, in a brief but striking performance). Rain pours, fans spin, Spanish moss roosts and beaded curtains sway as Mr. Altman gives Savannah all the murky exoticism that the film version of ''Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil'' missed (Maslin).  ''GREAT EXPECTATIONS,'' starring Ethan Hawke, Gwyneth Paltrow, Anne Bancroft and Robert De Niro. Directed by Alfonso Cuaron (R, 110 minutes). Those who like their Dickens straight had better stay home with ''Little Dorrit.'' But this uneven, free-spirited adaptation by the director of ''A Little Princess'' does share much of that film's visual enchantment. When filmmakers today talk of updating the classics, chances are they have a music video format in mind, and to some extent that's true here: voluptuous pop transpositions take the place of Dickensian detail. A directorial approach this bold and vulgar may have no business working, but here it often does. Mr. De Niro, as a neo-Magwitch on the Florida Gulf Coast and then in New York City, comes closest to cutting a Dickensian figure, but even Ms. Bancroft's campy Baby Jane has her Miss Havisham moments. Mr. Hawke makes a tepid young artist, but Ms. Paltrow, ever fashionable and appearing in a longish nude scene, makes herself a suitably elegant object of desire (Maslin).  * ''NIL BY MOUTH,'' starring Kathy Burke, Ray Winstone and Charlie Creed-Morris.  Written and directed by Gary Oldman (R, 128 minutes). Drinking and violence shape the lives of this film's staunch South London characters, whose troubles Mr. Oldman clearly knows so well. But what he knows best, on the evidence of this brutally truthful family portrait, is what it's like to grow up in the midst of such emotional turbulence and still come out whole. Galvanized by fine acting (Ms. Burke was voted best actress at last year's Cannes Film Festival) and liberating wisdom, the film watches all the carousing, self-deception, fury and unexpected tenderness that keeps its characters bound together. There's a strong, touching performance by Mr. Oldman's truck-driving sister, billed as Laila Morse, and a seductively bluesy Eric Clapton score (Maslin).  ''SPHERE,'' starring Dustin Hoffman, Samuel L. Jackson and Sharon Stone. Directed by Barry Levinson (PG-13, 120 minutes). Down to the Pacific Ocean floor goes a team of scientists with the skills to study alien invasions from outer space. But as based faithfully on Michael Crichton's 1987 thriller, it's not as simple as that. In a story that proves uncharacteristically touchy-feely for Mr. Crichton (and not just because things with tentacles mean so much to its plot), the film begins in crisp neo-''Aliens'' mode, then grows increasingly trippy and vague. Mr. Hoffman plays a psychologist (and the film definitely needs one); Mr. Jackson plays the story's toughest, most unpredictable character; Ms. Stone plays an ace biochemist, but she walks the walk and talks the mumbo-jumbo as credibly as the others do. While this is no quick-witted treat on a par with Mr. Levinson's ''Wag the Dog,'' it's a solid thriller with showy scientific overtones, which means the cast will be explaining what a black hole is and how fast coral grows before the film is over (Maslin).  * ''TITANIC,'' starring Leonardo DiCaprio and Kate Winslet. Directed by James Cameron (PG-13, 197 minutes). For once, a much-touted event movie is exactly that: a glorious throwback to the days when epic storytelling really filled the screen. Despite the astonishing technological advances behind Mr. Cameron's great visual spectacle, gimmicks are never allowed to intrude on the film's central illusion: that the audience is drawn back into the Gilded Age and intimately involved in the fateful voyage. For all its painstaking historical detail, this ''Titanic'' proves anything but quaint, thanks to the phenomenal immediacy of its sights and the pure Hollywood hokum of its story. As two young lovers whose romance is skillfully interwoven with real historical detail, Ms. Winslet and Mr. DiCaprio are a duo with serious chemistry. With his ''Gone With the Wind''-caliber ambitions, Mr. Cameron dared to dream of the impossible and came up with the movie of the year (Maslin).  * ''WAG THE DOG,'' starring Dustin Hoffman, Robert De Niro and Anne Heche. Directed by Barry Levinson (R, 100 minutes). Also slap the knee, because this sidelong, poison-tipped political satire is discreetly hilarious through and through. Taking aim at the world of spin with a dead-on screenplay by David Mamet and Hillary Henkin, this comedy imagines political operatives who casually concoct an international incident to hide the fact that their candidate has misbehaved with a young female scout on a brief visit to the Oval Office. Starting there, and spiraling into the absurdist stratosphere, the film imagines an army of fraudmeisters led by Mr. De Niro's brooding top-secret consultant, who has never seen a problem too tricky to solve. Washington takes its hits, but the film's real target is Hollywood, thanks to Mr. Hoffman, whose fond yet murderous version of a Hollywood producer is liable to win prizes. Enjoy, but beware: if you see this movie, you will no longer believe that the real President has a real dog (Maslin).  ''THE WEDDING SINGER,'' starring Adam Sandler and Drew Barrymore. Directed by Frank Coraci (PG-13, 95 minutes). Oozing niceness, Mr. Sandler plays it semi-sincere in this comedy with a dual personality: half of it is squeaky clean love story, while the better half consists of pop-culture time-warp jokes set in 1985. Or as Mr. Sandler's title character says to the girlfriend who jilts him, ''Now please get out of my Van Halen T-shirt before you jinx the band and they break up.'' In the wake of ''Austin Powers'' (and before Macarena nostalgia hits us), this is funny enough if you think a Material Girl outfit or a Boy George impersonator has intrinsic wit. Costumes and soundtrack hits add to the party atmosphere, and Mr. Sandler's performance is savvier than his bottom-feeding early film roles. An enjoyably silly film for the whole family, if the whole family feels like remembering ''Miami Vice.'' Parenthetically, the screenplay repeatedly calls attention to the effects of heavy drinking (Maslin).</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>''VIEWS OF MERCHANT IVORY: 3 CONTINENTS, 14 FILMS.'' The title of the series at the Paris Theater tells much, but not all. This retrospective of the films of Merchant Ivory Productions is at once an overview of more than 30 years of the filmmaking partnership of Ismail Merchant and James Ivory, an opportunity to revisit some of their acclaimed creations and a chance to relish the high style and fine acting that characterizes their work. And there's a bonus: three of the actresses on view as Merchant Ivory heroines -- Judi Dench of ''A Room With a View,'' Julie Christie of ''Heat and Dust'' and Helena Bonham Carter of ''A Room With a View'' and ''Howards End'' -- are nominees for Academy Awards this year. The films in the current series are set in Europe, India and America. Each day, five films are being shown. Among the highlights of this weekend's lineup are ''Remains of the Day'' (1993) and ''The Bostonians'' (1984) today, ''Mr. and Mrs. Bridge'' (1990) and ''Howards End'' (1992) tomorrow and ''Shakespeare Wallah'' (1965) on Sunday. The series continues through March 6 at the Paris, 4 West 58th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $8.50; $5 for the elderly and children under 12. Information: (212) 688-3800 (Van Gelder).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
