<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Small Strategy for Troubled Giants</title>
    <meta content="16EAST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/16/nyregion/16EAST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010517T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1293773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holloway, Lynette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland/Geneva</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (New York)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (New York)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Richmond (South Africa)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Upper East Side (Manhattan)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Cambria Heights (New York)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Williamsburg</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Enterprise</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Grand Street (New York)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Geneva</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (New York)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Cardozo High School</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Board of Education</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Stuyvesant High School</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Roosevelt, Theodore</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jackson, Andrew</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DE123AF935A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Small Strategy for Troubled Giants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNETTE HOLLOWAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holloway, Lynette</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Education column examines theory that neighborhood high schools, large, factory-size buildings attended by most people who grew up on streets of New York City, should be broken up into smaller schools in effort to revive academic process; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Neighborhood high schools, the large, factory-size buildings attended by most people who grew up on the streets of New York City, may be in their twilight years.</p>
        <p>Last month, Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy announced plans to seize control of two more traditional high schools in the Bronx that have long been symbols of educational neglect. The schools, Theodore Roosevelt and William H. Taft High Schools, are regarded as outdated structures because impersonal environments have allowed violence and academic failure to get out of hand, officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Neighborhood high schools, the large, factory-size buildings attended by most people who grew up on the streets of New York City, may be in their twilight years.</p>
        <p>Last month, Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy announced plans to seize control of two more traditional high schools in the Bronx that have long been symbols of educational neglect. The schools, Theodore Roosevelt and William H. Taft High Schools, are regarded as outdated structures because impersonal environments have allowed violence and academic failure to get out of hand, officials said.</p>
        <p>But education experts say that some large high schools, like Benjamin N. Cardozo High School and Bayside High School in Queens, are offering a variety of courses in safe environments and are sending students to college with Regents diplomas.</p>
        <p>Breaking up large high schools into smaller schools, however, has been a proven method for reviving a few of the city's most troubled schools, like Julia Richmond on Manhattan's Upper East Side; Andrew Jackson in Cambria Heights, Queens; and the old Eastern District High School in Williamsburg, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Roosevelt and Taft, coincidentally named, respectively, for the 26th and 27th presidents, will open next fall as complexes of several small schools, probably with new principals and some new teachers.</p>
        <p>The model Mr. Levy plans to use to whittle away at the educational behemoths is already being tried. A good example is Eastern District, which seemed to have a permanent lock on its place on the state's list of failing schools.</p>
        <p>Eastern District was on the state's list of failing schools for 12 years before it was placed in the Chancellor's District, a collection of perennially failing schools. In its last year of operation, in the 1995-96 school year, 30 percent of the 2,500 students dropped out and only 62.3 percent attended classes on a regular basis, officials said.</p>
        <p>The four-story beige-brick fortress was also under siege. Slashings and fistfights were almost as common as the school bell, and students were required to walk through metal detectors to enter the building.</p>
        <p>A student fracas that spilled onto the street six years ago prompted a parental and community boycott that helped change the face of the school. The next school year, the board divided the building into three small schools: Progress High School for Professional Careers, the High School for Legal Studies and the High School for Enterprise, Business and Technology.</p>
        <p>Today, Eastern District, with 1,800 students, is a faded remnant of its former self. But last year, the dropout rate was 3.4 percent and 80 percent of the students attended classes regularly.</p>
        <p>The metal detectors are gone and change is palpable throughout the building, with its high-gloss beige tiled floors. The campus started a debate team and a football team. Students must apply to attend the schools, whose populations are largely black and Hispanic.</p>
        <p>''Before I got here, I heard there were a lot of gangs and that they tried to bomb the school,'' said William Brunson, a 14-year-old freshman at Progress High School, who was attending an afternoon literacy class. ''But I was surprised when I got here, because everybody is cool.''</p>
        <p>The Board of Education changed the name of the school to 850 Grand Street Campus to help shed the Eastern District image. Each mini-school was assigned about 600 students and given its own principals. Each school started fresh with a ninth-grade class, shipping older students to schools throughout the city.</p>
        <p>The principals hired new teachers and administrators to invigorate the staff. But they kept some solid veteran teachers, like Geneva Watson Dean, chairwoman of the science department at the School for Legal Studies. The other day, she was enthusiastic about up-to-date textbooks that discuss cloning and the genome theory.</p>
        <p>''The smaller schools have taught students to be more focused,'' Mrs. Dean said. ''The environment is safe now. When students were frisked and had to walk through metal detectors, it added doubt and suspicion. I don't think we accomplished anything being afraid of one another.''</p>
        <p>Because the schools were placed in the Chancellor's District, they received an infusion of resources, like before- and after-school and Saturday programs, new textbooks, laboratory equipment and distinctive literacy and math programs. All schools in the Chancellor's District must adhere to a 90-minute literacy block, which includes individual reading and literary analysis.</p>
        <p>All three principals were new to running troubled high schools. William C. Jusino, principal of Progress High School, had worked as an assistant principal at an elementary school in Brooklyn. Jerry Cioffe, principal of Legal Studies, is a veteran Board of Education administrator. Juan S. Méndez, principal of the School for Enterprise, Business and Technology, was the coordinator of technology at Stuyvesant High School in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jusino and Mr. Méndez both said that it was difficult getting the community to agree to allow them to remove the metal detectors, because they were still concerned about safety issues. But much of that doubt subsided with time.</p>
        <p>Progress High School came off the state's list of failing schools last year with its first graduating class, 85 percent of the students graduating and 82 percent of its students passing the state's standardized test in English language arts. Officials expect the Business and Technology school to come off the state's list at the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''What you need is consistency and stability at school,'' Mr. Jusino said. ''Board of Education officials are looking forward to learning whether Eastern District's model can work at Theodore Roosevelt, in the Fordham section of the Bronx, and at Taft, in Morrisania. Taft recently returned to the state's list of failing schools after only 45 percent of students who were supposed to graduate last June passed the English Regents exam. It had undergone a brief period of academic improvement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cioffe, a former deputy superintendent in the Chancellor's District, said he believed that with smaller schools Taft, too, could be revamped, much like Eastern District.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 17, 2001, Thursday  An article on the Education Page yesterday about the strategy of breaking up low-performing high schools into smaller ones misspelled the surname of the principal of the High School for Legal Studies in Brooklyn, an offshoot of Eastern District High. He is Jerry Cioffi, not Cioffe.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 19, 2001, Saturday  An article on the Education Page on Wednesday about the strategy of breaking up low-performing high schools into smaller ones misspelled the name of a high school on the Upper East Side where the strategy was used. It is Julia Richman High School, not Richmond.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 17, 2001, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on the Education Page yesterday about the strategy of breaking up low-performing high schools into smaller ones misspelled the surname of the principal of the High School for Legal Studies in Brooklyn, an offshoot of Eastern District High. He is Jerry Cioffi, not Cioffe.</p>
        <p>Correction: May 19, 2001, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on the Education Page on Wednesday about the strategy of breaking up low-performing high schools into smaller ones misspelled the name of a high school on the Upper East Side where the strategy was used. It is Julia Richman High School, not Richmond.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
