<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Shogun' Postpones Opening After Star Is Injured</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="401104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WITCHEL, ALEX</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CASNOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SHOGUN (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DF1730F936A25752C1A966958260" item-length="521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Shogun' Postpones Opening After Star Is Injured</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX WITCHEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WITCHEL, ALEX</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Shogun," the new Broadway musical based on James Clavell's best-selling novel, will resume performances tonight, and the official opening has been rescheduled for Tuesday, the show's press representative said yesterday. Philip Casnoff, the show's leading actor, was injured on Tuesday evening when a large piece of scenery fell and struck him on the head.</p>
        <p>Mr. Casnoff was injured near the end of the second act of a critics' preview performance at the Marquis Theater. Mr. Casnoff was about to sing a number titled "Death Walk" when a large screen fell on him in what the press representative, Shirley Herz, called a "freak accident." The performance was halted, and the actor was taken to St. Vincent's Hospital and Medical Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"Shogun," the new Broadway musical based on James Clavell's best-selling novel, will resume performances tonight, and the official opening has been rescheduled for Tuesday, the show's press representative said yesterday. Philip Casnoff, the show's leading actor, was injured on Tuesday evening when a large piece of scenery fell and struck him on the head.</p>
        <p>Mr. Casnoff was injured near the end of the second act of a critics' preview performance at the Marquis Theater. Mr. Casnoff was about to sing a number titled "Death Walk" when a large screen fell on him in what the press representative, Shirley Herz, called a "freak accident." The performance was halted, and the actor was taken to St. Vincent's Hospital and Medical Center.</p>
        <p>The matinee and evening performances yesterday were also canceled. Ms. Herz said performances were scheduled to resume tonight despite reports that Mr. Casnoff had not fully recovered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Casnoff, who plays the role of John Blackthorne, an English sea captain, in the musical, was given a series of tests and kept overnight for observation at the hospital. Ms. Herz said he suffered "bad bruises to his head, neck and shoulders, and a scratch on his forehead, and his face was swollen on one side." She said that a CAT scan had determined that there was no internal injury and that Mr. Casnoff was under the care of Dr. Stuart Hirshon, a specialist in sports medicine. Cast Reassured</p>
        <p>Ms. Herz said that a full check of the scenery was made before the show began on Tuesday and that what happened was "a freak accident." She said that when one of the pillars of a castle was moved offstage, it swung into a large screen and knocked it loose on its track. Every scenic change in "Shogun," as in most Broadway shows, is computerized, and when something goes wrong, the computer is programmed to shut down and lock everything in place. Because the screen began to move before the computer shut down, she said, it could not be stopped. It moved with such force that it broke through its lock.</p>
        <p>Ms. Herz said the cast met at the theater yesterday afternoon and was assured by the producers that the scenery mechanisms had been doubly reinforced, and that it was safe to return to the stage. Asked if Mr. Casnoff might sue because of his injuries, Ms Herz said: "Nothing like that has been discussed. He just wants to get back in the theater."</p>
        <p>"Shogun," whose cost is estimated at $8 million, had its premiere on Sept. 6 at the Kennedy Center in Washington. Mr. Casnoff assumed the lead in the New York production, replacing Peter Karrie, a British actor who opened the show in Washington. The musical is the story of a 17th-century English sea captain who is shipwrecked on the coast of Japan, falls in love with a Japanese woman and becomes involved in that country's political power struggles. It is produced by Mr. Clavell, Joseph Harris and Haruki Kadokawa, a Japanese publisher and film producer.</p>
        <p>Critics have been invited to return to the show starting with this evening's performance. Others in Tuesday's audience are entitled to either a full refund or exchange.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
