<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Dance; Garth Fagan Is Beginning 20th Season</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="401101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FAGAN, GARTH, BUCKET DANCE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNNING, JENNIFER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB1630F936A25752C1A966958260" item-length="716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Dance; Garth Fagan Is Beginning 20th Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNNING, JENNIFER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Garth Fagan Dance opened its two-week season at the Joyce Theater on Tuesday night with a triumphant declaration of achievement, growth and fidelity to its origins. In the 20 years since it was founded by Mr. Fagan in Rochester, the troupe has moved far from its rough beginnings but has not lost its early quality of idealism and commitment. It is a company in the tradition of the founding American modern dance troupes -- an instrument of a choreographer's earliest and developing ideas. And Mr. Fagan has used it well.</p>
        <p>One ought not go to a performance by Fagan Dance expecting ballet technique, though the dancers are trained in it, or anything approaching the kind of sleek modern dance created by some of the most recent practitioners of the art. Mr. Fagan's first dancers were largely untrained and were late starters, and he used their qualities, drawing also on his own experience with West Indian and American modern dance, to form a vocabulary. Hunching, tilting bodies and crooked limbs are the norm here, as are skittery traveling steps and luscious, looping turns off balance. Still, it all packs a powerful punch. These dancers move fast, in big gulps of jumps and runs that often take them right across the stage. Yet there is always a sense of vivid personality in the dancers and in what they do.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Garth Fagan Dance opened its two-week season at the Joyce Theater on Tuesday night with a triumphant declaration of achievement, growth and fidelity to its origins. In the 20 years since it was founded by Mr. Fagan in Rochester, the troupe has moved far from its rough beginnings but has not lost its early quality of idealism and commitment. It is a company in the tradition of the founding American modern dance troupes -- an instrument of a choreographer's earliest and developing ideas. And Mr. Fagan has used it well.</p>
        <p>One ought not go to a performance by Fagan Dance expecting ballet technique, though the dancers are trained in it, or anything approaching the kind of sleek modern dance created by some of the most recent practitioners of the art. Mr. Fagan's first dancers were largely untrained and were late starters, and he used their qualities, drawing also on his own experience with West Indian and American modern dance, to form a vocabulary. Hunching, tilting bodies and crooked limbs are the norm here, as are skittery traveling steps and luscious, looping turns off balance. Still, it all packs a powerful punch. These dancers move fast, in big gulps of jumps and runs that often take them right across the stage. Yet there is always a sense of vivid personality in the dancers and in what they do.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fagan's new "Until, By and If" is set to a hauntingly melodic score by Don Pullen, the jazz pianist -- a score that is full of wistful dawdles and cacophonous crescendos. The work gets off to a purposefully faded, dusty start when a regiment of dancers in street clothes designed by Phyllis Gomer slowly shuffles about the stage as a group in tiny mechanical steps. They seem automatons, their humanity proved by sudden breaks into jagged lines, hunches and falls.</p>
        <p>They form a ragged, huddling circle that gathers speed and loops and gallops across the stage in a typical Fagan transcendence. A gnarled tangle of bodies, the dancers fall to the floor and lie still in a single line. The line begins to roll, crooked legs rising like weeds and arms reaching out across the stage. The air is drenched with shimmering, coursing piano music designed for movers but accompanying slumber.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fagan then works his peculiar magic with couples -- dancers who wrap around each other, the women's hands hiding the men's eyes, and who wedge their limbs onto pedestals made from their partners' limbs and roll through unwieldy somersaults. Two elegant dancers pull away and together. Others wheel and skitter galvanically through the crowd. Eventually, though, it's back to that crowd of automatons.</p>
        <p>The closing section is a dream, beginning with sleepers, interspersed with strollers on a peaceful landscape. Two little girls embrace. Jumps and tumbles tear at the peacefulness, but it all seems to be happening in a drowse. The dream explodes into fast-moving, buttery-footed dancers with the idlers among them standing out. Here, as throughout the evening, there is not a familiar move in sight, but it all looks like pyrotechnics.</p>
        <p>"Until, By and If" was superbly performed by Norwood Pennewell, Natalie Rogers, Steve Humphrey, Sharon Skepple, Valentina Alexander, A. Roger Smith, Bit Knighton, Bill Ferguson, Rebecca Gose, Chris Morrison, Juel Bedford and Lavert Benefield. The score was performed by Mr. Pullen, James Genus and Reggie Nicholson. C. T. Oakes designed the lighting.</p>
        <p>"Mask Mix Masque," a 1986 piece, gets off to a profoundly troubling start. Bits of a recorded interview with Grace Jones, echo chamber laughter and the refrain "slave to the rhythm," a line from one of Miss Jones's songs, suggest nothing, seem to have nothing to do with the choreography and are repeated to no particular effect. Have the shticks of heedless, post-post-modernism been visited upon Mr. Fagan, one of the last choreographers one would have expected to fall into such temptation? But slowly, surely, Mr. Fagan establishes a quite different world of his own. His dancers appear and disappear, inhabiting that world like cartoon figures emerging from frame to frame in a dance that is Mr. Fagan at his most exuberant and mysterious.</p>
        <p>Garth Fagan Dance performs in this and two other programs, through Nov. 25 at the Joyce, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
