<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>J.P. Morgan's Pioneering Offspring</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="386529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL RESERVE SYSTEM</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MORGAN, J P, &amp; CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MORGAN, J P, SECURITIES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUINT, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDE153FF936A1575AC0A966958260" item-length="1369" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>J.P. Morgan's Pioneering Offspring</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL QUINT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">QUINT, MICHAEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: It is not often that a four-year-old securities firm attracts much attention on Wall Street. But in the case of J. P. Morgan Securities Inc., the prestige and power of its parent, the J. P. Morgan banking company, provide far more influence than is normal for a newcomer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: It is not often that a four-year-old securities firm attracts much attention on Wall Street. But in the case of J. P. Morgan Securities Inc., the prestige and power of its parent, the J. P. Morgan banking company, provide far more influence than is normal for a newcomer.</p>
        <p>It is not often that a four-year-old securities firm attracts much attention on Wall Street. But in the case of J. P. Morgan Securities Inc., the prestige and power of its parent, the J. P. Morgan banking company, provide far more influence than is normal for a newcomer.</p>
        <p>Last week, in a historic step, the Federal Reserve gave Morgan Securities authority to trade and sell corporate stocks, making it the first bank-related securities firm with a full range of securities powers. Initially, the securities unit could handle only Treasury and municipal bonds. Then last year the Fed granted the Morgan unit and a handful of other banking companies authority to trade and sell corporate bonds.</p>
        <p>One-Stop Service Planned</p>
        <p>The Fed's action comes nearly 60 years after the Glass-Steagall Act forced the breakup of the House of Morgan into a banking company, J. P. Morgan &amp; Company, and a securities firm, Morgan Stanley &amp; Company. Congress acted in 1933 to separate banking and securities businesses following abuses in the 1920's.</p>
        <p>Executives at Morgan declined to be interviewed following the Fed's approval. But their earlier comments make it clear that the authority to float new issues of stocks and bonds is a key part of their business plan to become a one-stop financial service firm for large corporations.</p>
        <p>By taking advantage of the banking company's close ties to board rooms of the nation's largest corporations as a financial adviser and lender, officials at J. P. Morgan Securities hope they will be selected to handle new offerings of stocks and bonds - a business that generated more than $4.1 billion in revenue for Wall Street firms in 1989.</p>
        <p>While analysts say that the banking company's expertise as a financial adviser and roster of corporate clients were unmatched by any other bank or Wall Street firm, Dennis Weatherstone, Morgan's chairman, said the advisory and banking businesses alone were not enough to keep Morgan in the front ranks of the world's financial institutions. To remain competitive, he said, Morgan needed authority to provide any service, whether it be a loan, advice or a securities offering.</p>
        <p>''We are the top U.S. commercial bank-affiliated underwriter, but in relation to the volume of business conducted by the biggest investment firms, we have barely scratched the surface,'' Joseph P. MacHale, a Morgan managing director, said in a recent internal newsletter.</p>
        <p>To manage its securities ventures, Morgan has grown its own talent, avoiding the problems of salary squabbles and dissent between traders and deal makers that have disrupted other firms.</p>
        <p>The securities unit's staff of 800 is headed by Peter L. Woicke, who joined Morgan's Frankfurt office in 1969. Mr. Woicke headed the London petroleum department and the bank's Brazilian business before becoming president of the securities unit in February 1989.</p>
        <p>Proving Efficiency</p>
        <p>Early indications are that Morgan Securities is gaining ground on the traditional Wall Street firms and proving that it can sell corporate stocks and bonds with the same seamless efficiency it has long shown in the Treasury and municipal bond markets. Since June 1989, when it was the first bank affilate approved by the Fed to sell new corporate bond issues, Morgan has had a hand in in 50 offerings, more than the total for all other bank-related securities firms.</p>
        <p>Among the companies that have selected Morgan Securities recently are the Chubb Corporation, an insurance concern. It chose Morgan as the lead underwriter in a $100 million offering of five-year notes last January.</p>
        <p>''They made a very convincing presentation about their ability to distribute the notes,'' said Gail E. Devlin, senior vice president for finance. She added that Morgan Securities had a leg up on the financing because of the Morgan bank's advisory work with Chubb's real estate development unit, which was to get the proceeds of the note sale.</p>
        <p>Corporate treasurers, always looking for ways to diversify their sources of financing, have been willing to tell the firms managing new issues that Morgan should be included in the underwriting syndicate. In the last six months, for example, Morgan was a manager for offerings by Dow Chemical; the National City Corporation, Cleveland; ITT Financial; Westinghouse Credit, and BellSouth, and was the sole underwriter for Telephonos de Mexico.</p>
        <p>Morgan Securities' total of $667.7 million of new issues thus far this year is a drop in the bucket compared with such pacesetters as Merrill Lynch, with $17.7 billion, Morgan Stanley, with $15.4 billion, or Goldman, Sachs, with $12.5 billion. (The figures come from IDD Information Services.) Nevertheless, Morgan's volume exceeds the totals of such Wall Street firms as Paine Webber; Smith Barney, Harris Upham and Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Gains Expected</p>
        <p>''In terms of developing new business, I expect that Morgan can eventually operate on a par with industry leaders, like Goldman, Sachs,'' said Jean Louis Lelogeais, an analyst at the consulting firm of Booz Allen &amp; Hamilton Inc. ''In the distribution end of the business, they will concentrate on the large institutions, and rely on hookups with other Wall Street firms with networks of branch offices to reach smaller buyers.''</p>
        <p>Securities dealers declined to comment publicly on Morgan Securities partly because they use the Morgan bank for financing and other services. They acknowledge that Morgan's name is likely to appear with increasing frequency in the list of underwriters for new corporate securities.</p>
        <p>Morgan has been prominent in private placements, in which securities are sold to a handful of institutions. Banking companies were never barred from handling private placements. Because such placements have limited distribution, the banks' lack of securities branches is not a disadvantage.</p>
        <p>Morgan's success in private placements suggests that it has the customer contacts needed to rise in the rankings of firms handling public offerings of bonds and stocks. According to IDD , in the first half of this year Morgan Securities ranked fifth in placing corporate bonds and second, after Goldman, Sachs, in private placements of bond issues.</p>
        <p>Although the Morgan bank was far less active than other large banks in making high-risk loans to finance corporate takeovers, the securities unit is preparing to become a major player in ''junk bonds,'' including some issued by companies to which Morgan bank would not lend money.</p>
        <p>Morgan Securities' first move in junk bonds was to create a research staff of a dozen analysts drawn from the ranks of Morgan bank. Morgan Securities has not yet handled any new issues of junk bonds, but its research reports and trading of bonds have been good enough to earn a following from more than 100 institutions, like pension funds and insurance companies.</p>
        <p>In the mortgage securities market, Morgan has not tried to imitate the business at other banks of making mortgages and converting them into mortgage-backed securities. Instead, it has concentrated on trading the thousands of different mortgage-backed issues, a part of the market where there is enough opportunity for Mr. Woicke to say in an employee newsletter, ''We have established ourselves among the few firms that are profitable in the business.''</p>
        <p>But at a time when business on Wall Street is slumping and many people say there are simply too many securities firms, Morgan Securities is doing more than just imitating the prevailing business practices.</p>
        <p>For example, it is backing a system for electronic auctions of new corporate bonds called Capitalink that would allow investors to buy high-quality issues directly from corporations. The electronic auctions, which have not yet been held but have been in preparation for more than a year, would bypass the traditonal system of underwriting syndicates, where Morgan is a newcomer and faces fierce resistance from other wall street firms.</p>
        <p>Claus Lowe, a managing director of Morgan Securities, noted that the proposed auction system would help Morgan reduce costs of its participation in high-quality bond offerings, and allow it to use workers for other kinds of financings where profit margins are greater. Primericad (Smith Barney)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
