<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sweet Life After Bitter Start</title>
    <meta content="03CWHA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/03/dining/03CWHA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1540069"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chocolate</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moskin, Julia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chocolate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D81E3AF930A35751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sweet Life After Bitter Start</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chocolate: A Sweet Life After Bitter Start</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA MOSKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moskin, Julia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julia Moskin describes life of chocolate, from its start as ripe cacao pod, to finished chocolate; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL chocolate starts as a ripe cacao pod, about the size and shape of a football, growing on a tree somewhere within 20 degrees of the equator, mainly in Ivory Coast, Ghana and Venezuela. Within the pods are sweet white fruits; within each fruit is a dusty brown cacao bean; within each bean is a fingertip-size, inedibly bitter nib of pure chocolate. (In the unrefined state, the pod and beans are called cacao. Once processing begins, the word cocoa is used instead.)</p>
        <p>Globally, three major strains of cocoa beans are grown and traded. Criollo, which accounts for about 5 percent of the world's crop, has the richest, most intense flavor when roasted. Trinitario, accounting for a similarly small percentage, is a hybrid originally developed on Trinidad. It also has very fine flavor. A vast majority of beans are Forastero, hardy and easy to grow, but with mild flavor. It is the source of all commercial chocolate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL chocolate starts as a ripe cacao pod, about the size and shape of a football, growing on a tree somewhere within 20 degrees of the equator, mainly in Ivory Coast, Ghana and Venezuela. Within the pods are sweet white fruits; within each fruit is a dusty brown cacao bean; within each bean is a fingertip-size, inedibly bitter nib of pure chocolate. (In the unrefined state, the pod and beans are called cacao. Once processing begins, the word cocoa is used instead.).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALL chocolate starts as a ripe cacao pod, about the size and shape of a football, growing on a tree somewhere within 20 degrees of the equator, mainly in Ivory Coast, Ghana and Venezuela. Within the pods are sweet white fruits; within each fruit is a dusty brown cacao bean; within each bean is a fingertip-size, inedibly bitter nib of pure chocolate. (In the unrefined state, the pod and beans are called cacao. Once processing begins, the word cocoa is used instead.)</p>
        <p>Globally, three major strains of cocoa beans are grown and traded. Criollo, which accounts for about 5 percent of the world's crop, has the richest, most intense flavor when roasted. Trinitario, accounting for a similarly small percentage, is a hybrid originally developed on Trinidad. It also has very fine flavor. A vast majority of beans are Forastero, hardy and easy to grow, but with mild flavor. It is the source of all commercial chocolate.</p>
        <p>Manufacturers roast the beans and remove the husks. The nibs are ground into a thick paste called cocoa liquor or cocoa mass The cocoa mass is sweetened, and vanilla is added (vanilla is a key note in the flavor of chocolate). The cocoa mass is then milled and kneaded smooth for hours or even days, in a process called conching. Lecithin is added during this step to ensure an even texture. Bean origin, roasting temperature and even the micron size of the cocoa particles help determine the taste and texture of the finished chocolate.</p>
        <p>The higher the percentage of cocoa mass, the more strong, bittersweet, complex flavors in the chocolate.</p>
        <p>Dark chocolate (about 50 percent to 99 percent cocoa mass) is generally cocoa mass, sugar and lecithin. A whisper of vanilla or another spice is sometimes added. American-made dark chocolate can be labeled bittersweet or semisweet; semisweet is sweeter.</p>
        <p>For milk chocolate (5 percent to about 50 percent cocoa mass) manufacturers add dry or condensed whole milk.</p>
        <p>To a purist, what is usually called white chocolate is not chocolate at all, because it does not contain any of the cocoa solids that give chocolate its flavor. White chocolate is usually made of cocoa butter, milk, and sugar, but it often contains hydrogenated fats instead of cocoa butter. In January, Food and Drug Administration regulations will go into effect requiring white chocolate to contain at least 20 percent cocoa butter, with no vegetable fats or other additives.</p>
        <p>Some chocolate also contains corn syrup, skim milk and vanillin, an inexpensive vanilla substitute.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
