<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Neediest Cases; After Loss Of Two Jobs, A Safety Net</title>
    <meta content="08NEED$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1454792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Catholic Charities</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bovino, Arthur</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4D7123EF93BA35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Neediest Cases; After Loss Of Two Jobs, A Safety Net</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ARTHUR BOVINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bovino, Arthur</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Times Neediest Cases Fund appeal; describes how fund, through Catholic Charities, Diocese of Brooklyn and Queens, was able to help family struggling to pay rent after woman in family was injured on the job and can no longer work; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wilmer Rodriguez likes to bring his work home with him. But his family is not complaining. His wife, Lidilia, and his daughters, Marcia, 18, and Brook, 15, watch him settle in at a special table with his array of tiny tools. They look on in fascination as he mounts small diamonds and other precious stones in intricate, delicate jewelry.</p>
        <p>''I like to watch him,'' Mrs. Rodriguez said in Spanish through a translator. ''I get entertained by him making things.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wilmer Rodriguez likes to bring his work home with him. But his family is not complaining. His wife, Lidilia, and his daughters, Marcia, 18, and Brook, 15, watch him settle in at a special table with his array of tiny tools. They look on in fascination as he mounts small diamonds and other precious stones in intricate, delicate jewelry.</p>
        <p>''I like to watch him,'' Mrs. Rodriguez said in Spanish through a translator. ''I get entertained by him making things.''</p>
        <p>To the Rodriguez family, there are few things more important than a strong work ethic. For Mr. Rodriguez, a jeweler, that extra work has always helped bring in a little more money for the necessities of life -- food and rent.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Rodriguez, 49, also worked, as a home assistant for the elderly.</p>
        <p>Between them, they earned enough to raise a family in Elmhurst, Queens. They also counted themselves lucky to hold jobs they happened to love. And in the 17 years since he learned his trade, Mr. Rodriguez, 60, has even been able to afford to make some things that went to his family rather than ending up on the necks and fingers of strangers.</p>
        <p>But then, a little over a year ago, everything started to change. And this hard-working family was confronted with an exasperating problem: what happens when you want to work, but you cannot?</p>
        <p>In December 2001, Mrs. Rodriguez had to quit her job after she hurt her back. She was helping a 200-pound patient out of bed when she felt shooting pains in her neck, shoulder and right arm. Her doctor said she had to stop working, even though her injury has not yet been diagnosed.</p>
        <p>The loss of Mrs. Rodriguez's income made it hard for the family.</p>
        <p>And the loss of time with the people in her care was hard for Mrs. Rodriguez, too. Her daughters would often return home to find their mother crying.</p>
        <p>''I loved to work with senior citizens,'' Mrs. Rodriguez said. ''It makes me feel very happy because it makes me think of my grandparents when I used to care for them. I liked to talk with them. You learn different customs, foods and cultures. You have to give them a lot of love because they often have no children.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Rodriguez's unhappiness began to affect the rest of the family.</p>
        <p>''My husband was depressed because he saw that I was not the same anymore,'' Mrs. Rodriguez said.</p>
        <p>A few months later, he had yet another reason to be depressed. In August, he was laid off, because business at the jewelry store where he worked was slow.</p>
        <p>And while food stamps helped keep the family fed, Mrs. Rodriguez's $317-a-month welfare check and their meager savings were not enough to pay their $737.87-a-month rent.</p>
        <p>Their older daughter, Marcia, who works at a sporting goods store, had been trying to save money for college, and had planned to start this month. Instead, she put off her plans and gave her parents $425 toward each month's rent. Mr. Rodriguez's sister, Ady Simmonds, helped with part of the rent in August and September. Their son, Fabricio, 27, has also tried to help his parents, but Mrs. Rodriguez said, ''He has his own family with four children.''</p>
        <p>Unable to pay the October rent and faced with the prospect of eviction, Mrs. Rodriguez sought free legal assistance. She was referred by the legal aid agency to Catholic Charities, Diocese of Brooklyn and Queens, one of the seven local charities that benefits from The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>There, she met Marybel Diaz, a caseworker at the Astoria Community Center of Catholic Charities, and explained her situation. Ms. Diaz wrote a letter to Housing Court guaranteeing the rent and thus preventing an eviction, then gave the Rodriguezes $737.87 of Neediest Cases fund money to pay the October rent.</p>
        <p>''She was very nice and gentle,'' Mrs. Rodriguez said of Ms. Diaz. ''Catholic Charities is a very good agency. I don't have words to explain it. But they're really nice people.''</p>
        <p>Despite the help, Mrs. Rodriguez's pain -- emotional and physical -- has hardly ebbed. She takes medication for depression. Her daughters try not to leave her alone. After she left her job, she started therapy at the Puerto Rican Family Center in Rego Park, Queens.</p>
        <p>Still, things are looking up at last for the Rodriguez family. At the end of October, Mr. Rodriguez got a full-time job, at another jewelry store.</p>
        <p>He is bringing work home again -- although it is his employer's, not his own -- so he he can display his industriousness.</p>
        <p>''Things have improved since he got his job,'' Mrs. Rodriguez said. ''We should be O.K. with the next couple of months.''</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to 4 Chase Metrotech Center, 7th Floor East, Lockbox 5193, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11245, or any of these organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE  285 Schermerhorn Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK  1011 First Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS  191 Joralemon Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES  281 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK  Church Street Station P.O. Box 4100 New York, N.Y. 10261-4100</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>Donations may be made with a credit card by phone at (212) 556-5851 (ext. 7) or online, courtesy of CharityWave.com, an Internet donations service, at www.nytimesneediest.charitywave.com. For instructions on how to donate stock to the fund, call (212) 556-1137 or fax (212) 556-4450.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
        <p>Previously recorded: $6,357,684.62  Recorded Monday: $358,154.80  Total: $6,715,839.42  Last year to date: $7,497,870.26</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
