<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Farewell, Sautéed Foie Gras, It's Time for Steak and Spuds</title>
    <meta content="08NOTE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/08/dining/08NOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1454725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7D7153EF93BA35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Farewell, Sautéed Foie Gras, It's Time for Steak and Spuds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Farewell, Sautéed Foie Gras, It's Time for Steak and Spuds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Grimes Critic's Notebook column on slump in New York City's restaurant economy in 2002 after several years in which good restaurants opened regularly and seldom failed; says 2003 will be year of living timorously, with restaurants simplifying their menus, dropping prices and trying to present themselves as bistros, brasseries or diners; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LET'S open the menu and see what looks good to eat in the New Year. I see a juicy sirloin steak at Savannah Steak. I'm sure you could get a baked potato with that. There's a New York strip steak at M. J. Grill, an offshoot of Mark Joseph Steakhouse, and plenty of the same at Frankie &amp; Johnnie's. Terrance Brennan, of Picholine and Artisanal fame, has just opened a seafood and chops house, where, lo and behold, one cannot help noticing the filet mignon, porterhouse and other big-shouldered members of the beef family. Just for variety, there's the 48-ounce steak at Shula's Steak House in the Westin New York, where the menu is written on a football.</p>
        <p>Tender steaks for tough times. That's the forecast. It's doubly glum, because the spoiled diners of this overindulged city were living in a culinary paradise through the late 1990's and well into last year. Never have so many been so gloriously fed, even as the economic storm clouds gathered. Year after year, in unfeigned amazement, the Zagat Survey reported an abnormally high number of openings and a low number of closings. In an industry notorious for its near-lethal failure rate, opening a first-class restaurant in New York almost made sense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>2002: Never have so many New Yorkers been so gloriously fed. 2003: Tender steaks for tough times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LET'S open the menu and see what looks good to eat in the New Year. I see a juicy sirloin steak at Savannah Steak. I'm sure you could get a baked potato with that. There's a New York strip steak at M. J. Grill, an offshoot of Mark Joseph Steakhouse, and plenty of the same at Frankie &amp; Johnnie's. Terrance Brennan, of Picholine and Artisanal fame, has just opened a seafood and chops house, where, lo and behold, one cannot help noticing the filet mignon, porterhouse and other big-shouldered members of the beef family. Just for variety, there's the 48-ounce steak at Shula's Steak House in the Westin New York, where the menu is written on a football.</p>
        <p>Tender steaks for tough times. That's the forecast. It's doubly glum, because the spoiled diners of this overindulged city were living in a culinary paradise through the late 1990's and well into last year. Never have so many been so gloriously fed, even as the economic storm clouds gathered. Year after year, in unfeigned amazement, the Zagat Survey reported an abnormally high number of openings and a low number of closings. In an industry notorious for its near-lethal failure rate, opening a first-class restaurant in New York almost made sense.</p>
        <p>A confluence of trends helped ensure that the restaurants that did open were, by any standard, of very high quality. The honor roll, in just the last couple of years, is extraordinary, with restaurants like Ilo, Pico, 71 Clinton Fresh Food, Town, Alain Ducasse, Craft, Atelier, Fiamma Osteria and L'Impero. Wall Street money and a booming tourist economy encouraged restaurateurs to roll the dice. Daniel Boulud calculated, correctly, that New York could handle a $29 hamburger. With a little hemming and hawing, the city even adjusted to the almost insolent prices at Alain Ducasse.</p>
        <p>The steady improvement in the city's fortunes, and safer streets, made the city attractive to tourists as never before. Making up for lost time, developers built hotels. Each of those hotels had a restaurant. In fact, there seemed to be an unwritten law that a hotel, to rate as chic, had to have a first-rate restaurant. It might be French, but not necessarily. These prestige showcases allowed a new generation of American chefs -- the successors to the likes of David Burke, Charlie Palmer and Larry Forgione -- to step forward. They turned out to be a nervy, highly talented bunch.</p>
        <p>The city's rising fortunes made formerly fringe neighborhoods ripe for colonization. Just as the Flatiron district lured forward-looking restaurateurs a decade ago, the meatpacking district and the Lower East Side in Manhattan, and Smith Street in Brooklyn, attracted chefs and backers with big ideas and limited budgets. Wylie Dufresne, operating out of a space the size of a coat closet on Clinton Street, established the model for a new kind of restaurant, a supercafe with tiny tables, no décor to speak of and huge ambitions in the kitchen. With the Red Cat and the Harrison, Jimmy Bradley created a new kind of American brasserie, and the long-suffering Upper West Side got its fair share of quality restaurants, led by the splashy Ouest.</p>
        <p>New Yorkers never had it so good. But last year, the luck ran out. The city's restaurant economy, already dealt a stunning blow by the attacks on the World Trade Center, succumbed to the inevitable, as bad economic news became routine. Yes, there were fine restaurants. Italian food got a classy setting and a top-notch chef, Michael White, at Fiamma Osteria. Scott Conant, who labored valiantly at City Eatery on the Bowery, turned up at L'Impero in Tudor City, of all places. His cleanly executed, powerfully flavored cooking, a kind of Italian-Mediterranean hybrid of his own creation, put him in the first rank of younger New York chefs, and Rick Moonen, after an abrupt departure from Oceana, worked the old magic on a new cramped stage at RM.</p>
        <p>I had a few quibbles with Atelier when it opened, but I also sensed enormous potential and genuine daring in the refined, herb-based cuisine of Gabriel Kreuther. This is the restaurant I most want to revisit in the coming year. I suspect it is the last truly brave restaurant New York is likely to see in quite a while.</p>
        <p>If anyone needed a tip-off that the dining climate had changed, the sudden disappearance of Cello provided it. Opened to universal acclaim three years ago, it epitomized the late 90's spirit in Manhattan. It was expensive, exquisite and highly dependent on the kind of money that was simply not being spent in the last couple of years, especially by the Wall Street companies that make the wining and dining of clients a multimillion-dollar subindustry in New York. Restaurants that seemed to be doing brisk business night after night were often dying a slow death, as their highly profitable private dining rooms remained unbooked. If Cello, one of the finest restaurants to open in the last decade, could not survive, what hope was there for serious dining in New York?</p>
        <p>Downtown, David Bouley's imperial vision also came to grief. His grand plans for a combination cooking school, Asian restaurant and all-around culinary Xanadu in the Mohawk Building had to be abandoned after the attacks on the World Trade Center forced Bouley Bakery and Danube to close for months.</p>
        <p>For entirely different reasons, the Russian Tea Room limped to an ignominious end three years after Warner LeRoy tried to remake it in his gaudy image. It was a doomed effort. The Tea Room was always more and less than a restaurant. It served as a kind of social club and business center for the agents, performers and power brokers in the cluster of entertainment businesses that grew up around Carnegie Hall over the decades. The business changed. The old agents and moguls died off. The Russian Tea Room lost its reason for existence, and its soul. Nothing could have brought it back to vigorous life, but the idea that the old place could become a golf museum is shocking.</p>
        <p>I suspect that 2003 will shape up as the year of living timorously. Already, restaurants all over town are simplifying their menus, dropping their prices and trying to present themselves as bistros, brasseries or diners. Guastavino's has refashioned itself as an American brasserie, and Pico, a restaurant that by rights should be turning away business, has opened a cafe up front. Increasingly, the smart money seems to be flowing toward restaurants that serve the dual function of restaurant and lounge, like Theo, Hudson Cafeteria or Meet. The food may or may not be good at such establishments, but it can get away with being truly bad, as Hudson Cafeteria and Tao have shown. Food is present, but it is not the point. The way it looks is often more important than the way it tastes.</p>
        <p>There are points of light on the horizon. The smallest may be the brightest, WD50, Mr. Dufresne's economically named follow-up to 71 Clinton Fresh Food, up the block on Clinton Street. Expectations could not possibly be any higher. Jean-Georges Vongerichten, the last chef on earth who needs to open another restaurant, plans to open one anyway. This one, in TriBeCa, called 66, will be devoted to the cuisine of Shanghai.</p>
        <p>Alain Ducasse, perhaps the only chef who can make Mr. Vongerichten seem lacking in get-up-and-go, plans to open a populist dining spot called the Mix, at 68 West 58th Street. Jeffrey Chodorow, who brought New York Hudson Cafeteria and Tuscan Steak (soon to be reborn, with the help of Rocco DiSpirito, as Tuscan), is Mr. Ducasse's partner in this venture, as yet only hazily defined. Mr. Ducasse has given Paris macaroni and cheese. Now let's see what he can do with a root-beer float. Mario Batali is on the verge of opening Otto, at 1 Fifth Avenue, his attempt to show New York what pizza should be.</p>
        <p>Yes, 2003 looks like the year when New York holds its breath for a pizza parlor. Meanwhile, the hapless AOL Time Warner has a corporate palace ready to open on Columbus Circle, just as its stock is flirting with single digits. Naturally, as if the recession never happened, there will be no shortage of budget-breaking restaurants to marvel at. Gray Kunz, at loose ends ever since leaving Lespinasse, looks ready to raise the curtain on the third act of his career. Thomas Keller, perhaps the most critically celebrated chef in the United States, will open a branch of the French Laundry. Masa Takayama plans a Manhattan version of his brutally expensive Los Angeles sushi restaurant, Ginza Sushi-Ko. And the inescapable Mr. Vongerichten is scheduled to chime in with -- what else? -- a steakhouse.</p>
        <p>I'll bet you can't get a baked potato with that.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
