<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets' Kent Turns Jeers Into Some Rare Cheers With Three Timely Hits</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="856618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FLORIDA MARLINS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAMOS, JASON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3D71639F93AA35755C0A960958260" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets' Kent Turns Jeers Into Some Rare Cheers With Three Timely Hits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAMOS, JASON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is by far the least-favorite Met. On a team where few are playing well, he is the only regular consistently booed by the home fans. And his aloof demeanor  off the field hasn't helped his image.</p>
        <p>But every now and then, Jeff Kent has one of those games, the kind he seemed  to have a lot of in early 1994, when he looked like he was going to be a fixture in the Mets' infield for a long time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He is by far the least-favorite Met. On a team where few are playing well, he is the only regular consistently booed by the home fans. And his aloof demeanor  off the field hasn't helped his image.</p>
        <p>But every now and then, Jeff Kent has one of those games, the kind he seemed  to have a lot of in early 1994, when he looked like he was going to be a fixture in the Mets' infield for a long time.</p>
        <p>Last night was one of those nights. Kent delivered three hits in three at-bats, driving in three runs. With Mark Clark (5-6) his usual solid self on the mound, and some timely two-out hitting, the Mets actually provided their starter with some runs for a change. And then they survived a scare to rebound from a 12-2 drubbing Friday night for a 7-6 victory last night over the Florida  Marlins at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>Not even the bullpen could blow this one. But it sure tried.</p>
        <p>After Clark had tired in the eighth, the Marlins rallied against Doug Henry and John Franco and had the go-ahead run on base when Lance Johnson ran down Gregg Colbrunn's liner in left-center field. That gave the shaky Franco his 12th save, after he had come on with the bases loaded and two out and surrendered a two-run single to Jeff Conine and a run-scoring single to Gary Sheffield.</p>
        <p>"If they want to boo me, that's fine," said Franco, who was pitching for the  first time in seven days. "I'm better than what happened tonight."</p>
        <p>The bullpen aside, it is Kent who hears the overwhelming majority of catcalls. It is no secret that the Mets would gladly listen to offers for Kent and his $1.96 million contract should any other team be interested. It is also no secret that the boos at Shea bother Kent -- who is playing out of position at third base this season -- a lot more than he lets on.</p>
        <p>But those jeers actually turned into cheers last night after Kent rolled a two-out, two-run single up the middle -- and off shortstop Edgar Renteria's glove -- with the bases loaded in the fifth.</p>
        <p>"I think they were all for Clark," Kent said when asked about the rare cheers.</p>
        <p>Kent's single capped a three-run rally that began with the two quick outs. It chased David Weathers (2-1), against whom Kent has got 9 hits in 15 career at-bats, with 8 runs batted in.</p>
        <p>"I thought Jeff played a tremendous game," said Manager Dallas Green. "But it's the same old thing. We'd like more consistency out of everybody."</p>
        <p>Save Clark, who allowed his first earned run in 23 innings last night. The big right-hander has now gone at least 6 innings in 11 of his 12 starts this season. His 7 strikeouts last night were a career high. And his 3.08 earned run  average is the team's best.</p>
        <p>Clark, who surrendered eight hits and three runs in his seven and a third innings last night, allowed a mammoth 427-foot home run to Devon White that bounded off the back of the Mets' bullpen in right field leading off the third.  That was about it until the eighth.</p>
        <p>A late March acquisition, Clark retired the next 13 batters before pitching his way out of a little trouble in the seventh. By that time, Clark, had -- for  him -- a comfortable lead.</p>
        <p>"It makes it a little bit easier, anyway," Clark said of the unusual support.</p>
        <p>The Mets had tied the score in the fourth with an unearned run off Weathers,  who was starting because Brown had injured an ankle in a fishing mishap earlier  in the week. Bernard Gilkey had led off the inning with a pop-up just left of home plate. But the usually sure-handed Terry Pendleton, who had called catcher  Rob Natal off the ball, dropped it.</p>
        <p>Given the reprieve, Gilkey singled up the middle, took third on a Todd Hundley single off the right-field fence, and scored on Kent's single to right.  On the play, Sheffield threw Kent out at second as he tried to stretch the hit into what would have been his second double of the game.</p>
        <p>It was the only mistake Kent would make all evening.</p>
        <p>When he came to bat in the fifth, the Mets had taken a 2-1 lead on Johnson's  infield single that second baseman Ralph Milliard could not come up with, and a  Jose Vizcaino double into the gap in left-center. Conine had dived unsuccessfully for Vizcaino's hit and Johnson beat Pendleton's relay home with a nice slide, knocking Natal's back leg off the plate before Natal could apply the tag.</p>
        <p>Gilkey then walked on four pitches, as did Hundley, to load the bases. Kent,  who was batting a tepid .209 with runners in scoring position entering the game, took a ball -- the ninth consecutive pitch by Weathers out of the strike zone -- then delivered his two-run single for a 4-1 lead.</p>
        <p>That lead would become 7-1 after a three-run seventh, highlighted by Hundley's 14th home run of the season, a two-run shot that sailed over the red apple in center field. The blast measured 429 feet.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
