<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.B.I. Tightening Its Rules On Files for White House</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="856601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS: ADMINISTRATION ACTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL BUREAU OF INVESTIGATION (FBI) FEDERAL BUREAU OFINVESTIGATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, NEIL A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEH, LOUIS J (DIR) LOUIS J FREEH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5D71639F93AA35755C0A960958260" item-length="496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.B.I. Tightening Its Rules On Files for White House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, NEIL A;</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Louis J. Freeh, the director of the F.B.I., has ordered new restrictions on sharing confidential information with the White House after the disclosure that  the Clinton White House had improperly obtained the files of several prominent Republicans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeh's order was in a letter to Representative William F. Clinger Jr., a Pennsylvania Republican who spoke to him on Friday about possible abuses by the  White House in obtaining confidential files. Mr. Clinger released the letter today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Louis J. Freeh, the director of the F.B.I., has ordered new restrictions on sharing confidential information with the White House after the disclosure that  the Clinton White House had improperly obtained the files of several prominent Republicans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeh's order was in a letter to Representative William F. Clinger Jr., a Pennsylvania Republican who spoke to him on Friday about possible abuses by the  White House in obtaining confidential files. Mr. Clinger released the letter today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeh said he would seek to modify the procedures that allow the White House to simply requisition confidential information.</p>
        <p>"While many of the requests are simple name checks, others involve sensitive  personal information from background investigations," he said.</p>
        <p>The White House said on Friday that it had sought and received files on several Republicans from the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, after investigating the dismissal of seven employees of the White House travel office, Mr. Clinger said he had discovered that the White House obtained the F.B.I. file on Billy R. Dale, seven months after Mr. Dale was dismissed as the office director in May 1993. The reason listed on the request form sent to the F.B.I. was that Mr. Dale was being checked for a security clearance for the White House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinger asserted that the real reason might have been to learn damaging information about Mr. Dale to discredit him. On Friday, White House officials said his file was sought with as many as 340 others as part of a broader but innocent bureaucratic mistake.</p>
        <p>Mark Fabiani, a special White House counsel, said a civilian employee of the  Army detailed to help the White House security office had mistakenly used an old list. Mr. Fabiani said the employee had been assigned to update security clearances of Republican holdovers working in the Clinton Administration.</p>
        <p>Among the Republicans whose files were obtained in 1993 and 1994 were James A. Baker 3d, former Secretary of State; A. B. Culvahouse, former White House counsel, and Kenneth Duberstein, former White House chief of staff and now an adviser to Gen. Colin L. Powell.</p>
        <p>Representative Dick Armey of Texas, the House Republican leader, promised today that there would be an inquiry. Kenneth W. Starr, the independent counsel  investigating Whitewater-related matters, has also begun an investigation.</p>
        <p>The Army employee, Anthony Marceca, told The Associated Press that he had been assigned to help clear up a backlog on security clearances. Mr. Marceca said some of the work might have been reviewed by Craig Livingstone, who headed  the security office and was a Clinton political appointee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fabiani was unable to say whether Mr. Livingstone had reviewed any of the files of the Republicans. The files were returned to the F.B.I. on Thursday.</p>
        <p>POLITICS: ADMINISTRATION ACTION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
