<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summer Grilling: Some Fine Points on Seafood</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="856333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E2DA1639F93AA35755C0A960958260" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summer Grilling: Some Fine Points on Seafood</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEAFOOD on the grill may dominate the menu for the next three months. Skewering seafood simplifies preparation and serving. I like to use 12-inch wood skewers for seafood. Because wood does not conduct heat as readily as metal, it  is less likely that delicate seafood will be overcooked.</p>
        <p>And using two skewers side by side for each brochette holds the food securely, preventing it from twisting around as it is turned. Soaking the skewers in water for about 30 minutes before threading them with food will prevent burning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEAFOOD on the grill may dominate the menu for the next three months. Skewering seafood simplifies preparation and serving. I like to use 12-inch wood skewers for seafood. Because wood does not conduct heat as readily as metal, it  is less likely that delicate seafood will be overcooked.</p>
        <p>And using two skewers side by side for each brochette holds the food securely, preventing it from twisting around as it is turned. Soaking the skewers in water for about 30 minutes before threading them with food will prevent burning.</p>
        <p>Shrimp is excellent for grilling on skewers. Meaty fish like swordfish, shark, tuna, monkfish and salmon are also excellent.</p>
        <p>Swordfish, Bay Leaf And Orange Brochettes  Total time: 1 hour</p>
        <p>48bay leaves 2pounds fresh swordfish, cut in 36 1 1/2-inch cubes 1/2 cup fresh orange juice 2large cloves garlic, finely minced 2tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil Hot red pepper flakes to taste Salt to taste 2juice oranges, each cut in 12 wedges 2cups steamed white rice seasoned with salt and black pepper 1tablespoon finely minced parsley.</p>
        <p>1. Soak the bay leaves and 24 12-inch wooden skewers in warm water.</p>
        <p>2. Put the swordfish cubes in a shallow dish. Mix the orange juice, garlic, oil, pepper flakes and salt together. Pour over the swordfish, turning the fish  to coat it. Refrigerate to marinate 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>3. Light a grill.</p>
        <p>4. Holding two skewers close together, thread with alternating swordfish, bay leaf, orange wedge and another bay leaf, repeating the ingredients and ending with a piece of swordfish.</p>
        <p>5. Grill the brochettes about 10 minutes, until the swordfish is cooked through. Serve on a bed of rice seasoned with salt and pepper. Sprinkle with parsley.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings. Shrimp Brochettes With Asian Glaze Total time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>1tablespoon light soy sauce 1tablespoon rice-wine vinegar 2tablespoons sesame oil 1teaspoon chili oil 1teaspoon honey 24large shrimps (about 1 pound) 2tablespoons sesame seeds 1lime, cut in wedges.</p>
        <p>1. Soak 12 8-inch wooden skewers in water.</p>
        <p>2. Mix the soy sauce, vinegar, sesame oil, chili oil and honey together, and  set aside. Preheat a grill.</p>
        <p>3. Holding two skewers close together, thread each pair with four shrimps, taking care that they all lie in the same direction. Brush with the soy sauce mixture.</p>
        <p>4. Just before grilling, spread the sesame seeds on a plate and dip each skewer lightly into the seeds to coat the shrimps with seeds.</p>
        <p>5. Grill the shrimps about two minutes on each side, just until they turn pink. Serve as an appetizer with wedges of lime.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 appetizer servings.</p>
        <p>Mediterranean Mixed Grill  Total time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>16jumbo shrimps, peeled and deveined 1 1/2pounds fresh tuna, in 16 1 1/2-inch cubes Juice of 1 lemon 3tablespoons extra-virgin olive oil 1/2teaspoon ground cumin 1teaspoon finely minced fresh coiander Salt and freshly ground black pepper 2chorizo sausages 2sweet red peppers, cut in 24 1 1/2-inch squares 1lemon, quartered.</p>
        <p>1. Put the shrimps and tuna in a shallow dish. Beat the lemon and oil together with the cumin and coriander. Season with salt and pepper, and pour over the seafood, turning the seafood to coat it. Put in the refrigerator to marinate 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Soak 16 12-inch wooden skewers in water.</p>
        <p>3. Saute the chorizo in a skillet until lightly browned. Remove from the skillet and set aside to cool. Cut in quarters.</p>
        <p>4. Preheat a grill. Holding two skewers about half an inch apart, thread each pair of skewers with a shrimp, a piece of pepper, a piece of tuna, a piece of chorizo, a piece of tuna, a piece of pepper and a shrimp. Repeat, threading eight skewers.</p>
        <p>5. Grill the brochettes about 10 minutes, until the shrimps are cooked and lightly charred and the tuna is cooked on the outside but still rare within. Serve at once with lemon wedges.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
