<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Twist in a Russian Cellphone Caper</title>
    <meta content="24phone" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/24/business/worldbusiness/24phone.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1799417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Moscow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Moscow (Russia)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Motorola Inc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EEDB173FF937A15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="620" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Twist in a Russian Cellphone Caper</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A New Twist in a Russian Cellphone Caper</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW E. KRAMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kramer, Andrew E</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Oct. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tale of the 167,000 Motorola cellphones took another turn on Monday.</p>
        <p>In the first chapter seven months ago, the Interior Ministry seized the phones at a Moscow airport. The ministry said first that the phones were counterfeit, then contraband and then a health hazard. A month later, government officials, with Russian news media cameras flashing, fed thousands of the phones into a chipping machine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moscow prosecutors say they are investigating whether 30,000 handsets that were supposedly destroyed were, in fact, sold at knockdown prices in stores in the Russian provinces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The tale of the 167,000 Motorola cellphones took another turn on Monday.</p>
        <p>In the first chapter seven months ago, the Interior Ministry seized the phones at a Moscow airport. The ministry said first that the phones were counterfeit, then contraband and then a health hazard. A month later, government officials, with Russian news media cameras flashing, fed thousands of the phones into a chipping machine.</p>
        <p>But in the latest chapter, Moscow prosecutors say they are investigating whether 30,000 handsets that were supposedly destroyed were, in fact, sold at knockdown prices in stores in the Russian provinces.</p>
        <p>The phones were tagged with electronic serial numbers called I.M.E.I., or international mobile equipment identity, which have registered for months on cellphone networks in Russia, the prosecutors said. The investigation is being conducted by the Moscow prosecutor's office; it is not clear why the city authority was handling the case.</p>
        <p>The revelation raised the possibility that in a brazen example of corruption even by Russian standards, the police had simply seized the phones and sold them for personal profit.</p>
        <p>Motorola's case had already became a cautionary tale about doing business in Russia, where despite the great economic gains in recent years, demands for kickbacks and bribes are an everyday part of life. As the state's share of the economy grows, so has the sense of entitlement by government employees at all levels, government experts say.</p>
        <p>Motorola has taken a low-key approach to sorting out what happened. The company did not bill the Russian government for the missing phones, valued at $2 million. The balance of the initial shipment of 167,000 was returned in August.</p>
        <p>By Monday, Motorola had not been formally notified of the latest investigation, and so could not comment, said Kirill M. Lubnin, a spokesman for Motorola's Russian office. The company provided the Russian authorities with the identification numbers last spring, he said.</p>
        <p>Svetlana Petrenko, a spokeswoman for the Moscow prosecutor's office, confirmed the investigation in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>Moscow prosecutors, working with identification numbers and network operators, suspect about 30,000 handsets that were supposed to have been destroyed are now in use, according to the business daily Vedomosti, which first reported the developments Monday.</p>
        <p>Phone calls were not answered at the press office of the police division known as Department K, which had previously notified Motorola that the 50,000 phones had been destroyed.</p>
        <p>Even before the latest revelation, analysts of Russia's booming cellphone market say they had noticed strange sales patterns for Motorola's C115 model, a no-frills, black plastic phone about the size of a cigarette pack that retails for around $50 but briefly got a lot cheaper last spring.</p>
        <p>Prices for C115's during the week of May 7 in the Krasnodar region, an agricultural area 700 miles south of Moscow, dropped to $19 to $22, according to Eldar V. Murtazin, chief analyst at the Mobile Research Group, a Russian company researching the handset phone market.</p>
        <p>''We can't confirm that these were the phones,'' he said. ''We can say that during this time we saw a noncharacteristic drop in price for this model in some parts of the country.''</p>
        <p>At the time, he said, his company decided the slump in C115 prices resulted from retailers dumping the model because of concern that the Russian authorities would ban sales of the unit. Now, he said, it appears the drop was simply a market reaction to a flood of cheap phones being dumped quickly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murtazin said that a private contractor was hired to grind up the phones and that it was not clear whether the latest investigation was aimed at the police from Department K or at employees of the contractor.</p>
        <p>''This was not Motorola's problem,'' he added.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
