<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italian Settles Fraud Charges in MGM Deal</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="820171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SECURITIES AND COMMODITIES VIOLATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINES (PENALTIES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS ANDSWINDLING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MGM/UA COMMUNICATIONS CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SECURITIES AND EXCHANGE COMMISSION(SEC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PATHE COMMUNICATIONS CO SECURITIES &amp; EXCHANGE COMMISSION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARRETTI, GIANCARLO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FIORINI, FLORIO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAPPUCCIO, FERNANDO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EFDD1239F937A35752C0A960958260" item-length="475" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italian Settles Fraud Charges in MGM Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Giancarlo Parretti, the Italian financier and former owner of MGM studios, and two associates settled Federal securities-fraud charges today related to the 1990 takeover of MGM, without agreeing to financial penalties.</p>
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission filed civil fraud charges in United States District Court here against Mr. Parretti, former chief executive of the Pathe Communications Corporation. The charges concerned Pathe's purchase of MGM/ UA Communications and a deal in 1989 involving several European theaters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Giancarlo Parretti, the Italian financier and former owner of MGM studios, and two associates settled Federal securities-fraud charges today related to the 1990 takeover of MGM, without agreeing to financial penalties.</p>
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission filed civil fraud charges in United States District Court here against Mr. Parretti, former chief executive of the Pathe Communications Corporation. The charges concerned Pathe's purchase of MGM/ UA Communications and a deal in 1989 involving several European theaters.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. also filed related administrative charges against Florio Fiorini, former chairman of Pathe, and Fernando Cappuccio, the company's former chief financial officer.</p>
        <p>The three agreed to settle the cases without admitting or denying wrongdoing. While no financial penalties were levied, the men agreed that they would not violate securities laws in the future.</p>
        <p>The charges are the latest headache for Mr. Parretti, who was held in October on a French arrest warrant charging him with misuse of company assets, forgery,  embezzlement and perjury. France charged him with defrauding the state-owned bank Credit Lyonnais, which foreclosed on MGM shortly after Pathe acquired the movie studio.</p>
        <p>In 1992, Mr. Parretti was indicted in Delaware on charges of perjury and evidence tampering related to the Credit Lyonnais dispute.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. case had charged that during Pathe's acquisition of MGM/ UA Communications, Mr. Parretti and Mr. Fiorini failed to record in Pathe's books a $305 million short-term loan and a sale of licensing rights that raised $113 million in cash. It charged further that the two took out the loan when they could not raise the financing needed for the MGM deal, then obligated Pathe to repay the loan after the merger.</p>
        <p>The commission brought charges against all three men concerning Pathe's sale  and lease-back of theaters in Britain and the Netherlands to a company called Cinema 5 N.V., a transaction that raised $231 million.</p>
        <p>It said the deal had been falsely recorded in Pathe's S.E.C. filings as a sale to an independent company. The complaint said the transaction "was a sham because Cinema 5 was not independent of Pathe." It said that Pathe provided the  funds to establish Cinema 5 and that the executives of the company were friends  of Mr. Parretti. The commission also charged that the deal overstated Pathe's financial results for 1989 and the first quarter of 1990.</p>
        <p>In July 1992, Pathe Communications was delisted from the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>Jay Coggan, Mr. Parretti's lawyer, said, "Mr. Parretti has not been found responsible for any wrongdoing."</p>
        <p>S.E.C. officials said Mr. Fiorini and Mr. Cappuccio were not represented by lawyers and were living somewhere in Switzerland.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
