<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garden Q. and A.</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="820240"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PENNSYLVANIA HORTICULTURAL SOCIETY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E2DC1239F937A35752C0A960958260" item-length="582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garden Q. and A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dora Galitzki</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Annual Gold Medal Winners</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Annual Gold Medal Winners</p>
        <p>Unlike the Oscar, Emmy and Tony, not all awards go to the famous. Since 1988, the Pennsylvania Horticultural Society Gold Medal Plant Awards have given attention to underused woody plants.</p>
        <p>Nurserymen, horticulturists and amateur gardeners nominate plants that they  feel are outstanding. Three specimens of each plant, all landscape size and from the mid-Atlantic region, are evaluated by a committee of professionals who then  choose the winners. By introducing these plants to a wider audience, the society hopes to encourage more diversity in garden planting and to increase the number  of growers and retailers offering these plants.</p>
        <p>The four winners for 1996 are Acer triflorum, a small specimen maple with spectacular fall colors; Ilex x meserveae Mesid Blue Maid, a heat- and cold-tolerant evergreen holly; Ilex verticillata Scarlett O'Hara, a deciduous holly with small, red fruit, and Syringa reticulata Ivory Silk, a summer flowering tree lilac.</p>
        <p>A list, including sources and descriptions, of the 50 winners since 1988 can  be obtained by sending a self-addressed envelope bearing 52 cents in stamps to:  Gold Medal Plant Award, Pennsylvania Horticultural Society, 325 Walnut Street, Philadelphia 19106-2777.</p>
        <p>Growing Popcorn  Q.  While we were taking down the Christmas tree, my kids asked if we could grow our own popcorn for next year's roping. One of them also asked me, what makes it pop? Can you offer any help?</p>
        <p>A.  To pop, a kernel of corn needs three things. It needs enough moisture to create pressure of 135 pounds a square inch when heated to 400 degrees Fahrenheit. It has to contain a hard starch that turns gelatinous and is carried along when the moisture becomes steam and bursts through the hull. And it needs  a hull strong enough to hold in pressure, but not so much as to turn a bowl of kernels into a weapon of mass destruction. Only special varieties of corn provide the right combination.</p>
        <p>Plant popcorn in the spring, after the danger of frost is past. Popcorn has to grow past the time when sweet corn is ready, so that the kernels can become hard and mature. Some varieties are ready in September; others may need to grow  through October. To judge, pick a bright, hard kernel. Scrape the edge where it  joined the cob and look for a thin black layer that forms when the corn is ready.</p>
        <p>Husk the corn, and let it dry on the cob in a dry, airy place. It can take several weeks to reach the right moisture level. Removing some kernels occasionally for a test pop is the only way to tell. Shell the kernels, and store in an airtight jar.</p>
        <p>There are only a few varieties sold for home gardens, while there are about 40 choices for commercial growers. Popcorn varieties are available from Johnny's Selected Seeds, Foss Hill Road, Albion, Me. 04910-9731, and from Stokes Seeds, Box 548, Buffalo 14240-0548 (catalogues from both are free).</p>
        <p>There must not be much taste difference among varieties. Otherwise, at the movie theater, one would hear: "I'll have the Idaho-grown Robust 10-84 with double butter, no salt. And she'll have the Kansas varietal White Cloud, half-butter, half-margarine, with the salt substitute."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
