<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clemency Granted to 25 Women Convicted for Assault or Murder</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="410283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BATTERED SPOUSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMNESTIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">OHIO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILKERSON, ISABEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CELESTE, RICHARD F (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amnesties and Pardons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D9113EF931A15751C1A966958260" item-length="1248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clemency Granted to 25 Women Convicted for Assault or Murder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISABEL WILKERSON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILKERSON, ISABEL</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAG0, Dec. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Richard F. Celeste of Ohio granted clemency today to 25 women who had been convicted of killing or assaulting husbands or companions who the women said had physically abused them.</p>
        <p>Twenty-one of the women are to be freed in the coming weeks, and the remaining four will be required to serve at least two years of their sentences before release.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Richard F. Celeste of Ohio granted clemency today to 25 women who had been convicted of killing or assaulting husbands or companions who the women said had physically abused them.</p>
        <p>Twenty-one of the women are to be freed in the coming weeks, and the remaining four will be required to serve at least two years of their sentences before release.</p>
        <p>It was the first mass release of battered women inmates in this country, advocates of abused women said. The move was praised by women's rights advocates but assailed by judges and prosecutors.</p>
        <p>Governor Celeste, who is leaving office next month, cited a ruling by the state's highest court this year that allowed female defendants to present expert testimony, for the first time, in a defense of being a "battered woman." In light of this, he said, he reviewed the records of more than 100 women imprisoned for killing or assaulting a spouse or male companion and decided to commute the sentences of 25 of them.  'These Women Were Entrapped'</p>
        <p>Governor Celeste defended the releases as recognition of the complicated lives and motivations of the women. "These women were entrapped emotionally and physically," Governor Celeste said in a telephone interview. "They were the victims of violence, repeated violence. They loved these men even though they beat them and feared them. They were so emotionally entangled they were incapable of walking away. If I thought they would be a threat I wouldn't have commuted their sentences."</p>
        <p>Dr. Lenore Walker, executive director of the Domestic Violence Institute, a nonprofit research and advocacy group in Denver, said: "This is a signal to the rest of the country that women will no longer permit themselves to be battered and abused by men. They should never have been in prison in the first place. Women don't kill men unless they've been pushed to a point of desperation."</p>
        <p>But prosecutors said the action today could encourage more women to use violence to escape abuse. "The fact that you're battered does not give you the license to kill," said Dennis Watkins, the Trumbull County prosecutor and president of the Ohio Prosecuting Attorneys' Association, which represents most of the state's prosecutors. "Now, instead of going to the courts or getting a divorce, these women will think, 'Maybe I'll kill him.'</p>
        <p>"Taking a human life is not something we want to promote."</p>
        <p>Last summer, after the Ohio Supreme Court's ruling, the State Legislature approved a bill that essentially ratified the court's ruling. The bill was signed by the Governor.</p>
        <p>Granting the clemency was Governor Celeste's last major action before leaving office and an especially symbolic one for a man who, with his wife, Dagmar, turned their Cleveland home into a shelter for battered women when he moved to Columbus to became Lieutenant Governor in the mid-1970's. Mr. Celeste, who has served two terms, is barred by state law from seeking a third term.</p>
        <p>For several months, the Governor said, he reviewed the files of 105 women, rejected the requests of 48 of them and today returned the cases of 32 others to the State Parole Board for further review.</p>
        <p>The 25 women whose sentences were commuted will have to perform 200 hours of community service in a domestic violence program. The Governor's action does not expunge the crimes from their records.</p>
        <p>The longest time served by any of the women has been nine years and the shortest six months. The Governor's office did not release details of the crimes for which the women were convicted or any of the abuse they said they had endured.</p>
        <p>Ohio was one of the last major states where women were barred from presenting expert testimony about being physically abused, women's rights advocates and the Governor's aides said. This barred them from presenting a genuine defense when they contended they had been abused.  Overturning Manslaughter</p>
        <p>In the Ohio Supreme Court ruling, it overturned the manslaughter conviction of Brenda Koss of Cleveland, who shot and killed her husband on May 2, 1986, after having been beaten by him for years. The court ruled that Mrs. Koss had suffered from a "battered woman syndrome" in which the victim suffers repeated physical and psychological blows and may be driven to lash out at her abuser. The court said that Mrs. Koss should have been allowed to present testimony describing the effects of such abuse at her trial.</p>
        <p>But prosecutors argue that because the Ohio Supreme Court did not make its ruling retroactive, it was not necessarily intended for these women the Governor is freeing. In addition, they say, the inmates' claims of abuse are no guarantee that they would have been acquitted of the charges had such evidence been permitted at their trials.</p>
        <p>"When the victim is killed while he is sleeping, battering is not a proper self-defense claim," said John Murphy, executive director of the Ohio Prosecuting Attorneys' Association. "Our concern is that in the future we're going to get a lot of women claiming to be battered. In our view, it is not a proper defense for murder."</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins put it another way: "There are women who are battered -- no question. But some of these women are making this up."</p>
        <p>The Governor's effort started a year ago when he told his aides to review the records of women convicted of violent crimes against spouses or companions that may have been brought on by physical abuse.</p>
        <p>The Governor's aides said that the effort to distinguish the truly abused inmates required months of investigation into almost 10 percent of the 1,958 women incarcerated in Ohio, most of them for homicide and assault.</p>
        <p>They came up with the cases of more than 100 inmates, who were given a chance to go before the State Parole Board and present evidence of past abuse. The women produced emergency room records documenting bruises and broken bones, brought in police reports and doctor's statements and in some cases had witnesses testify to the abuse.  Most Convicted in Slayings</p>
        <p>Most of the women were convicted of killing a spouse or companion, or of having hired a killer to do so. The ages of the women ranged from early 20's to late 60's. A 31-year-old Cleveland woman who is to be released has lost sight in one eye and hearing in one ear. A woman in her 20's has been in prison since she was 16, serving 15 years to life for killing her father, who had been sexually molesting her, prison officials said. The officials said they were unable to identify the women today.</p>
        <p>Governor Celeste said he considered the women's previous records, their behavior in prison and whether it was the woman's first offense and selected the 105 for review.</p>
        <p>"I don't belive anyone in his right mind should take this as any kind of a license to kill," he said. "Being battered is no guarantee of an acquittal. These women were not able to introduce any evidence of battering in any aspect of their defense. They were not able to describe the most profound events when the violence occurred."</p>
        <p>Women's rights advocates viewed the developments in Ohio as a landmark in their crusade. "Just the recognition that our prisions are full of women abused is so overdue, so long in coming," said Sue Osthoff, director of the National Clearinghouse for the Defense of Battered Women, a nonprofit research group. "His actually taking the time to look into these cases is phenomenal. The follow-through is unprecedented. These women have endured punishment I hope I never get near."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
