<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Seems Like Old Times as Kelly and Young Take to the Air</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="556500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BUFFALO BILLS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Buffalo Bills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/San Francisco 49ers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D71731F937A2575AC0A964958260" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Seems Like Old Times as Kelly and Young Take to the Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL MARTINEZ,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Sept. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When they were younger and there used to be something called the United States Football League, Jim Kelly and Steve Young had these kinds of days almost routinely. But this was a long way from the Houston Gamblers and the Los Angeles Express.</p>
        <p>Kelly and Young passed and passed into the fading afternoon sun today. Kelly threw for 403 yards and three touchdowns. Young had 449 yards and three more touchdowns. But at the end of the day, a missed field goal by the 49ers' Mike Cofer prevented overtime and allowed the Buffalo Bills to hold on to a 34-31 victory over San Francisco at Candlestick Park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When they were younger and there used to be something called the United States Football League, Jim Kelly and Steve Young had these kinds of days almost routinely. But this was a long way from the Houston Gamblers and the Los Angeles Express.</p>
        <p>Kelly and Young passed and passed into the fading afternoon sun today. Kelly threw for 403 yards and three touchdowns. Young had 449 yards and three more touchdowns. But at the end of the day, a missed field goal by the 49ers' Mike Cofer prevented overtime and allowed the Buffalo Bills to hold on to a 34-31 victory over San Francisco at Candlestick Park.</p>
        <p>"It seems every time I get into a game with Steve Young, it's a shootout going back to our U.S.F.L. days," said Kelly, the former Gamblers quarterback.</p>
        <p>Kelly completed 22 of 33 passes, two of them third-quarter touchdowns to tight end Pete Metzelaars that erased an 11-point halftime deficit. Kelly reached 20,000 yards in career passing, and his yardage total was a regular-season career best. Together, the teams combined for 852 yards passing, 33 short of the National Football League record, set by the Jets and Dolphins in 1986.</p>
        <p>Young was 26 of 37, but he threw one fourth-quarter interception that stopped a drive and missed two late passes that left the 49ers with a fourth down at the Bills' 29-yard line. Cofer, who had missed a 33-yarder in the opening period, then was wide to the right from 47 yards with one minute left.</p>
        <p>The Bills (2-0) finished with 488 yards in offense. The 49ers (1-1) had a team-record 598 yards and averaged 8.8 yards per play.</p>
        <p>There was also an N.F.L. first: no punts by either team.</p>
        <p>"We didn't need any punters today," said Bills wide receiver James Lofton.</p>
        <p>The 49ers had to contend with Buffalo's no-huddle offense, and Kelly's quick passes to Thurman Thomas, Lofton and Metzelaars kept the deciding drive moving. Lofton made up for a dropped touchdown pass in the second period when he caught a 9-yarder from Young on fourth down at the 49ers' 11. On the next play, Thomas ran up the middle for a touchdown and the lead with 3 minutes 4 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Asked later about his miss, Lofton smiled and said, "I think there was a mild tremor in the area." Two 49er Receivers Out</p>
        <p>Young threw a first-quarter touchdown to the former Giant Odessa Turner and a second-quarter touchdown to John Taylor, but his interception was right into the arms of Bills cornerback Nate Odomes at Buffalo's 28. It was meant for Mike Sherrard, who ended the day with 6 catches for 159 yards.</p>
        <p>"I had thrown that route a couple of times, but I just threw it behind him," Young said. "He was open. If you throw enough balls, that's a chance you take."</p>
        <p>The 49ers were without two of their more dependable receivers. Jerry Rice suffered a concussion in the opening minutes and never returned. Tight end Brent Jones sustained a sprained hamstring in the second period and sat the rest of the afternoon. Between them, they had 97 receptions last season.</p>
        <p>Down by 24-13 at the half, Kelly brought his team back quickly. On the fifth play of the third quarter, he found Metzelaars in a seam in the middle of the field at the 30 and threw it. Metzelaars then ran in for the score.</p>
        <p>The Bills forced a turnover on San Francisco's next possession when defensive end Bruce Smith forced a fumble on a run by Keith Henderson. The ball was recovered by Cornelius Bennett at the Buffalo 40.</p>
        <p>Kelly completed four consecutive passes out of a shotgun formation, including the last one to Metzelaars for 24 yards and a 27-24 lead. Andre Reed had two receptions in the drive and totaled 10 for 144 yards.</p>
        <p>The 49ers moved back in front when Young threw a 54-yard touchdown pass to Taylor, but it was their last lead.</p>
        <p>"Nobody outsmarted anybody this afternoon," said Bills Coach Marv Levy. "There was no magic, no mirrors."</p>
        <p>Nothing but passing.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
