<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Microsoft to Back a Browser Keyword System</title>
    <meta content="Y14REA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1183826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">RealNames Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harmon, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DC103BF937A25750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Microsoft to Back a Browser Keyword System</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY HARMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harmon, Amy</byline>
      <dateline>SCOTTSDALE, Ariz., March 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Microsoft Corp is xpected to announce that it is backing keyword system that aims to enable Internet users to navigate Web without typing in cumbersome addresses known as URL's; technology, developed by RealNames Corp, allows Web users to type in name of company or product--without ususal'www.' precede and '.com' suffix--and zip directly to site of entity that has paid RealNames to lock up that keyword; Microsoft will take 20 percent equity stake in RealNames, which has filed for initial public offering (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Microsoft Corporation is expected to announce Tuesday that it is throwing its considerable weight behind a keyword system that aims to enable Internet users to navigate the Web without typing in the cumbersome addresses known as U.R.L.'s.</p>
        <p>The technology, developed by RealNames Corporation of Redwood City, Calif., allows Web users to type in the name of a company or product -- without the usual ''www.'' precede and ''.com'' suffix -- and zip directly to the site of the entity that has paid RealNames to lock up that keyword.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Microsoft Corporation is expected to announce Tuesday that it is throwing its considerable weight behind a keyword system that aims to enable Internet users to navigate the Web without typing in the cumbersome addresses known as U.R.L.'s.</p>
        <p>The technology, developed by RealNames Corporation of Redwood City, Calif., allows Web users to type in the name of a company or product -- without the usual ''www.'' precede and ''.com'' suffix -- and zip directly to the site of the entity that has paid RealNames to lock up that keyword.</p>
        <p>As part of the deal, company officials said today, Microsoft will take a 20 percent equity stake in RealNames, which has filed for an initial public offering of its stock. Microsoft's chief executive, Steve Ballmer, is expected to announce the move at PC Forum, the annual technology conference here sponsored by Edventure Holdings.</p>
        <p>RealNames charges large corporations $100,000 to $300,000 a year to license a keyword, and 10 cents to $1 per visit generated. Small businesses can buy a keyword for $100 a year. AltaVista, Inktomi and the Go Network are among the Internet companies using the system.</p>
        <p>At least for now, the system also takes users in many cases to the most likely intended site, even if the keyword has not been purchased. For example, Apple Computer's homepage comes up if the word ''apple'' alone is typed as the U.R.L., or uniform resource locator. Generic terms like ''pizza'' generates a list of search results.</p>
        <p>In recent months Microsoft has incorporated the technology into its Internet Explorer browser. It will now do so with its MSN online service as well, alowing it to compete more effectively with America Online, which has long used its own keyword system.</p>
        <p>Netscape Navigator, the other popular Web browser, which is owned by AOL, does not use the RealNames keyword system, although it sometimes gives similar results. The deal with Microsoft does not prevent AOL from adopting the technology.</p>
        <p>The RealNames system includes an elaborate tracking scheme that the company says allows it to measure the effectiveness of off-line advertisements that mention the keyword. RealNames hopes keywords will replace domain name addresses and 800 numbers in print and television advertising.</p>
        <p>Esther Dyson, the host of the conference here, said that using keywords would be a welcome new way to surf the Web. ''It's a very nice concept,'' she said. ''There are lots of different ways to get to U.R.L.'s and this is one of them. The world needs more creative navigation interfaces.''</p>
        <p>But she added that just as with the system of allocating domain names, which is in being opened up to competition, there is a potential danger of a keyword monopoly. (Ms. Dyson leads the group that is overseeing the new domain name system, but she did not speak in that capacity because the organization works by consensus and only sets policies for the domain system.)</p>
        <p>''Now that they've done a deal with Microsoft, that obviously puts them in a much stronger position,'' she said. ''Clearly, as long as people have alternatives there are no issues, but when people don't have alternatives, there are.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
