<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets or Expos Will Be Crowned the N.L. Least</title>
    <meta content="21CHAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/21/sports/baseball/21chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1613124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="On Baseball"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montreal Expos</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Montreal Expos</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National League</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EEDD1239F932A1575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets or Expos Will Be Crowned the N.L. Least</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets or Expos Will Be Crowned the N.L. Least</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murray Chass On Baseball column discusses National League East, which will see either New York Mets or Montreal Expos finish last; so-called race will be decided in two three-game series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FORGET Red Sox-Yankees. Never mind the National League wild card. Oakland-Anaheim, Los Angeles-San Francisco? Who cares? The most compelling race left is the pursuit of last place in the National League East.</p>
        <p>Major League Baseball's very own team, the Montreal Expos, has occupied last place since April 15, virtually the entire season. But now the Wilpon Nine, the no-longer lovable Mets, are threatening to displace the Expos and claim last place for themselves for the third successive season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most compelling race left is the pursuit of last place in the National League East between the Mets and Montreal Expos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FORGET Red Sox-Yankees. Never mind the National League wild card. Oakland-Anaheim, Los Angeles-San Francisco? Who cares? The most compelling race left is the pursuit of last place in the National League East.</p>
        <p>Major League Baseball's very own team, the Montreal Expos, has occupied last place since April 15, virtually the entire season. But now the Wilpon Nine, the no-longer lovable Mets, are threatening to displace the Expos and claim last place for themselves for the third successive season.</p>
        <p>The day the season resumed after the All-Star Game break, the Mets were only a game out of first and were 14 games ahead of the Expos. Now only two games separate the teams, and they will settle the difference in face-to-face confrontations. They open a three-game series in Montreal tonight, then finish the season with a three-game series at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>What great timing. The schedule maker deserves a bonus for having such great foresight in scheduling these series in the final two weeks of the season.</p>
        <p>Mets-Expos. Last place. Baseball fans live for this.</p>
        <p>Orlando Cabrera, the Expos' shortstop for six years, will not be part of that late-season excitement. Instead, he is almost certainly headed for the American League playoffs with his new team, the Boston Red Sox.</p>
        <p>If Cabrera, the latest casualty of Major League Baseball's ownership of the Expos, had a more reasonable choice, however, he would still be the shortstop for the Expos.</p>
        <p>There is nothing reasonable about the Expos' situation. This is hostage-holding, Year 3. Baseball officials have said there won't be a Year 4, but they have also said they would make a decision on the team's future by various dates, only to have all of those dates pass without a decision.</p>
        <p>Mid-September was the most recent period, cited in early August. Today is Sept. 21. By any definition, this is beyond the middle of the month. The Expos have no better idea where they will play next season than they had at any time in the past three seasons.</p>
        <p>Cabrera experienced all of this until the Expos, faced with their inability to sign him when he was a free-agent-in-waiting, traded him to the Red Sox on July 31. The Expos acted after Cabrera rejected a four-year contract offer for $30 million.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't about the money,'' Cabrera said. ''After you play for five or seven years, you make money anywhere. It was a bad situation all around. It's my career.</p>
        <p>''I want a team that I know will be here and they are building to win. Not that the Expos aren't doing that, but it's difficult for Omar to do that because he has to have permission from everybody before he can make a trade or go after somebody.''</p>
        <p>Major League Baseball doesn't tell Omar Minaya, the Montreal general manager, whom to trade or not sign, but it gives him a payroll limit, and that limit forces him to make deals and let players leave as free agents. Vladimir Guerrero, Javier Vazquez, Bartolo Colón, Michael Barrett, Cabrera, casualties all.</p>
        <p>They are casualties because for the most part they wanted to stay with the Expos, but the team had to shed them because a payroll of $42 million or less wouldn't hold them.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Bud Selig has often said that the Expos have had to make difficult decisions just like other teams. But other teams, other owners, make their own decisions; they don't have decisions made for them.</p>
        <p>If Fred Wilpon decides the addition of two established pitchers at midseason is worth the extra money for their salaries, the Mets make the deals. If Arte Moreno wants to offer Guerrero enough money to lure him to Anaheim, that's his prerogative as the Angels' owner.</p>
        <p>The Expos, however, operate in a straitjacket.</p>
        <p>''Last year, Sept. 1,'' Cabrera said, off on the date by only three days, ''we were tied for first place for the wild card, and we can't have September call-ups. We couldn't do any trades. We couldn't go after anybody. The team that won the wild card won the World Series. We had the possibility to win and they don't care. They didn't want us to win.''</p>
        <p>Adding an expensive player in a trade is one thing. It's another matter to bring up minor leaguers and give them $50,000 each for the month and meal money. The Expos, as Cabrera said, were not allowed to do that, limiting their ability to compete with the Florida Marlins for the N.L. wild card.</p>
        <p>Minaya and his manager, Frank Robinson, have done a marvelous job keeping the team sane and competitive. Given their extended road trips made longer by playing ''home'' games in Puerto Rico, the players could be expected to wilt. That's what happened last year.</p>
        <p>''They still haven't done it,'' Cabrera said of the absence of a decision. ''It's just a bad situation. They have to figure out what to do. They're going to have a young team all the time. I don't think any veteran wants to go up there and make all those travels or be in a city where no one wants the team.''</p>
        <p>But this season the young Expos have refused to quit. On the contrary, in the last two months the Expos have compiled a 30-26 record compared with the Mets' 18-38 record. That's a difference of 12 games, and that's why the Expos could dump the Mets into last place.</p>
        <p>It would be a fitting send-off for the Expos, if only they knew where they were being sent.</p>
        <p>On Baseball</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
