<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Missing Little League in Hope of Big Money</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="824311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="MINDING YOUR BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSONAL FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7D81339F932A15752C0A960958260" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Missing Little League in Hope of Big Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA PEDERSEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. I would like to start saving for my child's college education by getting him  work in modeling or commercials. Any advice?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. I would like to start saving for my child's college education by getting him  work in modeling or commercials. Any advice?</p>
        <p>A. If the lure of substantial or merely steady earnings is your only motivation  for coaxing your child in front of a camera, forget it and buy a bus ticket to Atlantic City. You'll have a lot more fun, and the odds of winning at the craps  tables are at least as good.</p>
        <p>Don't get me wrong. There is good money to be made in modeling and commercials. Hourly modeling fees for print advertising range from $60 to $75, while the daily rate for network television commercials is $414.25. And residuals, which are paid to actors every time their commercial is shown, are the original gift that keeps on giving.</p>
        <p>According to Natasha Esch, the president of Wilhelmina Models in New York and author of "Wilhelmina's World of Child Modeling" (Career Press, 1994, $14.95), "There are children making as much as $200,000 a year because they have worked on commercials that are being frequently aired in major markets."</p>
        <p>But of the tens of thousands of youngsters who sign on with casting agents and managers each year, only a handful wind up working regularly or earning big  dollars. And only a few make it to Hollywood. Jodie Foster went from being the Coppertone child to a two-time Academy-Award-winning actress.</p>
        <p>This is not an argument for squelching the idea if you believe that your child has the requisite looks, presence, talent and temperament. But don't move ahead on the assumption that it is a sound investment with an acceptable risk-reward ratio. It is anything but.</p>
        <p>When I say investment, I am measuring the potential losses for you and your child in time, energy, wounded pride and missed Little League practices. Although the train and taxi fares involved in darting to auditions and callbacks can add up, major financial risk should not be part of the picture. Reputable agents and managers work strictly on commission, and anyone demanding payment up front may well be pulling a fast one.</p>
        <p>"The only way an agent makes money is when your child makes money," said Sheila Manning, a Los Angeles casting agent. "Then the agent gets 10 percent. It's an unbreakable rule."</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, a disproportionate number of phony talent agents, managers and modeling schools show up on the Better Business Bureau's hit list each year. Many have been accused of bilking parents out of fees for overpriced publicity photos, fake "showcases" and useless directory listings. In 1993, one agent who  ran modeling agencies in several states drew a 37-month jail term after being convicted of mail fraud and money laundering. Among other excesses, he had collected $395 each from thousands of parents for photographs on false assurances that he had an extensive clientele of companies that hired models and actors.</p>
        <p>As a rule, it is not necessary to invest in expensive 8-by-10 publicity photographs for your youngster. Good-quality snapshots are perfectly acceptable.</p>
        <p>There is another inviolable rule, and it is probably the most important: Do not push your child into modeling if he or she is not willing. While some children love performing in school plays, hamming it up in front of friends and  otherwise being the center of attention, others clearly do not. Only a minority  will readily tolerate the intrusions into their lives, the depersonalization of  "cattle calls" and the inevitable rejections.</p>
        <p>"It can be a wonderful experience or an awful one, for both parents and child," said Kathleen Cirioli of Belle Mead, N.J., whose daughter, Meghan, 19, worked steadily and happily from the time she was 8 and is now financing her college education with earnings from modeling and television commercials. "An audition call can come in at any time, and you both have to be prepared to rearrange your lives on a moment's notice."</p>
        <p>Ms. Cirioli would sometimes appear without warning at Meghan's school to take her into Manhattan, 90 minutes away by train. Outings and play dates with friends might have to be scrubbed, and Meghan would have to do her homework in transit. "We'd spend half a day getting to and from a 10-minute audition that might or might not result in a callback," Ms. Cirioli said.</p>
        <p>Repeated rejections leave some parents thinking their children aren't sufficiently photogenic or telegenic. Not so. While physical beauty can be a plus, the right "look" is whatever the casting director wants for a given commercial. When Ms. Cirioli's daughter lost a front tooth the night before her  first commercial shoot, the family went into a panic. "But when we showed up," Ms. Cirioli said, "the director thought Meghan looked really cute."</p>
        <p>Children who are small for their age have an edge, however, because they may  have the memorization skills and maturity that younger children may lack.</p>
        <p>As a first step, you might get in touch with the dozens of agencies that deal with children and young adults. Many listings can be found in "The New York Agent Book" by K.  Callan (Sweden Press, fourth edition, 1995, $17.95). Or check the listings of managers and agencies in the trade publications Backstage and Ross Reports.</p>
        <p>Parents may choose to have a manager as well as an agent for their child. Compared with the agents' 10 percent, commissions for managers are typically 15  percent. Managers work with multiple agencies and tend to look out more for their clients. But the agencies get the calls, which they then pass on to the managers, so parents end up paying commissions to both, for a total of 25 percent.</p>
        <p>Keep in mind that there is no guarantee that your child will get a single audition, much less a job. "I'd say give it a year," advises Ms. Cirioli, who, as the director of two dance schools, works with many young students who audition regularly. "If your child hasn't landed at least one job, or seems stressed-out or is doing poorly in school, cut your losses." Life will be more relaxed, your child can still ham it up in front of friends, and you can save for college with zero-coupon bonds instead.</p>
        <p>Questions about investing, careers and personal finance can be sent to Minding Your Business, Money and Business, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York 10036. Or send them by E-mail to yourmind@nytimes.com. Questions can be answered only in the column, not by mail, E-mail or telephone.</p>
        <p>MINDING YOUR BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
