<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lace and Brocade, Wedding Gowns From Eras Past</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="824546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOUTHPORT CONGREGATIONAL CHURCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FITZPATRICK, JACKIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3D61339F932A15752C0A960958260" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lace and Brocade, Wedding Gowns From Eras Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACKIE FITZPATRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FITZPATRICK, JACKIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY were tucked away in attics, in boxes under beds, or hung in the far corner of closets. They were family treasures -- wedding gowns, dating back as far as 1790, many of which had aged remarkably well, the only hint of time passing being the golden color of a gown that once was white.</p>
        <p>The gowns come from families in Fairfield County and other parts of Connecticut, found by volunteer sleuths from the Southport Congregational Church and the Fairfield Historical Society. They will be featured in "The Connecticut Wedding: 200 Years of Tradition and Style," from 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. on Feb. 3 and 4 at the Southport Congregational Church, 524 Pequot Avenue, Southport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY were tucked away in attics, in boxes under beds, or hung in the far corner of closets. They were family treasures -- wedding gowns, dating back as far as 1790, many of which had aged remarkably well, the only hint of time passing being the golden color of a gown that once was white.</p>
        <p>The gowns come from families in Fairfield County and other parts of Connecticut, found by volunteer sleuths from the Southport Congregational Church and the Fairfield Historical Society. They will be featured in "The Connecticut Wedding: 200 Years of Tradition and Style," from 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. on Feb. 3 and 4 at the Southport Congregational Church, 524 Pequot Avenue, Southport.</p>
        <p>Colleen Everett, a chairwoman of the event said, "We wanted to show what women wore and what the traditions were when people married here 200 years ago.  We also wanted to reflect the trends of today."</p>
        <p>The exhibition will feature a wedding exhibit curated by the historical society as well as displays from bridal designers including Patricia Moran of Razook's in Greenwich, from florists, caterers and other suppliers to today's weddings.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 3 at 2 P.M., there will be a show, Bridal Gowns Through the Ages, and on Feb. 4 at 2 P.M. a Mother of the Bride and Groom Fashion Show. Ticket prices  for the events, range from $10 to $20, with the proceeds benefiting the church and the historical society.</p>
        <p>The first challenge for Mrs. Everett and her volunteers was to find the gowns of bygone eras. While the Fairfield Historical Society has an extensive collection of gowns from some of the founding families of the town, Ellen Endslow, the curator, said they were simply too fragile to be moved. Instead, the society lent a brocaded corset with metal stays, white silk wedding boots worn by a bride in the 1850's, wedding invitations from the late 1800's and lace handkerchiefs, a popular accessory, as well as other items.</p>
        <p>Church members and historical society volunteers started asking for old wedding gowns from anyone they happened to bump into. Word spread. Shirley Paustian, who as the archeologist for the Fairfield Historical Society is usually tracking other kinds of artifacts, and Karen Kaczenski were invited into people's closets, basements and attics.</p>
        <p>They and other volunteers found gowns worn by two and three generations of a  family, wedding clothes from families who were among the first to settle in Fairfield and more modern gowns from the free spirit 60's. Still others represented a style "when Fergie and Di were all the rage," said Ms. Paustian.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kaczenski said that when they found a gown, they almost always also came  across accessories the bride took with her down the aisle -- something from a mother, a grandmother, an aunt. "It was as if they had to take a piece of their  family with them," she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Paustian added, "A wedding seems to be a time when a family wants to make those connections, to keep binding the ties. It was a treasure hunt, really because a wedding gown is a treasure and a wedding is a defining moment for two  families that are brought together."</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Sesselberg, who is not a member of the church but said, "You can't  help but find out when something is going on in Southport," heard of the request and lent her mother's wedding gown and a gown from an ancestor dating back to about 1790. Her mother's gown was a silk chiffon with a beaded waist and its veil, which swept to the floor, included a lace panel which was a family heirloom dating back to the 1850's.</p>
        <p>The gown from the 1790's is an olive-colored silk brocade dress, with thistle and forget-me-nots in the fabric. "That dress has its own special history -- the groom's grandfather rode the same night as Paul Revere to warn the British were  coming," Ms. Sesselberg said.</p>
        <p>While the olive color might surprise some, Ms. Endslow said it was not until  the Victorian era and also when photographing weddings became popular that brides started to wear white.</p>
        <p>"Before that women were married in their best dress," she said. "They might be colored dresses or checked. They could wear the dress again because people dressed so much more formally then. Fashion was also determined by the social status of the family."</p>
        <p>The wedding celebrations in the late 1700's and early 1800's might go on for  several days, be it at a farmhouse or at a series of formal gatherings. The wedding cake, the flowers, the food, drink and merriment were integral parts of  the celebration.</p>
        <p>Lisa Maronian, owner of Sweet Lisa's of Greenwich, said the wedding cake has  always been and continues to be a centerpiece but tastes have changed. "People are getting away from the traditional white cake. Chocolate is our most popular  cake," she said, noting that a triple chocolate with dark chocolate icing and ribbons made of chocolate, "is really a show stopper."</p>
        <p>Tastes have changed in flowers as well. Whereas in centuries gone by, a bridal party had to make do with whatever could be grown in the local hothouse and often chose of pink and white if available, Peter Stephens, owner of Elegant Effects of Fairfield, said brides and grooms today want their personalities to show through. They might supplement flowers with berries, fruit or vegetables and today's popular colors are soft yellows, peaches, jewel tones and some white.</p>
        <p>Still, it is the wedding gown that continues to play a particularly prominent role. Ms. Moran of Razook's said the 1996 bride is steering clear of lace and opting instead for a simple, clean line, a return to the Jackie O. look. In place of lace there is "the drama of juxtaposing fabrics, the shine of satin combined with matte silk taffeta or pin-striped organza."</p>
        <p>The Rev. Paul Whitmore, minister of the Southport Congregational Church, said 200 years ago weddings played a powerful role in the life of a family and were a prime reason a community came together. Weddings continue to be major milestones, hence the emphasis on the day, from bridal gown to wedding cake.</p>
        <p>"Everyone goes into a wedding with hope and the expectation, I believe, that  they will be married forever. Obviously, there are a lot of challenges today," he said. "But people are still very hopeful."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
