<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Frantic Finale For Cities Vying For '12 Games</title>
    <meta content="04OLYM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/04/sports/othersports/04olympics.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1685014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Singapore</location>
        <org class="online_producer">International Olympic Committee</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4DC1E3AF937A35754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1332" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Frantic Finale For Cities Vying For '12 Games</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Frantic Finale for Cities Vying for 2012 Games</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <dateline>SINGAPORE, Monday, July 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International Olympic Committee members warily stepped out of elevators, looking both ways for solicitous representatives from the cities bidding to be host for the 2012 Olympics who might be lurking in the lobby.</p>
        <p>Soldiers who look barely old enough to drive were pacing outside the doors, toting machine guns and appearing impervious to the sweltering heat. The mayor of Paris, Bertrand Delanoë, huddled with advisers in the lobby bar, chain smoking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A vote by I.O.C. members on Wednesday in Singapore will decide what many consider the most hotly contested Olympics ever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International Olympic Committee members warily stepped out of elevators, looking both ways for solicitous representatives from the cities bidding to be host for the 2012 Olympics who might be lurking in the lobby.</p>
        <p>Soldiers who look barely old enough to drive were pacing outside the doors, toting machine guns and appearing impervious to the sweltering heat. The mayor of Paris, Bertrand Delanoë, huddled with advisers in the lobby bar, chain smoking.</p>
        <p>The entire scene paused as a huge security detail ushered Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain through the doors and into the elevator, a burst of camera flashes lighting his way.</p>
        <p>The frantic world of Olympic bidding has descended on this city-state in Southeast Asia, and a vote by I.O.C. members Wednesday will decide what many consider the most hotly contested Olympics ever -- with New York, Paris, London, Madrid and Moscow vying to win the 2012 Games.</p>
        <p>By all accounts, there are far more undecided I.O.C. members than usual this time around, making all the posturing and wooing necessary, and endlessly intriguing.</p>
        <p>As is their habit, I.O.C. members rarely tip their hands, addressing the race as evasively as possible. Most say the outcome will be extremely close, with voting going several rounds before a winner is determined. It has become an outsized civic beauty pageant.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen a contest like it,'' said Kevan Gosper of Australia, an I.O.C. member since 1977. ''It has got to be the greatest peacetime competition between five of the greatest and most historic cities in history, not just in Olympic history.''</p>
        <p>The scene swirls around two adjacent hotel lobbies, at Raffles and Swissôtel, with their various restaurants and bars, ringed by armed soldiers and metal detectors, and occasionally preoccupied with the arrival of a major dignitary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair created the biggest stir Sunday, with Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg of New York opting for an unpublicized arrival in his private jet. But by Wednesday, dignitaries like President Jacques Chirac of France, Queen Sofia of Spain, Prime Minister Mikhail Fradkov of Russia and Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, Democrat of New York, will have caused their own commotion, as will the sports superstars David Beckham and Muhammad Ali. The gathering has attracted about 1,500 members of the news media, outnumbering the 116 I.O.C. members by more than 10 to 1.</p>
        <p>Most of the work of courting votes, however, happens out of plain view, although I.O.C. members brave enough to venture through the lobby are met quickly by representatives from bid cities. In the evening, the mingling moves to the bars and restaurants nearby.</p>
        <p>But the task is more complicated than simply finding favor. The voting goes by rounds; if one city has not received a majority of votes after the first round, the city receiving the lowest number of votes is eliminated. The rounds continue until one city receives a majority. I.O.C. members from a country that has a city competing for the bid cannot vote until after their city is eliminated.</p>
        <p>''I don't get lobbied much,'' said Craig Reedie, an I.O.C. member from Britain. ''It's my goal not to vote.''</p>
        <p>But voters have to think beyond their first choice, which may be knocked out quickly. NYC2012, New York's bid committee, has a delegation of more than 200 people here. The bid officials have worked to make New York the second choice of a lot of voters, even lobbying I.O.C. members they believed were favoring another city.</p>
        <p>Daniel L. Doctoroff, New York's bid founder and the deputy mayor for economic development, says New York can gain steam if it survives into the later rounds. Paris is expected to have the most first-round votes, but it may be less aggressive about picking up votes from members committed to another city.</p>
        <p>''My gut view is that most people know what they're going to do in the first round,'' said Sebastian Coe, a two-time gold medalist in the 1,500 meters who is London's bid leader. ''But it's a bit like I knew how I was going to start most races for the first 30 or 40 yards, but then you weren't always able to factor everything in. Yes, I have a number of scenarios in my mind what could happen, but that will unravel anyway.''</p>
        <p>The run-up to this vote has helped shape its ambiguity. I.O.C. rules now forbid members to visit bid cities as a way to prevent the kind of vote-buying that resulted in the Salt Lake City scandal, in which some I.O.C. members received bribes and special favors for their votes on the 2002 Winter Games. Bid leaders are allowed to approach I.O.C. members only at I.O.C.-sanctioned events, so the lobbying has been contained to organized settings.</p>
        <p>''I think that the rules have resulted in people being both more cautious and waiting until the latest moment,'' Mr. Gosper said.</p>
        <p>None of the cities' bid officials admit to taking anything for granted. Paris officials often say that they do not believe their city is the front-runner. Madrid's bid leader, Feliciano Mayoral, insists his city received the top marks from the evaluation commission, although most interpreted the review for Paris as the best. New York officials are still questioned about the possibility that New York's State Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver, would kill a second stadium plan, forcing them to rebut the idea that their Olympic stadium hangs in perpetual limbo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coe trumpets London's momentum; that is not a hard claim to back up considering that the bid had little public support even within Britain until Mr. Coe took over a year ago and gave it an aggressive posture. The London bid will require a huge urban renewal project, even more ambitious than New York's now that the West Side makeover has been scrapped. They provide a stark contrast to Paris's modest building plans.</p>
        <p>Singapore has added its own particular flair to this process. On Saturday, with I.O.C. members beginning to arrive and bid cities jockeying for access, the country unfurled a fascinating distraction. What appeared to be a significant portion of the Singapore military paraded through the streets, with legions of soldiers, dozens of tanks driven by men in full camouflage, and trucks carrying missiles. The display ended with a flyover and a 21-gun salute.</p>
        <p>The event was one of seven practice sessions for a National Day parade in August. While the rehearsal was taking over Singapore's streets, New York's bid leaders were forced to walk through a maze of underground malls to reach their scheduled news conference. They emerged from the crowded string of stores joking about the prospect of Manhattan needing to stage seven practice runs for all of its parades.</p>
        <p>NYC2012, however, has repeatedly rehearsed for its big moment Wednesday, when it makes a 45-minute presentation before the I.O.C. membership. The presentation is being choreographed down to the minute, although it is not being directed by the filmmaker Steven Spielberg, contrary to a rumor reported in a local newspaper. That rumor captivated even the French filmmaker Luc Besson, who is directing Paris's effort. Mr. Besson declared Spielberg his hero. ''To lose in front of him will be an honor,'' he said. ''To win in front of him will be a super honor.''</p>
        <p>There will be no Mr. Spielberg, but plenty of others will swoop through the hotels, where the entertainment on parade needs no Hollywood stagecraft.</p>
        <p>A prime minister's entrance here or there will do.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
