<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fears of 47 New Red Lights</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="769516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BRONX UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PORNOGRAPHY AND OBSCENITY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH BRONX (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LII, JANE H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DB1338F93BA25755C0A963958260" item-length="479" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fears of 47 New Red Lights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE H. LII</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LII, JANE H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Growing up on the gritty streets of the South Bronx, Juana Pena, 21, has seen her share of devastation and despair. But in recent years, she has seen the neighborhood change for the better.</p>
        <p>Construction of houses and renovation of vacant buildings have brought in families, new businesses and jobs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Growing up on the gritty streets of the South Bronx, Juana Pena, 21, has seen her share of devastation and despair. But in recent years, she has seen the neighborhood change for the better.</p>
        <p>Construction of houses and renovation of vacant buildings have brought in families, new businesses and jobs.</p>
        <p>Now, as the city considers new zoning laws for adult entertainment businesses to largely industrial districts, Ms. Pena fears that residential communities like hers that are mixed in with or close to industrial areas will become seedy.</p>
        <p>"It's now safe to sit outside and hang out," said Ms. Pena, who lives in the Mill Brook Houses on East 137th Street and St. Ann's Avenue, across the Major Deegan Expressway from a district of rail yards and industrial buildings. "Why does the city want to bring us back down?"</p>
        <p>In an effort to reduce the city's 177 adult entertainment establishments, the Department of City Planning and the City Council have proposed new regulations that would limit their sizes and prohibit them within 500 feet of houses of worship, hospitals, schools or day-care centers.</p>
        <p>But while city officials hope the proposal will effectively drive adult businesses out of most neighborhoods in the city, or out of the city altogether, the business owners could opt to relocate to the sorts of industrial areas common in Bronx neighborhoods like Hunts Point, Port Morris, Mott Haven and Unionport.</p>
        <p>Based on the proposal's specifications, Roberto Crespo, the district manager of Community Board 1 in the South Bronx, estimated that as many as 47 adult businesses could move to the community. There is currently one adult entertainment business, a topless bar at Cypress Place and Bruckner Boulevard, within the board's boundaries, Mr. Crespo said.</p>
        <p>"Our area has enough problems," Mr. Crespo said. "We have a high number of H.I.V. and TB cases. We have a medical incinerator that's making people sick. Give us schools, give us libraries."</p>
        <p>During a raucous meeting held by Community Board 1 on Thursday night, angry residents shouted down representatives of the Department of City Planning as they tried to explain the proposal.</p>
        <p>"Garbage! Garbage!" cried Bernice Kornegay, a mother of four children who bought a home in the area two years ago.</p>
        <p>Another resident, Diane Pinkston, a mother of four who lives near the topless bar, told the city representatives that she has been mistaken for a prostitute and harassed by the bar's customers.</p>
        <p>William Bernstein, the first deputy executive director of the Department of Planning, said the city would work with local residents to create options that would not result in red-light districts near their neighborhoods. The current proposal, which still has to be approved by the City Council, could be amended to rezone the industrial areas near residential areas, Mr. Bernstein said. JANE H. LII  NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BRONX UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
