<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Schools Closed, Capital Is in a Bind</title>
    <meta content="03DEEC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="954879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E0DB1430F930A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Schools Closed, Capital Is in a Bind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public schools in Washington, DC, fail to open on schedule for third time in four years because of repairs needed at more than third of 146 buildings; situation is more irritating than usual for parents since fixing school system was one of highest priorities of financial control board created by Congress in 1995 to solve District's problems; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The playgrounds behind Brookland Elementary School were filled with children today. They kicked soccer balls, shot basketballs and dangled from jungle gyms. Few adults watching them could have imagined a more unfortunate scene.</p>
        <p>''This is totally inexcusable,'' said Erle Doweary, a father of two young girls in the District of Columbia public school system, expressing a view heard all across the nation's capital today, which was supposed to have been the first day of school for 78,000 children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The playgrounds behind Brookland Elementary School were filled with children today. They kicked soccer balls, shot basketballs and dangled from jungle gyms. Few adults watching them could have imagined a more unfortunate scene.</p>
        <p>''This is totally inexcusable,'' said Erle Doweary, a father of two young girls in the District of Columbia public school system, expressing a view heard all across the nation's capital today, which was supposed to have been the first day of school for 78,000 children.</p>
        <p>It was not.</p>
        <p>In the latest, and perhaps most visible, demonstration of problems that have turned a financially strapped city into a national embarrassment, public schools did not open on schedule for the third time in four years because of repairs needed at more than a third of the system's 146 buildings.</p>
        <p>What makes the situation more irritating than usual to residents who have grown accustomed to sporadic trash pickup and high crime rates is that fixing the school system was one of the highest priorities of the financial control board created by Congress in 1995 to solve the District's problems and balance the budget.</p>
        <p>Recurring difficulties with the school system have pushed the target date for this year's opening to Sept. 22, the system's latest start ever and a three-week delay that has local officials blaming each other, and parents cursing the lot of them.</p>
        <p>The city's recreation department, meanwhile, has scrambled to find people to supervise more than 10,000 youngsters who have signed up for ad hoc programs that fill the breach, like those at the Turkey Thicket Playground, which uses the equipment of Brookland Elementary. Mayor Marion S. Barry Jr. ordered 64 recreation centers and 10 city swimming pools to stay open. But Mr. Barry is now lobbying to get $400,000 in a tight budget to pay for the staffing the programs require.</p>
        <p>''We're lucky,'' said Estella Carroll, a grandmother of two school-aged children playing in the Brookland playground. ''We knew what we had here. I don't know what people are doing in other areas.''</p>
        <p>The delay, which was ordered by a local judge who feared the repair work might jeopardize children's safety, has turned the lives of many parents upside down. Those without benefit of a nearby recreation center or pool with lifeguards have been forced to make hasty arrangements for child care or take a leave of absence from work. Some parents have combined resources to hire idle teachers on a temporary basis to teach groups of neighborhood children at home.</p>
        <p>''It comes to the point, what's the point in staying here?'' said Cindy Morgan Jaffe, a mother of three young children at Lafayette Elementary School who brought two of them to a downtown protest this morning in front of the offices of the school's board of trustees.</p>
        <p>Hers was not an idle question. The District population has steadily eroded in recent years, to 543,000 from 606,000 in 1990, as thousands of families have sought the stability of suburban life in Maryland and Virginia. Ms. Jaffe said she knew of a dozen Lafayette families now contemplating a move from the District and others who have spent $6,000 or more to enroll a child in a Maryland public school.</p>
        <p>In years past, fire-code violations kept the District school doors closed, by order of Judge Kaye K. Christian of the District of Columbia Superior Court. This year, she ruled that schools would not begin until roofs on 54 buildings were repaired or replaced.</p>
        <p>But Judge Christian is rarely faulted by angry parents for the current delay. More often, the target of their anger is Gen. Julius W. Becton Jr., head of a board of trustees that was appointed last year by the city's financial control board to run the school system. The trustees were given all the powers once held by an elected school board.</p>
        <p>It appeared things would be different. The trustees' first pledge was an assurance that schools would open on time. But efforts to assess physical problems, secure the financing of $36 million and line up contractors took longer than General Becton had expected. Beyond that, work on the roofs began late, well after the 1996-1997 school year ended.</p>
        <p>By last month, it was clear that the opening of the fall term might be delayed, and Judge Christian confirmed it by refusing the city's request to allow children into schools while construction was under way.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barry and several parents' groups suggested that the trustees at least open those schools that did not require roof work and find alternative sites, like churches, for children attending schools under construction.</p>
        <p>But those efforts were rebuffed by General Becton who did not favor a staggered start for a school year in which new academic standards are being put into place.</p>
        <p>''We considered that option,'' Loretta Hardge, a spokeswoman for General Becton, said of scheduling different starting times. ''But this is a huge undertaking at the same time we're launching a new academic thrust. How could we do that, have some people start and some not start? We did not think that made a whole lot of sense.''</p>
        <p>Many parents said they were less disturbed about the refusal to open some schools than about the circumstances that allowed the school buildings to crumble in the first place. Many roofs now getting replaced have been plugged and patched many times over in recent years.</p>
        <p>In addition, the fire-code violations that delayed the opening of schools twice before were only addressed after a parents' group sued the school system in 1992.</p>
        <p>The impact of so many physical problems to the schools, as well as poor academic performances by many children, led the control board last year to dismiss the superintendent of schools, Franklin Smith, and strip the elected school board of any meaningful power.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Barry, who has lost virtually all of his powers to the control board, the delay offers him a political victory of sorts. While the District school system was never under the mayor's authority, he often complained that it should be. Now, he is using the fact that it is not as a way to criticize the trustees, as he did today, speaking at the Turkey Thicket Playground to publicize his extended recreation program.</p>
        <p>''Any upsetness should be directed to General Becton,'' he said in his message to parents. ''Maybe all the repairs will not get done by the 22d. I wonder what the General's going to do then?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
