<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shiite Leaders Reporting Progress in Talks on Najaf, But the Fiery Cleric Balks</title>
    <meta content="Y13IRA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/13/international/middleeast/13IRAQ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1581335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: PEACE EFFORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Najaf (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Karbala (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Filkins, Dexter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sadr, Moktada Al-</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Sadr, Moktada Al-</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4D7113CF930A25756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shiite Leaders Reporting Progress in Talks on Najaf, But the Fiery Cleric Balks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shiite Leaders Report Progress in Talks on Najaf, but Cleric Balks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG and DEXTER FILKINS; Edward Wong reported from Karbala, Iraq, for this article and Dexter Filkins from Baghdad.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Filkins, Dexter; Wong, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>KARBALA, Iraq, Thursday, May 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shiite leaders report progress toward agreement that would end five-week-old standoff with radical cleric Moktada al-Sadr in holy city of Najaf, but Sadr himself vows to fight on and gun battles continue between American forces and his followers; in Karbala, Sadr's militia keeps up attacks against American forces after Americans occupy their stronghold in fierce battle; Sadr urges his fighters in Karbala to resist American troops and expresses his own willingness to die; he has said he would dismantle his army if senior clerics in Najaf asked him to; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shiite leaders reported progress Wednesday toward an agreement that would end a five-week-old standoff with the radical cleric Moktada al-Sadr in the holy city of Najaf, but Mr. Sadr himself vowed to fight on and gun battles continued between American forces and his followers.</p>
        <p>In Karbala, Mr. Sadr's militia, known as the Mahdi Army, kept up attacks against American forces Thursday morning after the Americans occupied their stronghold in a fierce battle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The radical cleric Moktada al-Sadr vowed to fight on and gun battles continued between American forces and his followers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shiite leaders reported progress Wednesday toward an agreement that would end a five-week-old standoff with the radical cleric Moktada al-Sadr in the holy city of Najaf, but Mr. Sadr himself vowed to fight on and gun battles continued between American forces and his followers.</p>
        <p>In Karbala, Mr. Sadr's militia, known as the Mahdi Army, kept up attacks against American forces Thursday morning after the Americans occupied their stronghold in a fierce battle.</p>
        <p>A religious leader offered to negotiate a truce between the two sides in Karbala, but was rebuffed Wednesday afternoon by the local leader of the Mahdi Army, American military officials said.</p>
        <p>In Najaf, several Shiite leaders said Wednesday they were close to reaching an agreement that would include the disbanding of Mr. Sadr's militia. Mr. Sadr, while making no mention of an agreement, said at a news conference that he would disband his army if senior clerics in Najaf asked him to. But he also urged his fighters in Karbala to resist American troops and expressed his own willingness to die.</p>
        <p>The negotiations were part of the intense maneuvering taking place as American forces, which have been ringing Najaf and Karbala for weeks, have in recent days struck decisively at Mr. Sadr's militia.</p>
        <p>In Karbala, American soldiers killed at least 22 insurgents in an 11-hour battle around a mosque that began late Tuesday night. Soldiers killed at least three more in fighting in the same neighborhood on Wednesday, said Col. Peter Mansoor, the commander of the First Brigade of the First Armored Division, who is charged with crushing the insurgency by Mr. Sadr's militia. At least seven Americans were wounded.</p>
        <p>The fighting at the Mukhaiyam Mosque and the warrens of the surrounding neighborhood brought hundreds of American soldiers within a quarter mile of two of the most sacred places in Shiite Islam, the golden-domed shrines of Hussein and Abbas. Though the Americans say they are determined to destroy Mr. Sadr's forces, they have been cautious about bringing the war to the holy areas here and in Najaf. Invading the city centers of either place, they fear, could stir the wrath of Shiite Muslims around the world, even those who dislike Mr. Sadr.</p>
        <p>Tuesday night, the Americans made a high-risk gamble by trying to breach the Mukhaiyam Mosque, situated just west of the Shrine of Hussein. The attack was one of the largest operations carried out in the past year by the First Armored Division, which until now was responsible for controlling Baghdad. Fighting raged on all sides of the mosque, with soldiers scrambling through rubble-strewn streets and ducking sniper shots and rocket-propelled grenades.</p>
        <p>The Americans relied heavily on the devastating cannons and machine guns of their M-1 Abrams tanks and Bradley fighting vehicles, which pounded surrounding buildings, setting many on fire.</p>
        <p>Colonel Mansoor said that he believed the attack on the mosque had broken the back of the insurgents and that their activities would drop off sharply. But he also observed that the insurgents were ''tenacious.''</p>
        <p>''They kept sniping at us today,'' he said. ''I expect them to come back at us, but perhaps not in the same numbers.''</p>
        <p>After the main assault force left, the military left a company of tanks in the shattered neighborhood. More than 100 Iraqi policemen were also posted around the mosque, said Colonel Mansoor.</p>
        <p>Though fighting did not reach the shrines of Hussein or Abbas, American soldiers were forced to fight insurgents holed up in the Mukhaiyam shrine, a domed building next to a high school and near the Mukhaiyam Mosque. Militiamen had regrouped at the shrine in the middle of the fighting and had begun launching mortars from there at the American-occupied mosque. Special Forces soldiers led teams of Iraqi commandos to the area and drove the insurgents from the shrine during an intense firefight.</p>
        <p>The two dozen or so Iraqi commandos who helped the Americans in the battle were part of the Iraqi Counter Terrorist Force, trained in Jordan to combat insurgents. They acted under the supervision of Special Forces, who instructed them on clearing munitions from the Mukhaiyam Mosque and shrine and from the high school. Special Forces soldiers guided much of the battle on the ground, storming the mosque and setting up a base there to direct troops.</p>
        <p>The Special Forces soldiers appeared impressed by the weapons caches found in the area. Those included powerful 155-millimeter artillery shells, Italian land mines and sniper rifles. In all, the munitions were the equivalent of more than 100 roadside bombs, one of the most effective killers of American soldiers in Iraq, a military intelligence analyst said. Sappers wired the caches with plastic explosives and detonated them as most of the American troops left the area.</p>
        <p>A huge cache in a storage shed at the rear of the mosque compound had been detonated at the start of the battle, resulting in thunderous explosions that continued for more than two hours.</p>
        <p>Posters of chubby, black-turbaned Mr. Sadr decorated walls and pillars in various rooms of the mosque. One poster displayed a message from Mr. Sadr calling on his followers to rally against the Americans. A large room had dozens of small wooden couches with soft cushions and was presumably the place where militiamen slept. A metal plate of rice with a half-finished chunk of lamb remained on one couch.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday afternoon, a religious leader representing Hussein al-Sadr, a respected uncle of the young Mr. Sadr, came to the American base here to offer to negotiate a truce with Hamza al-Tai, the leader of the Mahdi Army in Karbala, Colonel Mansoor said. The tribal leader, who is from Karbala and is also from the Tai tribe, later spoke with Mr. Tai, who said he would not relent in his fight against the Americans, the colonel said.</p>
        <p>In Najaf, meanwhile, Shiite leaders said negotiations were under way on a deal that would include the withdrawal of American forces and the disbanding of Mr. Sadr's militia. But other Shiites described the negotiations as extremely tentative.</p>
        <p>Shiite leaders in Baghdad and Najaf said the proposed agreement had received the ''blessing'' of Muhammad Ridha al-Sistani, the son and representative of Grand Ayatollah Ali al-Sistani, the country's most powerful Shiite leader.</p>
        <p>''If the agreement is achieved, then we will have completely demilitarized the holy city,'' Hachim Alkam Al-Shibli, the local leader of the National Iraqi Tribal Coalition, said in Najaf.</p>
        <p>Shiite leaders said any deal would probably include delaying criminal proceedings against Mr. Sadr, who is wanted by Iraqi authorities for his suspected role in murdering a rival cleric last year.</p>
        <p>Despite these reports of progress, Mr. Sadr made no mention of the negotiations in a public appearance on Wednesday, but he sent ambiguous signals about his willingness to give up without a fight.</p>
        <p>''We are ready for any escalation, and we expect nothing less from the occupiers,'' Mr. Sadr said. ''If the U.S. chooses to escalate, we will do so; if they want to ease the tension, we will, too.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sadr urged his fighters in Karbala to fight on and indicated that he was willing to go down fighting.</p>
        <p>''My desire is to die a martyr in this country,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It was unclear whether Mr. Sadr, as some Shiite leaders suggested, was merely talking tough to cover an inevitable retreat. Though he made no mention of an agreement, Shiite leaders said one of his key aides had put his signature to it.</p>
        <p>As he has often done in recent weeks, Mr. Sadr offered some words that suggested he was considering a peaceful deal. He appealed to mainline Shiite clerics, the followers of Ayatollah Sistani, for help. He suggested that he would disband his militia, estimated to number several hundred fighters, if the senior council of clerics in Najaf publicly asked him to do so.</p>
        <p>But he has made that offer before, and the Shiite clerics, who are said to loathe Mr. Sadr, have never responded. His uprising has left many Shiite leaders disgruntled, saying they believe that he is endangering the chances of the country's majority Shiite community to win power in democratic elections.</p>
        <p>One problem yet to be resolved was the disbanding of Mr. Sadr's militia, which American officials say numbers in the hundreds in the two cities. Taking guns away from young men in a country where nearly every household contains at least one AK-47 assault rifle is no simple matter.</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: PEACE EFFORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
