<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chinese Parents Not Tricked, Judge Says in Custody Case</title>
    <meta content="13CUST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/13/national/13custody.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1581318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Memphis (Tenn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hart, Ariel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">He, Shaoqiang</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">He, Qin Luo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Childers, Robert (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee/Memphis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Custody and Support</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1D8113CF930A25756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chinese Parents Not Tricked, Judge Says in Custody Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chinese Parents Not Tricked, Judge Says in Custody Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ARIEL HART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hart, Ariel</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, May 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Circuit Court Judge Robert Childers of Memphis, Tenn, terminates parental rights of Chinese couple who say they were tricked into giving up their daughter, now 5, to foster parents when she was baby; says couple, Shaoqiang He and Qin Luo He, were 'negligent and inattentive' to child and that their home is 'unhealthy and unsafe'; says they sought custody only so they would not be deported; couple has spent four years trying to get their daughter back; they say they signed papers to give her up temporarily at her birth because they were overwhelmed and without medical insurance; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A judge in Memphis has terminated the parental rights of a Chinese couple who say they were tricked into giving up their daughter, now 5, to foster parents when she was a baby.</p>
        <p>Judge Robert Childers of Circuit Court said that the couple, Shaoqiang and Qin Luo He, had ''failed to establish a meaningful relationship'' with the girl, Anna Mae, because of ''neglect and inattentiveness'' and that the ''physical environment of the Hes' home is unhealthy and unsafe.'' Judge Childers said they sought custody only so that they would not be deported.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A judge in Memphis has terminated the parental rights of a couple who say they were tricked into giving up their daughter, now 5, to foster parents when she was a baby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A judge in Memphis has terminated the parental rights of a Chinese couple who say they were tricked into giving up their daughter, now 5, to foster parents when she was a baby.</p>
        <p>Judge Robert Childers of Circuit Court said that the couple, Shaoqiang and Qin Luo He, had ''failed to establish a meaningful relationship'' with the girl, Anna Mae, because of ''neglect and inattentiveness'' and that the ''physical environment of the Hes' home is unhealthy and unsafe.'' Judge Childers said they sought custody only so that they would not be deported.</p>
        <p>''We are just shocked,'' Mr. He said. ''We did not abandon our child.''</p>
        <p>They will appeal, he said, adding, ''We are convinced that in Memphis, Tenn., justice does not come easy, especially for minorities and immigrants.''</p>
        <p>The Hes have spent four years trying to get their daughter back, saying the foster parents, Jerry and Louise Baker, enjoyed wealth, connections and community support that stacked the deck against them.</p>
        <p>The Bakers, who have sold their house to pay legal bills, said they feared that Anna Mae would be taken from the only home that she has known and sent to live in what they view as a life of poverty with unstable parents in a dirty house.</p>
        <p>The proceedings became a cause célèbre in the Chinese community in Memphis. Representatives of the Chinese Embassy from Washington attended court.</p>
        <p>The battle has it roots months before Anna Mae was born, with an unrelated case in 1998. A fellow student at the University of Memphis, where Mr. He was studying for a graduate degree in economics, accused him of sexual assault. He was cleared of the charge, but lost his place at the university, his scholarship and his stipend, the couple's sole means of support. His student visa was revoked, and the old Immigration and Naturalization Service began deportation proceedings, which have halted for the custody case.</p>
        <p>Overwhelmed and without medical insurance, the Hes turned to Mid-South Christian Services when Anna Mae was born in January 1999. Through Mid-South, the Hes found the Bakers, experienced foster parents who agreed to take in Anna Mae while the Hes got back on their feet.</p>
        <p>Three months later, the Hes signed papers to extend the arrangement to temporary custody. They say they did not know that those signatures put in play the child's permanent custody. They could get her back only with the consent of a judge. The judge said that was not accurate.</p>
        <p>The Bakers have said there was also a verbal agreement that they would raise her to adulthood.</p>
        <p>The Hes say they were not advised to hire their own lawyer. When they signed over guardianship in court, witnesses testified, the arrangement was described as temporary and no one detailed its pitfalls for the Hes.</p>
        <p>The Hes, who found work at Chinese restaurants, visited Anna Mae about 80 times in the next two years and began to ask for the child's return. On her 2nd birthday, the Bakers would not let the Hes take her out for a family portrait, hostility peaked, and the Bakers called the police.</p>
        <p>The Hes say the police ordered them to stay away from the house. They did. The Bakers said their absence over the next four months constituted legal abandonment and grounds for terminating the Hes' parental rights, a provision of Tennessee law that the Hes say they did not know.</p>
        <p>In addition to the abandonment question, much of the argument in the case seems to double as a culture clash. The Hes have said that where Americans see big families in close quarters as a sign of low living standards, the Chinese culture values close association with extended families.</p>
        <p>Ms. Baker has testified that she was afraid that the Hes would summarily ''ship'' Anna Mae out of the country. In China it is not uncommon for children to be partly raised by relatives, both for the parents' convenience and for the family's bonding, Twila Tardif, a developmental psychologist at the University of Michigan and faculty associate with the Center for Chinese Studies, said. ''Typically, it goes until nursery school, maybe age 3, or elementary school, would be the most common,'' but can last longer, she said.</p>
        <p>The Bakers' lawyer, Larry Parrish, said that they were motivated just by concern for the girl and that he was glad that the judge had taken into account the couples' character.</p>
        <p>The decision calls Ms. He impetuous and calculating. Citing Mr. He's answers on loan and visa applications, it says his conduct is ''marked by deceitfulness and dishonesty.''</p>
        <p>''I think it would have been cruel and unusual punishment for this child to be taken out of her present circumstances,'' Mr. Parrish said. ''I couldn't conceive of a child being so innocent and so punished.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
