<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Carlson and Thomas Cook to Merge Leisure Travel in Britain</title>
    <meta content="Y06TRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1051940"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carlson Cos</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cook, Thomas (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdowell, Edwin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E1DB1F38F935A35753C1A96E958260" item-length="477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Carlson and Thomas Cook to Merge Leisure Travel in Britain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWIN McDOWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcdowell, Edwin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carlson Companies, owner and franchiser of worldwide network of hotels, restaurants and cruise ships, plans to merge its leisure travel business in Britain with worldwide travel operations of Thomas Cook, one of oldest and best known names in travel; intended transaction is valued at more than $1 billion; it would make two companies major force in leisure travel with annual sales of about $42.5 billion; merger partners will likely retain Thomas Cook name and that of Worldchoice, brand name of Carlson's 412 company-owned travel agencies in Britain (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Carlson Companies, the Minneapolis-based owner and franchiser of a worldwide network of hotels, restaurants and cruise ships, plans to merge its leisure travel business in Britain with the worldwide travel operations of Thomas Cook, one of the oldest and best known names in travel. The intended transaction, to be formally announced today, is valued at more than $1 billion.</p>
        <p>It would make the two companies, which together also own 800 travel agencies in Britain and three charter airlines, a major force in leisure travel with annual sales of about $42.5 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Carlson Companies, the Minneapolis-based owner and franchiser of a worldwide network of hotels, restaurants and cruise ships, plans to merge its leisure travel business in Britain with the worldwide travel operations of Thomas Cook, one of the oldest and best known names in travel. The intended transaction, to be formally announced today, is valued at more than $1 billion.</p>
        <p>It would make the two companies, which together also own 800 travel agencies in Britain and three charter airlines, a major force in leisure travel with annual sales of about $42.5 billion.</p>
        <p>The newly created company would include the financial services business of Thomas Cook, the world's biggest issuer of traveler's checks outside the United States and owner of the biggest network of retail foreign exchange bureaus, including 100 at major airports. The merger partners would likely retain both the Thomas Cook name and that of Worldchoice, the brand name of Carlson's 412 company-owned travel agencies in Britain.</p>
        <p>Since 1992, Thomas Cook -- founded in 1841 by the English travel agent who originated the guided tour -- has been owned by Westdeutsche Landesbank, Germany's third-biggest bank.</p>
        <p>Carlson Companies earlier combined with Wagonlit, the French travel company owned by Accor, to forge Carlson Wagonlit Travel, a business travel empire. Neither that arrangement nor Carlson's travel operations in the United States will be affected by the Carlson-Thomas Cook deal, the partners said.</p>
        <p>Because Carlson and WestLB, as Cook's owner is known, are privately owned, financial terms of the agreement were not disclosed, beyond the value of the proposed merger and  that WestLB will own a majority stake.</p>
        <p>''The intent is to merge in order to create a huge leisure travel group in the United Kingdom and also to own a part of their financial services,'' said Douglas Cody, the Carlson communications director who is in London preparing for the formal announcement this morning. But he stressed that the intended merger still faced approval by the British regulatory authorities, adding that both companies hoped that would come before the year-end holidays.</p>
        <p>The proposed merger was discussed for several months, and the Carlson end of the deal was put together by Marilyn Carlson Nelson, who became chief executive last March at the retirement of her father and company founder, Curtis L. Carlson.</p>
        <p>''We view this as yet another step in our company's global strategy to seek meaningful, mutually beneficial partnerships with strong brands,'' Mrs. Nelson said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
