<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Players Are Back, but Are Card Collectors?</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="754802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRADING CARDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIKES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANDOMIR, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6D81138F930A25757C0A963958260" item-length="1067" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Players Are Back, but Are Card Collectors?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SANDOMIR, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the start of the major league baseball season less than two weeks away, trading-card makers are looking to rebound from the 234-day baseball strike that has shrunk their business by as much as 75 percent.</p>
        <p>Photographers for the six card companies are in spring training camps taking pictures of players who have switched teams through free agency or trades since the strike ended. Sales forces have fanned out nationally to drum up delayed orders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the start of the major league baseball season less than two weeks away, trading-card makers are looking to rebound from the 234-day baseball strike that has shrunk their business by as much as 75 percent.</p>
        <p>Photographers for the six card companies are in spring training camps taking pictures of players who have switched teams through free agency or trades since the strike ended. Sales forces have fanned out nationally to drum up delayed orders.</p>
        <p>Normally, this would be the hottest part of the baseball card-buying season. Opening day usually sends collectors searching for the cards of the next Frank Thomas or Ken Griffey Jr. The period around opening day "is hotter than when the new card sets come out in December and January," said Doug Kale, editor of Sports Card Trader, "because that's when the statistics start."</p>
        <p>But these are slow times in the baseball tier of the trading-card arena. From a peak of $1.3 billion in 1991, baseball card sales fell to $946 million in 1993, according to a survey by Action Packed Cards, and have certainly fallen much more since. "It's very depressed," Kale said.</p>
        <p>With opening day II arriving on April 25, the six card makers do not know how quickly they can recover their business.</p>
        <p>"We're all elated that the major leaguers are back, but we don't know what consumer demand is going to be," said Ray Abrahamsen, the vice president of marketing for Fleer, a division of Marvel Entertainment.</p>
        <p>Marty Appel, a spokesman for Topps, said, "Reports from the field are that some dealers are increasing their orders a lot and some are not."</p>
        <p>The market uncertainty for 1995 may mean a slimmed-down industry for a few years, said Jill Krutick, an analyst for Salomon Brothers.</p>
        <p>"Our expectation is the industry won't snap back to its pre-strike highs for a few years," she said. "There's a lot of ill will, and kids have found other things to do, like video games and Pogs."</p>
        <p>The strike clarified even more the loss of enthusiasm for baseball among fans and collectors. Once, baseball cards almost always served as youngsters' entree into collecting, but basketball has made serious inroads.</p>
        <p>"Basketball has jumped dramatically, so that if you had 100 collectors, 75 percent would still go for baseball, but 60 to 75 percent would also collect basketball," Kale said. "That's up at least 15 percent from last year."</p>
        <p>Collectors have also been turned off in recent years by the companies' past practices of overproduction and increasing the numbers of sets.</p>
        <p>Even before the strike, baseball was waning in popularity among collectors. According to Action Packed, the number of baseball card collectors, defined as those who buy at least 100 cards a year, had declined from 15.7 million in 1991 to 11.1 million in 1993. The number of basketball collectors climbed from 4.2 million to 4.4 million in that period.</p>
        <p>Arthur Gottwein, owner of Collector's Stadium, a card and memorabilia store in Greenwich Village, said: "We're more conservative than ever. In December, 1990, when the new Topps set came out, I'd immediately buy five or six cases because I knew I could sell it. This December, I bought 10 boxes, and I barely sold it by March. That's 120 boxes down to 10."</p>
        <p>Despite his reduced purchases recently, Gottwein said the companies still raised prices on some of their products.</p>
        <p>"Topps went from 12 cards in a pack for 79 cents to 15 cards for $1.29," he said. "They must have figured they lost so many of their customers, that they'll stick it to the people who feel they must absolutely buy cards."</p>
        <p>Appel of Topps said the price increase was to account for including more cards, of higher quality, with gold embossing.</p>
        <p>Like all the card companies, Topps does not know how much it will increase production once the season unfolds. The strike sent production plummeting to its lowest levels in 30 years, a time before the introduction of competition in the market in 1981. For the three months ended Feb. 25, Topps's net income tumbled 77 percent, to $1.02 million. For the past year, net income fell 68 percent.</p>
        <p>The soured business caused 200 layoffs at its printing plant in Pennsylvania. "We learned a lesson, but we came out well under difficult circumstances," Appel said. "We didn't lose money."</p>
        <p>At Upper Deck, production of its Collector's Choice, which came out last December, was down 75 percent from the previous year. Series I of the Upper Deck brand came out on schedule -- with many players in uniforms they have swapped for new ones -- but at only one-third of the 1994 production level.</p>
        <p>Rich Bradley, an Upper Deck spokesman, said the company suffered no layoffs, and did not lose money, because its workers in Carlsbad, Calif., and Europe, were occupied with increased football and basketball card business. Hockey card production perked up when its lockout ended.</p>
        <p>All six companies licensed by Major League Baseball and the players union are awaiting retail orders before they know how much lingering damage the strike and the shortened 1995 season will continue to wreak on their sales. All six have had some of their series of 1995 cards on the market since late last year.</p>
        <p>They hope that forgiving fans will head back into the card-buying market, but they said they have had mixed reports about retailers' enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>"We think the recovery will be more like a bell curve, not a rocket ship," said Brad Bartlett, vice president of marketing for Pinnacle, which makes the Score and Pinnacle brands. Production of series I of its brands was half their 1994 levels. Series II, usually out last month, has been delayed from 30 to 90 days until new photographs can position all players on the correct teams and it can gain a stronger fix on orders. "There's no quick fix for this," Bartlett said. "Baseball has alienated too many people for that."</p>
        <p>Abrahamsen said Fleer's baseball card printing ended in February, as the company warily assessed the market. "It's not a question of wanting to flood the market quickly now; we don't want to flood it slowly," he said.</p>
        <p>Marvel did not suffer great baseball-related losses. The company, which makes comic books, entertainment cards, stickers and other products, reported that its 1994 net income rose 12 percent, to $61.8 million.</p>
        <p>But Krutick said that Fleer's 1995 revenues will be down about 70 percent, to $30 million this year. "This year is mostly a wash," he said.  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
