<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Healy's Stops Could Make Him a Playoff Starter</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="759351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ON HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDE1E38F932A35756C0A963958260" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Healy's Stops Could Make Him a Playoff Starter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Lapointe</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Rangers and Flyers regrouped for a face-off, John LeClair remained behind, shouting at Ranger goalie Glenn Healy.</p>
        <p>"He was antagonizing me," LeClair said after yesterday's game in the Spectrum. "He was getting under my skin."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Rangers and Flyers regrouped for a face-off, John LeClair remained behind, shouting at Ranger goalie Glenn Healy.</p>
        <p>"He was antagonizing me," LeClair said after yesterday's game in the Spectrum. "He was getting under my skin."</p>
        <p>What prompted Healy's comments?</p>
        <p>"He took his stick and smacked it on the ice," Healy said. "I let him know the game was on Fox and I didn't want kids to see that."</p>
        <p>This was classic Healy, using more than his stick, pads and glove to shut out the Flyers, 2-0, as the Rangers clinched a berth in the Stanley Cup playoffs.</p>
        <p>Earlier, as the Flyers apparently scored the tying goal on the power play, the whistle blew just before the puck crossed the line. It seemed as if the net had moved, thanks to Healy's shoulder.</p>
        <p>"When I leaned up against the post, the net gave way," Healy said, adding that the cage had come slightly ajar moments before, when he swung his stick in a poke-check attempt.</p>
        <p>His shove, no doubt accidental, served to illustrate the net's loose condition to the referee and to prevent a goal. Strangely enough, a similar dislodging of Healy's net also occurred in the first period. Just coincidence, no doubt.</p>
        <p>All this was part of a day's work that included 24 Philadelphia shots. One, by Anatoly Semenov, cracked off the side of Healy's caged and helmeted head and left him momentarily stunned.</p>
        <p>"Glanced off my ear," he said. "I was checking to see if it was still on. A little van Gogh."</p>
        <p>Always quick with wit, Healy remained serious when reporters began to flip the serious, obvious questions at him like so many wrist shots, slappers and backhands. In that Healy was chosen over Mike Richter to start a key game, is he the first-string goalie when the Rangers begin the playoffs on Saturday night or Sunday afternoon?</p>
        <p>"I'm not going to look that far along," said Healy. "That's pre-emptive. I'm just looking forward to a nice ride home and a chance to get a break. Playoffs is a fabulous time of year. Everyone gets a chance to go to the dance."</p>
        <p>Yesterday's victory was an upbeat ending to a season of vindication for Healy. It raised his record to 8-5-1 and the team's to .500. A year ago, as the backup to Richter under Coach Mike Keenan, Healy said he felt humiliated by long weeks of inactivity and a lack of communication with the coach.</p>
        <p>"Last year, I was consumed by it," Healy said. "I let it affect me."</p>
        <p>Healy said that now, under Coach Colin Campbell, he felt "respect, something that wasn't there last year," and he added, "I'm appreciative."</p>
        <p>A year ago, it was Richter leading the Rangers to their first Stanley Cup championship in 54 years. But the year before that, when he was still with the Islanders, Healy was the puck-stopping star of a mediocre team that reached the third round.</p>
        <p>Campbell, who tends to lean toward his veterans, was asked who would be his starting goalie if Tuesday marked the beginning of the playoffs, instead of the end of the regular season.</p>
        <p>"I've got to go," he said, ending his news conference with a smile.</p>
        <p>Healy has finished four of the last six games and has a 3-1 record in them. When the Rangers let go of John Vanbiesbrouck two years ago, it seemed as if the goalie controversy was over and that Richter had been declared the winner.</p>
        <p>Now, things aren't so certain.</p>
        <p>"Colin has had some tough decisions," Healy said.</p>
        <p>Another might be the question of Aleksei Kovalev, who has replaced Petr Nedved as the coach's primary whipping boy.</p>
        <p>After a turnover early in the third period, Kovalev spent the rest of the game on the bench. His slump has worsened and his confidence is rattled. Not only is Kovalev a young player working for a coach who prefers veterans, he is also a European working for a coach who seems to prefer North Americans, especially those from Canada.</p>
        <p>Perhaps that is part of the reason the Rangers have defenseman Jay Wells in uniform instead of Mattias Norstrom, a Swede, and why they use Healy instead of the American-born Richter. It might also be one of the reasons the visiting Igor Demitriev, formerly the assistant coach of the Soviet national team, was in the dressing room after the game. He was informally chatting with Russian Rangers.</p>
        <p>With the overworked Mark Messier suffering from a sore back, the rookie coach needs to get Kovalev on track as he prepares to coach in his first tournament. Perhaps it is time for both Kovalev and Campbell to accept counsel from someone whose hockey worldview extends beyond the borders of Ontario.</p>
        <p>Any way you mix them, Messier's health, Kovalev's confidence and the goalie issue are primary ingredients for an intriguing and simmering post-season stew. Chef Campbell must stir carefully, lest the pot boil over and burn him.  ON HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
