<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Incredible Shrinking Sound of Home Theater</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="827456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDING EQUIPMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, LAWRENCE B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD81739F937A35751C0A960958260" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Incredible Shrinking Sound of Home Theater</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence B. Johnson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, LAWRENCE B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHETHER YOU CALL IT home theater or home cinema, the idea is the same: to bring to the living room the sensory impact, visual and aural, that you experience at the movies. The key word here is "impact." Mark it well. It is a reference point to keep in mind as the audio industry, exploiting the popularity of home theater, presses its advantage toward an ever wider market with ever smaller (and cheaper) surround-sound loudspeaker systems. In the new vogue for "home theater in a box," one envisions a reductio ad absurdum: the visceral power of cinema sound diminished to the scale of a shoe box.</p>
        <p>There is much to be said for reducing the complexity, and the cost, of home theater systems. For serious hobbyists, who might be seen as the audio buffs of  the multimedia age, a real home theater layout consists of a surround-sound processor and six-channel amplifier complemented by five high-performance loudspeakers, plus a subwoofer or two to make the trousers flap when helicopters swoop across the screen. The parts might come from three or four manufacturers and cost several thousand dollars. But that's more expense, bother and physical  encumbrance than most people will put up with.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHETHER YOU CALL IT home theater or home cinema, the idea is the same: to bring to the living room the sensory impact, visual and aural, that you experience at the movies. The key word here is "impact." Mark it well. It is a reference point to keep in mind as the audio industry, exploiting the popularity of home theater, presses its advantage toward an ever wider market with ever smaller (and cheaper) surround-sound loudspeaker systems. In the new vogue for "home theater in a box," one envisions a reductio ad absurdum: the visceral power of cinema sound diminished to the scale of a shoe box.</p>
        <p>There is much to be said for reducing the complexity, and the cost, of home theater systems. For serious hobbyists, who might be seen as the audio buffs of  the multimedia age, a real home theater layout consists of a surround-sound processor and six-channel amplifier complemented by five high-performance loudspeakers, plus a subwoofer or two to make the trousers flap when helicopters swoop across the screen. The parts might come from three or four manufacturers and cost several thousand dollars. But that's more expense, bother and physical  encumbrance than most people will put up with.</p>
        <p>Fair enough. It is certainly possible to pare down the parts and the cost and, in the process, make the whole thing easier to use. A good-quality receiver, for example, goes a long way toward making home theater manageable without eviscerating performance. Processing, power and system control are all contained in one convenient box. But don't confuse that familiar item with the container in the term "home theater in box."</p>
        <p>That box is a shipping carton; and though the phrase has become a metaphor for a miniaturized system, its basic import is that you can buy and take home everything you need to recreate the cinema experience in one box. To which I might reply: No, you can't.</p>
        <p>Until now, it was at least possible to apply a cardinal rule of thumb, or ear: Anything is better than the sound of a television set. Alas, after</p>
        <p>surveying some of the all-in-one home theater systems on display recently at the Winter Consumer Electronics Show in Las Vegas, Nev., I'm inclined to amend the rule to read: Any hi-fi system is better than the sound of a television set. Some of what was passed off as "home theater" sound was little more than enhanced television audio. What looked like a duck and quacked like a duck turned out to be a rubber ducky.</p>
        <p>The problem is twofold: dynamic range and deep bass. The sound system in a television set can deliver neither. The amplifiers and speaker cones, designed to deliver the evening news without interfering with the adjacent picture tube,  are simply unequal to the hair-curling sound effects of "True Lies" or "Jurassic Park." So are many of the tiny little devices now bundled together as home theater in a box -- almost in a bottle, like a quick remedy.</p>
        <p>None of which is to say that you can't derive a measure of satisfaction from  a prefab surround-sound system. Celestion's package, which goes by the generic name Home Theater in a Box ($1,200), combines four very small matching speakers  with a slightly larger center channel speaker plus a subwoofer that houses a surround-sound processor and full system power. The Celestion system is a snap to set up and operate, and in a modest-size room it can create a far more involving field of sound than any television set.</p>
        <p>In a full-size living room, however, the diminutive Celestion speaker array and its modest amplifier cannot produce the huge tapestries of sound required to make the curtains move, your chest thump or your socks fly off. It's the old story: You get what you pay for. Home theater audio is like any other hi-fi. There is no magic, and there are no miracles. The same physics apply, the same design requirements, the same costs.</p>
        <p>Cost is the dark side of legitimate home theater. The two loudspeakers of traditional hi-fi have mutated into five; six, if you count a subwoofer. All five principal speakers must be able to play accurately and loudly, because the  tendency -- and here is cinema come home -- is to play movie soundtracks louder  than music. As for the subwoofer, it is a hugely misunderstood factor of home theater sound and one sold far short in miniaturized sound systems.</p>
        <p>FOR A SUBWOOFER TO MAKE A really visceral impact, it must move lots of air at very low frequencies. So in a large listening space, it must be an enclosure large enough to house one or two sizable cone drivers and often a power amplifier as well. Well-designed, effective subwoofers don't come cheap. You can expect to pay $600 or more for one that will fill a large room with realistic deep bass: not an indeterminate whomp but articulated sounds with character and  definition.</p>
        <p>Value and convenience never stood in a more delicate balance than in the expanding world of home theater. It is not that you must spend a fortune or lumber your living space with bulky speakers to put together a satisfying system. But you do need to be mindful of what you're getting, what a package of  components can deliver and what is beyond the bounds of realistic expectation, or claims. You can't turn a 99-cent burger into a gourmet meal.</p>
        <p>One of the most impressive surround-sound demonstrations heard at the Las Vegas exposition presented a matched set of five bookshelf-size speakers, a new  model from Infinity, called the Compositions Overture I. Each unit, measuring 12 inches high, 12 inches deep and 6 inches wide, included a side-firing eight-inch woofer with its own 150-watt amplifier built in. This very efficient design produced a potent, enveloping sound. The price: $2,500. No processor or multichannel power amp. Just the speakers.</p>
        <p>That's a streamlining of home theater this cinema buff could live with. In a  shoe box, I still expect to find shoes.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
