<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Defining Forms of Ownership</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="827482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="Q.&amp; A."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REAL ESTATE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D71739F937A35751C0A960958260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Defining Forms of Ownership</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q How is owning property by the entirety different from owning it by joint tenancy or by tenancy in common? . . . Marcian E. Ferdinand, the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q How is owning property by the entirety different from owning it by joint tenancy or by tenancy in common? . . . Marcian E. Ferdinand, the Bronx.</p>
        <p>A Robert E. Parella, a senior professor of property law at St. John's University Law School, provided the following explanation:</p>
        <p>In a tenancy in common, each owner has an equal or specified share of the property and each has a right to possession. However, any owner's interest can be sold at any time and any owner can obtain a court order for the sale of the entire property by filing an action for partition. When an owner dies, the decedent's ownership interest in the property passes to his or her heirs.</p>
        <p>In joint tenancies and tenancies by the entirety, on the other hand, each owner has a right of survivorship. If one owner dies, the survivor becomes the sole owner.</p>
        <p>With a joint tenancy, however, either owner can unilaterally destroy the joint tenancy by selling his or her interest or by forcing the sale of the entire property through partition. A joint tenancy may also be destroyed if a creditor of one of the owners forces a sale of that owner's interest to satisfy  a debt. In such a case, the remaining owner and the new owner become tenants in  common.</p>
        <p>The most secure form of ownership is a tenancy by the entirety, which can only be formed by a married couple. Except by mutual agreement, neither spouse can do anything that would result in the other spouse's losing the rights of possession and survivorship. So if a third party ends up with one spouse's interest in the property -- no matter how that might happen -- the third party takes title subject to the other spouse's rights of possession and survivorship.</p>
        <p>Getting Information On Escrow Deposit</p>
        <p>Q On April 27, 1995, I purchased a co-op apartment in Manhattan. As a condition of acceptance, the co-op board required me to pay two-year's maintenance at the closing, an amount in excess of $10,000. This payment was to  be placed in an escrow account. The building's managing agent handled the escrow transaction and has been evasive about where the money has been deposited.</p>
        <p>I have made many attempts both by telephone and in writing asking the managing agent which bank holds the escrow account and what is the account number. I have approached each attorney involved with the purchase to seek help  in gaining cooperation. I have been promised the information numerous times, but nine months have passed and I still have no answers. What laws govern an account of this type?  Where can I turn next? . . . Daniel Lauferswiler, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A David Clurman, a Manhattan lawyer who specializes in real estate, said that the first thing to do is to look through the closing documents to determine whether the deposit is mentioned in any of the documents.</p>
        <p>"The first question that has to be answered is: 'How was this characterized in the documents?' " Mr. Clurman said. It is not clear, he said, whether the money was a prepayment of maintenance charges, a security deposit for the payment of maintenance charges, or an escrow payment that would be returned after a specific time period.</p>
        <p>Nor, he said, is it clear whether the purchaser asked his lawyer about the escrow account.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clurman said the lawyer who handled the closing for the purchaser should  know why and where the money is being held or should find out immediately if he  or she doesn't know. And while it is doubtful that the payment of interest on the deposit would be required under the law, Mr. Clurman said, the person who paid the money certainly has a right to know where it is.</p>
        <p>"He should make an application to appear before the board, make a complaint about the managing agent and ask the board where the money is being held," Mr. Clurman said. In addition, he said, if the lawyer who handled the closing for the purchaser does not provide information regarding the status and location of  the deposit, the state bar association should be notified. And finally, Mr. Clurman said, if all else fails, an action can be filed in Civil Court for the return of the deposit.</p>
        <p>Q.&amp; A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
