<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Students From Two Lands Celebrate Shared Traditions</title>
    <meta content="02VAGA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="999222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vaganova Ballet Academy (St Petersburg)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kirov Ballet</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">School of American Ballet (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E1DC1731F931A35750C0A96E958260" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Students From Two Lands Celebrate Shared Traditions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews joint program presented at Brooklyn Academy of Music by Vaganova Ballet Academy, training ground for Kirov Ballet in Russia, and School of American Ballet, New York City Ballet school; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is not only nothing new under the sun, there is also a past that ballet, more than other art form, consistently reveals, re-examines and renews.</p>
        <p>Such were the lessons of a lively joint program presented at the Brooklyn Academy of Music on Saturday afternoon by the Vaganova Ballet Academy, the training ground for the Kirov Ballet in Russia, and the School of American Ballet, the New York City Ballet school.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is not only nothing new under the sun, there is also a past that ballet, more than other art form, consistently reveals, re-examines and renews.</p>
        <p>Such were the lessons of a lively joint program presented at the Brooklyn Academy of Music on Saturday afternoon by the Vaganova Ballet Academy, the training ground for the Kirov Ballet in Russia, and the School of American Ballet, the New York City Ballet school.</p>
        <p>Tradition as a springboard was the implied theme in this milestone hands-across-the-sea occasion. There was no spirit of competition; good humor and warmth prevailed among the adults and children in the packed house.</p>
        <p>The American students, led by their teacher Suki Schorer, presented an outright lecture-demonstration and showed how George Balanchine, a 1921 graduate of the Vaganova in St. Petersburg, had reworked 19th-century choreography into 20th-century neoclassicism for City Ballet.</p>
        <p>The Russians, in a performance segment, made a similar point without telling anyone.</p>
        <p>Like the Americans, they performed a 20th-century version of an excerpt from ''The Nutcracker.'' In place of a ballerina and a cavalier, as in the 1892 Russian original by Lev Ivanov and the 1954 Balanchine version, there was a ballerina tossed around and partnered by five men in classical style.</p>
        <p>The choreography was by Vasily Vainonen for a landmark Soviet ballet. This 1934 version for the Kirov (the basis of Mikhail Baryshnikov's and Rudolf Nureyev's ''Nutcracker'' in the West) infused new dramatic realism into the scenario, played down the divertissement and attempted to modernize the classical idiom to which it remained faithful.</p>
        <p>That the method is still valid was proclaimed on Saturday by a vision in a pink tutu, the exquisite young Alesia Boyko, partnered by a stalwart, tall cavalier, Artyom Pykhachov, backed up by Dmitri Rudachenko, Mikhail Sivakov, Andrei Shatalin and Denis Morozov.</p>
        <p>In the revelation department, one would pick out an excerpt from ''The Little Humpbacked Horse,'' previously unknown in the United States. Originally choreographed in St. Petersburg in 1864 by Arthur Saint-Leon to music by Cesare Pugni, this fairy tale ballet was re-choreographed in 1895 by Marius Petipa. The excerpt, ''Frescoes,'' refers to four dancers, here in bare midriffs,  romantic tutus and Oriental-style bodices, who are figures that come to life in the frescoes of a palace in central Asia.</p>
        <p>Although Petipa is credited in the program, the ballet was further reworked by others, including Aleksandre Gorsky, and it would be interesting to know how authentic this excerpt is. It does show Petipa's love of diagonals, and the counterpoint between one woman and three others in a pure-dance passage is not contrary to the interplay of design in his choreography. Olga Ziuzina, Irina Kolesnikova, Tatyana Milzeva and Olga Stepanova, seniors in the school, gave the solos and unison work a bold thrust. There were other unfamiliar items. Fyodor Lopukhov's awkward version of the ''Coppelia'' pas de deux was performed with flourish by Yekaterina Osmolkina and Anton Korsakov. Yelena Onegina and Aleksandr Murzho were the teen-agers who knew how to characterize a courtship with nonstop dancing in Leonid Yakobson's choreographic miniature ''Lovers.'' The urban-inflected music was by Timur Kogan.</p>
        <p>The Americans had one advantage, which was the choreography of Balanchine. Ms. Schorer, a whiz at making connections with clarity and technical analysis, described the course his career had taken. With Nancy McDill as the pianist, an exuberant cast (Davena Gross, Megan Pepin, Janie Taylor and Jeremy Cox) danced an excerpt from the Gershwin ballet ''Who Cares?''</p>
        <p>Amanda Knox and Ryan Kelly did fine in the knotty duet from ''Symphony in Three Movements.''</p>
        <p>It was somewhat misleading to compare Balanchine's dynamic ''Nutcracker'' pas de deux, danced vibrantly by Ellen Bar and Jared Angle, with a tepid version, danced reticently by Rebecca Krohn and Jonathan Stafford. Ms. Schorer covered herself by saying this was the original Ivanov choreography ''as it has come down to us.'' Had the casting been reversed, the purported original would have received more projection. Igor Belski, the Vaganova director, disputed the authenticity of this choreography.</p>
        <p>The difference between Petipa and Balanchine was seen more convincingly in two different solos from ''Raymonda'' as danced by Kristin Sloan, Ms. Bar and Nicole Epstein.</p>
        <p>It was left to a luminous performance of the flowing duets in ''Divertimento No. 15'' to demonstrate Balanchine's faith in the classical idiom. Dancing superbly were Ms. Taylor, Mr. Stafford, Tempe Ostegren, Adam Hendrickson, Ms. Krohn, Mr. Angle, Genevieve Labean and Melissa Barak.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
