<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>R.O.T.C. Arrives at Mt. Vernon High School</title>
    <meta content="04ROTC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1051248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reserve Officers Training Corp (Rotc)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mount Vernon (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smalls, F Romall</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7DB1E39F937A35753C1A96E958260" item-length="1462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>R.O.T.C. Arrives at Mt. Vernon High School</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By F. ROMALL SMALLS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smalls, F Romall</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT VERNON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Air Force Junior Reserve Officer Training Corps program, science elective, is introduced at Mount Vernon High School in Mount Vernon, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SERGEANT HYMES, please come to the main office.'' That boomed over the intercom system throughout the sprawling building of Mount Vernon High School just before the start of the new school year.  Along with this simple request came a new science elective course and lofty expectations that the sky will be the only limit to the opportunities  available to the 2,400 students here.</p>
        <p>Last month, an Air Force Junior Reserve Officer Training Corps program was introduced at the high school. Retired Master Sgt. James E. Hymes and the program's superior officer, Retired Lieut. Col. John F. Kirk, are responsible for running and teaching the unit aerospace science.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SERGEANT HYMES, please come to the main office.'' That boomed over the intercom system throughout the sprawling building of Mount Vernon High School just before the start of the new school year.  Along with this simple request came a new science elective course and lofty expectations that the sky will be the only limit to the opportunities  available to the 2,400 students here.</p>
        <p>Last month, an Air Force Junior Reserve Officer Training Corps program was introduced at the high school. Retired Master Sgt. James E. Hymes and the program's superior officer, Retired Lieut. Col. John F. Kirk, are responsible for running and teaching the unit aerospace science.</p>
        <p>The cadet corps is only the second of its kind in Westchester. Roosevelt High School in Yonkers has the other Air Force R.O.T.C. unit and will serve as Mount Vernon's mentor.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview the two officers, both of whom recently retired  after serving a combined 47 years in the Air Force, spoke about their goals for the program.</p>
        <p>Before the beginning of the new academic year, about 60 students expressed interest in the unit. Colonel Kirk said that each newly chartered R.O.T.C. unit is given three years to establish a cadet corps of 100 students. Mount Vernon High School now has 80 students enrolled as cadets, 29 of whom are girls. Both Sergeant Hymes and Colonel Kirk said it was mainly word-of-mouth that brought about the positive response.</p>
        <p>The program offers high school students in any grade an opportunity to earn up to three science elective credits, and it introduces them to industrial and military opportunities in aerospace technology.</p>
        <p>The officers also give credit to Brenda L. Smith, principal of Mount Vernon High School, for bringing in the program.</p>
        <p>''She had the vision of getting this program here from scratch,'' said Colonel Kirk, a former Michigan-based Air Force pilot with 23 years' experience in the military. ''It was her idea and she went through all the leg work, and there is a considerable amount of it. When it came time for them to designate a program, they didn't hesitate to give it to Mount Vernon.''</p>
        <p>Sometime last year the principal  began the quest for the R.O.T.C. program, an idea picked up from fellow principals in Yonkers and the Bronx. ''I applied to all of the branches of the military and was prepared to accept, with the school board's approval, any branch that would afford us a unit,'' Mrs. Smith said. ''And I was told by the Army, Navy and Marines that we would have to be placed on a waiting list. The Air Force also put us on a waiting list.''</p>
        <p>When she was told that Mount Vernon was sixth or so out of 134 schools on the Air Force Junior R.O.T.C. waiting list, Mrs. Smith stepped up her campaign for a cadet corps.</p>
        <p>''We went more aggressively after the Air Force, because of the aerospace-science component, and also we felt that it was the most prestigious of the branches,'' she said.</p>
        <p>To bolster her application, she obtained written endorsements from key political officials, including Congresswoman Nita Lowey and Mayor Ernest D. Davis of Mount Vernon, who had been a member of the Air Force R.O.T.C. when he was in college.</p>
        <p>The basic tenets of the Air Force Junior R.O.T.C. are character, leadership and respect. Sergeant Hymes, who served as an Air Force aerospace mechanic in Idaho, said, ''We are here to build character, including moral character.''</p>
        <p>In a glossy brochure, ''Air Force Junior R.O.T.C. and You,'' there is a curriculum outline, which includes subjects like the heritage of the Air Force and the development and history of flight, which are taken in the first year of the program. In the second year students study flight and navigational principles, and in the third year the cadets cover areas like space vehicles and rocketry. In the fourth year students are given several options, one of which is an honors program allowing them to enroll in ground school to obtain a pilot's license.</p>
        <p>Admission to Junior R.O.T.C. is fairly simple and available by registering with a school counselor. All that is required is United States citizenship, good character and physical fitness. Staying in the program is more difficult. Cadets have Junior R.O.T.C. classes five days a week and are expected to maintain a grade point average of at least 2.0.</p>
        <p>They are also required to dress in uniform once a week. And once they become part of the Junior R.O.T.C. they are expected to conduct themselves as leaders.</p>
        <p>Besides doing regular course work, students have the opportunity to join the unit's color guard, which will perform in parades and at ceremonies. They will also take field trips to Air Force bases, airports and Federal Aviation Administration units.  Students who complete the program may gain extra benefits like college scholarships or entrance to the Air Force with higher than normal initial standing.</p>
        <p>Estella V. Able, chairwoman of Mount Vernon High School's science department, said the program can provide opportunities for students interested in the military.</p>
        <p>''I think this program is going to give some of our students additional options,'' she said. ''I know of a young girl who wants to be an astronaut, so she is interested in going into this program because she feels that it will give her additional experiences. It will expose her to areas we may not have covered in the traditional classroom.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Able also reported that there were some parents who had reservations about bringing a military cadet corps to the high school, but such feelings were assuaged after the parents received more information about the program. She conceded that the daily regimen may not be appropriate for all students.</p>
        <p>At Roosevelt High School in Yonkers, the Air Force Junior R.O.T.C. program is only three years old, but  Dr. Michael V. Yazurlo, the principal, credits it with improving his school's academic reputation and expanding many of his students' career goals.</p>
        <p>Colonel Kirk said that less than 1 percent of the commercial pilots in the United States are black. He said he believes that his program can offer a service to the pupils of Mount Vernon High School, which has a predominantly black student body. ''We want to expose kids to something different, something challenging,'' he said. ''I don't know how many African-American kids at this age are thinking about how an airplane flies. Here's an opportunity for them to do and experience that.''</p>
        <p>Tech. Sgt. Jack L. Gardner, an aerospace science instructor at Roosevelt High School, said that from his vantage point many young people are yearning for the type of discipline and structure that the Junior R.O.T.C. provides. ''The Air Force Junior R.O.T.C. is not about militaristic training,'' he said. ''What we are interested in in the Junior R.O.T.C. is introducing young men and women to aerospace science, math and technology. It also teaches a very important life skill, and that is responsibility.''</p>
        <p>During the seventh-period class of R.O.T.C at Mount Vernon High School on the first day of school this semester, Colonel Kirk met with 13 of his new cadets in the school's main auditorium because their classroom, which once served as the home for the school's electrical science program, was still being painted.</p>
        <p>He went over some basic goals and standards of the cadet corps and emphasized that the Junior R.O.T.C. was a ''student-centered program,'' which will require each of them to take different types of leadership roles as officers in the unit. He also told the students, who listened quietly and occasionally raised their hands to ask questions, that their uniforms and books, which are furnished by the Air Force at no cost, would be given to them shortly.</p>
        <p>After class Gavin T. Walters, a shy freshman, said that he had registered for the Junior R.O.T.C. after he received an introductory letter about the program this summer. At the moment, he said, he is considering a career in the Air Force and added  that he has always dreamed of becoming a pilot. ''It was interesting,'' he said of his first day of R.O.T.C. class.</p>
        <p>And if Colonel Kirk, Sergeant Hymes and school officials have their way, Gavin's dreams may be a lot closer than he thinks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
