<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Catholic School Is Accused Of Shortchanging Athletes</title>
    <meta content="04DIPL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1051541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Education (Handicapped)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grading of Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Galveston (Tex)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">O'Connell High School (Galveston)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russell, Billy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmerle, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ducote, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Galveston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grading of Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Education (Handicapped)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EED91038F937A35753C1A96E958260" item-length="1174" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Catholic School Is Accused Of Shortchanging Athletes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>GALVESTON, Tex.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>O'Connell High School, Catholic school in Galveston, Texas, is accused of recruiting and giving diplomas to student athletes who lacked necessary credits; Texas Assn of Private and Parohial Schools penalizes school for violating recruiting and other rules, as one graduate, Billy Russell, prepares to sue; 17-year-old special education student says he was promised tutoring and aid, but was not helped; photo; school has released principal Thomas Ducote and football coach Sam Zimmerle (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After graduating from O'Connell High School here last May, Billy Russell planned to go to a community college and play football this fall. Instead, he is sitting at home with a diploma that is little more than a piece of paper in a nice red folder.</p>
        <p>Billy, 17, who was a special education student, said in a recent interview that he had been recruited to play football at O'Connell, a Roman Catholic school, with the promise of tutoring and financial assistance. ''The coach said if there would be less kids, it would be better for me and I can learn,'' Billy said in an interview recently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After graduating from O'Connell High School here last May, Billy Russell planned to go to a community college and play football this fall. Instead, he is sitting at home with a diploma that is little more than a piece of paper in a nice red folder.</p>
        <p>Billy, 17, who was a special education student, said in a recent interview that he had been recruited to play football at O'Connell, a Roman Catholic school, with the promise of tutoring and financial assistance. ''The coach said if there would be less kids, it would be better for me and I can learn,'' Billy said in an interview recently.</p>
        <p>But the help never came, he said, and he failed most of his classes. Still, he and six other students who were athletes were allowed to graduate even though they lacked the necessary credits.</p>
        <p>It was only when Billy's mother, Catherine Russell, asked for her son's transcript last summer that she and her son learned that Billy should never have graduated. By that time, the school had released its principal, Thomas Ducote, and the football coach, Sam Zimmerle, and the diocese said it had taken steps to insure that such a situation did not happen again.</p>
        <p>The Texas Association of Private and Parochial Schools has penalized O'Connell High School for several violations, including breaking recruiting rules, and Billy and his parents have retained a lawyer.</p>
        <p>''This school cheated him for a year,'' said Charles J. Argento, the family lawyer. ''As far as I'm concerned, they have to get him the tutors, and I think they need to pay for it. They're using these kids. When football is done, they drop them.''</p>
        <p>But others connected to the school say its problems go beyond an overemphasis on sports.</p>
        <p>''High school football in Texas is out of hand,'' said Alan Slay, a retired telephone employee who taught computer science at the school last year. ''That is the top layer of the story. But move down a notch. O'Connell is a Catholic school not really equipped to handle a variety of students.''</p>
        <p>In the past 10 years, the enrollment at O'Connell High School, grades 9 through 12, has dropped to 133 students from about 300, and parents have been concerned that the diocese might close its doors. Teachers said academic standards had declined.</p>
        <p>And there was another problem. The school's bookkeeper, Cheryl Zimmerle, the wife of the football coach, committed suicide after the  school's financial records were subpoenaed in connection with a fraud.</p>
        <p>''Last year was the crowning of the bad times, we had so many tragedies,'' said Pat Teltschik, who has taught at the school for 25 years.</p>
        <p>It was the only year that Mr. Ducote and Billy would be at O'Connell.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ducote, who had been a principal at a Roman Catholic school in Boca Raton, Fla., said he had taken the job at O'Connell to be closer to relatives. He is now unemployed.</p>
        <p>Billy said he had been recruited by Mr. Zimmerle while working out at a local college after returning from Rialto, Calif., in the summer of 1997. Billy, who played on the school's offensive and defensive lines, said he had been drawn to the school because of the promised academic help. ''I told them I wasn't no A-B student,'' Billy said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Russell said that when she asked whether her son would be able to keep up at the school, she was assured by Mr. Zimmerle that Billy would be tutored. Mrs. Russell said the coach said he would take care of Billy's annual tuition of $4,250.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zimmerle, who is teaching and coaching football at Needville (Tex.) High School, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ducote said in a recent interview that by the end of Billy's first month in school, September 1997, teachers said of him: ''He can't read. He can't write. He can't spell. He can't do anything.''</p>
        <p>Last October, Mrs. Zimmerle committed suicide after the school's financial records were sought in connection with a $1.3 million theft at Mrs. Zimmerle's previous place of employment. An audit after her death found about $300,000 in school money unaccounted for, diocese officials said.</p>
        <p>District Attorney Michael Gaurino said he had traced the missing $300,000 to Mrs. Zimmerle. He said his office had been unable ''to substantiate any evidence to charge anyone else.''</p>
        <p>In January, after football season had ended, Mrs. Russell was called into the principal's office and told Billy was failing, she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ducote said he told her, ''We're not meeting your child's need, and I think he needs to leave.'' He said Mrs. Russell became angry and threatened to sue the school if her son did not graduate. ''We couldn't afford a suit,'' Mr. Ducote said.</p>
        <p>So teachers continued to work with Billy as they had been.</p>
        <p>Patrick Danesi, a teacher and a football coach at O'Connell last year, was promoted to principal this year. Mr. Danesi said teachers modified work to help Billy understand, read test questions to him and gave him longer to complete work.</p>
        <p>Melissa Musick, a counselor, said she had tried to get Billy into special education at a nearby public high school (O'Connell has none), but that could not be arranged because he did not live in Galveston but in nearby Texas City.</p>
        <p>In May, with graduation at hand, Mr. Ducote said he had been confronted with what to do about 12 students who did not qualify to graduate out of a senior class of 48. In four cases, he said, students with failing grades, including two athletes, were given blank diplomas. Three other students, including one athlete, made arrangements to make up work to complete their credits. In four other cases, three of them involving athletes, Mr. Ducote said, he had gone against school policy and averaged first and second semester scores and allowed the students to graduate although they had failed the second semester. The 12th student, Billy, was given a diploma.</p>
        <p>''I tried to make the best decision possible with the information I had at hand,'' Mr. Ducote said. He said of the athletes, ''These children had been used and just cast aside.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Danesi disputes Mr. Ducote, saying that all 12 students were given signed diplomas when none were eligible to graduate.</p>
        <p>O'Connell officials have appealed the sanctions by the Association of Private and Parochial Schools, which put the school on a one-year probation and barred its teams from going to district playoffs this year.</p>
        <p>''It's unfair to the kids,'' Mr. Danesi said. ''If you looked at all the schools in Galveston and Houston,  you would find a lot of cases like it. We've been brought to light, and we're doing something about it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
