<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sculptor in Search Of Discerning Eyes</title>
    <meta content="04WOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1051273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kent, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weizel, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EEDC1638F937A35753C1A96E958260" item-length="1356" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sculptor in Search Of Discerning Eyes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD WEIZEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weizel, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of wood sculptor William Kent, 79, of Durham, Conn; he comments on art establishment's rejection of his work and what he is trying to achieve; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILLIAM KENT, a sculptor in pine, walnut and mahogany, makes carvings of the mundane, woodblocks of the politically incorrect -- work, in short, as eccentric and original as he is.</p>
        <p>Reclusive, nearly 80, Mr. Kent rises each day at 4:30 A.M. to work in a converted barn connected to his  home in Durham, where he lives alone with two cats. In the barn, Mr. Kent's creations -- many six feet high -- look as if they might spring to life from underneath their dusty plastic coverings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILLIAM KENT, a sculptor in pine, walnut and mahogany, makes carvings of the mundane, woodblocks of the politically incorrect -- work, in short, as eccentric and original as he is.</p>
        <p>Reclusive, nearly 80, Mr. Kent rises each day at 4:30 A.M. to work in a converted barn connected to his  home in Durham, where he lives alone with two cats. In the barn, Mr. Kent's creations -- many six feet high -- look as if they might spring to life from underneath their dusty plastic coverings.</p>
        <p>A pair of basswood trousers hanging over an ironing board looks pliable enough to wear; a crushed beer can in white pine could have just been squeezed and twisted into its grotesque condition. An old boot rendered in maple looks comfortable enough to slide right onto Mr. Kent's feet, a carved football helmet onto the shaven head that some say gives him a Picasso-esque look.</p>
        <p>His carvings of zippers and safety pins look real enough to fasten and unlock; his carved chains sturdy enough to imprison.</p>
        <p>Then, without warning, the artist -- described by friends and associates as deeply insightful, but abrasive after numerous art world rejections -- unveils a work that perhaps best symbolizes his penchant for the satirical, and politically incorrect.</p>
        <p>It spoofs both one of our country's most patriotic symbols, and a lovable American icon; the American Eagle, rendered as Donald Duck, sitting atop a trash can on wheels so lifelike it appears ready to roll across the room.</p>
        <p>Just as outrageous are the dozens of wood carvings and prints Mr. Kent created during the 1960's and 70's that one colleague described as ''erotica . . . with an edge.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kent refuses to interpret his art. That, he says, is for the people who view it. And he bristles when asked how he comes up with an idea.</p>
        <p>''I can't say what gives me an idea, you can get an idea from anything at all,'' he said. ''I just see something, and I'm inspired to take a block of wood and transform it into a thing of beauty, something that people will want to look at.''</p>
        <p>How long does it take to finish a piece? ''How do you answer such a question?'' he replied. ''The real answer is that it has taken 40 years of hard work, craftsmanship and learning how to do it that makes what I do possible.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kent is a self-taught artist. He  came to Connecticut in 1944 from his native Kansas City to attend Yale University -- to study not art, but music, specifically piano, under Paul Hindemith. Four years later, he says, he began carving.</p>
        <p>''I don't know why, really, it's just what I wanted to do, so I did it,'' he said. ''I never stopped to think about why I do it, I only know that I must.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kent says neither he nor his art can be neatly categorized or easily interpreted, which may account for the more than 30 rejections over the years from curators, galleries and museums where he and his admirers have submitted pieces from among the hundreds he has done.</p>
        <p>While he has from time to time exhibited his sculptures of the everyday -- apples, light bulbs, corkscrews, pipes, shoehorns -- and the more abstract and surreal works like a kneeling man with a wasp and praying mantis on his back, Mr. Kent says he still barely makes a living from his art.</p>
        <p>''If it weren't for Social Security I couldn't do it,'' said Mr. Kent, whose works are priced from $1,500 to $4,000. ''I guess I don't fit in with the art establishment, and never have, but what do they know anyway? They tell me it's impossible to sell my work, that it doesn't fit their needs. What does that mean?''</p>
        <p>Friends, colleagues and art dealers who have worked with Mr. Kent say his lack of commercial success may rest in too much realism, not being in the mainstream; some say his works are too large, that the artist is too abrasive. But they all are convinced he will someday be recognized as a master.</p>
        <p>''Most of the great artists throughout history have not fit in with mainstream society during their time, and Bill Kent is a perfect example of that,'' said Leo Jensen, an Ivoryton artist who has known Mr. Kent since  the 1960's. ''He is a master sculptor who expresses a point of view that is not popular. But his work also captures images of the everyday so powerful they make you notice things you never did before.''</p>
        <p>Sandra Swan, a Block Island artist who displayed and sold Mr. Kent's works at a former Charlestown, Mass., gallery, has known the sculptor for more than 40 years. ''He is the greatest living carver of wood in the world,'' she said. ''There's not even anyone close.''</p>
        <p>''Ordinary objects really do become transformed through him into works of exquisite beauty so moving they are unparalleled,'' said Ms. Swan. ''Nobody can do what Bill Kent does, and I just wish more people would discover him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kent's admirers have tried.</p>
        <p>Monique Knowlton, who owns galleries in New York City and Connecticut and has herself bought Mr. Kent's works, tried for two years to sell them with little success.</p>
        <p>''I think his works are irresistible,'' said Ms. Knowlton. ''But wood sculptures, particularly the type of finely crafted works he does, are not in right now in the art world and there just isn't a market for them.''</p>
        <p>Marvin Beloff, a retired Meriden businessman and sculptor who has known Mr. Kent for three decades and has in recent years taken on a crusade to gain recognition for him,  said it is ''a travesty that his works are not in every major museum in the country.''</p>
        <p>''I have a fantasy,'' he went on. ''If I had the money I would build a museum myself and put 50 of his best works on permanent display, and the world would know how extraordinary this man's works are.''</p>
        <p>Richard Castellane, an attorney and former New York art dealer who has displayed Mr. Kent's works and has known him the longest, says his old friend is ''an original American eccentric'' who, had he lived in a different time, would have been ''one of the great Greek sculptors.''</p>
        <p>''The American public has historically been very slow to catch on to great art and great artists, and I think that is the case with Bill,'' he said. ''But he also has a right to be bitter because he is the premier sculptor of wood I have seen, and relatively few people know it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kent says it does annoy him that people often don't grasp or appreciate what he does. He describes going to a doctor recently and telling him he still carves wood. The doctor, he said, told him it was good for a man his age to relax with such a nice hobby.</p>
        <p>''I told him, the hell it is, that I've been breathing in wood and sawdust for 40 years, and that this is damn hard work,'' said Mr. Kent. ''It's not relaxing at all.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kent says he'll keep working until he can no longer maneuver the mallets, saws and chisels to carve and weave his wooden magic.</p>
        <p>''What am I going to do, watch television all day long? I would rather keep breathing the sawdust.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
