<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Battle Plan to Fight Pollution</title>
    <meta content="04SEWE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1051294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sewers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grauer, Kenneth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brenner, Elsa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4D61638F937A35753C1A96E958260" item-length="1584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Battle Plan to Fight Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brenner, Elsa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arrest of Yonkers (NY) Joint Treatment Works superintendent Kenneth Grauer in wake of massive sewage spill in Hudson River is seen as marking new trend holding people, rather than companies, criminally responsible for environmental violations; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO is at fault? It is a question often asked after an environmental spill or another type of accident. Should a faceless corporation be required to pay a fine that it can easily afford and then pass along the cost to its customers? Or should the blame be placed elsewhere -- say on a company vice president who turned a blind eye to violations or an employee who threw the wrong switch?</p>
        <p>This summer, after 122 million gallons of unchlorinated sewage rushed into the Hudson River from the Yonkers Joint Treatment Works, fouling sections of the giant waterway and causing two beaches to close, the superintendent of the plant was charged by the District Attorney's Office with a criminal offense -- a knowing violation of a state pollutant discharge elimination system permit, which is a felony.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO is at fault? It is a question often asked after an environmental spill or another type of accident. Should a faceless corporation be required to pay a fine that it can easily afford and then pass along the cost to its customers? Or should the blame be placed elsewhere -- say on a company vice president who turned a blind eye to violations or an employee who threw the wrong switch?</p>
        <p>This summer, after 122 million gallons of unchlorinated sewage rushed into the Hudson River from the Yonkers Joint Treatment Works, fouling sections of the giant waterway and causing two beaches to close, the superintendent of the plant was charged by the District Attorney's Office with a criminal offense -- a knowing violation of a state pollutant discharge elimination system permit, which is a felony.</p>
        <p>The superintendent, Kenneth Grauer, a 25-year employee of the county, faces up to four years in jail, if convicted. But his lawyer claims that his client has become the scapegoat of a system that must place the blame somewhere.</p>
        <p>The arrest of Mr. Grauer, 49, in August by District Attorney Jeanine Pirro's Environmental Crimes Bureau marks a new trend in recent years: holding people criminally responsible for environmental violations. The complaint contends that even though Mr. Grauer was alerted to the failure of the plant's chlorination system on July 13, he did not take steps to limit the discharge until the next day. For now, he is suspended without pay until the charges are resolved.</p>
        <p>His case is not unusual. Throughout the United States, not only are corporations paying heavy fines but company executives and employees who are found responsible for crimes against the environment are also facing time behind bars.</p>
        <p>''Companies are just low-hanging fruit,'' said Earl E. Devaney, director of criminal enforcement in the forensics and training division of the Federal Environmental Protection Agency. ''It's time to pierce the corporate veil and go for the individual.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Devaney said that large companies can often absorb even heavy penalties but that when corporate executives, plant supervisors and other employees are arrested, the charges serve as a greater deterrent to future crimes. ''It's one thing to have fines levied on your company,'' he said. ''It's considered to be the cost of doing business, but it's another thing to have to tell your pals at the country club that you're going to the slammer for 15 years.''</p>
        <p>Take, for example, the case of George E. Betts, president of Lam Pine, a company in LaGrande, Ore., who was sentenced on May 18 in Federal District Court in Boise, Idaho, to pay $163,177 to the protection agency's superfund. The court also sentenced Mr. Betts to six months in prison. He was convicted of being involved in the illegal transportation of more than 230 55-gallon drums of paint and solvent wastes to another plant he owned in Payette, Idaho.</p>
        <p>''I rejected the notion that these were just good people doing bad things,'' said Mr. Devaney, a former special agent in charge of fraud for the Secret Service. ''They had the same motivations as other white-collar criminals -- lying, stealing and cheating. They knew the violations were crimes, and they went and did it anyway.'' Robert F. Kennedy Jr., the director of the Environmental Litigation Clinic at Pace University in White Plains, said Congress ''has passed all these wonderful environmental laws since 1970'' but the public will not benefit unless the Government continues to take a hard line with polluters. The Clean Water Act was adopted 26 years ago.</p>
        <p>On May 21, 1997, in Federal District Court in Anchorage, Edward Hanousek, a supervisor for the White Pass &amp; Yukon Railroad, was sentenced to serve six months in prison and six months in a halfway house and also to pay a $5,000 fine for his Clean Water Act conviction for the negligent discharge of oil from a company pipeline in Skagway, Alaska, in October 1994. He has since appealed the verdict. The discharge was the result of an accident that occurred during the illegal removal of rock from United States Forest Service land. The case was investigated by the protection agency's criminal investigation division.</p>
        <p>In Westchester, the County Attorney, Alan D. Scheinkman, said he approved of such enforcement actions, saying that they ''put employees on notice that they will be held responsible for their actions.''</p>
        <p>In the Westchester case, Mr. Grauer was one of three employees suspended in connection with the incident, which occurred on July 13 and 14. No charges have been filed against the other two employees. The County Executive's office has conducted an investigation into the actions of Mr. Grauer, who reportedly did not alert senior officials or use backup procedures to treat the water. For four hours, waste water that had not been disinfected flowed into the Hudson at the rate of nearly four million gallons an hour. The release of the waste water prompted county health officials to order the beach at Croton Point Park and another in Sleepy Hollow -- Philipse Manor Beach -- closed for two days.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Howard N. Adel of the County Health Department, said he was heartened that the county was taking action against polluters. ''It's very reassuring that our department's concerns are reflected in the county's policies,'' Dr. Adel said.</p>
        <p>The chlorine-pumping system at the Yonkers plant broke down twice in two days, but even the second time, County Executive Andrew J. Spano said, no one notified top officials. ''We have strict procedures in place for this,'' he said at the time. ''It just baffles me why they didn't tell anybody.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grauer's lawyer, David M. Rosoff, said last week that the county was brandishing its get-tough policy at his client's expense. ''They're attempting to make an example of Mr. Grauer,'' the lawyer said. ''Whatever environmental problems occurred, they weren't a result of criminal negligence on his part.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosoff described the District Attorney and the County Executive as overzealous. But Mr. Spano said his office and the District Attorney were not targeting workers in general but rather ''an individual who did not carry out his responsibility and consequently jeopardized the people of Westchester.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Pirro said the charges against Mr. Grauer did not represent a new policy but rather a continuation of a course set in motion in 1994, when her office established its Environmental Crimes Bureau. ''From the onset,'' she said, ''this office has held both individuals and corporations criminally liable for pollution.''</p>
        <p>For example, in 1996, Mrs. Pirro charged seven owners of dry cleaning establishments with criminal offenses in a 32-count indictment brought before Justice Kenneth H. Lange of State Supreme Court in White Plains. The top charge, first-degree, unlawful dealing in hazardous waste, carried a maximum penalty of four years in prison and a fine of $100,000. All of the defendants were found guilty of paying undercover agents (officials from the State Department of Environmental Conservation who were posing as illegal hazardous waste haulers) to transport their illegal waste. They were fined, sentenced to probation and required to perform community service.</p>
        <p>The State Department of Environmental Conservation does not handle criminal offenses, referring cases like the Westchester dry cleaners to a district attorney, Gary F. Sheffer, a spokesman for the department, said.</p>
        <p>That is why in the case of the July spill at the Yonkers sewage treatment plant, the state fined the county only for administrative violations of permits, and Mrs. Pirro proceeded with the criminal charges against Mr. Grauer. Answering the state charges, the county agreed in August to pay the Department of Environmental Conservation $600,000 in penalties for violations in Yonkers and other plants, Frank V. Bifera, general counsel for the department, said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bifera said that even though his department does not prosecute offenders, it nevertheless tries to hold individuals responsible when appropriate. In the case of two oil firms in the last year, the state successfully filed administrative, but not criminal, charges against the individual owners and levied heavy fines.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes it's a matter of an individual trying to get ahead in a company,'' Mr. Bifera said. ''Sometimes he or she is trying to cover up incompetence or just acting recklessly.''</p>
        <p>Judson W. Starr, a former chief of the Federal Justice Department's environmental crimes section and now a lawyer with Venable, a law firm in Washington, said the latest policies ''imposed great powers'' on some corporate executives like senior vice presidents in charge of the safety and health of the environment. ''They were little heard from before,'' he said. ''Now companies are becoming more sensitive to the fact that there are extreme risks in violating environmental laws.''</p>
        <p>But John Cronin, the Hudson Riverkeeper, said that while governments talked a good game about getting tough with environmental polluters, officials were often inconsistent. ''Too often, politics gets in the way,'' he said. ''When the economy is bad, they don't want to do anything to interfere and make it get worse. When times are good, they don't want to rock the boat.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad to hear they're talking about taking a stronger stance, but I'm skeptical.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
