<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>North of Chateauneuf</title>
    <meta content="05TAST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1166133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TASTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3DF163BF936A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>North of Chateauneuf</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the hierarchy of French red wine regions, the Rhone ranks a distant third behind Burgundy and Bordeaux. But knowledgeable wine drinkers everywhere are grateful. While trophy hunters spend huge sums bagging the top-of-the-line Pauillacs and Chambertins and pay outrageous prices even for mediocre bottles, the Rhones are for the most part reasonably priced and available.</p>
        <p>The grape-growing region surrounding the Rhone River in southern France actually breaks into two separate and distinct areas: the south, where many grape varieties are blended into wines like Chateauneuf-du-Pape, and the much smaller north, where the syrah grape rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the hierarchy of French red wine regions, the Rhone ranks a distant third behind Burgundy and Bordeaux. But knowledgeable wine drinkers everywhere are grateful. While trophy hunters spend huge sums bagging the top-of-the-line Pauillacs and Chambertins and pay outrageous prices even for mediocre bottles, the Rhones are for the most part reasonably priced and available.</p>
        <p>The grape-growing region surrounding the Rhone River in southern France actually breaks into two separate and distinct areas: the south, where many grape varieties are blended into wines like Chateauneuf-du-Pape, and the much smaller north, where the syrah grape rules.</p>
        <p>The best of the northern Rhone wines, from appellations like Hermitage, Cornas and Cote Rotie, are intense and full bodied and can age for many years. Secondary appellations, like Crozes-Hermitage and St.-Joseph, are lighter and more accessible, and cheaper, too.</p>
        <p>St.-Josephs in particular are easy to appreciate with minimal aging, though the wines can last 10 years or more. Their accessibility and relative lack of harsh tannins lead some people to consider St.-Joseph the Beaujolais of the Rhone; yet, the wines can also convey the complexity of the best northern Rhones, though without their power.</p>
        <p>Young St.-Josephs are inky purple, almost black, with a flavor that always reminds me of olives. The more complex wines also have spicy notes of black pepper and sometimes even a smokiness. Food-matching experts typically recommend drinking syrah with game, but when was the last time you brought home a grouse? These wines are just as good with roast chicken, steak, pastas (without tomato sauce) and even meatloaf.</p>
        <p>Like all of the northern Rhone appellations, St.-Joseph is a tiny area. Most good wine shops don't carry many St.-Josephs, but they generally have at least one or two.</p>
        <p>TASTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
