<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeking Statesmanship, Farrakhan Softens Tone</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="803339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATION OF ISLAM</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TERRY, DON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARRAKHAN, LOUIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D71F3FF936A15753C1A963958260" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeking Statesmanship, Farrakhan Softens Tone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON TERRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TERRY, DON</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Oct. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the week since hundreds of thousands of black men heeded his call and poured into Washington for a day of prayer and protest, Louis Farrakhan, the leader of the Nation of Islam, has begun to moderate his language in an apparent campaign to broaden his political support.</p>
        <p>In a speech here on Monday night to hundreds of Muslims and non-Muslims packed into his ornate mosque on the South Side, Mr. Farrakhan said he would try to become more statesmanlike in his language and behavior because the march had elevated his stature and his responsibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the week since hundreds of thousands of black men heeded his call and poured into Washington for a day of prayer and protest, Louis Farrakhan, the leader of the Nation of Islam, has begun to moderate his language in an apparent campaign to broaden his political support.</p>
        <p>In a speech here on Monday night to hundreds of Muslims and non-Muslims packed into his ornate mosque on the South Side, Mr. Farrakhan said he would try to become more statesmanlike in his language and behavior because the march had elevated his stature and his responsibility.</p>
        <p>"You can say things in the basement that you can't say when you're on the first floor," he said. "As God starts taking you up, you have to practice more statesmanship."</p>
        <p>Whether Mr. Farrakhan is moving closer to the political mainstream, or merely changing his message, is unclear. He has reached out before, particularly to Jews who felt aggrieved by his comments, only to plunge into new controversy.</p>
        <p>In any case, the political fallout and broad debate touched off by the march have broadened his visibility well beyond his core followers. The major television networks have interviewed him, the BBC has followed him home to Chicago, his face (half in shadow) is on the latest cover of Newsweek magazine, and more and more black elected officials and political hopefuls, like the son of the Rev. Jesse Jackson, are willing to be seen embracing the fiery Muslim minister.</p>
        <p>In his speech on Monday, he called once again for a meeting with the leaders of major Jewish organizations in another attempt to exorcise the ghosts and accusations of anti-Semitism that have haunted him for more than a decade. As he pounded the white marble pulpit in his gleaming mosque, he bellowed, "I am not a racist."</p>
        <p>"It doesn't make sense for intelligent people to be fighting each other," he said. "We are dying in the streets. We don't have time for that."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Farrakhan has flirted with the mainstream in the past and has reached out to Jewish groups before, only to be embroiled in fresh controversies about his sharp bitter words.</p>
        <p>"If he truly wants to dialogue, then he's got to publicly, specifically and continuously purge himself of his racism and anti-Semitism," Abraham H. Foxman, director of the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, said in an interview today. "To continue saying he wants to meet is a nonstarter. It doesn't mean anything."</p>
        <p>At least three times during his speech, Mr. Farrakhan denied being an anti-Semite. Far from hating Jews, Mr. Farrakhan said, he admired them. He said he hoped black people would follow the example of Jews, "who wield a tremendous amount of power for such a small group," because they are politically organized.</p>
        <p>"I'm mentioning Jews in a complimentary way," he said. "Jewish people are organized and they are effective and that's a good example."</p>
        <p>Mr. Foxman said such talk of Jewish power and influence is "another classic, anti-Semitic stereotype."</p>
        <p>"I guess he's a moderate now," Mr. Foxman said. "He didn't really beat up on the Jews."</p>
        <p>But in another sign of his journey toward the mainstream, or at least its right bank, Mr. Farrakhan said he would put the force of his organization behind voter registration drives. Nation of Islam members will go door to door, he said, from southern Mississippi to the South Chicago to build a black force of voters trained to use their ballots like bullets.</p>
        <p>"The enemy," Mr. Farrakhan said, sounding like a general trying to pump up his troops, "didn't see a march, he saw an army."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Farrakhan acknowledged that he knows almost nothing about electoral politics.</p>
        <p>"I'm in water I've never been in before," Mr. Farrakhan said of politics. "But I do want to get in."</p>
        <p>Mr. Farrakhan said that he did not think he would ever run for elective office because "a man is a fool who tries to be something he's not."</p>
        <p>Mr. Farrakhan also called for more United States aid to Africa and a national convention where a black political agenda will be drawn up and used as a litmus test for Presidential candidates next spring.</p>
        <p>"We don't want to be loyal to parties," Mr. Farrakhan said, "because the parties have never been loyal to us."</p>
        <p>Mr. Farrakhan was interrupted several times by applause and shouts of "teach" and "preach, Brother Minister," during his speech, which came at the end of a long evening billed as "a victory party," celebrating the Million Man March.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson, along with Benjamin F. Chavis Jr., the national director of the march, and several other black politicians and advocates also spoke, but Mr. Farrakhan was clearly star.</p>
        <p>Mr. Farrakhan also dismissed accusations that he was sexist because women were asked not to attend the march in Washington on Oct. 16. He said he loved and respected women.</p>
        <p>"My mother was a woman," he said. "I'm sure yours is too."</p>
        <p>Maybe all the press attention has put Mr. Farrakhan in a good mood because on Monday he gave a speech here that in many ways was in sharp contrast to the uneven and sometimes rambling two-and-a-half-hour "lecture" he delivered in Washington.</p>
        <p>In Chicago, Mr. Farrakhan spoke for about 70 minutes, although he began by saying, "I didn't come tonight to do any long teaching, just six hours."</p>
        <p>Then he smiled and everyone relaxed once they realized he was joking.</p>
        <p>"I love the minister," a man whispered to his friend. "But I got to get up and go to work in the morning."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
