<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just Being There Is Not Enough for the Indians</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="803138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORLD SERIES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ATLANTA BRAVES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CLEVELAND INDIANS CLEVELAND INDIANS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E2D81E39F936A15753C1A963958260" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just Being There Is Not Enough for the Indians</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Indians limped home from Atlanta after losing the first two games of the World Series, a theory sprouted on these shores of Lake Erie: The Indians had already achieved their psychological goal of reaching the World Series, and  subconsciously, at least, they were just happy to be here and had no challenges remaining.</p>
        <p>However long the players have been with the Indians, from their first day in  Cleveland they heard that the Indians had not been in the World Series since 1954. No one in town told them the Indians hadn't won the World Series since 1948; the year that was seared into their consciousness was 1954.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Indians limped home from Atlanta after losing the first two games of the World Series, a theory sprouted on these shores of Lake Erie: The Indians had already achieved their psychological goal of reaching the World Series, and  subconsciously, at least, they were just happy to be here and had no challenges remaining.</p>
        <p>However long the players have been with the Indians, from their first day in  Cleveland they heard that the Indians had not been in the World Series since 1954. No one in town told them the Indians hadn't won the World Series since 1948; the year that was seared into their consciousness was 1954.</p>
        <p>By winning 100 games and the American League Central championship, by beating Boston in the first round of the playoffs and Seattle in the A.L. Championship Series, the 1995 Indians achieved everything they had learned was important to the good citizens of this unfairly maligned town. They reached the  World Series, obliterating 1954 from the Cleveland lexicon, just as "1940" never has to be heard again at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Indians fans certainly seemed to be satisfied. When the scene of the World Series switched here Monday, a cab driver remarked that a strange mood seemed to have settled over the city. The fans, he said, were delighted that the team was  playing in the Series after these 41 years, but they didn't seem to be bothered  by the losses in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>"They're just happy to be here," he said.</p>
        <p>But Omar Vizquel chose to differ with that view.</p>
        <p>"That's not the case," the Indians' good young shortstop said. "I think the case is we have some guys who try to overdo stuff. They're not being patient enough. They're putting too much weight on their shoulders. Guys are putting too much pressure on themselves. We just have to relax and have fun, just like we did in the playoffs."</p>
        <p>Last night Carlos Baerga relaxed. Hitless in eight times at bat in the first  two games, Baerga stroked two run-scoring singles after driving in the Indians'  second run with a groundout. Then he lashed a double in the 11th inning that led to the winning run in the Indians' 7-6 victory and drowned the theory of the subconscious in the lake.</p>
        <p>"After the first two games, I was down a little bit," Baerga said. "I want to do something to help the team tonight. I was more relaxed."</p>
        <p>Vizquel, something of a seer apparently, foresaw an improvement in the Indians' play, suggesting earlier that the return to Jacobs Field could be the spur the players needed.</p>
        <p>"Now that we're here in Cleveland, I just hope everybody gets their rhythm back nice and easy," Vizquel said. "Don't try to do too much, and the little guys have to do what they're capable to do, get on base for the big guys, and we can score some runs."</p>
        <p>By the little guys, Vizquel meant the hitters at the top of the lineup. In the first two games, Kenny Lofton, Vizquel and Baerga combined for 3 hits in 25  times at-bat. From Vizquel's mouth to their bats.</p>
        <p>Lofton, the leadoff batter, led off the first inning with a single and the third with a double. Vizquel, No. 2 in the order, lashed a triple to right field in the first inning, driving home Lofton with the tying run, then bunted for a single in the third, moving Lofton to third base. Baerga, the third hitter, drove in Vizquel in the first inning with an infield grounder and Lofton in the  third with a single.</p>
        <p>In those two innings, the Indians stroked six hits, only two fewer than they  had in the two games in Atlanta. The four runs they scored missed by only one the two-game total, except all of these runs were well earned, unlike three of the five runs in Games 1 and 2.</p>
        <p>Later, in the seventh inning, Lofton walked, moved to second as Vizquel grounded out, stole third and scored on Baerga's infield single. And finally, in the 11th inning, Baerga led off with a double and his pinch-runner, Alvaro Espinoza, scored the winning run.</p>
        <p>If the Indians had happy-walked their way through the first two games, they served notice last night their intensity and desire and determination were back. They rediscovered all of that at a players' meeting before the game.</p>
        <p>"If we were going to go down, we were going to go down fighting," Sandy Alomar Jr. said of the meeting's message.</p>
        <p>"We had a meeting and we said everybody has to do something," Baerga said. "We did it all year. We said let's do it. We can do it. We showed all year nobody can beat us. Everybody said something. Everybody believed in ourselves. The first two games we were down a little bit. We gave in to Maddux and Glavine  too much. They're two good pitchers. Today we were of different minds."</p>
        <p>Jim Thome, the Indians' third baseman, said the problem in the first two games was not any absence of desire among the Indians but a presence of good pitching by the Braves.</p>
        <p>"You have to give the Braves' pitching staff credit," Thome said. "They've done a great job. They're intelligent. They know how to pitch. Their pitching has taken control. I think they've risen to another level."</p>
        <p>But Vizquel disagreed.</p>
        <p>"They don't have to rise to another level," he said. "They just have to keep  their regular level. We are the ones who haven't been in our regular level."</p>
        <p>The Indians, the best offensive team in the American League this year, acted  like water last night, seeking their level. They did it against John Smoltz, a hard thrower, not a finesse pitcher like Greg Maddux and Tom Glavine.</p>
        <p>They needed all of their runs because the Braves' hitters proved Thome prophetic.</p>
        <p>Throughout the American League Championship Series, Lou Piniella, the Seattle Mariners' manager, kept cautioning people not to ignore Cleveland's pitching. The Indians, Piniella said more than once, didn't win 100 games just because they had good hitters; their pitching, he said, had been overlooked.</p>
        <p>The Braves, of course, are noted for their pitching. Beginning with Maddux, the best pitcher on the planet, they have a string of starters who can baffle any lineup and a relief corps that can shut down any threat. But Thome, paraphrasing Piniella, made another observation.</p>
        <p>"You have to give their offense credit," he said. "It's kind of overlooked. They know how to manufacture runs and they know what to do in situations."</p>
        <p>The Braves' hitters did all of that and more last night, but the Indians played like they were thinking of 1948, not 1954.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
