<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loon over Miami: The On-Target Humor of Dave Barry</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="386188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HUMOR AND WIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICHMOND, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRY, DAVE (COLUMNIST)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRY, DAVE (BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D9113AF930A1575AC0A966958260" item-length="4971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loon over Miami: The On-Target Humor of Dave Barry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Richmond; Peter Richmond, a former reporter for The Miami Herald, is a feature writer for The National.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICHMOND, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The humor community of the kinder and gentler 90's is being swept by waves of touchy-feely caution and cloying cuteness. From network to newsprint, a new timidity abounds. Calvin and Hobbes and Arsenio Hall rule the earth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The humor community of the kinder and gentler 90's is being swept by waves of touchy-feely caution and cloying cuteness. From network to newsprint, a new timidity abounds. Calvin and Hobbes and Arsenio Hall rule the earth.</p>
        <p>The humor community of the kinder and gentler 90's is being swept by waves of touchy-feely caution and cloying cuteness. From network to newsprint, a new timidity abounds. Calvin and Hobbes and Arsenio Hall rule the earth.</p>
        <p>Into the void, thank goodness, rushes Dave Barry. In Dave Barry's column, no one is safe, from ''Vice President for Real'' Dan Quayle to Senator Jesse Helms (''R.-Spider Family'') to former President Gerald ''R'' Ford to the citizens of Oklahoma who, after Barry suggested selling their state to Japan to rectify the trade imbalance, besieged him with letters ''containing many correctly spelled words.''</p>
        <p>In Dave Barry's column, Gov. Bob Martinez of Florida ''exudes the warm personal charm of a millipede,'' the air-fare wars have produced a new generation of ''Frequent fliers with bare feet and live carry-on chickens,'' and Manuel Noriega is assured a fair trial only if the courts can summon ''12 unbiased jurors with the mental alertness of moist towelettes.''</p>
        <p>In Dave Barry's column, we learn that Senator John Glenn ''couldn't electrify a fish tank if he threw a toaster in it,'' that Canada's motto is ''Technically a Nation'' and that the average big-league baseball team consists mostly of ''two dozen guys named Julio from friendly spider-infested nations to the south.''</p>
        <p>Happily, some of Barry's sharpest thrusts are reserved for his own ethnicity: ''Wealthy WASP's have less fun in their entire lifetimes,'' he wrote a few months ago, ''than members of other ethnic groups have at a single wedding reception. I have been to both WASP and non-WASP weddings, and your WASP couple can get married, go on their honeymoon, come home, pursue careers, have children and get divorced in less time than it takes for a non-WASP couple to get to the part of their reception where everyone drinks champagne from the maid of honor's brassiere.''</p>
        <p>By now, it should be eminently clear that the Barry sword of equal-opportunity insult is wielded with a clear absence of malice, in the spirit of unadulterated - and distinctly un-adult - buffoonery.</p>
        <p>Lest there be any misunderstanding, however, Barry is well aware that his broad brush can give offense. ''I realize I am generalizing here,'' he admitted in a recent column, ''but, as is often the case when I generalize, I don't care.''</p>
        <p>neither apparently do the rest of us. three hundred newspapers now carry the weekly musings of Dave Barry. ''Mr. Barry is the funniest man in America and we should encourage him,'' The New York Times Book Review has said - just a small sampling of the many accolades he has received. In 1988, Barry won the Pulitzer Prize for commentary. In 1989, ''Dave Barry Slept Here,'' a lunatic-revisionist history of the United States (the Wright brothers first flight was canceled because of equipment problems at O'Hare) achieved legitimacy with 11 weeks on the Times best-seller list. And his 10th and latest book, ''Dave Barry Turns 40'' (published by Crown), which delineates the panic of growing fat, bald and slow, has sold nearly 200,000 copies, enjoying lengthy stints on both the Times and Publishers Weekly lists. His surging popularity has led to appearances on Letterman, Carson, Koppel and at the National Tupperware Convention in Orlando, Fla.</p>
        <p>From Seattle to Miami, and all stops in between, the nation is eagerly devouring a verbal gumbo that encompasses the burlesque vulgarity of Samurai John Belushi, the indiscriminate insults of Monty Python and the literate lunacy of the original National Lampoon, all tinged by unmistakeable traces of 60's activism. But what else would you expect from a former conscientious objector who played lead guitar for a band called the Phlegmtones?</p>
        <p>Millions of American households now have the opportunity to feast on a regular diet of hyperbole (a bureaucrat has ''the I.Q. of a bowl of soup''; Americans have ''thighs the size of research submarines''), one-liners (''Is that [Michael Milken's]  real hair? Or is he wearing a Motel 6 bathmat?'') and, of course, Mr. Language Person:</p>
        <p>''Dear Mr. Language Person: I am with the Defense Department, and I'd like to know whether it's correct to say 'Four million dollars apiece IS not that much for the B-79 Hellfire Amphibious Assault Salad Bar,' or 'Four million dollars ARE not, etc.'</p>
        <p>''A: Does that price include the optional SS-863 Shrieking Eagle Tactical Sneeze Shield? ''Q: Of course not. ''A: I didn't think so.''</p>
        <p>Equal parts incisive observer and eighth-grade class clown, Barry may be our best antidote to the ugly sound-bite sensibilities of Eddie Murphy, Sam Kinison and Andrew Dice Clay. Barry's blossoming suggests that more than a few members of the younger generations, wearying of MTVidiocy, have secretly been lusting for the topical humor fix that only the written word can provide. They're finding it - if Barry's sales figures are any indication - in a direct disciple of Robert Benchley, by way of Russell Baker, with pinches of Calvin Trillin, Fran Lebowitz and P. J. O'Rourke.</p>
        <p>A Barry column often takes aim at the conventional targets of the conventional columnists, but in a distinctively skewed light, whether he's laying waste to the U.S. Senate (''White Male Millionaires Working for You''), examining current financial trends (''Statistics show that . . . investing your money in the stock market is nearly twice as secure, over the long term, as feeding it to otters'') or critiquing ''The Hubble Orbiting Space Paperweight . . . It would have been cheaper to take a regular telescope and put it on top of an 87-mile-high pile of $50 bills.''</p>
        <p>But for all of the topicality, when a Barry column is digested, it is usually the imagery that leaves us laughing; more often than not, a Barry piece is laced with the kind of language that gets kids tossed out of classrooms, if not suspended altogether. His column overflows with locutions like ''rat saliva,'' ''nasal discharge,'' ''bat-emission products,'' ''saliva-drenched gobs of tobacco,'' ''pig doots'' and ''toad secretions.''</p>
        <p>It should not be forgotten, after all, that in a contest in Tropic, the Sunday magazine of Barry's employer, The Miami Herald, the winning parody of his work consisted of a single word: ''boogers.''</p>
        <p>''There are certain themes that will forever run through my writing, like the sophomoricism,'' Barry admitted recently over lunch in a mall in South Miami, a ferny suburban refuge of margarine-colored homes and barking Dobermans. ''As long as there are people in New York who will sneer at it, who consider that kind of humor sophomoric, I'll keep cranking it out.''</p>
        <p>Like most of what he writes, this manifesto contains a certain amount of exaggeration - and a large grain of truth. Above all, Barry shuns all things trendy. Instead of a Range Rover, mandatory in South Florida, he drives a bulbous Dodge Ram with the heart of a Winnebago. And he has spurned job offers in Washington and Los Angeles. Apparently, Barry does not like big cities. In a memorable spoof of a New York Times Magazine cover story on Miami, he wrote, ''New York has more commissioners than Des Moines, Iowa, has residents, including . . . the Commissioner for Bicycle Messengers Bearing Down on You at Warp Speed With Mohawk Haircuts and Pupils Smaller Than Purely Theoretical Particles.''</p>
        <p>If nothing else, Barry's columns are refreshingly unpedantic, pretense-free pensees from which the commentary soon sloughs away, to expose the real Dave Barry: a former business seminar instructor, a survivor of more than his share of life's sledgehammerings, a 43-year-old man now anchored in American middle age by the seminal accouterments of our time - moist towelettes, sneeze shields and motel bathmats - but possessed of a mind just gleefully adolescent enough to bring them all to life.</p>
        <p>''Well, most of the funniest things in life happened in sophomore year, didn't they?'' says Jeff MacNelly, the three-time Pulitzer-prize-winning cartoonist for The Chicago Tribune who illustrates Barry's column each week for about 95 papers. ''If you're going to be really, truly funny, you have to use the language of sophomore year.''</p>
        <p>Barry's former editor at The Herald, Gene Weingarten, says, ''He has total recall of the experience of being 12 - it's locked in his head.'' Weingarten's dog Clementine makes regular appearances in the column. ''Clementine once ate aquarium gravel,'' Barry has written, ''without even heating it up.''</p>
        <p>When Barry was enjoying his real adolescence, the nation was at the height of its revolutionary convulsions, and his father, the Rev. Dr. David W. Barry, was devoting his life to the poor, the civil-rights movement and the founding of alcohol-abuse progams in New York State prisons - all of which provide some insight into the genesis of Barry's semicomic take on the weighty issues. He was old enough to enjoy the delirium of the national upheaval, and too young to let the more serious dogma get in the way of the fun - hence his penchant for leading Dada-esque sit-down strikes at his suburban high school, protesting such injustices as the existence of fruit.</p>
        <p>It is Barry's special talent now that he can take that back-of-the-classroom irreverence and layer it onto the mundane ingredients of his generation's everyday experience, which now encompasses everything from visits to the doctor (''Deep down, I have a large inflamed cyst of respect for the medical community'') to the men's movement: ''Today's man is making radical lifestyle changes such as sometimes remembering to remove the used tissue wads from his pockets before depositing his pants on the floor to be picked up by the Laundry Fairy.''</p>
        <p>But if there are those among us who think we have found a spokesman, don't tell it to Barry. It's hard to ruffle him. Despite the personal misfortunes of recent years, there are no edges to his face, which seems designed for nothing but to leap into smiles of all kinds. Yet he will bark at the mere suggestion that he is carrying anyone's flag.</p>
        <p>''I'm no one's spokesman,'' he insisted, as he raked a fish sandwich, a departure from his usual cheeseburger, through a film of ketchup and tartar sauce. ''In no sense do I think of myself as any kind of philosopher. I hate self-importance. All I ever was was a guy making jokes. I like it when people tell me I'm funny, but I'm extremely uncomfortable when people go beyond that and attach social significance to it.</p>
        <p>''I'm making people laugh because I'm receiving the same signals they are about the times we're living in, and rebroadcasting them at a slightly different frequency. But in 20 years the signals will be different, and the column won't strike people as funny. Tom Wolfe said that aesthetic achievements mired in their time are all fashion. He's right. People like to think they're invoking timeless truths. They're not. We're all dilettantes.''</p>
        <p>He paused, a little embarrassed to have been so strident, and immediately reached for his humor reflex.</p>
        <p>''I'm just worried,'' he confided, ''that there aren't enough bodily fluids to sustain my career.''</p>
        <p>There is no need for concern. He has risen from cult status to the plateau of national phenomenon. At the Miami Book Fair International last fall, the auditorium was too small to hold the crowd for a Barry reading - a room that had been plenty big enough for readings by such literary stars as Russell Banks and Tracy Kidder. This may have had something to do with his being a hometown hero in a fractured frontier town desperate for heroes. In Miami, Barry knows no peace.</p>
        <p>''Excuse me, Dave,'' our waitress says, ''but there's a woman behind me over here madly in love with you who wants to know if you'd go to bed with her.''</p>
        <p>''Tell her not tonight,'' Dave says, without missing a beat. ''Tell her I have a headache.''</p>
        <p>As a kid, his horn-rimmed glasses, home-sheared haircuts and wax-bean physique forced Barry to hone his sense of humor - largely out of self-defense. (Now he wears contacts, and he's upgraded his hair style to late-70's lounge act, but he still looks like someone you knew in high school.) The class clown at Pleasantville (N.Y.) High School, he was suspended just once, for getting drunk at a dance.</p>
        <p>''But I never threw up on anyone, which is more than I can say for a lot of people at high school,'' he said one day in his office, which is in the garage behind his house. ''That's what it should have said under my high school yearbook picture: ''He drank a lot of Scotch, but never threw up.''</p>
        <p>''I was heavy into nihilism . . . and I tended to be disruptive. If I could say one more thing, and get thrown out of class but make the other kids laugh, I'd say it. It was the way we related to each other as a family. We made a lot of jokes, and that's why I'm very good at it now. My mother was the funniest person I've ever known. My brothers and I would say, 'We're going swimming,' and she'd put on a June Cleaver voice and say, 'Don't drown!'</p>
        <p>''This is going to sound almost grim, but the day we buried my father, which was a devastating time for all of us - he was a great guy - we went to the cemetery and we were walking up to the hole where we were going to bury him. I have my arm around my mother, and she's got hers around me, and she looks down and sees the name of another person buried there, and she says, 'So that's why we never see him around anymore.' And we both started laughing.''</p>
        <p>Barry's years at Haverford College passed largely undistinguished, save for earning a degree in English literature, smoking his share of marijuana, and, for real recreation, occasionally lying down at the end of the runway at Philadelphia International Airport as the jumbo jets came in to land. He played guitar in various bands, and listened to the normal menu of psychedelic rock bands, with the exception of Iron Butterfly: ''Even when I was so high I was interested in carpet fiber, or could talk about dirt for a week, I didn't like 'In-A-Gadda-Da-Vida.' ''</p>
        <p>Barry professes to have given up all manner of controlled substances after college. He has never used cocaine - an aversion, he says, to putting things up his nose. This is not surprising; nasal passages have been good to him. ''I've done nose hair pretty well,'' he agrees. His father and brother were both alcoholics, though, and Barry will admit to concern over his excess consumption of beer, a theme that runs faithfully through many of his columns.</p>
        <p>After graduating in 1969, he spent two years doing conscientious objector duty for the Episcopal Church in New York, then wound up in the suburbs of Philadelphia writing for a small paper called The Daily Local News. There he met an editor named Beth Lenox, now his wife.</p>
        <p>He took a job at The Associated Press in Philadelphia, but found the work so mind-numbing that, when his neighbor asked him one day if he'd like to teach business seminars, Barry accepted on the spot. With no idea what he was doing, he found himself telling a lot of jokes, and his Willy Lomans, packed into hotel seminar rooms around the country, seemed to like it. Meanwhile, Beth suggested he start writing a weekly column for the feature section of The Daily Local News, and within a year, to his surprise, editors from around the nation were clamoring for more.</p>
        <p>The early columns were much like the ones he writes now, slices of suburban life dotted by the usual broadsides at Big Government and Big Business - the same stuff, then, that a hundred columnists at a hundred newspapers chew on every day. But there were a few things from the start about Barry that were different - for one thing most columns contained at least one reference to the bodily functions of various mammals (as in his visit to a wine tasting: 'Much too woody,' said one person. 'Heavily oxidized,' said another. 'Bat urine,' I offered.'').</p>
        <p>Most distinctive, though, was his willingness - no, eagerness - to deflate the self-puffery of the craft of journalism itself, ''the essence of which,'' he recently wrote, ''is writing authoritative stories about things you don't actually understand. I can remember, as a young reporter, writing lengthy, disapproving analyses of international banking practices at a time when my personal investment portfolio consisted entirely of discount pizza coupons.''</p>
        <p>''Maybe it's just that as a business-seminar instructor I wasn't being groomed the Journalism Way to become a columnist,'' he says. ''I was living a life so far removed from journalism it gave me a point of view about what was really worth writing about. I wasn't like other people who became columnists after being reporters. It was deliberately irresponsible and non-journalistic'' - as was apparent in a 1984 column in which Barry suggested that, given Ronald Reagan's abominable first-term record, his campaign slogan should have been ''Reagan: Most of his polyps were benign.''</p>
        <p>Mary Hadar, an editor at The Washington Post, whose Sunday magazine runs Barry as its only syndicated feature writer, recalls: ''The first column we took off the wire, the copy desk had scrawled, 'Poor taste! Sexist! Racist!' all over it. But the reader response was tremendous.''</p>
        <p>''The outrage was tremendous at the beginning,'' says Gene Weingarten, who lured Barry into a full-time position at Tropic in 1983, allowing his new columnist to stay in Pennsylvania. ''There was an unrelenting avalanche of letters from humorless people. Now, though, the humor-impaired no longer read him, and the rest get the joke, so it's slowed to a trickle.''</p>
        <p>The outrage is usually from the hinterlands; Barry's favorite is still the note from an Englishwoman who'd read one of his columns in The Columbus (Ohio) Dispatch, and fired off this: ''I would like to know just why you should suggest it to be a good idea for the 'explosion of Barry Manilow's head'? Constructive criticism is one thing, but you're sick.''</p>
        <p>In 1986, The Washington Post and The Los Angeles Times came calling. Barry is no deal-maker, and, confronted with a path directly into the white burn of fame, he recoiled. The Post, he feared, would want to rein him into the tight political world that lies within the Beltway, and the Times signified the land of sushi, the very mention of which brings to his face the cast of a fish's underbelly. Following his tropism toward the unchic, Barry decided not only to stay with The Herald, but also to move to Florida.</p>
        <p>If the move meant a loss in his potential earnings, now squarely in the six-figure range (''Someone told my son at school that I make $100,000 a word - it's not true''), it also provided fertile ground for a man who draws his humor from the weirdness of his species.</p>
        <p>''I shocked and appalled everyone I knew,'' Barry says of his decision. ''But there's a certain outsiderness about Miami. I like living someplace else.''</p>
        <p>It's about as some place else as you can possibly get. His airy, high-ceilinged house sits on two acres hidden away in the middle of South Miami, several square miles of former jungle now subdivided, immaculately relandscaped and barricaded against all the Vice to the north by a moat of malls, most stocked with Range Rovers rooting at the designer yogurt emporiums. It's a step up from Barry's previous neighborhood, which featured a house occupied by the requisite drug dealers. ''At least that's what we all thought,'' he wrote in a recent piece entitled ''Why I Love South Florida,'' ''based on the fact that it was an expensive house occupied by a constantly changing group of highly secretive people with no apparent means of support other than washing their own cars.''</p>
        <p>Barry feels no urge to live amid the vibrant and furious tangle of cultures in the city that lies a dozen miles to the north; for a man who churns out humor by the square yard, isolation is essential, and more soothing than the buttery sun. He does not reread past columns, lest one prove less funny than intended, which he'd find unbearable. So concerned is he with the quality of his work that he limits himself to one per week, where tradition calls for more; Russell Baker, the contemporary columnist with whom Barry feels the most affinity, does two.</p>
        <p>Each morning, seven days a week, Barry pads out across the sun-dappled backyard to his garage, pausing occasionally to flip a Frisbee at Earnest, his large, main dog, and Zippy, ''our small emergency back-up dog,'' before attacking the word processor with all the diligence of a man laying a brick wall.</p>
        <p>''People think it takes 10 minutes to write them - it doesn't,'' Barry says. He is picking at an acoustic guitar, one of the principal furnishings of the office. The bookshelves brim with an eclectic mix, from the complete works of Benchley to those of South Florida mystery writers, Edna Buchanan and Carl Hiassen.</p>
        <p>''I usually spend two hours on the first sentence,'' he says. ''That's no exaggeration. Then I finally write the second sentence. Then I rewrite the first. I rewrite each sentence a dozen times. It was never easy for me to write.</p>
        <p>''The writing is very important to me. Writing columns is very important to me. I can't imagine doing anything else. It pays well, it's fun and I feel it validates me. So far it seems like the best job I could possibly have.''</p>
        <p>A job? Spending most of your life in the back row of your eighth-grade biology class giggling like a madman - and being paid for it? Spending your workday weighing the literary merits of ''duck spit'' versus ''weasel spit''?</p>
        <p>''Hey,'' he says, ''I agonize over that stuff: 'What would Proust do?' ''</p>
        <p>The selection of his weekly fodder is the easy part. If the detritus of daily life isn't inspiration enough - from the troglodyte mechanic who crashed his car to the loyal readers who keep him apprised from as far away as New Zealand of recent happenings on the exploding animal front (thus far: cows, bison, flounder, snails, whales and a finch) - a glance at the morning's paper usually does the trick.</p>
        <p>''Sure, I get furious about politics,'' Barry says. ''To write funny stuff you have to be outraged. When Bush did his flag thing it infuriated me that we had a man so silly being the President of the United States, and people were buying it. But I'm not going to write that - I use that anger to make jokes. Beth thinks I'm intensely hostile. I think she's right. If I weren't a humor columnist I'd have ulcers. Because I really do get angry.''</p>
        <p>To temper the outrage, he overlays it with lunacy - ''President Bush, reversing a major campaign pledge, has announced that he is appointing convicted rapist Willie Horton to be Secretary of the Treasury.'' When the politics he addresses are of the sexual kind, Barry is likely to deflate both sides, calling on the borderline-cretin persona that lies somewhere in the back of all our brains, but a lot closer to the front in his - the voice that recently wrote, ''Do you women think that all men are just animals? Do you really think that all they want to do is get you into bed? Wrong! A lot of guys, especially in bars, would be happy to get you into a phone booth! Or right there on the bar! ('Nobody will notice us,' the guy will say, being suave.</p>
        <p>'They're watching Wheel of Fortune.')''</p>
        <p>''It's part me adopting that person, and it's part me,'' Barry says. ''I very rarely go out in my normal life making sophomoric jokes. I hate to think I'd be trusted with a driver's license if I had the personality of the person doing that column. I try to make it clear that this column doesn't want to be taken seriously. It doesn't want you to take seriously the concept of newspapers being sacrosanct repositories of important opinion.'' At the 1988 Democratic Convention in Atlanta, Barry and two friends showed up in an area designated for protests, wearing boxes over their heads. Within minutes, camera crews descended. ''We're people with boxes on our heads,'' Barry said. The next day, he wrote a column about it. The day after that, angry reporters demanded to know why he'd staged a ''hoax.'' It wasn't a hoax, he explained. We didn't lie. We told you who we were: people with boxes on our heads.</p>
        <p>The fear of taking himself too seriously lies behind Barry's urge to avoid the public; so, too, does an innate shyness. Unlike other successful columnists - Lewis Grizzard, for example - he rarely goes on the lecture circuit. When he does stray into public, he is likely to throw out an instant force field of one-liners.</p>
        <p>''I use humor partly as a defense, a way to keep people from getting too close,'' Barry says. ''If I walk into a room and everyone knows I'm Dave Barry, which is what happens now a lot, then I'll be Dave Barry for them, because it's a very easy way to relate.''</p>
        <p>For the most part, he stays close to home, strumming his guitar and listening to the Beatles or the Beach Boys (''I don't get rap music - I'm a white guy who lives a suburban life''). For a parade in Miami last year, he and Weingarten formed the Chickenfoot Blues Band, playing in the back of a pick-up truck that drew a crowd of admirers - until they realized that the souvenirs that Dave was tossing out of the bed of the truck were real chicken feet.</p>
        <p>He will, however, unfailingly accept charity appearances, as well as invitations to read in public in his home city. At one such local gathering last fall, after reading an excerpt from ''Dave Barry Turns 40'' about liposuction, Barry uncharacteristically requested that the book-signing be kept short: ''If you could do me that favor,'' he said to the audience. ''I don't want to bum anyone, but my wife's in the hospital, and I'd like to get over there.''</p>
        <p>In fact, doctors had removed lymph nodes from under Beth Barry's arm that same morning, prompting several people to observe that it was nothing short of astounding for Barry to have shown up at all. ''We're in the Life-Goes-On stage,'' Barry explained. It's a stage with which he has grown distressingly familiar. Six years ago, his father died of heart disease. Barry's subsequent column on his mother's grieving, one of only a handful of serious columns he's written in eight years, was one of his Pulitzer-winning entries.</p>
        <p>Then, in 1987, his mother took her own life with an overdose of prescription drugs and alcohol. It had not been entirely unforeseen; each year after her husband's death she would note the date on the calendar, and write, ''Come back, Dave.''</p>
        <p>Within 48 hours of his mother's death, Barry submitted a fresh column. It was about his son's gerbils.</p>
        <p>''It was hilarious,'' Weingarten said. ''I said, 'How can you be so funny?' But a few years ago I'd asked Dave to define a sense of humor, for a special issue, and I remember he called in two sentences: 'Sense of humor is a measurement of the extent to which you realize you are trapped in a world almost totally devoid of reason. Laughter is how you release the anxiety you feel about this.' ''</p>
        <p>''My mom wasn't a particularly happy person, but I really felt she did the right thing for her,'' Barry says. ''I don't want to sound brutal or cruel, but her whole life my mother said she viewed suicide as a legitimate option. She just couldn't handle life without my father.''</p>
        <p>He is behind the wheel of his van, a silver-and-blue zeppelin with a chrome ladder on the back and wooden trim inside. He is navigating a shortcut to the mall.</p>
        <p>It is suggested that all of the classic ingredients for comedy are here - the underpinnings of tragedy, the Tears of a Clown.</p>
        <p>''No, I'm not like that,'' he says, after a moment's thought. ''I think humor is a fundamental part of your psyche, not an add-on out of nowhere. If you looked beneath my happy surface, you'd find a happy person most of the time. I sort of lucked out on the happiness quotient. I'm just naturally not a worrier. I had a normal upbringing. Yeah, my mother was unhappy . . . but I'm basically amused by the world.'' Even while his wife is undergoing chemotherapy?  ''Yeah,'' he laughs, but only with his mouth: ''Your lymph system was fine, so now we're going to drip poison into your veins for six months. . . .''</p>
        <p>We drive silently for a few minutes past exotic and wonderful foliage. Suddenly, we're on a back road whose flora is original, and wild; we're in the Florida of 50 years ago. It is as if we've slipped into a warp, out of the familiar. Here, Dave Barry is not a maelstrom of one-liners.</p>
        <p>''We're only on the cusp of suffering,'' he says. ''Imagine your wife getting cancer and not beating it. Imagine losing your kid.'' Silence. Then he says, ''I could not go on.''</p>
        <p>He pauses again, and steers the van away from the past, toward one of the ubiquitous malls. He smiles.</p>
        <p>''But I don't feel I'm hiding a terrible, dark secret,'' he says, ''and one day I'll kill myself and everyone will say, 'Gee . . .' ''</p>
        <p>''More likely, they'll say, 'Ha, ha!' ''</p>
        <p>In fact, his future appears to hold no surprises. The more the star-making machinery crowds in on him, the more he wants to be left alone. He steadfastly refuses even to consider writing for television or the movies; he admits to no ambition beyond what he has already achieved. His idea of a perfect future is to keep turning out the column for another 40 years, only maybe in Iowa, or somewhere without telephones.</p>
        <p>''I don't want more money,'' he says, browsing a toy counter. ''If I were into marketing, I could make a lot. But what would we spend it on?'' What, then, does he want, that he doesn't already have? ''I just want more normalness,'' he says. ''I just want more time.''</p>
        <p>He finds a toy train set on sale - the perfect gift for his only child, Robby, age 9. He puts it on the counter, and, with a nod at the sales tag, asks the saleswoman if that's the retail price or the discounted price. ''I'm afraid that's the sale price,'' she says. ''That's O.K.,'' Dave Barry says, reaching for his wallet. ''I make $100,000 a word.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
