<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Neediest Cases; Support for Foster Mother In a Round-the-Clock Role</title>
    <meta content="24NEED" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1354063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donovan, Aaron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Evina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E7D71731F937A15751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Neediest Cases; Support for Foster Mother In a Round-the-Clock Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AARON DONOVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Donovan, Aaron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, charity supported by New York Times Neediest Cases Fund, provides help for Evina Lewis, who is caring for six-year-old girl with severe disabilities; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a typical afternoon in the Lewis family's town house in East Flatbush, Brooklyn. Six-year-old Elizabeth sits in her wheelchair, eyes darting back and forth as if she could see. Her arms and legs jerk spastically, clearly not under her control. Her brain is able to hear what people say but not comprehend it.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth is blind and has a severe form of cerebral palsy, and nobody interviewed would say what her life expectancy was. Because she cannot swallow, she is fed formula by her foster mother through a tube attached to her stomach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is a typical afternoon in the Lewis family's town house in East Flatbush, Brooklyn. Six-year-old Elizabeth sits in her wheelchair, eyes darting back and forth as if she could see. Her arms and legs jerk spastically, clearly not under her control. Her brain is able to hear what people say but not comprehend it.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth is blind and has a severe form of cerebral palsy, and nobody interviewed would say what her life expectancy was. Because she cannot swallow, she is fed formula by her foster mother through a tube attached to her stomach.</p>
        <p>''She cannot stand by herself, sit, or do anything by herself,'' said her foster mother, Evina Lewis, 58, a former nursing home aide who now devotes her time to raising Elizabeth and two other children, one a foster child, one adopted.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth arrived at Bronx Lebanon Hospital Center three years ago malnourished and weighing only 13 pounds. She was put into foster care by the city's Administration for Children's Services, which enlisted a small nonprofit agency in Manhattan, New Alternatives for Children, to help find a foster parent for her.</p>
        <p>New Alternatives is a member of the Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, one of the seven local charities supported by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund. Staff members at New Alternatives approached Ms. Lewis, whom they already knew because they had placed another child with her. She later adopted that child, Sarai Jacobs Lewis, now 4, who has spina bifida.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Well, I'm an older woman, she's going to need somebody to play with,' '' Ms. Lewis recalled, speaking of Sarai. ''I told the social worker, if there was a child available I would take that child to give her company.''</p>
        <p>At first, Ms. Lewis was a little reluctant to take on the challenge of caring for another medically fragile child. When she first took Elizabeth, ''it was a temporary situation,'' Ms. Lewis said. She has grown to love caring for Elizabeth, but it is nonetheless a round-the-clock job. ''She cannot tell you she's hungry, she cannot tell you something's hurting her,'' Ms. Lewis said.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth cannot control her arm and leg movements, and her limbs would occasionally become tangled in the vertical metal bars of her crib and she would bruise herself, Ms. Lewis said. So Ms. Lewis asked for help in getting bumpers that would prevent Elizabeth from sticking her arms through the bars.</p>
        <p>New Alternatives paid for the guards with $90 from the Neediest Cases Fund. Since they were installed in July, Elizabeth has been sleeping more soundly, Ms. Lewis said.</p>
        <p>New Alternatives, which would not provide Elizabeth's last name because of foster-care privacy regulations, intends to tap into the Neediest Cases Fund again soon. It will use the money to assist Ms. Lewis and her sister, Martina Sylvester, 63, who lives with her and helps take care of the children.</p>
        <p>Every time Elizabeth leaves the house, the two women, both widows, must carry Elizabeth and her wheelchair down and back up the 10 steps that lead to their front door. But it is difficult for them. Stephanie Knox, the social worker who works with them, said that early next year the agency would provide an electronic wheelchair lift for the house. The lift, which will cost $4,940, will be paid for with money from the fund.</p>
        <p>She said the agency was lucky to have found Ms. Lewis, who said she so enjoys helping people with disabilities that when she was growing up in Grenada she used to walk a blind man home every day after school. ''Evina is very thoughtful in the way she cares for the kids,'' Ms. Knox said. ''She's really focused on their futures and wants to make plans for them.''</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to P.O. Box 5193, General Post Office, New York, N.Y. 10087, or any of these organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE  285 Schermerhorn Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK  1011 First Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS  191 Joralemon Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES  281 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK*  FDR Station  P.O. Box 5314  New York, N.Y. 10150</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>Donations may be made with a credit card by phone at (212) 556-5851 (ext. 7) or online, courtesy of CharityWave.com, an internet donations service, at www.nytimesneediest.charitywave.com. For instructions on how to donate stock to the fund, call (212) 556-1137 or fax (212) 556-4450.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on Federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
        <p>Previously recorded: $4,574,989.59  Recorded Thursday: 419,830.46</p>
        <p>Total: $4,994,820.05  At similar period last year: $6,560,838.28</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
