<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Florida Bank Merger May Ruffle Customers</title>
    <meta content="07FLOR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="SPENDING IT" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="955820"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="SPENDING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Carolina</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barnett Banks of Florida Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nationsbank</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">First Union Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morrow, David J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DA1030F934A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Florida Bank Merger May Ruffle Customers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID J. MORROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morrow, David J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nationsbank's planned acquisition of Barnett Banks, biggest banking company in Florida, has been unsettling for some customers of its 629 statewide branches; has caused concern among huge number of state's elderly residents who shun ATM machines in favor of teller services; consumer groups are worried that merger will raise banking fees to new highs; are particularly alarmed that two banks--Nationsbank and First Union, both based in North Carolina--will control about half of Florida market (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MERGERS like Nationsbank's planned acquisition of Barnett Banks, the biggest banking company in Florida, are nothing new for Manu Patel. When completed, the $15.5 billion deal, one of the biggest yet on Wall Street, will mark the fifth time since 1979 that his bank account has changed hands through a buyout or a merger.</p>
        <p>Bank buyouts in Florida have been so frequent that Mr. Patel, 56, an accountant in Lakeland, cannot remember all the banks' names anymore, though he knows the directions to the branches he once visited.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MERGERS like Nationsbank's planned acquisition of Barnett Banks, the biggest banking company in Florida, are nothing new for Manu Patel. When completed, the $15.5 billion deal, one of the biggest yet on Wall Street, will mark the fifth time since 1979 that his bank account has changed hands through a buyout or a merger.</p>
        <p>Bank buyouts in Florida have been so frequent that Mr. Patel, 56, an accountant in Lakeland, cannot remember all the banks' names anymore, though he knows the directions to the branches he once visited.</p>
        <p>''I can remember 10 years ago when there was a lot of competition,'' he said. ''They'd say, 'Come on over and we'll give you a television or an alarm clock.' ''</p>
        <p>The pending acquisition of Barnett has been unsettling for some customers of its 629 branches in Florida. And because this state has huge numbers of elderly residents,  the deal may prompt special concern: Many older customers shy away, for instance, from A.T.M.'s, preferring teller services. But in the interest of cutting costs, merging banks tend to move away from teller services and to stress technological advances like computerized banking or A.T.M.'s on virtually every corner. Merging banks also tend to close branches, which means more inconvenience for the elderly, who may find it hard to travel to another bank's branch.</p>
        <p>Consumer groups are concerned that the merger will raise banking fees to new highs.  They are particularly alarmed that two banks -- Nationsbank and First Union, both based in North Carolina -- will control about half the Florida market.</p>
        <p>''Usually, bigger means better for consumers,'' said Mark Ferrulo, executive director of the Florida Public Interest Research Group, a consumer rights organization based in Tallahassee. ''But in banking it means a raw deal. The banks don't pass on their savings to consumers. This lack of competition here is going to be a serious problem.''</p>
        <p>Barnett customers may not feel any pain immediately. A Nationsbank spokesman  said the company had yet to decide about  branch closings. And, after raising its banking fees in July, Nationsbank recently froze all service charges through August 1998.</p>
        <p>But banking analysts expect Nationsbank to close some Barnett branches and to raise some fees. While both banks already have some of the highest fees in Florida -- Barnett levies a $29.50 charge for every bounced check -- Nationsbank has become especially aggressive about fee revenue.</p>
        <p>Along with First Union, Nationsbank is one of the few banks in the country to charge for deposit and withdrawal slips inside  branches. Call Nationsbank's automated computer too many times to check your balance, and you could be charged 50 cents a call. Customers who call the bank's operator more than once may be charged $2, then placed on hold; low-profit accounts go to a separate operator.</p>
        <p>''What we're seeing in Florida is a three-fold strategy by the big banks,'' Mr. Ferrulo said. ''They are increasing fees, making it harder to avoid existing fees and then after all that, they're inventing new fees. There's no way fees are going to go down in a merger.''</p>
        <p>While rising fees and closing branches could hurt the banks' elderly customers, wealthy account holders could gain from the merger. Nationsbank's recent deal to acquire Montgomery Securities should give Barnett's customers easier access to the market and to their investments. ''There's usually a silver lining to these takeovers,'' said William Gregor, a senior vice president at Gemini Consulting, a management consulting firm in Morristown, N.J. ''The merger will allow Barnett's customers to be exposed to new products and services.''</p>
        <p>Consumer groups offer some options for Barnett's customers. Instead of paying higher fees, Mr. Ferrulo said, they can move their accounts to local banks or credit unions, which usually offer most of their services free. One drawback is that credit unions usually have only one A.T.M. machine, while big banks like Nationsbank have networks of thousands.</p>
        <p>Other people in the banking industry say that staying put may be best, at least for a while. ''It's not a bad idea in any merger to keep your account where it is until you see what happens,'' said Michael Auriemma, managing director of the Auriemma Consulting Group, a banking consulting company in Westbury, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Consumer advocates also suggest that customers check their statements closely, because mergers tend to produce computer mistakes. Customers should also ask questions of tellers, since visits inside both Barnett and Nationsbank branches are free.</p>
        <p>And if a fee seems too high, complain, Mr. Ferrulo says.</p>
        <p>SPENDING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
