<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home, in Sometimes Odd Poses</title>
    <meta content="7ART.$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="ART" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="955690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Griswold, Florence, Museum (Old Lyme, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DC1230F934A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home, in Sometimes Odd Poses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews exhibition of works by American impressionists, with home as theme, at Florence Griswold Museum, Old Lyme, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AN exhibition with home in its title has a head start. Home -- as in ''home cooking,'' say -- signals comfort and viewers are automatically prepared to like it. At the Florence Griswold Museum in Old Lyme, ''Visions of Home: American Impressionist Images of Suburban Leisure and Country Comfort,'' running through Sept. 28, has this advantage.</p>
        <p>The 35 paintings all have a house or other dwelling in them somewhere. But early on, the theme, for all of its pleasantness, shows itself as also elementary. Despite a thick well-annotated catalogue with several scholarly essays, the show becomes inflated and vague. For instance, the show's press release says that these painters were ''emphasizing the view of the house and grounds as private refuge, a place where the American dream is realized.'' There is no traction here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AN exhibition with home in its title has a head start. Home -- as in ''home cooking,'' say -- signals comfort and viewers are automatically prepared to like it. At the Florence Griswold Museum in Old Lyme, ''Visions of Home: American Impressionist Images of Suburban Leisure and Country Comfort,'' running through Sept. 28, has this advantage.</p>
        <p>The 35 paintings all have a house or other dwelling in them somewhere. But early on, the theme, for all of its pleasantness, shows itself as also elementary. Despite a thick well-annotated catalogue with several scholarly essays, the show becomes inflated and vague. For instance, the show's press release says that these painters were ''emphasizing the view of the house and grounds as private refuge, a place where the American dream is realized.'' There is no traction here.</p>
        <p>Many of the works are landscapes with incidental houses, and it is vaguely annoying that a large number are really garden paintings going under another name. Phalanxes of flowers are the bread and butter of  Impressionism, so one can't blame the artists for having indulged in them, but too often they are in the way of the stated issue, domestic life</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, several paintings here stick. Some look the show's theme in the face and depict activity (or inactivity) on the front porch. Robert Blum's ''Two Idlers,'' dated 1888-1889, is done in a kind of hard-edge Impressionism that verges on academic realism and has an aura of decadence associated with the French artist James Tissot whose work has been described as having ''chocolate box charm.'' Under the surface of the Blum painting centering on a too-well-dressed man in a wicker chair next to a woman in a hammock is a lot of psychological tension. The man seems to be saying something to his companion; she faces him but she's asleep.</p>
        <p>Two female companions are featured in Frank W. Benson's ''Afternoon in September'' (1913). Side by side, reading and sewing are two women, identified as the artist's daughters. The interest lies in the rendering of the figures, not dissolved in light as would be expected, but rather, in their white dresses,  tangible visions of purity. This painting has a relative in John Henry Twachtman's ''On the Terrace'' of 1897. His vision in white is his wife, with three of his five children. Twachtman has put this tight group of figures off to the side to balance a garden thick with bloom. The exhibition's curator, Lisa N. Peters, writes  that the garden makes ''a transitional zone between the domestic sphere and the landscape at large.'' This is a potentially dramatic concept but the Impressionist style is not suited to conveying it. Rather what is compelling about the painting is that it seems so ungraspable, so thoroughly spectral.</p>
        <p>Several houses do stand out as crucial to their paintings. Part of the appeal of William Merritt Chase's ''Chase Homestead, Shinnecock,'' painted around 1892 is Chase's role in the history of American painting. He was an influential teacher and an arbiter of art and culture who held salons in his studio on 10th Street in Manhattan. His importance is reflected in the elaborate shingle style house designed by Stanford White at Shinnecock, L.I., a landscape consisting mostly of barren sand dunes. The dwelling in this stark but light-infused environment acts as a beacon of refinement.</p>
        <p>Twachtman also availed himself of Stanford White, who added a portico with columns to his house in Greenwich. In ''My House,'' which Twachtman painted around 1899, the porch is seen from the side and echoes a Greek temple. Rather than dominating its surroundings,  Twachtman's house is a source of illumination, both literally and metaphorically, at the center of the painting. This portico has a rival for grandest edifice in the exhibition.</p>
        <p>Sometime in the second two decades of this century Charles W. Hawthorne depicted the entrance and bell tower of Laurelton Hall, Louis Comfort Tiffany's house at Oyster Bay, L.I. With its intense color this painting stands out from Impressionism's general effect of indistinctness. Ms. Peters remarks that ''Hawthorne brought out the color harmonies that Tiffany achieved in his stained glass.'' Viewers might also wonder whether Hawthorne had digested the advanced art of his time and was influenced by Matisse's bold and direct use of color.</p>
        <p>On what looks like the other side of the tracks, if only because of white laundry flapping on the line, J. Alden Weir does a couple of interesting turns on the show's theme in ''The Laundry, Branchville,'' painted around 1894. Rather than present women in white as do Twachtman and Benson, he provides more mysterious evidence of their presence. He also adopts an unusual vertical format. The painting is two-thirds lawn; the red house on what becomes the horizon line is the sought-after place of repose, a goal to be achieved.</p>
        <p>Most of the paintings are set in spring or summer. Autumn has always been a symbol of decline, but 19th-century painters fully exploited this metaphor, having autumn stand at the end of the wilderness or Eden. Daniel Garber in a 1925 painting, a late date for this show, depicts not only autumn scenery with trees in the foreground denuded, but also a decaying stone building.</p>
        <p>The exhibition winds up in an urban setting with, ''Winter Landscape, Washington Bridge'' by Ernest Lawson, whose forte was winter in the upper reaches of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
