<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fashion's Nobility Bowed to Her</title>
    <meta content="07FASH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="53" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="VIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="955841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diana, Princess of Wales</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E3D91030F934A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="1268" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fashion's Nobility Bowed to Her</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY M. SPINDLER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gianni Versace was one of few designers recognized as style setters who had chance to dress Princess Diana; earlier on, Diana tried to play by rules of aristocracy, wearing only British designs and hats</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SAM McKNIGHT was styling Naomi Campbell's hair for Gianni Versace's fall 1991 couture photographs when the Princess of Wales gave him a call on the set.</p>
        <p>Ms. Campbell was modeling a baby blue dress of stretch fabric with gold studs up the side just as Diana told Mr. McKnight, her hairdresser at the time, that she was interested in Versace couture.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SAM McKNIGHT was styling Naomi Campbell's hair for Gianni Versace's fall 1991 couture photographs when the Princess of Wales gave him a call on the set.</p>
        <p>Ms. Campbell was modeling a baby blue dress of stretch fabric with gold studs up the side just as Diana told Mr. McKnight, her hairdresser at the time, that she was interested in Versace couture.</p>
        <p>''I was so excited that after the dress was photographed, I said, 'Send it to the Princess!' '' said Donatella Versace, Mr. Versace's sister, who is the creative director for the house. ''Gianni said, 'To a princess you sent that dress with golden studs? She's never going to wear it!' He couldn't believe I sent her that dress.''</p>
        <p>But Diana was photographed in it for Harper's Bazaar and ordered six or seven more of the same, in pastel colors. ''It became the Diana dress,'' Ms. Versace recalled Wednesday. ''The dress was beautiful, but she was the one who made the dress.''</p>
        <p>There are two kinds of fashion icons: the ones designers take cues from, and the ones designers want to dress because the world takes cues from them. Not many designers would say the Princess of Wales was an inspiration for their runway clothes.</p>
        <p>But far from the manipulative trends that designers show each season, they often concocted something with her in mind, just in case. Those who had wanted to dress Diana in recent years learned what that entailed: a column dress for evening, decolletage, lots of leg. For day, a style typified by the sportswear of Yves Saint Laurent and Ralph Lauren: starched white shirt, slim trousers and boxy jacket.</p>
        <p>Dressing Diana meant a designer could overcome his own obvious signatures, and enter another, time-honored realm: that of a couturier bending to the will, and needs, of a client. In her case, the most important client of contemporary times.</p>
        <p>Not that many had the chance. Among the designers recognized as style setters today -- those who dress the Hollywood celebrities Diana seemed to have modeled herself after -- Mr. Versace was one of the few who had the honor.</p>
        <p>After the death of any famous figure, shorthand for his accomplishments sets in. The shorthand for Diana's contribution to fashion has been that she saved British designers from obscurity.</p>
        <p>It says much about the British class system that there isn't much truth in that statement.</p>
        <p>The British fashion renaissance that has seen John Galliano taking over at Christian Dior, Alexander McQueen at Givenchy and Stella McCartney at Chloe was not due, surprisingly, to Diana's support. Their clothes got attention for being precisely what the Princess's could not be: intentionally controversial. Mr. McQueen, for example, made his reputation with so-called bumster trousers, which don't cover the rear.</p>
        <p>It wasn't until Mr. Galliano, long celebrated as the most important British designer of his generation, took over at Dior late last year that he designed a gown for Diana, the first dress from the Dior ateliers under his direction.</p>
        <p>Reined in by the restrictions of her class, she influenced fashion mostly in subtle ways -- with her tousled haircut or an accessory like choker necklaces or the Lady Dior handbag.  By the time she could break from convention (and thus set trends), she had lost interest in experimenting with fashion.</p>
        <p>''There's an extraordinary expression from the 1960's, which is 'occasion dressing,' '' said Annette Worsley-Taylor, who founded the London runway shows in the 1970's and is now a director of the British Fashion Council. ''Every day of her life was an occasion when she was wearing British fashion. Those occasions have their own rules. The cutting-edge designers aren't occasion-bound.''</p>
        <p>The occasion-bound designers she favored as the wife of Prince Charles were Catherine Walker, Bruce Oldfield, Victor Edelstein and Jasper Conran, none of whom have leaped from the platform provided by Diana into international businesses that become household names. They are a bit too stuffy for the hyped media coverage that creates global acclaim. What Diana did for these more sedate designers was to create an environment in which British society could eschew French couturiers and shop at home instead.</p>
        <p>A T a time when she was literally casting away fashion as undermining her charitable image by auctioning her wardrobe at Christie's, Diana had found a look. Like so many things about her that women everywhere identified with, her struggle through the morass of styles in her 16 years of public life had led to an image all her own.</p>
        <p>''In lots of ways, Diana's clothes told the story of her life,'' said Hamish Bowles, the European editor for Vogue magazine. ''In recent years, there appeared to be that realization that what mattered was the person inside the clothes, and so the clothes became low-key foils to what her public really wanted, which was Diana herself.''</p>
        <p>Early on, ''Shy Di,'' a broad-brimmed hat hiding the cropped hair so copied by British women, was often criticized as a fashion victim. But there are many kinds of fashion victims. Some embrace grotesque trends to reinvent themselves. Women find those victims, in their trendy clothes, threatening and unsympathetic. Diana, struggling in the public eye, was a fashion victim who appealed, a victim only because she was trying to play by the rules of aristocracy. It was when she broke them that she began to look chic, sexy and worldly.</p>
        <p>''Initially, when as Lady Diana Spencer she made her first forays into public life that required the kind of formal clothes she hadn't worn before, it was her mother who was choosing them for her,'' Mr. Bowles said. ''Her mother's milliner, her mother's dressmaker. You had this sense of a 19-year-old woman dressing in a way that cross-referenced her own mother's 50's debutante youth.''</p>
        <p>''And there was no question of her being able to appear in public without a hat,'' he added. ''It's not as though she was sweetly obliging her new in-laws. It just wasn't an issue. Those are the requirements of, even, I would say, upper-middle-class formal dressing at that point.''</p>
        <p>The rules had not changed by the time Diana doffed her hats as much as Diana herself had changed. She initially consulted the editors of British Vogue, who guided her toward what were considered appropriate English designers. ''Then, she started getting to know them herself, getting interested and forming her own opinions,'' Ms. Worsley-Taylor said.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, that led to her sartorial declaration of freedom from official demands that she wear only British fashion. She began wearing Versace.</p>
        <p>Even as she tried to rise above her fashion-plate image, she was never able to escape it completely.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Versace's funeral in Milan, an American news magazine called around for reactions to whether it had been appropriate for Diana to wear a somber black dress by Mr. Versace to the service. As if any designer could imagine a better memorial than that.</p>
        <p>VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
