<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For 2 Huskies, It's Not Just Another Hike</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="422288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOG SLEDDING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LLOYD, BARBARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DF1230F932A25751C0A967958260" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For 2 Huskies, It's Not Just Another Hike</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA LLOYD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LLOYD, BARBARA</byline>
      <dateline>HELENA, Mont.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is nothing fancy about Mason and Bosco. They are stringy-looking dogs, not fluffy or pretty. They do not appear strong or excitable but they have been training their entire lives for this moment.</p>
        <p>When they are hitched to the front of a snow country sled, they paw the ground, leap up and down and yip with anticipation. If dogs are born to serve a master, these two huskies have learned to carry their weight in gold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is nothing fancy about Mason and Bosco. They are stringy-looking dogs, not fluffy or pretty. They do not appear strong or excitable but they have been training their entire lives for this moment.</p>
        <p>When they are hitched to the front of a snow country sled, they paw the ground, leap up and down and yip with anticipation. If dogs are born to serve a master, these two huskies have learned to carry their weight in gold.</p>
        <p>Mason and Bosco are lead dogs on one team in the Race to the Sky, a six-day competition that wends its way through 500 miles of Montana wilderness and 7,000-foot elevations. Twenty-five teams set out from here Saturday, with 11 sleds -- including Mason's and Bosco's -- taking the long-distance route. The others follow a 250-mile course.</p>
        <p>A lack of snow downtown, where the race was to begin, prompted organizers to stage a ceremonial start on city pavement. The teams then loaded their dogs in trucks and carted them off to a mountain site 12 outside town.</p>
        <p>It is Mason's and Bosco's jobs to listen and react to the commands of their musher, Laurie Beckstrom of Kalispell, Mont. Behind them are 14 other dogs, all Alaskan huskies, trained to pull a driver and a loaded 230-pound sled up hills, around corners, under low-lying branches, and through the dead of night. As of noon yesterday, Beckstrom was in second place, having passed the second checkpoint 145 miles into the race.</p>
        <p>Mason and Bosco, harnessed together, are trained to turn right when Beckstrom yells, "Gee," and left when she says, "Haw." The word they have come to relish is "hike," meaning get moving.</p>
        <p>Lead dogs are born not made. Unlike other puppies who roll over or pull back on their haunches when their first leashes are attached, Mason and Bosco forge ahead with their master in tow.</p>
        <p>"There is a definite physical change when they start moving," the 38-year-old Beckstrom said in an interview last week. "Their heads go down, their ears go back, and their tails drop. You can see them leaning forward."</p>
        <p>A photo of Mason, a brown husky with very dark markings around his eyes and nose, is encased in a frame in Beckstrom's living room. Beckstrom's favorite, Mason weighs 45 pounds and has never been dropped in the 16 competitions (including 4 previous appearances in the Race to the Sky) he has entered. That record is meaningful, since dropping a dog requires a musher to load the stricken animal on the sled until it can be replaced with another dog at the next checkpoint.</p>
        <p>"Mason wants to please," Beckstrom said. "He acts as if he really cares whether or not he does a good job. He and I work well together."</p>
        <p>Bosco, 6 years old, who weighs 52 pounds, is not as compliant. "He's trying me all the time," Beckstrom said.</p>
        <p>Of course, Mason is not without faults. During spring training last year, he got into a tiff with another dog. "Mason bit his own tongue, and you'd think he had his head cut off," Beckstrom said.</p>
        <p>Behind Bosco and Mason in the sled line is a pair of female huskies. If Bosco and Mason are the team's quarterbacks, then Toggle and Charlie Coal Briquets are offensive linemen. Their jobs are to protect the lead, keep the sled on line and maintain direction.</p>
        <p>"They're not afraid of speed," said Beckstrom, referring to the 21 miles an hour she has reached going downhill. "They won't hold back."</p>
        <p>The wheel dogs, who are positioned directly in front of the sled far behind the lead dogs, are the blocking backs for the sled and the musher. The wheel dogs' jobs are to manuever the sled along the best route and keep it from skidding around trees or at intersections. Ross, who is named after Beckstrom's pastor, and Coyote, who looks like a wild animal, are her wheelers.</p>
        <p>In the middle are a group of 10 huskies. Two of them, Jackson and Josh, tend to growl at each other across the dog yard in Kalispell, but then trot together gleefully when they're hitched together. Their ability to keep up pace makes them ideal team players. The black-coated Jackson is competing, despite splayed feet that tend to form cracks between the paws. He wears fleece booties for protection.</p>
        <p>Beckstrom trains the huskies year-round. In the summer, when lowland snows are a dim memory, she hitches an all-terrain vehicle to the dog team and puts the gears in neutral. To prepare for the Race to the Sky, she loads her team of 16 dogs into a pickup truck in November and drives them to trails near Glacier National Park, where snow is abundant. The team spends as much as seven hours on the trail.</p>
        <p>Preparations for the race itself include providing food and supplies for the dogs. Each dog will eat more than two pounds of dry food each day. The team will consume 200 pounds of snacks on the trip and 200 pounds of meat to flavor the drinking water. They enjoy liver pops, concoctions of liver and corn oil, but the treats must be kept in coolers to keep them from freezing. Beckstrom takes along 600 fleece booties to protect the dogs' feet in sub-zero weather, granular snow or ice. She also packs a tube of Super Glue for split toenails.</p>
        <p>Beckstrom is confident this year. She is the only woman to have competed in the Montana race since its inception in 1986. She finished fourth both times she entered, in 1987 and '89; she competes on alternate years with her husband, Jack. This year one other woman, Irene Chilinski, started the race, in the 250-mile competition.</p>
        <p>Still, Beckstrom knows that dogs more than people make the difference in dogsled racing, and eagerness is what she looks for most in all her huskies.</p>
        <p>"You can tell by how they react with the team," she said. "There is a willingness there. They're not afraid of anything or anybody. They're gung-ho from the time we say, 'Hike.' They don't look behind, and they don't look around them."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
