<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Demand for Rentals Rises in Manhattan</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19910818T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="464821"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APARTMENT HOUSES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MANHATTAN (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUECK, THOMAS J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DF163DF937A3575BC0A967958260" item-length="1793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Demand for Rentals Rises in Manhattan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LUECK, THOMAS J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR Matthew Auerbach, a comedy writer, freelance rock critic and Manhattan renter, the real estate slump could be worse. Later this month, he will bid adieu to a quintessentially New York home, a fifth floor walk-up railroad flat on York Avenue in the 80's that he calls "the North Pole."</p>
        <p>He is moving downtown and up scale, joining thousands of New Yorkers who have seized upon the depressed market to seek the best deals they can find in rental housing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR Matthew Auerbach, a comedy writer, freelance rock critic and Manhattan renter, the real estate slump could be worse. Later this month, he will bid adieu to a quintessentially New York home, a fifth floor walk-up railroad flat on York Avenue in the 80's that he calls "the North Pole."</p>
        <p>He is moving downtown and up scale, joining thousands of New Yorkers who have seized upon the depressed market to seek the best deals they can find in rental housing.</p>
        <p>"I don't run my personal life on the basis of real estate cycles, but hey," Mr. Auerbach said, "this is a good time to move." He has signed the lease on a large, 16th-floor one-bedroom with curved walls, a bay window and keys to the health club at the Corinthian, a sleek condominium tower at 38th and First Avenue.</p>
        <p>"Renters used to be treated like second-class citizens," said John Robertson, the owner of a Manhattan advertising agency who last month rented a large, fully furnished two-bedroom apartment on 66th Street off Park Avenue. "I was wined and dined," he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Auerbach and Mr. Robertson are among a new wave of renters who have entered the New York City market since the first unmistakable signs of a real estate downturn emerged in 1988. Unwilling to buy, they have reinforced New York's position as the nation's preeminent city of renters after the burst of co-op conversion and condominium construction of the 80's created a large new class of homeowners.</p>
        <p>Demand for rentals has grown sharply, but so, too, has the supply, offering renters more options and a more inviting market than at any time since the mid-70's. That is because thousands of co-ops and condominiums have been put on the market as rentals by frustrated developers and owners who are unable to sell them.</p>
        <p>The result, experts say, is a new dynamic in which many more apartments fall outside the city's rent-control and rent-stabilization laws, rates on most of the unregulated apartments have declined, and renters are bargaining hard to lower even more the rents asked by landlords. But demand is robust and rents are rising for some apartments, particularly large ones and those in a handful of fashionable new buildings.</p>
        <p>One truism of New York living remains unshaken -- rent-regulated apartments priced below the market rate still are in intense demand, and are rarely advertised or listed with brokers. As always, these apartments tend to be passed on to people who know the landlord or are already living the building where a vacancy occurs.</p>
        <p>Those looking for the bargain of a lifetime are likely to be disappointed. But because of the real estate slump and uncertainty about the market's near term prospects, executives say many more people, including the affluent, are in the market to rent for a year or two or however long it takes before confidence is restored that values will again begin to rise.</p>
        <p>"THE rental market has zoomed," said Hank Sopher, president of J.I. Sopher and Company, a Manhattan brokerage. Its records show average rentals of 1,200 apartments a month in May, June and July, nearly double the number it rented in the same months in the previous four years.</p>
        <p>"A lot of people who would normally buy are now renting," he added. "They consider a rental a safe haven."</p>
        <p>Experts point to several recent developments that reflect the surge in rentals:</p>
        <p>* At a time when the prices of the city's most expensive co-ops and condominiums have fallen sharply, in some cases more than 30 percent, a small number of expensive new rental buildings are in high demand. The Lucerne, a 45-story rental building at 79th Street and First Avenue, opened in January and all 236 apartments were rented by July.  Rents are lofty, with two bedroom apartments fetching $3,800 to $4,750 a month.</p>
        <p>* Although no precise count is available, the number of co-ops and condominiums now rented or on the market for rent has climbed into the thousands and continues to grow.  Some brokers say less than half their rental listings are now in rental buildings.</p>
        <p>* After a decline of over 10 percent since 1988 on most unregulated Manhattan apartments that are vacated and offered for rent, prices appear to have flattened out or increased slightly this year.</p>
        <p>* Some tenants have negotiated lower rents -- or at least put off increases -- while remaining in their apartments. But in most cases -- almost always in apartments that are rent-controlled or rent stabilized -- tenants in occupancy have agreed to slight rent increases, and only those willing to move have been able to exploit their full negotiating clout to lower asking rents.</p>
        <p>In one measure of how rents have declined on the most expensive Manhattan apartments, The Feathered Nest, a rental agency, has tracked thousands of transactions it has brokered since 1987. The company's inventory of rentals is evenly split among co-ops, condominiums and stabilized units in rental buildings, according to its president, Nancy Packes.</p>
        <p>The analysis, which categorized apartments by neighborhood, size and other factors, found that a studio in an unregulated, doorman building on the Upper West Side would have rented for $1,225 in 1987, but the rent would have fallen to $1,000 by the first half of this year.</p>
        <p>RENTS on one-bedrooms in unregulated Upper East Side buildings without doormen fell less, the study showed, from $1,350 in 1987 to $1,275 this year. Rents on some larger apartments rose. The study showed that a two-bedroom apartment in a unregulated doorman building on the Upper East Side would have rented for $2,950 in 1987, and was up to $3,000 this year.</p>
        <p>The Feathered Nest inventory of current listings also made clear that many apartments in recently completed condominium buildings, which have been slow to sell, are now being offered for rent by their developers. Examples include a one-bedroom, two-bath unit at 3 Lincoln Center, completed in 1990, which is available at $2,180 a month, and a two-bedroom apartment at the Alexandria, a condominium completed this year at 72d Street and Broadway, which can be had for $3,999 a month.</p>
        <p>Some real estate executives maintain that the increased rental activity represents a return to more normal times in a city where renters have always dominated the housing market. They say history may prove the 80's surge of co-op conversion and condominium construction to be an aberration.</p>
        <p>"People were buying apartments because it was a way of going into business -- they were speculating," said Daniel Brodsky, a Manhattan developer, who in May began marketing the Concerto, a new, 35-story, 247-unit rental building at 60th Street and Amsterdam Avenue. So far, he said, 60 percent of the apartments have been leased at rents ranging from $950 a month for the smallest studio to $3,900 a month for a three bedroom apartment.</p>
        <p>"We are going back to a state of normalcy, where New York is a rental town," said Mr. Brodsky, who added that he plans to break ground on another new rental building at 61st Street and West End Avenue next year.</p>
        <p>Other new rental buildings, including some more expensive than the Lucerne or Concerto, have also been attracting tenants, albeit more slowly.</p>
        <p>At One East River Place, which was completed in 1988 at 72d Street and the Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive, 75 percent of 415 apartments have been rented at an average of $42 a square foot a year -- $4,100 to $5,300 a month for two-bedrooms.</p>
        <p>Analysts say the success of the new buildings makes clear that, despite its economic duress, New York is still home to many wealthy people willing to pay a high price for a fashionable address, a sweeping view, marble bathroom fixtures, and perhaps a doorman with that properly authoritative style of calling a cab. The difference now, they say, is that many would prefer to rent.</p>
        <p>"We have a different profile of the renter now," said Jack Heller, a Manhattan developer and president of Heller Equities. "These are high income people who don't want to be required to purchase, and for the first time we have buildings where they can get the amenities they want in a rental."</p>
        <p>Mr. Heller said he, too, is planning at least one new rental building.</p>
        <p>STILL, although the success of the new rental buildings is heartening to some, landlords and apartment owners in other relatively expensive buildings, including rentals, co-ops and condominiums, are struggling to find tenants.</p>
        <p>"The buildings in secondary locations are taking a beating," said Allan Rogers, managing director of Douglas Elliman, a brokerage and management company in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>"We are seeing much more mobility within the market, more tenants moving from building to building," he added. "But people are still nervous about New York and their own positions. They are reluctant to spend the maximum they can for housing."</p>
        <p>One renter with fresh experience in the market is Harvey Kaufman, the comptroller of a women's apparel company who in July rented a large, 45th floor studio for $1100 a month at the Sheffield, a rental building on 57th Street between Eighth and Ninth Avenues. He looked at 20 apartments before signing a lease.</p>
        <p>"This is a renter's market, but not everyone seemed to be facing reality," he said, adding that he had looked at several far less attractive apartments -- including a tiny one room studio without a kitchen -- whose owners were asking over $1,000 a month.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Robertson, the advertising executive, finding a luxurious rental at a price he considers a bargain came as consolation for other another real estate headache. Having purchased a four-bedroom, waterfront home in Stamford, Conn., at the height of the boom in 1986, he now owns what he refers to as the "Stamford turkey."</p>
        <p>When he decided to move into Manhattan this year, Mr. Robertson said he did not even try to sell the Connecticut house after it was appraised at far below what he had paid.  Instead, he has rented it out, fully furnished, and rented his current apartment from a couple who, like himself, have been forced into the role of landlord because of the housing slump.</p>
        <p>Even by Manhattan standards, the East 66th Street apartment is not inexpensive -- his rent is $2,800 a month. Still, he estimated that the rent is $2,000 a month less than he would have had to pay for a comparable furnished Manhattan apartment in the mid-80's.</p>
        <p>And for Mr. Auerbach, the comedy writer, the move to the Corinthian condominium, which he is renting from the apartment's owner, will mean higher rent checks. Currently paying $850 a month for his York Avenue walkup, his new rent is $1,600.</p>
        <p>Still, he said, he will pay less than he expected for what he is getting. "This is a big step up from York Avenue," he said. "As a renter, I've found New York a very friendly place."</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 18, 1991, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Aug. 4 with an article about Manhattan rentals misidentified the building shown. It is the Concerto, at 60th Street and Amsterdam Avenue, not the Lucerne.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 18, 1991, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Aug. 4 with an article about Manhattan rentals misidentified the building shown. It is the Concerto, at 60th Street and Amsterdam Avenue, not the Lucerne.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
