<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Autograph for Child? Say It Ain't So, L. T.</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="464907"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOGRAPHS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TAYLOR, LAWRENCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAMSEY, WES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D9153CF937A3575BC0A967958260" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Autograph for Child? Say It Ain't So, L. T.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wes Ramsey, a 9-year-old from Jonesboro, Ga., a suburb of Atlanta, wanted an autographed photo of his favorite football player, Lawrence Taylor. So he had his grandmother write to the Giants linebacker and request one.</p>
        <p>Wes Ramsey never got the photo. What he got instead was bitter disappointment and an introduction to the often impersonal nature of the autograph business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wes Ramsey, a 9-year-old from Jonesboro, Ga., a suburb of Atlanta, wanted an autographed photo of his favorite football player, Lawrence Taylor. So he had his grandmother write to the Giants linebacker and request one.</p>
        <p>Wes Ramsey never got the photo. What he got instead was bitter disappointment and an introduction to the often impersonal nature of the autograph business.</p>
        <p>It all started back in December when Wes's grandmother, Patricia Ramsey, sent a letter and a Christmas photo of Wes -- dressed in Giants helmet and jersey, bearing Taylor's No. 56 -- to Taylor in care of the team, requesting an autographed photo. From December to April there was no word.</p>
        <p>"I called my grandmother every day to see if she had gotten anything," Wes said. "She never did."</p>
        <p>In April, Patricia Ramsey wrote directly to the Giants about the possibility of getting an autographed photo of Taylor. The team responded in June with a form letter that said that her best chance of getting an autographed photo was to contact Steiner Associates, a Manhattan company that operates a fan club for Taylor and four other Giants players.</p>
        <p>A brochure included in the letter said that the cost for joining the Lawrence Taylor fan club was $25 and that autographed photos went for $18, jerseys were $175 each, an autographed football $110 and a helmet $300.</p>
        <p>Patricia Ramsey was incensed.</p>
        <p>"It got all over me," she said. "We've been football fans for a long time and I've never seen the likes of this. It broke Wes's heart."</p>
        <p>The year before, she wrote a similar letter to John Elway, the Broncos' quarterback, for Wes's older brother, Russell. Denver promptly sent an autographed photo of Elway, which Russell displays on the dresser in his bedroom.</p>
        <p>Karen Ramsey, Wes's mother, said her son couldn't understand why his brother had received a free autographed photo of Elway and why he was expected to pay for a photo of Taylor. She said she thought that her son had been victimized by the increasingly booming business of autographed collectibles.</p>
        <p>"Wes was after something that was preprinted," she said. "He just wanted something he could put in his room, like his brother. He wasn't interested in getting something that he could sell."</p>
        <p>Wes said that despite the fact that he hadn't received an autographed photo, Taylor was still his favorite football player.</p>
        <p>Brandon Steiner, owner of Steiner Associates, said his company started to pick up Taylor's fan mail from the Giants in April, about the time that Patricia Ramsey wrote her second letter to the Giants. He said that his workers had gone through over 2,500 pieces of fan mail for Taylor since then. He said athletes who receive loads of mail often seek out companies to read and answer their mail, because the players don't have the time to do it themselves and feel guilty about letting it pile up.</p>
        <p>"We read all the letters," Steiner said. "We categorize them for the players. And we send out free autographs to the people who warrant them. We fulfill a lot of people's fantasies."</p>
        <p>So what about kids like Wes Ramsey, who can't pop for $25 to join a fan club, then spring for another $18 for an autographed photo?</p>
        <p>"If we got a letter from a kid stating his position, we would send him something for free," Steiner said.</p>
        <p>Steiner acknowledged that his company was not all kids' stuff.</p>
        <p>"A lot of this stuff is for collectors," he said. "The expensive stuff, like the $300 helmet or the personalized items, are for the wife who is getting her executive-type husband, who has everything, a very special gift. That's what makes it all so confusing."</p>
        <p>For Karen Ramsey, it's hard to explain the business side of autographs to her young son, who recently started practicing at outside linebacker for his first year of midget league football.</p>
        <p>"A long time ago, p.r. was more important to these athletes and the fans really mattered," she said. "Now, instead of feeling thankful that they have been given such gifts, they feel like the fans should be thankful that they even play for them."</p>
        <p>The bottom line is that as long as some athletes and businessmen can make money from autographs, they will be reluctant to give them away. Raider Won't Wait</p>
        <p>All eyes in the league are on Freeman McNeil's lawsuit against the National Football League, seeking free agency for players. Players have been slow to sign lengthy contracts because they're expecting some type of free agency to come out of the suit.</p>
        <p>Greg Townsend, the Raiders defensive end, must have his eyes closed. Townsend, who led the Raiders with 12 1/2 sacks last year, recently signed a six-year deal, which will pay him $1 million this year, $1.2 million next year and increase by $100,000 increments in each of the remaining years. Tackling the Language Barrier</p>
        <p>The Dolphins and the Raiders, who will play an exhibition game at the Tokyo Dome today, were supplied with 18 Japanese interpreters during their week in Japan. . . . When Buffalo beat Philadelphia, 17-13, last week in London, it was the first opening exhibition victory for the Bills since 1982, when they defeated Dallas, 14-10. . . . The Chicago Bears, who panned the World League of American Football and didn't contribute any money to its operation, have remained true to their beliefs. They have not signed any W.L.A.F. players as free agents.</p>
        <p>NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
