<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Save Bankers From Themselves by Regulation; Stop the Big Kill</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="465138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ASHLEY, THOMAS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUENTHER, KENNETH A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDF1030F937A3575BC0A967958260" item-length="369" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Save Bankers From Themselves by Regulation; Stop the Big Kill</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your profile of President Bush's friend and policy adviser Thomas Ashley (July 19) began to develop a policy issue of profound significance to the future of our banking system and economy, but then you let Mr. Ashley dismiss it with the words, "We aren't putting trusts back together, we're lifting 50-year-old restrictions that have strangled the industry."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your profile of President Bush's friend and policy adviser Thomas Ashley (July 19) began to develop a policy issue of profound significance to the future of our banking system and economy, but then you let Mr. Ashley dismiss it with the words, "We aren't putting trusts back together, we're lifting 50-year-old restrictions that have strangled the industry."</p>
        <p>At issue is whether or not commercial organizations should control banks, and this was the focus of President Theodore Roosevelt's trust-busting activities at the beginning of this century. President Bush wants this ownership door opened wide. The matter is being hotly debated in Congress and in editorial columns.</p>
        <p>Two voices should be set against Mr. Ashley's response. One is the highly regarded former Federal Reserve chairman, Paul Volcker, who on July 17 wrote to Donald Riegle, Senate Banking Committee chairman, expressing strong support for Senator Riegle's bill intended to maintain the separation of banking and commerce. Mr. Volcker stated:</p>
        <p>"As time passes, it seems to be more evident that no case has been made, in the broader public interest, for changing the long United States tradition in that respect . . . little or no sympathy exists in other leading countries for such a banking structure, and banks are demonstrating their ability to raise capital in the markets as their circumstances stabilize and improve. I know a relative handful of firms want the option to buy a bank to further their commercial interest, but that hardly provides a dispassionate base for public policy."</p>
        <p>John D. Dingell, House Energy and Commerce Committee chairman, who will, fortunately, be reviewing the Treasury proposal, was even blunter. In a June 6 letter to Thomas S. Foley, Speaker of the House, requesting the right for "close and careful" scrutiny of the proposal by his committee, Mr. Dingell stated, "this complex and dangerous proposal should not be railroaded through without that scrutiny."</p>
        <p>The stakes in the pending financial reform bill are very high for every American. We are at a historic watershed.  KENNETH A. GUENTHER Executive V.P., Independent Bankers Assn. of America Washington, July 22, 1991</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
