<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dole Appears to Be More at Ease As Election Going Gets Tougher</title>
    <meta content="20DOLE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="POLITICS: THE REPUBLICAN" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="878397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS: THE REPUBLICAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dole, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3DC143DF933A1575AC0A960958260" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dole Appears to Be More at Ease As Election Going Gets Tougher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>LAS VEGAS, Nev., Sept. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Dole appears undaunted by series of mishaps that have befallen his campaign recently; despite onslaught of bad news and discouraging polls, Dole labors on, delivering long and energetic speeches even when audience turnout is sparse; aides maintain that Dole remains convinced he will win this election; but some wonder if capturing his party's nomination is being seen by Dole as appropriate capstone for lifetime in politics; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Bob Dole's plane rumbled over California on Wednesday night, the Republican candidate strolled uncharacteristically to the back of his aircraft in search of the news photographers on board.</p>
        <p>Undaunted by his fall off a stage at a rally in Chico, Calif., a few hours earlier -- as he has been consistently undaunted by any of the mishaps that have befallen his campaign recently -- Mr. Dole wanted to see the picture of his tumble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Bob Dole's plane rumbled over California on Wednesday night, the Republican candidate strolled uncharacteristically to the back of his aircraft in search of the news photographers on board.</p>
        <p>Undaunted by his fall off a stage at a rally in Chico, Calif., a few hours earlier -- as he has been consistently undaunted by any of the mishaps that have befallen his campaign recently -- Mr. Dole wanted to see the picture of his tumble.</p>
        <p>He reviewed the color image displayed on the photographer's computer screen, taking in the portrait of a Presidential candidate lying on his back in the dust, his face twisted in shock, his body crumpled, his head supported by another news photographer who had tried to break his fall. ''There -- that's not bad,'' Mr. Dole murmured, as his aides shifted uncomfortably behind him.</p>
        <p>''My hair stayed all right -- I had enough hair spray on,'' Mr. Dole said, continuing the banter. He made only one request for the picture that was, at that moment, being transmitted around the world. ''Don't show it to my wife,'' Mr. Dole said, raising an eyebrow and flashing a grin at the crowd of reporters and aides around him.</p>
        <p>By any conventional measure, the Republican candidate has endured a rough stretch of politicking recently.</p>
        <p>Before falling about four feet off the stage in Chico, in Northern California, he had described the National League baseball team in Los Angeles as the Brooklyn Dodgers, a reminder that the 73-year-old candidate had attended college in Brooklyn in World War II, more than a dozen years before the team moved from New York to Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>He was greeted by a lunch-time audience in Los Angeles so sparse that it could almost have fit aboard his campaign plane, a Boeing 727, and still left room for his staff. He has been smothered with news of discouraging polls, from California, Texas and Ohio. Crime, his latest campaign issue, was undercut by Government statistics showing a decline in violent crime.</p>
        <p>But if there is one upbeat element in the Dole campaign in these difficult days, it is Mr. Dole himself. There may be gallows humors among some of the candidate's staff -- talk of new careers after Election Day, gossip about the next Presidential race, and discussion of Mr. Dole's affinity for the unfortunate metaphor.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Dole himself has remained, by all appearances and accounts, calm, unflappable and even chipper.</p>
        <p>In one of the indelible and chilling images captured by the Reuters photographer, Rick T. Wilking, on Wednesday evening in Chico, Mr. Dole's face displays the kind of mortification familiar to anyone who has tripped and toppled in full public view.</p>
        <p>But the next photograph shows  him back on his feet, smiling and stoic as he tries to change the story line on this latest metaphor for his sometimes-hapless campaign.</p>
        <p>''Don't be afraid of standing close to the stage,'' Mr. Dole said as he addressed a rally in the MGM Grand Hotel here today, keeping up his humor even in the morning light. ''I'm not going to dive off today. I was trying to do that new Democratic dance -- the Macarena. I'm not going to try that anymore.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, Mr. Dole is an experienced politician, and some of this -- his bantering with reporters, the extra time he spent shaking hands after his fall, the jokes -- is orchestrated to try to counter the political damage. But he has never been a man adept at hiding his emotions, and there is little reason to think that now, in the final weeks of the campaign, he has suddenly learned how to do it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole, according to his aides, suffered no serious injury from his fall. He was examined by an MGM hotel ophthalmologist, who reported that he suffered a conjunctival abrasion, resulting in a patch of redness to his left eye.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole also complained about a bruised ankle. And in one sure sign that he was feeling out of sorts, he raced out of his last campaign stop in Denver to fly home, leaving the reporters behind.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Dole's usual demeanor these days is becoming one of the more intriguing aspects of this campaign, raising questions that have perplexed even his own associates.</p>
        <p>Is he optimistic about his prospects for defeating President Clinton, notwithstanding the relentless onslaught of bad news and discouraging polls? Could it be that Mr. Dole's contentment means that he considers the capture of his party's nomination last August an appropriate capstone for a lifetime in politics?</p>
        <p>At this time four years ago, President George Bush, who also seemed on the road to defeat, could barely restrain his anger, snapping at Mr. Clinton one day and at the news media the next. And Mr. Dole's staff, which has always been fractious, is awash in recriminations, particularly over the mistakes by his advance team like the one that led to his fall, an unfastened decorative railing placed on the stage.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Dole's senior advisers today compared the campaign's advance staff to the Keystone Kops.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Mr. Dole seems to find the bright edge to every dark cloud that comes rolling over his campaign. If he noticed those big open patches of space at his rally in Los Angeles the other day, he gave no sign of it, delivering a long and energetic speech.</p>
        <p>And if a new report shows that crime is going down, no matter. ''They're scared to death in America!'' Mr. Dole declared. ''They're scared to death in America!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole's aides maintain that the candidate remains convinced that he will win this election. Perhaps. Mr. Dole is given to doing things that politicians are not supposed to do, as happened in a little-noticed moment in an interview broadcast last week with Barbara Walters. What, Ms. Walters wanted to know, would Mr. Dole do if he lost the election?</p>
        <p>Most candidates would have dismissed the question as unrealistic, asserting there was no chance they would lose. Mr. Dole's reply: He would spend more time with his wife and give speeches. And he looked almost peaceful as he considered the possibility.</p>
        <p>POLITICS: THE REPUBLICAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
