<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Terrific Spot for a Murder</title>
    <meta content="25crimebk" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/25/books/review/25crime.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1727219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CRIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stasio, Marilyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, P D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corwin, C R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcbain, Ed</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lighthouse, the (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DIG (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Gutter and the Grave, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">James, P D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5D81F31F936A15751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Terrific Spot for a Murder</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Terrific Spot for a Murder</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marilyn Stasio</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stasio, Marilyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marilyn Stasio reviews books The Lighthouse by P D James, DIG by C R Corwin and The Gutter and the Grave by Ed McBain; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE setting of a P. D. James novel is always the key to the mystery. Whether it's a theological college slowly toppling off a cliff into the North Sea (''Death in Holy Orders''), an ancient abbey overshadowed by a nuclear power plant (''Devices and Desires'') or a small museum devoted to England's history between the two world wars (''The Murder Room''), the setting represents some aspect of English tradition James values highly and feels is under threat. A murder committed in such a hallowed place poses more than a knotty puzzle for Commander Adam Dalgliesh and his crack team of Scotland Yard detectives. It signals another assault on an orderly civilization from the encroaching forces of cultural barbarism and social misrule.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For P. D. James, murder in a hallowed place is more than a knotty puzzle for Adam Dalgliesh: it's an assault on civilization.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE setting of a P. D. James novel is always the key to the mystery. Whether it's a theological college slowly toppling off a cliff into the North Sea (''Death in Holy Orders''), an ancient abbey overshadowed by a nuclear power plant (''Devices and Desires'') or a small museum devoted to England's history between the two world wars (''The Murder Room''), the setting represents some aspect of English tradition James values highly and feels is under threat. A murder committed in such a hallowed place poses more than a knotty puzzle for Commander Adam Dalgliesh and his crack team of Scotland Yard detectives. It signals another assault on an orderly civilization from the encroaching forces of cultural barbarism and social misrule.</p>
        <p>THE LIGHTHOUSE (Knopf, $25.95) is set on a private island off the coast of Cornwall, a high-security retreat offering ''solitude, silence and peace'' to those who have labored hard ''in the service of the Crown and of their country.'' Exposed to the elements and battered by the sea, Combe Island is both nature's healing ground and ''a place of violent emotions, of danger.'' Which is to say, it's a terrific spot for a murder.</p>
        <p>James obliges, in an intricate and welldesigned plot, with the picturesque homicide of Nathan Oliver, a celebrated novelist whose body is discovered dangling from the lighthouse that soars above the rocky coastline. If ever there were someone who deserved killing, it's Oliver, a frequent visitor who was born on the island and is now determined to exercise what he considers his birthright -- to live there permanently in the cottage of his choice. Unfailingly obnoxious, he threatens to displace the formidable Miss Emily Holcombe, the last surviving member of the original proprietary family, and offends the other guests, along with the entire staff.</p>
        <p>Unlike Oliver, whose singular failing as a writer is his lack of emotion (''he can describe but he can't feel, not for other people''), James creates emotionally complex characters. And because those characters reveal themselves in oblique ways, her watchful detectives must be masters at reading behavior, knowing that even the manner in which the housekeeper stitches a piece of embroidery can tell them something about her. In this setting, though, the real clues are to be found in the way people relate to the island, how they respond to its beauty and deal with its hardships, how they let it work itself into their bones. Even Dalgliesh falls under the spell, finding the tranquillity to make a major decision about his future life -- although not necessarily one that will please all his fans.</p>
        <p>Whenever hard-boiled cops and private eyes try to show us their sensitive side, they look off into the middle distance and tell some maudlin story about their own sorry lives. John Harvey's detectives, on the other hand, are the real deal -- strong men who are sensitive enough to empathize with other people. Even people who happen to be women. In ASH &amp; BONE (Otto Penzler/Harcourt, $25), his second novel (after ''Flesh &amp; Blood'') about a retired Nottingham police officer named Frank Elder, Harvey writes insightfully about women who are unable to recover from the trauma of sexual abuse. Not that Elder is what you would call mentally well adjusted. Estranged from his wife and dispirited, he has quit the force and is holed up in an isolated cottage, reading J. B. Priestley, drinking and brooding. But the murder of a former colleague and the delinquent behavior of his own 17-year-old daughter bring him out of seclusion and involve him in two interlocking cases of sexual brutality. While the male villains are no better than thugs, Harvey shows great compassion for the women they batter; in Elder, he has given them a champion who really does feel their pain.</p>
        <p>Every hometown newspaper has some colorful old crab like Dolly Madison (Maddy) Sprowls on the premises, and C. R. Corwin had the wit to make her the heroine of his amusing debut mystery, ''Morgue Mama.'' Having rejected graceful retirement for the more rewarding role of staff busybody, Maddy is back in all her despotic glory in DIG (Poisoned Pen, $24.95), presiding over the archives of The Hannawa (Ohio) Herald-Union and poking her nose into another local murder. When Gordon E. (Sweet Gordon) Sweet, a professor of ''garbology,'' is found shot to death at an archaeological dig in the town landfill, Maddy's thoughts leap back to the 1950's, when he and she were campus beatniks, charter members of the Meriwether Square Baked Bean Existentialist Society. ''We listened to jazz, drank little cups of coffee and talked and talked and talked,'' she explains to the young librarian who gives her a hand on this case, which is both a brainteaser and a comic salute to the rather terrifying charm of its heroine.</p>
        <p>''I'm a drunk. I think we'd better get that straight from the beginning.'' Can you imagine any of today's sensitive sleuths coming out with that line? I can't either, which is why THE GUTTER AND THE GRAVE (Hard Case Crime, paper, $6.99) is such a guilty pleasure. Ed McBain wrote this noir head-banger almost 50 years ago and was revising it right up until he died last summer. He can't have cleaned up his hero, a cynical New York private eye living like a bum on the Bowery, or censored his own politically incorrect sensibility, because all that good stuff is what gives this vintage story its backbone. The fashions may be quaint (a detective looks sharp in a ''tropical suit and a snapbrim straw'') and the expressions dated (''I don't go for shenanigans,'' a Greenwich Village landlord informs the P.I. when he pays a visit to an unmarried woman). But there's a toughness to this funny old town, an air of danger McBain picked up from the way people talk when they're scared. He always did have a great ear -- the best.</p>
        <p>CRIME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
