<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lives They Lived; Pride and Prejudice</title>
    <meta content="25haidercelestinemotley-3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/25/magazine/25motley.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1727276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Constance Baker Motley | b. 1921"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn for the Advancement of Colored People</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7DA1730F936A15751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1099" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lives They Lived; Pride and Prejudice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pride and Prejudice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Melissa Fay Greene</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>February 1941, Constance Baker, age 19, a bright and ambitious young woman from New Haven, left home for college. She was slender and stylish, wearing a wool overcoat with a fur collar and black leather gloves. Her dark wavy hair fell from under a slanted wide-brimmed hat. She'd found a hometown mentor -- a white philanthropist named Clarence Blakeslee --who had heard her speak up at a community meeting and subsequently offered to pay her tuition. Despite the fact that female lawyers were rare creatures, and black women lawyers almost unheard-of, Constance Baker had set her sights on law school.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>She conquered segregation with a sense of her own superiority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>February 1941, Constance Baker, age 19, a bright and ambitious young woman from New Haven, left home for college. She was slender and stylish, wearing a wool overcoat with a fur collar and black leather gloves. Her dark wavy hair fell from under a slanted wide-brimmed hat. She'd found a hometown mentor -- a white philanthropist named Clarence Blakeslee --who had heard her speak up at a community meeting and subsequently offered to pay her tuition. Despite the fact that female lawyers were rare creatures, and black women lawyers almost unheard-of, Constance Baker had set her sights on law school.</p>
        <p>Strikingly attractive and full of promise that February day, she toted her suitcase on the train from New Haven to New York and from New York to Cincinnati. In Cincinnati, she disembarked and watched as an older and rustier passenger car was connected to the train. When she tried to return to her seat for the journey across Kentucky to Nashville, home of her destination, Fisk University, the porter blocked her. ''You have to go in this car,'' he said, directing her to the older one. Then she saw the ''Colored'' sign.</p>
        <p>''Although I had known this would happen, I was both frightened and humiliated,'' she would write in her autobiography 57 years later, by which time she had become one of the most famous lawyers in America: she had worked with Thurgood Marshall on the N.A.A.C.P. Legal Defense and Educational Fund team that overturned school segregation; she had been James Meredith's chief counsel in his battle for admission to the University of Mississippi; she had argued 10 cases before the Supreme Court (and won nine of them); she was the first black woman elected to the New York State Senate and the first woman to serve in the powerful position of Manhattan borough president; and in 1966 she became the first black woman to serve on the federal judiciary and the first to serve as chief judge for the Southern District of New York.</p>
        <p>Of her appalling day in Cincinnati, she wrote that having grown up in Connecticut, ''I did not know the extent to which segregation affected the daily lives and freedom of movement of all black people south of the Mason-Dixon Line.''</p>
        <p>There is another part to this story. ''Yeah, well, she stole the Colored sign out of that train car,'' says her only child, Joel Wilson Motley III, a New York investment banker. ''She wanted to show it to her parents, a bit of evidence of what was happening in the country. My grandparents were shocked. They weren't surprised by the sign, they knew about the signs; they were shocked by my mother's audacity in stealing it.''</p>
        <p>Connie Baker grew up in a stately world, a star student in New Haven schools, where she was one of very few black children. ''We seemed to have no more and no less than everyone else,'' she wrote in her autobiography, ''Equal Justice Under Law.'' ''The grammar school was two short blocks away.. . .</p>
        <p>There was beautiful Edgewood Park with a playground nearby. There were two beaches.. . .Fear and racial conflict were simply not a part of the landscape.''</p>
        <p>Both her mother and father were immigrants from the Caribbean island of Nevis, and their friends were mostly other West Indians, preferably Nevisians, all properly educated in the English Standard Schools of their island. They were men ''who appeared in public with white shirts, starched collars, ties and jackets'' and their dignified wives. ''Every West Indian we knew,'' she wrote, ''had an upright piano in the parlor.''</p>
        <p>Motley was the ninth of 12 children, three of whom died in infancy. Her father was a Yale University chef, ''who stood and dressed and walked like he was president of the First National Bank.'' Later in life she would recognize that her father's ''arrogant attitude'' could be explained by the fact that his ''maternal grandfather was white'' and that all his grandparents were free people.</p>
        <p>''West Indians are famous for being a proud people -- some even might say arrogant,'' Joel Motley says. ''My mother inherited a great self-confidence.'' Constance Baker (who married Joel Wilson Motley, Jr., a real-estate broker, in 1946) never had to fight off the inner demons of fear and inferiority sometimes instilled in Southern black people by the deprivation and violence of segregation. Even as she became a lightning rod for the massive white resistance to school desegregation and the target of taunting mobs, demonstrations and verbal abuse, she retained an erect posture, a calm demeanor, a string of pearls and a thousand-mile stare.</p>
        <p>''I don't believe she was ever scared of those people or ever intimidated by them,'' her son says. ''She saw them as benighted, primitive, ignorant.''</p>
        <p>As a young lawyer, Derrick Bell, who now teaches law at New York University and is a leading authority on constitutional law, worked with Motley on desegregation cases in the South. When Motley argued, courtrooms became ''places of rich racial drama,'' Bell wrote in an e-mail message. ''Whites on one side, exhibiting silent hostility, and blacks on the other side, barely able to restrain their pride. Here was a black woman, obviously better prepared than her white opponents, speaking firmly and with full knowledge of her case. The judge. . .usually ruled against her, but no matter! For these black people, many of whom had spent their lives in involuntary deference to whites, these hearings were priceless scenes.'' The stories would spread rapidly outside the courtroom, ''embellished at the barbershops and beauty parlors for weeks to come.''</p>
        <p>Motley displayed a rare mix of aristocracy and compassion. The catcalling and threats and jostling angry mobs seemed barely to catch her attention. ''Connie took it all in stride,'' Bell wrote. ''On one occasion, we ran into the opposing attorney in many of these cases at the airport. Connie extended her hand in greeting, and the attorney refused to take it. 'Oh,' she said, 'you still don't shake black people's hands. Very well, then,' and off she glided to her flight.''</p>
        <p>Constance Baker Motley | b. 1921</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
