<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coach's Correct Choice</title>
    <meta content="31ANDE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/31/sports/football/31ANDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1363816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Patriots</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Rams</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bledsoe, Drew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brady, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belichick, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/St. Louis Rams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New England Patriots</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Belichick, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4DB1F3AF932A05752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coach's Correct Choice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Coach's Correct Choice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column praises New England Patriots coach Bill Belichick's choice to start Tom Brady rather than Drew Bledsoe at quarterback position in Super Bowl against St Louis Rams; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVEN before Bill Belichick chose Tom Brady over Drew Bledsoe as the New England Patriots starting quarterback in Super Bowl XXXVI, the $100 million backup had put the coach's decision in perspective.</p>
        <p>''Whoever plays,'' Bledsoe said on Tuesday, ''he's got to win.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill Belichick made the correct choice. Tom Brady has been brilliant. Drew Bledsoe is still rusty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVEN before Bill Belichick chose Tom Brady over Drew Bledsoe as the New England Patriots starting quarterback in Super Bowl XXXVI, the $100 million backup had put the coach's decision in perspective.</p>
        <p>''Whoever plays,'' Bledsoe said on Tuesday, ''he's got to win.''</p>
        <p>But unless the Patriots win, Belichick can't win. If the Patriots lose to the St. Louis Rams, their coach will be second-guessed forever from Foxboro to Faneuil Hall for not having started Bledsoe, who came off the sideline to preserve Sunday's 24-17 triumph in Pittsburgh after Brady had departed with a sprained left ankle.</p>
        <p>It says here, though, that Belichick made the correct choice. Brady has been brilliant. Bledsoe is still rusty.</p>
        <p>In waiting until after viewing a videotape of yesterday's practice, Belichick wanted to be sure that Brady, the starter since Bledsoe suffered a sheared blood vessel in his chest in the season's second game, could practice properly with a brace on his damaged ankle.</p>
        <p>Like most coaches, Belichick believes that a player must practice during the week in order to play on Sunday, especially a quarterback.</p>
        <p>''It's one of those injuries where it's a tolerance thing,'' Brady had said. ''I can brace it up. This is the biggest game of my life.''</p>
        <p>It's also the biggest game of Bledsoe's life, an opportunity to atone for the Patriots' loss to the Green Bay Packers five years ago in Super Bowl XXXI.</p>
        <p>''You want to get in the game,'' Bledsoe had said, ''and to have that taken away would be a very difficult thing.''</p>
        <p>Belichick's preference for Brady didn't figure to affect the betting line that has the Rams a solid 14-point favorite, mostly because it didn't figure to alter either the Patriots' offensive game plan or the Rams' defensive game plan.</p>
        <p>''Whoever is in there,'' Charlie Weis, the Patriots' offensive coordinator, said before yesterday's practice, ''we're running the same thing.''</p>
        <p>According to Weis, each quarterback's talents fit the coordinator's play selection. As for personality, Brady is what Bledsoe has become.</p>
        <p>''One is a natural fiery guy,'' Weis said, alluding to Brady, ''and one developed into a natural fiery guy. When Bledsoe first came up as the No. 1 draft chice, he was a laid-back guy from Washington State who turned into a natural fiery guy. Brady has always been that natural fiery guy who would head butt his linemen.''</p>
        <p>Lovie Smith, the Rams' defensive coordinator, described Brady and Bledsoe as ''dropback, pocket passers,'' saying ''that's what we're preparing for.'' Middle linebacker London Fletcher thought that Brady is more likely to move out of the pocket and Bledsoe has a stronger arm, but the All-Pro cornerback Aeneas Williams didn't sound concerned.</p>
        <p>''If the Patriots' offensive coordinator had changed,'' Williams said, ''that would be something different. But it's the same offensive coordinator. We have pretty much a feel for the parameters of which plays will be called.''</p>
        <p>If injuries to both Brady and Rams quarterback Kurt Warner, who described his bruised ribs as ''still a little bit sore,'' dissolved the Super Bowl into a duel of backups, Bledsoe has accomplished much more than the virtually unknown and untested 31-year-old Jamie Martin.</p>
        <p>''Kurt's our leader, he controls the huddle,'' running back Marshall Faulk said last week. ''He gets everybody in plays, he distributes the football and it would be different if he got hurt, but at the same time, we got to do a job.''</p>
        <p>But that job surely would be much different with Martin, who rejoined the Rams in September after having been a transient with Washington, Jacksonville and Cleveland. For all of his dazzling numbers at Weber State, including seven touchdown passes in one game, he has appeared in only 18 games in eight seasons, one as a starter. Martin mopped up twice this season, completing all 3 of his passes for 22 yards in victories over the Jets and Carolina.</p>
        <p>''I think Jamie would step in and we'd continue to do what we do,'' Coach Mike Martz said last week before Warner needed a flak jacket and a pain-killing injection in the 29-24 victory over Philadelphia. ''Jamie is well versed in what we're doing.''</p>
        <p>But not as well versed as Bledsoe in what the Patriots are doing. And for all the debate over Bill Belichick's decision to start Brady, if Brady were to limp off again, the Patriots would be depending on Bledsoe after all.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
