<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brady Will Start for Patriots</title>
    <meta content="31PATS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/31/sports/football/31PATS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1363843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Rams</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Patriots</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belichick, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bledsoe, Drew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brady, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/St. Louis Rams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New England Patriots</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brady, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E2DA1F3AF932A05752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brady Will Start for Patriots</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Brady Will Start for Patriots</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, Jan. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New England Patriots coach Bill Belichick announces that Tom Brady, rather than Drew Bledsoe, will start at quarterback in Super Bowl against St Louis Rams; Bledsoe expresses disappointment and says he will do everything he can to help win game; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New England Coach Bill Belichick made the same decision tonight that he made in November. After watching practice and reviewing the film, Belichick again chose Tom Brady over Drew Bledsoe.</p>
        <p>Brady, the second-year quarterback who sprained his left ankle Sunday against the Pittsburgh Steelers, will start Super Bowl XXXVI against the St. Louis Rams. With his ankle heavily taped and wearing a plastic brace, Brady took his regular snaps as the starter in today's practice and showed no signs of being hindered by the injury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New England Coach Bill Belichick chose Tom Brady, who sprained his ankle against the Steelers on Sunday, to start Super Bowl XXXVI.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New England Coach Bill Belichick made the same decision tonight that he made in November. After watching practice and reviewing the film, Belichick again chose Tom Brady over Drew Bledsoe.</p>
        <p>Brady, the second-year quarterback who sprained his left ankle Sunday against the Pittsburgh Steelers, will start Super Bowl XXXVI against the St. Louis Rams. With his ankle heavily taped and wearing a plastic brace, Brady took his regular snaps as the starter in today's practice and showed no signs of being hindered by the injury.</p>
        <p>''Tom Brady demonstrated in practice today that he is fit to play,'' Belichick said. ''He will be our starting quarterback on Sunday.''</p>
        <p>''I'm obviously very disappointed,'' Bledsoe said tonight. ''It's something I probably expected, to be honest with you. But I'll do everything I can to help Tom win the game.''</p>
        <p>It is the second time this season that Belichick chose Brady over Bledsoe, the former starter who lost his job after sustaining a serious chest injury in the second game of the season. Brady stepped in and held on tight to the job, leading the Patriots on an 11-3 run after an 0-2 start and a thrilling come-from-behind victory in a driving snowstorm over Oakland in the divisional playoffs.</p>
        <p>In late November, with Brady's Cinderella season well under way, Bledsoe was declared healthy to play. But Belichick stuck with Brady, creating the remarkable situation of having a Pro Bowl quarterback with a $100 million contract sitting on the bench. Bledsoe has supported Brady publicly throughout the season, but when Brady sprained his ankle late in the second quarter of the American Football Conference championship game, Bledsoe seized his opportunity. As he entered the huddle for the first time since being hurt Sept. 23 against the Jets, he told his offense, in his best Jack Nicholson impersonation, ''I'm b-a-a-ck.''</p>
        <p>Then he led the Patriots to their only offensive touchdown of the day against the Steelers and a spot in Sunday's Super Bowl. Afterward, Bledsoe wept on the field.</p>
        <p>That created the rare situation of a team going into Super Bowl week without knowing who its starting quarterback would be, although it seemed almost certain that Brady would start if he was healthy enough. Bledsoe said on Tuesday that he wanted to play more than he has ever wanted anything.</p>
        <p>But sticking with Brady, who was selected to go to the Pro Bowl because of his magic-dusted season, was a no-brainer for Belichick, once he knew that Brady was able to move adequately on the ankle.</p>
        <p>A decision to go with Bledsoe would have created a full-blown controversy with the Super Bowl just four days away and might have shattered Brady's confidence. If Brady is limited by the injury during the game, Belichick could always put Bledsoe in.</p>
        <p>Still, for as obvious as this decision seemed to be this week, Belichick extended the drama to an almost absurd extreme. A pool reporter was allowed to watch practice but was not told of the decision. Belichick delayed his announcement until after he returned to the team hotel and watched the tape with his coaches. Then he informed Brady and Bledsoe of his decision in a meeting. The coronation was finally announced at 8 p.m. by the team's director of media relations, Stacey James.</p>
        <p>''They both worked, and I was satisfied with how they worked,'' Belichick said after the practice. Asked if he was pleased with how Brady moved in and out of the pocket, Belichick said, ''I'm going to wait to take a look at the tape on that one.''</p>
        <p>According to the pool report, Brady moved well throughout, from the jog he took before practice to the times he was orchestrating full-squad plays in practice.</p>
        <p>''I feel normal,'' Brady said as he walked off the field.</p>
        <p>Bledsoe and Brady were not available after the decision was announced, but both spoke at the morning news conference. Brady expressed confidence that he would play, and Bledsoe sensed that the decision would probably go against him when asked if he thought he would start Sunday.</p>
        <p>''I would certainly love to play in this game,'' Bledsoe said. ''There's no question this game is the one that everybody plays for and, if given the opportunity, I would take it and run with it.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the Patriots' owner, Robert Kraft, injected himself into the situation, saying today that he would prefer to keep both quarterbacks on the roster next season. Then he added that it would take a blockbuster deal for the Patriots to consider trading one of them, but that it would be Belichick's decision on that, too.</p>
        <p>''The future's the future, and right now we're focused on this game,'' Bledsoe said. ''And whatever happens after that, happens.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
