<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lalibala Journal; In Ethiopia, Islam's Tide Laps at the Rock of Ages</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="499909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTMAS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ETHIOPIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LALIBALA (ETHIOPIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERLEZ, JANE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ethiopia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD71239F930A25752C0A964958260" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lalibala Journal; In Ethiopia, Islam's Tide Laps at the Rock of Ages</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PERLEZ, JANE</byline>
      <dateline>LALIBALA, Ethiopia, Jan. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the cool dawn air of the Ethiopian highlands, hundreds of priests in white and red robes, their heads swathed in turbans, emerged from one of the 11 churches here to sing psalms and give thanks to the medieval king under whose rule the churches, carved from solid rock, were built 800 years ago.</p>
        <p>It was Christmas, which in the Ethiopian Orthodox Church is celebrated according to the Julian calendar, and this year's service was the first held in peace for nearly 20 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the cool dawn air of the Ethiopian highlands, hundreds of priests in white and red robes, their heads swathed in turbans, emerged from one of the 11 churches here to sing psalms and give thanks to the medieval king under whose rule the churches, carved from solid rock, were built 800 years ago.</p>
        <p>It was Christmas, which in the Ethiopian Orthodox Church is celebrated according to the Julian calendar, and this year's service was the first held in peace for nearly 20 years.</p>
        <p>The civil war around these 8,000-foot mountains did not deter native peasants, who for centuries have walked long distances to reach these remote shrines at Christmas.</p>
        <p>But for almost a decade this imposing cluster of 11 churches, chiseled out of the pink-hued volcanic rock as a symbol of the endurance of Christianity in a surrounding world of Islam, has been out of bounds for foreigners. After a new Government took power in Ethiopia last May, Lalibala was made accessible again. Fears of Fundamentalists</p>
        <p>The ceremony today, replete with young deacons thumping a haunting beat on elongated silver drums and lines of priests dancing a slow jig, was performed at a critical juncture for Ethiopia, a country long viewed as a bastion of Christianity. Fears are mounting again among Christians in Ethiopia about another onslaught from Muslim fundamentalists.</p>
        <p>Founded in the fourth century in the highlands north of here by missionaries from the Byzantine Empire, Ethiopian Christianity was born as a state church and as such withstood the inroads of the Muslims who settled in the lowlands. Until the toppling of Emperor Haile Selassie in 1974, Ethiopian rulers were always Christians.</p>
        <p>The Marxist regime of Lieut. Col. Mengistu Haile Mariam interrupted the tradition by confiscating church lands and co-opting many of its leaders. Still, the churches remained open and the congregations large.</p>
        <p>But the new Government, led by President Meles Zenawi, is not only unsympathetic to the church but is more accommodating to Islamic fundamentalism, Ethiopian officials and diplomats here say.</p>
        <p>There are, by most accounts, almost as many Muslims in Ethiopia as Christians, most of them among the Oromo, the largest ethnic group. In this Christian stronghold, however, there is little sense of the surge of Islam elsewhere in the country.</p>
        <p>Thousands of peasants, many of whom had traveled for days, attended Christmas Eve services at the Beta Mariam Church here, peering down into the church courtyard from atop the surrounding "walls" -- actually the volcanic plain into which the church was carved -- for two hours of singing, praying and dancing.</p>
        <p>One 70-year-old woman, Teke Wolde Giorgis, her face crinkled from sun and hard toil, said she had walked 16 days from Makale in the province of Tigre. It was her eighth trip to Lalibala, she said.  Legend of Churches</p>
        <p>According to Ethiopian legend, the 11 churches were excavated by King Lalibala, who lived from 1190 to 1225 and is credited with leading the second wave of Ethiopian Christianity after the fourth-century conversions at Aksum in northern Tigre.</p>
        <p>Why the King had churches built below ground with surrounding trenches and interconnecting passageways is not entirely clear. But David Buxton, an English specialist in medieval Ethiopian structures, notes that when the Islamic leader Ahmad Gran conquered large parts of Ethiopia in the 1500's, the above-ground churches at Aksum were destroyed but the camouflaged structures of Lalibala were left untouched.</p>
        <p>After years of fighting around the mountains of Lalibala, the Tigrean Peoples Liberation Front -- now the core of the new Meles Government -- took control of Lalibala and its approximately 5,000 villagers two years ago. At the time, the local Bishop, Berhane Selassie, was not in the town; he returned from the Ethiopian capital, Addis Ababa, for the first time only a few days before the Christmas celebrations.</p>
        <p>Like the rest of the Ethiopian church's hierarchy, the 50-year-old Bishop Berhane was perceived by many as sympathetic to the Mengistu Government. He was a member of Parliament in the Mengistu era. Bishop Is Arrested</p>
        <p>In his absence, the new authorities occupied the Bishop's house and on his return forced him to sleep in his office. Then, on Christmas Eve, an armed squad marched him off to the local Government headquarters.</p>
        <p>Later, Bishop Berhane said he had been questioned about his supposed membership in Mengistu's Communist Party and whether he had worked as part of the security police. He said he had denied that he had been a member of either organization.</p>
        <p>He said he doubted the new Government's pledge to stay out of church affairs. "The Government's charter states there should be freedom of religion," he said. "But I am skeptical."</p>
        <p>Asked if he was concerned about the spread of Muslim fundamentalism, Bishop Berhane shrugged. "The nonbelievers will always fight us, secretly or in front," he said. "That we expect. But this Government will make it easier for them."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
