<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fresh Face to Wake Up 'Good Morning'</title>
    <meta content="31SIGN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="59" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1020848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="SIGNOFF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gerston, Jill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccree, Lisa</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Good Morning America (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E6DE1638F932A05756C0A96E958260" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fresh Face to Wake Up 'Good Morning'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jill Gerston</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gerston, Jill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Kevin Newman, 38-year-old, Toronto-born television newsman who has been named co-host, with Lisa McRee, of ABC's Good Morning America; photo of Newman and McRee (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Kevin Newman was called into the office of the ABC News president, David Westin, in March, he thought he was going to be admonished for some gaffe he might have made as the news anchor of ''Good Morning America.''</p>
        <p>Instead, he was offered the plum assignment of co-host for the network's morning show. He took over with Lisa McRee on May 4, when ''Good Morning America'' introduced a citified set and new theme music.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Kevin Newman was called into the office of the ABC News president, David Westin, in March, he thought he was going to be admonished for some gaffe he might have made as the news anchor of ''Good Morning America.''</p>
        <p>Instead, he was offered the plum assignment of co-host for the network's morning show. He took over with Lisa McRee on May 4, when ''Good Morning America'' introduced a citified set and new theme music.</p>
        <p>''Being the host is very different from being the news anchor,'' Mr. Newman  said. ''You have to reveal yourself because there is almost no script; it's all out of your head. It's all about how comfortable you are.''</p>
        <p>Never mind that the high-profile job has sent his anxiety level ''way up there.'' On camera, Mr. Newman, 38, appears totally at ease. More important to viewers who are finicky about whom they share their morning coffee with, he seems like a regular guy, someone you'd see standing in line at the Gap.</p>
        <p>''He's very unassuming in a lot of ways,'' said Shelley Lewis, the executive producer of ''Good Morning America.'' ''He doesn't see himself as some big star.''</p>
        <p>Late-night news hounds became acquainted with Mr. Newman when he was the anchor of ABC's overnight news programs, ''World News Now'' and ''World News This Morning,'' from 1994 to 1996. His next stint was as a correspondent for ''World News Tonight'' and co-anchor of ''Good Morning America Sunday.''</p>
        <p>However, Mr. Newman's star-making turn came last August when the Princess of Wales died in a Paris car crash. For four hours nonstop Mr. Newman held forth as anchor of that breaking news story.</p>
        <p>''It was a holiday weekend, so the A-string folks weren't as close as I was to be called in,'' said Mr. Newman, who was home in New Jersey with his family. ''As we began chasing the story it was apparent it was much more serious than a car accident. I assumed that someone else would be brought in to take over, but they hung with me.''</p>
        <p>Said Ms. Lewis: ''Kevin never loses his place or his cool during a breaking news story. He has that key gift for live television of being very organized in his mind.''</p>
        <p>BORN in Toronto, Mr. Newman graduated from the University of Western Ontario and began his career ''carrying coffee cups'' in the newsroom of a regional Canadian television station. He eventually became the parliamentary correspondent for the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation and the anchor of ''Midday,'' a show similar to ''Good Morning America.''</p>
        <p>Why would a Canadian news star take a job as a news anchor in the wee hours of the morning in the United States?</p>
        <p>''Television in Canada was becoming a shrinking thing,'' he said of his move to ABC four years ago. ''There were more challenges here.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Newman has found a challenge with ''Good Morning America,'' whose declining ratings have put it far behind NBC's ''Today'' show.</p>
        <p>By giving ''Good Morning America''  a new pair of anchors, a new set, new music and a looser pacing, the network is trying to reinvigorate a program that had become somewhat predictable with its longtime hosts Joan Lunden and Charles Gibson.</p>
        <p>''I kind of feel we're like 'Star Trek, the Next Generation,' '' Mr. Newman said. He added that no one at the network expected an instant turnaround in ratings. ''They say, 'Don't worry, it's a marathon,' and I take them at their word.''</p>
        <p>Before accepting his newest post, Mr. Newman said he discussed it with his wife, Cathy, and children, Alex, 12, and Erica, 8.</p>
        <p>''With most other promotions it has been, 'Thanks, great, when do I start?,' but this is a very public job that, as Charlie Gibson told me, is all consuming,'' he said. ''I wasn't sure I wanted that for my family.''</p>
        <p>His family urged him to grab ABC's offer.</p>
        <p>''They focused me on how I felt about the challenge,'' he said. ''Ultimately, I thought, I don't want anybody else taking it. It's too good a job.''</p>
        <p>SIGNOFF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
