<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Affirming Vibrant Freedom of Method</title>
    <meta content="31ART.$17" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1020947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braff, Phyllis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yektai, Manoucher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Semmel, Joan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E6DC1238F932A05756C0A96E958260" item-length="978" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Affirming Vibrant Freedom of Method</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phyllis Braff</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Braff, Phyllis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phyllis Braff reviews exhibitions of works of artists Manoucher Yektai and Joan Semmel at Guild Hall Museum in East Hampton, NY; also reviews exhibition entitled On the Edge at Arlene Bujese Gallery in East Hampton; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Manoucher Yektai</p>
        <p>Guild Hall Museum 158 Main Street, East Hampton. To June 7. 324-0806.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Manoucher Yektai</p>
        <p>Guild Hall Museum 158 Main Street, East Hampton. To June 7. 324-0806.</p>
        <p>This 47-year painting overview does much to clarify the career of the Iranian-born, Paris and New York-educated, Manoucher Yektai, who now divides his time between Sagaponack and Manhattan. The exhibition demonstrates, for example, how the timely ideas he explored within the milieu of Abstract Expressionism served as roots for the gestural applications of thick pigment that have long been part of his work. Tracing such  concerns from the 50's tends to make the subsequent technical and thematic variations seem stronger.</p>
        <p>In ''Open Window,'' 1951, the vertical slabs of color stand apart as if they were collage elements. One is impressed, too, by the way the scale of these separate paint units contributes to the impact. This calls attention to Mr. Yektai's decisions about effective scale in his swift crusty forms from later decades.</p>
        <p>A 1954 still life, ''The Yellow Curtain,'' suggests the range of Mr. Yektai's experiments with portraying an image through the action of his materials. The irregular, heavy paint is held in controlled paths in one section, but in another is more akin to a sudden freezing of random applications and seems to be just one step before process art. Responding to the paint activity seems instinctive, and there is a constant sense of suspension between this and the shift to grasp a motif, like a foreground bouquet. One feels this keenly in the more memorable later canvases like ''A Body of Landscape'' and ''Sagaponack Corner,'' a work that emphasizes sensuous responses to nature and recalls the spirit of Willem de Kooning.</p>
        <p>Affirming both familiar images and vibrant freedom of method can be hard to balance, and some canvases are more successful than others. There are instances when a full figure can seem to be an intrusion, although everything integrates well in ''Concierge.''</p>
        <p>Picking up on the intense physicality and invented topography, some paintings from the 80's and 90's seem more objectlike. The surface character of ''Sagaponack Corner'' is close to that of a gleaming ceramic, and in ''Road to the Water,'' interest focuses on the way high peaks reflect light and create artificial patterns.</p>
        <p>Joan Semmel</p>
        <p>Guild Hall Museum. To June 7.</p>
        <p>Joan Semmel's forceful paintings concentrate on both visual impact and psychological message. The 10 massive figurative works in this high-powered exhibition touch on aspects of her approach since 1977, a decade after she began to show regularly in museums and galleries -- initially in Spain, where she lived during the 60's. In recent years she has divided her time between East Hampton and Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Ms. Semmel's assertive and occasionally confrontational canvases entice viewers to ponder multiple meanings. Some are autobiographical, yet they also address broad feminist issues.  Others are transparent overlays, suggesting the transience of relationships between individuals  and their surroundings.</p>
        <p>Still others use mannequins as surrogates for exploring human situations. There is an edgy probing of aging implied in two over-life-sized examples. The warm-toned ''Galetea'' is vibrant and confident.  Her head is raised and her outstretched, well-manicured hand seems capable of anything. An icy blue tone covers all but the bright red lipstick in ''Hot Lips,'' which poses the mannequin with head lowered and one hand missing.</p>
        <p>Ms. Semmel uses bodies as both vehicles for social commentary and as pliable expressive forms for building strong perceptual sensations. Unusual angles, reminiscent of the quirky distortions possible with a camera, contribute to a number of the dramatic effects.  Others have an up-close cinematic orientation and still others incorporate mirrors that radically alter the picture space and provide the repetition of shapes useful in establishing formal harmony.</p>
        <p>Illumination is frequently exaggerated, which introduces a mystical quality in ''Out of Darkness'' and ''Red Spread.'' A central light mass gives additional power to ''Abeyance.''</p>
        <p>On the Edge</p>
        <p>Arlene Bujese Gallery, 66 Newtown Lane, East Hampton. Through Thursday. 324-2823.</p>
        <p>Whether or not it becomes a primary subject, the edge, or boundary, has a role in determining the character of an artwork and the response to it. This group exhibition looks at different ways in which sharp, torn or burnt edges act as major creative forces.</p>
        <p>A serene show that leans toward the cool side in emotional content might be expected, but there are ample surprises. For example, Sidney Butchkes puts excitement in his rhythmically precise flat wooden surfaces by inserting such devices as a band of shimmering nailheads in the wallpiece, ''Four Square.'' In another direction, the seemingly pure geometrics in Eric Ernst's approach actually go a next step by suggesting stagelike spaces in some paintings and objects for contemplation in other works that have a scroll format.</p>
        <p>Rhythmic cascades of shapes defined by burnt edges make Kathleen Kucka's drawings particularly engaging. Impressive, too, are Darlene Charneco's boldly contoured aluminum-covered wooden wall objects that push toward a conceptual mode with hieroglyphic-like letters formed by hundreds of nails.</p>
        <p>Irregular and unpredictable qualities emerge as a sub-theme.  Faith-Dorian Wright sets up vertical alignments with the feathery edges of torn and collaged painted papers in a dense compositional scheme and Sarah Berney activates her strong iconic shapes with the chance characteristics of richly patterned handmade paper. In luminous colored-pencil drawings, Hilary Helfant counterpoints the exactness of her crisp abstract elements by giving them the randomness of scratchy antique surfaces.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
