<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEST SELLERS: May 31, 1998</title>
    <meta content="31BESTHAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1020814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5D81339F932A05756C0A96E958260" item-length="1353" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEST SELLERS: May 31, 1998</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Fiction</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>''N'' IS FOR NOOSE, by Sue Grafton. (Wood/Holt, $25.) Kinsey Millhone pursues the facts behind the sudden, strange death of a cop in a California town.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>YOU BELONG TO ME, by Mary Higgins Clark. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.) A popular radio talk-show host finds herself endangered when she undertakes to expose a killer who targets lonely women on cruise ships.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>A WIDOW FOR ONE YEAR, by John Irving. (Random House, $27.95.) Three looks at the complex emotional life of a writer and single mother.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>MESSAGE IN A BOTTLE, by Nicholas Sparks. (Warner, $20.) After finding a seaborne bottle containing an enigmatic letter, a divorced woman encounters love.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>BLACK AND BLUE, by Anna Quindlen. (Random House, $23.) After her husband turns violent, a woman flees to Florida with her young son to start a new life.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>THE LONG ROAD HOME, by Danielle Steel. (Delacorte, $25.95.) A woman who grew up in a fractured family tries to find the courage to confront the past.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>THE STREET LAWYER, by John Grisham. (Doubleday, $27.95.) A young lawyer comes to terms with himself after discovering his prestigious firm's dirty secret.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>SECRET PREY, by John Sandford. (Putnam, $24.95.) Lucas Davenport pursues the killer of a company chairman who was on a hunting trip with four colleagues.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>CITIES OF THE PLAIN, by Cormac McCarthy. (Knopf, $24.) The concluding volume of a trilogy about two cowboys vexed by changing times.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>MEMOIRS OF A GEISHA, by Arthur Golden. (Knopf, $25.) The life of a young woman growing up in Kyoto who has to reinvent herself after World War II begins.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>A PATCHWORK PLANET, by Anne Tyler. (Knopf, $24.) Estranged from his affluent Baltimore family, a self-destructive, voyeuristic underachiever tries to cope with life and love.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>47</p>
        <p>COLD MOUNTAIN, by Charles Frazier. (Atlantic Monthly, $24.) A wounded Confederate soldier journeys home toward the end of the Civil War.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>DAMASCUS GATE, by Robert Stone. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) Two Americans, a journalist and a singer, get entangled in a plot to blow up holy places in Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>PANDORA, by Anne Rice. (Knopf, $19.95.) A 2,000-year-old vampire recounts her experiences, from imperial Rome to 20th-century Paris and New Orleans.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE TARGET, by Catherine Coulter. (Putnam, $19.95.) The mother of a speechless girl and the hermit who finds her near his cabin are pursued by mysterious men.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Nonfiction</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>32</p>
        <p>TUESDAYS WITH MORRIE, by Mitch Albom. (Doubleday, $19.95.) A sportswriter tells of his weekly visits to his old college mentor, who was near death's door.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>WE ARE OUR MOTHERS' DAUGHTERS, by Cokie Roberts. (Morrow, $19.95.) The television news anchor's personal reflections on women in politics and business and as mothers, wives, sisters and friends.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>STILL ME, by Christopher Reeve. (Random House, $25.) The stage and film actor looks back at his life, especially since his crippling accident three years ago.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>89</p>
        <p>ANGELA'S ASHES, by Frank McCourt. (Scribner, $25.) An Irish-American writer recalls his childhood amid the miseries of Limerick.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>71</p>
        <p>THE MILLIONAIRE NEXT DOOR, by Thomas J. Stanley and William D. Danko. (Longstreet, $22.) An analysis of the lives of wealthy Americans. (+)</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>41</p>
        <p>THE MAN WHO LISTENS TO HORSES, by Monty Roberts. (Random House, $23.) The memoirs of a professional horse trainer.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>*THE GIFTS OF THE JEWS, by Thomas Cahill. (Talese/ Doubleday, $23.50.) What Western civilization owes an ancient nomadic tribe.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>*TALKING TO HEAVEN, by James Van Praagh. (Dutton, $22.95.) A ''world-famous medium'' discusses communication with the other side.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>AMAZING GRACE, by Kathleen Norris. (Riverhead, $24.95.) A poet reflects on her discovery of religious faith and the meaning of its language. (+)</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>TRIUMPH OF JUSTICE, by Daniel Petrocelli with Peter Knobler. (Crown, $25.95.) The lawyer who represented the Goldmans in the O. J. Simpson civil trial explains what it told him about Simpson and our legal system. (+)</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>202</p>
        <p>MIDNIGHT IN THE GARDEN OF GOOD AND EVIL, by John Berendt. (Random House, $25.) The mysterious death of a young man in Savannah, Ga. (+)</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>76</p>
        <p>CONVERSATIONS WITH GOD: BOOK 1, by Neale Donald Walsch. (Putnam, $19.95.) The author addresses questions of good and evil, guilt and sin. (+)</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>CONSILIENCE, by Edward O. Wilson. (Knopf, $26.) The biologist argues that a few fundamental natural laws govern the principles of every branch of learning. (+)</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>APHRODITE, by Isabel Allende. (Harper Flamingo, $26.) A novelist celebrates the pleasures of food and sex.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>51</p>
        <p>THE PERFECT STORM, by Sebastian Junger. (Norton, $23.95.) The story of the nor'easter of 1991, focusing on a crew of fishermen from Gloucester, Mass.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>IN THE MEANTIME, by Iyanla Vanzant. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $23.) Ways to find what you truly need, particularly ''the love that you want.'' (+)</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>SUGAR BUSTERS! by H. Leighton Steward et al. (Ballantine, $22.) A diet designed for losing weight, increasing energy and combating disease. (+)</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>THE 9 STEPS TO FINANCIAL FREEDOM, by Suze Orman. (Crown, $23.) Practical and spiritual steps for managing your money. (+)</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>112</p>
        <p>SIMPLE ABUNDANCE, by Sarah Ban Breathnach. (Warner, $21.) Advice for women seeking to improve the way they look at themselves. (+)</p>
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ending May 16, at almost 4,000 bookstores plus wholesalers serving 50,000 other retailers (gift shops, department stores, newsstands, supermarkets), statistically weighted to represent all such outlets nationwide. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger (+) indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available from The New York Times on the Web: www.nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>And Bear in Mind  (Editors' choices of other recent books of particular interest)</p>
        <p>THE ACCIDENTAL ASIAN: Notes of a Native Speaker, by Eric Liu. (Random House, $23.) Liu, child of a middle-class suburb, feels a certain guilt-ridden ambivalence toward Chinese culture but rejects identity politics and commends a sort of ''omniculturalism'' as America's end product.</p>
        <p>ARK BABY, by Liz Jensen. (Overlook, $24.95.) The author's disorderly second novel satirically examines Darwinism, progress and the notion of scientific certainty through 150 years of Britain.</p>
        <p>THE EVERLASTING STORY OF NORY, by Nicholson Baker. (Random House, $22.) The novelist turns his magnifier on the mentation of a 9-year-old girl protagonist; the details, and the comedy they bring forth, are sharp and clear.</p>
        <p>EVERYBODY WAS SO YOUNG. Gerald and Sara Murphy: A Lost Generation Love Story, by Amanda Vaill. (Houghton Mifflin, $30.) A skillful and comprehensive study of the rich, beautiful American couple who knew everyone there was to know in Paris and Antibes in the 1920's.</p>
        <p>THE KNIFE THROWER: And Other Stories, by Steven Millhauser. (Crown, $22.) Stories whose characters -- dreamers, artists, illusionists -- all run to excess as the author explores our responses to the products and projections of our own minds.</p>
        <p>THE LAST PATRICIAN: Bobby Kennedy and the End of American Aristocracy, by Michael Knox Beran. (St. Martin's, $23.95.) A lively, audacious argument that Robert F. Kennedy in his last years had become what we would now call conservative.</p>
        <p>MAN OR MANGO? A Lament, by Lucy Ellmann. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.) A rambling rant, sometimes very funny, about love and loneliness; its heroine is a grumpy hermit named Eloise.</p>
        <p>A MOTHER'S PLACE: Taking the Debate About Working Mothers Beyond Guilt and Blame, by Susan Chira. (HarperCollins, $25.) From personal experience, interviews and research, the author, an editor at The New York Times, makes the case that good motherhood doesn't require martyrdom.</p>
        <p>OUTSIDE PASSAGE: A Memoir of an Alaskan Childhood, by Julia Scully. (Random House, $23.) Life with a mother present and absent, in San Francisco, an orphanage, Alaska, recalled in a quiet rhetoric with a forgiving moral imagination.</p>
        <p>THE TIME OF OUR TIME, by Norman Mailer. (Random House, $39.50.) A large anthology of his own work in the 50th year of ''The Naked and the Dead'' and the 75th of himself; a veritable social history of postwar America as Mailer (so often correctly) saw it and sometimes made it.</p>
        <p>TITAN: The Life of John D. Rockefeller, Sr., by Ron Chernow. (Random House, $30.) A large-scale, sustained narrative portrait of the founding father, free of visible ideological predispositions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Fiction</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>''N'' IS FOR NOOSE, by Sue Grafton. (Wood/Holt, $25.) Kinsey Millhone pursues the facts behind the sudden, strange death of a cop in a California town.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>YOU BELONG TO ME, by Mary Higgins Clark. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.) A popular radio talk-show host finds herself endangered when she undertakes to expose a killer who targets lonely women on cruise ships.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>A WIDOW FOR ONE YEAR, by John Irving. (Random House, $27.95.) Three looks at the complex emotional life of a writer and single mother.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>MESSAGE IN A BOTTLE, by Nicholas Sparks. (Warner, $20.) After finding a seaborne bottle containing an enigmatic letter, a divorced woman encounters love.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>BLACK AND BLUE, by Anna Quindlen. (Random House, $23.) After her husband turns violent, a woman flees to Florida with her young son to start a new life.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>THE LONG ROAD HOME, by Danielle Steel. (Delacorte, $25.95.) A woman who grew up in a fractured family tries to find the courage to confront the past.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>THE STREET LAWYER, by John Grisham. (Doubleday, $27.95.) A young lawyer comes to terms with himself after discovering his prestigious firm's dirty secret.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>SECRET PREY, by John Sandford. (Putnam, $24.95.) Lucas Davenport pursues the killer of a company chairman who was on a hunting trip with four colleagues.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>CITIES OF THE PLAIN, by Cormac McCarthy. (Knopf, $24.) The concluding volume of a trilogy about two cowboys vexed by changing times.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>MEMOIRS OF A GEISHA, by Arthur Golden. (Knopf, $25.) The life of a young woman growing up in Kyoto who has to reinvent herself after World War II begins.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>A PATCHWORK PLANET, by Anne Tyler. (Knopf, $24.) Estranged from his affluent Baltimore family, a self-destructive, voyeuristic underachiever tries to cope with life and love.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>47</p>
        <p>COLD MOUNTAIN, by Charles Frazier. (Atlantic Monthly, $24.) A wounded Confederate soldier journeys home toward the end of the Civil War.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>DAMASCUS GATE, by Robert Stone. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) Two Americans, a journalist and a singer, get entangled in a plot to blow up holy places in Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>PANDORA, by Anne Rice. (Knopf, $19.95.) A 2,000-year-old vampire recounts her experiences, from imperial Rome to 20th-century Paris and New Orleans.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE TARGET, by Catherine Coulter. (Putnam, $19.95.) The mother of a speechless girl and the hermit who finds her near his cabin are pursued by mysterious men.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Nonfiction</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>32</p>
        <p>TUESDAYS WITH MORRIE, by Mitch Albom. (Doubleday, $19.95.) A sportswriter tells of his weekly visits to his old college mentor, who was near death's door.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>WE ARE OUR MOTHERS' DAUGHTERS, by Cokie Roberts. (Morrow, $19.95.) The television news anchor's personal reflections on women in politics and business and as mothers, wives, sisters and friends.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>STILL ME, by Christopher Reeve. (Random House, $25.) The stage and film actor looks back at his life, especially since his crippling accident three years ago.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>89</p>
        <p>ANGELA'S ASHES, by Frank McCourt. (Scribner, $25.) An Irish-American writer recalls his childhood amid the miseries of Limerick.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>71</p>
        <p>THE MILLIONAIRE NEXT DOOR, by Thomas J. Stanley and William D. Danko. (Longstreet, $22.) An analysis of the lives of wealthy Americans. (+)</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>41</p>
        <p>THE MAN WHO LISTENS TO HORSES, by Monty Roberts. (Random House, $23.) The memoirs of a professional horse trainer.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>*THE GIFTS OF THE JEWS, by Thomas Cahill. (Talese/ Doubleday, $23.50.) What Western civilization owes an ancient nomadic tribe.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>*TALKING TO HEAVEN, by James Van Praagh. (Dutton, $22.95.) A ''world-famous medium'' discusses communication with the other side.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>AMAZING GRACE, by Kathleen Norris. (Riverhead, $24.95.) A poet reflects on her discovery of religious faith and the meaning of its language. (+)</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>TRIUMPH OF JUSTICE, by Daniel Petrocelli with Peter Knobler. (Crown, $25.95.) The lawyer who represented the Goldmans in the O. J. Simpson civil trial explains what it told him about Simpson and our legal system. (+)</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>202</p>
        <p>MIDNIGHT IN THE GARDEN OF GOOD AND EVIL, by John Berendt. (Random House, $25.) The mysterious death of a young man in Savannah, Ga. (+)</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>76</p>
        <p>CONVERSATIONS WITH GOD: BOOK 1, by Neale Donald Walsch. (Putnam, $19.95.) The author addresses questions of good and evil, guilt and sin. (+)</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>CONSILIENCE, by Edward O. Wilson. (Knopf, $26.) The biologist argues that a few fundamental natural laws govern the principles of every branch of learning. (+)</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>APHRODITE, by Isabel Allende. (Harper Flamingo, $26.) A novelist celebrates the pleasures of food and sex.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>51</p>
        <p>THE PERFECT STORM, by Sebastian Junger. (Norton, $23.95.) The story of the nor'easter of 1991, focusing on a crew of fishermen from Gloucester, Mass.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>IN THE MEANTIME, by Iyanla Vanzant. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $23.) Ways to find what you truly need, particularly ''the love that you want.'' (+)</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>SUGAR BUSTERS! by H. Leighton Steward et al. (Ballantine, $22.) A diet designed for losing weight, increasing energy and combating disease. (+)</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>THE 9 STEPS TO FINANCIAL FREEDOM, by Suze Orman. (Crown, $23.) Practical and spiritual steps for managing your money. (+)</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>112</p>
        <p>SIMPLE ABUNDANCE, by Sarah Ban Breathnach. (Warner, $21.) Advice for women seeking to improve the way they look at themselves. (+)</p>
        <p>Rankings reflect sales, for the week ending May 16, at almost 4,000 bookstores plus wholesalers serving 50,000 other retailers (gift shops, department stores, newsstands, supermarkets), statistically weighted to represent all such outlets nationwide. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger (+) indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders. Expanded rankings are available from The New York Times on the Web: www.nytimes.com/books.</p>
        <p>And Bear in Mind  (Editors' choices of other recent books of particular interest)</p>
        <p>THE ACCIDENTAL ASIAN: Notes of a Native Speaker, by Eric Liu. (Random House, $23.) Liu, child of a middle-class suburb, feels a certain guilt-ridden ambivalence toward Chinese culture but rejects identity politics and commends a sort of ''omniculturalism'' as America's end product.</p>
        <p>ARK BABY, by Liz Jensen. (Overlook, $24.95.) The author's disorderly second novel satirically examines Darwinism, progress and the notion of scientific certainty through 150 years of Britain.</p>
        <p>THE EVERLASTING STORY OF NORY, by Nicholson Baker. (Random House, $22.) The novelist turns his magnifier on the mentation of a 9-year-old girl protagonist; the details, and the comedy they bring forth, are sharp and clear.</p>
        <p>EVERYBODY WAS SO YOUNG. Gerald and Sara Murphy: A Lost Generation Love Story, by Amanda Vaill. (Houghton Mifflin, $30.) A skillful and comprehensive study of the rich, beautiful American couple who knew everyone there was to know in Paris and Antibes in the 1920's.</p>
        <p>THE KNIFE THROWER: And Other Stories, by Steven Millhauser. (Crown, $22.) Stories whose characters -- dreamers, artists, illusionists -- all run to excess as the author explores our responses to the products and projections of our own minds.</p>
        <p>THE LAST PATRICIAN: Bobby Kennedy and the End of American Aristocracy, by Michael Knox Beran. (St. Martin's, $23.95.) A lively, audacious argument that Robert F. Kennedy in his last years had become what we would now call conservative.</p>
        <p>MAN OR MANGO? A Lament, by Lucy Ellmann. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.) A rambling rant, sometimes very funny, about love and loneliness; its heroine is a grumpy hermit named Eloise.</p>
        <p>A MOTHER'S PLACE: Taking the Debate About Working Mothers Beyond Guilt and Blame, by Susan Chira. (HarperCollins, $25.) From personal experience, interviews and research, the author, an editor at The New York Times, makes the case that good motherhood doesn't require martyrdom.</p>
        <p>OUTSIDE PASSAGE: A Memoir of an Alaskan Childhood, by Julia Scully. (Random House, $23.) Life with a mother present and absent, in San Francisco, an orphanage, Alaska, recalled in a quiet rhetoric with a forgiving moral imagination.</p>
        <p>THE TIME OF OUR TIME, by Norman Mailer. (Random House, $39.50.) A large anthology of his own work in the 50th year of ''The Naked and the Dead'' and the 75th of himself; a veritable social history of postwar America as Mailer (so often correctly) saw it and sometimes made it.</p>
        <p>TITAN: The Life of John D. Rockefeller, Sr., by Ron Chernow. (Random House, $30.) A large-scale, sustained narrative portrait of the founding father, free of visible ideological predispositions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
