<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="31FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1021188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7D91F38F932A05756C0A96E958260" item-length="627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-10</p>
        <p>Pakistan, Spurning Critics, Holds More Nuclear Tests  Pakistan said it exploded another nuclear test device, spurning worldwide criticism and calls for restraint after its tests two days ago. But the Government also said that Pakistan was ready to ''talk peace'' with India and that ''it is not our purpose to enter into an arms race.''</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>India's Cool Response  India delayed a formal response to Pakistan's latest nuclear test, but a senior official said India did not regard nuclear testing as a ''competition'' requiring New Delhi to match each move by Pakistan.</p>
        <p>8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-10</p>
        <p>Pakistan, Spurning Critics, Holds More Nuclear Tests  Pakistan said it exploded another nuclear test device, spurning worldwide criticism and calls for restraint after its tests two days ago. But the Government also said that Pakistan was ready to ''talk peace'' with India and that ''it is not our purpose to enter into an arms race.''</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>India's Cool Response  India delayed a formal response to Pakistan's latest nuclear test, but a senior official said India did not regard nuclear testing as a ''competition'' requiring New Delhi to match each move by Pakistan.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Anger in Washington  The U.S. reacted with anger and frustration to Pakistan's test, and Administration officials said they had few new ideas about how to stop an arms race in South Asia.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Indonesia Deadlines Eased  Responding to the deepening economic and political uncertainties in Indonesia, a top I.M.F. official said deadlines for austerity measures would be eased.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Japanese Coalition Splits  Japan's four-year-old governing coalition fractured as the weakened Social Democratic Party formally announced it would quit.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>12-22</p>
        <p>Disabled Students Lose on Language Policy  A Federal judge ruled that Boston University did not have to allow liberal arts undergraduates with learning disabilities to substitute other courses for a two-year foreign-language requirement.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>New Action on Old Drug Route  Drug enforcement officials say that the seizure of 4,000 pounds of cocaine from a pleasure boat in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., was another indication that after concentrating on other routes in the 1980's and 1990's, Colombian drug traffickers are returning with renewed intensity to the familiar routes between the Bahamas and Florida.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>Acceptance of Homosexuals  Although American acceptance of gay men and lesbians has swelled dramatically in recent years, as has support for their civil rights, they remain one of the least liked groups in the country, according to a study by the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force.</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Boxer in Stride in California  In California, a state that dependably provides its share of political surprises, one unexpected development this election season is that Senator Barbara Boxer is not slouching but striding toward the primary on Tuesday and the general election in November, an underdog transformed into a front-runner.</p>
        <p>18</p>
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>25-31</p>
        <p>A Polyglot Library  The Flushing branch of the Queens Borough Public Library, the busiest branch in the nation's busiest library system, shows clearly that the immigrant's path to the American dream includes frequent trips to the local library. For three years, the branch has been shoehorned into a former furniture store on Main Street. But soon, a new $35 million building will open nearby.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Pursuing a Housing Dream  Seven years ago, a group of Dominican immigrants set out to transform an abandoned Bronx apartment house into a homesteaders' dream. But none of them envisioned the lawsuits, eviction notices, and confrontations with city housing officials .</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>New Building for Trump  The General Motors Building, situated across Fifth Avenue from Central Park, has been sold to Donald Trump and an Indianopolis insurance company for $800 million.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>FRESH AIR FUND</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>Television</p>
        <p>32</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>31</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
