<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inquiry Finds Secret Deal Between Workers for L.I.R.R. and Garden</title>
    <meta content="25LIRR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/25/nyregion/25lirr.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1637195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Madison Square Garden</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Rail Road Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chan, Sewell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dermody, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Long Island Rail Road Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1DA1E30F936A15751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inquiry Finds Secret Deal Between Workers for L.I.R.R. and Garden</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Inquiry Finds Secret Deal Between Workers for L.I.R.R. and Garden</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEWELL CHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chan, Sewell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investigation finds that conductors on Long Island Railroad allow workers at Madison Square Garden free rides on trains in exchange for free entry into events at MSG; arrangement may have lasted since 1999; James Dermody, railroads president, takes immediate action to stop arrangement that he calls clear violation of rail pass policy; Madison Square Garden says it has not seen report, but that they had been first to bring issue to attention of LIRR; report does not find that any laws were broken; MSG sit atop LIRR terminal at Pennsylvania Station (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Conductors on the Long Island Rail Road allowed employees of Madison Square Garden to ride without paying, and in return workers at the arena gave employees of the commuter railroad free admission to sports events, the inspector general for the Metropolitan Transportation Authority has found.</p>
        <p>The arrangement may have lasted from 1999 until this year, although it was not approved by top officials at either entity, according to a recent report by the inspector general, Matthew D. Sansverie, whose office is responsible for investigating allegations of waste, fraud or abuse at the authority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Conductors allowed employees of Madison Square Garden to ride without paying, and in return workers at the arena let employees of the commuter railroad attend events for free.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Conductors on the Long Island Rail Road allowed employees of Madison Square Garden to ride without paying, and in return workers at the arena gave employees of the commuter railroad free admission to sports events, the inspector general for the Metropolitan Transportation Authority has found.</p>
        <p>The arrangement may have lasted from 1999 until this year, although it was not approved by top officials at either entity, according to a recent report by the inspector general, Matthew D. Sansverie, whose office is responsible for investigating allegations of waste, fraud or abuse at the authority.</p>
        <p>''It is impossible to quantify the amount of lost revenue attributable to either entity as a result of this agreement,'' Mr. Sansverie wrote in a report dated Oct. 28. He urged the railroad to reinstruct its train conductors on fare collection policies. A copy of the report was obtained from the inspector general's office under the state's Freedom of Information Law.</p>
        <p>The arrangement is not the first time that employees of the railroad have been found to have accepted improper gifts. The railroad's last president, Kenneth J. Bauer, and five managers received meals and entertainment worth thousands of dollars from companies that worked for the railroad or sought work from it, according to an investigation by Mr. Sansverie's office last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bauer, who resigned before that investigation was completed, denied any impropriety at the time.</p>
        <p>The railroad's current president, James J. Dermody, took action before the last investigation was completed, according to documents. The railroad's chief transportation officer, Jane F. Dietz, issued a notice on June 11 warning train conductors that the inspector general had ''confirmed numerous instances in which Madison Square Garden employees have been allowed free rail travel in return for free admissions.''</p>
        <p>In the notice, Ms. Dietz warned that the arrangement was ''in clear violation of our rail pass policy'' and ''will not be tolerated.'' She added that train conductors should note the name and organization of anyone who offers an invalid pass.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dermody took prompt action after learning of the problem, said a spokesman, Brian P. Dolan, adding, ''We don't believe it's continued.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Madison Square Garden said its officials had not seen the report, but noted that they had been the first to bring concerns about the arrangement to the attention of investigators.</p>
        <p>''While the M.T.A. has not furnished us with its report, we did inform the M.T.A. of our concerns,'' said the spokesman, Barry Watkins. ''Any activity like that described in the report is in violation of our company policies and will be handled appropriately.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Sansverie's report does not find that any laws were broken, it provides a window into a cozy and informal arrangement that apparently existed between employees of the two entities. Madison Square Garden, which opened at its current location in 1968, is located on top of Pennsylvania Station -- the Manhattan terminus of the railroad -- on Seventh Avenue between 31st and 33rd Streets. Cablevision, a cable television and telecommunications company based in Bethpage, N.Y., owns the arena.</p>
        <p>In October 2002, the arena's general manager at the time, Michael Julian, informed the inspector general's office after he observed ''an inordinate number of people'' spilling into the arena's tunnels at a Rolling Stones concert, according to the report. The activity at the concert led Mr. Julian to believe that some of those people had not purchased tickets but had been given free entry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Julian also told investigators he had previously seen uniformed railroad workers at odd hours during the day and had believed they were passing time inside the arena between work shifts. Employees at the arena told him the arrangement had existed ''for at least three years,'' according to the report.</p>
        <p>On 21 occasions between November 2002 and February 2003, investigators received free passage on the railroad by presenting Madison Square Garden identification cards. Conductors refused to accept the credential four times, according to the report.In turn, the report shows, investigators bearing railroad identifications were allowed free admission into three events at the arena: a New York Liberty women's basketball game on July 15, 2003; a heavyweight boxing event on Dec. 6, 2003; and a sold-out New York Knicks men's basketball game on Jan. 9, 2004. Mr. Sansverie concluded that ''this arrangement is unsanctioned and results more from underground, and therefore uneven, communication rather than any officially circulated accommodation.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
