<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Migrant Oasis; Central American Day Laborers Are Drawn to a Suburb</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="688559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIGRANT LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ILLEGAL ALIENS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SPRING VALLEY (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MAMARONECK (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOUNT KISCO (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GUATEMALA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EL SALVADOR</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HONDURAS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERNANDEZ, RAYMOND</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMPSON, ALLAN (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/El Salvador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Honduras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Guatemala</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migrant Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6D81338F932A15756C0A962958260" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Migrant Oasis; Central American Day Laborers Are Drawn to a Suburb</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERNANDEZ, RAYMOND</byline>
      <dateline>SPRING VALLEY, N.Y., May 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Journeying across nations in search of work, Lazaro Chinchilla arrived here about a month ago to share a run-down bungalow with seven other men in a rugged settlement of migrants like himself.</p>
        <p>"Hunger brought us here," Mr. Chinchilla, an immigrant from Guatemala, said the other day as he wandered along one of the dusty roads that lace the settlement, called El Petencito by its residents. "But it feels like we have come to the edge of the earth."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Journeying across nations in search of work, Lazaro Chinchilla arrived here about a month ago to share a run-down bungalow with seven other men in a rugged settlement of migrants like himself.</p>
        <p>"Hunger brought us here," Mr. Chinchilla, an immigrant from Guatemala, said the other day as he wandered along one of the dusty roads that lace the settlement, called El Petencito by its residents. "But it feels like we have come to the edge of the earth."</p>
        <p>In fact, the small community of some 20 bungalows housing slightly more than 100 is only a few steps from the buzz and neon glow of Route 59, a typically suburban strip of dairy marts, fast-food joints and car dealerships in this Rockland County village.</p>
        <p>But tucked behind a wooded area alongside a waterfall, El Petencito -- named after part of Guatemala's frontier -- is an outpost of Central American workers who have come here in search of jobs laying bricks, planting trees, mowing lawns, tending gardens, cleaning homes, whatever they can get.</p>
        <p>Only a generation or so ago this same cluster of bungalows was known simply as Hyenga Lake, a popular summer retreat for New York City residents seeking a respite from the urban grind. Its transformation into a migrant camp underscores how the quest for work has driven some of the metropolitan New York region's newest immigrants to improbable places.</p>
        <p>The Guatemalans and Salvadorans who have settled in El Petencito are little different from the Mexican day laborers who gather at dawn on a street corner in Mamaroneck in Westchester County or the Hondurans who wait each morning for jobs along Main Street in Mount Kisco farther up county. The Center for Immigrants Rights in Manhattan estimates that there are about 3,000 such day laborers in the region, most of them from Central American countries.</p>
        <p>But the striking thing about El Petencito -- where the yards and paths are a jumble of clothes lines, wooden crates, gardening tools and broken cars -- is that, only 25 miles north of the George Washington Bridge, it resembles a tightly knit and secluded Central American village. At dusk, men gather alongside bungalows trading stories and news about their homeland as the rattle of pans and dishes echo from within the houses.</p>
        <p>Many of its settlers -- including some who admit they are in the country illegally -- say they are simply passing through with the aim of amassing enough savings to take back a nest egg for their families at home.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, El Petencito represents an inexpensive way station where the rents -- which residents say run $600 to $700 a month for each bungalow -- are split among the men who cram themselves into its bungalows.</p>
        <p>"I sleep on the floor or wherever," said Mr. Chinchilla, who is 45 years old.</p>
        <p>This is not the first time that Mr. Chinchilla has come to Spring Valley for work. He spent a year here in 1987 washing dishes at a local restaurant for $300 a week before returning to his wife and four children with $1,500 in savings.</p>
        <p>This time he makes as much as $50 a day in landscaping and construction work. "I don't know when I will go back," he said. "But this area is good because there are many jobs."</p>
        <p>Not everyone is pleased about El Petencito, most of which is within the boundaries of Clarkstown. As the newcomers have proliferated in the last few years, some longtime residents have complained of litter, overcrowding and other problems that they contend have put a strain on local services.</p>
        <p>"I've been down there a couple of times, and I'm appalled by the conditions," said Spring Valley's Mayor, Allan Thompson. "I'm sure most of them are law-abiding people who want an opportunity. But it is not the kind of environment I like to see close to my village."</p>
        <p>The entrance to El Petencito is marked by rows of metal mailboxes often stuffed with letters arriving from abroad. The people of the settlement gather there each morning, on the edges of Route 59, to secure a day's work from anyone who will hire them.</p>
        <p>Their way of life has its risks. Juan Hernandez, 39, said the owner of a landscaping company had hired him to plant trees and flowers one day four months ago. At the end of the day, however, the man drove Mr. Hernandez back to the settlement and refused to pay.</p>
        <p>"He told me he'd pay me the next day, but never did," Mr. Hernandez recalled. "Almost all of us have been through something like that. It's part of the life here."</p>
        <p>These days, though, he works full time at a factory where he prints designs on shirts. Earning about $200 a week, Mr. Hernandez regularly wires money to his wife and three children in Guatemala.</p>
        <p>"It saddens me not to be with them." he said. "But it's a sacrifice that I have to make to support my family."</p>
        <p>Jobs are not the only thing that bring the newcomers to suburban hamlets. Many say that such areas offers them a level of security and tranquillity that they feel is lacking in larger cities like New York and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>"My intention was to stay in New York City when I came," said Juan Jose Ramirez, as he washed his car at the edge of a lake near his bungalow.</p>
        <p>"But in the city," the 22-year-old Guatemalan immigrant continued, "we would live in despair, locked up inside apartments. This is much calmer; it reminds me of our country."</p>
        <p>Likewise, Alejandro Medina, 22, said he left Bridgeport, Conn., where he was living with a friend, after his family urged him to join them in El Petencito. "They told me that there was work and that I would be living with my own people," he recalled.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
