<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A.L. Central Has Taken the Beast Out of the East</title>
    <meta content="02baseball" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/02/sports/baseball/02baseball.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1773460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="AROUND THE MAJORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Minnesota Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E5D81530F931A35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A.L. Central Has Taken the Beast Out of the East</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A.L. Central Has Taken the Beast Out of the East</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the last three weeks of June, the Detroit Tigers, the Chicago White Sox and the Minnesota Twins played better baseball than any other teams in the major leagues. They kept playing, they kept prevailing and, because of that mutual consistency, they mostly stayed status quo in the powerful American League Central.</p>
        <p>While it is easy to argue that the standings are fluid in July because so much can still change, what is not irrelevant is how the three bulldozing teams may eventually influence the wild-card tussle. With the teams from the Central soaring, some team from the A.L. East could end up being vulnerable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American League East has taken a back seat to the Central.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the last three weeks of June, the Detroit Tigers, the Chicago White Sox and the Minnesota Twins played better baseball than any other teams in the major leagues. They kept playing, they kept prevailing and, because of that mutual consistency, they mostly stayed status quo in the powerful American League Central.</p>
        <p>While it is easy to argue that the standings are fluid in July because so much can still change, what is not irrelevant is how the three bulldozing teams may eventually influence the wild-card tussle. With the teams from the Central soaring, some team from the A.L. East could end up being vulnerable.</p>
        <p>The Yankees and Boston, which just ended a 12-game winning streak, have almost viewed playoff spots as their birthright. But that may not happen this season. The Yankees and the Red Sox, who fight for everything anyway, could be fighting with the Toronto Blue Jays for one spot.</p>
        <p>''That might be the case this time,'' the Yankees' Johnny Damon said. ''We know how precious it is.''</p>
        <p>Yankees reliever Mike Myers, who, like Damon, played for the Red Sox last year, said the Tigers, the White Sox and the Twins had impressed him with their nonstop winning. The White Sox won 16 of their last 20 games in June, and the Tigers and the Twins each won 18 of 20 before yesterday's games.</p>
        <p>''You can talk about the last two weeks,'' Myers said. ''But that's only one-twelfth of the season.''</p>
        <p>With half the season almost over, however, the surprising Tigers and the White Sox, the defending World Series champion, can do more than dream about making plans to play in October.</p>
        <p>The Tigers led the majors with a 3.48 earned run average entering yesterday, and their sturdy pitching staff should enable them to avoid a letdown. Although it is has been chic to predict that the once-terrible Tigers will tumble, the wait continues and it may continue for a while.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the White Sox, whose vaunted starters carried them to a title last season, may be a superior team this season. Even though they have had uneven performances from Jon Garland and Javier Vázquez, they have a stronger lineup with Jim Thome and the look and feel of a team that could repeat.</p>
        <p>''I think the way we play right now, it seems like everything bounces our way,'' White Sox Manager Ozzie Guillén said. ''It seems like we are in the World Series.''</p>
        <p>If a team from the Central secures the wild card, that will mean that either the Yankees, who have appeared in the postseason for 11 straight years, or the Red Sox, who have been in the playoffs for five of the last eight years, will not qualify. For the last three years, the Yankees have won the A.L. East and the Red Sox the wild card.</p>
        <p>As of now, the Yankees would be the ones squeezed. There is an irritating situation brewing for George Steinbrenner, the principal owner of the Yankees: the Mets and the Red Sox may make the playoffs and the Yankees may not.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre said he always wants the Yankees to shoot for the division title, adding that the A.L. East and the wild card were not decided until the final weekend of 2005.</p>
        <p>''Anytime you feel like you have a safety net, that's going to come back and bite you,'' Torre said. ''You can't sit back and think you'll get the wild card.''</p>
        <p>Torre seemingly thinks the Yankees will have to overtake the Red Sox to reach the playoffs. When he was asked about the possibility of the Tigers or the White Sox deteriorating, he spoke highly of them and did not sound as if he envisioned that happening.</p>
        <p>''We have to win our share of games and hope that's enough,'' Torre said. ''It's certainly not going to be easy.''</p>
        <p>Vote Early and Often</p>
        <p>The Pittsburgh Pirates are playing host to the All-Star Game at PNC Park on July 11, and they decided to be hands-on hosts, really hands-on. The Pirates have been aggressive and creative in trying to assure that their players get as many fan votes as possible.</p>
        <p>In a marketing blitz that would make the shrewdest politicians applaud, the Pirates have repeatedly reminded fans to vote, vote and vote some more for their favorite locals. The actions are legitimate, although they are somewhat dubious because the Pirates have the worst record in the National League.</p>
        <p>The strategy has worked because Jason Bay is the leading vote-getter among outfielders. When the voting totals were first announced, on May 30, Bay was 19th among outfielders. In addition to Bay, third baseman Freddy Sanchez has the most write-in votes and shortstop Jack Wilson is second in the voting at shortstop.</p>
        <p>Jim Trdinich, the Pirates' media relations director, said the radio and television broadcasters offered reminders 5 to 10 times a game. There are scoreboard reminders during games, too. The team set up a kiosk outside the park so fans who do not go to games can vote online. Employees received e-mail messages asking them to vote and to persuade others to vote.</p>
        <p>To help the candidacy of Bay, a Canadian who attended Gonzaga University, the Pirates asked the Canadian Baseball Hall of Fame and his alma mater to send e-mail messages supporting him to their constituents. A fan may vote 25 times for each e-mail address, so the bulk of Pittsburgh's plans have revolved around online voting.</p>
        <p>''They've gotten the word out as much as anyone I can remember,'' said Pat Courtney, a spokesman for Major League Baseball. ''It's pretty remarkable.''</p>
        <p>While Bay deserves to be an All-Star, Pittsburgh's zealousness could get dicey for major league officials if, for instance, Wilson passes the Mets' José Reyes. Reyes is the worthier candidate. The starters will be announced today.</p>
        <p>Trdinich has thoroughly embraced the campaign. When Pearl Jam played at Mellon Arena in Pittsburgh recently, Trdinich, who is friends with one of the band's roadies, explained the team's push for Bay. During the encore, Eddie Vedder, the lead singer, told fans to vote for Bay.</p>
        <p>''That was the biggest coup we got,'' Trdinich said.</p>
        <p>Red Sox Serenade</p>
        <p>Ben Harper's music is an appealing combination of soul, funk, blues and rock. But Harper's allegiances as a fan are not so varied. Harper is strictly Los Angeles. He adores the Dodgers, the Lakers and the Kings.</p>
        <p>So how did a Southern California surfer write a song featuring Babe Ruth and Johnny Damon? Harper said he was inspired to compile ''Get It Like You Like It'' on the album ''Both Sides of the Gun'' because he considered Damon's grand slam in the decisive game of the 2004 American League Championship Series a defining moment in sports.</p>
        <p>''When that curse was about to be broken, the emotion of it transcended what team you were a fan of,'' Harper said. ''When he hit that grand slam, you knew something was going to shift in that city like never before.''</p>
        <p>Shortly after Damon's Red Sox shocked the Yankees and won their first World Series title in 86 years, Harper wrote these lyrics: ''In 1918, the Great Bambino kicked a piano into Willis Pond. But Johnny Damon swung a bat. Grand slam, that was that. An 86-year curse is gone.''</p>
        <p>Damon is aware of the song but has not heard it. When Damon finally hears it, he may feel as if he were standing beside Harper on the beach with a bonfire blazing. It is that kind of tune.</p>
        <p>''It just shows you how big that was,'' Damon said. ''It never goes away.''</p>
        <p>While Bostonians were aghast when Damon became a Yankee, Harper said it gave him an opportunity.</p>
        <p>''One thing about him being in New York, now at least I can play the song there,'' Harper said.</p>
        <p>Hunter's Fate</p>
        <p>Torii Hunter has a $12 million option with Minnesota for 2007, but it seems doubtful the Twins will exercise it. Or will they? Hunter is puzzled about his uncertain future.</p>
        <p>''If I was a betting man, I think I might be here with a long-term deal,'' Hunter said.</p>
        <p>Later, Hunter wondered if he might be traded for prospects. ''If I was the G.M., I'd do that,'' Hunter said.</p>
        <p>Later still, Hunter noted that the Twins were in the postseason hunt and concluded, ''I can't see them trading me.''</p>
        <p>Good Field</p>
        <p>Everyone knows pitching and defense win championships, right? So the Red Sox should feel optimistic because they set a major league record Friday by playing their 17th straight game without making an error. (The streak ended last night, when they made two errors.) Boston, with new starters in the four infield spots and in center field, has 25 errors, fewest in the majors.</p>
        <p>As impressive as their defensive statistics are, it is worthwhile to remember that defense was not a Red Sox specialty when they won the title in 2004, when only five major league teams had more errors. Poor defense did not stall them then. Will nifty defense power them now?</p>
        <p>AROUND THE MAJORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
