<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grieving, and Tired of Fighting the Current</title>
    <meta content="02towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/02/nyregion/02towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1773422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Our Towns"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D91530F931A35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grieving, and Tired of Fighting the Current</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Grieving, and Tired of Fighting the Current</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>Livingston Manor, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN he saw how bad it was -- 400,000 soggy cards to throw in the Dumpster, a life's worth of memories turned to waterlogged garbage -- Barry Foster thought: This is it. No more.</p>
        <p>And then he thought, what kind of an example does he set if he quits? What kind of a message is that? So he'll be back in business as soon as the store dries out, selling what he has left at Hot Corner Sports Collectibles to whoever shows up at what should have been the best weekend of the short Catskill summer. And then after the summer he'll think about it again. He's not a quitter, but he's not an idiot, either.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many residents in Livingstone Manor, N.Y., face a tough road to recovery after recent flooding but few talk of giving up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN he saw how bad it was -- 400,000 soggy cards to throw in the Dumpster, a life's worth of memories turned to waterlogged garbage -- Barry Foster thought: This is it. No more.</p>
        <p>And then he thought, what kind of an example does he set if he quits? What kind of a message is that? So he'll be back in business as soon as the store dries out, selling what he has left at Hot Corner Sports Collectibles to whoever shows up at what should have been the best weekend of the short Catskill summer. And then after the summer he'll think about it again. He's not a quitter, but he's not an idiot, either.</p>
        <p>''Fords, Mantles, Sniders, Koufaxes, I can't tell you everything I threw out,'' said Mr. Foster, a former high school principal who opened up his dream store in time for three nightmare floods, the largest of which came last week, ruining perhaps $100,000 worth of collectibles, a life's work. ''To be honest, I can't think of too many times I've been worse.''</p>
        <p>Across Main Street on Friday, the tapestry on the wall at Fir Brook Flies and Supplies showed a fish and the logo ''Welcome to our piece of paradise.'' Paradise had mud on the floor that had reached three feet high when the flood crested and was still caked up in a muddy goo under the fixtures.</p>
        <p>Inside was a remarkable craftsman named Richard Bradley, who makes custom-made fly reels he sells all over the world. Ninety percent of his inventory was destroyed.</p>
        <p>He'll have to see what, if anything, can be salvaged of the machinery, buried in water and muck, that he used to make the rods. He figures he'll be back too, though he's not sure how.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to be a Benedict Arnold and cut and run,'' he said, workers sweeping mud off the linoleum behind him. ''But I don't know when people say, ''Enough is enough' ''</p>
        <p>Offered good luck, he didn't seem to want any. ''Luck,'' he said, ''is for rabbits.''</p>
        <p>You can tell the story of the Catskills in this little town at the intersection of three streams, where the sign on Main Street reads: ''Welcome to Livingston Manor: Small town. Big back yard.''</p>
        <p>During the golden days of the 50's and 60's it flourished with the Catskill resorts and bungalows. During the grim years, which hit their nadir in the early 90's, it felt like a place in a death spiral, kept alive only because the Livingston Manor lifers were too stubborn to desert the corpse.</p>
        <p>And these days, it's been the image of the Catskills reborn, both rustic and fashionable, with cool shops and galleries, a bookstore and a bakery. And the population now is a mix -- not always a happy one -- of wary old-timers and hip transplants from New York City.</p>
        <p>That was before three storms of the century in 22 months. Before the businesses on Main Street dug out three times. And before a 15-year-old girl, who walked around town all day listening to music on her Walkman, was washed away in Wednesday's flood. So there's still brave talk about the town's future. Some buy it. Some don't.</p>
        <p>''After the last storm, I said we'd have water running down Main Street, we'd lose houses and we'd lose lives,'' said John Parker. ''No one listened.''</p>
        <p>He's standing in front of his house, across from a sign, green spray paint on plywood, reading ''R.I.P. Jaime,'' and the wreckage of the house where the girl, Jaime Bertholf, was swept away when a cascade of water cut a new channel around a bridge clogged with debris, reducing her house to rubble. Had the water stayed where it was, it would have washed away Mr. Parker's house instead. He's not planning to stay around for the next one. ''It's a nice town, but if something isn't done, eventually there isn't going to be a Main Street,'' he said.</p>
        <p>STILL, on Friday there were fevered efforts to prepare for the weekend. Andrea Brown was cleaning up her month-old gallery, the Outsider Art Studio, to prepare for a show opening today. It's not too often you get to say you'll be ready come hell or high water and mean it literally.</p>
        <p>Across the street at the terrific Hamish &amp; Henry bookstore, Jeff Christensen said people were trying to look ahead.</p>
        <p>''The first order of business is bucking up the spirits of downtrodden retailers,'' he said. ''We just have to see what kind of financial support we can get so retailers don't say, 'We can't do this anymore.' ''</p>
        <p>Actually if that's Item 1, then Item 1A, after years of bickering and delay, is getting critical mass from state and federal officials for a regional plan for dealing with flood control and river maintenance.</p>
        <p>It's one of those things that never seem too urgent, until a 15-year-old girl is swept away into a roaring flood, until a town and a region face three catastrophes in two years, until people realize you can face three strikes but maybe you just can't handle one more.</p>
        <p>Our Towns E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
