<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ULTIMATUM</title>
    <meta content="16HOCK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/16/sports/16hockey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1650452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Hockey League Players Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bettman, Gary</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DD133AF935A25751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1343" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ULTIMATUM</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sides Move Closer, but N.H.L. Stands by 'Final Offer'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE; Jason Diamos contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NHL rejects players union's final proposal for $49 million salary cap per team and union responds by saying it will make no further offers, signaling what will likely be cancelled 2004-5 hockey season; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A rapid exchange of compromises on the critical issue of a salary cap stalled late last night when N.H.L. Commissioner Gary Bettman told the locked-out players ''we cannot afford your proposal'' for a payroll limit of $49 million per team.</p>
        <p>Around midnight, Bob Goodenow, the executive director of the players union, responded with a letter detailing what he called flaws in Bettman's calculations and ending with ''you will receive nothing further from us.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The players on Tuesday debated an ultimatum issued by their employers: accept a payroll limit of $42.5 million per team by 11 a.m. Wednesday or sacrifice the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A rapid exchange of compromises on the critical issue of a salary cap stalled late last night when N.H.L. Commissioner Gary Bettman told the locked-out players ''we cannot afford your proposal'' for a payroll limit of $49 million per team.</p>
        <p>Around midnight, Bob Goodenow, the executive director of the players union, responded with a letter detailing what he called flaws in Bettman's calculations and ending with ''you will receive nothing further from us.''</p>
        <p>Bettman and the 30 team owners said they would stick to their demand for a $42.5 million salary cap, what they described as their final offer on a day of unusually public negotiations. The talks were conducted electronically between league headquarters in New York and union headquarters in Toronto and published quickly on their respective Web sites.</p>
        <p>If the union refuses to accept the league's proposal by today's 11 a.m. deadline, Bettman says he will hold a news conference at a Manhattan hotel to cancel the season. The N.H.L. would become the first North American sports league to cancel a season because of a labor dispute.</p>
        <p>The new proposals followed secretive talks on Monday night between top union and league officials, who dropped significant philosophical demands that had caused the league to shut down Sept. 16.</p>
        <p>The union dropped its opposition to a salary cap; the league dropped its demand for ''cost certainty,'' a link between payrolls and revenue. The sides also agreed to a union proposal for a salary rollback of 24 percent.</p>
        <p>''We have no more flexibility and there is no time for further negotiation,'' Bettman told Goodenow. Bettman warned that the deal could ''only get worse for the players if we cancel the season'' and that ''whatever damage we have suffered to date will pale in comparison to the damage from a canceled season.''</p>
        <p>Goodenow responded: ''We, too, believe that our sport will be damaged greatly by the cancellation of this season and the continuation of the lockout through next season.''</p>
        <p>The union also proposed an exception to the salary cap that would allow a team to pay as much as $53.9 million in two seasons of a six-year deal so that successful teams would not have to dismantle their rosters. The payroll difference between $49 million and $53.9 million would be taxed at a rate of 150 percent.</p>
        <p>Bettman rejected the plan in a letter sent to the union. ''It was disappointing to receive the fax of your 'final' offer,'' Bettman wrote. ''If every team spent to the $49 million level you have proposed, total player compensation would exceed what we spent last season and, assuming for discussion purposes, there was no damage to the game, our player compensation costs would exceed 75 percent of revenues.''</p>
        <p>The union also proposed a luxury-tax system beginning at a rate of 25 percent for payrolls above $40 million. The tax rate would increase to 50 percent on payrolls of $43 million to $46 million; the rate would be 75 percent for payrolls of $46 million to $49 million.</p>
        <p>''We appreciate your willingness to adjust your position, and we work to respond in kind,'' Goodenow wrote to Bettman, before Bettman's rejection. ''We wish that the N.H.L. had offered a no-linkage proposal before yesterday so that negotiations in that arena could have commenced sooner.''</p>
        <p>Goodenow also called the offer of a salary cap ''a radical step'' for the union.</p>
        <p>The new offers also included a league proposal of $2.2 million in benefits per team.</p>
        <p>The union made the greater concession by agreeing to a salary cap. The league's major concession was to drop its demand for a fixed compensation formula in which a team's salaries could not exceed 55 percent of revenue.</p>
        <p>Earlier yesterday, the league proposed a $40 million cap and the union one of $52 million after a meeting in Niagara Falls, N.Y., between Bill Daly, the N.H.L.'s executive vice president, and Ted Saskin, the union's senior director.</p>
        <p>Some players were upset about a salary cap and the effort of a splinter group of players that supported it even before the league's take-it-or-leave-it offer. According to several players and news reports, the group included Jarome Iginla of the Calgary Flames, Chris Pronger of the St. Louis Blues and Jeremy Roenick and Robert Esche of the Philadelphia Flyers. They explored the willingness of players to accept a cap, and their effort gained momentum after several players met last weekend in Philadelphia with Ed Snider, the owner of the Flyers.</p>
        <p>Roenick told The Philadelphia Inquirer that the players wanted a proposal not tied to revenues and that they were not trying to bypass union leaders.</p>
        <p>''Bob Goodenow should not be threatened,'' Roenick said. ''He should be encouraged that the players care. Bob Goodenow works for the players.''</p>
        <p>But some players expressed dismay over the splinter group and the union's acceptance of a salary cap. Michael Peca of the Islanders said that he was ''very surprised'' at the salary cap and that ''a lot of guys were shocked.'' But he said he supported Goodenow and the executive board, led by the Canucks' Trevor Linden, the union president.</p>
        <p>Referring to the splinter group, Peca said, ''The steps a few guys made behind their backs to go and lobby other players on accepting a salary cap and going to the league is very disrespectful and unprofessional, and I can't believe it happened.''</p>
        <p>Peca said the effort of the splinter group had nothing to do with the union's concession to accept a cap, although that compromise -- a cap without linkage to revenue -- appeared to be exactly what the dissidents sought.</p>
        <p>Peca said union leaders were ''doing what they think is in the best interest of the entire membership, not 10 or 12 guys.''</p>
        <p>''Our executive committee will not be undermined by a handful of guys,'' he said. ''I don't think the direction would change drastically just because of them. I think there was a plan all along, and they just had to execute it when they had to.''</p>
        <p>Doug Weight, a teammate of Pronger's, said, ''I think we bit off a little more than we could chew'' with the offer to accept a salary cap. ''I just hope we didn't do it for the wrong reasons, a handful of players going behind people's backs for the wrong reasons,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He said the union had resisted the salary cap for so long that ''it was a little bit embarrassing to come off that stance.''</p>
        <p>If a settlement is reached, the N.H.L. hopes to play a 28-game season in March and April, followed by four full rounds of Stanley Cup playoffs in May and June. The season would begin after a training camp of about seven days, Bettman said last week.</p>
        <p>Many N.H.L. players are physically ready because 379 are playing in Europe, according to the International Ice Hockey Federation, and others are playing in minor leagues in North America. But some have not signed N.H.L. contracts this season.</p>
        <p>If play resumes, ESPN will pick up some games under terms of its new one-year contract with the N.H.L. for an estimated $55 million a year. The games would be televised on ESPN2 in the regular season and on ESPN and ESPN2 in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
