<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.D.A. Imposes Tougher Rules For Acne Drug</title>
    <meta content="13fda" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/13/health/13fda.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1694442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pregnancy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Food and Drug Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1D9153EF930A2575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.D.A. Imposes Tougher Rules For Acne Drug</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">F.D.A. Imposes Tougher Rules for Acne Drug</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GARDINER HARRIS</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Food and Drug Administration announced tough new regulations Friday for use of the acne drug Accutane. Officials of the agency said they hoped that the rules would reduce the hundreds of miscarriages, birth defects and abortions associated with the drug each year.</p>
        <p>The regulations, which apply to generic versions of Accutane as well, require doctors and patients to register in an electronic database before it can be dispensed. Female patients of childbearing age must take two pregnancy tests and use two forms of birth control to get the drug. And doctors and pharmacists must confirm that the requirements have been met.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials said they hoped that the rules would reduce the miscarriages, birth defects and abortions associated with Accutane.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Food and Drug Administration announced tough new regulations Friday for use of the acne drug Accutane. Officials of the agency said they hoped that the rules would reduce the hundreds of miscarriages, birth defects and abortions associated with the drug each year.</p>
        <p>The regulations, which apply to generic versions of Accutane as well, require doctors and patients to register in an electronic database before it can be dispensed. Female patients of childbearing age must take two pregnancy tests and use two forms of birth control to get the drug. And doctors and pharmacists must confirm that the requirements have been met.</p>
        <p>The new program is the latest and by far most drastic of more than 40 efforts by the agency in the last 22 years to reduce harm from Accutane, an oral medicine made by Roche Holding, while allowing its continued use.</p>
        <p>Dr. Nancy Green, medical director for the March of Dimes, cheered the announcement.</p>
        <p>''If this doesn't work,'' Dr. Green said, ''we will call for the F.D.A. to take this drug off the market.''</p>
        <p>A Roche spokeswoman, Shelley Rosenstock, said the company also welcomed the rules.</p>
        <p>''Roche continues to support, to the extent possible, efforts to reduce fetal exposures'' to Accutane, Ms. Rosentstock said.</p>
        <p>Health officials say the new plan is the latest sign the F.D.A. is losing faith that the nation's doctors and pharmacists can adequately safeguard the health of patients. Before 1998, the agency largely confined itself to advising physicians and pharmacists about how to prescribe and dispense safely any drugs with potentially dangerous adverse effects, and trusted that its advice would be followed. But experts say that time after time over the last decade, medical professionals have ignored the advice, providing drugs to patients at risk of severe complications.</p>
        <p>In some cases, the agency has asked that a drug be withdrawn because physicians and pharmacists proved unwilling to control its use. But such withdrawals have left stranded thousands of patients who contend that they needed those drugs to lead normal lives.</p>
        <p>So instead, the agency has begun fashioning restricted distribution programs, like the one it announced on Friday, to ensure that health professionals follow its guidelines. Among the first was a program created in 1998 to ensure that thalidomide, infamous for causing thousands of birth defects in European babies during the 1960's, could be safely used as a leprosy drug. More such programs have followed, including one for the abortion drug Mifeprex.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sidney Wolfe, director of Public Citizen's Health Research Group, a consumer advocacy organization, said the F.D.A. was recognizing that patients needed protection from irresponsible physicians and pharmacists. Dr. Wolfe added that drug companies were largely to blame, though, saying their huge marketing efforts often encouraged doctors to prescribe drugs excessively.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Mark Naylor, an Oklahoma dermatologist, said with regret that many doctors would stop prescribing Accutane because of the F.D.A.'s new restrictions. While it is unfortunate that some doctors may have failed to follow earlier, voluntary guidelines on Accutane, Dr. Naylor said, ''it's up to physicians and patients to decide how the drug gets used, not the F.D.A.''</p>
        <p>The drug agency approved Accutane in 1982 for patients suffering from severe, disfiguring acne. There are about 6,000 patients with this severe condition in the United States, most of them men. For such patients, the drug has provided a nearly miraculous cure. By 2002, the last year before generic versions of the medicine entered the market, sales of Accutane in the United States had risen to $380 million, with doctors writing 170,000 prescriptions a month, half of which went to women.</p>
        <p>Although animal studies had suggested that Accutane caused birth defects, the drug agency initially imposed few restrictions on its sale. When the first reported birth defect occurred in 1983, the agency responded by requiring pharmacists to affix red warning stickers to every bottle of Accutane describing its effects on fetuses. More than 40 label or other regulatory changes followed, but birth defects only increased. The drug, reports suggest, may also cause some patients to become suicidal.</p>
        <p>In 2001, Roche and the F.D.A. announced a plan to cut fetal exposures of Accutane to zero. Patients were asked to sign a consent form describing Accutane's risks. Doctors were asked to affix yellow stickers to their prescriptions to verify that female patients capable of bearing children had undergone two pregnancy tests and promised to use two forms of birth control.</p>
        <p>But the system was entirely voluntary, and it did nothing to reduce the number of pregnancies among women taking the drug. Some women never got pregnancy tests or, in a few cases, had positive pregnancy tests and still were given it. From 2001 to 2003, the agency received reports of 325 pregnancies among women taking it, and agency officials say such a number is probably only a fraction of the real total, because most miscarriages and abortions are most likely not reported to them.</p>
        <p>In February 2004, an advisory committee recommended that many aspects of the program to control Accutane's risks become mandatory. With its announcement Friday, the F.D.A. has followed that advice. The new plan, called iPledge, is expected to become fully operational by the end of the year. The program will apply to men as well as to women, in part because of the reports of Accutane's psychiatric effects but also because it seeks to bar male patients' sharing the drug with women not eligible to receive it.</p>
        <p>Under the program, doctors who wish to prescribe Accutane or its generic forms must first go to a Web site, list the patient's name in the registry and, using an identification number for the patient, confirm in the case of women that two pregnancy tests have been performed. Patients, using the same identification code, must either call an 800 number or visit a Web site to receive education about the drug's risks, and women must confirm that they are taking two forms of birth control.</p>
        <p>When the patient goes to a pharmacy, the pharmacist must check the Web site to make sure that both doctor and patient have complied. The pregnancy tests must have been taken within the previous seven days and been performed by a certified laboratory. Another pregnancy test will be required before the prescription is refilled.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
