<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Boneyard for Paupers, Signs of Honor and Respect</title>
    <meta content="02ORLE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1058983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Holt Cemetery (New Orleans)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E0DB133FF931A35752C1A96E958260" item-length="1515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Boneyard for Paupers, Signs of Honor and Respect</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, Nov. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>There are signs of love, honor and respect at Holt Cemetery in New Orleans as All Saints Day approaches; ragged cemetery established as boneyard for paupers in 1879 is symbol of city's poverty, just as its richer, older cemeteries are record of its gentry; Holt contains thousands of graves, as well as uncounted bodies of poor buried in muck atop each other, whereas interment in cemeteries for well-to-do is above ground in expensive granite and marble crypts because of low water table; it is not unusual for several generations buried at Holt to occupy same family plot, and some families must wait at least two years before burying members in same plot in city-owned cemetry since interment can only take place as their bones decay; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a graveyard where rows of crosses lean left and right, where one-inch-thin headstones bow to the dirt or tilt toward the sky and misspelled missives to the dead are inked onto rotted plywood markers, Cleveland Cobb spent a long time making sure he got the flowers just right.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cobb, 75, first pounded the dirt of the family plot as smooth as he could with the flat of his shovel, then, with his hands, scooped a hollow place just big enough to root a small clutch of white flowers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a graveyard where rows of crosses lean left and right, where one-inch-thin headstones bow to the dirt or tilt toward the sky and misspelled missives to the dead are inked onto rotted plywood markers, Cleveland Cobb spent a long time making sure he got the flowers just right.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cobb, 75, first pounded the dirt of the family plot as smooth as he could with the flat of his shovel, then, with his hands, scooped a hollow place just big enough to root a small clutch of white flowers.</p>
        <p>''My mother,'' he said, in explanation. ''Mary. I like to see her grave looking good. Nothing else I can do for her.''</p>
        <p>Her headstone bears other names. Here, in this obscure cemetery in a city that lists its graveyards in tourist guidebooks because of their beauty and history, the dead are housed not in ornate crypts but buried in the soil, the bones of generations -- six, eight, more -- mingling in a single hole.</p>
        <p>''I got a daughter in here, too,'' Mr. Cobb said. ''She was 12, no, she was 7. Got hit by a car.'' He poured some water on the flowers, perfectly straight, and after a little while he looked up, embarrassed.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' he said, ''why can't I recall that child's name?''</p>
        <p>Then, as if in penance, he went back to his knees and fussed some more with the little rectangle of dirt in Holt Cemetery, where his family, too many to recall, sleep.</p>
        <p>Today is All Saints' Day, a day to honor the dead, and in New Orleans this Roman Catholic holiday is embraced by Protestants, Jews, everyone, it seems. People bring food, sit in the shade and visit in the long, granite rows of old and new crypts, what people here call cities of the dead. Because the water table is only a few feet beneath the surface, it is necessary to inter most people above ground -- everyone except the poor, who must rest in the muck.</p>
        <p>Marble and granite are expensive, but dirt is just dirt. Here in Holt Cemetery, established as a boneyard for paupers in 1879, people like Mr. Cobb cannot change the fact that, in death as in life, people with money can sleep easier. But all around this ragged place on this day for the dead are signs of love, honor and respect, signs that rival anything the richer people do in their manicured cities of fresh-cut flowers on polished stone.</p>
        <p>If richer, older cemeteries are a record of New Orleans society, Holt Cemetery is a symbol of its potholed streets, its peeling shotgun houses, its un-air-conditioned churches, bingo halls, blue-collar social clubs and beer joints.</p>
        <p>Just a few steps from where Mr. Cobb, a retired truck driver, knelt by his mother and daughter, 75-year-old Luella Marshall limped slowly away from a small but brand-new brass headstone inscribed with her husband's name. A young man, one of her great-nephews, held her hand, steadying her.</p>
        <p>''If my husband was the one living, I know he'd be out here today, seeing about me,'' said Mrs. Marshall, whose husband died last year from a blood clot.</p>
        <p>The gleaming headstone -- ''Edward Marshall, U.S. Army, World War II, Born Oct. 7, 1927, Died June 27, 1997'' -- tells only a little about him. In the hot sun of the afternoon -- the only shade here is from a few oaks, gnarled with age, shrouded in Spanish moss -- she told the things about him that mattered.</p>
        <p>''He was a beautiful man,'' Mrs. Marshall said. ''He treated me like a baby. If we was ever in the house, we was in the same room, always together. If I washed the clothes, he'd put them on the line. If we cooked, he'd cook one thing and I'd cook another thing, just so we could be in the kitchen.''</p>
        <p>Her arthritis is so bad now, she said, it is hard to tend the graves right, to make this annual trek to pull weeds and smooth the ground over her husband and other people she loves. But Mrs. Marshall, who spent her lifetime caring for other people's children and ailing loved ones as what she calls ''a sitter,'' swears she will find a way to care a little while longer for the man who made life sweet.</p>
        <p>''As long as I can put one foot down in front of the other, I will be out here to visit my husband,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her husband's marker was designed to be laid flat on the ground, but she has it propped up, so people can see it better.</p>
        <p>New Orleans, as poets and other intellectuals have often written, has seen more death than most other American cities, perhaps because it predates them, because disease, floods, storms and war have ravaged the city since its beginning, in the early 1700's.</p>
        <p>Holt is a relatively new cemetery, having been built in the late part of the 19th century, but here are thousands of graves and uncounted bodies buried one atop the other. People tending the graves said a family has to wait at least two years before burying someone in the same plot in the city-owned graveyard.</p>
        <p>''You can put them in, as their bones decay,'' Sidney Scott said as he painstakingly used gold paint and a tiny brush to trace the names of a faded, weather-worn headstone. ''Some people call it a potter's field, but that's not what it is.'' That would mean the people buried here were unwanted, forgotten, and that would be wrong, said Mr. Scott, a maintenance man at a church.</p>
        <p>''Momma and Daddy taught me to love,'' he said when asked why he came out each year on All Saints' Day to make these graves look nice, to make them look remembered.</p>
        <p>Harry W. Scott, his father, died in 1958. Since then, Mr. Scott's father has been joined in that grave by a grandmother, two brothers and a niece. Because almost every inch of ground is used, only the people whose families are buried here can bury others here.</p>
        <p>''I think they like it,'' Mr. Scott said as he finished painting in the names. He was referring to the dead. ''At least, no one's come back and told me they didn't.'' He smiled at that.</p>
        <p>People used to do more, on All Saints' Day and the days leading up to it, said Lillie Lewis, 72, and her sister, Ara R. Dozier, 74. They came to tend the grave that holds their mother, two grandmothers, a brother, another brother's first wife and ''two babies.''</p>
        <p>''The Lord took them,'' Ms. Dozier said.</p>
        <p>She promised her mother, before her death, she would tend the graves on All Saints' Day.</p>
        <p>''Momma used to drive us here, and we'd have a picnic and stay all day,'' Ms. Dozier said. The cemetery would be crowded with people, eating, talking, enjoying life as they remembered the lives of the dead.</p>
        <p>People still do, but not as much. ''They come but they don't stay,'' Ms. Dozier said.</p>
        <p>She remembered a sweet potato vine that used to grow here. She wondered if it was still there.</p>
        <p>Like many people here, there seemed no sadness in them. Mourning is not what All Saints' Day is for, people said, certainly not here, where people leave behind a favorite food and even a loved one's favorite beer -- emptied, of course -- on the graves.</p>
        <p>As the two elderly sisters walked to their cars, they joked like children.</p>
        <p>''She,'' Mrs. Lewis said of her sister, ''is an old maid schoolteacher.''</p>
        <p>''She,'' Ms. Dozier said of her sister, ''is not right, and has been that way all her life.''</p>
        <p>Because the burials here have far outnumbered the changes to the headstones, because it is impossible to tell where one grave ends and another begins, there is no telling how many people have been put here and forgotten. Once, the people say, stillborn babies and even body parts from surgeries were buried here, a less than dignified place, some people might believe, for a loved one.</p>
        <p>But in this place where bones and memories mingle, where people work so hard to smooth the dirt and get flowers to grow straight and sometimes just remember a forgotten name, the dignity is in not letting the weeds and complacency claim the simple plots.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing,'' said Cleveland Cobb, ''I look forward to.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
