<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gooden and Mets Feel Chill of Shutout No. 11</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="541557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSTON ASTROS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEXTON, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D81038F933A25754C0A964958260" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gooden and Mets Feel Chill of Shutout No. 11</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SEXTON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SEXTON, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, July 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The season of shutouts stretches on for the Mets. The total is 11, and it includes the strange, the heartbreaking, the predictable, the embarrassing and the back-to-back.</p>
        <p>Labels for tonight's addition? Call it inexcusable. Call it pathetic. Call it, if the fatalism has become too much, inevitable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The season of shutouts stretches on for the Mets. The total is 11, and it includes the strange, the heartbreaking, the predictable, the embarrassing and the back-to-back.</p>
        <p>Labels for tonight's addition? Call it inexcusable. Call it pathetic. Call it, if the fatalism has become too much, inevitable.</p>
        <p>The Mets -- despite being afforded the break of Houston's starting pitcher being forced from the game because of injury after only three innings -- were inept at the plate from the first inning to the last, and they left the Astrodome 4-0 losers.</p>
        <p>There wasn't palpable energy on the field. There wasn't anger from the manager afterward. And so there were private questions among players in the clubhouse about the club's remaining desire for 1992.</p>
        <p>"The anger doesn't go through you the same way when you don't hit," said Manager Jeff Torborg, whose club's 11 shutouts lead the major leagues. "You are just kind of numb."</p>
        <p>The victim who felt most acutely the latest failure to score was Dwight Gooden. The right-hander struck out six in seven innings and pitched with often overpowering effectiveness. He got his eighth loss of the season for his troubles.</p>
        <p>"Game after game after game, it's tough," said Gooden. "You pitch, and every inning feels like the ninth inning. There have been 11 shutouts. I can't say they have all been great games."</p>
        <p>The Mets, who managed one hit off Mark Portugal through the first three innings, finished with four more over six innings against the emergency replacement, Willie Blair. The Mets, their record at 40-45 for the season, have scored six runs in their last four games against the Astros, the second-worst hitting club in baseball.</p>
        <p>The Mets, of course, are the unrivaled worst, and they lived up to their billing. After Portugal left with stiffness in his elbow, Blair came on to throw pure gas at the Mets. There wasn't so much as a spark offered in response.</p>
        <p>Blair set the Mets down in order in the fourth. He got them to strand their obligatory allotment of men in scoring position when he left Mets at second and third in the fifth. He then faced only one more than the minimum over the final four innings.</p>
        <p>"People have made excuses all year," said Gooden (6-8). "We're just not doing it."</p>
        <p>Gooden, who had given up two runs in the first two innings to doom his shot at a victory, yielded a third in the fifth via a Jeff Bagwell run-scoring single. Left-handed reliever Paul Gibson tacked on a run to the total in the eighth.</p>
        <p>Gooden, his shoulder's arbitrary condition a mystery until he took the mound, had to like what he felt. And heard. His fastball fired out of his right hand and smashed into the catcher's glove as he warmed up for the Astros and the first inning. All-Star Starts It Off</p>
        <p>The sounds turned unfortunate almost instantly. Craig Biggio, in his first at-bat since being named to the National League All-Star team, cracked a double inside third base to lead off the game. Gooden, after getting an out when Biggio was sacrificed to third, rallied from a 3-0 count to plaster three strikes past Bagwell.</p>
        <p>Gooden then flat-out overmatched Eric Anthony to get ahead 0-2. Biggio was 90 feet from scoring. Gooden was one strike from recording a shutout inning. Anthony didn't get much of another fastball from Gooden, but Mackey Sasser, making a rare start in left field, didn't get anything of a jump on the ball. It fell in short left for a 1-0 lead.</p>
        <p>"You make the pitch you want, and you don't get out of it," said Gooden, who gave up a run in the second on Juan Guerrero's triple. "I took the first inning out there with me for the second and third."</p>
        <p>And the Mets took their bats to the plate for innings one through nine and did nothing. INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>JOHN FRANCO, the closer for the Mets who has been sidelined with an inflamed tendon in his left elbow, was placed on the 15-day disabled list. Franco worked out the elbow in Atlanta earlier in the week and concluded that he shouldn't throw again until after the All-Star Game break. It marked the first time the left-hander had been disabled in his career. He was replaced on the roster by PAT HOWELL, an outfielder who will be used as defensive help and to pinch-run.</p>
        <p>WILLIE RANDOLPH did not start the game at second base. Manager JEFF TORBORG, asked about the 38-year-old's productivity, said he had no great concerns about Randolph's physical ability to remain an asset through 1992. "He's suffered from wear and tear, yeah," said Torborg. "He's had hamstring problems, a rib cage injury, difficulty with his knee. But he's not the only one who hasn't hit in big spots." Randolph, however, has hit only .159 with men in scoring position this season, and of late he has repeatedly surfaced as a culprit in the crippling missed scoring opportunities the Mets have suffered through. Randolph struck out with men on second and third in the seventh inning of Wednesday night's 2-1 defeat in Atlanta, and he grounded into the game-ending double play with the bases loaded in the ninth. Randolph has hit .210 since June 8. "He's been battling," said Torborg.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
