<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Humana May Split Insurance and Hospital Parts</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="541717"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HUMANA INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREUDENHEIM, MILT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DB1530F933A25754C0A964958260" item-length="363" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Humana May Split Insurance and Hospital Parts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MILT FREUDENHEIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREUDENHEIM, MILT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Humana Inc., the big hospital and health insurance company, said yesterday that it might split into two separate businesses, signaling the failure of an integrated health-care strategy that analysts said might have been ahead of its time.</p>
        <p>The split would separate the hospital chain, based in Louisville, Ky., from Humana's health maintenance organizations and other group-insurance units, which were supposed to provide a steady, dependable supply of hospital patients.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Humana Inc., the big hospital and health insurance company, said yesterday that it might split into two separate businesses, signaling the failure of an integrated health-care strategy that analysts said might have been ahead of its time.</p>
        <p>The split would separate the hospital chain, based in Louisville, Ky., from Humana's health maintenance organizations and other group-insurance units, which were supposed to provide a steady, dependable supply of hospital patients.</p>
        <p>Humana stock, which had been sliding on company forecasts of declining earnings this year, rose 87.5 cents yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange, closing at $23.125. It had been as high as $34.125 in the last 12 months and had fallen as low as $19.375 as investors began to shun health-care stocks.</p>
        <p>Carl Sherman, a health-care securities analyst at Dillon, Read &amp; Company, said that Humana hospital profits should rise because the company would be able to reach out to other insurance plans and physicians instead of depending heavily on its own units to provide hospital patients.</p>
        <p>But Joyce Albers at First Boston said that based on current earnings, the split would not add to the company's value "in the near term." 2 Chiefs for 2 Divisions</p>
        <p>In the division, which might take place early next year, David Jones, Humana's chairman and co-founder, would head the health insurance division, which covers 1.7 million people. David Pollard, the president and chief operating officer, would run the 78 Humana hospitals, the company said.</p>
        <p>Humana had net income of $355 million on sales of $5.87 billion last year. It gets about 60 percent of its revenue from hospitals and 40 percent from health plans.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that the insurance side of the business had been growing well but that the hospitals had suffered because Humana had alienated independent physicianswhen many hospitals were wooing doctors. Owning its own health plans was supposed to give Humana leverage over the doctors, but the doctors wound up with the leverage, Mr. Sherman said.</p>
        <p>He noted that in a somewhat similar development, the Hospital Corporation of America gave up on Equicor, its joint-venture H.M.O.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
