<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pants, for an Era of Vacillating Hemlines</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="491318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORRIS, BERNADINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D6113FF930A35751C1A967958260" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pants, for an Era of Vacillating Hemlines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNADINE MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORRIS, BERNADINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hemlines are no problem, right? Spring collections, on average, showed about 10 percent of skirt lengths passing the knees, the rest baring them. Retailers are picking the styles that appeal to them on grounds other than length. There is absolutely no talk about short skirts being made obsolete by the downward hemline movement, except perhaps by some nervous women who worry whether their short skirts will be viable next year.</p>
        <p>The conventional wisdom is that long and short skirts will coexist for the next season or two, that short skirt wearers will be able to switch to long skirts when the mood hits them and that there is no reason to be concerned. All that has happened since the spring fashion openings began two months ago is that very short skirts, the kind that barely clear the hips, look hopelessly passe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hemlines are no problem, right? Spring collections, on average, showed about 10 percent of skirt lengths passing the knees, the rest baring them. Retailers are picking the styles that appeal to them on grounds other than length. There is absolutely no talk about short skirts being made obsolete by the downward hemline movement, except perhaps by some nervous women who worry whether their short skirts will be viable next year.</p>
        <p>The conventional wisdom is that long and short skirts will coexist for the next season or two, that short skirt wearers will be able to switch to long skirts when the mood hits them and that there is no reason to be concerned. All that has happened since the spring fashion openings began two months ago is that very short skirts, the kind that barely clear the hips, look hopelessly passe.</p>
        <p>So why is there a surge of interest in pants?</p>
        <p>A high moment in the New York shows last month was the presentation of Ralph Lauren's man-tailored pants suits, complete with mannish accoutrements including suspenders, shirts and ties. Donna Karan's show also focused on men's-style suits, and store buyers enthusiastically began ordering them. Her suits were shown with lingerie touches like lace edges, lots of jewelry and visible bras. There was also a spurt in retailers' orders for that perennial spring favorite, the navy suit with white collar and cuffs. Calvin Klein, a pants enthusiast even in times when the fashion pendulum swung to skirts, offered a strong selection of trouser fashions.</p>
        <p>A week later, each of the designers said retailers' orders for trousers were unusually strong. Mr. Lauren said that in addition to his mannish styles, the trousers in his nautical styles were doing well with buyers. Ms. Karan said buyers were choosing her nipped-waist jackets, which heighten the feminine mood, in men's fabrics like pin stripes. And Mr. Klein said his calm, understated pants suits were being ordered vigorously.</p>
        <p>The American designers were not alone. Faced with the same problem of variable skirt lengths, European designers also turned quite enthusiastically to pants. Giorgio Armani, who kept all his daytime skirts quite short, added a generous compendium of trouser suits for women who prefer to keep their legs under wraps. Gianfranco Ferre who makes the best pipestem pants, turned out some wide-leg versions as well. Gianni Versace made exotic animal-print pants and Mariuccia Mandelli of Krizia some jodhpur-shaped casual styles.</p>
        <p>The trouser fashion spectrum is obviously much broader today than it was 20 years ago when the modern pants era began. Then, jackets were long, the tailoring soft and the idea of pants so revolutionary in itself that designers did not try to attract attention with unusual shapes. The classic ground is still strong, especially at American houses, but there really are no limits on design. Some trouser suits are shown with visible bra tops or with bare midrfiffs. Some are in extravagant prints or in thin, almost transparent fabrics. And wider trouser legs look newer to some buyers than sleek narrow styles; both register significantly in spring orders.</p>
        <p>Twenty years ago, when the miniskirt abruptly gave place to awkward calf-length styles, women rebelled. That was when jeans became acceptable for many social and some business occasions. For more formal day wear, the pants suit, popularized by Yves Saint Laurent and his imitators, was widely adopted. Even women who had previously considered slacks suitable only for gardening or walks in the country succumbed.</p>
        <p>It wasn't all roses. Some restaurants refused to seat a woman wearing pants -- they're all out of business today. Corporate employers sometimes frowned on pants, even when the hips were well covered and the jackets fit gently.</p>
        <p>The "dress for success" formula that arose in the late 1970's forbade pants as too masculine looking. Women entering the professions and the higher ranks of business did not want to emulate men. They wore plain, neutral suits with skirts instead.</p>
        <p>By now, much of the fervor about pants, pro and con, is dissipating. Female lawyers will wear pants suits when they argue a case in court. And women not willing to decide about skirt lengths are expected to turn to pants, as they did 20 years ago. It is time for another pants era.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
