<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Family of Captive Rejoices at Release</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="491287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOSTAGES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORRISTOWN (PA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LEBANON</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CICIPPIO, JOSEPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DB163CF930A35751C1A967958260" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Family of Captive Rejoices at Release</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL deCOURCY HINDS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</byline>
      <dateline>NORRISTOWN, Pa., Dec. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Soon after hearing that Joseph J. Cicippio had been released in Lebanon, a half-dozen members of his family gathered for an early morning ceremony on the lawn outside a brother's stone-fronted house here.</p>
        <p>They stood in front of a large white sign stenciled with the names of eight past and present American hostages in Lebanon. Each day for five years Mr. Cicippio's brother had changed the number on the sign to reflect the time Mr. Cicippio was in captivity. But today, members of his family took turns hammering a new sign over the number 1,908. It said, "Free At Last!"</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Soon after hearing that Joseph J. Cicippio had been released in Lebanon, a half-dozen members of his family gathered for an early morning ceremony on the lawn outside a brother's stone-fronted house here.</p>
        <p>They stood in front of a large white sign stenciled with the names of eight past and present American hostages in Lebanon. Each day for five years Mr. Cicippio's brother had changed the number on the sign to reflect the time Mr. Cicippio was in captivity. But today, members of his family took turns hammering a new sign over the number 1,908. It said, "Free At Last!"</p>
        <p>After a week of trying to contain their emotions amid persistent rumors of Mr. Cicippio's likely release, family members said they exploded with happiness after the State Department's 4 A.M. telephone call telling them he was finally free.</p>
        <p>But the happiness was soon leavened with sadness and concern as more than a dozen family members gathered around a television to watch an 8:30 A.M. news conference from Syria. Mr. Cicippio, speaking very briefly at the conference, looked frail, worn out and at least 50 pounds thinner than he used to be, his family and friends said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cicippio, who is 61 years old, was taken hostage in Beirut on Sept. 12, 1986, while he was walking to the American University, where he was acting comptroller. He said today that he has not seen or heard any news of the world for five years. During his captivity, Mr. Cicippio became a grandfather and his first-born son, Joseph, and an older sister, Rose, died.</p>
        <p>Another of Mr. Cicippio's sisters, 71-year-old Helen Fazio, cried when she saw her brother on television. Mrs. Fazio has cancer, and last year her doctors placed advertisements in Lebanese newspapers, begging Mr. Cicippio's captors to free him before she died. "Waiting for Joe has been her therapy," said Alan E. Melnick, one of her sons-in-law. "Now she's really hyper-happy, on cloud nine."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Fazio and other family members thought they had been prepared for the worst by grim photographs that Mr. Cicippio's captors had made public, but they said today that they were deeply disturbed by his physical appearance on television.</p>
        <p>"I was very shocked," said Thomas J. Cicippio, the former hostage's 68-year-old brother who lives here. "Joe has aged 15 or 20 years in 5 and by the look of his condition, he could have something worse than ulcers."</p>
        <p>Thomas Cicippio said his brother had a history of stomach ulcers, but he could not explain his brother's reference at the news conference this morning to a life-threatening illness or the operation he underwent this fall.</p>
        <p>The family's concern about Mr. Cicippio's health increased when the State Department postponed four members' reunion with Mr. Cicippio at the American military base in Wiesbaden, Germany. The State Department had initially arranged that the four would leave tonight, but called back later to say that the trip would not take place until possibly Tuesday night, pending an evaluation of Mr. Cicippio's health. The reason for the postponement, the State Department said, its concern that Mr.  Cicippio's health might warrant his being rushed to the Walter Reed Army Medical Center in Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cicippio's family and friends said they hoped the former hostage to recover quickly from his ordeal. They said his remarks at the news conference, especially his comment about this being the "first day of the rest of my life," were characteristic of his positive outlook.</p>
        <p>Joseph James Cicippio was born in Norristown on Sept. 13, 1930, the youngest of eight children, to Camillo and Julia Cicippio. His father worked as a railroad laborer, and his mother earned money by taking in some sewing. Mr. Cicippio graduated from Norristown High School in 1948 and took business courses at Bucknell University and Villanova University. In 1954, he married, and he and Theresa Frascino Cicippio had seven children, who are now in their early 20's and early 30's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cicippio worked for 22 years at a Norristown bank, and was an assistant vice president when he left, in 1974, to work at several banks in Cape May, N.J. His first marriage ended in divorce after 20 years, and a brief second marriage shortly afterward also ended in divorce.</p>
        <p>"He was upset over the second divorce and felt he had to get away to start something new," said Mary Brown, a close friend of Mr. Cicippio in Norristown for over 30 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cicippio's search for a new life took him to England, where he worked for a hotel, and to Saudi Arabia, where he worked for a helicopter manufacturer. He returned to Norristown in 1984, but his family said he could not find work to his liking. Later that year, he accepted a position as acting comptroller for the American University in Beirut.</p>
        <p>In 1985, he married Elham Ghandour, a Lebanese secretary at the United States Embassy in Beirut. She has continued to live in Beirut. A year after their marriage, the Revolutionary Justice Organization kidnapped him as he was walking to work.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
