<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Residents Try to Salvage Memories From the Rubble</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="838362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUILDINGS (STRUCTURES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOWER EAST SIDE (NYC)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E0D61739F931A15750C0A960958260" item-length="692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Residents Try to Salvage Memories From the Rubble</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS MARTIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Faith Lange returned to her shattered apartment in a collapsed East Side building yesterday morning to retrieve pieces of her life. She came out with little but school papers from third grade, a tiny chair she had as a 3-year-old, some special pictures.</p>
        <p>The bedroom was gone, literally. The kitchen was pulled apart, with cabinets, table and stove piled in the middle of the living room. Dust and debris were everywhere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Faith Lange returned to her shattered apartment in a collapsed East Side building yesterday morning to retrieve pieces of her life. She came out with little but school papers from third grade, a tiny chair she had as a 3-year-old, some special pictures.</p>
        <p>The bedroom was gone, literally. The kitchen was pulled apart, with cabinets, table and stove piled in the middle of the living room. Dust and debris were everywhere.</p>
        <p>Now, I want to know what happened," Ms. Lange, a 29-year-old securities broker, said. "The anger is settling in."</p>
        <p>The four-story building at 349 East 54th Street near First Avenue collapsed on Monday, after the demolition of a building next door, leaving 10 people suddenly homeless. Those who had lived on the bottom two floors were allowed back in for an hour yesterday to pick up at least some of their belongings; those on the upper two floors were to get their chance today.</p>
        <p>With wooden trusses propping up sagging ceilings, the residents gingerly made their way inside; they went alone, forbidden to bring along relatives or friends for fear of the extra weight. An engineer stared through a surveyor's instrument, watching for any signs that the building was beginning to teeter. Police barriers blocked 54th Street between First and Second avenues.</p>
        <p>Big things like beds and sofas could not be removed. Because the residents had little time, most clothes had to be left behind; most had been damaged by water from broken pipes anyway. It was a day to pick up small things, things several residents separately characterized with the same all-encompassing phrase, "my life."</p>
        <p>There was Tadashi Matsuda, 57, whose one-room apartment was crammed from top  to bottom with the eclectic collection of antiques he had hoped to turn into a business someday. He briskly carried out lamps and chandeliers from the 1930's,  an Art Deco radio and enormous paintings. He put them in a U-Haul truck, but said he had no idea where he was going to take them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Matsuda, a bartender in a Japanese restaurant, had lived in Apartment 2B  for more than 18 years. "It is just bad luck," he said.</p>
        <p>As a fourth-floor resident, Oleksiy Kolodyazany, superintendent of the Ukrainian Consulate, was not supposed to get his things until today. But the diplomat felt bereft of an identity without his passport and diplomatic credentials, and city housing officials permitted him to climb up to his apartment. While there, he grabbed a photograph of a 1 1/2-month-old granddaughter he has yet to meet.</p>
        <p>"In a way, my whole life was in there," he said. Certainly, all of the diplomat's nice American clothes were. He now has only one suit and has worn it  since becoming homeless, a Ukrainian model decidedly not featured in any recent issues of GQ.</p>
        <p>Another diplomat lingered outside the building, looking at his former home, which he will be allowed to enter for the last time today. The diplomat, Calvin  Widdows, 47, of the Australian Mission to the United Nations said he was eager to retrieve some pieces of furniture designed specifically for his apartment by  a friend, as well as numerous official papers. "I've got to get my identity out," he said.</p>
        <p>Mark Leach, 26, a banker, and Alexandra Ries, 25, who works at an advertising agency, seemed a little dumbstruck to see all of their remaining possessions stacked in one van. Since all of their clothes and large furniture must now be replaced, Ms. Ries said, they will have to search for a cheaper apartment.</p>
        <p>In June, they would have lived for two years in the ground-floor apartment where they liked to barbecue and garden in the patio. But they were able to remove only such treasures as an antique desk, Mr. Leach's beer stein collection and Ms. Ries's diamond earrings, a gift from her companion.</p>
        <p>"We got more than we expected," she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
