<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Richmond Journal; Ashe Returns to the City He Disowned in Youth</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="526649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACQUIRED IMMUNE DEFICIENCY SYNDROME (AIDS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RICHMOND (VA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ASHE, ARTHUR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia/Richmond</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D7103FF934A35756C0A964958260" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Richmond Journal; Ashe Returns to the City He Disowned in Youth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</byline>
      <dateline>RICHMOND, May 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"When I decided to leave Richmond," Arthur Ashe wrote in his autobiography, "Off the Court," in 1981, "I left all that Richmond stood for at the time -- its segregation, its conservatism, its parochial thinking, its slow progress toward equality, its lack of opportunity for talented black people. I had no intention then of coming back."</p>
        <p>Today, Arthur Ashe came back.</p>
        <p>"It's nice to be home," he said, beginning a round of speeches, press conferences and tennis clinics for young people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"When I decided to leave Richmond," Arthur Ashe wrote in his autobiography, "Off the Court," in 1981, "I left all that Richmond stood for at the time -- its segregation, its conservatism, its parochial thinking, its slow progress toward equality, its lack of opportunity for talented black people. I had no intention then of coming back."</p>
        <p>Today, Arthur Ashe came back.</p>
        <p>"It's nice to be home," he said, beginning a round of speeches, press conferences and tennis clinics for young people.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ashe seems to have mellowed, and not just about Richmond, the city that once forced him to play tennis on courts designated "Colored Only." He also seems to have mellowed about life in general.</p>
        <p>Actually, he is almost serene, like a man resigned, like someone who at the age of, say, 88, having done all and succeeded, is resigned to whatever comes next, at peace.</p>
        <p>Except that Arthur Ashe is not 88 years old. He is 48.</p>
        <p>He has AIDS, as the world now knows, and he has a weak heart. In fact, he says he contracted the AIDS virus while receiving a blood transfusion during a heart operation.</p>
        <p>It is all enough to make a man very angry, to turn him inward.</p>
        <p>The smooth, powerful stroke that once made Arthur Ashe the best tennis player on earth, the first black ever to achieve that rank, is too soon gone. Now he plays only a "social" game, often forgoing that for a round of less strenuous golf. He speaks of his wife, Jeanne, as a "co-patient" and says that when schoolmates of his 6-year-old daughter, Camera, blurt "Your daddy has AIDS," she has learned to reply, "I know."</p>
        <p>But Arthur Ashe seems anything but angry and focused on himself. In the worst year of his life, so far, he is pushing on, promoting tennis, talking up racial equality, spreading the word about the killer disease he carries.</p>
        <p>He puts all this more bluntly.</p>
        <p>"There is a finite amount of time," he says. "I'm reassessing what I'm going to do with the rest of my life."</p>
        <p>One thing he knows he wants to do is work with young people, especially young blacks. That is what brought him back to Richmond, not some fear that he had better make a final visit home while there is still a chance. He has been back now and again since leaving as a teen-ager in the early 1960's, and if his love for the old Confederate capital is not burning, he is willing to say, frankly, "I started here, got my values and attitudes right here, and I think they have stood me in good stead."</p>
        <p>So there he was this afternoon, back in Richmond, back home, conducting a tennis clinic for children out on the city courts in Byrd Park, the same courts where he could not play as a youngster because of Jim Crow.</p>
        <p>The smooth, powerful stroke that won Wimbledon may be gone, but Arthur Ashe can still swing a mean racquet, as a wide-eyed third-grader named Joe Cannon was learning.</p>
        <p>"It's smooth, smooth, smooth," Mr. Ashe said, grabbing Joe's wrist and sweeping the racquet back, then forward.</p>
        <p>The bright yellow ball sailed smoothly over the net. A clutch of youngsters rushed up, requesting autographs, and Mr. Ashe obligingly signed their racquets, racquet covers and instruction booklets.</p>
        <p>Earlier, at a luncheon where some of the city's best athletes were honored, Mr. Ashe had some advice to offer.</p>
        <p>From personal experience, he said, he knows that the competition, discipline and camaraderie of sport can mold a youthful life, and for the youth who is exceptionally talented, sport can open up an entirely new world.</p>
        <p>"There are opportunities out there," he advised. "But it is up to you to take advantage of them."</p>
        <p>He was not talking about opportunities to win Wimbledon or a World Series game. He was talking about a longer-range view. He said the wise youngster should aspire as much to own the Chicago Bulls as to be a member of the team.</p>
        <p>The man credited with discovering Arthur Ashe's tennis talents, John Watson, came to see and hear his old friend today and later marveled at his handling of adversity.</p>
        <p>"It must be the discipline and the competitive drive that's always been there," said Mr. Watson, the head of the foreign language department at Virginia Union University here and the university's tennis coach for many years.</p>
        <p>"I'll tell you about Arthur Ashe," he continued. "When I first remember him he was so eager to succeed that he would get out of bed every morning at 5 o'clock, winter and summer, rain and shine, and before breakfast he would hit 1,000 tennis balls. One thousand. Think about that."</p>
        <p>Mr. Ashe says he knows that some day his doctor will tell him that blood tests indicate he is on the "downhill" side of the disease, and then he will have to reassess himself yet again.</p>
        <p>"But I've been rock solid with my tests for the past three and a half years," he added, "and I'm not down yet."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
