<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Home for Teenage Mothers Sparks Some Sleepless Nights</title>
    <meta content="18GUAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1575077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: DYKER HEIGHTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E7DB123BF93BA25757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Home for Teenage Mothers Sparks Some Sleepless Nights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAKE MOONEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sitting by a window with her 5-month-old baby curled up quietly in her lap, 18-year-old Taisha Santos doesn't look scary. But to some residents of Dyker Heights in Brooklyn, Ms. Santos represents something very unsettling.</p>
        <p>A longtime resident of foster homes, Ms. Santos now lives in a home for teenage mothers in Park Slope that is maintained by mercyFirst, a service organization run by the Sisters of Mercy. But the group also owns the Angel Guardian Home, a 105-year-old former orphanage at 12th Avenue and 63rd Street, and it plans to convert the building to house a ''mother-baby residential program'' similar to the one in Park Slope. That's what makes some people in Dyker Heights nervous.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sitting by a window with her 5-month-old baby curled up quietly in her lap, 18-year-old Taisha Santos doesn't look scary. But to some residents of Dyker Heights in Brooklyn, Ms. Santos represents something very unsettling.</p>
        <p>A longtime resident of foster homes, Ms. Santos now lives in a home for teenage mothers in Park Slope that is maintained by mercyFirst, a service organization run by the Sisters of Mercy. But the group also owns the Angel Guardian Home, a 105-year-old former orphanage at 12th Avenue and 63rd Street, and it plans to convert the building to house a ''mother-baby residential program'' similar to the one in Park Slope. That's what makes some people in Dyker Heights nervous.</p>
        <p>The Angel Guardian campus sits on a full square block, and some residents complain about noise arising from its current use as an office building and foster care visiting facility, said City Councilman Vincent Gentile, who represents the area. But now, he said, people worry that a home for teenage mothers will lead to double-parking, blocked driveways, loud music and frequent traffic in and out of the building. After news of the planned conversion, fliers went up in the neighborhood predicting that ''reformed gang members'' would ''roam the streets,'' The Brooklyn Skyline, a local newspaper, reported.</p>
        <p>Program administrators say there will be far less activity on the property under the new use, and point to area residents who support the program. One, Artie Maresca, called the home valuable and said the opposition was rooted in uncertainty. ''What you don't know in life, you automatically fear, you become apprehensive of,'' he said last week.</p>
        <p>To hear Mr. Gentile tell it, much of that uncertainty is the fault of mercyFirst officials. They told residents at first that the program would serve 10 mothers and their children, he said, but then asked the City Council for $650,000 to renovate the building for use by twice as many people. Organizers say there are no immediate plans to include more than 10 mothers, but Mr. Gentile said lingering distrust remained.</p>
        <p>''The way they've gone about it has induced resentment and anger from the community, because it appears that they wanted to do this under the radar,'' Mr. Gentile said.</p>
        <p>Liz Giordano, chief executive officer of mercyFirst, stressed that while the renovated building would be able to hold more than 10 mothers and 10 children, any increases would come only after consultation with a new local advisory panel.</p>
        <p>''That's what the purpose of the advisory board is, so that if we do increase capacity, we do it with community support,'' Ms. Giordano said.</p>
        <p>To Ms. Santos, far from the wrangling, the value of the program is clear. ''Basically, it teaches you how to be a parent,'' she said. Without it, she added, ''I don't really think my child would be with me right now.''</p>
        <p>JAKE MOONEY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: DYKER HEIGHTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
