<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>County vs. State on Bankruptcy Issue</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="383023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKRUPTCIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROPERTY TAXES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROPOSITION 13 (CALIFORNIA INITIATIVE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BUTTE COUNTY (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEUKMEJIAN, GEORGE (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BISHOP, KATHERINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDE1139F933A2575AC0A966958260" item-length="1246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>County vs. State on Bankruptcy Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE BISHOP, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BISHOP, KATHERINE</byline>
      <dateline>OROVILLE, Calif., Sept. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Twelve years after Proposition 13 slashed property tax revenues in California, the supervisors of Butte County face a wrenching decision in the coming week: whether to make theirs the first county in the nation to declare bankruptcy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Twelve years after Proposition 13 slashed property tax revenues in California, the supervisors of Butte County face a wrenching decision in the coming week: whether to make theirs the first county in the nation to declare bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>More than a decade of citizens' tax revolt has left county governments in California starved for property and other tax revenues at the same time that social service programs mandated by the state have grown rapidly.</p>
        <p>Butte is one of a number of California's 58 counties hurt by the financial squeeze that originated with Proposition 13, which imposed tight restrictions on property tax increases. The problem has become most acute in rural counties, because their low costs of housing have made them what one official called a ''poverty magnet,'' pulling in the chronically unemployed or low-paid unskilled workers, welfare recipients and retirees on fixed incomes.</p>
        <p>In Butte County, one in six residents receives some form of public assistance, and welfare programs alone account for 57 percent of the county budget. The county of 185,000 people has met the crisis by gutting services like the Sheriff's Department and the libraries to pay for increases in welfare programs that range from 300 percent to 2,000 percent.</p>
        <p>''We have closed our libraries and fired librarians to pay social workers,'' said William H. Randolph, the county's chief administrative officer. ''But we cannot continue the process of eating our hands and feet - of cannibalizing the whole system. County government as we have known it, is going to die.''</p>
        <p>Threats to Larger Counties</p>
        <p>A report published last month by the County Supervisors Associations of California found that some large urban counties including San Diego and Alameda are also threatened by the soaring costs of the areas of public health and criminal justice, largely due to the war on drugs, driving up the need for everything from emergency hospital services to larger jails.</p>
        <p>And Thomas Goodman, a spokesman for the National Association of Counties in Washington, said some county governments in Kentucky, Oklahoma and West Virginia are on the brink of bankruptcy because the downturn in their economies has forced down property values and thus county tax revenues.</p>
        <p>Richard P. Simpson, director of research for the County Supervisors Association report, said there are a dozen counties in California in ''acute fiscal stress,'' with at least six ''really in terrible shape.''</p>
        <p>Even if Butte County is bailed out with an infusion of state money this year, he said, ''we are going to face further Butte Counties. There is no question about it.''</p>
        <p>Bankruptcy Is a Mystery</p>
        <p>Since no county has ever gone bankrupt, it is not clear just what will happen if Butte does. Chapter 9 of the Federal Bankruptcy Law protects county and city governments from actions by their creditors, and the county would stop paying its bills until it could work out a payment plan with creditors from the telephone company to the state itself. Paychecks to county employees would not stop, but the state might have to take over paying the workers if the county could not do so. The county does not expect any disruption in local services.</p>
        <p>For the past three years, it has been a tossup as to which of the rural counties would go under first. Like its neighbors, Butte County has kept going by closing libraries or having some branches open a few hours per week staffed by volunteers. County employees have not had a cost-of-living raise in four years, and the staff at the Sheriff's Department has been slashed so that only 24 deputies are available to patrol more than 1,600 square miles.</p>
        <p>The County Supervisors Association report concluded that Butte had financed state-mandated programs ''on the backs of county employees and by deferral of essential maintenance of the county's infrastructure.'' Had it not done so, the report said, the county would have encountered bankruptcy three years ago.</p>
        <p>Several other counties are in a similar position. Shasta County to the north staved off bankruptcy by closing the county hospital, laying off more than 200 employees in the process. Others have sought creative solutions, like Kern County, which is trying to impose a fee on cities for every prisoner arrested and booked into the county jail.</p>
        <p>Refusal to Raise Taxes</p>
        <p>But taxpayers firmly refuse to raise taxes until the overall issue of how state-mandated programs will be financed is addressed on a statewide level. Voters here and in other counties have rejected local ballot measures seeking special assessments to finance libraries, jails and other services.</p>
        <p>''Even with a state bailout this year, we won't have money for more police or fire protection services,'' said Nell Lind, president of the 5,000-member Butte County Taxpayers Association. ''The state has stolen our tax money to pay for all these social welfare programs and their bureaucracy. Bankruptcy is the only solution because there has to be structural change on a state level.''</p>
        <p>Like other rural counties in California, Butte has cities that are incorporated and can rely on their own revenue from sales taxes. Chico, a city that has a campus of California State University, is financially sound and has even used its own money to keep open a branch of the Butte County Library, A Call for Change Larry E. Naake, the executive director of the County Supervisors Association of California, said the tax revolt is alive and well in this state and will continue to resist tax increases as the solution to problems. ''There is a somewhat stingy group of Californians who continue to think you can freeze or reduce taxes and still have the same or a higher level of services,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Naake has proposed changes, including forcing the state to pay the entire cost of welfare programs and guarantee counties a stable source of revenue for other mandated programs like courts and the public defender's office.</p>
        <p>Ed McLaughlin, an almond farmer who is chairman of the Butte County Board of Supervisors, agrees that any restructuring of the traditional division of duties between the state and the counties must leave some duties to the counties.</p>
        <p>''County government here is so accessible,'' he said. ''People feel frustrated if they have to call Sacramento when they can catch a member of their Board of Supervisors at a lunch counter.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
