<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Expos Continue To Pester Pirates</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="383090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Pittsburgh Pirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDB1738F933A2575AC0A966958260" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Expos Continue To Pester Pirates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, Sept. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Andres Galarraga and Mike Fitzgerald homered as the Montreal Expos took an early four-run lead and went on to beat the Pittsburgh Pirates, 9-5, today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Andres Galarraga and Mike Fitzgerald homered as the Montreal Expos took an early four-run lead and went on to beat the Pittsburgh Pirates, 9-5, today.</p>
        <p>The loss was just the second in nine games for Pittsburgh, which maintained its three-and-a-half game lead over the Mets.</p>
        <p>Martinez, 2-1 with a 1.69 earned run average against Pittsburgh, left after Wally Backman's line drive off the pitcher. The ball richocheted nearly to the third-base line, but Martinez recovered to throw Backman out before grabbing his right shoulder in pain.</p>
        <p>Martinez, later diagnosed as having a bad bruise, threw one warmup pitch and was replaced by Mel Rojas (2-1).</p>
        <p>Galarraga's 18th homer, a two-run drive in the second, gave Montreal the lead and the Expos made it 4-0 in the third on Dave Martinez's run-batted-in triple and DeShields's run-scoring double.</p>
        <p>Bonds hit his career-high 26th homer in the fourth amd King hit a two-run homer in the fifth, his 13th.</p>
        <p>Giants 5, Astros 1</p>
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) - Kevin Mitchell drove in three runs and Mark Portugal lost to San Francisco for the first time in six career decisions as the Giants won.</p>
        <p>Mitchell, who began the game in an 0-for-16 slump, hit an r.b.i. single with two outs in the first and a two-out, two-run homer in the sixth, his 33d home run of the season. It tied him with Ryne Sandberg of the Chicago Cubs for the National League lead.</p>
        <p>Dodgers 6, Reds 4</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES (AP) - Alfredo Griffin drove in the go-ahead run with a fifth-inning squeeze bunt as Los Angeles reduced the Reds' lead to five and a half games in the National League West.</p>
        <p>Ramon Martinez (17-6) won for only the second time in six starts, increasing his record against the West to 10-0 this year. The Cincinnati third baseman Bill Doran made two errors that led to a pair of unearned runs.</p>
        <p>Martinez allowed eight hits in his ninth complete game, the most in the majors. He struck out eight to give him 200 and regain the league lead from David Cone of the Mets.</p>
        <p>Mariners 3, Red Sox 1</p>
        <p>BOSTON (AP) - Boston found a replacement for Roger Clemens, but Seattle's Matt Young spoiled the plan.</p>
        <p>Young worked out of two bases-loaded jams and pitched seven strong innings as the Mariners won. With just their fourth loss in 16 games, Boston's lead in the American League East was trimmed to four and a half games over Toronto. Young (8-14) tied a major league record with four strikeouts in the first inning and went on to outduel the veteran reliever Joe Hesketh (0-2), pushed into his first start since 1986 because of Clemens's shoulder injury.</p>
        <p>Young began the first inning by striking out Jody Reed and Carlos Quintana. Boggs also struck out, but reached first on a passed ball.</p>
        <p>After Ellis Burks singled, Young struck out Mike Greenwell. Young blanked Boston until Reed's run-scoring infield single with two outs in the seventh.</p>
        <p>Hesketh was released this season by Montreal and Atlanta before signing with Boston.</p>
        <p>Orioles 3, Angels 1</p>
        <p>BALTIMORE (AP) - Anthony Telford, a rookie, earned his second major-league victory with six and one-third solid innings and Baltimore completed a three-game sweep.</p>
        <p>The Orioles won their third straight game for the first time since beating Chicago four straight, July 19-22.</p>
        <p>Telford, called up from Class AA ball in mid-August, improved to 2-2. He gave up five hits and one run, before getting relief help from Jose Bautista and Joe Price in the seventh. Curt Schilling worked one inning and Gregg Olson finished for his 30th save.</p>
        <p>Indians 12, Twins 9</p>
        <p>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) - Candy Maldonado's two-out, seventh-inning double scored the go-ahead runs in Cleveland's seven-run rally to lead the Indians past.</p>
        <p>After making three errors and missing several scoring opportunities over the first six innings, the Indians rallied from a 5-1 deficit off the starter Mark Guthrie and the reliever Jack Savage (0-2) with eight of their season-high 20 hits in the seventh.</p>
        <p>Blue Jays 6, White Sox 1</p>
        <p>TORONTO (AP) - Fred McGriff and Greg Myers hit consecutive home runs in a four-run sixth inning as Toronto won.</p>
        <p>The Blue Jays broke their American League attendance record with a sellout crowd of 49,870. It was the club's 48th consecutive sellout and increased the season total to 3,386,385.</p>
        <p>The slumping White Sox made a season-high four errors in losing for the third straight day to the Blue Jays. Chicago fell nine and a half games behind Oakland in the West.</p>
        <p>McGriff led off the sixth with his 33d home run. Myers followed with a homer to the middle deck in right for his fifth homer of the season and first since June 16.</p>
        <p>Tigers 5, Brewers 0</p>
        <p>MILWAUKEE (AP) - Scott Aldred gave up four hits over five innings to win his major league debut as Detroit snapped a four-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Aldred, 6-15 with a 4.90 earnerd-run average at Triple-A Toledo, walked five and fanned two before leaving. Edwin Nunez pitched four innings of two-hit relief for his fifth save.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
