<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pressed by Media, China Accuses Mine Officials of Cover-Up</title>
    <meta content="Y01CHIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/01/international/asia/01CHIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1321533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nandan County (China)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckholm, Erik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Li Dongming</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3D61030F932A3575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pressed by Media, China Accuses Mine Officials of Cover-Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pressed by Media, China Accuses Mine Officials of Cover-up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIK ECKHOLM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eckholm, Erik</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, Aug. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eleven mine officials and four Nandan County, China, political leaders are arrested in probe of July flooding at tin mine in which 81 workers drowned and of attempted cover-up; mine officials are charged with mismanagement, illegal extraction, chaotic digging and illegal blasting; disaster attracted wide attention because of role of unusually dogged Chinese newspaper reporters in drawing lurid picture of local kingpin Li Dongming, reporting he got rich running mines with backing of armed gang and government officials he bribed; more arrests are expected (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eleven mine officials and four county political leaders have been arrested in connection with the deadly flooding last month of a tin mine in southern China and an attempt to cover up the disaster, government investigators said today.</p>
        <p>Eighty-one workers drowned after carelessly planned blasting on July 17 opened up a water-filled shaft, sending torrents into nearby tunnels at the mine complex in Nandan County, in Guangxi region. Investigators from Beijing determined that the disaster was ''the direct result of mismanagement, illegal extraction, chaotic digging and explosions contrary to regulations,'' according to a report by the official New China News Agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eleven mine officials and four county political leaders have been arrested in connection with the deadly flooding last month of a Chinese tin mine</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eleven mine officials and four county political leaders have been arrested in connection with the deadly flooding last month of a tin mine in southern China and an attempt to cover up the disaster, government investigators said today.</p>
        <p>Eighty-one workers drowned after carelessly planned blasting on July 17 opened up a water-filled shaft, sending torrents into nearby tunnels at the mine complex in Nandan County, in Guangxi region. Investigators from Beijing determined that the disaster was ''the direct result of mismanagement, illegal extraction, chaotic digging and explosions contrary to regulations,'' according to a report by the official New China News Agency.</p>
        <p>After the disaster, county officials ''acted in collusion with the mine owner and used illegal means to cover up the accident,'' the agency reported today, calling this ''particularly egregious.''</p>
        <p>The disaster attracted wide attention not only because of the high death toll but also because of the role of unusually dogged Chinese newspaper reporters in disclosing it.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, national investigators and press accounts have drawn a lurid picture of a local kingpin, Li Dongming, reporting that he got rich running this and other mines with the backing of a gun-toting gang and government officials whom he plied with cash and free cars. Mr. Li is now in police custody, along with 10 other mine officials, the county's Communist Party secretary and deputy secretary, and the two top administrative officials of the county government.</p>
        <p>Further arrests are likely, government investigators said, for crimes of negligence, bribery and ''Mafia operations.''</p>
        <p>The deadly accident occurred at 3:40 a.m. on July 17, when mine officials set off two explosions in a 550-foot-deep shaft, ''even though they knew there was a danger of flooding,'' according to the account today.</p>
        <p>Soon after the disaster, mine officials offered large sums of money to relatives of lost miners to keep quiet.</p>
        <p>Angry relatives notified newspaper reporters, who persisted in trying to visit the site and question survivors despite threats from armed thugs.</p>
        <p>On July 30, even as Nandan County officials insisted there had been no deaths, accounts of a huge disaster and cover-up appeared in several newspapers. The charges gained credibility when reporters for People's Daily, the Communist Party paper, reported damning details on the paper's Web site.</p>
        <p>Investigators sent by the central government supervised the draining of the inundated tunnels and found the decomposed bodies of 78 miners, according to the account today. Two bodies found at the time of the collapse were secretly cremated. One other miner is missing and presumed dead, for a total of 81.</p>
        <p>Hundreds more men in the shafts that night were able to run for safety, officials now say.</p>
        <p>The case has been hailed by state-run newspapers as an example of the role the media should play in uncovering official crimes and corruption. But all media remain under political control, and in some other cases of apparent malfeasance, the press has been muzzled and zealous reporters and editors have lost their jobs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
