<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paterno Goes for 323, Coker for One</title>
    <meta content="01COLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/01/sports/ncaafootball/01COLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1321555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Miami (Florida)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Davis, Butch</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bowden, Bobby</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3DC1130F932A3575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paterno Goes for 323, Coker for One</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Paterno Goes for 323, Coker for One</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <dateline>STATE COLLEGE, Pa., Aug. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unless Miami and Penn State tie in their college football season opener here Saturday night, one of the head coaches will reach a milestone.</p>
        <p>If the Nittany Lions upset the Hurricanes, Joe Paterno will tie Bear Bryant's record of 323 victories in Division I-A. If Miami wins, Larry Coker will attain his first victory as a head coach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unless Miami and Penn State tie in their college football season opener on Saturday, one of the head coaches will reach a milestone for victories</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unless Miami and Penn State tie in their college football season opener here Saturday night, one of the head coaches will reach a milestone.</p>
        <p>If the Nittany Lions upset the Hurricanes, Joe Paterno will tie Bear Bryant's record of 323 victories in Division I-A. If Miami wins, Larry Coker will attain his first victory as a head coach.</p>
        <p>There will be other elements of excitement in this rare night game at this site. More than 106,000 fans -- the biggest crowd yet at expanded Beaver Stadium -- will greet Adam Taliaferro as he returns to the field. Although his playing career ended last season when he injured his spine as a freshman defensive back, Taliaferro's remarkable recovery has been one of few recent happy stories around a once-powerful program hoping to rebound from a 5-7 record, the worst in Paterno's 36 seasons.</p>
        <p>For Coker and the Hurricanes, who are led by quarterback Ken Dorsey, it will be their first appearance since finishing 11-1 as Big East champions and Sugar Bowl victors. The team was ranked second in the nation last season under Butch Davis. With 47 lettermen back, including eight starters on a potent offense, the Hurricanes are contenders for a national championship.</p>
        <p>''This is probably the toughest opening game we have played since we played Nebraska in the Kickoff Classic in 1983, when they kicked our ears in,'' Paterno said this week. ''It is a real challenge.'' In Penn State's 1983 opener, the Cornhuskers won by 44-6 at Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>While Dorsey is an experienced junior, Paterno's team will be led by an inexperienced junior, quarterback Matt Senneca. ''I think it is going to be very difficult, obviously, for a kid like Matt Senneca to go in there when people are going to compare him to a kid that may be the Heisman Trophy winner,'' Paterno said. ''That is how good the Dorsey kid is and the cast of characters that he has offensively with all of the experience and explosiveness.''</p>
        <p>Among other Miami stars are the offensive tackles Joaquin Gonzalez and Bryant McKinnie, who facilitate the efforts of running back Clinton Portis.</p>
        <p>Paterno said he did not want to hear his staff discussing his pursuit of Bryant's mark. ''I better not,'' Paterno said. ''There isn't anybody in this organization that even thinks about it. What happens, happens. If it happens, that would be great and we would all have a little fun and then we will walk away from it. You can't be playing a team like Miami and be thinking about whether I am going to tie a record or something.''</p>
        <p>Bobby Bowden of Florida State is close behind with 315 victories; the Seminoles open Saturday at Duke.</p>
        <p>There are other important games in the first busy week of the season. In Tuscaloosa, Alabama will play host to U.C.L.A. in a matchup of prestigious programs coming off poor seasons. Alabama, which finished 3-8 last season, has replaced Coach Mike DuBose with Dennis Franchione. The Bruins, 6-6 last season, have Bob Toledo back.</p>
        <p>Another attractive game pits Wisconsin at Oregon. The Badgers have already played, beating Virginia. But they may be without quarterback Brooks Bollinger, who is recovering from a bruised liver. The Ducks finished 10-2 last season and tied for the Pac-10 title. With the Heisman candidate Joey Harrington returning at quarterback, anything less this season may be considered a disappointment.</p>
        <p>In other games involving top teams, Oklahoma takes its 1-0 record to Air Force; Colorado State visits Colorado; Oregon State is at Fresno State; and Syracuse, which lost last Sunday to Georgia Tech, gets another tough test at Tennessee. Hofstra, meanwhile, will play its first Atlantic 10 game after eight years as an independent. It will face visiting Northeastern.</p>
        <p>But the Miami-Penn State game has cachet. The two schools have met only 12 times, with the Lions holding a 7-5 edge. Both used to be independent, but Miami now represents the Big East and Penn State is in the Big Ten.</p>
        <p>In their last meeting, in 1999, Penn State beat Miami by 27-23. In their most memorable game, the 1987 Fiesta Bowl for the national championship of the 1986 season, the Nittany Lions won, 14-10. Players from that team are having a reunion at halftime Saturday, another emotional spur for the underdogs.</p>
        <p>Although Coker has never been a head coach, he is 53 and experienced as an assistant. When Davis took a job with the Cleveland Browns, Coker's players lobbied for his promotion.</p>
        <p>Referring to the emotion of the home opener in the remodeled stadium and the appearance of the recovering Taliaferro, Coker said, ''It's going to be a very strong psychological advantage for Penn State.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Coker added, ''I'll be applauding when he leads their team out.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
