<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Was Who in the Cover-Up and Uncovering of Watergate</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="536290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="WATERGATE, THEN AND NOW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATERGATE AFFAIR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERNSTEIN, CARL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUTTERFIELD, ALEXANDER P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KALMBACH, HERBERT W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLSON, CHARLES W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COX, ARCHIBALD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EHRLICHMAN, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, L PATRICK 3D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALDEMAN, H R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUNT, E HOWARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEINDIENST, RICHARD G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KROGH, EGIL JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAGRUDER, JEB STUART</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, JOHN N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIRICA, JOHN J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLS, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOODWARD, BOB</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCORD, JAMES W JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARKER, BERNARD L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GONZALEZ, VIRGILIO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARTINEZ, EUGENIO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STURGIS, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEWITT, KAREN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Watergate Affair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DC1F3CF936A25755C0A964958260" item-length="2181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Was Who in the Cover-Up and Uncovering of Watergate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DE WITT,</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The discovery of an attempted burglary of the office of the Democratic National Committee on June 17, 1972 -- an incident President Richard M. Nixon referred to as "that pipsqueak Watergate" -- led to disclosures that unraveled over the next two years like a ball of twine.</p>
        <p>Entangled in that skein were dozens of men implicated in the scandal, many of whom were top aides to the President. As it steadily unwound, the American people watched a parade of witnesses expose the details of a political crime whose proportions were nearly unfathomable: wiretapping, money laundering, destruction of documents, payment of hush money, character assassination, disinformation and deception -- all perpetrated by people at the highest levels of Government. More than 30 people pleaded guilty or were convicted of crimes like perjury, burglary, wiretapping and obstruction of justice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The discovery of an attempted burglary of the office of the Democratic National Committee on June 17, 1972 -- an incident President Richard M. Nixon referred to as "that pipsqueak Watergate" -- led to disclosures that unraveled over the next two years like a ball of twine.</p>
        <p>Entangled in that skein were dozens of men implicated in the scandal, many of whom were top aides to the President. As it steadily unwound, the American people watched a parade of witnesses expose the details of a political crime whose proportions were nearly unfathomable: wiretapping, money laundering, destruction of documents, payment of hush money, character assassination, disinformation and deception -- all perpetrated by people at the highest levels of Government. More than 30 people pleaded guilty or were convicted of crimes like perjury, burglary, wiretapping and obstruction of justice.</p>
        <p>"That pipsqueak Watergate" finally ran itself out in the Oval Office. Mr. Nixon, described by the House Judiciary Committee in its impeachment articles as the "unindicted co-conspirator" in his Administration's cover-up of the connections between the Watergate burglary and the White House dirty-tricks department, resigned on August 9, 1974. "Resignation meant life without purpose as far as I was concerned," Mr. Nixon said later.</p>
        <p>Following are a more than a score of others who were major players in coordinating the break-in and cover-up, or in unraveling the scheme. Although some were willing to reminisce about Watergate, others could not be reached for comment or declined to be interviewed. Carl Bernstein Washington Post reporter</p>
        <p>With Bob Woodward, Mr. Bernstein was half of the Washington Post reporting team that uncovered the Watergate scandal and earned a Pulitzer Prize. The scandal thrust the pair into the limelight, especially after they wrote "All the President's Men" and "The Final Days" about Watergate. Mr. Bernstein went on to work for ABC News and Time magazine, and recently wrote a memoir of his parents. Mr. Bernstein, 48 years old, said that the lesson of Watergate was that "the system really did work." Alexander P. Butterfield Nixon aide</p>
        <p>Mr. Butterfield, who disclosed the existence of the "Watergate tapes," the Oval Office conversations that had been recorded, said he is still angry at Mr.  Nixon for what he considers his refusal to take responsibility for Watergate. The tapes showed that Mr. Nixon had approved paying hush money to the Watergate burglars and sought to block the investigation of the break-in. Mr. Butterfield, now 66 and chief executive of Armistead &amp; Alexander, a management consulting firm in San Diego, said: "The President was trying to get people to believe that this was something his aides had gone off and done on their own. That was the myth he was trying to perpetuate." Although he said he still admired some of the former President's attributes, he added, "On the issue of morality, I just give Richard Nixon the lowest possible marks." Charles W. Colson Special counsel to Nixon</p>
        <p>Mr. Colson, known as a master of dirty political tricks, once said that he would "walk over my grandmother if necessary" to insure Mr. Nixon's re-election. He was instrumental in setting up the break-in team, and he disseminated false information about Daniel Ellsberg, the Pentagon researcher who said he gave the Pentagon Papers on the Vietnam War to the press in 1971. In 1973, Mr. Colson pleaded guilty to obstruction of justice and other offenses. He served seven months in prison and became a born-again Christian. Now 60, he is a lay minister and chairman of Prison Fellowships Ministries and has written several books. Archibald Cox Watergate prosecutor</p>
        <p>As the first special Watergate prosecutor, Mr. Cox laid the legal groundwork for prosecution of the conspirators and for the Supreme Court decision requiring President Nixon to turn over tapes of converstaions in the Oval Office. Appointed by Attorney General Elliott L. Richardson, a former student, Mr. Cox promised to pursue his investigation wherever it led. But five months later, in what became known as the "Saturday Night Massacre," Mr. Cox was fired, on Mr. Nixon's orders, by Acting Attorney General Robert Bork after Mr. Richardson resigned rather than execute the President's order. He was replaced by Leon Jaworski, a Texas lawyer. Mr. Cox, 80, recently retired after 45 years on the Harvard Law School faculty. John Ehrlichman Nixon adviser</p>
        <p>Mr. Ehrlichman supervised the covert actions of the Special Investigations Unit, known as "the Plumbers," organized to plug leaks to the press. Mr. Ehrlichman was convicted of conspiracy to obstruct justice and perjury in the Watergate cover-up and conspiracy in the 1971 raid on the office of Daniel Ellsberg's psychiatrist. Mr. Ellsberg, a Pentagon researcher, has said he leaked the Pentagon Papers to the press. Mr. Ehrlichman served 18 months in prison before his release in 1978, and was suspended from the practice of law. Now 67, he lives in Atlanta where he works for Law Companies Group, a consulting firm. L. Patrick Gray 3d Acting F.B.I. Director</p>
        <p>Mr. Gray hampered the investigation of the burglary by destroying documents under pressure from the White House. During hearings on his nomination to be F.B.I. director in early 1973, he admitted turning over F.B.I. files on the Watergate affair to John W. Dean 3d, the White House counsel. President Nixon withdrew his name from nomination, saying he had done so at Mr. Gray's request. Mr. Gray, 63, is now a lawyer in New London, Conn. H. R. Haldeman White House chief of staff</p>
        <p>Mr. Haldeman and John Erhlichman, an adviser to President Nixon, were dubbed "The Prussians," not only because of their German surnames but also because of their peremptory manner in protecting Mr. Nixon. A former advertising executive and Mr. Nixon's closest confidant, Mr. Haldeman served 18 months in jail for conspiracy to obstruct justice and perjury in the Watergate cover-up. Mr. Nixon turned down his request for a pardon, and Mr. Haldeman later accused his former boss of being behind the cover-up "from day one." Mr. Haldeman, 65, now lives in Santa Barbara, Calif., and is a real-estate developer with interests in restaurants and hotels. E. Howard Hunt Consultant</p>
        <p>A former C.I.A. agent and prolific mystery writer, Mr. Hunt worked for Charles W. Colson, President Nixon's master of political tricks. Mr. Hunt was dismissed by John Erlichman after taking part in covert political operations like the coordination of the Watergate break-in and the burglary of the Los Angeles office of Daniel Ellsberg's psychiatrist in search of incriminating information about a Nixon "enemy." He served 33 months in prison for burglary, conspiracy and wiretapping. Mr. Hunt asserted that he had agreed to plead guilty because Mr. Colson had promised him that the President would grant him clemency. Now 73, he lives in Miami where he has just completed his 74th book. Richard G. Kleindienst United States Attorney General</p>
        <p>Mr. Kleindienst resigned as Attorney General in April 1973, citing a conflict of interest because the scandal had implicated "persons with whom I had close personal and professional associations." Though not charged in the Watergate conspiracy, Mr. Kleindienst pleaded guilty to a misdemeanor charge of refusing to testify fully and accurately before the Senate Watergate committee about the White House role in a Justice Department suit against the International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation, a corollary scandal. His $100 fine and one-month jail sentence were suspended. He practiced law in Washington until 1979, when he moved to Tuscon, Ariz. Mr. Kleindienst, 68, said that he had often been lumped with those involved in the Watergate affair. Of the scandal, he said, "The carnival-type atmosphere surrounding Watergate, you just can't imagine what it was like." Egil Krogh Jr. Aide</p>
        <p>Mr. Krogh headed the Special Investigations Unit, known as "the Plumbers," organized to plug leaks to the press at the time of the break-in of the office of Daniel Ellsberg's psychiatrist. Mr. Krogh admitted authorizing the break-in and served four months in prison on a conspiracy conviction.  "At the time, in 1971, I thought that what we were doing was dictated inescapably by the national security interests," he said. Mr. Krogh said Watergate taught him that "You have to remain true to your deepest sense of what is right. You have to be willing to question what you're being asked to do. I wasn't willing to question what I was doing." He said he sees President Nixon, John Ehrlichman, Donald Segretti and other players in the Watergate affair perhaps once a year.  Since 1980, Mr. Krogh, 52, has been a partner with Culp, Dwyer, Guterson &amp; Grader law firm in Seattle, where he lives. John J. Sirica Judge</p>
        <p>Judge Sirica of United States District Court in Washington sentenced 12 of the Watergate defendants to jail and also ordered President Nixon to release his White House tapes. Recently recovered from pneumonia, Judge Sirica, 88, retired four years ago and lives in Washington. His son, Jack, a reporter in the Washington bureau of Newsday, said the judge considered the Watergate trial the high point of his career. Frank Wills Security guard</p>
        <p>Mr. Wills discovered the break-in at the Watergate office and called the police, uncovering a burglary that eventually brought down a president. Unlike some others, including several of the co-conspirators, Mr. Wills did not profit from the scandal. A celebrity for an instant, he quickly sank from public view. He worked sporadically as a security guard and in 1983 he was sentenced to a year in jail for shoplifting a $12 pair of sneakers. "Watergate hasn't really changed my life," he said. "I was just doing my job. If anything, the crooks benefited. They got famous." Since 1990, Mr. Wills, 45, has been living in North Augusta, S.C., caring for his sick mother.  Bob Woodward Washington Post reporter</p>
        <p>Mr. Woodward, 49, is now managing editor for investigative reporting at the newspaper. After writing two books about Watergate with Carl Bernstein, he went on to write several more bestsellers. When asked whether Watergate could happen again, Mr. Woodward said, "Maybe it has, and we don't know it." Herbert W. Kalmbach Nixon lawyer</p>
        <p>Mr. Kalmbach was associate finance chairman of the 1968 Nixon for President campaign and was an unoffical fund-raiser for the Committee for the Re-election of the President, controlling several secret funds. Mr. Kalmbach served six months in jail and was fined $10,000 for operating an illegal campaign committee and for offering an ambassadorship in return for political support. He also handled a secret $500,000 fund to finance sabotage and espionage operations in the salary of Donald H. Segretti, a lawyer, whose job it was to discredit the Democrats. Mr. Kalmbach is now 69 and an investor in Newport Beach, Calif. Jeb Stuart Magruder Deputy campaign director</p>
        <p>Mr. Magruder, 57, said he would have stayed in government service had it not been for Watergate. For his part in the cover-up, Mr. Magruder pleaded guilty to conspiracy to obstruct justice and served seven months in prison. The former cosmetics company executive is today the senior minister at First Presbyterian Church in Lexington, Ky. The ministry, he said, is not a direct result of his experiences after Watergate but offers him the same chance to serve that being in government did. John N. Mitchell Campaign director</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell, President Nixon's former law partner and a former Attorney General resigned after his wife, Martha, demanded publicly that he leave politics and "all those dirty things that go on." The couple separated in 1974, and Mrs. Mitchell blamed Mr. Nixon. Mr. Mitchell was accused of having knowledge of numerous dirty tricks in the Watergate cover-up but denied that he had done anything but withhold some information from investigators, for what he termed were solid political reasons. He was convicted of conspiracy, obstruction of justice and perjury and served 19 months in jail. Mr. Mitchell left prison in 1979 and was disbarred. He lived quietly in Washington until his death Nov. 9, 1988 at the age of 75. The Burglars</p>
        <p>JAMES W. McCORD JR., a former C.I.A. employee and chief of security for the Nixon re-election committee, was the lead burglar inthe Atergate break-in. After implicating the White House, he was sentenced to four months in jail.</p>
        <p>Of the others, BERNARD L. BARKER, 75, was one of three Cuban exiles recruited by a former C.I.A. agent, E. Howard Hunt. Mr. Barker, who is a retired zoning inspector in Miami, said: "We did our jobs. Under the circumstances, I have no regrets about it." Mr. Barker said that he occasionally sees his fellow burglars, VIRGILIO GONZALEZ, 67, a retired locksmith, and EUGENIO MARTINEZ, 68, a sales manager at a car dealership. The fifth burglar, FRANK STURGIS, 67, also lives in Miami.  WATERGATE, THEN AND NOW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
