<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Belarus Charges Detained Opposition Leader</title>
    <meta content="27belarus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/27/international/europe/27belarus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1750054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belarus</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kazulin, Aleksandr V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lukashenko, Aleksandr G (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belarus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belarus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Belarus</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Lukashenko, Aleksandr G</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EEDC1430F934A15750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Belarus Charges Detained Opposition Leader</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Belarus Charges Detained Opposition Leader</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chivers, C J</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, March 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aleksandr Kazulin, detained opposition leader in Belarus, faces charge of criminal hooliganism and is denied prison visits; he was seized when riot police attacked peaceful protesters marching to prison where opposition members are jailed; protesters report several people with serious injuries; Kazulin challenged Pres Aleksandr G Lukashenko, whose landslide re-election has been declared invalid by Western observers; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A detained opposition leader in Belarus faced a criminal charge on Sunday and was denied prison visits by a doctor and a lawyer, his wife said. Minsk, the capital, fell quiet after a violent police crackdown against antigovernment demonstrators on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Aleksandr V. Kazulin, who had challenged the authoritarian president, Aleksandr G. Lukashenko, in an election earlier this month, was seized Saturday when riot police officers with batons attacked a column of peaceful protesters who were marching to a prison where opposition members had been jailed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A detained opposition leader faced a charge of hooliganism and was denied prison visits by a doctor and a lawyer, his wife said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A detained opposition leader in Belarus faced a criminal charge on Sunday and was denied prison visits by a doctor and a lawyer, his wife said. Minsk, the capital, fell quiet after a violent police crackdown against antigovernment demonstrators on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Aleksandr V. Kazulin, who had challenged the authoritarian president, Aleksandr G. Lukashenko, in an election earlier this month, was seized Saturday when riot police officers with batons attacked a column of peaceful protesters who were marching to a prison where opposition members had been jailed.</p>
        <p>He was held Sunday at a detention center well outside Minsk, on a charge of hooliganism, said his wife, Irina Kazulin. The charge can carry penalties ranging from a fine to several years in prison.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kazulin said she visited the jail but was not allowed to see her husband or speak with him by phone. She said she demanded that he be examined by a doctor and allowed to consult a lawyer, but was told by a prison official that there would be no visits before Monday.</p>
        <p>''Human rights do not work on Sunday in Belarus,'' she said bitterly in a telephone interview. She said she was not sure whether her husband had been injured.</p>
        <p>Opposition members said at least three people were in serious medical condition with either skull fractures or spinal injuries after being beaten by the police when the march was broken up on Saturday.</p>
        <p>One man with a skull injury had been hovering near death, but had survived so far, said Aleksei Shein, a spokesman for Aleksandr Milinkevich, the principal challenger to Mr. Lukashenko.</p>
        <p>''Thank God this man is still alive,'' Mr. Shein said of the injured demonstrator, who was one of at least two men seen lying immobile on the street after lines of officers from SOBR, a special rapid-reaction force that has been widely accused of extensive human rights abuses, attacked the marchers.</p>
        <p>The march was the third opposition event of the day. The police forcibly blocked demonstrators, estimated at 6,000, from reaching a rally planned for October Square, punching and kicking many of them as they tried to push through police lines or block traffic, and ultimately clearing the sidewalks with advancing formations that pummeled people in their path.</p>
        <p>A peaceful rally then took place at Yanka Kupala park, which the police videotaped but did not break up. At Mr. Kazulin's urging, several hundred demonstrators left for a march to the prison, during which the worst violence of the day occurred.</p>
        <p>Austria, which holds the rotating presidency of the European Union, said in a statement on Sunday that the Union ''is appalled by the violence used against demonstrators'' and called for the release of Mr. Kazulin and the other protesters.</p>
        <p>Such statements by the West have had little visible effect on the Belarussian government, which retains many of the features of the Soviet police state Mr. Lukashenko apparently admires.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lukashenko, whose landslide re-election on March 19 has been declared invalid by the West because of charges of wide-scale rigging and abuses of state power, has resorted to police sweeps, mass arrests and violence to try to quell the unrest. Russia, his closest ally, has offered him unequivocal support.</p>
        <p>For the first time during Mr. Lukashenko's 12 years of rule, however, demonstrators have defied the police and vowed to carry out more peaceful actions in the face of arrests, state violence and expulsions from universities or jobs. Another rally is set for April 26, the 20th anniversary of the Chernobyl nuclear disaster.</p>
        <p>The authorities have not released arrest figures or provided information about the injured, making it difficult to assess the extent of the arrests, or the conditions or even the identities of some of the detained.</p>
        <p>Among those thought to be held are a small number of journalists from Russia, Canada and Western Europe, as well as foreign demonstrators, including Ukrainians, Poles and at least one man from Ireland, who was interviewed at a small protest camp Friday shortly before the riot police smashed the camp and arrested demonstrators there.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
