<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Hands Out Its 'I Like Mike' Buttons</title>
    <meta content="Y05TYS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/05/national/05TYSO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1373072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Organization for Women</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyson, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Lennox</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Anthony A (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Organization for Women</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E2DA1730F936A35750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Hands Out Its 'I Like Mike' Buttons</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Washington Hands Out 'I Like Mike' Buttons</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Proposed heavyweight title bout in June between Mike Tyson and Lennox Lewis creates controversy in Washington, DC; idea of allowing fight is denounced by church leaders, National Organization for Women and city's Board of Trade because of Tyson's reputation, and is enthusiastically endorsed by city's tourist industry, its blue-collar and pro-boxing public and Mayor Anthony A Williams; fight is expected to produce largest arena and television gate in history, including as much as $10 million in profit for city businesses; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 57 years of capital city life and 53 prizefights studded with 14 defeats, Adrian F. Davis seems entitled to bask in moral relativism as he discusses the merits of Bill Clinton, Richard M. Nixon and Mike Tyson, the heavyweight ex-convict with the knockout punch and notorious résumé.</p>
        <p>''I've seen backsliding by the leaders of the most powerful country on earth,'' Mr. Davis, speaking over the rat-tat-tat of punching bags, said of the two former presidents. ''So don't tell me Mike Tyson can't come and help the city make some money now that our economy is hurting.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The debate about the proposed fight between Mike Tyson and Lennox Lewis is as much about hypocrites as role models.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After 57 years of capital city life and 53 prizefights studded with 14 defeats, Adrian F. Davis seems entitled to bask in moral relativism as he discusses the merits of Bill Clinton, Richard M. Nixon and Mike Tyson, the heavyweight ex-convict with the knockout punch and notorious résumé.</p>
        <p>''I've seen backsliding by the leaders of the most powerful country on earth,'' Mr. Davis, speaking over the rat-tat-tat of punching bags, said of the two former presidents. ''So don't tell me Mike Tyson can't come and help the city make some money now that our economy is hurting.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Davis, a well-known trainer at the Round 1 boxing gym, the sweet science in Washington is as much about politics as pugilism. And the rope-a-dope debate in this city about the proposed June title fight between Mr. Tyson and Lennox Lewis, the world champion, is as much about hypocrites as role models.</p>
        <p>''He served his time; it's over,'' Mr. Davis said of Mr. Tyson, who spent three years in prison for a rape conviction. ''Till he commits another crime, he's an innocent man trying to see to his constitutional right to work for a living.''</p>
        <p>A hearing by the city's Boxing and Wrestling Commission is set for next week on the proposed fight, which is expected to produce the largest arena and television gate in history, including as much as $10 million in profit for city businesses.</p>
        <p>The proposed fight has already occasioned severe denunciations from church leaders, the National Organization for Women and the D.C. Board of Trade because of Mr. Tyson's record of abusing women, biting opponents in the ring and sucker-punching rivals at news conferences.</p>
        <p>But there have been enthusiastic endorsements, too, from the city's tourist industry, its blue-collar and pro-boxing public exemplified by Mr. Davis, and even the office of Mayor Anthony A. Williams, a classically cautious politician who nevertheless predicted ''a very positive impact'' if the tourist-starved city eventually licenses the fight.</p>
        <p>''It's been tough, but this is the fight game,'' said Michael Brown, vice chairman of the boxing commission, which set off a storm by offering fast preliminary approval of the proposed match.</p>
        <p>''We've heard legitimate outrage from women's groups criticizing Tyson, and rightfully so,'' Mr. Brown added. ''But there's also those who loudly register their opposition, then call us later asking for tickets to the fight.''</p>
        <p>Not all the city's boxing lovers want the match.</p>
        <p>''I got a bad sense about this fight,'' said Jeffrey Gildenhorn, former chairman of the boxing commission.</p>
        <p>''Tyson's aberrations have no place in boxing,'' said Mr. Gildenhorn, an unsuccessful mayoral candidate four years ago. ''He's degrading the sport.''</p>
        <p>Like other residents, Mr. Gildenhorn questions whether the city, which has acquitted itself handily in containing recent anarchist street threats, might somehow embarrass itself in dealing with ''gangsta nation'' elements that critics warn will come for the big fight.</p>
        <p>''We live in a chaotic world,'' Mr. Gildenhorn said. ''God forbid if some deranged guy stands in front of the arena and -- boom -- blows himself up.''</p>
        <p>But one of the city's boxing elders, Jim Finley, who closed his city gym last year after four decades of training youngsters, said some city would eventually stage the fight, so it might as well be Washington.</p>
        <p>''Tyson is very popular in the black community, particularly among the young,'' said Mr. Finley, who is black. He said he found Mr. Tyson, for all his bad sportsmanship in the ring, to be profanity-free and considerate when he trained in his gym last year. ''Maybe a lot of what we call the bourgeoisie wouldn't want this fight, but it really boils down to a Rock Creek-Southeast political situation,'' Mr. Finley said, using geographical shorthand for the city's racial dividing lines.</p>
        <p>At least the debate is more accessible and galvanizing to ordinary residents these days than the heavyweight, big-purse fight on Capitol Hill over the arcana of soft-money campaign donations for the other Washington, inhabited by national politicians.</p>
        <p>The Washington Post did not pull its punches in an editorial headlined: ''Not Here, Mr. Tyson.'' Nevada, Colorado, Texas and Georgia have turned down the fight, the newspaper noted, warning that ''with the troubled Mr. Tyson comes too much commotion, tawdriness and public disorder.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Finley, who has refereed many a match, argues that Mike Tyson should be penalized inside the ring, not outside, for his bad sportsmanship.</p>
        <p>''Remember, as long as there's two men on the face of the earth, one is going to challenge and the other will accept,'' he said, getting to the heart of the Washington arena.</p>
        <p>''From a boxing sense, we'll never get rid of man-on-man competition. We'll always have it,'' said the retired corner man, looking forward to a good fight, wherever it turns up.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
