<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Boots Could Reduce Knee Injuries</title>
    <meta content="15SKII$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/15/sports/15SKII.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1270935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THE SKI REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DE1430F936A25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Boots Could Reduce Knee Injuries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses new ski boot, Lange V9, that has rear releasing mechanism attached to back of boot that could help in reducing knee injuries; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They say you are safer skiing down the mountain than you are driving your car to get there. They say you are safer skiing than you are riding a bike. Some studies insist most team sports are more dangerous than skiing.</p>
        <p>Maybe, but picture a ski lodge and people usually visualize somebody in a leg cast reading a book by the fire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They say you are safer skiing down the mountain than you are driving your car to get there. They say you are safer skiing than you are riding a bike. Some studies insist most team sports are more dangerous than skiing.</p>
        <p>Maybe, but picture a ski lodge and people usually visualize somebody in a leg cast reading a book by the fire.</p>
        <p>The fact is, that person has all but disappeared. That's right. He or she had to go home to start rehabilitating a surgically repaired knee.</p>
        <p>Well, that's not fair either. Better ski-binding technologies and advanced trail grooming have made skiing far safer. Fractures of the lower leg are down by 90 percent in the past 20 years -- largely because of modern, harder plastic ski boots that come up to the middle of the calf.</p>
        <p>But under the duress of certain falls, the ankle and the lower leg are protected but the stress has shifted to the knee. Injuries are down over all, but the rate of knee injuries has doubled. Disturbingly, the anterior cruciate ligament has been particularly vulnerable to tearing. This can be a most complicated, debilitating injury. It also seems to strike women at a greater rate than men.</p>
        <p>Research in the United States and in Europe has also shown that a big chunk of the A.C.L. tears have occurred with the skier falling in exactly the same manner.</p>
        <p>A skier loses his or her balance and begins to fall backward, with at least one ski still positioned beneath the skier's torso. An arm may flail back, then the hips sink lower than the knees. If the skier falls all the way back, nearly sitting on the tails of the skis with knees bent greater than 90 degrees. . . . You get the picture and it comes with a soundtrack. Ouch!</p>
        <p>People have been falling like this for decades, but the old, flexible leather ski boots often allowed skiers to rescue themselves, or at least bend in such a way that lessened the strain on the knee.</p>
        <p>Several years ago, researchers at the University of Vermont, started to wonder if there was some way to maintain the performance and safety benefits of the high, rigid modern ski boot and reduce the stress on the knee under emergency circumstances. They devised a boot that had a rear-releasing mechanism attached to the uppermost cuff. Under the maximum pressure and tension of a backward fall, the device at the back of the boot released, enough to allow the skier's leg to straighten by 15 percent.</p>
        <p>The extra flexibility might permit a skier to recover sufficiently to avoid the fall. Or, it would ease the strain on the A.C.L. Once the skier regained his or her balance, the boot would relock in its natural, forward-leaning position.</p>
        <p>The Vermont researchers found their way to Lange Boots, whose founder Bob Lange pioneered modern boot technology. It took some guts for Lange to pursue a project that essentially conceded that modern boots, by their very design, are an implicated cause of a major injury.</p>
        <p>''Plus the first ones made looked like Frankenstein's monster's boots,'' said Charlie Adams, a Lange vice president.</p>
        <p>Seven years in the making, this winter Lange introduced its V9 boot for men and V9L for women, with its Rear Release System.</p>
        <p>Lange says on-hill tests and experiments with cadavers confirmed the rear-releasing system could significantly reduce the strain on the A.C.L. This is not a soft, spongy boot, nothing like the generally reviled, rear-entry boot.</p>
        <p>The release system -- no bigger than a bottle opener running up the back vertical portion of the boot -- can also be cranked up and loosened to adjust for various skiing abilities, styles and physical attributes.</p>
        <p>The knock on the boot so far has been that it is not a hard-charging, stiff racing boot, which is true. The new V9's that I tried did not make me want to throw out my old Lange racing boots, but then, we all have our security blankets.</p>
        <p>I did have a lot of fun throwing myself down on the snow trying to get the release mechanism to engage. It is a good way to get attention. Especially from ski patrol.</p>
        <p>The V9's provided a precise, firm and comfortable response from foot to ski. And really, how many recreational skiers need -- or want -- the feel of a racing boot? And those who have had knee trouble, and still want to ski, will definitely want to consider the potential benefits of Lange's V9.</p>
        <p>Dr. James Williams is a former coach with the United States Ski Team and now a surgeon with the Cleveland-Euclid Orthopedic Clinic in Ohio. He has skied with the new Lange boots and examined the clinical experiments.</p>
        <p>''It should buy time during a fall and the force on the knee shouldn't be so sudden,'' Williams said. ''I'll bet over time that it does lead to a reduction in A.C.L. injuries.''</p>
        <p>Williams recently expressed his support of the V9 in a more quantifiable way. His 18-year-old son was heading West to ski over the holidays.</p>
        <p>''He wears the same shoe size as mine, so I gave him my Lange V9's,'' Williams said. ''Next year, he wants to play sports in college.''</p>
        <p>Now if they could only come up with safer footwear for those other, more dangerous sports.</p>
        <p>THE SKI REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
