<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="07CLAS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1189848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6D6123FF934A35757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the New York metropolitan region.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>AMATO OPERA. The homespun but attractive qualities of this company's productions, and the intimacy of its shoe-box theater offer a useful change of perspective for operagoers used to the big houses uptown. The casts here vary: at the very least the singers are eager and enthusiastic; sometimes the singing shows great promise. And Anthony Amato, the company's founder, conducts the performances with an evident love of the music. Puccini's ''Madama Butterfly'' is currently on the boards. Tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 2:30 p.m. the Amato Opera, 319 Bowery at Second Street, East Village, (212) 228-8200. Tickets: $25, $20 for the elderly and children. (Allan Kozinn).</p>
        <p>''IL BARBIERE DI SIVIGLIA.'' The cast changes continue in the Metropolitan Opera's production of Rossini's ''Barbiere di Siviglia.'' The excellent mezzo-soprano Theodora Hanslowe sings Rosina, and the tenor Michael Shade is the poor student she loves who turns out to be, of course, Count Almaviva. The baritone Russell Braun is the clever, indispensable Figaro, so much more than the town barber. And Paul Plishka, a Met veteran who owns the role of Dr. Bartolo, sings it again. Bruno Campanella conducts. Metropolitan Opera House; tonight at 8, (212) 362-2000. Tickets: $26 to $225; sold out but returns may be available (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''LA BOHEME,'' Metropolitan Opera. Yet again, all Paris descends on the Latin Quarter in Act II of Puccini's opera, and viewers will get their fill. Listeners are another matter. In Franco Zeffirelli's extravaganza of a production, from 1981, it is hard for any singer of less than Pavarottian amplitude in both voice and physique even to register, let alone make a vivid impression. Certainly, Leontina Vaduva and Luis Lima, in the lead roles, did not exactly shine on opening night. Oh, well; there is always that wonderful orchestra, mercurially conducted here by Marco Armiliato. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-6000. Tickets: $26 to $225; sold out but returns may be available (James R. Oestreich).</p>
        <p>''CARMEN.'' The New York City Opera's colorful, effective production of Bizet's ''Carmen'' offers the mezzo-soprano Angela Horn in the title role. The hefty-voiced tenor Carl Tanner, who had been singing Mario in the company's updated production of ''Tosca,'' switches to Bizet's Don Jose. The soprano Barbara Shirvis will be Micaela and the baritone Jorge Lagunes will sing Escamillo. New York State Theater, tonight at 8, (212) 496-0600. Tickets: $22 to $95 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''LA CLEMENZA DI TITO.'' Harry Bicket conducts a lively, moving and thrilling New York City Opera performance of Mozart's glorious late score. The cast is led by Lorraine Hunt Lieberson in superb form as Sesto, caught between friendship for -- and loyalty to -- the emperor on the one side and sheer blind love for the scheming Vitellia on the other. Marie Plette, as Vitellia, achieves majesty when she gives up hope of the throne. Mark Thomsen takes over from Kurt Streit in the title role. Sunday at 1:30 p.m., New York Theater, (212) 496-0600. Tickets: $22 to $95 (Paul Griffiths).</p>
        <p>''LUCIA DI LAMMERMOOR.'' Since the Dicapo Opera presents three productions a weekend, the company, understandably, double-casts roles in demanding works. This weekend's production of Donizetti's ''Lucia di Lammermoor,'' at its intimate theater on East 76th Street, is one example. The title role will offer, alternately, the sopranos Oleksandra Hrabova and Indira Mahajan. The tenors Barton Green and Emmanuel di Villarosa share the role of Edgardo; and the baritones Gregory Keil and David Templeton do the same with Enrico. The bass Ding Gao has the role of Raimondo to himself. The production, sung in Italian, is directed by Michael Capasso and conducted by Valery Ryvkin. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and Sunday at 5 p.m., Dicapo Opera Theater, 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-9438 or (212) 759-7653. Tickets: $33 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''THE MOTHER OF US ALL,'' New York City Opera. Although this inscrutable work by Virgil Thomson and Gertrude Stein was written well before Lauren Flanigan was born, it seems to have been written for her. At the opening of this new production, Ms. Flanigan sang the title role of the suffragist Susan B. Anthony with fervor, sensitivity and sheer flowing beauty. Christopher Alden's direction seemed strenuous and earthbound, making more of the circus aspects of Thomson and Stein's conception than of the humane sensibility that lay underneath. In this context, Ms. Flanigan's touching portrayal was even more remarkable. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., New York State Theater, (212) 870-5570. Tickets: $22 to $95 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>''PELLEAS ET MELISANDE.'' Jonathan Miller's somber and affecting version of Debussy's great turn-of-the-century opera has returned to the Met with a marvelous American and English cast. Featured are Dawn Upshaw, Dwayne Croft, Willard White and Robert Lloyd. James Levine conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-2000. Tickets: $26 to $225; sold out but returns may be available (Bernard Holland).</p>
        <p>''TANIKO''/''DER JASAGER.'' The Nohgaku-za of Tokyo perform ''Taniko,'' about a sick boy's decision to sacrifice himself for the good of the group. So quiet, so slow, so stylized, the drama comes across as powerful, immediate and real. The same story, but with all the pathos, intensity, grace, wisdom and humanity taken out, is the basis for ''Der Jasager,'' by Brecht and Weill, which is presented by American performers in the second half. Today at 7:30 p.m., tomorrow at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan (212) 832-1155. Tickets: $55; $50 for members (Griffiths).</p>
        <p>''TOSCA.'' Television viewers recently got a chance to see Mark Lamos's spare, modern production of Puccini's ''Tosca'' for the New York City Opera, set in 1930's Italy, when ''Live From Lincoln Center'' carried it over PBS. For tomorrow night's performance, the soprano Holly Hall takes over the title role. The cast includes the tenor Alfredo Portilla as Tosca's politically radical lover, Mario Cavaradossi, and the baritone Jeffrey Kneebone as the villainous chief of police, Baron Scarpia. Small flaws aside, this is an evening of compelling musical theater. Tomorrow night at 8, New York State Theater, (212) 496-0600. Tickets: $22 to $95 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMSTERDAM BAROQUE ORCHESTRA AND CHOIR. Lincoln Center, in its Great Performers series, is doing its part, and maybe more, to commemorate the 250th anniversary of Bach's death. Here, some will say, it is going too far, in a reconstruction of Bach's lost ''St. Mark Passion'' by Ton Koopman that fits out a surviving text with music from other Bach works as well as bits newly composed. Mr. Koopman has already recorded the work with these forces for Erato, and, as there, the performance will undoubtedly be persuasive on its own terms. Still, don't believe everything you hear. Sunday at 4 p.m., Church of St. Ignatius Loyola, Park Avenue at 84th Street, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $38 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>BACHMANN-KLIBONOFF-FRIDMAN TRIO. This fine young piano trio is offering a series of programs that explore a great expanse of the repertory and are organized geographically. The current installment looks at Russian music by way of works by Stravinsky, Prokofiev and Mussorgsky. Tonight at 7 (with a preconcert talk at 6:30), Morgan Library, 29 East 36th Street, Manhattan, (212) 685-0008, extension 347. Tickets: $30, $20 for library members (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC. The arrival of spring increases the always considerable attraction of concerts at this floating concert hall on the East River: if the weather is warm, concertgoers can take a glass of wine on the upper deck during intermission. Not that the musical attractions are not sufficient. Tonight and Sunday afternoon the program includes big string works -- the Schubert Trio in B flat, the Mendelssohn Quintet in the same key and Tchaikovsky's lush sextet ''Souvenir de Florence.'' The players are Mark Peskanov and Julie Rosenfeld, violinists; Toby Hoffman and Paul Cortese, violists; and Deliana Momtchilova and Ronald Thomas, cellists. Tomorrow afternoon Mr. Peskanov is playing a recital -- works by Dvorak, Sibelius, Kreisler and Sarasate -- with Doris Stevenson at the piano. Today at 7:30 p.m., tomorrow at 2 p.m. and Sunday at 4 p.m. Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083 or (718) 624-4061. Tickets: $23; $20 for the elderly; $15 for students (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>CONTINUUM. This ensemble presents a portrait of the Puerto Rican composer Roberto Sierra, whose music combines vivid Caribbean rhythms and colors with tricks he learned from new music as a pupil of (and influence on) Gyorgy Ligeti. There are new pieces -- ''Tema y Variaciones'' for clarinet and piano, ''Cancionero Sefardi'' for soprano and instruments -- as well as music tracking the composer back to the mid-80's. Tomorrow night at 8:30, Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330. Tickets: $15, students and the elderly, $7.50 (Griffiths).</p>
        <p>KELLER QUARTET. Formed in the 1980's at the Budapest Academy, one of the finest schools for chamber music, this is an exceptional quartet. The strong program begins with one of the quartets Mozart dedicated to Haydn (K. 387), goes on to Bartok's strangest and loveliest quartet (his second) and ends with Schubert's ''Death and the Maiden,'' a work close to these musicians' hearts and the subject of one of their first, thrilling recordings. Tonight at 8, Weill Recital Hall, (212) 247-7800. Tickets: $36 (Griffiths).</p>
        <p>TON KOOPMAN. Unlike the other pillar of Lincoln Center's Bach commemoration, Andras Schiff, who did one thing -- played Bach suites on the piano -- supremely well, Mr. Koopman is all over the map. But here, simply as organist, he is on firmer ground than in his reconstruction of the ''St. Mark Passion'' with the Amsterdam Baroque, listed above. He offers an interesting mix of Bach works, including several great chorale preludes, on the excellent Mander organ at an Upper East Side church that Lincoln Center's Great Performers series has happily annexed. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Church of St. Ignatius Loyola, Park Avenue at 84th Street, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $30 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK CHAMBER SYMPHONY. Itzhak Perlman is a ubiquitous presence in New York as a violinist. On Sunday he makes what is essentially his New York conducting debut. He has occasionally conducted a work here and there on a particular program when he is performing as a violin soloist, but this time he conducts an entire all-Beethoven program himself. He offers two works: the Triple Concerto, with the Perlman Nikkanen Bailey Trio (that's Navah Perlman) as soloists, and the Seventh Symphony. Tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Sunday at 2 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $35 and $50 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC. Some of Kurt Masur's more memorable achievements as music director of the orchestra have come in the big choral works of Bach. Here, with the American Boychoir and men of the Westminster Symphonic Choir, Mr. Masur arrives at the St. John Passion, a vivid setting from the Gospel of John. Perhaps too vivid in taking up John's accusations against Jews, but the score's best moments remain eloquent and edifying. The veteran Peter Schreier is the Evangelist, and the other vocal soloists include Hakan Hagegard, Heidi Grant Murphy and Marietta Simpson. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Avery Fisher Hall, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $26 to $92 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>SEQUENTIA. The first good news is the mere survival of this superb early-music group, in its first visit to New York since the death of its co-founder Barbara Thornton in 1998. Here it is represented by its male contingent, Sons of Thunder, directed by the other founder, Benjamin Bagby, but the female contingent also remains active. The program, ''Pilgrims to the Apocalypse,'' includes works by Hildegard von Bingen and other music from the 10th through 13th centuries. Tonight at 8, St. Jean Baptiste Church, Lexington Avenue at 76th Street, (212) 570-2130. Tickets: $25 and $30 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>LES BALLETS GRANDIVA. That madcap ballet choreographer Peter Anastos is back, and Victor Trevino, a male ballerina who also choreographs, has got him. The program, which stars ballet luminaries like Suzanne Farewell, Sylvie Gruyere and Lotte Latte, includes spoofs of dance by George Balanchine, William Forsythe and Marius Petipa. Sunday night at 7, Pace Downtown Theater, 3 Spruce Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 346-1715. Tickets: $25; $20 for students, the elderly and dancers (Jennifer Dunning).</p>
        <p>BALLET TECH. Eliot Feld's high-energy ballet troupe bounds through its spring season with a large repertory that includes the premieres of Mr. Feld's ''Coup de Couperin,'' to the Baroque music of Francois Couperin, and ''Nodrog Doggo,'' to a score by Michael Gordon. (Hint: spell the first word of that odd title backward.) Among the many revivals are five works with music by Steve Reich. Damian Woetzel of the New York City Ballet is appearing as guest artist in all performances of Mr. Feld's ''Mending.'' Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at noon and 4 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800. Tickets: Evenings and at 4 p.m. Sunday, $35; tomorrow at 2 p.m. and Sunday at noon, $25 adults, $15 children, (Jack Anderson).</p>
        <p>JEFFREY BAUER. Two years in the making, Jeffrey Bauer's ''Throne Room'' examines the interplay among three people. Tonight through Sunday night at 8, Music Under Construction, 10 East 18th Street; (212) 924-7882. Tickets: $10; $8 students and the elderly; TDF vouchers accepted (Dunning).</p>
        <p>SIGAL BERGMAN. This charming Israeli-born dancer, who seems alive to every moment on the stage, will present ''Circuit,'' a piece that examines a newcomer's perception of postmodern dance in New York City. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Washington Square United Methodist Church, 133 West Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 802-9136. Tickets: $15; $12 for students and low-income audiences (Dunning).</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN ARTS EXCHANGE: FIRST WEEKENDS. This program of performance and discussion features Aaron Landsman's new ''No Place Like Home,'' set in an anonymous office, and Jon Kinzel's new ''Stop Ahead,'' dance with video about Prospect Park. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8; Sunday night at 6, Brooklyn Arts Exchange, 421 Fifth Avenue, at Eighth Street, Park Slope; (718) 832-0018. Tickets: $12; $6 for low-income audiences (Dunning).</p>
        <p>JESUS CANO AND LISA BOTTALICO. Dance soloists and a group of musicians pay tribute to Antonio, one of the greatest Spanish dancers of the 20th century. In addition to traditional Flamenco, the program includes music by Manuel de Falla, whose scores were used by Antonio, and there will be a guest appearance by Eva Lucena, director of the Alborada Spanish Dance Theater. Sunday night at 7, Symphony Space, Broadway at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400. Tickets: $20; $10 for children and students (Anderson).</p>
        <p>COMPANY APPELS. With paintings by Chuck Close as a backdrop, the Company Appels will perform new solos and duets by Jonathon Appels. Tonight at 8, PaceWildenstein Gallery, 142 Greene Street, SoHo, (212) 355-4172. Tickets: $15; $12 for students and the elderly (Dunning).</p>
        <p>TINA CROLL AND JAMES CUNNINGHAM: ''THE HORSE'S MOUTH.'' One of the most heartwarming and revealing recurring dance events is back in town. Tina Croll and James Cunningham are eloquent performers and choreographers who have witnessed several decades of downtown dance history in New York. In their cannily assembled ''Horse's Mouth'' series, that history and more comes radiantly alive through the bodies, minds and memories of those who lived it. This weekend's performers include Grover Dale, Stuart Hodes, Yvonne Rainer, Sara Rudner and Gus Solomons Jr. Today and Sunday at 8:30 p.m.; tomorrow at 3 and 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194. Tickets: $15; TDF vouchers accepted (Dunning).</p>
        <p>EIFMAN BALLET OF ST. PETERSBURG. Boris Eifman, one of Russia's most controversial choreographers, has returned to New York with a repertory reflecting his love of strong dramatic passions. This week's attraction is ''Red Giselle,'' a hallucinatory dance-drama based on the life of Olga Spessivtseva, a Russian ballerina who fled the Soviet Union in 1923 and whose career was eventually cut short by mental illness. Today at 8 p.m.; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2 and 7 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212. Tickets: $30 to $55 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>FLAMENCO EXTRAVAGANZA. The cast may change from performance to performance, depending on which guest artists turn up at this intimate club to sing, dance or play flamenco guitar. But the star of the evening is Carmen La Sala, featured with performers like La Conja, Paco Ortiz and Juan Amaya. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30; ''Scheherazade's Tales,'' an evening of belly dancing, may be seen on Tuesdays at 8:30 p.m. Theater East, 211 East 60th Street, Manhattan, (212) 838-9090. Tickets: $25 for the flamenco program; $15 for ''Scheherazade's Tales'' (Dunning).</p>
        <p>MAIA CLAIRE GARRISON/M'ZAWA DANZ.  The three-part ''Panther Peace'' contrasts human aggressiveness with our desire for peace, and the dance's inspirations range from the political ideas of the Black Panthers to the teachings of the Dalai Lama. Tomorrow night at 8; Sunday afternoon at 5, Playhouse 91, 316 East 91st Street, Yorkville, (212) 415-5553 (tomorrow) and (212) 996-1100 (Sunday). Tickets: $15 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>SCOTT HERON. For ''The Water,'' a fantastic meditation on urban and rural life, areas of the stage become an interactive sound sculpture and a magic forest of wigs and heads. The characters include a Kabuki drag queen, a sobbing clown, a rope walker, a country singer and a tap-dancing little girl. Tonight through Sunday night at 8:30, Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 477-5288. Tickets: $15 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>GABRIELLE LANSNER. A director and choreographer, Gabrielle Lansner approaches dance through drama, telling stories that explore the human heart with humor, poignancy and intelligence. Her ''Crush'' is about infatuation. ''Man Suit(e)'' is about male and female stereotypes, with quotations from ''Extracts from Adam's Diary'' and ''Eve's Diary,'' by Mark Twain. Tonight through Sunday night and Tuesday night at 8; April 16 at 3 p.m. Here, 145 Avenue of the Americas, at Dominick Street, South Village, (212) 647-0202.  Tickets: $15 (tonight through Sunday); $12 (weekdays) (Dunning).</p>
        <p>SARAH MICHELSON AND JULIE ATLAS MUZ. Soaking wet, the downtowners Sarah Michelson and Julie Atlas Muz will ''jump off a ledge,'' the advance publicity says, into the possibly murky waters of demolition, death without rebirth, high-caloric intake and makeovers. Thursday through Saturday nights through April 22 at 8, Dixon Place at Vineyard 26, 309 East 26th Street, Manhattan, (212) 532-1546 Tickets: $12; $8 students and the elderly; TDF vouchers accepted (Dunning).</p>
        <p>NEAR EASTERN DANCE FEST: ANAHID SOFIAN DANCE COMPANY AND HASSAN HAKMOUN. Ethnic dances from Greece, Morocco, Egypt, Turkey, Persia and Armenia. Tonight at 8. Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-6661. Tickets: $30 and $35 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>92ND STREET Y HARKNESS DANCE CENTER: FRIDAYS @ NOON. A free series that offers a look at new dances and works in progress by lesser-known choreographers, this time Andrew Jannetti, Toni Taylor and Melinda Jackson. Today at noon. Buttenweiser Hall, 92nd Street Y, at Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5553 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>TERE O'CONNOR. ''Hi Everybody!,'' a Bessie Award-winning production by Tere O'Connor, once more examines homophobia, cancer, Christianity, medical ethics in song and dance with frequent character changes.  Thursday through Saturday nights through April 22 at 8; Sundays through April 23 at 3 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077. Tickets: $15 this weekend, $20 after; one-third off for students, the elderly and children under 12; TDF vouchers accepted (Dunning).</p>
        <p>PILAR RIOJA. One of the most versatile of Spanish dancers offers solo programs designed to reveal the unusual richness of Spanish dance. The presentations include cheerful works in folk style, passionate flamenco dances, solos to music by Spanish classical composers and a choreographic adaptation of poetry by Federico Garcia Lorca. Tomorrow night at 8, Sunday afternoon at 2, Repertorio Espanol's Gramercy Arts Theater, 138 East 27th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $25 to $40, (212) 889-2850 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>RACHAEL WILDE AND ANDREW MEGGINSON. ''Persistence: Invitation,'' conceived and performed by Rachael Wilde and Andrew Megginson, is the result of a three-year collaboration with eight other choreographers, including Susan Braham, Margarita Guergue, Sondra Loring and Vicky Shick. Tonight at 9, tomorrow night and Sunday night at 8, Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, West Village, (212) 780-2146. Tickets: $12 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>WORKS AND PROGRESS: TWYLA THARP AND AMERICAN BALLET THEATER. Find out all you need to know about Twyla Tharp's new ''Variations on a Theme by Haydn,'' performed here in excerpts by dancers of American Ballet Theater, before you see it during the company's summer season at the Met. Sunday and Tuesday nights at 8, Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3587 Tickets: $15; $10 for students and the elderly; sold out but returns may be available (Dunning).</p>
        <p>WORLD MUSIC INSTITUTE: LAKOTA SIOUX INDIAN DANCE THEATER. This 12-member company from South Dakota will present storytelling, film and traditional and sacred music and dance that celebrate the Lakota culture. Tonight at 8, Symphony Space, Broadway at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400. Tickets: $26 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>YARA ARTS GROUP. The Yara Arts Group, a resident at La MaMa, has collaborated with Siberian theater artists to produce ''Circle,'' an unlikely-sounding mix of Siberian legend and punk. Today and tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 3:30 and 8 p.m. La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710. Tickets: $20; $15 for Sunday performances; TDF vouchers accepted (Dunning).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the New York metropolitan region.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>AMATO OPERA. The homespun but attractive qualities of this company's productions, and the intimacy of its shoe-box theater offer a useful change of perspective for operagoers used to the big houses uptown. The casts here vary: at the very least the singers are eager and enthusiastic; sometimes the singing shows great promise. And Anthony Amato, the company's founder, conducts the performances with an evident love of the music. Puccini's ''Madama Butterfly'' is currently on the boards. Tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 2:30 p.m. the Amato Opera, 319 Bowery at Second Street, East Village, (212) 228-8200. Tickets: $25, $20 for the elderly and children. (Allan Kozinn).</p>
        <p>''IL BARBIERE DI SIVIGLIA.'' The cast changes continue in the Metropolitan Opera's production of Rossini's ''Barbiere di Siviglia.'' The excellent mezzo-soprano Theodora Hanslowe sings Rosina, and the tenor Michael Shade is the poor student she loves who turns out to be, of course, Count Almaviva. The baritone Russell Braun is the clever, indispensable Figaro, so much more than the town barber. And Paul Plishka, a Met veteran who owns the role of Dr. Bartolo, sings it again. Bruno Campanella conducts. Metropolitan Opera House; tonight at 8, (212) 362-2000. Tickets: $26 to $225; sold out but returns may be available (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''LA BOHEME,'' Metropolitan Opera. Yet again, all Paris descends on the Latin Quarter in Act II of Puccini's opera, and viewers will get their fill. Listeners are another matter. In Franco Zeffirelli's extravaganza of a production, from 1981, it is hard for any singer of less than Pavarottian amplitude in both voice and physique even to register, let alone make a vivid impression. Certainly, Leontina Vaduva and Luis Lima, in the lead roles, did not exactly shine on opening night. Oh, well; there is always that wonderful orchestra, mercurially conducted here by Marco Armiliato. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-6000. Tickets: $26 to $225; sold out but returns may be available (James R. Oestreich).</p>
        <p>''CARMEN.'' The New York City Opera's colorful, effective production of Bizet's ''Carmen'' offers the mezzo-soprano Angela Horn in the title role. The hefty-voiced tenor Carl Tanner, who had been singing Mario in the company's updated production of ''Tosca,'' switches to Bizet's Don Jose. The soprano Barbara Shirvis will be Micaela and the baritone Jorge Lagunes will sing Escamillo. New York State Theater, tonight at 8, (212) 496-0600. Tickets: $22 to $95 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''LA CLEMENZA DI TITO.'' Harry Bicket conducts a lively, moving and thrilling New York City Opera performance of Mozart's glorious late score. The cast is led by Lorraine Hunt Lieberson in superb form as Sesto, caught between friendship for -- and loyalty to -- the emperor on the one side and sheer blind love for the scheming Vitellia on the other. Marie Plette, as Vitellia, achieves majesty when she gives up hope of the throne. Mark Thomsen takes over from Kurt Streit in the title role. Sunday at 1:30 p.m., New York Theater, (212) 496-0600. Tickets: $22 to $95 (Paul Griffiths).</p>
        <p>''LUCIA DI LAMMERMOOR.'' Since the Dicapo Opera presents three productions a weekend, the company, understandably, double-casts roles in demanding works. This weekend's production of Donizetti's ''Lucia di Lammermoor,'' at its intimate theater on East 76th Street, is one example. The title role will offer, alternately, the sopranos Oleksandra Hrabova and Indira Mahajan. The tenors Barton Green and Emmanuel di Villarosa share the role of Edgardo; and the baritones Gregory Keil and David Templeton do the same with Enrico. The bass Ding Gao has the role of Raimondo to himself. The production, sung in Italian, is directed by Michael Capasso and conducted by Valery Ryvkin. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and Sunday at 5 p.m., Dicapo Opera Theater, 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-9438 or (212) 759-7653. Tickets: $33 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''THE MOTHER OF US ALL,'' New York City Opera. Although this inscrutable work by Virgil Thomson and Gertrude Stein was written well before Lauren Flanigan was born, it seems to have been written for her. At the opening of this new production, Ms. Flanigan sang the title role of the suffragist Susan B. Anthony with fervor, sensitivity and sheer flowing beauty. Christopher Alden's direction seemed strenuous and earthbound, making more of the circus aspects of Thomson and Stein's conception than of the humane sensibility that lay underneath. In this context, Ms. Flanigan's touching portrayal was even more remarkable. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., New York State Theater, (212) 870-5570. Tickets: $22 to $95 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>''PELLEAS ET MELISANDE.'' Jonathan Miller's somber and affecting version of Debussy's great turn-of-the-century opera has returned to the Met with a marvelous American and English cast. Featured are Dawn Upshaw, Dwayne Croft, Willard White and Robert Lloyd. James Levine conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-2000. Tickets: $26 to $225; sold out but returns may be available (Bernard Holland).</p>
        <p>''TANIKO''/''DER JASAGER.'' The Nohgaku-za of Tokyo perform ''Taniko,'' about a sick boy's decision to sacrifice himself for the good of the group. So quiet, so slow, so stylized, the drama comes across as powerful, immediate and real. The same story, but with all the pathos, intensity, grace, wisdom and humanity taken out, is the basis for ''Der Jasager,'' by Brecht and Weill, which is presented by American performers in the second half. Today at 7:30 p.m., tomorrow at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan (212) 832-1155. Tickets: $55; $50 for members (Griffiths).</p>
        <p>''TOSCA.'' Television viewers recently got a chance to see Mark Lamos's spare, modern production of Puccini's ''Tosca'' for the New York City Opera, set in 1930's Italy, when ''Live From Lincoln Center'' carried it over PBS. For tomorrow night's performance, the soprano Holly Hall takes over the title role. The cast includes the tenor Alfredo Portilla as Tosca's politically radical lover, Mario Cavaradossi, and the baritone Jeffrey Kneebone as the villainous chief of police, Baron Scarpia. Small flaws aside, this is an evening of compelling musical theater. Tomorrow night at 8, New York State Theater, (212) 496-0600. Tickets: $22 to $95 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMSTERDAM BAROQUE ORCHESTRA AND CHOIR. Lincoln Center, in its Great Performers series, is doing its part, and maybe more, to commemorate the 250th anniversary of Bach's death. Here, some will say, it is going too far, in a reconstruction of Bach's lost ''St. Mark Passion'' by Ton Koopman that fits out a surviving text with music from other Bach works as well as bits newly composed. Mr. Koopman has already recorded the work with these forces for Erato, and, as there, the performance will undoubtedly be persuasive on its own terms. Still, don't believe everything you hear. Sunday at 4 p.m., Church of St. Ignatius Loyola, Park Avenue at 84th Street, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $38 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>BACHMANN-KLIBONOFF-FRIDMAN TRIO. This fine young piano trio is offering a series of programs that explore a great expanse of the repertory and are organized geographically. The current installment looks at Russian music by way of works by Stravinsky, Prokofiev and Mussorgsky. Tonight at 7 (with a preconcert talk at 6:30), Morgan Library, 29 East 36th Street, Manhattan, (212) 685-0008, extension 347. Tickets: $30, $20 for library members (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC. The arrival of spring increases the always considerable attraction of concerts at this floating concert hall on the East River: if the weather is warm, concertgoers can take a glass of wine on the upper deck during intermission. Not that the musical attractions are not sufficient. Tonight and Sunday afternoon the program includes big string works -- the Schubert Trio in B flat, the Mendelssohn Quintet in the same key and Tchaikovsky's lush sextet ''Souvenir de Florence.'' The players are Mark Peskanov and Julie Rosenfeld, violinists; Toby Hoffman and Paul Cortese, violists; and Deliana Momtchilova and Ronald Thomas, cellists. Tomorrow afternoon Mr. Peskanov is playing a recital -- works by Dvorak, Sibelius, Kreisler and Sarasate -- with Doris Stevenson at the piano. Today at 7:30 p.m., tomorrow at 2 p.m. and Sunday at 4 p.m. Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083 or (718) 624-4061. Tickets: $23; $20 for the elderly; $15 for students (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>CONTINUUM. This ensemble presents a portrait of the Puerto Rican composer Roberto Sierra, whose music combines vivid Caribbean rhythms and colors with tricks he learned from new music as a pupil of (and influence on) Gyorgy Ligeti. There are new pieces -- ''Tema y Variaciones'' for clarinet and piano, ''Cancionero Sefardi'' for soprano and instruments -- as well as music tracking the composer back to the mid-80's. Tomorrow night at 8:30, Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330. Tickets: $15, students and the elderly, $7.50 (Griffiths).</p>
        <p>KELLER QUARTET. Formed in the 1980's at the Budapest Academy, one of the finest schools for chamber music, this is an exceptional quartet. The strong program begins with one of the quartets Mozart dedicated to Haydn (K. 387), goes on to Bartok's strangest and loveliest quartet (his second) and ends with Schubert's ''Death and the Maiden,'' a work close to these musicians' hearts and the subject of one of their first, thrilling recordings. Tonight at 8, Weill Recital Hall, (212) 247-7800. Tickets: $36 (Griffiths).</p>
        <p>TON KOOPMAN. Unlike the other pillar of Lincoln Center's Bach commemoration, Andras Schiff, who did one thing -- played Bach suites on the piano -- supremely well, Mr. Koopman is all over the map. But here, simply as organist, he is on firmer ground than in his reconstruction of the ''St. Mark Passion'' with the Amsterdam Baroque, listed above. He offers an interesting mix of Bach works, including several great chorale preludes, on the excellent Mander organ at an Upper East Side church that Lincoln Center's Great Performers series has happily annexed. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Church of St. Ignatius Loyola, Park Avenue at 84th Street, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $30 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK CHAMBER SYMPHONY. Itzhak Perlman is a ubiquitous presence in New York as a violinist. On Sunday he makes what is essentially his New York conducting debut. He has occasionally conducted a work here and there on a particular program when he is performing as a violin soloist, but this time he conducts an entire all-Beethoven program himself. He offers two works: the Triple Concerto, with the Perlman Nikkanen Bailey Trio (that's Navah Perlman) as soloists, and the Seventh Symphony. Tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Sunday at 2 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $35 and $50 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC. Some of Kurt Masur's more memorable achievements as music director of the orchestra have come in the big choral works of Bach. Here, with the American Boychoir and men of the Westminster Symphonic Choir, Mr. Masur arrives at the St. John Passion, a vivid setting from the Gospel of John. Perhaps too vivid in taking up John's accusations against Jews, but the score's best moments remain eloquent and edifying. The veteran Peter Schreier is the Evangelist, and the other vocal soloists include Hakan Hagegard, Heidi Grant Murphy and Marietta Simpson. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Avery Fisher Hall, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $26 to $92 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>SEQUENTIA. The first good news is the mere survival of this superb early-music group, in its first visit to New York since the death of its co-founder Barbara Thornton in 1998. Here it is represented by its male contingent, Sons of Thunder, directed by the other founder, Benjamin Bagby, but the female contingent also remains active. The program, ''Pilgrims to the Apocalypse,'' includes works by Hildegard von Bingen and other music from the 10th through 13th centuries. Tonight at 8, St. Jean Baptiste Church, Lexington Avenue at 76th Street, (212) 570-2130. Tickets: $25 and $30 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>LES BALLETS GRANDIVA. That madcap ballet choreographer Peter Anastos is back, and Victor Trevino, a male ballerina who also choreographs, has got him. The program, which stars ballet luminaries like Suzanne Farewell, Sylvie Gruyere and Lotte Latte, includes spoofs of dance by George Balanchine, William Forsythe and Marius Petipa. Sunday night at 7, Pace Downtown Theater, 3 Spruce Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 346-1715. Tickets: $25; $20 for students, the elderly and dancers (Jennifer Dunning).</p>
        <p>BALLET TECH. Eliot Feld's high-energy ballet troupe bounds through its spring season with a large repertory that includes the premieres of Mr. Feld's ''Coup de Couperin,'' to the Baroque music of Francois Couperin, and ''Nodrog Doggo,'' to a score by Michael Gordon. (Hint: spell the first word of that odd title backward.) Among the many revivals are five works with music by Steve Reich. Damian Woetzel of the New York City Ballet is appearing as guest artist in all performances of Mr. Feld's ''Mending.'' Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at noon and 4 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800. Tickets: Evenings and at 4 p.m. Sunday, $35; tomorrow at 2 p.m. and Sunday at noon, $25 adults, $15 children, (Jack Anderson).</p>
        <p>JEFFREY BAUER. Two years in the making, Jeffrey Bauer's ''Throne Room'' examines the interplay among three people. Tonight through Sunday night at 8, Music Under Construction, 10 East 18th Street; (212) 924-7882. Tickets: $10; $8 students and the elderly; TDF vouchers accepted (Dunning).</p>
        <p>SIGAL BERGMAN. This charming Israeli-born dancer, who seems alive to every moment on the stage, will present ''Circuit,'' a piece that examines a newcomer's perception of postmodern dance in New York City. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Washington Square United Methodist Church, 133 West Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 802-9136. Tickets: $15; $12 for students and low-income audiences (Dunning).</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN ARTS EXCHANGE: FIRST WEEKENDS. This program of performance and discussion features Aaron Landsman's new ''No Place Like Home,'' set in an anonymous office, and Jon Kinzel's new ''Stop Ahead,'' dance with video about Prospect Park. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8; Sunday night at 6, Brooklyn Arts Exchange, 421 Fifth Avenue, at Eighth Street, Park Slope; (718) 832-0018. Tickets: $12; $6 for low-income audiences (Dunning).</p>
        <p>JESUS CANO AND LISA BOTTALICO. Dance soloists and a group of musicians pay tribute to Antonio, one of the greatest Spanish dancers of the 20th century. In addition to traditional Flamenco, the program includes music by Manuel de Falla, whose scores were used by Antonio, and there will be a guest appearance by Eva Lucena, director of the Alborada Spanish Dance Theater. Sunday night at 7, Symphony Space, Broadway at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400. Tickets: $20; $10 for children and students (Anderson).</p>
        <p>COMPANY APPELS. With paintings by Chuck Close as a backdrop, the Company Appels will perform new solos and duets by Jonathon Appels. Tonight at 8, PaceWildenstein Gallery, 142 Greene Street, SoHo, (212) 355-4172. Tickets: $15; $12 for students and the elderly (Dunning).</p>
        <p>TINA CROLL AND JAMES CUNNINGHAM: ''THE HORSE'S MOUTH.'' One of the most heartwarming and revealing recurring dance events is back in town. Tina Croll and James Cunningham are eloquent performers and choreographers who have witnessed several decades of downtown dance history in New York. In their cannily assembled ''Horse's Mouth'' series, that history and more comes radiantly alive through the bodies, minds and memories of those who lived it. This weekend's performers include Grover Dale, Stuart Hodes, Yvonne Rainer, Sara Rudner and Gus Solomons Jr. Today and Sunday at 8:30 p.m.; tomorrow at 3 and 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194. Tickets: $15; TDF vouchers accepted (Dunning).</p>
        <p>EIFMAN BALLET OF ST. PETERSBURG. Boris Eifman, one of Russia's most controversial choreographers, has returned to New York with a repertory reflecting his love of strong dramatic passions. This week's attraction is ''Red Giselle,'' a hallucinatory dance-drama based on the life of Olga Spessivtseva, a Russian ballerina who fled the Soviet Union in 1923 and whose career was eventually cut short by mental illness. Today at 8 p.m.; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 2 and 7 p.m., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212. Tickets: $30 to $55 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>FLAMENCO EXTRAVAGANZA. The cast may change from performance to performance, depending on which guest artists turn up at this intimate club to sing, dance or play flamenco guitar. But the star of the evening is Carmen La Sala, featured with performers like La Conja, Paco Ortiz and Juan Amaya. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30; ''Scheherazade's Tales,'' an evening of belly dancing, may be seen on Tuesdays at 8:30 p.m. Theater East, 211 East 60th Street, Manhattan, (212) 838-9090. Tickets: $25 for the flamenco program; $15 for ''Scheherazade's Tales'' (Dunning).</p>
        <p>MAIA CLAIRE GARRISON/M'ZAWA DANZ.  The three-part ''Panther Peace'' contrasts human aggressiveness with our desire for peace, and the dance's inspirations range from the political ideas of the Black Panthers to the teachings of the Dalai Lama. Tomorrow night at 8; Sunday afternoon at 5, Playhouse 91, 316 East 91st Street, Yorkville, (212) 415-5553 (tomorrow) and (212) 996-1100 (Sunday). Tickets: $15 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>SCOTT HERON. For ''The Water,'' a fantastic meditation on urban and rural life, areas of the stage become an interactive sound sculpture and a magic forest of wigs and heads. The characters include a Kabuki drag queen, a sobbing clown, a rope walker, a country singer and a tap-dancing little girl. Tonight through Sunday night at 8:30, Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 477-5288. Tickets: $15 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>GABRIELLE LANSNER. A director and choreographer, Gabrielle Lansner approaches dance through drama, telling stories that explore the human heart with humor, poignancy and intelligence. Her ''Crush'' is about infatuation. ''Man Suit(e)'' is about male and female stereotypes, with quotations from ''Extracts from Adam's Diary'' and ''Eve's Diary,'' by Mark Twain. Tonight through Sunday night and Tuesday night at 8; April 16 at 3 p.m. Here, 145 Avenue of the Americas, at Dominick Street, South Village, (212) 647-0202.  Tickets: $15 (tonight through Sunday); $12 (weekdays) (Dunning).</p>
        <p>SARAH MICHELSON AND JULIE ATLAS MUZ. Soaking wet, the downtowners Sarah Michelson and Julie Atlas Muz will ''jump off a ledge,'' the advance publicity says, into the possibly murky waters of demolition, death without rebirth, high-caloric intake and makeovers. Thursday through Saturday nights through April 22 at 8, Dixon Place at Vineyard 26, 309 East 26th Street, Manhattan, (212) 532-1546 Tickets: $12; $8 students and the elderly; TDF vouchers accepted (Dunning).</p>
        <p>NEAR EASTERN DANCE FEST: ANAHID SOFIAN DANCE COMPANY AND HASSAN HAKMOUN. Ethnic dances from Greece, Morocco, Egypt, Turkey, Persia and Armenia. Tonight at 8. Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-6661. Tickets: $30 and $35 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>92ND STREET Y HARKNESS DANCE CENTER: FRIDAYS @ NOON. A free series that offers a look at new dances and works in progress by lesser-known choreographers, this time Andrew Jannetti, Toni Taylor and Melinda Jackson. Today at noon. Buttenweiser Hall, 92nd Street Y, at Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5553 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>TERE O'CONNOR. ''Hi Everybody!,'' a Bessie Award-winning production by Tere O'Connor, once more examines homophobia, cancer, Christianity, medical ethics in song and dance with frequent character changes.  Thursday through Saturday nights through April 22 at 8; Sundays through April 23 at 3 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077. Tickets: $15 this weekend, $20 after; one-third off for students, the elderly and children under 12; TDF vouchers accepted (Dunning).</p>
        <p>PILAR RIOJA. One of the most versatile of Spanish dancers offers solo programs designed to reveal the unusual richness of Spanish dance. The presentations include cheerful works in folk style, passionate flamenco dances, solos to music by Spanish classical composers and a choreographic adaptation of poetry by Federico Garcia Lorca. Tomorrow night at 8, Sunday afternoon at 2, Repertorio Espanol's Gramercy Arts Theater, 138 East 27th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $25 to $40, (212) 889-2850 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>RACHAEL WILDE AND ANDREW MEGGINSON. ''Persistence: Invitation,'' conceived and performed by Rachael Wilde and Andrew Megginson, is the result of a three-year collaboration with eight other choreographers, including Susan Braham, Margarita Guergue, Sondra Loring and Vicky Shick. Tonight at 9, tomorrow night and Sunday night at 8, Merce Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, West Village, (212) 780-2146. Tickets: $12 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>WORKS AND PROGRESS: TWYLA THARP AND AMERICAN BALLET THEATER. Find out all you need to know about Twyla Tharp's new ''Variations on a Theme by Haydn,'' performed here in excerpts by dancers of American Ballet Theater, before you see it during the company's summer season at the Met. Sunday and Tuesday nights at 8, Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3587 Tickets: $15; $10 for students and the elderly; sold out but returns may be available (Dunning).</p>
        <p>WORLD MUSIC INSTITUTE: LAKOTA SIOUX INDIAN DANCE THEATER. This 12-member company from South Dakota will present storytelling, film and traditional and sacred music and dance that celebrate the Lakota culture. Tonight at 8, Symphony Space, Broadway at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400. Tickets: $26 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>YARA ARTS GROUP. The Yara Arts Group, a resident at La MaMa, has collaborated with Siberian theater artists to produce ''Circle,'' an unlikely-sounding mix of Siberian legend and punk. Today and tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 3:30 and 8 p.m. La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 475-7710. Tickets: $20; $15 for Sunday performances; TDF vouchers accepted (Dunning).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
