<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2D DAY OF VIOLENCE WRACKS VENEZUELA</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="573339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUPS D'ETAT AND ATTEMPTED COUPS D'ETAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VENEZUELA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CARACAS (VENEZUELA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEREZ, CARLOS ANDRES (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela/Caracas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED8113AF93AA15752C1A964958260" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2D DAY OF VIOLENCE WRACKS VENEZUELA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela, Nov. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Breaking a nervous calm that followed the unsuccessful coup attempt on Friday, rebellious Venezuelan policemen hijacked a civilian helicopter here today and raked the presidential palace and surrounding Government buildings with rifle fire.</p>
        <p>The presidential guard returned fire and repulsed the attack. But the clash, in turn, set of a series of sniper attacks from slum high-rises surrounding the palace. No one was reported wounded, and President Carlos Andres Perez worked "at top speed" in the bomb-damaged palace today, an aide said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Breaking a nervous calm that followed the unsuccessful coup attempt on Friday, rebellious Venezuelan policemen hijacked a civilian helicopter here today and raked the presidential palace and surrounding Government buildings with rifle fire.</p>
        <p>The presidential guard returned fire and repulsed the attack. But the clash, in turn, set of a series of sniper attacks from slum high-rises surrounding the palace. No one was reported wounded, and President Carlos Andres Perez worked "at top speed" in the bomb-damaged palace today, an aide said.</p>
        <p>Security forces loyal to President Perez shot down the helicopter, killing four policemen aboard. Officials said the copter raid had been the work of a group of deserters from the Caracas metropolitan police force. An Estimated 100 Deaths</p>
        <p>In the uprising on Friday, the second coup attempt here in 10 months, an estimated 100 civilians and soldiers were killed, figures from city morgues indicated. Hospitals treated dozens of people from gunshot wounds. In the earlier coup attempt, on Feb. 4, about 40 people were killed.</p>
        <p>Most Caracas residents stayed indoors today, listening to news bulletins on radio or television.</p>
        <p>Under military guard, work crews swept up broken glass and started filling craters in city streets around the palace. Rebel air force pilots flying Bronco OV-10 planes, had dropped several bombs in the downtown area on Friday, including one that blew a 60-foot hole in a wall of the presidential palace. At the high point of the bombing, the 70-year-old President reportedly crawled on his hands and knees to an underground palace bunker, from which he rallied loyal units.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perez's pilots shot down three rebel Bronco planes on Friday.</p>
        <p>Tonight, explosions echoed through middle-class residential areas as munitions experts exploded bombs that had failed to go off on Friday after falling on the city's downtown airstrip. Main Airport Reopens</p>
        <p>Caracas's principal airport reopened today to both domestic and international flights. But the expressways that link the region were largely empty.</p>
        <p>There had been scattered outbreaks of looting Friday. But poor neighborhoods remained largely quiet today, and authorities postponed the start of an all-night curfew by four hours, to 10 P.M.</p>
        <p>Military intelligence officers began interrogating the more than 100 officers and soldiers arrested in the failed coup, which in the main involved air force and marine units.</p>
        <p>The Government has identified five officers in the Venezuelan armed forces who are believed to have led the uprising, working with some civilians described by officials as "leftist extremists." Searching for Leftists</p>
        <p>Today, soldiers raided the Central University of Venezuela here, searching for armed leftists.</p>
        <p>A number of top officers signed a statement in which they assumed the "historical responsibility for rising up" against "a regime that is destroying the country." The signers were Rear Adm. Luis Cabrera Aguirre and another rear admiral, Hernan Gruber Odreman; Brig. Gen. Francisco Visconti of the Air Force; Lieut. Col. Alejandro Coleoglu Dore of the National Guard, and Col. Higinio Castro of the Army.</p>
        <p>None of these officers were reported to have been arrested, but Angel Zambrano, the Information Minister, said that 92 soldiers and civilians flew to Peru on Friday night in a Hercules C-130. They are seeking asylum from the Peruvian Government.</p>
        <p>The Government has not yet identified any civilians connected with the leaders of the coup.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perez's administration is unpopular because of charges of corruption and a free-market economic program that critics say has hurt the poor. Water rationing in much of Caracas and cuts in social programs because of declining oil revenue have also angered many people.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
