<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suffolk Shootout Goes Bellport's Way</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="573407"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERSCHOLASTIC ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BELLPORT HIGH SCHOOL (NY)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WEST ISLIP HIGH SCHOOL (NY)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DA103FF93AA15752C1A964958260" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suffolk Shootout Goes Bellport's Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WEST ISLIP, L.I., Nov. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Suffolk County Conference II championship game came down to Long Island high school football's version of a soccer shootout before Bellport defeated West Islip, 12-9, yesterday.</p>
        <p>Bellport will play Garden City for the Long Island ClassII title at Hofstra on Saturday at 5 P.M.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Suffolk County Conference II championship game came down to Long Island high school football's version of a soccer shootout before Bellport defeated West Islip, 12-9, yesterday.</p>
        <p>Bellport will play Garden City for the Long Island ClassII title at Hofstra on Saturday at 5 P.M.</p>
        <p>The county's No. 1-rated defense, West Islip, and No. 2 defense, Bellport, kept each other's offenses out of the end zone and headed for overtime knotted at 3-3.</p>
        <p>Under the New York State Athletic Association's overtime procedure, each team was given a series of four downs from the opponent's 10-yard line to score either a touchdown or a field goal. First Shot, Bellport</p>
        <p>West Islip won the toss and elected to defend. Two plays later, Ron Lawson ran a 6-yard sweep into the end zone to give Bellport a 9-3 edge. The Clippers' coach, Joe Cipp, elected for a 1-point conversion kick rather than a 2-point run or pass, but a bad snap caused Jim McGowan, the quarterback who doubles as the team kicker, to miss the attempt.</p>
        <p>West Islip responded on its second play when Chip Jankow found Dom Pellegrino alone in the end zone. Bellport's chances of a second consecutive conference II title appeared doomed when Skip Thomas, an all-county kicker, entered the game and attempted the potential game-winning extra point. But Thomas's kick was wide.</p>
        <p>The teams went into the second overtime session, and this time Bellport won the toss and elected to give West Islip first crack at scoring. The Lions were held to 1 yard on three plays and attempted a 17-yard field goal, which Thomas missed.</p>
        <p>He had hit a 47-yarder with 8 minutes 30 seconds left in the game to tie the score, but then missed a 43-yard attempt with 9 seconds left in regulation time.</p>
        <p>On the first play of Bellport's ensuing series, Greg McGraw motored 10 yards around the left end into the end zone with what looked to be the game-winning touchdown. But an illegal procedure penalty wiped the play out.</p>
        <p>Cipp disputed the call for nearly 10 minutes. "That was as mad as I've ever been," said the Bellport coach, who chose to run three plays up the middle to set up a 25-yard game-winning field-goal try.</p>
        <p>"I knew we got our touchdown on that series already," he continued. "So I said, 'Let's get the field goal and get out of here.' "</p>
        <p>McGowan put the ball through the center of the uprights to give Bellport the title.</p>
        <p>"I wanted to redeem myself," said McGowan, who completed only 4 of 16 passes for 39 yards. "Of course, I wanted Greg's touchdown to count. But when it didn't, I wanted a chance to kick the ball."</p>
        <p>In another game that went down to the wire, Farmingdale defeated Hempstead, 7-6, in the Nassau County Conference I championship.</p>
        <p>The game was scoreless until the final minute, when Hempstead quarterback Larry Watts threw a 59-yard pass to Courtney Watson that put the Tigers at Farmingdale's 5-yard line. Watts then ran the ball in on the next play to put Hempstead up by 6-0. The extra point was no good.</p>
        <p>Farmingdale responded with a 50-yard pass from tailback Mike Townsend to John Tavolacci to the Hempstead 10. The Farmingdale quarterback, Richard Solberg, then hit Mike Bush for a touchdown with no time left. Anthony Tufano kicked the extra point for a 7-6 victory.</p>
        <p>Farmingdale will play Connetquot at Hofstra next Saturday at 1 P.M. to determine the Long Island Class I title.</p>
        <p>HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
