<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mutual Funds; When the Time Is Right to Sell</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="573285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUTUAL FUNDS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DCA/WIESENBERGER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOULD, CAROLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DD153BF93AA15752C1A964958260" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mutual Funds; When the Time Is Right to Sell</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carole Gould</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOULD, CAROLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BUYING mutual fund shares is simple, partly because the industry is so eager to help. But when it comes to deciding to sell, investors are on their own.</p>
        <p>While people hang on to losing shares for many reasons -- benign neglect, for one -- most fund purchases are not lifelong commitments, investment advisers say. It makes sense to periodically review a portfolio and prune. Some clues: changes in performance, management or asset base.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BUYING mutual fund shares is simple, partly because the industry is so eager to help. But when it comes to deciding to sell, investors are on their own.</p>
        <p>While people hang on to losing shares for many reasons -- benign neglect, for one -- most fund purchases are not lifelong commitments, investment advisers say. It makes sense to periodically review a portfolio and prune. Some clues: changes in performance, management or asset base.</p>
        <p>"People need long-term outlooks, but if you have serious doubts about a fund, there's probably a good alternative," said Kenneth E. Gregory, who edits the L/G No-Load Fund Analyst in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>A fund manager's departure is a red flag. "It doesn't mean you should automatically sell, but you'll have to assess how important the manager really is and who the replacement is," Mr. Gregory said.</p>
        <p>A manager's departure means something different at different funds. Some rely heavily on their managers' quirky stockpicking styles; Janus and New England Growth are two examples. Others -- Twentieth Century and the American funds, for instance -- take a team approach, so losing a manager has less impact. Still others, like Vista Growth and Income Fund or the Valueline Fund, use more defined approaches to stockpicking so the manager has less discretion.</p>
        <p>Then there is the question of evaluating the new manager. In the case of Fidelity Magellan, the nation's largest equity fund, the two who have succeeded Peter Lynch since he departed in 1990 had built excellent track records elsewhere. But in many cases, the new managers are unknown.</p>
        <p>Because most manager shifts are not as widely publicized as the changes at Magellan, experts recommend calling the fund once a year to verify the manager's status.</p>
        <p>A seller must also factor in tax costs.  Investors with huge taxable capital gains might think twice about cashing out. But because funds pay capital gains annually, on which investors then pay taxes even if the money is reinvested, the potential tax bill on selling may not be as big as you think.</p>
        <p>Even so, investors who plan to leave fund shares to heirs, and avoid some capital gains liability, might take that tax break into account, said Nadine Lee, a tax partner with Ernst &amp; Young, in New York.</p>
        <p>Some experts would be wary of a big drop in assets during rising markets; it can indicate poor strategy, poor shareholder services or other problems. And if a fund no longer conforms to investment guidelines -- a small-cap value fund starts buying earnings-oriented stocks -- "that's a clear sell signal," said Don Phillips, vice president of Morningstar Inc., fund researchers in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Most of these changes show up in a fund's performance. But evaluating performance itself can be tricky.</p>
        <p>When some funds lag, it may be related to a reasonable strategy. For instance, the hallmark of some stock funds, like the Phoenix Growth Fund, is a defensive approach. While they might underperform in strong rallies, they maintain superior returns by limiting their losses when the market sours.</p>
        <p>Most important is to compare a fund's performance with that of its peers. Because the market rewards various stockpicking styles at different times, the proper benchmark is critical. A fund that buys small stocks using a value approach, like Nicholas Limited Edition, should be compared with similar funds, like Pennsylvania Mutual. If realistic competitors are performing better, "that's a reason to get out," Mr. Phillips said.</p>
        <p>But experts caution against weighing quarterly, monthly or annual performance too heavily. Mutual funds are based on long-term investing, and even great stockpickers have bad years. Mr. Gregory looks for trends.  "Two years of underperformance would be a concern." he said. After three disappointing years, "I'd look for alternatives."</p>
        <p>One reason to dump a fund is that you originally misunderstood it. For example, many shareholders of short-term global income funds found they could not handle the risks during Europe's currency crisis in September.</p>
        <p>Radical increases in fund size, especially of small stock funds that grow rapidly after being discovered by investors, should also raise a red flag. A small fund that owns 30 stocks is very different from a fund that is five times larger in assets and owns 200 stocks. The Janus Venture Fund, for instance, closed when assets reached $1.2 billion; now it manages $1.6 billion. While its performance hasn't suffered, "it's worth watching," Mr. Gregory said.</p>
        <p>Then there are changes in your own financial situation. As you grow older, for example, it may be wise to begin trimming risks by replacing some aggressive growth funds with, say, equity-income funds.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, "if you picked a fund because you like the ability of its manager and its style, stick with it," said Mr. Phillips, who still owns shares in the Templeton Growth Fund, which he bought more than 15 years ago. Assuming your original research is still valid, he suggests, rebalance your portfolio occasionally by selling some shares that have performed strongly and replacing them with shares of a fund that has done less well. TWO STRATEGIES PUT TO THE TEST</p>
        <p>WHO would add more value to a fund: a money manager who excels at market timing, or one who can identify the best industry sectors?</p>
        <p>The industry selector wins hand down, says a recent study by CDA/Wiesenberger, mutual fund researchers in Rockville, Md.  The study, which compared the performance of two theoretical money managers, assumes the market-timer correctly called every market swing of at least 10 percent, while the industry selector chose the winning sector each year among energy, financial services, gold, health care, technology and utilities.</p>
        <p>The market-timer parlayed $1,000 into $14,650. The industry selector's $1,000 grew to $62,640. A buy-and-hold S.&amp; P. 500 investment would have grown to only $6,030. The study shows that industry selection is more important than market timing, which most investors can't do anyway, said Steve Savage, managing editor for CDA/Wiesenberger.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
