<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amaker Gets His Wish With Revival of Series</title>
    <meta content="19MENS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1063443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL: MEN'S COLLEGE ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seton Hall University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Drexel University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3D91430F93AA25752C1A96E958260" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amaker Gets His Wish With Revival of Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seton Hall defeats Drexel, 83-70, in college basketball; other results noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SETON HALL 83, DREXEL 70</p>
        <p>Tommy Amaker did not put Drexel on Seton Hall's schedule for the first time in 60 years in order to put his Pirates through a highly contested gut-check of a basketball game. The Seton Hall coach rekindled the series with the Dragons because he knew that after a tough season-opening weekend in Indiana, his Pirates would need to build their confidence and enhance their record. And with superior size and athleticism, they did just that last night before a crowd of 6,073 at Continental Arena in East Rutherford, N.J.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SETON HALL 83, DREXEL 70</p>
        <p>Tommy Amaker did not put Drexel on Seton Hall's schedule for the first time in 60 years in order to put his Pirates through a highly contested gut-check of a basketball game. The Seton Hall coach rekindled the series with the Dragons because he knew that after a tough season-opening weekend in Indiana, his Pirates would need to build their confidence and enhance their record. And with superior size and athleticism, they did just that last night before a crowd of 6,073 at Continental Arena in East Rutherford, N.J.</p>
        <p>Behind a balanced offensive attack that yielded four players who scored at least 12 points, the Pirates ran to a solid, if not spectacular, 83-70 victory over Drexel. The all Big-East point guard Shaheen Holloway had 18 points and 10 assists as Seton Hall won its second straight contest to even its mark at 2-2.</p>
        <p>While Holloway controlled the perimeter, forward Duane Jordan used his bulk to dominate inside, scoring 17 points and grabbing 8 rebounds. Guard Rimas Kaukenas returned from a sprained ligament in his left knee to score 14 points and grab 9 rebounds, and Gary Saunders, who entered the game averaging 20 points, scored 12.</p>
        <p>The Pirates received a gift when Drexel's all-league center, Joe Linderman, was forced to sit out this season opener for the Dragons because of bronchitis. A 6-foot-9-inch junior, Linderman averaged team highs of 18.4 points and 8.5 rebounds in earning all-America East Conference honors last season. Without him at least creating a presence in the middle, the Pirates attacked the basket without fear, and the freshman center Charles Manga enjoyed his most productive outing of the season.</p>
        <p>They say he's a great inside player, Jordan said of Linderman. Drexel played hard to try and make up for him. But it had to hurt.</p>
        <p>At 6-10, Manga had at least three inches on every Drexel player and, to the delight of Amaker, his play showed it. Looking nothing like the youngster who was foul-prone and tentative in Indiana, Manga grabbed eight of his season-best nine rebounds before halftime. Manga also recorded 8 points, six more than in any of his first three games.</p>
        <p>Kaukenas entered the game at 15 minutes 3 seconds of the first half, and within minutes, he provided one of the game's highlights by driving toward the foul line and delivering an impressive bounce pass to Manga between two defenders. Manga converted the layup, giving the Pirates a 28-15 lead that never dipped below 9 points.</p>
        <p>You can see the impact that Kaukenas has for our team, Amaker said. He brings great energy and effort.</p>
        <p>CHRIS BROUSSARD</p>
        <p>UTAH STATE 62, UTAH 54</p>
        <p>Rick Majerus had said his No. 9 Runnin' Utes were inexperienced, unpolished and unworthy of their ranking. Turns out he was right.</p>
        <p>Donnie Johnson scored 18 points and Troy Rolle had 11 as Utah State shocked Utah last night in Logan, Utah. The Utes held a 49-45 lead with 4 minutes 25 seconds to play, but the Aggies ran away with the game by scoring on their last eight possessions. (AP)</p>
        <p>NORTH CAROLINA 65, GEORGIA 58</p>
        <p>Kris Lang scored 21 points, Ademola Okulaja added 14 and each took turns shutting down Georgia's Jumaine Jones as No. 10 North Carolina beat the Bulldogsin the second round of the Preseason N.I.T. at Chapel Hill N.C.</p>
        <p>The Tar Heels (3-0), who blew a 13-point second-half lead before rallying for the win, now head to New York to play Purdue in the semifinals next week. (AP)</p>
        <p>L.S.U.</p>
        <p>Louisiana State University will be barred from 1999 post-season tournaments and lose six scholarships in the next three years because a booster paid Lester Earl $5,000 to play basketball there, the National Collegiate Athletic Association announced yesterday.</p>
        <p>Earl had accused Johnny Jones, a former L.S.U. assistant, of paying him to attend the school, but the N.C.A.A. investigation cleared both Jones and the retired head coach Dale Brown, who was in charge of the program during Earl's brief stay with the Tigers. (AP)</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL: MEN'S COLLEGE ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
