<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rape Accusation Reinforces Fears In a Divided Iraq</title>
    <meta content="21iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/21/world/middleeast/21iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1827733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santora, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maliki, Nuri Kamal Al- (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4D9123EF932A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1416" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rape Accusation Reinforces Fears In a Divided Iraq</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rape Accusation Reinforces Fears in a Divided Iraq</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA; Damien Cave and Iraqi employees of The New York Times contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santora, Marc</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Feb. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Twenty-year-old Iraqi Sunni woman from Baghdad appears on television with horrific account of kidnapping and rape by three officers in Shiite-dominated National Police, stunning country in which such crimes are never discussed; Shiite leaders line up to call charge propaganda; bitter exchanges on television are interspersed with clips of veiled, tearful woman telling story; she says Americans rescued her and gave her medical treatment; Prime Min Nuri al-Maliki first promises investigation but, in second statement only hours later, calls woman liar and criminal who was not attacked and orders rewards for officers involved; Sunni denounce sectarian reaction; woman was kidnapped while husband was out, which is not disputed; she describes being raped at garrison and says attack was videotaped; nurse who says she treated woman at local Sunni clinic reports signs of sexual and physical assault; unrelenting violence in Baghdad kills at least 17 people; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most wicked acts are spoken of openly and without reserve in Iraq. Torture, stabbings and bodies ripped to pieces in bombings are all part of the daily conversation.</p>
        <p>Rape is different.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most wicked acts are spoken of openly and without reserve in Iraq. Rape is different.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most wicked acts are spoken of openly and without reserve in Iraq. Torture, stabbings and bodies ripped to pieces in bombings are all part of the daily conversation.</p>
        <p>Rape is different.</p>
        <p>Rape is not mentioned by the victims, and rarely by the authorities. And when it is discussed publicly, as in several high-profile cases involving American soldiers and Iraqi women, it is usually left to the relatives of the victim to give the explicit details.</p>
        <p>So when a 20-year-old Sunni woman from Baghdad appeared on the satellite television station Al Jazeera on Monday night with a horrific account of kidnapping and sexual assault at the hands of three officers in the Shiite-dominated Iraqi National Police, people across the country were stunned, some disbelieving, others horrified, but all riveted.</p>
        <p>Almost immediately, Shiite leaders lined up to condemn the woman, calling her charges propaganda aimed at undermining the new security campaign. Sunni politicians offered the woman their support. Whatever the truth of the accusation, though, it played to sectarian fears on both sides.</p>
        <p>For many Shiites, the charges appeared to be an attempt to smear them and attack the Shiite-led government; for Sunnis, the woman's account only highlighted what they already believed to be true -- that the Iraqi government cares little for justice and promotes a Shiite agenda.</p>
        <p>Bitter exchanges between politicians of various sects were relayed to millions on television, interspersed with clips of the woman telling her story, her face veiled, just the tears in her eyes visible.</p>
        <p>The Americans, who have advisers working with the Iraqi National Police, found themselves caught in the middle without answers. The woman said the Americans had rescued her from the officers and gave her medical treatment. The American-backed, Shiite-led government said the Americans would show the woman's claims to be false.</p>
        <p>The American military said only that it was investigating the charges.</p>
        <p>That was also the first response of Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki, who issued a statement soon after the woman appeared on television on Monday, promising a full investigation and the most severe punishment for anyone involved.</p>
        <p>Only hours later, however, Mr. Maliki reversed himself. His office released a second statement after midnight, that one calling the woman a liar and a wanted criminal and going on to praise the officers involved.</p>
        <p>''It has been shown after medical examinations that the woman had not been subjected to any sexual attack whatsoever, and that there are three outstanding arrest warrants against her issued by security agencies,'' said the second statement. ''After the allegations have been proven to be false, the prime minister has ordered that the officers accused be rewarded.''</p>
        <p>The government did not elaborate on the statement or say why the prime minister had so quickly reversed himself. His office only said that ''known parties'' had been responsible for the allegations.</p>
        <p>But in siding with the security forces, Mr. Maliki threatened to only heighten the tensions surrounding the already highly charged case. His government also released the woman's name, which is not being published by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Sunni politicians rushed to her defense, accusing the government of revealing its true sectarian bias.</p>
        <p>The case ''should not be dealt with on a sectarian basis,'' said Saleem Abdullah, a spokesman for the Tawafiq bloc of Sunni parties, which helped the woman come forward. ''She is a sister for all Iraqis.''</p>
        <p>He went on to say the government's handling of the issue could undermine its credibility in directing the security crackdown.</p>
        <p>With fears of violence pervasive throughout the country, many Iraqis stay inside their homes whenever they can. Satellite television is their connection to the outside world and, just as often, their own country. On the two most prominent channels, Al Jazeera and Al Arabiya, they would have heard the woman telling her story over and over.</p>
        <p>If she made up the story, it was an elaborate piece of propaganda and the contradictory statements by the Iraqi government only added to its power.</p>
        <p>The woman was lying on a bed as she was interviewed, a blue blanket pulled up nearly to her chin. She had a light pink scarf covering her hair and a black scarf covering her face.</p>
        <p>She said she was taken from her house on Sunday morning by the National Police while her husband was out, something no one disputes. The officers, she said, were looking for weapons but when they arrived at the police garrison, they accused her of cooking for Sunni insurgents.</p>
        <p>It was at the garrison that she says the first officer raped her, covering her mouth to muffle her screams. Others were in the room at the time.</p>
        <p>''I begged one of them to get me out,'' she said. ''He said, 'No, no. I will after you give me one thing.' '' She asked what that was, and he told her he wanted to ''get close to me.'' She said she was led into a small room with a bed and a machine gun against the wall. Another officer came in and told the first man to leave. ''Leave her to me,'' the man said, according to her account.</p>
        <p>''I swear on the Koran and the Prophet Muhammad, I am not that kind of woman,'' she said she told the officer. He repeated her words scornfully and beat her with a black water hose, she said.</p>
        <p>''If we want something, we will take; and things we don't want, we will kill,'' the woman said she was told.</p>
        <p>She said that the attack was videotaped and that she was told she would be killed if she told anyone about it.</p>
        <p>A nurse who said she treated the woman after the attack said that she saw signs of sexual and physical assault. The woman, according to the nurse, could identify one of her attackers because he was not wearing a mask, as were the others, and could identify a second attacker by a mark on his genitals.</p>
        <p>The nurse would speak only on the condition of anonymity because she feared that Shiite militiamen would kill her for speaking out. The nurse said she was also wanted by the authorities, who believed the clinic she works at was used by insurgents.</p>
        <p>She said the clinic was simply for Sunnis in the Amil neighborhood who were too afraid to the visit the Shiite-run hospital.</p>
        <p>In Amil, which has been almost totally cleared of Sunnis, people were outraged, but not surprised. The woman's charges seemed to confirm their worst fears that the security forces were little better than militias in uniform.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the American military here in Baghdad, Lt. Col. Josslyn Aberle, confirmed that the woman had been detained by the Iraqi National Police on Sunday morning, but said that everything that happened after that was under investigation.</p>
        <p>But a senior Iraqi official, speaking only on the condition of anonymity because he did not want to be seen as critical of the Americans, said that he had alerted the American ambassador to Iraq, Zalmay Khalilzad, on the day the woman made her allegations, cautioning him that if the case was not handled delicately, it could further inflame sectarian passions.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Khalilzad could not be reached.</p>
        <p>The sectarian tensions further complicated an already delicate topic in Iraqi society.</p>
        <p>The most high-profile rape cases since the American invasion four years ago have involved charges against American soldiers. And even in those cases, it was left to the relatives to speak publicly. Iraqis said they could not remember the case of a rape victim going on television.</p>
        <p>Sabah Salem, a professor at the Baghdad University College of Law, said that while men were occasionally charged with rape in Iraq and punished, many cases went unreported.</p>
        <p>''Rape cases in Iraq are viewed as a shameful thing to any woman regardless of the fact that she is the victim,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>The charges and countercharges occurred on yet another day of unrelenting violence in the capital, as two car bombs and a suicide bomber, in separate attacks, killed at least 17 people. One of the car bombs exploded in a neighborhood that was visited earlier in the day by Mr. Maliki, on a rare foray outside of the Green Zone.</p>
        <p>North of Baghdad, a truck carrying chlorine exploded, killing nine people, The Associated Press reported. More than 150 others were made violently ill by the toxic fumes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
