<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; Lessons Of Disaster</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="775498"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA (YUGOSLAVIA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service"></org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MLADIC, RATKO (GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KARADZIC, RADOVAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DF1138F934A25754C0A963958260" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; Lessons Of Disaster</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two days after the fall of Srebrenica, Gen. Philippe Morillon, a member of the French General Staff, said: "We have to declare war on General Mladic or get out." Ratko Mladic is the commander of Bosnian Serb forces, the architect of the assault on Srebrenica and the ethnic cleansing that followed.</p>
        <p>General Morillon's words pithily summed up one lesson of Bosnia for the Western alliance: To intervene in a conflict and pretend there is no difference between the aggressors and the victims is not only dishonorable but ineffectual.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two days after the fall of Srebrenica, Gen. Philippe Morillon, a member of the French General Staff, said: "We have to declare war on General Mladic or get out." Ratko Mladic is the commander of Bosnian Serb forces, the architect of the assault on Srebrenica and the ethnic cleansing that followed.</p>
        <p>General Morillon's words pithily summed up one lesson of Bosnia for the Western alliance: To intervene in a conflict and pretend there is no difference between the aggressors and the victims is not only dishonorable but ineffectual.</p>
        <p>For three years now Britain, France and the United States -- acting through the United Nations -- have been doing just that: pretending. The U.N. Protection Force proclaimed its neutrality between the Serbs and their Bosnian victims even while it said it was protecting "safe areas" from Serbian attack.</p>
        <p>To carry on the pretense, various Unprofor officers and U.N. officials closed their eyes to horrifying brutalities carried out by General Mladic's forces. The justification was that General Mladic and the political leader of the Bosnian Serbs, Radovan Karadzic, would then be nice and let relief convoys through. They often did promise to do so, but they seldom kept the promises.</p>
        <p>The Western officers and envoys who dealt with the Bosnian Serb leaders believed, or at any rate acted on the premise, that they were ultimately rational men open to bargaining. But in fact they are fanatics, committed to killing and raping and torturing other human beings because they are of a different religion.</p>
        <p>Only one thing moves Dr. Karadzic and General Mladic: the credible threat of force. When they thought Unprofor might call in meaningful air strikes, they stopped sniping at children in Sarajevo. Now, with Unprofor's credibility gone, they have tightened the noose on the capital.</p>
        <p>You can't do business with Hitler. So the world learned when Neville Chamberlain boasted that cringing to Adolf Hitler at Munich in 1938 had brought "peace in our time." To Hitler, diplomacy was just an interlude on the way to military victory.</p>
        <p>Similarly in Bosnia, the United States and the West Europeans came up with a proposal to settle the conflict by giving the Serbs 49 percent of the country. An international Contact Group pressed the idea. But the Serbs already had 70 percent, and they thought they could keep at least that by force of arms -- that and perhaps Sarajevo, too.</p>
        <p>Those are some of the illusions that have led the West to humiliation in Bosnia. Or perhaps it would be better to say self-deceptions. No one of ordinary intelligence could have looked at what was happening and believed the premises on which Western capitals and Unprofor were operating.</p>
        <p>In the last week General Mladic and Dr. Karadzic have made their policy, and their character, clearer than ever. When decent behavior at Srebrenica might actually have helped them politically, they turned their men loose to rape and kill. But even then British officials said Unprofor should stick with its position of neutrality.</p>
        <p>The Western failure in Bosnia traces back to the original decision, made by President Bush in 1991, not to resist Serbian aggression in the former Yugoslavia. With Margaret Thatcher gone from Downing Street, the British and others were happy to agree. So that they would not look altogether indifferent to the horror, the allies came up with the idea of neutral humanitarian relief.</p>
        <p>More than a year ago Alain Juppe said at a Washington dinner that the humanitarian policy had not worked, that it would have been better for the West to have acted resolutely against Serbian aggression from the start. Mr. Juppe was France's Foreign Minister then; now he is Prime Minister in the new Government of President Jacques Chirac.</p>
        <p>President Chirac is the only Western leader not tainted by the past failures of courage and wisdom in Bosnia. So he commanded attention when he warned on Bastille Day that the Western democracies were behaving there as Chamberlain and Edouard Daladier of France did at Munich.</p>
        <p>The choice, as General Morillon said, is for the West to fight the aggressors in Bosnia or pull Unprofor out. The West has the means to act effectively, if it stops pretending. NATO's overwhelming air power, for one, has scarcely been used; General Mladic's headquarters is a safe area. It is a question of will.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
