<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Upheaval in the East;   Karl-Marx-Stadt Swings to the Right</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="338849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAST GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KARL-MARX-STADT (EAST GER)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAMM, HENRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DA1E3DF93AA15750C0A966958260" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Upheaval in the East;   Karl-Marx-Stadt Swings to the Right</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY KAMM, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAMM, HENRY</byline>
      <dateline>KARL-MARX-STADT, East Germany, March 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A bronze head of Marx, about as tall as four men, broods from a massive stone pedestal in front of the nine-story headquarters of the old Communist Party. Behind the towering monument, a wide swath of the building is covered by a bronze plaque on which is repeated many times, in four languages and huge letters, the message, ''Workers of the World, Unite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A bronze head of Marx, about as tall as four men, broods from a massive stone pedestal in front of the nine-story headquarters of the old Communist Party. Behind the towering monument, a wide swath of the building is covered by a bronze plaque on which is repeated many times, in four languages and huge letters, the message, ''Workers of the World, Unite.</p>
        <p>A bronze head of Marx, about as tall as four men, broods from a massive stone pedestal in front of the nine-story headquarters of the old Communist Party. Behind the towering monument, a wide swath of the building is covered by a bronze plaque on which is repeated many times, in four languages and huge letters, the message, ''Workers of the World, Unite.''</p>
        <p>On March 18, the workers of this heavily industrialized district of Saxony did not unite, but they voted overwhelmingly against the party that in 1953 gave their city, Chemnitz, the name of Marx, and in favor of forces that are pledged to dismantle the system that bears his name.</p>
        <p>Karl-Marx-Stadt was known before the Nazis came to power as ''Red Chemnitz'' for the local strength of parties of the left. But in the March 18 voting, the most strongly anti-Communist party, the German Social Union, received 14.8 percent of the vote here, its best showing in any of the country's 15 election districts and far above its national average of 6.3 percent. The conservative Christian Democrats received 44.9 percent in Karl-Marx-Stadt, also above their national share of 40.9 percent.</p>
        <p>The Party for Democratic Socialism, the Communists' successors, received 11.2 percent of the vote here, well below its national total of 16.3 percent; and the leftist Social Democrats managed only 15.6 percent, compared with 21.8 percent nationwide. #30 or 40 Communist Officials ''We're glad to have survived,'' said Michael Drechsler, a spokesman for the Party for Democratic Socialism. ''We did better than expected. The elections have given us democratic legitimacy. I think we'll have to get used to being in opposition. It, too, has its place.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Drechsler, who until a few weeks ago taught at the party's ideological school, now dissolved, was interviewed in his oversized office, containing a conference table around which a pretty big party cell could be seated. The party has retained only the seventh and eighth floors of the vast, nine-story modern building that it had built for itself alone and decorated with the imposing monument in front.</p>
        <p>Where there used to be hundreds of Communist officials and employees, who ran in all but name everything in this district, including this city of 310,000, Mr. Drechsler said there were now only 30 or 40, rattling about the two floors. The lower floors will be occupied by municipal offices.</p>
        <p>On the ninth floor, many of the opposition parties and citizens' movements that sprang up last autumn to unseat the Communists, have set up their offices. Mr. Drechsler said he found the new variety in the once-monotone headquarters pleasing.</p>
        <p>Lost Chance to Change Society</p>
        <p>In the Social Democrats' office, Maike Bellmann, the party spokeswoman, said that clearly not enough people in Chemnitz, as almost everybody calls it again, wanted to unite with the left, and even less to be proletarian. ''The proletarians want to be citizens now,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The saddest thing about the result for herself and her friends of her generation, the 18-year-old spokeswoman said, is that with the sweeping victory of the conservative parties, who received dominant support from their sister parties in West Germany, the views of East Germans will not matter in the coming united Germany.</p>
        <p>''We have lost the chance to change our society as we wanted to,'' she said. ''We didn't go into the street to demonstrate to let Helmut Kohl change our country. We didn't want another group to force its policy down our throats. We've had enough of that.'' Surprisingly, a successful Christian Democratic candidate, interviewed at the party's headquarters in a suburban villa, sadly shared the Social Democratic spokeswoman's opinion that the West German Chancellor and the many others who spoke for the coalition of conservative parties and virtually ran their campaign played too dominant and too tactless a role.</p>
        <p>Hope for Control of Local Vote</p>
        <p>''Wild things happened here,'' he said of the comportment of West German party campaigners, accusing them of running more a preview of West Germany's parliamentary elections in December than taking into consideration the wishes of local voters and parties. Asking not to be identified, he expressed concern that trouble might break out if the promises of quick improvements in the standard of living that the West German politicians made are not soon redeemed.</p>
        <p>Juliane Weiss, head of the local office of Die Union, the Christian Democratic daily for Saxony, said that West German Christian Democrats even reserved for themselves the choice of where in this city Mr. Kohl made his campaign speech. He drew a crowd estimated at 200,000.</p>
        <p>Christian Democratic leaders here hope that they will be more fully in control of the important local elections May 6, in which all opposition parties hope to remove the Communist officials who remain in most city halls and village councils, including here.</p>
        <p>Opinions are divided on what to do with the monument, the work of Lev Kerbel, a Soviet sculptor, which was dedicated in 1971. ''It is not in dispute,'' said Deputy Mayor Hartmut Lange. Others dispute it strongly, including citizens' groups that have requested its removal. Miss Bellmann said dissidents close to the Protestant Church, which gave its protection to opposition groups when they still needed it, want the head melted down to be founded into church bells.</p>
        <p>Rumors circulate that Trier, the West German town where Marx was born, has offered to buy the monument. Others say that such an offer has been received from Japan.</p>
        <p>A Communist group has filed a petition with hundreds of signatures saying that to remove the monument would be the equivalent of the Nazis' burning of books. ''Culture should not be destroyed,'' the petition said.</p>
        <p>Many said they would like to preserve the statue as a memorial to the demonstrations that overthrew the Communists.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
