<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Transactions</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="597549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DF1138F930A15750C0A965958260" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Transactions</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball  American League</p>
        <p>BOSTON RED SOX -- Sent Jeff McNeely, outfielder, and Derek Livernois, pitcher, to their minor-league camp for reassignment.</p>
        <p>CHICAGO WHITE SOX -- Optioned Jeff Schwarz, pitcher, and Esteban Beltre and Chris Cron, infielders, to Nashville of the American Association; Johnny Ruffin, pitcher, and Brandon Wilson, infielder, to Birmingham of the Southern League, and Robert Ellis, pitcher, to Sarasota of the Florida State League. Sent Scott Ruffcorn and Chris Howard, pitchers; Clemente Alvarez, catcher; Drew Denson, infielder, and Brad Komminsk, outfielder, to their minor-league camp for reassignment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Baseball  American League</p>
        <p>BOSTON RED SOX -- Sent Jeff McNeely, outfielder, and Derek Livernois, pitcher, to their minor-league camp for reassignment.</p>
        <p>CHICAGO WHITE SOX -- Optioned Jeff Schwarz, pitcher, and Esteban Beltre and Chris Cron, infielders, to Nashville of the American Association; Johnny Ruffin, pitcher, and Brandon Wilson, infielder, to Birmingham of the Southern League, and Robert Ellis, pitcher, to Sarasota of the Florida State League. Sent Scott Ruffcorn and Chris Howard, pitchers; Clemente Alvarez, catcher; Drew Denson, infielder, and Brad Komminsk, outfielder, to their minor-league camp for reassignment.</p>
        <p>KANSAS CITY ROYALS -- Optioned Mike Magnante, pitcher; Terry Shumpert, second baseman; and Bob Hamelin, first baseman, to Omaha of the American Association.</p>
        <p>MINNESOTA TWINS -- Optioned Rich Garges and George Tsamis, pitchers, to Portland of the Pacific Coast League. Sent Damian Miller, catcher, to their minor-league camp for reassignment.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK YANKEES -- Optioned Sterling Hitchcock, pitcher, to Columbus of the International League. Sent Kiki Hernandez, catcher, to their minor-league camp for reassignment.</p>
        <p>SEATTLE MARINERS -- Sent Reggie Harris, pitcher, outright to Calgary of the Pacific Coast League.</p>
        <p>TEXAS RANGERS -- Signed Mike Schooler, pitcher, to a minor-league contract with Oklahoma City of the American Association. National League</p>
        <p>COLORADO ROCKIES -- Assigned Brett Merriman, Mo Sanford, Dana Ridenour and Scott Fredrickson, pitchers, and J. Owens, catcher, to Colorado Springs of the Pacific Coast League.</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES DODGERS -- Optioned Mike Busch and Eddie Pye, infielders, and Billy Ashley, outfielder, to Albuquerque of the Pacific Coast League. Released Lance McCullers and Wally Ritchie, pitchers.</p>
        <p>SAN DIEGO PADRES -- Optioned Scott Sanders and Tim Worrell, pitchers; D.J. Dozier, outfielder; and Luis Lopez, infielder, to Las Vegas of the Pacific Coast League. Sent Joe Strong and Ray Young, pitchers; Bob Geren, catcher; and Jarvis Brown, outfielder, to their minor-league camp for reassignment.</p>
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS -- Sent Craig Colbert, catcher; Steve Hosey, outfielder; J.R. Phillips and Andres Santana, infielders, to their minor-league camp for reassignment. Football  National Football League</p>
        <p>CHICAGO BEARS -- Agreed to terms with Jim Harbaugh, quarterback, on a four-year contract.</p>
        <p>NEW ENGLAND PATRIOTS -- Signed Scott Secules, quarterback.</p>
        <p>PHOENIX CARDINALS -- Signed Gary Clark, wide receiver, to a three-year contract.</p>
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS -- Signed Derek Loville, running back, and Anthony Moss, linebacker. Canadian Football League</p>
        <p>HAMILTON TIGER-CATS -- Signed Ken Evraire, slot back. Hockey  National Hockey League</p>
        <p>BUFFALO SABRES -- Traded Mike Ramsey, defenseman, to the Pittsburgh Penguins for Bob Errey, left wing.</p>
        <p>EDMONTON OILERS -- Traded Craig Muni, defenseman, to the Chicago Blackhawks for Mike Hudson, center.</p>
        <p>HARTFORD WHALERS -- Traded Steve Konroyd, defenseman, to the Detroit Red Wings for a 1993 sixth-round draft choice.</p>
        <p>MINNESOTA NORTH STARS -- Sent James Black, center, to Kalamazoo of the International League.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK RANGERS -- Acquired John McIntyre, center, from the Los Angeles Kings for Mark Hardy, defenseman, and a 1993 fifth-round draft choice. Traded Randy Gilhen, center, to the Tampa Bay Lightning for Mike Hartman, left wing.</p>
        <p>TAMPA BAY LIGHTNING -- Traded Peter Taglianetti, defenseman, to the Pittsburgh Penguins for a 1993 third-round draft pick.</p>
        <p>VANCOUVER CANUCKS -- Traded Robert Kron, left wing; a 1993 third round draft pick and future considerations to the Hartford Whalers for Murray Craven, forward, and a 1993 fifth-round draft pick. Acquired Dan Ratushny, defenseman, from the Winnipeg Jets for a 1993 ninth-round draft pick.</p>
        <p>WINNIPEG JETS -- Traded Rick Tabaracci, goalie, to the Washington Capitals for Jim Hrivnak, goalie, and future considerations. College</p>
        <p>CUMBERLAND, TENN. -- Named Mike Petrone men's basketball coach.</p>
        <p>MIAMI -- Named Rick Mello associate athletic director for external affairs.</p>
        <p>MICHIGAN -- Announced it will drop men's gymnastics as a varsity sport after the 1993-94 season and add women's soccer in the fall of 1994.</p>
        <p>NEVADA -- Named Pat Foster men's basketball coach.</p>
        <p>NORTH CAROLINA-WILMINGTON -- Announced the resignation of Sherri Tynes, women's basketball coach.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS -- Gave offensive coordinator Stan Parrish the additional duties of assistant head football coach. Named Mike Nelson defensive line coach.</p>
        <p>STETSON -- Fired Caren Truske, women's basketball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
