<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Treasury Issues Advance Slightly</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="597524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTEREST RATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREASURY BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDC1739F930A15750C0A965958260" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Treasury Issues Advance Slightly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The prices of Treasury securities bounced around yesterday and ended slightly higher as concerns about inflation seemed to keep traders and investors in check.</p>
        <p>The intensifying struggle in Russia between President Boris N. Yeltsin and Parliament did not have a major impact on the American bond market. But traders noted that the tension was a cause of declines in both bond and stock markets in Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The prices of Treasury securities bounced around yesterday and ended slightly higher as concerns about inflation seemed to keep traders and investors in check.</p>
        <p>The intensifying struggle in Russia between President Boris N. Yeltsin and Parliament did not have a major impact on the American bond market. But traders noted that the tension was a cause of declines in both bond and stock markets in Europe.</p>
        <p>In Germany, long-term bonds were off about 1/3 point in moderate trading. In France, bonds were down slightly and did not seem to get a lift from the better than expected performance of the conservative coalition in the first round of elections Sunday. In London, bond futures were off about half a point, in part because of the announcement of an auction on Friday. Problems In Russia Cited</p>
        <p>In the United States, the problems in Russia seemed to give a little support to shorter maturities, some traders said. But because the dollar did not strengthen, it does not appear that there is a significant flight to the relative security of United States investments.</p>
        <p>The auction of two-year and five-year Treasury notes this week is on the mind of every trader, and analysts will be looking to see if the results give any signal about the direction of the market, which has been locked in a narrow trading range for two weeks.</p>
        <p>Early in trading yesterday, the focus turned to inflation and the jump in the closely watched Commodity Research Bureau index of commodity prices, like lumber. The index rose to a 1993 intraday high of 214.27 before easing back to finish the day at 213.03, down from Friday's closing high for the year of 213.67.</p>
        <p>Since Feb. 8, the index has jumped from 198.46. If the rise continues, traders and analysts could find it more difficult to argue that moderate economic growth will bring the index back down again. Already, the Producer Price Index and the Consumer Price Index for February have risen more than expected.</p>
        <p>Nancy Lazar, an economist at the ISI Group, said that if the index broke though the 214 level, she would begin to be worried about her prediction that the rate of inflation will decline this year. The expectation of a decline in inflation is why many investors are still interested in buying long-term Treasury issues even though their yields are at their lowest levels in many years.</p>
        <p>There have been several instances in the last two years when the CRB index has jumped higher but then fell back again, Ms. Lazar said. The largest of these short-lived increases was a 7 percent jump, and if the index can break though 214, that would be more than a 7 percent rise.</p>
        <p>"We're fighting the tape given the rise in the CRB and the bad readings in the P.P.I. and the C.P.I.," she said of her forecast.</p>
        <p>But she said that she still expected the CRB index to fall because her forecast is that the economy, instead of picking up steam, will continue to move along at only a moderate pace. There are several reasons for this, she said, including the very slow growth in the nation's money supply; the continuation of layoffs around the country, and the recent decline in indexes of consumer confidence.</p>
        <p>Other forecasters are watching the CRB index closely but are less worried. Edward Yardeni, the chief economist at C. J. Lawrence, said that he will not worry about the index until it pierces the 225 level. 30-Year Bonds Prices Are Up</p>
        <p>In late trading yesterday, the price of the 30-year bond was up4/32 , to 104 6/32 and the yield was down to 6.80 percent, from 6.81 percent Friday. The price of the 10-year note was also up 4/32 as the yield inched down to 5.93 percent from 5.95 percent.</p>
        <p>The effect on short-term rates from the turmoil in Russia may have been reflected in the weekly auction of three-month and six-month Treasury bills. The average discount rate was 2.94 percent for the three-month bill, down from 3 percent a week ago, and the average discount rate was 3.05 percent for the six-month bill, down from 3.12 percent.</p>
        <p>In the when-issued, or pre-auction, market, the two-year note was trading at a yield 3.90 percent, down from 3.97 percent Friday, while the yield on the five-year note was at 5.17 percent, down from 5.20 percent. The two-year note will be auctioned tomorrow, the five-year note Thursday.</p>
        <p>Following are the results of the three-month and six-month bill auction yesterday: (000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>3-Mo. Bills</p>
        <p>6-Mo. Bills</p>
        <p>Average Price</p>
        <p>99.257</p>
        <p>98.458</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>2.94%</p>
        <p>3.05%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>3.00%</p>
        <p>3.14%</p>
        <p>High Price</p>
        <p>99.259</p>
        <p>98.463</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>2.93%</p>
        <p>3.04%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>2.99%</p>
        <p>3.13%</p>
        <p>Low Price</p>
        <p>99.257</p>
        <p>98.458</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>2.94%</p>
        <p>3.05%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>3.00%</p>
        <p>3.14%</p>
        <p>Accepted at low price</p>
        <p>66%</p>
        <p>73%</p>
        <p>Total applied for</p>
        <p>$49,133,875</p>
        <p>$40,689,700</p>
        <p>Accepted</p>
        <p>$11,220,145</p>
        <p>$11,203,710</p>
        <p>N.Y. applied for</p>
        <p>$45,661,985</p>
        <p>$37,258,495</p>
        <p>N.Y. accepted</p>
        <p>$10,194,175</p>
        <p>$10,049,495</p>
        <p>Noncompetitive</p>
        <p>$1,243,330</p>
        <p>$991,170</p>
        <p>Both these issues are dated March 25, 1993. The three month bills mature June 24, 1993 and the six-month bill mature on Sept. 23, 1993.  CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
