<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PRO FOOTBALL: Sports of The Times; When 'Everything Went White'</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="664221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BUFFALO BILLS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">KANSAS CITY CHIEFS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, DAVE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Buffalo Bills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Kansas City Chiefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4DD1130F937A15752C0A962958260" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PRO FOOTBALL: Sports of The Times; When 'Everything Went White'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDERSON, DAVE</byline>
      <dateline>ORCHARD PARK, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST after throwing the pass, Joe Montana was triple-teamed by the Bills' pass-rushers -- caught from behind by Phil Hansen, pounded from his left by Bruce Smith, crushed from his right by Jeff Wright. As he toppled forward near the Chiefs' 10-yard line early in the third quarter with the Bills leading, 20-6, his red helmet bounced off Rich Stadium's green rug.</p>
        <p>"Everything went white," the quarterback would say later, his blue eyes still somewhat dazed. "I had a real sharp pain in my head."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST after throwing the pass, Joe Montana was triple-teamed by the Bills' pass-rushers -- caught from behind by Phil Hansen, pounded from his left by Bruce Smith, crushed from his right by Jeff Wright. As he toppled forward near the Chiefs' 10-yard line early in the third quarter with the Bills leading, 20-6, his red helmet bounced off Rich Stadium's green rug.</p>
        <p>"Everything went white," the quarterback would say later, his blue eyes still somewhat dazed. "I had a real sharp pain in my head."</p>
        <p>Sharp enough to end his season. Also the Chiefs' season. Sharp enough for him to sit on the bench, hunched in a red-and-yellow jacket and still wearing his helmet in the gray mist for the remainder of a 30-13 loss. And the Bills marched yesterday into a Super Bowl XXVIII rematch with the reigning champion Dallas Cowboys next Sunday in Atlanta as the American Conference champions for the fourth consecutive year.</p>
        <p>"Joe had a mild concussion," Marty Schottenheimer, the Chiefs' coach, was saying now. "He wasn't in the kind of condition that would've helped us if he had been put in the game."</p>
        <p>If the Cowboys once were America's team, Joe Montana arrived in Buffalo as America's quarterback. But now, at age 37, he wouldn't be returning to the Super Bowl for the fifth time after having measured the 49ers for four rings. Instead, the team he played for would lose a playoff game for the sixth time, and he would be knocked out of a playoff game for the third time.</p>
        <p>When the Giants won the 1990 National Conference championship game from the 49ers, he wobbled to the sideline with a bruised sternum and a broken pinky after Leonard Marshall bear-hugged him.</p>
        <p>In the 1986 playoffs, he had rolled out of Giants Stadium flat on his back in an ambulance, his forehead wrapped in ice to soothe a concussion after nose tackle Jim Burt had flattened him.</p>
        <p>In the Chiefs' locker room now, Montana was taking a long shower as his teammates dressed. After misfiring on 11 of his first 14 passes in the first half, he suddenly hit 5 of 7 for 75 yards to move the Chiefs to the 5-yard line. But on a dart over the middle to Kimble Anders near the goal line, the ball bounced off the fullback's hands to safety Henry Jones.</p>
        <p>"The ball was pretty slick, I didn't quite get a grab on it," Anders said at his locker. "Joe told me the ball was slick, that it was slipping through his hands, too."</p>
        <p>That was typical Montana: never blame a teammate. But instead of having narrowed the Bills' lead to 20-13 at halftime, the Chiefs were still struggling when Montana's last pass was caught by tight end Keith Cash at the Chiefs' 29-yard line for a 17-yard gain. And now doctors and trainers surrounded the fallen quarterback as Marcus Allen stared at him.</p>
        <p>"He wasn't cognizant," Allen would say later.</p>
        <p>Montana rose, wobbled to the sideline with the doctors and trainers around him, then plopped onto the heated bench where he would hardly move as Dave Krieg, his backup, trotted onto the field.</p>
        <p>"I told Joe, 'Don't worry, we'll get 'em so we can play the next game,' " Allen said. "I don't think he understood me."</p>
        <p>Not far away, Carl Peterson, the Chiefs' general manager, was asked if he expected Montana to return for the 1994 season.</p>
        <p>"Oh, sure," Peterson said. "He signed a three-year contract. I expect him to fulfill it, and I guess he does, too."</p>
        <p>By now, Montana, carrying a hair-dryer in his left hand and with a white towel around his waist, had emerged from the shower. He walked slowly into the trainer's room as Paul Hackett, the Chiefs' offensive coordinator, accused the Bills of a late hit.</p>
        <p>"Joe had stopped," Hackett said. "His arm was down, he was relaxing and the guy busted him. And from behind. All that talk of protecting the quarterback."</p>
        <p>In a blue denim shirt over a black turtleneck and wearing a black LA Gear baseball cap, Montana soon was at the lectern in the interview room.</p>
        <p>"What they were saying," he said of his doctors and trainers, "was that my head bounced off the turf. I don't remember much about that part of it. I don't remember feeling anything when I got hit. I just remember right after that, grabbing my head. They said they thought it was more from the turf than it was from the hit, but I really don't know."</p>
        <p>Did he remember what happened in the game after that?</p>
        <p>"I didn't remember for most of the third quarter what even happened, much less what was going on," he said. "I was trying to pay attention, but I couldn't even remember what the score was or how they had gotten 20 points."</p>
        <p>Was he still dizzy now, about two hours after the hit?</p>
        <p>"Still a little bit," he said. "In quick movements my head hurts a little bit, but it's calming down"</p>
        <p>On his way out, a small boy held up a football and a pen.</p>
        <p>"No autographs," a bodyguard snapped. "No autographs."</p>
        <p>But having noticed the boy, Montana reached for the football.</p>
        <p>"You want to?" the bodyguard said. "If you want to."</p>
        <p>Montana nodded, stopped, took the football, autographed it with a black felt pen, handed it to the boy, 11-year-old Jayson Klein of East Amherst, N.Y., and walked back into the trainer's room. Helped into a black overcoat, he sat on a table against the wall, talking with those around him. Soon he was on his way to the Chiefs' buses in the parking lot, and when several hundred fans spotted him, they roared.</p>
        <p>"Love you, Joe," a man yelled.</p>
        <p>He was walking with his parents now, Joe Sr. and Theresa, and when he neared the players' bus, he hugged them both, one by one.</p>
        <p>"He's a little dinged up," his father would say later.</p>
        <p>"We'll see him in San Francisco tomorrow night," his mother said. "He told me he's all right, but I can tell by the way he's walking."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
