<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Taymor Wizardry Takes on Ribald Fantasy</title>
    <meta content="19BIRD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1193029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taymor, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gozzi, Carlo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFD71231F93AA25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Taymor Wizardry Takes on Ribald Fantasy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews The Green Bird, Julie Taymor's adaptation of Carlo Gozzi's 18th-century fable; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the Tony Awards had a category for best performance by a piece of fruit in a musical role, there's no question about which current Broadway show would provide the winner. Ditto for best performance by an actor denied the use of the upper two-thirds of his face. And for best use of eyelids by an oversize broken statue.</p>
        <p>These unlikely nominees are among the highlights of ''The Green Bird,'' Julie Taymor's alternately enchanting and tedious adaptation of Carlo Gozzi's 18th-century fable and a production that definitely stakes out an unclaimed patch in the shifting landscape of Broadway entertainments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the Tony Awards had a category for best performance by a piece of fruit in a musical role, there's no question about which current Broadway show would provide the winner. Ditto for best performance by an actor denied the use of the upper two-thirds of his face. And for best use of eyelids by an oversize broken statue.</p>
        <p>These unlikely nominees are among the highlights of ''The Green Bird,'' Julie Taymor's alternately enchanting and tedious adaptation of Carlo Gozzi's 18th-century fable and a production that definitely stakes out an unclaimed patch in the shifting landscape of Broadway entertainments.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taymor, whose distinctive brand of theatrical wizardry became world famous when she translated Disney's ''Lion King'' cartoon to the stage, sets her sights here on an adult audience with a childlike capacity for wonder, creating a ribald world in which the impossible is a matter of course.</p>
        <p>Big, shiny McIntosh-like apples split open to reveal platinum-blond sirens at their cores; a naked marble goddess of a statue melts into animation; a pyramid of chattering skulls guard the exquisite little bird of the title. Such visions occur often enough that toward the play's end, its characters grow impatient with all these fairy-tale shenanigans. ''What miracle?'' one of them asks. ''I'm used to this by now.''</p>
        <p>Theatergoers are unlikely to feel equally blase about the Ovidian transformations that Ms. Taymor and company keep conjuring in ''The Green Bird,'' which opened last night at the Cort Theater. It's the wait between miracles that's the problem.</p>
        <p>That Ms. Taymor has guts, style and artistic ambition to burn is indisputable. Who else would reintroduce masks as an essential part of actors' costumes and characters? Who else who would dare present a long philosophical fairy tale, performed in commedia dell'arte style and of a length and whimsy unsuitable for most children, in the land of ''Footloose'' and ''Saturday Night Fever''?</p>
        <p>As anyone knows who has seen her ''Lion King'' or her recent film fantasia of Shakespeare's bloody ''Titus Andronicus,'' Ms. Taymor plies a creative vocabulary unlike that of any other director in mainstream show business. The eclecticism that has been going under the rubric postmodern for several decades doesn't begin to describe her work.</p>
        <p>The sources of her theatrical tools, which range from shadow puppets to shamanlike masks, stretch back over millennia, not mere decades, and span all manner of civilizations. And there's no distancing irony in the presentation of these elements, no breezy quotation marks.</p>
        <p>Even in a lighter mood, which ''The Green Bird'' more or less represents, Ms. Taymor is gravely asking audiences to respond to the eternal in ritualized theater, to the ceremonial transfiguration of the ordinary into the symbolic. Or as a program note for ''The Green Bird'' concludes, ''Do we go to the theater to see ourselves reflected, or to be transported elsewhere?''</p>
        <p>Whatever the objective, a piece of theater has to keep you engaged on its own terms for as long as the house lights are down. ''The Green Bird,'' a long and winding tale of royal twins on an allegorical journey to self-knowledge, dazzles in its flights of imagery, but when the connecting story takes over, you may find your thoughts drifting to unreturned phone calls and unclaimed dry cleaning.</p>
        <p>This ''Green Bird'' -- which features attractively varied music by Elliot Goldenthal and the crack design team of Christine Jones (sets), Constance Hoffman (costumes) and Donald Holder (lighting) -- was first seen in an Off Broadway production at the New Victory Theater in 1996. Its basic elements, including its most spectacular set pieces and much of its cast, remain the same. Ms. Taymor and her ensemble have definitely come some distance in creating a cohesive style of performance.</p>
        <p>The best of the performers achieve an enlivening fusion of flesh and artifice. As Tartaglia, a self-described ''melancholy monarch,'' Derek Smith, who won an Obie award for the part four years ago, is saddled with an immense, jug-eared artificial head that suggests Prince Charles in a fun house mirror. He is also wonderfully expressive.</p>
        <p>True, he seems to wear his head as if it were an annoying but necessary encumbrance, but then don't we all from time to time? Mr. Smith has come up with an alphabet of physical gestures, exaggerated but fluid, that do indeed melt the man and the mask into one.</p>
        <p>Other performers, though not on the same level, often bring a balletic grace to antic shtick. They include Edward Hibbert as an evil queen mother who wears a bustle the size of a coffee table; Didi Conn and Ned Eisenberg as a Punch-and-Judy pair of sausage makers; and the wonderful Kristine Nielsen as Tartaglia's wronged queen, who is imprisoned in the castle sewers.</p>
        <p>There are also, memorably, Bruce Turk, who actually seems to become the green bird puppet he manipulates with a stick; Sophia Salguero as the Jean Harlowesque leader of a trio of singing apples with tree-tall stems and the heavy-lidded, house-size head of a statue named Calmon, whose voice is supplied by Andrew Weems.</p>
        <p>The only central characters who wear their own faces are Barbarina (Katie MacNichol) and Renzo (Sebastian Roche), orphaned twins who discover their parentage only after learning the perils of false philosophy, greed and vanity as well as of dragons and dancing skeletons.</p>
        <p>Their deliberately stilted performances bring to mind those story theater productions that tour schools. Not having your own mask in a Taymor production is definitely a disadvantage. You have to feel that Mr. Hibbert's queen has a point when he observes disdainfully of Barbarina that the girl has ''no dowry, no parents, no mask.''</p>
        <p>That is the pinnacle of verbal comedy in this ''Green Bird,'' which has been translated by Albert Bermel and Ted Emery from the Italian, although room seems to have been left for improvised jokes that range from the scatological to shameless topical puns. (Barbarina's lingerie is said to come from ''Vittoria's Da Secret.'')</p>
        <p>Many of the raunchier elements are provided by an evil soothsayer (Reg E. Cathey) who talks in rap and reggae and provides sexual services to the queen. Ms. Taymor's wit is clearly more visual than verbal, and her sense of the transcendent moment stronger than her gift for narrative.</p>
        <p>The problem with allegorical characters is that they walk a predetermined path and respond in predetermined ways. No matter how elaborately and imaginatively they are dressed up, there has to be something surprising about them that comes from within if they are to keep us company for any length of time.</p>
        <p>The visual eclat and creative energy in ''The Green Bird'' could happily fill a show half as long. At its current two hours and 15 minutes, the production is like an oversize art gallery where the pictures are ravishing but there's a lot of bare wall between them.</p>
        <p>THE GREEN BIRD</p>
        <p>By Carlo Gozzi; translated by Albert Bermel and Ted Emery from the Italian; original music composed and orchestrated by Elliot Goldenthal; directed by Julie Taymor; sets by Christine Jones; costumes by Constance Hoffman; lighting by Donald Holder; mask and puppet design by Ms. Taymor; sound by Jon Weston; wigs and makeup by Steven W. Bryant; production manager, Arthur Siccardi; general management, Nina Lannan Associates; production stage manager, Kristen Harris; musical director, Rick Martinez; vocal director, Joe Church; assistant director, Kamyar Atabai; musical staging by Daniel Ezralow; additional text by Eric Overmyer. Presented by Ostar Enterprises, with Theater for a New Audience, Jeffrey Horowitz, artistic director and Nina Lannan. At the Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>WITH: Reg E. Cathey (Brighella); Andrew Weems (Pantalone; voice of Calmon; Beauticians and Pierrot); Didi Conn (Smeraldina); Ned Eisenberg (Truffaldino); Katie MacNichol (Barbarina); Sebastian Roche (Renzo); Bruce Turk (the Green Bird); Kristine Nielsen (Ninetta); Derek Smith (Tartaglia); Edward Hibbert (Tartagliona); Lee Lewis (Pompea and voice of Serpentina); Sophia Salguero (soloist), Meredith Patterson and Sarah Jane Nelson (Singing Apples); and Erico Villanueva (soloist) and Ramon Flowers (Dancing Waters).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
