<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Unlikely Home for Ginsberg's Archive</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="713266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHIVES AND RECORDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POETRY AND POETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">STANFORD UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GINSBERG, ALLAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARGOLICK, DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archives and Records</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDD1F3BF933A1575AC0A962958260" item-length="1344" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Unlikely Home for Ginsberg's Archive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID MARGOLICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARGOLICK, DAVID</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Sept. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Allen Ginsberg went to Columbia University and still lives in New York. On its streets, and on the streets of San Francisco and Berkeley and Paris, he wrote many of his most famous poems, filled with gritty city imagery. But in the latest twist in his extraordinary life, Mr. Ginsberg's personal archives -- journals, tapes, letters, poems in progress, newspaper and beard clippings, even dried-up pieces of hallucinogenic vines and a pair of old tennis shoes -- will land at a place the Beats bypassed, a place so exurban it is called "the farm": balmy, palmy Stanford University.</p>
        <p>For much of his 68 years, Mr. Ginsberg has been a pack rat. He began keeping a journal when he was 12, and, as he came to believe his life embodied the struggle for sexual, social and political liberation in the 1950's and 60's, he was soon saving everything. The compulsive collecting took on new urgency in the Vietnam era as he saw counterrevolution and oppression approaching.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Allen Ginsberg went to Columbia University and still lives in New York. On its streets, and on the streets of San Francisco and Berkeley and Paris, he wrote many of his most famous poems, filled with gritty city imagery. But in the latest twist in his extraordinary life, Mr. Ginsberg's personal archives -- journals, tapes, letters, poems in progress, newspaper and beard clippings, even dried-up pieces of hallucinogenic vines and a pair of old tennis shoes -- will land at a place the Beats bypassed, a place so exurban it is called "the farm": balmy, palmy Stanford University.</p>
        <p>For much of his 68 years, Mr. Ginsberg has been a pack rat. He began keeping a journal when he was 12, and, as he came to believe his life embodied the struggle for sexual, social and political liberation in the 1950's and 60's, he was soon saving everything. The compulsive collecting took on new urgency in the Vietnam era as he saw counterrevolution and oppression approaching.</p>
        <p>Ultimately he amassed 300,000 items. Some he kept in his East Village apartment in New York, others in lockers, but most sat for the last 25 years in Butler Library at Columbia. But last year, when Mr. Ginsberg put the materials on the market, his alma mater did not bid. Worse, the air conditioning in its library broke down, threatening the hundreds of tapes he had amassed: readings, telephone chats with William S. Burroughs, jam sessions with Bob Dylan. When Stanford made its offer, for around $1 million, Mr. Ginsberg grabbed it.</p>
        <p>At first blush, Stanford's squeaky-clean, country club-like Palo Alto campus is the oddest of Ginsberg repositories. When Mr. Ginsberg and Beat buddies like Mr. Burroughs, Jack Kerouac and Lawrence Ferlinghetti became fixtures at many major American colleges in the late 1950's, Stanford never came calling.</p>
        <p>"Stanford was dominated by a very conservative, formalist poetry that very much rebelled against the kind of ecstatic, apocalyptic, William Carlos Williams-based naturalistic poetry we wrote," Mr. Ginsberg said last week over fried dumplings and shrimp with lobster sauce in San Francisco's Chinatown, just up the street from City Lights Books, publisher of his early miniature books with their famous black-and-white covers. "I gave readings for 10 years or so, at every university up and down the coast, and the one place that never invited me was Stanford."</p>
        <p>In some ways, not much has changed. "If he came down tomorrow, nine-tenths of the English department wouldn't turn out for him," said Marjorie Perloff, an English professor at Stanford who, with Profs. Diane Middlebrook and Gilbert Sorrentino, spurred on the purchase.</p>
        <p>But the Stanford library has recently begun collecting the papers of other avant-garde figures, including the poets Denise Levertov and Robert Creeley, and it considers Mr. Ginsberg even more important -- and durable.</p>
        <p>"Allen Ginsberg is one of the most important figures in postwar culture, literature and politics," said Tony Angiletta, the director of library collections for Stanford, who negotiated the deal with Mr. Ginsberg's agent, Andrew Wylie of New York. The papers, appraised in 1985 at $1.2 million, went for a bit less.</p>
        <p>"It was tough business, but we think we did quite well," Mr. Angiletta said. Mr. Ginsberg agreed. "They're getting it at bargain-basement rates," he said. What with cataloguing and secretarial costs over the last several years, he said he was losing money on the deal and complained that he had not cleared enough to buy a new apartment or loft in the East Village, complete with elevator, for himself and his 88-year-old stepmother.</p>
        <p>He would have been happier, Mr. Ginsberg confessed, had the papers ended up in New York, if not at Columbia, then in the Berg Collection of the New York Public Library, which also passed on the purchase. But his first priority, he said, was to find a place that would take loving care of his collection. That it was Stanford, home of the conservative Hoover Institution, was actually a plus.</p>
        <p>"It's fine by me, better maybe that they be in a bastion of conservatism," he said. "It will have a kind of osmotic influence. And people from the Hoover Institution can go through my files on the C.I.A.'s involvement with opium trafficking in Indochina." Mr. Ginsberg said he was not bothered by the unwillingness of Columbia -- which already owns an original typescript of "Howl" and assorted other Ginsberg papers -- to buy the rest. "It did about 10 years ago when I offered it to them, but that lasted about two days," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ginsberg's early journals contain passages about his mother's mental illness and his growing awareness of his homosexuality. His correspondence includes letters of advice from Williams, Kenneth Rexroth ("With persistence and postage anybody can get published, and you're pretty good") and Marianne Moore. "Patient or impatient repudiating of life just repudiates itself," she chided him in 1952. "What can be exciting to others is one's struggle with what is too hard."</p>
        <p>There is mail from an admiring high school student named Abbie Hoffman, the sneakers Mr. Ginsberg was wearing when he was kicked out of Czechoslovakia in 1965, and backstage passes from Mr. Dylan's 1975 Rolling Thunder Revue tour. The Ginsberg papers, which are to begin arriving at Stanford later this month, also include report cards from East Side High School in Paterson, N.J., electric bills and restaurant receipts, many with Mr. Ginsberg's annotations.</p>
        <p>"Allen always wrote on everything, so it would be 'I had lunch with Bob Dylan and we had rice and beans,' " said Bill Morgan, an archivist in New York who has spent the last 15 years cataloging the collection and lamented that no matter how hard he worked, he was always 15 years behind.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ginsberg, who suffers from diabetes and a heart ailment, appeared frail and tired during his visit here, a far cry from his formerly burly, bushy-bearded self. His fatigue also stemmed, no doubt, from a whirlwind of readings, interviews and signings coinciding with the recent release of "Holy Soul Jelly Roll," a set of four compact disks of poems and songs, including early readings of "Howl" and "Kaddish."</p>
        <p>The visit was his second here in recent months; in June he chanted an anti-war poem called "Hum Bom" from the pitcher's mound at Candlestick Park. It was one of many signs that the Beats have become disconcertingly mainstream in San Francisco; a local map now shows Via Ferlinghetti and Jack Kerouac Alley. "Don your beret and dark glasses -- Beat legend Allen Ginsberg is coming to Barnes &amp; Noble," stated an advertisement in The San Francisco Bay Guardian for a book signing last week in Berkeley.</p>
        <p>That signing attracted a throng of admirers -- and a few old-timers, Mr. Ginsberg noted, using the Yiddish phrase for fuddy-duddies -- but mostly the latest crop of teen-agers and college students to whom his protest poems speak. He read two of them -- "A Supermarket in California" and "Death to van Gogh's Ear!" -- and then they lined up for autographs, snaking through the store past college-admissions and science fiction/fantasy sections and into poetry, carrying copies of "Kaddish," "Hydrogen Jukebox" and "The Portable Beat Reader."</p>
        <p>Mr. Ginsberg signed them all, as well as the advertisement he had done recently for the Gap clothing stores. "Allen Ginsberg wore khakis," it stated. (And he still does.) Only one autograph per customer, though, and he would not sign the Bible or "Lady Chatterley's Lover." On each he also wrote "AH," the mantra given to him by his principal Tibetan teacher, Chogyam Trungpa, Rinpoche. Some students brought him their poems or term papers. Another swore to him she had just seen the reincarnation of Neal Cassady, Mr. Ginsberg's muse, who died in 1968.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Ginsberg, his continuing appeal is simple. "I think for the younger generation there is a sense of disenfranchisement, or, as they call it nowadays, diminishing expectations," he said afterward. "There's a kind of spiritual hunger. In a sense, the nation is Beat."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
