<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sabres Triumph But Trail Series, 2-1</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="436029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="N.H.L. PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL HOCKEY LEAGUE (NHL)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DF123FF93BA35757C0A967958260" item-length="504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sabres Triumph But Trail Series, 2-1</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO, April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defenseman Mike Ramsey's soft shot flipped over the shoulder of goalie Patrick Roy to snap a tie and give the Buffalo Sabres a 5-4 victory over the Montreal Canadiens tonight and their first victory in the three games of their playoff series.</p>
        <p>Ramsey moved in from the point to take a pass from Rob Ray before drifting a 12-footer over Roy at 2 minutes 28 seconds of the third period.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Defenseman Mike Ramsey's soft shot flipped over the shoulder of goalie Patrick Roy to snap a tie and give the Buffalo Sabres a 5-4 victory over the Montreal Canadiens tonight and their first victory in the three games of their playoff series.</p>
        <p>Ramsey moved in from the point to take a pass from Rob Ray before drifting a 12-footer over Roy at 2 minutes 28 seconds of the third period.</p>
        <p>The four-of-seven-game Adams Division series resumes Tuesday night here at Memorial Auditorium.</p>
        <p>Tony Tanti, Christian Ruuttu, Benoit Hogue and Grant Ledyard also scored for Buffalo. Montreal got two goals from Brent Gilchrist and single goals from Shayne Corson and Russ Courtnall.</p>
        <p>The Sabres jumped to an early lead 2:20 into the game when Roy juggled a high shot from the point by Doug Bodger. The rebound dropped into the crease and Tanti shoved it underneath Roy.</p>
        <p>Less than two minutes later, Montreal tied it on a power play. Corson walked in from the wing to take a pass from the point by Mathieu Schneider and snap a 17-foot shot between the legs of Buffalo goalie Clint Malarchuk.</p>
        <p>Buffalo got several 2-on-1 opportunities in the period and cashed in on one at 5:28 while Montreal was on the power play. With forward Denis Savard back as the lone Canadiens' defender, Ruuttu and Dave Snuggerud passed back and forth before Ruuttu shoved the puck into the open side.</p>
        <p>Gilchrist's third of the series at 9:56 tied it at 2. He broke free on the left wing, swept to the center and lifted a short backhander over Malarchuk's glove.</p>
        <p>Montreal went up 3-2 with a power play goal at 11:47. In a play similar to Corson's goal, Courtnall came off the wing to take a pass and fire a 15-foot shot past Malarchuk.</p>
        <p>The Sabres scored the next two goals in the second period to take a 4-3 lead before Gilchrist scored his second of the night with 2:02 left in the period to tie it at 4-4 going into the third period. Bruins 6, Whalers 3</p>
        <p>HARTFORD (AP) -- Dave Christian and Garry Galley scored 18 seconds apart to spark a four-goal third period as Boston took a 2-1 lead in the Adams Division semifinals.</p>
        <p>Bob Sweeney added a goal three minutes later for Boston and Craig Janney added a goal on a two-man advantage. Ray Bourque and Glen Wesley also had power-play goals for the Bruins.</p>
        <p>Boston goalie Andy Moog made 22 saves to shut down Hartford, which controlled the flow the first two periods.</p>
        <p>Galley scored 6:49 into the period, taking advantage of a Hartford mistake. Hartford rookie Geoff Sanderson, playing in his fifth league game, sent an errant pass back toward goalie Peter Sidorkiewicz. Sidorkiewicz attempted to clear it, but the puck went to Galley, who fired in the wrist shot.</p>
        <p>Christian, standing to the right of the slot, took a pass from Randy Burridge from behind the net and fired a shot into the far corner.</p>
        <p>On Sweeney's goal, the Whalers were unable to move the puck up ice. Sweeney took the puck, skated around defenseman Brad Shaw and hit a slow shot past the sprawled Sidorkiewicz.</p>
        <p>N.H.L. PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
