<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Ruling May Change Landscape For Media</title>
    <meta content="Y20IMP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1369290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">News Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Viacom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aol Time Warner</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cox Enterprises Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3D8173EF933A15751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Ruling May Change Landscape For Media</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL and BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth; Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of Federal appeals court ruling that government has to reconsider sharp limits on number of stations network can own and striking down regulation that had restricted cable operators from owning television stations; says rulings will probably prompt executives at companies including News Corp, Viacom and Walt Disney Co, which each own many television stations, to seriously consider expanding their empires by acquisition; holds major players in cable television market like AOL Time Warner and Cox Enterprises can now consider significantly expanding their relatively small broadcasting operations (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Investment bankers, start your engines.</p>
        <p>That was essentially the message to Wall Street and the media industry yesterday as a federal appeals court in Washington unleashed what is expected to be a major wave of deal making, with the titans of the television business snapping up their smaller brethren.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Investment bankers, start your engines.</p>
        <p>That was essentially the message to Wall Street and the media industry yesterday as a federal appeals court in Washington unleashed what is expected to be a major wave of deal making, with the titans of the television business snapping up their smaller brethren.</p>
        <p>Unless the Supreme Court overturns the rulings, the decisions will allow a single company to own both a cable television system and a local broadcaster in the same market. In addition, yesterday's rulings threw into serious doubt a rule that currently prevents a single company from owning broadcast stations reaching more than 35 percent of the nation's television households.</p>
        <p>In the wake of the rulings, the Federal Communications Commission could increase that 35 percent figure to perhaps 50 percent, or it could eliminate the cap altogether. Either way, the rulings will probably prompt executives at companies including the News Corporation, Viacom and the Walt Disney Company, which each own many television stations already, to seriously consider expanding their empires by acquisition.</p>
        <p>Moreover, major players in the cable television market like AOL Time Warner and Cox Enterprises can now consider significantly expanding their relatively small broadcasting operations.</p>
        <p>''This sets the stage for an enormous re-landscaping of the media business, probably over the next three years,'' said Larry Gerbrandt, the chief content officer of Kagan Worldwide Media. ''This should ignite the deal market. We'll see a whole new set of combinations possible out there.''</p>
        <p>Many of the most profitable broadcast stations are already owned by big companies. But there are still plenty of smaller and midsize broadcasters with valuable properties, including the Belo Corporation; Meredith; and Scripps-Howard, which is owned by E. W. Scripps.</p>
        <p>If the 35 percent cap is relaxed significantly, as is expected, the companies in broadcasting's second tier could prove attractive acquisition candidates for the industry's giants and could also consolidate among themselves.</p>
        <p>''If we get to a land-rush mentality, who knows what could happen,'' said Thomas Wolzien, a media analyst with Sanford C. Bernstein. ''My guess is that companies with $15 billion to $30 billion market cap, like Gannett and Tribune, will have incentive to make some serious moves.''</p>
        <p>One senior executive at a large owner of broadcast stationssaid: ''All the companies will get the message. You have to get bigger or sell. All the market forces will be pushing toward acquisitions.''</p>
        <p>Local broadcast stations are attractive assets because they are among the most profitable businesses in the media world. Networks like ABC and CBS generally pay their affiliates to distribute their programming and the local broadcasters transmit the network programs with very little commensurate cost. The networks make their profits by retaining most of the advertising time on their programs.</p>
        <p>For instance, the News Corporation's 33 local television stations had $526 million of revenue in the final quarter of 2001 while generating $259 million in earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization -- or cash flow -- for an Ebitda margin of almost 50 percent. That is excellent for just about any sort of business, especially in a poor advertising market. In fact, the News Corporation reaped more cash flow from its local broadcast group in the last quarter than from any of its other myriad far-flung divisions.</p>
        <p>Given the profitability of local stations, it was no surprise that yesterday's statements from the media behemoths could have been written by a common hand. AOL Time Warner, the News Corporation and Viacom each blandly said that it was ''pleased'' by the decisions. Describing the rules at issue, the News Corporation used the word ''outdated,'' NBC chose ''antiquated,'' while AOL Time Warner and Viacom opted for ''anachronism.'' A Disney spokesman declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's decisions have perhaps the most intriguing implications for AOL Time Warner, which owns the nation's No. 2 cable operation with about 12.8 million subscribers. Time Warner Cable's biggest market is New York City, followed in size by Tampa, Fla.; the Orlando, Fla., area; Houston; and the Raleigh, N.C., area.</p>
        <p>Until yesterday, AOL Time Warner could not own local broadcast television stations in any of those markets, or in any of its other cable markets. It could own stations in markets where it has no cable presence, like Chicago and San Francisco, but the company had decided against getting serious about the local television business with so many important markets beyond its reach.</p>
        <p>That is why the WB Network, owned by AOL Time Warner, had not owned its own broadcasting stations, though its minority partner, the Tribune Company, owns 17 WB stations.</p>
        <p>For now, AOL Time Warner owns only one broadcast station, the TBS superstation, which is broadcast over the air in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>After yesterday, that could all change. If yesterday's rulings are not overturned, AOL Time Warner will have many reasons to consider acquiring local broadcast stations or even a major network.</p>
        <p>''AOL Time Warner could go for some big TV stations, or they could go for NBC,'' Mr. Gerbrandt said. At the same time, he said, NBC's owner, General Electric, through its GE Capital subsidiary, already lends substantial amounts of money to cable operators. That relationship could now prompt NBC to get into cable itself.</p>
        <p>Another intriguing target, several analysts said, could be Disney, which has never been a favorite company of cable operators because of the hard bargains it drives on prices for its cable channels like ESPN. ''If Disney was considered to be in play before today, there are a lot more potential players now,'' said the senior executive of the big broadcasting company.</p>
        <p>As for the News Corporation (which owns Fox), Viacom (which owns CBS) and Disney (which owns ABC), they may look to expand their own broadcast groups if attractive stations become available. The News Corporation owns 33 stations and Viacom owns 34 while Disney owns 10.</p>
        <p>Disney could have chosen to expand its station group even before yesterday's decision, while the News Corporation and Viacom were already over the 35 percent cap. In that sense, those two companies may have been the most liberated by yesterday's decision. Now, those companies will probably be allowed to acquire more stations. A person close to the News Corporation said the company would probably continue to focus on the nation's biggest markets as it considered broadcasting acquisitions.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the News Corporation, Viacom and Disney are now cleared to buy their way into the cable business. Such a move appears somewhat unlikely, however, because none of the big cable companies appear to be for sale.</p>
        <p>If approved, Comcast's pending acquisition of AT&amp;T's cable unit would place the industry's No. 1 company under the control of the Roberts family. AOL Time Warner would not sell its cable business, the industry's second biggest. After the Comcast deal, the No. 3 cable company would be Charter Communications, which has just recently been assembled by Paul Allen, a co-founder of Microsoft. The fourth biggest would be Cox Communications, which is under the control of the Cox family.</p>
        <p>Cox, in fact, is one of the few companies with a significant presence in both cable and broadcast television. The Cox cable operation serves about 6.2 million customers while the company also owns five broadcast stations in markets not served by Cox cable. The company could now try to swap its existing stations for stations in its cable markets, potentially consolidating its operations and reducing costs.</p>
        <p>A Cox spokesman declined to comment.</p>
        <p>On a day when stocks generally fell, the shares of some of the biggest media companies were mixed yesterday. Shares of AOL Time Warner fell 53 cents, to $25.52. Disney shares slipped $1.04, to $22.86. The News Corporation rose 6 cents, to $26.27, while Viacom dropped $1.06, to $42.32.</p>
        <p>The stocks of Belo and Meredith were off only marginally and still near their 52-week highs. Belo closed down 18 cents, to $20.49, while Meredith was off 12 cents at $36.39.</p>
        <p>Shares of E. W. Scripps, meanwhile, rose 77 cents, to $74.02, which is just below the record high of $74.51 that the stock reached only last week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
