<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; LVMH Luxury Conglomerate Sells Its Art Auction House</title>
    <meta content="Y20PLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/20/business/20PLAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1369289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Market Place"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lvmh Moet Hennessy Louis Vuitton Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Phillips, De Pury &amp; Luxembourg</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnault, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Pury, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Luxembourg, Daniella</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Arnault, Bernard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D8173EF933A15751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; LVMH Luxury Conglomerate Sells Its Art Auction House</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">LVMH Sells Its Art Auction House</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and CAROL VOGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol; Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>LVMH Moet Hennessy Louis Vuitton chairman Bernard Arnault sells his company's majority stake in auction house Phillips, de Pury &amp; Luxembourg to partners Simon de Pury and Daniella Luxembourg, former Sotheby's officials who run art dealership based in Geneva and are chairman and president, respectively, of Phillips; LVMH will keep about quarter of Phillips; financial terms undisclosed; graph; photo (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bernard Arnault is slowly beginning to correct his mistakes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arnault, the chairman of LVMH Moët Hennessy Louis Vuitton, agreed yesterday to sell his company's majority stake in the world's No. 3 auction house, Phillips, de Pury &amp; Luxembourg. Just three years ago, he bought Phillips with hopes of building a business that would rival Sotheby's Holdings and Christie's International in profits and prestige.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bernard Arnault, the chairman of LVMH Moët Hennessy Louis Vuitton, agreed to sell his company's stake in the world's No. 3 auction house, Phillips, de Pury &amp; Luxembourg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bernard Arnault is slowly beginning to correct his mistakes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arnault, the chairman of LVMH Moët Hennessy Louis Vuitton, agreed yesterday to sell his company's majority stake in the world's No. 3 auction house, Phillips, de Pury &amp; Luxembourg. Just three years ago, he bought Phillips with hopes of building a business that would rival Sotheby's Holdings and Christie's International in profits and prestige.</p>
        <p>The foray into fine art auctions, a business that analysts estimate cost Mr. Arnault hundreds of millions of dollars, appears to be just one of several regrettable ventures. Last week, he shut his personal Internet investment company, Europ@Web. He is also looking to sell Sephora, a money-losing cosmetics retailer, and DFS, a chain of duty-free shops, executives close to the company said.</p>
        <p>In hindsight, Mr. Arnault's acquisition spree in the late 1990's, to expand beyond luxury goods like clothing and perfume, was ill timed, and possibly ill conceived. With the global economy in a slump, LVMH reported a 20 percent decline in operating profit last year, deeper than originally forecast, to 1.56 billion euros, or $1.37 billion. It predicts that a rebound in its business will not come until the second half of the year at the earliest.</p>
        <p>LVMH's stock has sagged to half its level at the beginning of 2000, in part because the highly profitable luxury goods businesses have been dragged down by some newer acquisitions. In its statement yesterday, LVMH seemed to acknowledge that it might have strayed too far afield in buying Phillips, explaining that it was selling the business to ''concentrate on the development of luxury products.''</p>
        <p>Both Phillips and DFS, which posted a 33 percent decline in sales in the fourth quarter of 2001, are pulling down LVMH. While Sephora's sales are still skyrocketing -- they rose 21 percent in the fourth quarter of 2001 -- LVMH is spending millions to open stores in some of the world's most expensive locations. Sephora has more than 300 stores worldwide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arnault's idea of creating a luxury conglomerate, however, never really came together.</p>
        <p>Phillips, for example, does not make use of the company's distribution network. ''The deal didn't make any sense to begin with,'' Sagra Maceira de Rosen, an analyst at J. P. Morgan in London, said of LVMH's acquisition. ''Auction houses are not luxury goods, so why bother with that? It was never accepted by investors as a smart strategy.''</p>
        <p>Smart strategy may not have been the point. In his quest to compete with François Pinault, the French luxury goods magnate who bought Christie's in 1998, Mr. Arnault first made an attempt to buy Sotheby's. When that failed, a year later he decided to buy the moribund Phillips auction house and make it a major player in the art world.</p>
        <p>When the deal closes in about a month, LVMH will keep about a quarter of Phillips after selling its majority stake to its partners, Simon de Pury and Daniella Luxembourg, former Sotheby's officials who run an art dealership based in Geneva and are the chairman and president, respectively, of Phillips. Terms of the deal were not disclosed, but company executives said Mr. de Pury and Ms. Luxembourg would own 72.5 percent of the business, up from 25 percent, and LVMH would retain a 27.5 percent stake.</p>
        <p>It remains unclear how much LVMH has made or lost on the business after spending about $93 million in November 1999 for the 75 percent stake. One executive close to the deal said that LVMH sold its stake for less than it paid for it.</p>
        <p>Anne Sutherland Fuchs, who was named chief executive of Philips in July, will ''assume new functions at LVMH,'' according to a company statement. She is being succeeded by Louise T. Blouin MacBain, Mr. de Pury's companion who has been a member of the supervisory board of Trader.com. Ms. MacBain, a co-founder of the Hebdo Mag Group of 296 publications and 62 Web sites and Hebdo's chief executive for 14 years, will invest in Phillips, Mr. de Pury said. She will run an auction house with 140 employees, a tenth the size of Sotheby's or Christie's, and offices in Geneva, London and New York. A Paris office is planned.</p>
        <p>From the time that LVMH bought Phillips in 1999, Mr. Arnault began taking big financial risks. To wrest major art collections away from Sotheby's and Christie's, LVMH invested large sums to procure art. It would either buy art works outright or offer a seller's form of financing known as a guarantee -- an undisclosed sum promised to a seller regardless of a sale's outcome. In both cases, officials sometimes sold the art at a loss, and rationalized it as part of a strategy for the long term.</p>
        <p>In November, the auction house sold 72 works, mostly early 20th-century French and German art that had belonged to the Los Angeles collectors Nathan and Marion Smooke. The Smooke heirs received a guarantee estimated at $185 million. Just before the sale, the heirs decided to retain works worth about $15 million, which came off the guarantee. But Phillips still lost about $80 million, according to art experts.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Pury said yesterday that Phillips would continue to offer guarantees for worthy collections. But his tone was more cautious than earlier in LVMH's involvement.</p>
        <p>''On the surface it would appear that they don't have the deep pockets they had before,'' said Robert Mnuchin, founder of C&amp;M Arts, a Manhattan art gallery. ''Maybe they do, but it's not obvious.''</p>
        <p>While officials at Sotheby's and Christie's declined to discuss the Phillips deal yesterday, some experts said they thought the threat from Phillips was over. ''If I were Sotheby's and Christie's, I'd feel as though I'd weathered a storm,'' Mr. Mnuchin said.</p>
        <p>As the auction world gears up for the spring auctions, art experts say that Phillips has not been a contender for the major collections and is no longer offering extravagant financial packages to sellers. Mr. de Pury and Ms. Luxembourg denied these reports and said the collections that have become available were not worth the investment.</p>
        <p>Market Place</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
