<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lehman Operagoers Can Still Attend on a Pittance</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="580531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OPERA</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHERMAN, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DF163CF930A35752C0A965958260" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lehman Operagoers Can Still Attend on a Pittance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHERMAN, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LET Metropolitan and New York City Opera fans moan about high ticket prices. For 25 years, the Bronx Opera, which has been called New York's best small opera group, has been presenting first-rate performances at the Lehman Center Theater for no more than the current top price of $13. Michael Spierman, the company's founder and director, said it was hard to believe that the group had been together for a quarter of a century, "discovering exciting new talents and making the acquaintance of wonderful scores not often presented in this area."</p>
        <p>An example of an unusual work on the company's agenda is Smetana's comic masterpiece, "The Bartered Bride," fully staged and sung in English translation with orchestra. The opera will be performed next Saturday at 8 P.M., with Miriam Burns conducting; Mr. Spierman will conduct a repeat performance next Sunday at 2 P.M. For those undaunted by a trip into Manhattan, there will be two performances at the John Jay College Theater on Jan. 15 and 16 at 8 P.M. For reservations at either location, the number to call is (212) 408-1661.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LET Metropolitan and New York City Opera fans moan about high ticket prices. For 25 years, the Bronx Opera, which has been called New York's best small opera group, has been presenting first-rate performances at the Lehman Center Theater for no more than the current top price of $13. Michael Spierman, the company's founder and director, said it was hard to believe that the group had been together for a quarter of a century, "discovering exciting new talents and making the acquaintance of wonderful scores not often presented in this area."</p>
        <p>An example of an unusual work on the company's agenda is Smetana's comic masterpiece, "The Bartered Bride," fully staged and sung in English translation with orchestra. The opera will be performed next Saturday at 8 P.M., with Miriam Burns conducting; Mr. Spierman will conduct a repeat performance next Sunday at 2 P.M. For those undaunted by a trip into Manhattan, there will be two performances at the John Jay College Theater on Jan. 15 and 16 at 8 P.M. For reservations at either location, the number to call is (212) 408-1661.</p>
        <p>The county's new classical season begins with an organ recital by Jean Thiel on Wednesday at 12:35 P.M., as the Downtown Music at Grace Series resumes at Grace Episcopal Church in White Plains. Normally in residence at Memorial Methodist Church, also in White Plains, Dr. Thiel comes to Grace with works of Mendelssohn, Seth Bingham and others. The number to call for more information is 949-0384.</p>
        <p>The Katonah Village Improvement Society sounds more like a civic than a cultural organization, but for the 27th year, the society is sponsoring a series of recitals at the Katonah Library. The first of the three concerts will be a performance by the Meridian Arts Ensemble next Sunday at 3 P.M.; the harpist Marie-Pierre Langlamet will play on Feb. 21, and the New World Saxophone Quartet will close the cycle a month later.</p>
        <p>The Meridian, founded at the Juilliard School in 1987, is one of America's finest brass quintets, earning special recognition for its innovative programming. At next Sunday's concert the ensemble will offer "Three Psalm Settings" by the early 17th-century composer Johann Schein and works by the contemporary composers Jan Radzynski, Ira Taxin and Jan Bach.</p>
        <p>The number to call for more information is 232-5214.</p>
        <p>The Emelin Trio will be performing at the Emelin Theater in Mamaroneck next Sunday at 3 P.M. The group will play works by favorite composers. For further information, the number to call is 698-0098.</p>
        <p>Another concert scheduled for next Sunday at 3 P.M. is a recital by Marian Hahn, the pianist of the resident Wave Hill Trio. She will play solo pieces by Haydn, Schumann, Bartok and Chopin in Wave Hill's Armor Hall in Riverdale. The number for more information is (212) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>The Pleasantville Cantata Singers, which begins rehearsals on Jan. 11 for a May 1 performance of Brahms's "German Requiem" and the Dvorak "Te Deum," is planning to add several new members. "Audition" is probably too strong a word to use here, because interested singers need not prepare anything in advance. They will just be asked to sing a few simple melodies to determine voice placement and sight-reading ability. The number to call for more information is 769-2314.</p>
        <p>There is a new school of dance in the county: the Scarsdale Ballet Studio. The company was founded late last year by Christian Claessens, recently retired soloist with the Dutch National Ballet, and his wife, Diana White, a soloist with the New York City Ballet. "It is a pleasure for us to share the inner feeling of movement with other dancers," Mr. Claessens said.</p>
        <p>"We sought a place where we could impart the knowledge and beliefs that are dear to us," Ms. White added, "and we chose Westchester as a community in touch with the arts with a receptive environment for what we have to offer."</p>
        <p>Classes and workshops will be available to students of all ages, whether or not they are seeking a career in dance, from creative movement for 5-year-olds to exercises for adults interested, as Mr. Claessens put it, "in the science and art of ballet." The studio's number is 725-8754.</p>
        <p>For the youngsters, the Emelin Theater in Mamaroneck will present the musical "Tom Sawyer" next Saturday at 11 A.M. And for jazz aficionados, the Emelin is offering on the same day at 8 P.M. the witty improvisations of the pianist Marian McPartland. The number to call for more information is 698-0098.</p>
        <p>Tom Chapin, one of America's top folk singers, has two engagements next Saturday at the Walkabout Clearwater Coffeehouse in Katonah. For his family show at 3 P.M., he will sing "Pretty Planet," "Family Tree" and lots more of his wise and witty children's ballads. Mr. Chapin will return at 8 P.M. with an adult show, showcasing contemporary issues. Catie Curtis, a young New England songwriter, will also perform that evening. The coffehouse's number is 242-0374.</p>
        <p>The pianist Hank Edmonds, the drummer Tootsie Bean and the bassist Michael Fleming will play music of jazz greats in a free program at the Ossining Public Library next Sunday at 3:30 P.M. The number to call for more information is 941-2416.</p>
        <p>The singer-songwriters Hugh Blumenfeld and Margo Hennebach will also be performing next Sunday. The folk event, the first Uptown Coffeehouse concert of 1993, will take place at the Ethical Culture building on Fieldston Road in the Bronx at 7 P.M. The numbers to call for more information are 682-0484 or (718) 543-3474.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
