<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seniors Show Rookie Coach How It's Done in March</title>
    <meta content="17oklahoma" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/17/sports/ncaabasketball/17oklahoma.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1747495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL: MINNEAPOLIS REGION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ncaa Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Oklahoma</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glier, Ray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E2DC1E31F934A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seniors Show Rookie Coach How It's Done in March</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Seniors Show Rookie Coach How It's Done in March</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY GLIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glier, Ray</byline>
      <dateline>JACKSONVILLE, Fla., March 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wisconsin University-Milwaukee defeats Oklahoma University, 82-74, in first round of men's NCAA tournament (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Wisconsin-Milwaukee opened the season with a 27-point loss to Memphis and lost again in the third game of the season to Tennessee Tech, there was some concern that the Panthers, with four returning senior starters, were going to be ruined by a change of coaches.</p>
        <p>Bruce Pearl, who guided Wisconsin-Milwaukee to the Round of 16 in the 2005 N.C.A.A. tournament with two upset victories, had left for Tennessee. The transition under the new coach, Rob Jeter, a former assistant and associate head coach at Wisconsin, was not going smoothly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The senior-dominated Wisconsin-Milwaukee team and their Coach Rob Jeeter ran away from sixth-seeded Oklahoma to win, 82-74.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Wisconsin-Milwaukee opened the season with a 27-point loss to Memphis and lost again in the third game of the season to Tennessee Tech, there was some concern that the Panthers, with four returning senior starters, were going to be ruined by a change of coaches.</p>
        <p>Bruce Pearl, who guided Wisconsin-Milwaukee to the Round of 16 in the 2005 N.C.A.A. tournament with two upset victories, had left for Tennessee. The transition under the new coach, Rob Jeter, a former assistant and associate head coach at Wisconsin, was not going smoothly.</p>
        <p>''Coach Pearl and Coach Jeter had different ways,'' the senior guard Chris Hill said. ''It was a little rough at the beginning.''</p>
        <p>There was a tug of war between the senior-dominated team and Jeter, who did not press as much as Pearl did. Jeter also installed a swing offense, a more deliberate attack than the freewheeling one used by Pearl.</p>
        <p>But as the season progressed, the Panthers and Jeter collected themselves. That partnership was on display in the first round of the N.C.A.A. tournament Thursday at Veterans Memorial Arena as 11th-seeded Wisconsin-Milwaukee ran away from sixth-seeded Oklahoma to win, 82-74, in the Minneapolis Region.</p>
        <p>The senior guard Boo Davis scored 26 points and the senior forward Joah Tucker added 24 to lead the Panthers (22-8) into the second round against third-seeded Florida on Saturday. The Gators defeated 14th-seeded South Alabama, 76-50, in another first-round game here Thursday.</p>
        <p>When Wisconsin-Milwaukee took control against Oklahoma (20-9) with a 13-2 run in the second half, there was hardly a buzz in the arena. After all, this was essentially the same team that defeated Alabama and Boston College in the 2005 tournament under Pearl (before losing to Illinois), so an upset was not unexpected.</p>
        <p>Four months ago, however, the seniors and Jeter had some disagreements that threatened what was expected to be a terrific season. As the veteran point guard, Hill was the one to take the seniors' messages to their coach. ''When Joah or Boo and him would bump heads, I was the guy they looked to talk to him,'' Hill said.</p>
        <p>Reminded of Hill's visits, Jeter smiled and said: ''You don't really do any negotiating with players. Basically, you just plant the seed. I knew what he was doing.''</p>
        <p>Tucker said that Jeter seemed to be flexible and that he adjusted the team's offense in the regular season. He said the system took advantage of the mobility of the Panthers' big men by using them on the perimeter and having the guards cut off the baseline and play more inside.</p>
        <p>The 6-foot-3 Davis went flying around the corners and off the baseline and made 7 of 15 shots. When Davis was not shaking free for jumpers, the 6-foot-5 Tucker was using his advantage in quickness over the Oklahoma forwards to drive from the wing to the basket.</p>
        <p>Tucker's aggressiveness took him to the free-throw line 16 times, and he made 13. Wisconsin-Milwaukee was 26 of 32 from the free-throw line; Oklahoma, using a more deliberate offense, was 5 of 8.</p>
        <p>''We match up better with traditional teams, teams that have three guards, two forwards,'' Oklahoma forward Kevin Bookout said. ''I think that had some impact today.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL: MINNEAPOLIS REGION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
