<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holzman Still Casts Silent Shadow</title>
    <meta content="17araton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/17/sports/basketball/17araton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1747489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holzman, Red</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Larry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Holzman, Red</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Marbury, Stephon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3DC1E31F934A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holzman Still Casts Silent Shadow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Holzman Still Casts Silent Shadow</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>Greenburgh, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column discusses New York Knicks coach Larry Brown, who has said that Red Holzman is his idol; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN my early-morning dream yesterday, one of Larry Brown's idols, Red Holzman, was named coach of an N.B.A. team of undisclosed identity, though we can venture an educated guess as to which one it was. I'm serious about this. On a platform stage, holding a ball, there was the late, great Holzman, with that trademark wry smile, stonewalling his way through another interview, as was his wont throughout his career.</p>
        <p>Subconsciously, it seems that I want to tell Brown he could do much worse than to emulate Holzman, who, like Brown, was born in Brooklyn, lived on Long Island and established indisputable Hall of Fame coaching credentials by preaching defense and sharing the ball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Subconsciously, it seems that I want to tell Larry Brown he could do much worse than to emulate Red Holzman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN my early-morning dream yesterday, one of Larry Brown's idols, Red Holzman, was named coach of an N.B.A. team of undisclosed identity, though we can venture an educated guess as to which one it was. I'm serious about this. On a platform stage, holding a ball, there was the late, great Holzman, with that trademark wry smile, stonewalling his way through another interview, as was his wont throughout his career.</p>
        <p>Subconsciously, it seems that I want to tell Brown he could do much worse than to emulate Holzman, who, like Brown, was born in Brooklyn, lived on Long Island and established indisputable Hall of Fame coaching credentials by preaching defense and sharing the ball.</p>
        <p>Unlike Brown, Holzman just wasn't too interested in sharing with reporters his deep, dark thoughts about his least favorite players. Brown thinks Stephon Marbury is such a nightmare to coach? He should have tried, all at once, Ray Williams, Sly Williams and Micheal Ray Richardson.</p>
        <p>And still, Holzman, who won championships with upstanding citizens like Bill Bradley and Willis Reed, wouldn't budge, wouldn't lash out for the back page.</p>
        <p>''Boy, are you in trouble,'' he'd say when, as a young beat reporter for The New York Post, I would call late at night, fishing for material. He knew desperation when he smelled it.</p>
        <p>Even when the aforementioned knuckleheads deserved public scorn, Holzman resisted. When they sent him to his permanent retirement after the 1981-82 season, he answered a request to talk about the season's saboteurs by saying, ''Maybe another time.'' But with perfect comic timing, he suggested we not hold our breath.</p>
        <p>Remember when the Knicks hired Brown last summer, and so much was made of his coming home to embrace the Holzman legacy? That day, I pointed out that Brown -- if only stylistically -- was actually the anti-Red.</p>
        <p>Holzman was a Madison Square Garden lifer because he was religiously tight-lipped, a classic backroom operator. As for Brown, it was not terribly difficult to foresee a stormy first season, given the state of the team and the emotions he has always worn on those well-starched sleeves.</p>
        <p>The best-dressed man in the house has never been the prototypical corporate animal. Or as Brown said yesterday, as he explained his motivation for engaging Marbury in an entertaining but embarrassing spitball fight this week, ''You ask me a question, I try to answer it honestly.''</p>
        <p>That simple? Perhaps in the N.F.L., where contracts are not guaranteed. In the N.B.A., where the vested and empowered player roams, the long-term fallout from such a feud isn't likely to make a bad situation such as this one any better, only worse.</p>
        <p>''I regret what's happened, but it's over,'' Brown said.</p>
        <p>Not likely. As détentes go, the one declared yesterday by Brown and to a lesser extent by Marbury sounded flimsier than a single-digit Knicks lead in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>Marbury seemed to think that Brown, who initiated the dialogue before practice, was more interested in letting him know who's boss. He said Brown played his ''juice card,'' informing him that ''he could do whatever he wants with the franchise,'' while conceding that Brown did say it wasn't his intention to trade him.</p>
        <p>Did Marbury believe Brown? ''I have no comment to that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Brown then said he also told Marbury he was pleased that Marbury didn't sulk when benched with the rest of the starters for the climax of the Knicks' victory over Atlanta on Wednesday night. But he cautioned reporters against characterizing the talk as a significant meeting to clear the air.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't real long,'' Brown said. ''Thirty seconds.''</p>
        <p>The Israelis and the Palestinians can hold the occasional summit, but half a minute is the best Brown and Marbury can do after days of unrest? Sounds like coach and point guard have reached their own existential impasse, in the middle of which will be the Garden chairman, James L. Dolan, the team president, Isiah Thomas, and the frustrated Knicks fans.</p>
        <p>See, Marbury's juice is the $60 million owed him over the next three years, which explains his playful demeanor yesterday and his intrepid statement that while Brown ''made me aware of what he can do, that didn't scare me at all.''</p>
        <p>It's possible that Brown, given his combative history, just needed a good shot of adversarial stimulation as he and the Knicks stagger through this god-awful season. Or perhaps his eagerness to take on Marbury was a message for Marbury's organizational ally, the ever-invisible Thomas, that his man must go. Ultimately, it was no more for the benefit of the team than were Marbury's Starbury delusions that set Brown off in the first place.</p>
        <p>If Brown has reached the conclusion that he cannot co-exist with Marbury -- and why wouldn't he have? -- how did this week's worth of headlines in the league's largest news media market help the already scant chance of unloading him?</p>
        <p>The last thing that a team with overpaid, underachieving players needs to do is broadcast its deficiencies, amplify its failures. The storms over the Garden have only dampened the chance for change, for Brown to get more players he can live and win with.</p>
        <p>Sometimes a coach has to suffer in silence for the sake of the long-term plan. Coincidentally, the Knicks had one not long ago who knew that. His name was Lenny Wilkens, also Brooklyn-bred, who coached Marbury and the Knicks for 81 games, and won 40. By this season's standards, that's a winning percentage to dream of.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: hjaraton@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
