<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Antarctica</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="361731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF133AF934A25755C0A966958260" item-length="418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Antarctica</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor: Magazine and newspaper articles plus TV programs have decried the impact of tourism on Antarctica. Having just completed a cruise on the Illiria to that area, the following observations are offered to contradict many erroneous allegations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor: Magazine and newspaper articles plus TV programs have decried the impact of tourism on Antarctica. Having just completed a cruise on the Illiria to that area, the following observations are offered to contradict many erroneous allegations.</p>
        <p>To the Editor: Magazine and newspaper articles plus TV programs have decried the impact of tourism on Antarctica. Having just completed a cruise on the Illiria to that area, the following observations are offered to contradict many erroneous allegations.</p>
        <p>First, it is said that tourists injure the Antarctic ecosystems and interfere with plant and animal life. This is simply not true. Prior to arriving at our destination, we passengers, accompanied and enlightened by seven naturalists, were indoctrinated again and again on preservation of the environment. We were instructed not to step on moss, which may take 200 years to regenerate. We all kept a respectful distance from the thousands of penguins and many seals that we saw. Closeup photos were easily obtainable with our telephoto lenses. On the contrary, curious penguins approached closely to us, rather than the reverse.</p>
        <p>We were advised to ''take nothing, leave nothing,'' an injunction all of us diligently obeyed. The 2,500 to 3,500 tourists that visit Antarctica each year are a minute number compared to the millions who visit the other six continents.</p>
        <p>It is also alleged that tourists interfere with the research activities of scientists at the stations they visit. Again, nothing could be further from the truth. Scientific research is done by high-tech monitoring systems, studying weather, ozone depletion, etc., and data are collected by pushing a button to obtain a computer readout. Moreover, like an army, each research station requires a large support group: port captains, air travel personnel, construction and maintenance workers, cooks, health workers, et al. Whenever we visited these stations we were greeted hospitably, offered refreshments, and often efforts were made to sell us souvenirs, payable only with American dollars.</p>
        <p>The fact is, most of these research station people are young, far from home and lonely. They were only too happy to see, converse and visit with a group of new faces. Again, we were all respectful of their endeavors and entered their quarters only when invited.</p>
        <p>Finally, a visit to any one of the abandoned stations reveals a mass of left-behind garbage, trash, old rusting oil barrels, construction detritus, boat and airplane ruins and other residue that have a far worse impact on the Antarctic environment than we tourists could ever make.</p>
        <p>In fact, all of us came away with a heightened awareness of the earth's environment.</p>
        <p>ROWLAND D. GOODMAN, 2d, M.D.</p>
        <p>Livingston, N.J.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
