<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JUST PLAIN FOLK: THE ART OF EVERYDAY OBJECTS</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="361691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CERAMICS AND POTTERY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICA HURRAH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REIF, RITA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COHEN, BARRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ceramics and Pottery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DA163AF934A25755C0A966958260" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JUST PLAIN FOLK: THE ART OF EVERYDAY OBJECTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RITA REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REIF, RITA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Barry Cohen's 30-year-long involvement with American 19th-century folk art was reflected in the artworks he constructed and the artifacts he collected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Barry Cohen's 30-year-long involvement with American 19th-century folk art was reflected in the artworks he constructed and the artifacts he collected.</p>
        <p>Barry Cohen's 30-year-long involvement with American 19th-century folk art was reflected in the artworks he constructed and the artifacts he collected.</p>
        <p>The artist's boxed constructions, which were exhibited in eight one-man shows between 1970 and 1989 at the Allan Stone Gallery in Manhattan, combine painted wood and metal toys, small carvings, miniature houses and assortments of curious objects.</p>
        <p>At Mr. Cohen's death, on Jan. 1 at the age of 55, his folk-art collection numbered 248 objects - toys, painted furniture, 19th-century ceramics, weather vanes, trade signs, game boards, decorated furniture, silhouettes, watercolors and paintings. The most important work, Edward Hicks's ''Peaceable Kingdom'' from about 1838, is one of 60 known versions of this folk-art classic.</p>
        <p>The collection, which he kept at his apartment in Greenwich Village in Manhattan, was sold by the executors in April for about $2 million to two New York folk-art dealers - David A. Schorsch, a private dealer, and America Hurrah, the gallery of Kate and Joel Kopp, at 766 Madison Avenue (at 66th Street). Mr. Schorsch and the Kopps are in the process of selling the collection at exhibitions and antiques fairs, with the help of a 102-page catalogue ($32).</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen's ceramic holdings - 36 boldly patterned stoneware and redware vessels - are on view at America Hurrah until July 6. The artist's eye for superb and offbeat decorated ceramics was documented in a 1975 exhibition of 50 platters, jugs, vases and bowls held at the Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Folk Art Center in Williamsburg, Va.</p>
        <p>Most of what was shown in Williamsburg remained in Mr. Cohen's collection. Among the most unusual of the pieces is a tall jug incised with a robust American eagle, its shield-shaped breast decorated with a Masonic symbol, its claws clutching an American flag and a sheaf of arrows. The choicest of the smaller works retained by the artist is an eight-inch-long pig-shaped flask from the 1880's, incised with a railroad map, a souvenir of travel a century ago.</p>
        <p>Some ceramics were later sold and several additions were made to the collection. One such acquisition is a redware prize - a Connecticut dish emblazoned in script with the words ''Day's Pottery.'' This salad-sized plate was made about 1825 by the Rev. Absolom Day, a potter, farmer and itinerant Methodist minister from Norwalk. Possibly the most important addition since 1975 was a stoneware punch bowl from 1811 attributed to John Crolius Jr. of New York City.</p>
        <p>Incised in cobalt blue with the name of its original owner, Elizabeth Crane, and with leaves and flowers in an exuberantly swirled pattern, the vessel is a tour de force of thinly potted, salt-glazed stoneware, at 15 inches in diameter one of the largest of the genre. The punch bowl was acquired at a Sotheby's auction in 1978 for $12,500, then the record for an American folk-art ceramic. The price at the show is $200,000. Mr. Schorsch and the Kopps said that Mr. Cohen's richly detailed ceramics are memorable for the intricacy of the painted or figural decoration. Two arresting stoneware jugs by Wallace Kirkpatrick of Anna, Ill., are enlivened by snakes that form the handles, images inspired both by the potter's collection of snakes and his views of the evils of drink and its association with political corruption. One jug, from 1862, combines snakes slithering in and out of the surface of the bottle with Union soldiers toasting and singing. The other is covered with snakes and includes a map of the Arkansas, Mississippi and Ohio Rivers.</p>
        <p>The rarest object in the exhibition is an apple-shaped cider cooler, a redware precursor of Pop Art more than 16 inches tall. The story of how Mr. Cohen acquired the vessel, as told by an executor of the estate, Gerald Kornblau, a New York folk-art dealer, reveals something about this stubbornly persuasive man.</p>
        <p>''He came to dinner and saw the apple, which I had earmarked for another collector,'' Mr. Kornblau said. '' 'I've got to have it,' Barry insisted, refusing to have dinner until I quoted him a price. When I did, he said, 'It's mine.' '' Mr. Kornblau did not disclose what Mr. Cohen paid but said it was far less than the price in the show - $17,500.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Cohen admired in the ceramic apple was the rich patina of its matte finish and the realistic modeling of the yellow and red surface. ''It just looks like an apple freshly picked off a tree, with a piece of twig and green leaf still attached,'' Mr. Kornblau said. The passion Mr. Cohen showed for objects was primary. ''With limited funds he managed to amass a collection of the finest material by buying one good piece and trading it up for another, better object,'' Mr. Kornblau said.</p>
        <p>The artist's constructions reflected his collecting, said his dealer, Allan Stone. ''He would create environments that had the feeling of primordial folk art,'' he said. ''Barry's things were open accumulations of things that invited you to see the subtle differences between objects. If he had been the curator of a folk-art museum, it would have had some collection.'' The remainder of Mr. Cohen's collection is to be offered at two antiques fairs. The paintings, watercolors and trade signs are to be shown by Mr. Schorsch at the Fall Antiques Show, which takes place at the Pier in Manhattan from Oct. 18 to 21. The weather vanes and whirligigs are to be offered at the America Hurrah booth at the Winter Antiques Show next January.</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
