<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wrigley Isn't the Only Place Balls Are Going, Going, Gone</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="362011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DE1130F934A25755C0A966958260" item-length="1632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wrigley Isn't the Only Place Balls Are Going, Going, Gone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Whitey Herzog, the outspoken manager of the St. Louis Cardinals, noted the deluge of runs that the Mets and the Chicago Cubs produced at Wrigley Field last week - 80 in four games - and didn't hide his disdain for the quaint old park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Whitey Herzog, the outspoken manager of the St. Louis Cardinals, noted the deluge of runs that the Mets and the Chicago Cubs produced at Wrigley Field last week - 80 in four games - and didn't hide his disdain for the quaint old park.</p>
        <p>Whitey Herzog, the outspoken manager of the St. Louis Cardinals, noted the deluge of runs that the Mets and the Chicago Cubs produced at Wrigley Field last week - 80 in four games - and didn't hide his disdain for the quaint old park.</p>
        <p>''With that wind blowing out, that ball park is a joke,'' Herzog said. ''I still can't understand why people say 'beautiful Wrigley Field.' Every park that ever looked like that has been razed.''</p>
        <p>Despite Herzog's feelings, Wrigley Field, 76 years old and the site of this year's All-Star Game, cannot be singled out as the culprit and cause of an orgy of runs. The National League is scoring runs in abundant numbers everywhere this season.</p>
        <p>The numbers entering the weekend speak succinctly for the most stunning development in the first half of the season:</p>
        <p>* The National League batting average, compared with the average for a corresponding period last year, is up from .243 to .262. Pittsburgh's average is up 37 points, Philadelphia's 32, San Diego's 30. Only St. Louis and Houston have had their averages drop.</p>
        <p>* The number of runs is up more than one a game, from 2,785, or 7.78 a game, to 3,133, or 8.83 a game. Five teams, including San Francisco at 304, have scored more runs than the 255 that led a year ago.</p>
        <p>* Home runs have increased by 27.6 percent, from 468 to 597. Last year, three teams had totals in the 50's, with the Giants' 57 the No. 1 total. This year, four teams have more than 57 home runs, with the Cubs and the Giants in the 60's and the Mets leading at 73, 20 more than their total at this time last year.</p>
        <p>* The league earned run average is 3.98 compared with 3.39 a year ago. Five teams have earned run averages over 4.00, including one (Atlanta) over 5.00. Last year, only Philadelphia's was higher than 3.85. The e.r.a.'s of five teams have soared by more than a run.</p>
        <p>The drastic difference can also be seen in the number of high-scoring games. Last year at this time, teams had scored in double figures 30 times; this season that number is 51. San Diego has scored 10 or more runs six times; five other teams have reached that height five times each.</p>
        <p>A recent eight-day period produced these results: Giants 23, Braves 8; Mets 19, Cubs 8; Expos 18, Cardinals 2; Mets 15, Cubs 10; Cubs 15, Phillies 2; Reds 13, Braves 4; Cardinals 12, Phillies 11; Padres 12, Dodgers 6.</p>
        <p>''It's just unbelievable,'' said Jim Frey, the Cubs' general manager. ''There's one or two of those blowouts a day. People now are saying the ball's alive, but they say that every year.''</p>
        <p>If the ball is livelier, it's livelier only in the National League. American League teams have actually scored fewer runs (8.66 a game to 8.62) and have a lower batting average (.260 to .256).</p>
        <p>''Since the offensive production had been down in the National League for a few years, these clubs went out and beefed up the attack,'' said Lou Piniella, who as manager of the Cincinnati Reds is a newcomer to the league.</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles Dodgers were one club that tried to bolster its offense, and they have succeeded, raising their batting average 28 points, practically doubling their home run output and increasing their run production by one a game. At the same time, however, their earned run average has skyrocketed by more than a run a game.</p>
        <p>''There have been a lot of long home runs and a lot of games where there have been a lot of home runs,'' Fred Claire, the Dodgers' general manager, said, speaking generally. ''I put a lot of that on the quality of the pitching. Pitching is at such a premium at the major league level and the Triple-A level. There's a scarcity.'' No one knows for certain what's behind the leaguewide eruption. Mediocre pitching and the shortened spring training were most often cited as the possible reasons.</p>
        <p>''I think this is another one of those questions that no one has a real answer for,'' Frey said. ''A lot of this stuff makes for good barroom conversation, but I'll be darned if I know the answer.''</p>
        <p>But then Frey suggested the pitching theory.</p>
        <p>''It appears that the second-line pitching isn't as strong this year,'' the Cubs' general manager said. ''Maybe there is a shortage in the bullpens.''</p>
        <p>Jim Leyland, the Pittsburgh manager, noted the absence, either for the entire season or part, of such pitchers as Orel Hershiser, Jay Howell and Todd Worrell, and the departure of such pitchers as Mark Davis to the other league.</p>
        <p>''It filters down,'' Leyland said. ''Suppose you have a guy in your bullpen and all of a sudden somebody goes down and now that guy is starting and you're bringing up someone from Triple A. The depth isn't as good.''</p>
        <p>Leyland also raised the spring training theory.</p>
        <p>''I think a lot of pitchers had gotten themselves in shape, then the thing hit and a lot of them probably got out of shape,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Claire said he thought that the starting pitchers didn't work the number of spring innings they normally would. ''In my view,'' he said, ''what happens is the vulnerability of a club's middle relief pitching is exposed. And once it is exposed, the batters take advantage of it.''</p>
        <p>Even Herzog subscribed to the theory of the effect the abbreviated spring training might have had on pitching. ''I don't think the pitching was as sharp,'' the Cardinals' manager said. ''You see a lot of big-name pitchers who probably didn't go down early and work as hard are struggling.''</p>
        <p>Frey, on the other hand, scoffed at any theory related to spring training.</p>
        <p>''We've played 60 games,'' he said. ''I hope people aren't still looking for an excuse of a shortened spring training. Some people wore that out a lot longer than I would have. I didn't take much stock in that after the first 15 games. After the first three starts for the starters and after the first two weeks of playing, I can't imagine that anyone would have an excuse.''</p>
        <p>Winfield Heating Up</p>
        <p>Because Bucky Dent acknowledged that he decided to platoon Dave Winfield and he urged his trade, the Yankees can make him the scapegoat for Winfield's comeback with the California Angels.</p>
        <p>Just as he did with the Yankees, Winfield started slowly with the Angels. However in the six games before Friday night's, Winfield batted .409 (9 for 22) with 4 home runs and 8 runs batted in. That's the kind of spurt the Yankees were too impatient to wait for.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, they have Claudell Washington, the man Dent used to platoon with Winfield. Washington is hitting .163 with the Yankees with no home runs and 6 r.b.i. In just about the same number of times at bat with the Angels (Winfield 85, Washington 80), Winfield has a .247 average, 6 home runs and 13 r.b.i.</p>
        <p>Did someone say panic move?</p>
        <p>The Wrong Direction</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, when the Yankees were champions or legitimate contenders for the championship, opposing teams would dredge up every left-handed pitcher they could find to face the left-dominated array of sluggers.</p>
        <p>If a team didn't have a rookie left-hander or a journeyman left-hander or an aging left-hander rusting away in an obscure corner of the bullpen, it would scour its minor league system, from Class AAA to Class A, to locate a left-hander whom it could summon for a one-day visit to the major leagues and a start against the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Who could forget, for example, the time in 1977 that the California Angels brought Fred Kuhaulua to Yankee Stadium for his first -and only - start of the season? That same season, Pablo Torrealba of Oakland started against the Yankees twice. Mike Willis of Toronto pitched in 43 games that year but started only 3 times. One was against the Yankees. The following season Willis made 2 starts in 44 appearances, both against the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Where have all the left-handers gone? The 1990 Yankees have not been good for their careers. The Yankees no longer pose a serious threat left-handed. Defying history, logic and the reality of Yankee Stadium, they have become a right-handed team. Neutralize the left-handed Don Mattingly, and the Yankees have great difficulty beating right-handers.</p>
        <p>The right-handed hitting Jesse Barfield leads the team in home runs and runs batted in, but he is no force against right-handed pitchers. Against left-handers, entering last night's game, Barfield had a .356 batting average, 6 home runs and 13 r.b.i. in 45 times at bat. Against right-handers, he was hitting .222 with 5 home runs and 20 r.b.i. in 135 times at bat.</p>
        <p>It should come as no surprise, then, that in games that right-handers have started against them the Yankees have won 13 and lost 30. In games left-handers have started, they have 8 victories and 7 defeats.</p>
        <p>The Struggles of Samuel</p>
        <p>Juan Samuel, who has been shunted from team to team and position to position, not long ago showed renewed signs that he could still hit. After batting .183, hitting 1 home run and driving in 4 runs in the Dodgers' first 40 games, Samuel had a 12-game spree in which he batted .422, hit 3 home runs and knocked in 11 runs. In nine games since then, however, he has 1 hit in 34 times at bat, leaving his average at .207.</p>
        <p>A TALE OF TWO SEASONs</p>
        <p>Here is a comparison of National League team batting averages and earned run averages for this season and a corresponding period last season (358 games last year, 355 this year, through Thursday night):</p>
        <p>$</p>
        <p>Team</p>
        <p>'89 BA</p>
        <p>'90 BA</p>
        <p>'89 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>90E.R.A.</p>
        <p>Braves</p>
        <p>.239</p>
        <p>.245</p>
        <p>3.39</p>
        <p>5.24</p>
        <p>Cubs</p>
        <p>.249</p>
        <p>.274</p>
        <p>3.12</p>
        <p>4.73</p>
        <p>Reds</p>
        <p>.256</p>
        <p>.273</p>
        <p>3.39</p>
        <p>3.03</p>
        <p>Astros</p>
        <p>.241</p>
        <p>.239</p>
        <p>3.23</p>
        <p>3.81</p>
        <p>Dodgers</p>
        <p>.227</p>
        <p>.255</p>
        <p>2.77</p>
        <p>3.94</p>
        <p>Expos</p>
        <p>.245</p>
        <p>.260</p>
        <p>3.85</p>
        <p>3.10</p>
        <p>Mets</p>
        <p>.234</p>
        <p>.257</p>
        <p>3.18</p>
        <p>3.74</p>
        <p>Phillies</p>
        <p>.238</p>
        <p>.270</p>
        <p>4.45</p>
        <p>4.33</p>
        <p>Pirates</p>
        <p>.241</p>
        <p>.278</p>
        <p>3.83</p>
        <p>3.45</p>
        <p>Cardinals</p>
        <p>.250</p>
        <p>.244</p>
        <p>3.13</p>
        <p>4.26</p>
        <p>Padres</p>
        <p>.244</p>
        <p>.274</p>
        <p>3.48</p>
        <p>3.91</p>
        <p>Giants</p>
        <p>.252</p>
        <p>.271</p>
        <p>2.95</p>
        <p>4.18</p>
        <p>League</p>
        <p>.243</p>
        <p>.262</p>
        <p>3.39</p>
        <p>3.98</p>
        <p>NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
