<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yeltsin's Nominee, Besieged, Is Not Without Allies</title>
    <meta content="12RUSS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1009293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeltsin, Boris N (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kiriyenko, Sergei N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEED6133DF931A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="1737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yeltsin's Nominee, Besieged, Is Not Without Allies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, April 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>35-year-old Sergei Kiriyenko, Pres Boris Yeltsin's besieged nominee for Prime Minister, has shown himself to be adept politician in brief period on national stage; his liabilities, mainly his youth and limited Government experience, are also his potential strengths since he has not been in Government long enough to make many enemies; he may be leader who can pursue market-economy measures without debilitating ideological battles that hobbled some predecessors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As workers took to the streets this week to demonstrate against the Government's chronic inability to pay back wages, a young Kremlin official huddled with labor leaders to defuse the protest.</p>
        <p>Even though Moscow has repeatedly failed to make good on its promises to pay the wages, the labor leaders agreed to give it yet another chance. ''Kiriyenko has given us hope,'' said Aleksei Surikov, the deputy head of the National Federation of Independent Trade Unions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As workers took to the streets this week to demonstrate against the Government's chronic inability to pay back wages, a young Kremlin official huddled with labor leaders to defuse the protest.</p>
        <p>Even though Moscow has repeatedly failed to make good on its promises to pay the wages, the labor leaders agreed to give it yet another chance. ''Kiriyenko has given us hope,'' said Aleksei Surikov, the deputy head of the National Federation of Independent Trade Unions.</p>
        <p>In the two weeks since President Boris N. Yeltsin stunned the nation by dismissing his Cabinet and nominating the 35-year-old Sergei N. Kiriyenko for Prime Minister, Mr. Kiriyenko has run into a buzz saw of criticism.</p>
        <p>The Communist opposition has portrayed the Government shake-up as a grave political crisis. Some Western analysts have questioned whether Mr. Yeltsin is mentally competent to govern.</p>
        <p>But in the brief period that Mr. Kiriyenko has been on the national stage, he has shown himself to be an adept politician.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the appointment is an enormous gamble. Mr. Kiriyenko's  government experience is limited to 11 months at Russia's Energy Ministry. But his liabilities -- his youth and limited Government experience -- are also his potential strengths.</p>
        <p>Russia has a surfeit of holdovers from the Soviet era, like former Prime Minister Viktor S. Chernomyrdin, who talk about change but are mired in the old ways.</p>
        <p>It has bold reformers, like Anatoly B. Chubais, a former Kremlin aide  whose every move seemed to stir up opposition from Communists and powerful financial interests.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kiriyenko is different. Unlike Mr. Chernomyrdin, he has made his mark as a young man in the brash new world of Russian capitalism. Unlike Mr. Chubais, he has not been in Government long enough to make a lot of enemies, and he eschews ideological battles.</p>
        <p>In short, Mr. Kiriyenko may be a leader who can quietly hammer away at changing the tax system, tightening controls over powerful monopolies and pursing other market-economy measures without the debilitating ideological battles that hobbled some of his predecessors.</p>
        <p>His appointment will be all the more important if, as Mr. Yeltsin has suggested, it signals a generational shift that propels other young politicians to the top echelons of power.</p>
        <p>The lower house of Parliament, as expected, rejected Mr. Kiriyenko's nomination. But that was just part of the horse-trading between Mr. Yeltsin and the Communist-dominated opposition, which wants to demonstrate that it is still an important political force and obtain a few posts in the new line-up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin resubmitted the nomination, and most analysts expect the process to end in Mr. Kiriyenko's approval as Prime Minister. But he could be handicapped if the price of the Parliament's consent is too high and the new Government is seeded with members of the opposition.</p>
        <p>So far Mr. Kiriyenko has been his own best advocate. He has not boasted about Government accomplishments, has patiently stroked his critics and has even appropriated some of their sound bites.</p>
        <p>The newspaper Nezavisimaya Gazeta described his initial program, which he outlined Tuesday, as ''truly apolitical'' and devoid of an ''ideological lining,'' a rarity in Russia's superheated political scene.</p>
        <p>Regional leaders have been heartened by Mr. Kiriyenko's talk about reapportioning tax revenues so the provinces get more.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiriyenko has tried to placate the Communists by emphasizing the need to struggle against poverty. Unlike other Yeltsin aides, he has not gone around boasting that Russia is  firmly embarked on the path of economic growth.</p>
        <p>Vladimir V. Semago, a senior Communist member of Parliament, said in a interview that he had met with Mr. Kiriyenko and considered him to be a politician in the tradition of Western European social democrats. ''I could see it in his eyes,'' said Mr. Semago, who added that he planned to support him.</p>
        <p>But economic reformers, like Mr. Chubais and Yegor T. Gaidar, consider Mr. Kiriyenko to be one of their own. And a review of Mr. Kiriyenko's career suggests that he has internalized the principles of the market economy.</p>
        <p>Born in the Black Sea town of Sukhumi, Mr. Kiriyenko, who married his childhood sweetheart, Maria, and has two children, got his start in the Volga River city of Nizhny Novgorod, which was called Gorky in Soviet times. His father was Jewish, but he adopted his mother's Ukrainian name, an effort to deal with the anti-Semitism of Soviet times.</p>
        <p>As a young man, he was studious and punched all the right tickets. He studied in the department of shipbuilding at the Gorky Institute of Water Transport Engineers, where his father headed the Department of Scientific Communism. After military service, he worked as a foreman at the Krasnoye Sormovo shipyard.</p>
        <p>He also joined the Komsomol, the  Communist youth organization, and from 1990 to 1992 was second secretary of the its regional branch. Mr. Kiriyenko has kept his Communist Party membership card as a kind of memento of those times, as have many Russians who are reluctant to write off years of their life as a waste.</p>
        <p>But unlike today's Communists, Mr. Kiriyenko was quick to take advantage of Russia's lurch toward the market. After a course on finance in Moscow, he served as chairman of a Nizhny Novgorod bank. He later became president of the Norsi oil refinery, one of the largest in Russia.</p>
        <p>His colleagues in Nizhny Novgorod dubbed him ''the little computer'' because of his organizational skills and attention to detail. One of his hobbies, however, is martial arts.</p>
        <p>''He had a reputation as a good manager and took a systematic approach,'' said Dmitry I. Bednyakov, a Nizhny Novgorod lawyer. ''Like every person he has drawbacks. His main one is his age and lack of experience.''</p>
        <p>[Dressed in blue jeans and a sweater vest, Mr. Kiriyenko made an informal appearance, with his wife and two children, on an interview program broadcast Saturday night on NTV, Russia's private television channel.</p>
        <p>[As he described his working style and his hobbies, he came across as a cool-headed, tough-minded, ideologically neutral manager, a type increasingly familiar in Russia these days. In his case, he said, he felt no tug for the luxury goods that are often the mark of Russia's new rich. ''I like what I like,'' he said, pulling at the collar of his plaid shirt. ''I don't pay any attention to the label.'']</p>
        <p>While Mr. Kiriyenko has not been in Government long, his experience is hardly trivial.</p>
        <p>After Boris Y. Nemtsov left his governor's post in the Nizhny Novgorod region to work as a top Kremlin aide, Mr. Kiriyenko was also invited to work in Moscow.</p>
        <p>He was appointed First Deputy Minister of Energy in May 1997. (Mr. Nemtsov initially served as minister, in addition to other tasks.)</p>
        <p>In a nation rich in oil and natural energy, the ministry is a powerful agency. And as Mr. Nemtsov was preoccupied with giving interviews to the press and tackling social issues like housing reform, Mr. Kiriyenko was the de facto minister.</p>
        <p>In November, Mr. Kiriyenko was officially appointed Minister of Fuel and Energy. He helped set the terms of the coming auction of the Rosneft state oil company and negotiated with Americans on oil projects in Russia, among other complex issues.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Yeltsin dies in office, the Prime Minister becomes President for three months while an election is organized.</p>
        <p>Some people blanch at the prospect of a neophyte's finger on the nuclear button, but in shaking up his Government Mr. Yeltsin left his national security team intact, retaining his Foreign Minister, Defense Minister and national security adviser.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiriyenko, who so far is not giving interviews to Western reporters, has said he made enough money as a businessman that he can afford to serve in government. He has a reputation for independence and is not believed to be the tool of any of Russia's business interests.</p>
        <p>Not that the Russian bankers and financiers have not tried.</p>
        <p>''I have already come across it,'' Mr. Kiriyenko told the Russian press. ''A careful offer of 'help' comes from somewhere. I ignore it. Then the next day some newspaper changes its tone.''</p>
        <p>Certainly, Boris A. Berezovsky, the powerful tycoon, does not control him. The terms of the Rosneft auction that Mr. Kiriyenko shaped were decidedly not in Mr. Berezovksy's favor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berezovksy recently began a media campaign against Mr. Yeltsin's Government shake-up and is backing the ousted Mr. Chernomyrdin, who has declared himself a candidate for the 2000 presidential election.</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Kiriyenko's critics question whether he has the strength to be his own man. They say he may turn out to be nothing more than a caretaker while the real decisions are made by Mr. Yeltsin, his daughter Tatyana Dyachenko and whatever group of financiers happens to be in favor at the moment. Before he was named Prime Minister he had met with Mr. Yeltsin only twice.</p>
        <p>''He isn't a political person,'' complained Grigory A. Yavlinsky, the head of the liberal Yabloko party. ''He doesn't represent any political forces. He is the technical executor of whatever the President orders him to do.''</p>
        <p>Others say that the new Government may turn out to be too much of a hodgepodge to accomplish much.</p>
        <p>''It will have representatives from very different political powers, financial powers, elite groups and clans,'' said Nikolai Petrov of the Carnegie Endowment. ''So to expect from it some realistic serious steps in the realm of economics will not be realistic.''</p>
        <p>But many reformers inside and outside of the Government believe that they may have found a new standard-bearer who may make headway as long as speaks quietly in  nonconfrontational tones.</p>
        <p>''The public understands what must be done,'' Mr. Kiriyenko said this week in a perfect example of his understated call to arms. ''The problem is how to do it, what mechanisms and instruments.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
