<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON THE TOWNS</title>
    <meta content="12TOWN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1009153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EED9143DF931A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="9307" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON THE TOWNS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An opinionated guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. To submit items for consideration, write to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036, or send a fax to (212) 556-7219.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An opinionated guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. To submit items for consideration, write to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036, or send a fax to (212) 556-7219.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC COMMUNITY COLLEGE Jonathan Edwards, folk musician. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $12.50 to $25. Walter Edge Theater, 5100 Black Horse Pike, Mays Landing. (609) 343-4907.</p>
        <p>BELLEVILLE PUBLIC LIBRARY Essex County Cherry Blossom Jazz Concert. Saturday at 7 P.M. Free; reservations required. 221 Washington Avenue, Belleville. (973) 450-3434.</p>
        <p>BORDERS BOOKS AND MUSIC Jake Schwartz, classical guitarist. Today at 2 P.M. Free.  530 West Mount Pleasant Avenue, Livingston. (201) 535-9001.</p>
        <p>CAPE MAY JAZZ FESTIVAL 9th annual festival, featuring Oscar Brown Jr., Jimmy Bruno, Ravi Coltrane, Terell Stafford and others. Friday: Jazz Vespers with the Michael Pedecin Jr. Quartet, 7:30 P.M. at the First Presbyterian Church; Oscar Brown Jr. with the Robin VanDuzee Quartet, 9 and 11 P.M. at the Rusty Nail; Tim Lekan Trio with Gina Roche, 9 P.M. at the Cafe at Congress Hall; George Rabbai with the Denis DiBlasio Quartet, 9 P.M. at Carney's in the main room; Lennie Roberts Quartet, 9 P.M. at Carney's; Tim Eyermann and the East Coast Offering, 9 P.M. at the Marquis de Lafayette Hotel. Saturday: Jam Session featuring more than 24 musicians, 1 to 4 P.M. at Carney's; Cape May County Youth All-Star Jazz Band, 7:30 P.M. at the First Presbyterian Church; Oscar Brown Jr. with the Robin VanDuzee Quartet, 7:30 and 10 P.M. at the Rusty Nail; Cecil Bridgewater with the Brian Trainor Quartet, 9 P.M. at the Cafe at Congress Hall; Jimmy Bruno with the Denis BiBlasio Quartet, 9 P.M. at Carney's; Ravi Coltrane with the Ralph Peterson Fotet, 9 P.M. at Carney's; Jeanne Brooks with the Bootsie Barnes Quartet, 9 P.M. at the Marquis de Lafayette Hotel; Tim Eyermann and the East Coast Offering, 9 P.M. at the Marquis de Lafayette Hotel; Frank Bey Sextet, 9 P.M.the at Grand Hotel Penthouse Ballroom. Sunday: Jazz and Gospel by the Fred Hughes Trio with Juanita Williams and Tim Eyermann, 11 A.M. to 2 P.M. at Carney's; jazz session featuring Barbara Walker and local musicians, 1 to 5 P.M. at the Rusty Nail. Tickets: $60 for weekend pass; $15 for Friday night events; $25 for Saturday night events; $15 for Saturday jam session; $15 for each event on Sunday. (609) 884-7277.</p>
        <p>CENTENARY PERFORMING ARTS GUILD ''Sacred Music, Sacred Dance,'' singers of the Drepung Loseling Monestery. Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 5 P.M. Tickets: $20; $15 for children. Little Theater, 400 Jefferson Street, Hackettstown. (908) 979-0900.</p>
        <p>CHATHAM HIGH SCHOOL AUDITORIUM The Manhattan Rhythm Kings present songs from the 1920's through the 1940's. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $26; $5 for students. 255 Lafayette Avenue, Chatham. (908) 766-7555.</p>
        <p>CHRIST CHURCH ''Channel Crossings,'' Baroque music. Wednesday at 12:15 P.M. Free. 5 Paterson Street, New Brunswick.  (732) 545-6262.</p>
        <p>CLUB BENE Dick Dale. Thursday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $17.50. Dem Brooklyn Bums and the Crescent City Maulers, swing bands. Friday at 9 P.M. Tickets: $10. Route 35, Sayreville. (732) 727-3000.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY THEATER OF MORRISTOWN Doc Severinsen and His Big Band. Thursday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $30 to $45. The New Philharmonic of New Jersey presents ''Great Gershwin.'' Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $15 to $32. 100 South Street, Morristown.  (201) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>FAIRLEIGH DICKINSON UNIVERSITY Violetta Dupont vocal competition. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $12. Lenfell Hall, 285 Madison Avenue, Madison. (973) 443-8620.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS Assaff Weisman, pianist, presented by the Juilliard Music Series. Thursday at 7 P.M. Tickets: $9 to $18. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>JERSEY CITY STATE COLLEGE Symphony of Winds and Percussion. Tuesday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10; $5 for students and the elderly. Ingalls Recital Hall, Rossey Hall, 2039 Kennedy Boulevard, Jersey City. (201) 200-3151.</p>
        <p>MIDLAND PARK BISTRO Richard Reiter Jazz Quartet. Through April. Fridays, 8 to 11 P.M. $10 minimum. 41 Central Avenue, Midland Park. (201) 445-4141.</p>
        <p>MINE STREET COFFEEHOUSE Carol Thompson, harpist. Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $4. First Reformed Church, Neilson and Bayard Streets, New Brunswick. (732) 828-1945.</p>
        <p>MINSTREL COFFEEHOUSE Hugh Blumenfeld and Acoustic Food Chain. Friday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $5. 190 Lord Stirling Road, Basking Ridge. (908) 766-2489 or (973) 335-9489.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR HIGH SCHOOL COMMUNITY AUDITORIUM Robert White, tenor. Next Sunday at 3 P.M. Tickets: $20 to $36. Park and Chestnut Streets, Montclair. (973) 744-6770.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR KIMBERLEY ACADEMY THEATER Catie Curtis, folk musician. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $22. 201 Valley Road, Montclair. (973) 744-1717.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY PERFORMING ARTS CENTER New Jersey Symphony Orchestra's finalists in the Young Artist Auditions. Friday at 8 P.M. Free; reservations required. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>OUTPOST IN THE BURBS Lucy Kaplansky, folk musician. Friday at 9 P.M. Tickets: $10. 40 South Fullerton Road, Montclair.  (973) 744-6560.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY CHAPEL Ensemble Corund, from Lucerne, Switzerland, presents ''Eros and Agape: Five Centuries of Love in Sacred Music.'' Tuesday at 8 P.M. Free. Mark Laubach, organist. Wednesday at 12:30 P.M. Free. William Street and Washington Road, Princeton. (609) 258-3654.</p>
        <p>RICHARDSON AUDITORIUM Mendelssohn's ''Elijah,'' performed by the Princeton University Glee Club with the Concerto Soloists of Philadelphia. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $12; $5 for Princeton University students. Alexander Hall, 126 Alexander Street, Princeton. (609) 258-5000.</p>
        <p>RIDGEWOOD UNITED METHODIST CHURCH The Orpheus Club Men's Chorus annual spring concert. Friday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 4 P.M. Tickets: $12; $10 for students and the elderly. 100 Dayton Street, Ridgewood. (201) 652-3590.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY Rutgers jazz groups. Thursday at 8 P.M. Free. Nicholas Music Center, George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7511.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY The Rutgers University Voorhees Choir's spring concert. Friday at 8 P.M. Free. Voorhees Chapel, Chapel Drive and George Street, Douglass Campus, New Brunswick. (732) 932-7511.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER Wynton Marsalis. Tuesday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $15 to $45. 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 249-5560.</p>
        <p>TAPLIN AUDITORIUM The Composers' Ensemble at Princeton presents the annual Generals Concert, featuring works of graduate students. Tuesday at 8 P.M. Free. Physics department annual recital. Saturday at 7:30 P.M. Free. Fine Hall, Princeton University. (609) 258-5000.</p>
        <p>TOMS RIVER HIGH SCHOOL NORTH The Garden State Philharmonic Orchestra. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $21 and $24.50; $8.50 and $10.50 for students. Old Freehold Road, Toms River. (732) 349-6277.</p>
        <p>TRIUMPH BREWING COMPANY Tom Fuller, singer and songwriter. Tomorrow at 9 P.M. Free. Joe Joe the Dog Face Boy, jazz band. Tuesday at 9 P.M. Free. Chain Smokers, rhthym and blues. Wednesday at 9 P.M. Free. 138 Nassau Street, Princeton. (609) 924-7855.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
        <p>BICKFORD THEATER ''Morning's at Seven,'' by Paul Osborn. Through April 26. Thursdays through Saturdays at 8 P.M.; Sundays at 2 P.M. Tickets: $21; $19 for the elderly; $7.50 to $18 for students. Morris Museum, 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (973) 538-8069.</p>
        <p>CAPE MAY CONVENTION HALL ''An Evening of Vaudeville,'' with juggling, magic and comedy. Tickets: $8. Beach Drive and Stockton Street, Cape May. (609) 884-5404.</p>
        <p>CLUB BENE The Amazing Kreskin. Saturday at 9 P.M. Tickets: $20. Route 35, Sayreville. (732) 727-3000.</p>
        <p>COUNTY COLLEGE OF MORRIS ''Joseph and the Amazing Technicolor Dreamcoat.'' Thursday through Friday, 8 P.M.; Saturday, 3 and 8 P.M. Tickets $12. Dragonetti Auditorium, 214 Center Grove Road, Randolph. (973) 328-5225.</p>
        <p>FELLOWSHIP THEATER ''Shoop Shoop Shoop Shoop,'' a play about young girls who want to become stars in the record business. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $15. 247 Broad Street, Red Bank. (732) 741-6190.</p>
        <p>GEORGE STREET PLAYHOUSE ''The Council of 30,'' Bob Clyman's play about child custody battles. Friday through Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 2 and 7 P.M. Through May 3. Tickets: $24 to $32. 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7717.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS Carrot Top, comedian. Wednesday at 8 P.M. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600.</p>
        <p>HUNTERDON HILLS PLAYHOUSE ''Romantic Comedy,'' by Bernard Slade. Through June 27. Exit 12 off Routes 78 and 22, Perryville. Show times and tickets: (800) 447-7313.</p>
        <p>KEAN COLLEGE Kean Dance Theater. Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $6; $5 for the elderly; $4 for students. Wilkins Theater, 1000 Morris Avenue, Union. (908) 527-2337.</p>
        <p>PARK THEATER ''The Passion Play.'' Through April 26. Saturdays and Sundays at 2 P.M. Tickets: $20. 560 32d Street, Union City. (201) 865-6980.</p>
        <p>PHOENIX STUDIO THEATER ''Godspell.'' Today at 4 P.M.; Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $12. 111 Monmouth Street, Red Bank. (732) 747-0014.</p>
        <p>PLAYWRIGHTS THEATER OF NEW JERSEY ''An Evening of Short Works,'' featuring Luigi Januzzi, Donna Wilshire, Okey Canfield Chenoweth and Bob Young. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $5; $3 for students. 33 Green Village Road, Madison. (973) 433-9125.</p>
        <p>RITZ THEATER ''Little Shop of Horrors.'' Through May 16. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $12 to $15. 915 White Horse Pike, Oaklyn.  (609) 858-5230.</p>
        <p>ROYALE THEATER ''The Fantasticks.'' Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $15. 42 Monmouth Street, Red Bank. (732) 219-0081.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY ''The Grapes of Wrath.'' Through April 26. Wednesdays through Saturdays at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16 and $18. Philip J. Levin Theater, George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7511.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY ''Danceplus April,'' choreographed by Paulette Sears, to music by Robert Benford. Thursday through Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $16. New Theater, George Street, New Brunswick. (732) 932-7511.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER ''Daughter of the Regiment,'' presented by the New York City Opera National Company. Thursday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $25 to $45. ''Forever Plaid,'' a parody of a 1950's singing group. Saturday at 3 and 8 P.M. Tickets: $16 to $32. 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7469.</p>
        <p>UNION COUNTY ARTS CENTER ''The Best Little Whorehouse in Texas.'' Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 3 P.M. Tickets: $17 to $24. 1601 Irving Street, Rahway.  (732) 499-8226.</p>
        <p>VILLAGERS THEATER ''Company.'' Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M.; next Sunday at 3 P.M. Tickets: $15 to $17. 475 DeMott Lane, Somerset. (732) 873-2710.</p>
        <p>WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER Comedy night, featuring Gary Greenberg, John McMenamin and Frank Giresi. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung.  (908) 753-0190</p>
        <p>MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES</p>
        <p>ALJIRA: A CENTER FOR CONTEMPORARY ART Small-scale paintings by Peter Homitzky. Paintings by Karen Sardisco. ''Lingua Franca,'' works by Portuguese photographers. All through April 24. Hours: Wednesday through Friday, noon to 5 P.M.; Saturday, noon to 4 P.M. 2 Washington Place, Newark. (201) 643-3594.</p>
        <p>AQUIFER ''The Pinelands: Nature and Magic.'' Through June. Hours: Saturdays and Sundays, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Thursdays 7 to 10 P.M.; other times by appointment. 700 West Bay Avenue, Barnegat. (609) 698-4120.</p>
        <p>ARTBUILDERS GALLERY ''Biblical Visions and Interpretations,'' drawings based on biblical writings. Through May 3. Hours: Fridays through Sundays, 2 to 7 P.M. 193 Montgomery Street, Jersey City. (201) 433-2682.</p>
        <p>BELSKIE MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE ''Amuse the Eye,'' photographs by Ralph Weber. Through May 1. Hours: Mondays and Wednesdays, 10 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Tuesdays, Thursdays, and Fridays, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 P.M. 280 High Street, Closter. (201) 768-0286.</p>
        <p>BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE ''Demons and Angels,'' paintings and works on paper by John Hultberg. Through May 3. ''Yielding to Delight,'' humorous sculptures by Mary Nicholas. Through May 10. Paintings by Gloria Ruiz Duzoglou. Through May 10. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 5 P.M. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248.</p>
        <p>HIRAM BLAUVELT ART MUSEUM ''Art and the Animal,'' a juried exhibition featuring 100 works by wildlife painters and sculptors. Through May 15. Hours: Wednesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 2 to 5 P.M. 705 Kinderkamack Road, Oradell. (201) 261-0012.</p>
        <p>CHAMOT GALLERY ''3D IT.'' Scuptures and paintings by Ruth Borgenicht, Iria and Christopher Johnson and Bonnie Maranz. Through April 26. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 3 P.M. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 610-1468.</p>
        <p>COOPER GALLERY ''Rhythm and Blues,'' new paintings by Cheryl Gross and Teri Richardson. Through Friday. Hours: Tuesday through Friday, noon to 7 P.M. 295 Grove Street, Jersey City. (201) 451-1074.</p>
        <p>DEY MANSION/WASHINGTON HEADQUARTERS MUSEUM Revolutionary War weapons, George Washington prints and maps of New Jersey. Through next Sunday. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 1 to 4 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 199 Totowa Road, Wayne. (973) 696-1776.</p>
        <p>THE EUROGALLERY Paintings and sculptures by Lazlo Ispanky. Through June 30. Hours: Wednesdays through Saturdays, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sundays, noon to 3 P.M. 37 West Broad Street, Hopewell. (609) 466-6885.</p>
        <p>EXTENSION GALLERY ''Atelier Members' Cast-Iron Sculpture Exhibition,'' featuring 34 artists. Through April 30. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 60 Ward Avenue Extension, Mercerville.  (609) 890-7777.</p>
        <p>FAIRLEIGH DICKINSON UNIVERSITY ''Fossil Icons,'' paintings by Tom Wagner. Through Friday. Hours: tomorrow through Friday, 9 A.M. to 9 P.M. Edgar Williams College, 150 Kotte Place, Hackensack. (201) 692-7337.</p>
        <p>FIREHOUSE GALLERY ''Contemporary Masters of Landscapes.'' Through April 24. Hours: Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Wednesdays, 11 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Saturdays, noon to 4 P.M. 8 Walnut Street, Bordentown. (609) 298-3742.</p>
        <p>GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE Paintings by Liz Whitney Quisgard. Fiber art by Michele Walker Wenske. Drawings and collages by Lori Field. Through next Sunday. Hours: Wednesdays and Thursdays, 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. and 4 to 6 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 P.M. and Baird Center, 5 Mead Street, South Orange. (201) 378-7754.</p>
        <p>HAND PAINTED FURNITURE Hand-painted antiques and new furniture. Through 1998.  111 First Street, Studio 1-2A, Jersey City. (201) 418-9405.</p>
        <p>JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS Linda AS Thayer, paintings. Through April. Hours: Monday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-5797.</p>
        <p>HISTORICAL SOCIETY OF PRINCETON ''Practical Photographers: The Rose Family Studio.'' Through 1998. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 4 P.M. 158 Nassau Street, Princeton. (609) 921-6748.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE AMERICAN HUNGARIAN FOUNDATION Victor Vasarely retrospective. Through Sept. 27. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 4 P.M. Free. 300 Somerset Street, New Brunswick. (732) 846-5777.</p>
        <p>ROBIN HUTCHINS GALLERY ''Endangered Spaces,'' photographs by Dennis Barna. Through Saturday. Hours: tomorrow through Saturday, 9 to 5 P.M.; Thursday to 7 P.M. 179 Maplewood Avenue, Maplewood.  (973) 762-4714.</p>
        <p>JERSEY CITY MUSEUM Paintings by Martin Beck. Through May 30. Lace paintings by David Ambrose. Through June 6. Sculptures by Orlando Cuevas. Through June 6. Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Wednesdays to 8 P.M. 472 Jersey Avenue, Jersey City. (201) 547-4514.</p>
        <p>JERSEY CITY STATE COLLEGE ''Urban Air Forms: Drawings and Studies for an Outdoor Sculpture Installation.'' Works by 14 sculptors. Through May 1. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Artspace, Hepburn Hall, 2039 Kennedy Boulevard, Jersey City. (201) 200-3441.</p>
        <p>KERYGMA GALLERY ''Offerings and Celebrations,'' paintings by Gracia Dayton. Through Saturday. Hours: today, 1 to 5 P.M.; Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.  38 Oak Street, Ridgewood. (201) 444-5510.</p>
        <p>MACCULLOCH HALL HISTORICAL MUSEUM ''Flora '98,'' an exhibition of floral art. Through next Sunday. ''The Lessons of Antique Toys.'' Through May 31. Admission: $3; $2 for students and the elderly. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays and Sundays, 1 to 4 P.M. 45 Macculloch Avenue, Morristown. (201) 538-2404.</p>
        <p>MARLBORO BRANCH OF MONMOUTH COUNTY LIBRARY ''In Praise of Local Landscapes,'' photographs by Kulbir Singh Bhalla. Through April 22. Hours: Mondays, Tuesdays and Thursdays, 9 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Wednesdays, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Fridays 1 to 5 P.M.; Saturdays, 9 to 5 P.M. 1 Library Court and Wyncrest Drive, Marlboro. (732) 431-7251.</p>
        <p>MIDLAND GALLERY ''Reworked Landscapes and the Journal Series,'' photographs by Jay Seldin. Through May 2. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 3 P.M. 13 Midland Avenue, Montclair. (973) 746-4884.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR STATE UNIVERSITY ''Visions on Three Continents,'' travel photographs by Ron Hollander. Through June 1. Hours: Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Tuesdays and Thursdays, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. Valley Road and Normal Avenue, Upper Montclair. (973) 655-7295.</p>
        <p>MORRIS COUNTY PARK COMMISSION Ed Schuh, paintings. Through May 1. daily, 9 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Great Swamp Outdoor Education Center, 247 Southern Boulevard, Chatham. (973) 635-6629.</p>
        <p>MORRIS MUSEUM Landscapes by Peter Schroth. Through April 26. ''The Neighborhood House: 100 Years of Caring for the Community.'' Through May 17. Recent sculptures by Leah Jacobson. Through May 24. ''Dolls From Around the World.'' Through June. ''Fresh Perspectives,'' 10th annual juried exhibition of high school artists. Through June 6. Hours: Sundays, 1 to 5 P.M.; Mondays through Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Thursdays, 10 A.M. to 8 P.M. Admission: $5; $3 for the elderly. 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (973) 538-0454.</p>
        <p>NABISCO GALLERY ''Seeing Red,'' an exhibition in conjunction with Women Artists of Montclair celebrating Women's History Month. Through Wednesday. Hours: daily, noon to 4 P.M. 100 DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (973) 503-3238.</p>
        <p>NATHANS ART GALLERY ''Visions From Hunterdon County.'' Through Saturday. Hours: Tuesday, Wednesday and Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Thursday, to 7 P.M.; Saturday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. 1205 McBride Avenue, West Paterson. (973) 785-9119.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS Retrospective by Robert Kushner. Through May 31. Photographs by Art Carlson. Through May 4. Sculptures by Peter Reginato. Through April 30. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturdays, noon to 4 P.M.; Sundays, 2 to 4 P.M. Palmer Gallery, 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY ''Teen-Age New Jersey: From Frank Sinatra to Bruce Springsteen.'' Through July.  Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. 52 Park Place, Newark.  (973) 483-3939.</p>
        <p>NEWARK ACADEMY Paintings by Toni Thomas and sculptures by Betty McGeehan. Through April 22. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 8 A.M. to 4 P.M. Elizabeth B. McGraw Arts Center, 91 South Orange Avenue, Livingston. (973) 992-7000.</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM Cityscapes and landscapes by George Bellows. Through May 31. ''Chinese Ceramics and Silks.'' Through May 31. ''Africa: The Arts of Power.'' Through 1999. ''Tibetan Buddhist Costumes and Ceremonial Textiles.'' Through 1998. ''Artisans of Ancient Rome: Production Into Art.'' Through 1998. ''Destination Mars.'' Through 1999. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, noon to 5 P.M. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550.</p>
        <p>NOYES MUSEUM OF ART ''Mystery and Allegory: A Decade of Works by Rob Evans.'' Through May 17. ''Past/Present/Future,'' recent photographs of Holocaust sites by Alex Nozick. Through May 10. ''Wind on Their Wings: Sea and Marsh Ducks of the Season,'' vintage decoys. Through May 23. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission: $3; $2 for the elderly and students. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville.  (609) 652-8848.</p>
        <p>PARAMUS PUBLIC LIBRARY Painting and drawings by Karrie Olick. Through April. Hours: Mondays through Thursdays, 9:30 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays, 9:30 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 5 P.M. East 116, Century Road, Paramus. (201) 599-1300.</p>
        <p>PASSAIC COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE Side show banner paintings by Marie Roberts. Through May 1. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Saturdays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Broadway and Memorial Drive, Paterson. (201) 684-6800.</p>
        <p>PALMYRA ART GALLERY ''Imaginary Landscapes,'' recent works on paper by Francesca Azzara. Through April 30. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 A.M. to 10 P.M. Free. 22 Hamilton Street, Bound Brook. (908) 302-0515.</p>
        <p>POLISH CULTURAL FOUNDATION ''Landscapes From the Harriman Park,'' by Ken Gruenbaum. Through May 1. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 5 to 9 P.M.; Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. Skulski Art Gallery, 177 Broadway, Clark. (732) 382-7197.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY ART MUSEUM ''Landscapes in the Painting and Art of Late Imperial China.'' Through June 7. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 5 P.M. Princeton University campus. (609) 258-3788.</p>
        <p>PRINTMAKING COUNCIL OF NEW JERSEY A retrospective of works by Zelda Burdick. Works by Robert Schwieger. Both through Tuesday. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Saturdays, 1 to 4 P.M. 440 River Road, North Branch. (908) 725-2110.</p>
        <p>RAMAPO COLLEGE ''Architecture of Shapes,'' performing and visual arts buildings by Hardy Holzman Pfeiffer Associates. Through April 24. Paintings by Richard Wawro, an autistic artist. Through next Sunday. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, noon to 2 P.M. 505 Ramapo Valley Road, Mahwah. (201) 529-7362.</p>
        <p>RARITAN VALLEY COMMUNITY COLLEGE ''Student Art Exhibit,'' photography, painting, monoprinting, sculpture and more. Through May 7. Hours: Mondays, 3 to 8 P.M.; Tuesdays, noon to 3 P.M.; Wednesdays, 1 to 8 P.M.; Thursdays, noon to 3 P.M. Art Gallery, Route 28 at Lamington Road, North Branch. (908) 218-8876.</p>
        <p>REEVES-REED ARBORETUM ''Lyrical Flowers and Landscapes,'' watercolors by Joan Pittis. Wednesday through May 31. Hours: Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 3 P.M. 165 Hobart Avenue, Summit. (908) 273-8787.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY GEOLOGY MUSEUM Geology exhibition including rocks, minerals, a Martian meteorite and dinosaur footprints. Through 1998. Hours: Mondays, 1 to 4 P.M.; Tuesdays through Fridays, 9 A.M. to Noon; Sundays, noon to 4 P.M. Geology Hall, Hamilton Street and College Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 932-7243.</p>
        <p>RUTGERS UNIVERSITY ''Paul Robeson: A Political Portrait, 1948-1959,'' more than 40 photographs focusing on Mr. Robeson's political work, and ''From These Roots,'' an exhibition chronicling Robeson's life. Both through May 2. Free. Mondays through Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Stedman Gallery, Fine Arts Center, Camden. (609) 225-6245.</p>
        <p>ROTUNDA GALLERY AT CITY HALL ''The Life and Times of a Pirate: An Art Portfolio.'' Through May 5. Hours: Monday through Saturday, 8 A.M. to 8 P.M. City Hall, 280 Grove Street, Jersey City. (201) 547-5522.</p>
        <p>ST. PETER'S COLLEGE ART GALLERY ''Ancient Worlds,'' featuring Hellenistic, Egyptian and Roman art. Friday through April 30. Hours: Mondays, Tuesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Wednesdays and Thursdays, 11 A.M. to 9 P.M. 2641 Kennedy Boulevard, Jersey City. (201) 915-9238.</p>
        <p>SETON HALL UNIVERSITY ''The Lure of Italy: Views From the 15th Century to the Present.'' Through May 15. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Walsh Library Gallery, 400 South Orange Avenue, South Orange. (973) 275-2033.</p>
        <p>SKIDMORE ART CONSULTANTS GALLERY Paintings by Patricia Davis-Ganek. Through May 8. 1 Airport Place, Route 206, Princeton. (609) 924-1875.</p>
        <p>SPRINGFIELD PUBLIC LIBRARY ''Joys of Travel,'' paintings by Hella Bailin. Through April 23. Hours: Mondays, Wednesdays and Thursdays, 10 A.M. to 8:30 P.M.; Tuesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 3:30 P.M. 66 Mountain Avenue, Springfield. (973) 376-4930.</p>
        <p>STARK &amp; STARK RECEPTION GALLERIES ''Lenses and Light: Personal Perspectives,'' photography. Thursday through July 17. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. 993 Lenox Drive, Building Two, Lawrenceville. (609) 896-9060.</p>
        <p>SWAIN GALLERIES Recent pastels by Nancy Brangaccio. Through April 30. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9:30 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Saturdays, 9:30 A.M. to 4 P.M. 703 Watchung Avenue, Plainfield. (908) 756-1707.</p>
        <p>WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER ''Earth, Water, Fire and Industrial Stuff,'' abstract photography. Through April. Hours: Mondays through Saturdays, 1 P.M. to 4 P.M. 18 Sterling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190.</p>
        <p>WYCKOFF GALLERY ''Spring Traditions,'' featuring 27 artists from the United States and Canada. Through May. Hours: Tuesday through Friday, 11:30 A.M. to 4 P.M. 648 Wyckoff Avenue, Wyckoff. (201) 891-7436.</p>
        <p>WHEATON VILLAGE ''Folk Art in Glass.'' Through Oct. 25. Hours: Daily, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Free. Gallery of American Craft, 1501 Glasstown Road, Millville. (609) 825-6800.</p>
        <p>ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM ''Paul Robeson: Artist and Citizen,'' a multi-media exhibition. Through July 31. ''Riding the Wave: The Japanese Influence on the Depiction of the Sea and Water in Western Art.'' Through July 5. ''Russia as Seen by Foreign Travelers: Maps of Russia, 16th to 18th Centuries.'' Through July 31. ''Appalachian Spring,'' illustrations for children's literature. Through July 31. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 P.M. Rutgers University, George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (732) 932-7237.</p>
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>APPEL FARM ARTS AND MUSIC CENTER ''The Jungle Book.'' Saturday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $6 in advance; $7.50 at the door. Reservations recommended. 457 Shirley Road, Elmer. (609) 358-2472.</p>
        <p>BERNARDSVILLE PUBLIC LIBRARY ''Poetry Time.'' Wednesday at 4 P.M. Free; registration required. Ages 5 and up. 2 Morristown Road, Bernardsville. (908) 766-0118.</p>
        <p>FORUM THEATER ''Rapunzel.'' Through May 30. Saturdays at 11 A.M. Tickets: $8. 314 Main Street, Metuchen. (908) 548-4670.</p>
        <p>H.M.D.C. ENVIRONMENT CENTER Kenneth Little Hawk teaches American Indian culture and traditions through song, dance and sign language. Next Sunday at 11 A.M. Tickets: $4.50; registration required. 2 DeKorte Park Plaza, Lyndhurst. (201) 460-8300.</p>
        <p>LIVING ARTS REPERTORY THEATER ''Yeb Sheu,'' the Chinese Cinderella story, performed in the style of the Theater of the Orient. Friday at 10 A.M.; Saturday at 11 A.M. Tickets: $5. 48 Haddon Avenue, Westmont. (609) 858-0333.</p>
        <p>MONMOUTH MUSEUM ''Changing Cultures: From the Lenape to the Urban Age, 1400 to 1900.'' Through June. Tuesdays through Fridays, 2 to 4:30 P.M.; Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sundays, 1 to 5 P.M. 761 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CHILDREN'S MUSEUM Daily programs: ''Fairy Tale Play,'' 10:30 A.M. ''Storytime,'' noon. Craft projects, 2:30 P.M. Museum hours: Mondays through Fridays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. Admission: $7. 599 Industrial Avenue, Paramus. (201) 262-2638.</p>
        <p>NOYES MUSEUM OF ART ''Creative Sparks,'' art activities that explore creativity for children. Saturday at 1 P.M. Free with museum admission: $3; $2 for students and the elderly; free under age 18. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848.</p>
        <p>PEDDIE SCHOOL ''The Swiss Family Robinson.'' Saturday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $8. Richard L. Swig Arts Center, South Main Street, Hightstown. (609) 490-7550.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY ART MUSEUM ''It Really Is Monet's Garden.'' Talk by Martha Challener, docent. Saturday at 11 A.M. Free for school-age children, kindergarten through fifth grade. (609) 258-3788.</p>
        <p>Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. OF NORTH JERSEY ''Winnie-the-Pooh. Thursday at 11 A.M. and 1:30 P.M. Tickets: $7 to $8. 1 Pike Drive, Wayne.  (201) 595-0100.</p>
        <p>SPOKEN WORD</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Russell Banks, Daniel Halpern, Joyce Carol Oates and others. Tuesday at 7 P.M. Free. Princeton Market Fair, Route 1, Princeton. (609) 392-0689.</p>
        <p>BARNES &amp; NOBLE Linda Leavitt, poet. Wednesday at 7:30 P.M. Free. 3981 State Highway 9, Freehold. (732) 308-0913.</p>
        <p>JERSEY CITY STATE COLLEGE Jacqueline Woodson, author of young adult novels. Tuesday at 7 P.M. Free. Room 202, Hepburn Hall, 2039 Kennedy Boulevard, Jersey City. (201) 200-3189.</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM ''Keepers of the Earth: Completing the Circles of Life,'' with Michael Caduto, writer and storyteller. Saturday at 2 P.M. Free. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (973) 596-6550.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY Merce Cunningham, choreographer. Wednesday at 5 P.M. Free. McCosh 10, Princeton University. (609) 258-4717.</p>
        <p>SETON HALL UNIVERSITY Maryse Conde, winner of France's Grand Prix Literaire de la Femme, will read from her book ''Desirada.'' Thursday at 7:45 P.M. Free. Kozlowski Hall Auditorium, 400 South Orange Avenue, South Orange. (973) 761-9388.</p>
        <p>WALT WHITMAN CULTURAL ARTS CENTER Ana Castillo and David Acosta present ''Latino Heritage Reading.'' Johnson Park at 2d and Cooper Streets, Camden. (609) 964-8300.</p>
        <p>WOMRATH'S Charles Johnson, winner of National Book Award, discusses his new novel, ''Dreamer.'' Saturday at 2 P.M. Free. 314 Main Street, Hackensack. (201) 487-6244.</p>
        <p>ETC.</p>
        <p>ESSEX COUNTY COLLEGE Fifth annual Invitational Sambo Championship, wrestling tournament with competitors from the United States, Canada, Russia, Morocco, Israel, Nigeria, Bulgaria, Latvia, Lithuania and Ukraine. Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Tickets: $3; $2 for students. 303 University Avenue, Newark. (973)877-3352.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR STATE UNIVERSITY International Film Festival. Through April 30. ''Eat, Drink, Man, Woman.'' Thursday at 4:30 P.M. Free. Sprague Library, Valley Road and Normal Avenue, Upper Montclair. (973) 655-4452.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CONVENTION AND EXPO CENTER International Collectible Exposition. Saturday and next Sunday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Tickets: $7 for one day; $10 for both days. Main Hall and Expansion, 97 Sunfield Avenue, Edison. (800) 332-3976.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY MUSEUM OF AGRICULTURE Spring Wine Festival, sponsored by the Garden State Winegrowers Association. Saturday and next Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Tickets: $12 for adults over 21; $3 under age 21. Route 1 and College Farm Road, North Brunswick. (732) 249-2077.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM ''Heavens and Earth Day.'' Saturday at 9:30 A.M. Free. Laser concerts on Fridays and Saturdays. ''Beatles Laser Anthology,'' 7 P.M. ''Electrolyte,'' 8:15 P.M. ''Laser Doors,'' 9:30 P.M. ''Pink Floyd: The Wall,'' 10:45 P.M. Tickets: $7; $5 for children. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 777-9444.</p>
        <p>SMITHVILLE VILLAGE GREEN Decoy Carvers' and Collectors' Show. Saturday and next Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Free. Six miles north of Atlantic City on Route 9; exit 48 on the Garden State Parkway, Smithville.</p>
        <p>STATE THEATER Charlie Chaplin Film Festival, with the Paragon Ragtime Orchestra. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $19 to $32. 15 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (732) 246-7469.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
