<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taxi Conversions Are Another Step In the City's Move to Cleaner Vehicles</title>
    <meta content="12GAS.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1009308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Garages and Service Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDE103DF931A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taxi Conversions Are Another Step In the City's Move to Cleaner Vehicles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS MARTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Martin, Douglas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City is taking first steps in building nation's largest fleet of gas-powered vehicles--from taxicabs, vans and buses--and establishing fueling stations to service them; industry officials and advocates of alternative fuels say growth of fueling stations would encourage buying and use of natural-gas-powered vehicles, which produce far less pollution than gasoline-powered cars (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last week, a Queens taxi garage made news with the announcement that it was buying 100 natural-gas-powered vehicles, but for some time New York City has been laying the groundwork for cleaning up automotive emissions.</p>
        <p>The first step has been to build the nation's largest fleet of natural-gas-powered vehicles -- 3,000 in all -- from taxis to delivery vans to buses. The second, and perhaps more important, step is to establish fueling stations to service the vehicles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last week, a Queens taxi garage made news with the announcement that it was buying 100 natural-gas-powered vehicles, but for some time New York City has been laying the groundwork for cleaning up automotive emissions.</p>
        <p>The first step has been to build the nation's largest fleet of natural-gas-powered vehicles -- 3,000 in all -- from taxis to delivery vans to buses. The second, and perhaps more important, step is to establish fueling stations to service the vehicles.</p>
        <p>Industry officials and advocates of alternative fuels say that the growth in fueling stations would encourage the buying and use of natural-gas-powered vehicles, which produce far less pollution than gasoline-powered cars. And the fueling stations could also be used to service vehicles powered by a newer technology: fuel cells, which, in effect, are batteries that never need recharging.</p>
        <p>And fuel cells mean that pure hydrogen could supplant natural gas, meaning no vehicle emissions and even better fuel economies.</p>
        <p>''When you look around the rest of the country, you don't find the same kind of concentrated forward motion as you find in New York,'' said Richard Kassel, senior attorney for the Natural Resources Defense Council.</p>
        <p>Robert B. Catell, chairman and chief executive of Keyspan Energy Company, a subsidiary of Brooklyn Union Gas that has been a leader in the city's natural-gas conversion efforts, said he expects that within a decade more than half the city's delivery vans will be powered by natural gas.</p>
        <p>But there are huge obstacles. One is the price of gasoline -- about $1.15 a gallon now -- which city transportation authorities fear may be too low to push car buyers to shift to natural gas. Another is that there are already millions of electrical outlets, which advocates of electric vehicles say can be used to recharge the vehicles. Still another is that the range of natural-gas vehicles is limited and that fueling stations are sparse, particularly in rural areas.</p>
        <p>Moreover, to many people, hydrogen power still seems more at home in laboratories than the marketplace.</p>
        <p>New York ranks first among cities east of the Mississippi in particulates and ozone, two forms of pollution that can severely damage lungs. Well over half of these pollutants could be removed in New York City by eliminating automotive emissions from gasoline-powered vehicles, Mr. Kassel and other experts suggest.</p>
        <p>Buses are a special problem. Despite its leadership in converting delivery vans and taxis, the city has been slow to switch over its bus fleet to natural gas, according to Inform Inc., an environmental research organization.</p>
        <p>But advocates of alternative energy draw inspiration from the city's record on encouraging a natural-gas-vehicle market. They point to 1,500 municipal vehicles, from pickups to full-size sanitation trucks; 1,000 vehicles owned by fleets, from United Parcel Service to the Postal Service to milk companies, and 700 vehicles owned by Brooklyn Union and Consolidated Edison, the principal sellers of natural gas in the city.</p>
        <p>And taxis represent perhaps the most expansive frontier. On Thursday, the Ford Motor Company announced that it sold Winner's Garage in Queens 100 natural-gas-powered cabs to replace its entire fleet. That brought the city's number of natural-gas taxis to 270.</p>
        <p>''I can't think of a city that's making a big push toward natural-gas taxis like New York,'' Mr. Kassel said.</p>
        <p>More than 300 additional cabs are expected to be sold under incentives offered by the state and Ford, totaling more than $10,000 per vehicle, enough to cover the additional expense of such cabs.</p>
        <p>In mass transit, the city Department of Transportation has bought 53 buses for the 7 bus franchises it operates. It has ordered 174 more and has said that it will exercise an option to buy 120 others. Its total fleet is 1,100 buses.</p>
        <p>The Metropolitan Transit Authority has been less aggressive. Just 39 buses in its fleet of 3,500 are powered by natural gas.</p>
        <p>But in total, the converted cars, vans, trucks and buses could begin to form the basis for a hydrogen-powered transportation system. Already, 50 natural-gas fueling stations exist in New York State, most in or around the city. These could be used to directly inject hydrogen into fuel tanks or to inject natural gas, from which pure hydrogen would be extracted in the vehicle.</p>
        <p>A fuel cell in the vehicle would combine the hydrogen with oxygen through an electrochemical process, without combustion. This process produces energy, leaving pure water as the only waste product.</p>
        <p>''Anything you can do to bring natural gas into the transportation system is paving the way for the hydrogen fuel cell,'' said James Cannon, senior energy fellow for Inform, the environmental research organization. ''Every conquest natural gas makes today will help people down the road get to hydrogen.''</p>
        <p>Private companies are pushing ahead on both natural gas and the fuel cell. All three big American auto companies -- Ford, General Motors and Chrysler -- are offering natural-gas-powered cars this year for the first time, and all three are developing prototype fuel cells. Brooklyn Union is already demonstrating fuel cells at industrial plants on Staten Island, while a waste-water treatment facility in Yonkers uses fuel-cell technology.</p>
        <p>New York State is also working on a number of fronts. One program gives buyers of cars powered by alternative fuels up to $5,000 in an investment tax credit and truck buyers $10,000.</p>
        <p>New York is also the only state to require 2 percent of all vehicles sold this year to have ''zero emissions,'' a program that can help in the sale of electric or gasoline cars.</p>
        <p>The city, under a 1991 law, is also stepping up its purchase of alternative-fuel vehicles. This year, 80 percent of new municipal cars and trucks must use fuels other than gasoline or diesel fuel. Another city and state idea is to paint some curbs green as free parking spaces for alternative-fuel vehicles.</p>
        <p>All this is beginning to add up to pressure for cleaner cars.</p>
        <p>''The technology's available right now,'' Mr. Catell of Keyspan Energy said. ''What's needed is a little bit of market pull.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
