<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>District of Columbia Journal; In a Sea of Killings, One Turns Heads</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="489998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, HENRY (MURDER SUSPECT)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEXIE, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DA1E3FF934A15752C1A967958260" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>District of Columbia Journal; In a Sea of Killings, One Turns Heads</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The killings have been going on here for so long and with such frequency that they are now taken as one of the givens of life in the nation's capital, along with politics, the humidity and the Redskins.</p>
        <p>There are streets and apartment buildings in poor sections of the inner city where there have been two, three, even half a dozen murders, most involving angry young men caught up in running drugs and guns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The killings have been going on here for so long and with such frequency that they are now taken as one of the givens of life in the nation's capital, along with politics, the humidity and the Redskins.</p>
        <p>There are streets and apartment buildings in poor sections of the inner city where there have been two, three, even half a dozen murders, most involving angry young men caught up in running drugs and guns.</p>
        <p>But there also are grassy schoolyards and popular restaurants and trendy clothing stores well removed from the inner city, even out in the suburbs, where people have lost their lives, cut down in robberies or arcane disputes or because they happened in their innocence to be in the wrong place at the wrong time.</p>
        <p>Ten days ago, there occurred a murder so heinous that even this city still is reeling in shock and rage. A young woman, newly married and embarked on a successful career, was riding along a city freeway when a car pulled along side and a man stuck a gun out the window and shot her dead, telling friends, the police said, that he just felt like killing someone.</p>
        <p>Citing that slaying as a symptom of a "virus and epidemic" that is sweeping through the city, Mayor Sharon Pratt Dixon went on prime time television tonight to propose still another crime control effort, one that would include additional police, extra education programs for troubled youths and their families, tougher bail regulations and stiffer penalities for violent juveniles, with some to be treated as adults.</p>
        <p>"This violence must come to an end," the Mayor declared. "We have allowed outselves to become armchair patriots in the fight."</p>
        <p>These days, just about every Washington citizen, whether in an armchair or not, seems to have a tale to tell about a murder in the building across the street or a shooting in a shop in the next block, not to mention the latest parking lot mugging or house burglary.</p>
        <p>When a car backfires on a Washington street, even at high noon in front of the White House, shoulders reflexively flinch and heads turn.</p>
        <p>For awhile the killings here seemed more shocking than those in cities elsewhere because so many were happening, literally, within a few blocks of the White House or Capitol Hill, in the very heart of the seat of government of the world's most powerful democracy. But now, nearing the end of still another year in which roughly two murders are taking place every 24 hours in the metropolitan area, the Washington psyche is overloaded, numb, shocked by only the most heinous of murders.</p>
        <p>The freeway slaying that occurred on Nov. 16, provided that kind of shock. It left residents saying: "It can happen anywhere. It can happen to me."</p>
        <p>This is what the police say about the slaying.</p>
        <p>Shortly before midnight after a Saturday evening of visiting with friends, Freddie and Patricia Lexie where driving through the eastern edge of the city on an interstate spur, headed for their home across the Potomac River in Alexandria, Va. Suddenly a car carrying four people pulled alongside the Lexie car and someone leaned out and fired a shot that struck Mrs. Lexie in the head. She died before her husband, who was driving, could get her to a hospital.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lexie, a 36-year-old office manager for a manufacturers association, and Mr. Lexie, a 29-year-old security specialist for a defense contractor, had been married only 11 months. Friends described them as a couple so close and in love that "they stuck together like glue."</p>
        <p>Four days after the shooting, acting on several tips, investigators arrested Henry James, a 19-year-old high school dropout, and charged him with what one detective called "a senseless execution." The investigators said that Mr. James had told friends just before the shooting, "I feel like killing someone." And after the shooting, according to the investigators, he telephoned law-enforcement officials and taunted, "Catch me if you can."</p>
        <p>Mr. James, known as "Little Man," has a long police record of criminal violence, much of it as a juvenile. Four days before the Lexie shooting, he was arraigned in a city court on charges of assault with intent to kill and released on $1,000 bond.</p>
        <p>When word of Mr. James's record and bail release spread after Mrs. Lexie's death, there were new calls in the city for youth offender programs and bail reform. The Mayor sought to answer those calls tonight. As for Mr. James's status, he is being held without bond pending a hearing.</p>
        <p>He has made no formal plea to the charges he faces growing out of the slaying. But at one point while he was being booked, he flashed a grin at reporters, asserted his innocence, and said he was "out maintaining my composure" on the night Mrs. Lexie was shot.</p>
        <p>Like many cities, Washington has experienced any number of drive-by shootings. A few have left investigators puzzled as to motive, but most have been drug-related, terribly violent but nevertheless explicable.</p>
        <p>The Lexie shooting is not explicable -- except as another disturbing sign of the times, as Mayor Dixon put it. Every indication is that it was, chillingly, a mindless, random act of violence.</p>
        <p>"It just leaves you feeling helpless, like there's nothing, absolutely nothing, that you or your friends or anybody can do to stay safe," said Henri Wingfield, one of Mrs. Lexie's co-workers. "You can't hide because you don't know where to hide. We've got to put a stop to it, somehow. We've got to take a stand."</p>
        <p>That is what Mayor Dixon tried to do tonight.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
