<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theater in Review</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="490065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">O'CASEY THEATER CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUSSOW, MEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CASEY, SEAN (1880-1964)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SHADOW OF A GUNMAN, THE (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DA1230F934A15752C1A967958260" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theater in Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEL GUSSOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUSSOW, MEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Shadow of a Gunman  Symphony Space 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street Manhattan Through Dec. 8 By Sean O'Casey; directed by Shivaun O'Casey; set design by Brien Vahey; set decoration, Josie MacAvin; costumes, Jan Bee Brown; lighting design, Rory Dempster; sound, Paul Bull; production stage manager, Bryan Young; music, Tommy Sands; produced by Sally de Sousa. Presented by the O'Casey Theater Company of Newry County Down, Northern Ireland.  WITH: Niall Buggy, Risteard Cooper, Michelle Fairley, Ian Fitzgibbon, Pauline Flanagan, Stephen Gabis, Richard Holmes, Doreen Keogh, Sean McCarthy, Shauna Rooney and George Vogel.</p>
        <p>Although it is nearly 70 years old, "The Shadow of a Gunman" retains its harsh immediacy within and also beyond its depressed Dublin environment. It is a tightly focused, unsentimental play about heroism both false and real and about how people respond to the challenge of an emergency. Shivaun O'Casey's production, brought to Symphony Space by the new O'Casey Theater Company, is more successful at capturing the raffish comedy than it is at suggesting the darker recesses of the drama.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Shadow of a Gunman  Symphony Space 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street Manhattan Through Dec. 8 By Sean O'Casey; directed by Shivaun O'Casey; set design by Brien Vahey; set decoration, Josie MacAvin; costumes, Jan Bee Brown; lighting design, Rory Dempster; sound, Paul Bull; production stage manager, Bryan Young; music, Tommy Sands; produced by Sally de Sousa. Presented by the O'Casey Theater Company of Newry County Down, Northern Ireland.  WITH: Niall Buggy, Risteard Cooper, Michelle Fairley, Ian Fitzgibbon, Pauline Flanagan, Stephen Gabis, Richard Holmes, Doreen Keogh, Sean McCarthy, Shauna Rooney and George Vogel.</p>
        <p>Although it is nearly 70 years old, "The Shadow of a Gunman" retains its harsh immediacy within and also beyond its depressed Dublin environment. It is a tightly focused, unsentimental play about heroism both false and real and about how people respond to the challenge of an emergency. Shivaun O'Casey's production, brought to Symphony Space by the new O'Casey Theater Company, is more successful at capturing the raffish comedy than it is at suggesting the darker recesses of the drama.</p>
        <p>The play's protagonist, Donal Davoren, allows his neighbors to regard him as a rebel on the run. "On the Run" was Sean O'Casey's original title, with a double meaning intended. Donal, a would-be poet, is not in flight from the authorities but from himself. Holed up in his tenement room with the peddler Seumas Shields, he is forced to confront his conscience and his responsibility to lovely young Minnie Powell, whose head is filled with idealism and love of poets. In Miss O'Casey's production of her father's play, the colorful characters are carefully in place. But there is a curious turnabout in our perspective.</p>
        <p>Because of Niall Buggy's resonant portrayal of Seumas, that character achieves a greater importance in the narrative. This is the most significant contribution of the revival. The regret is that the rest of the production is not equal to Mr. Buggy's performance. There is a concurrent loss, as Donal, given a rather stolid rendition by Ian Fitzgibbon, begins to fade into the background.</p>
        <p>Sharing that background are the other tenement dwellers. Some of them offer standard comic turns, but a few like Pauline Flanagan, as the nosiest of busybodies, bring the play closer to its tragicomic dimensions. The outcome, the martyrdom of Minnie (Michelle Fairley), should send a chill through the thin tenement walls, which has been the case in a number of other productions.</p>
        <p>One problem at Symphony Space is Brien Vahey's confined setting, which forces actors to enter and exit through a central door and to step forward to deliver set pieces. In several instances, actors remain partly hidden behind that door. The staging conveys little sense of a threatening exterior world.</p>
        <p>What intensity accrues comes largely from the text and from Mr. Buggy's performance. In this interpretation, Seumas is as crafty as he is craven. He is determined to preserve his safety, but he seems to have a self-awareness about the reasons for his inaction. Because of his intelligence, we begin to wonder why he is a peddler rather than a philosopher or poet. Seumas makes the most cynical observations about his compatriots, but when Mr. Buggy speaks those lines, they echo with a renewed relevance and the character's cantankerousness approaches despair.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
