<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Better Tools Needed on China</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="832782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHINA-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHINA-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-PAKISTAN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAKISTAN-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PAKISTAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PAKISTAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E1DD1139F935A15751C0A960958260" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Better Tools Needed on China</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>China's brazen export to Pakistan of magnets used in nuclear bomb production  is creating more problems for the Clinton Administration than it has for Beijing. That is because Washington now finds itself with no credible way to respond that does not also inflict serious harm on United States business interests.</p>
        <p>The best answer for now is to give priority to nuclear security and impose the penalties specified by law. But the Administration must also work to avoid similar dilemmas in the future by equipping itself with sharper policy tools. One obvious approach is to persuade America's allies (and business competitors)  to join in coordinated economic penalties against reckless nuclear suppliers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>China's brazen export to Pakistan of magnets used in nuclear bomb production  is creating more problems for the Clinton Administration than it has for Beijing. That is because Washington now finds itself with no credible way to respond that does not also inflict serious harm on United States business interests.</p>
        <p>The best answer for now is to give priority to nuclear security and impose the penalties specified by law. But the Administration must also work to avoid similar dilemmas in the future by equipping itself with sharper policy tools. One obvious approach is to persuade America's allies (and business competitors)  to join in coordinated economic penalties against reckless nuclear suppliers.</p>
        <p>The magnets sale violates the Nuclear Nonproliferation Treaty, signed by Beijing. Under United States law, this violation automatically triggers a cutoff of taxpayer-backed loan guarantees for many of the biggest American business deals with China. The Administration can protect American business interests by  waiving the penalties, but only at the cost of severely undermining its efforts  to halt the spread of nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>The Administration, pressured by Congress to signal disapproval to China and  pressured by business to avoid sanctions, is preparing to split the difference.  It intends to impose, and then immediately waive, the statutory punishment and then apply less drastic economic penalties. Such a compromise would confirm Beijing's impression that Washington will never carry out its threats of damaging economic sanctions for fear of hurting American business. If that impression is correct, the United States urgently needs to find other policy levers that it is actually prepared to use.</p>
        <p>Chinese challenges over nuclear technology and missile sales, copyright piracy and Taiwan cannot be ignored just because Washington has no available responses that do not also impose costs on Americans. Until less problematic forms of retaliation are developed, the United States must be prepared in cases  as serious as this one to invoke the economic sanctions that are now on the books.</p>
        <p>But the Administration is not wrong in thinking that penalties that affect only American business deals, leaving European and Japanese companies free to pick up the contracts United States companies might lose, are neither the smartest nor the most effective way to punish Beijing.</p>
        <p>It would be far more effective if all major trading powers applied concerted  economic penalties, from the withdrawal of government subsidies to tightened restrictions on high-technology imports. Some American allies might be reluctant to go along with a coordinated approach. But they can be reminded that any reduction in America's ability to influence Beijing on security issues damages them, too.</p>
        <p>America has tried to discourage dangerous Chinese behavior in recent years by rationing high-level official visits and imposing limited economic sanctions. These measures have had little apparent effect. Futile as these calibrated policies sometimes seem, they are clearly preferable to flaunting the Seventh Fleet or making implicit military threats.</p>
        <p>To restore its credibility, Washington must now try stronger forms of nonmilitary pressure. That means signing up American allies to apply coordinated penalties when international treaties are seriously breached. But until that can be achieved, Washington must be prepared to apply the full rigor of American law in cases like the magnets sale to Pakistan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
