<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED8103CF937A35750C0A965958260" item-length="609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Markets</p>
        <p>Long-term interest rates dropped to record lows again as traders appeared to accept the probability of modest economic growth with low inflation. The 30-year Treasury bond continued its two-week rally, dropping in yield to 6.78 percent.  [ Page D1. ]</p>
        <p>Stocks rose as equities became more attractive to investors than bonds, which have fallen to record-low yields. The Dow gained 3.51 points, to 3,404.04, and other indexes gained.  [ D8. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Markets</p>
        <p>Long-term interest rates dropped to record lows again as traders appeared to accept the probability of modest economic growth with low inflation. The 30-year Treasury bond continued its two-week rally, dropping in yield to 6.78 percent.  [ Page D1. ]</p>
        <p>Stocks rose as equities became more attractive to investors than bonds, which have fallen to record-low yields. The Dow gained 3.51 points, to 3,404.04, and other indexes gained.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar was mixed ahead of a meeting of German monetary officials. Gold was mixed.  [ D13. ]  Grain prices weakened.  [ D13. ] The Economy</p>
        <p>Some businesses are delaying plans to rent space in the World Trade Center and some tenants may not renew leases.  [ A1. ]  The Port Authority successfully sold $100 million in new bonds.  [ B5. ]</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court, in a case involving Ernst &amp; Young, made it harder to sue accountants, lawyers and other outside advisers to corrupt companies under RICO laws.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Democrats defeated the first Republican challenge to President Clinton's economic program, voting down a proposal to offset extended unemployment benefits with spending cuts.  [ A22. ]</p>
        <p>Clark M. Clifford won an indefinite postponement of his trial in the B.C.C.I. scandal. He is planning heart surgery.  [ D14. ]</p>
        <p>The New York City pension fund sued the S.E.C. for allowing companies to bar shareholder votes on hiring policies.  [ D8. ] Companies</p>
        <p>Talk radio will come to desktop computers in a few weeks under a plan by a Virginia entrepreneur to broadcast a daily 30-minute radio talk show on Internet, a computer network.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>Television stations are being told by regulators that cartoons like "The Jetsons" and "The Flintstones" can no longer count as "educational and informational" programming.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>Sales of North American-built vehicles rose 9 percent in late February. But the annual car-selling rate slipped.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>The U.A.W. said thousands more G.M. workers than expected had taken an offer of early retirement.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Mazda dropped discussions with Ford on joint European automobile production because the two could not agree.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Prudential's capital rose $79 million in 1992 despite a $900 million loss on insurance because of Hurricane Andrew.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Bristol-Myers Squibb named a president for its pharmaceutical group, which produces more than half its revenues.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>The New York Post was added to the S.E.C. fraud suit against Steven Hoffenberg, who is trying to buy the paper.  [ B3. ] International</p>
        <p>Airbus unveiled what it called a new airplane developed without government subsidies. But the A321 is not new by most measures, and it can be argued that it was subsidized.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Mexico's state oil company wants to become a modern oil giant with foreign help. But Pemex's self-imposed ceiling on production has limited its role as a major source of export revenue.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Administration officials say they are dissatisfied with Japan's efforts to open its market to American computer chips, but they are leaning against imposing any immediate sanctions.  [ D1. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>President Clinton's proposed B.T.U. tax will raise revenue, but the plan is generating a lot of grousing among environmentalists and economists. Peter Passell: Economic Scene.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>What seemed to be more grim news for Gtech Holdings, a maker of computerized lottery systems, has turned out to be good for its stock. Kurt Eichenwald: Market Place.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Anheuser-Busch has scheduled a new advertising campaign for Bud Dry as part of a multimillion-dollar strategy to "stimulate new interest" in the beer. Advertising.  [ D20. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
