<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Backing Vast Effort To Restore Florida Swamps</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="830959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUGAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EVERGLADES (FLA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES) WILLIAM JEFFERSON 'BILL'CLINTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Everglades National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DB1339F93BA25751C0A960958260" item-length="1325" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Backing Vast Effort To Restore Florida Swamps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR;</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton has decided to endorse a huge project to protect the Everglades by spending hundreds of millions of dollars to take farmland out of production and restore a more natural flow of fresh water across Florida's swampy southern half, according to senior Administration officials.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have been urging such a project for years over intense opposition from the region's sugar cane growers. It would be one of the biggest  ecological restoration efforts ever undertaken, the Administration officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton has decided to endorse a huge project to protect the Everglades by spending hundreds of millions of dollars to take farmland out of production and restore a more natural flow of fresh water across Florida's swampy southern half, according to senior Administration officials.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have been urging such a project for years over intense opposition from the region's sugar cane growers. It would be one of the biggest  ecological restoration efforts ever undertaken, the Administration officials said.</p>
        <p>Over the next 10 to 20 years, its effects would be felt across a region bursting with some of the nation's fastest growing metropolitan areas, where tourism and agriculture vie in an economy that has grown at the expense of an aquatic ecosystem unlike any other on the planet.</p>
        <p>The plan is expected to be announced by Vice President Al Gore on Monday at Everglades National Park, which contains the most pristine remnants of the vast  marsh of saw grass that was largely drained earlier in the century, either to be turned into farmland or to supply cities with water and protect them from floods.</p>
        <p>The Everglades restoration project has been in planning for three years, during continuous debate over its effects on agriculture, urban water supplies and the environment. This is the first time that the White House has given the enormous project its blessing or declared that the sugar industry must help pay  for it, as environmentalists have been demanding for years.</p>
        <p>The proposed expansion of existing efforts to reverse the Everglades' decline would be financed in part by fees imposed on the region's sugar industry, Administration officials said. For years, environmentalists, who blame sugar growers for much of the harm to the Everglades, have been campaigning to impose  a two-cent tax on every pound of sugar produced in the Everglades region. The Administration is expected to endorse a one-cent tax, although other options have also been discussed.</p>
        <p>Many elements of the Administration's plan, including any new fees on the sugar industry, would have to be approved by Congress, where the prospects for action this year are uncertain. But Administration officials noted that restoring the Everglades is a popular cause in the Florida Congressional delegation, and said they had high hopes of winning approval.</p>
        <p>Administration officials called the new plan one of the most significant environmental efforts of the Clinton Presidency, surpassing in scope even the famous plan for managing the spotted owl habitat of the Pacific Northwest forests.</p>
        <p>It calls for the Federal Government to spend an additional $500 million or more during the next several years, on top of the $100 million or so that Federal agencies already spend each year to protect the Everglades. The additional spending is a much bigger expansion than the Senate recently approved in passing a new farm bill, and it represents something of a bidding war, just before the Florida Presidential primaries, between the Administration and top Republicans, including Senator Richard G. Lugar of Indiana and Senator Bob Dole  of Kansas.</p>
        <p>The White House decision to push ahead attests to the political potency that  the Administration attributes to environmental issues, and to the importance of  Florida in the Presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups are welcoming the Clinton Administration's approach.</p>
        <p>"We are talking about a lot of money, we are talking about a lot of land, and we are talking about ecosystem restoration on a scale we have never seen before  anywhere in the world," said Ron Tipton, who is in charge of the Everglades project at the World Wildlife Fund.</p>
        <p>In effect, the plan would try to erase much of the human signature that has been etched with levees, canals and pumping stations on the central and southern Florida landscape in the past half century.</p>
        <p>"This is the replumbing of South Florida," said one senior Administration official.</p>
        <p>At the core of the plan is what scientists call an urgent need to restore the natural hydrologic patterns before the Everglades disappear entirely.</p>
        <p>In the past, water flowed south from the headwaters of the Kissimmee River to Lake Okeechobee, where it overflowed seasonally, spilling over the lake's southern shores and drifting in a broad, grassy sheet down the ever-so-subtle slope to Florida Bay.</p>
        <p>Now, that terrain is crisscrossed by a thousand miles of canals and levees, some of which divert the system's water directly out to the Atlantic tides.</p>
        <p>While it is impossible to bring about a complete return to the natural water  cycles of a hundred years ago, with their extensive floods, studies have shown how to imitate some of the natural rhythms of the water flow, without which the  vestiges of the Everglades would likely continue to dwindle.</p>
        <p>According to specialists involved in the planning, it requires two things: an engineering project on the scale of the one that took decades to drain the land at mid-century, and the purchase of a huge swath of land, on the order of 100,000 acres, mostly at the southern end of the Everglades Agricultural Area below Lake Okeechobee.</p>
        <p>"That land would be the heart being restored to the Everglades," said one senior Administration official.</p>
        <p>The plan was worked out in the last month by a task force under Vice President Gore along with such high-level Administration officials as Carol M. Browner, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency; Alice M. Rivlin,  Director of the Office of Management and Budget; Kathleen A. McGinty, Director of the White House Council on Environmental Quality; and Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt, as well as Florida State officials.</p>
        <p>It would go well beyond the provisions of a landmark settlement on water quality reached between sugar companies and the state and Federal governments in 1993 and ratified by the Florida Legislature in the Everglades Forever Act of 1994. That called for a program of land acquisition and water treatment costing  an estimated $700 million, including as much as $312 million contributed by the  sugar companies, which over the years have been accused of polluting Everglades  waters with fertilizer-laden runoff.</p>
        <p>The companies have said that is all they are willing to spend. But the Administration is now seeking hundreds of millions of dollars more.</p>
        <p>Administration officials called the new fees an attempt to recapture from the sugar industry "a fair share" of the perennial subsidies that have enabled it to take root in Florida.</p>
        <p>Like other elements of the Administration's proposal, any new Federal fees on sugar would have to be approved by Congress, either in the farm bill now being debated or in separate legislation. The cost of the project is likely to be shared by Florida as well.</p>
        <p>Despite opposition from farmers -- whose activities in the drained areas also include growing vegetables and raising cattle -- restoring the Everglades enjoys broad support in Florida, partly because the demise of the ecosystem has harmed  offshore waters like Florida Bay, where fishing and tourism are major industries.</p>
        <p>The White House's plan calls for a great deal of further scientific research  into how the complex and delicate Everglades functions as an ecosystem. Questions of water flow, biological diversity, invasions by foreign species, and water monitoring need to be better understood before all the decisions can be made about how much land to buy, and where.</p>
        <p>But some engineering work that is already under way on on the drawing boards  will be accelerated under the plan, Administration officials said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
