<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Idaho Siege Report Says F.B.I. Agents Violated Procedure</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="730904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHITE SUPREMACY GROUPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOSTAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHITE SUPREMACY GROUPS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL BUREAU OF INVESTIGATION (FBI)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSTON, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEAVER, RANDALL C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEAVER, VICKI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HORIUCHI, LON T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EED61E39F930A25751C1A962958260" item-length="1160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Idaho Siege Report Says F.B.I. Agents Violated Procedure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSTON, DAVID</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A confidential Justice Department study of a deadly 1992 standoff between a white separatist and Federal agents found that senior officials violated not only their own policies but also the Constitution when they relaxed the rules that govern when Federal agents may shoot a suspect.</p>
        <p>The study was prepared by a 24-member investigative team reporting to the Office of Professional Responsibility, the Justice Department's internal disciplinary unit. It traces the long chain of events that led to a 10-day siege around the remote mountain home of the separatist, Randall C. Weaver, after a sharpshooter for the Federal Bureau of Investigation mistakenly shot Mr. Weaver's wife, Vicki, as she stood in the doorway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A confidential Justice Department study of a deadly 1992 standoff between a white separatist and Federal agents found that senior officials violated not only their own policies but also the Constitution when they relaxed the rules that govern when Federal agents may shoot a suspect.</p>
        <p>The study was prepared by a 24-member investigative team reporting to the Office of Professional Responsibility, the Justice Department's internal disciplinary unit. It traces the long chain of events that led to a 10-day siege around the remote mountain home of the separatist, Randall C. Weaver, after a sharpshooter for the Federal Bureau of Investigation mistakenly shot Mr. Weaver's wife, Vicki, as she stood in the doorway.</p>
        <p>The 542-page report portrays the operation as a chaotic sequence of events that nearly spun out of control. The F.B.I. hurriedly dispatched officials to Idaho, and their superiors in Washington stumbled through a series of mistakes and misjudgments, at one point changing the rules of engagement for the operation and ordering agents on the scene to shoot at any armed adults if they had clear shots, the report said.</p>
        <p>Under traditional policies on the use of deadly force, agents do not shoot unless their lives or the lives of others are in jeopardy. The report said one agent involved in the standoff interpreted the rule change as a departure that meant, "If you see them, shoot them."</p>
        <p>"Certain portions of the rules of engagement not only departed from the F.B.I.'s standard deadly force policy but also contravened the Constitution of the United States" by violating Ms. Weaver's civil rights, the report said. "In addition we found these rules to be imprecise and believe that they may have created an atmosphere that encouraged the use of deadly force, thereby having the effect of contributing to an unintentional death."</p>
        <p>Frederick Lanceley, a hostage negotiator for the bureau during the standoff, told the investigators after the incident that he was "surprised and shocked" by the revised rules of engagement, the most severe he had seen in more than 300 hostage situations. Two F.B.I. lawyers, interviewed later, said the rules were "too broad" and could be misread.</p>
        <p>That criticism and the official findings of the report contrast sharply with the tepid reaction at the Justice Department, which has decided not to prosecute Lon T. Horiuchi, the F.B.I. sharpshooter who killed Vicki Weaver, or anybody else for violating Ms. Weaver's civil rights. In a still unreleased memorandum dated Oct. 15, Deval L. Patrick, assistant attorney general for civil rights, said that given the circumstances, Mr. Horiuchi had reason to believe that his life or the lives other agents were in jeopardy and thus was justified in his actions.</p>
        <p>Justice Department officials have said they expect some bureau officials to be disciplined, but the F.B.I. Director, Louis J. Freeh, has not said what action he intends to take. Today an F.B.I. spokesman would not comment on the report but said the possibility of disciplinary action was under review. Last week, Mr. Freeh promoted Larry A. Potts, who had overall responsibility for the operation, to be his chief deputy.</p>
        <p>For months, Justice Department officials have said they planned to make the report public after sharing it with prosecutors in Idaho and officials who were criticized in it. But lawyers for the Weaver family and legislators like Senator Larry E. Craig, Republican of Idaho, have contended that the department, which completed the report in April, has delayed public disclosure to avoid embarrassment.</p>
        <p>The report is based on dozens of interviews with F.B.I. agents and other law enforcement officials who took part in the siege, some of whom provided information under grants of immunity from prosecution.</p>
        <p>It provides a wealth of fresh details about the incident. The report concludes that the F.B.I. did not act with malice, but it documents how officials misjudged the threat that Mr. Weaver posed to Federal agents and initially adopted an aggressive assault plan to resolve the standoff without negotiations. One senior bureau official at the scene, not identified in the report, was quoted as saying that the Weaver crisis "was not going to last long" because it would be "taken down hard and fast."</p>
        <p>The report found that Mr. Potts, who was the assistant director in charge of criminal investigations at F.B.I. headquarters at the time of the incident, was correct in sending the full 50-member hostage rescue team -- H.R.T., in the bureau's parlance -- from its base in Quantico, Va., to Idaho on Aug. 21, 1992, after preparations to arrest Mr. Weaver led to an exchange of gunfire that day in which a deputy marshal and Mr. Weaver's 14-year-old son were killed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Potts's statement to the investigative team indicated that F.B.I. officials began the operation with poor information about events on Ruby Ridge, the mountaintop where the Weavers lived. Richard Rogers, commander of the rescue unit at the time, took control at the scene but made no attempt to interview the marshals who had survived the initial encounter, the report found.</p>
        <p>The next afternoon, Aug. 22, Mr. Horiuchi fired two shots. The first bullet struck Mr. Weaver in the shoulder as he emerged from the cabin with a family friend, Kevin Harris. The second, fired as the pair retreated to the Weaver cabin, struck and killed Ms. Weaver, 43, and then seriously wounded Mr. Harris as he dived into the cabin. F.B.I. agents later admitted that Vicki Weaver was shot by mistake. After a 10-day siege, Mr. Weaver surrendered.</p>
        <p>Later, Federal prosecutors obtained an indictment charging Mr. Weaver and Mr. Harris in the killing of the deputy marshal. Both were acquitted in the killing as the case collapsed in the welter of accusations that the Government had mishandled the entire episode.</p>
        <p>Several issues lingered after the siege, but the one most hotly debated was whether F.B.I. officials acted improperly by altering standard rules of engagement to direct sharpshooters to shoot at any adult seen outside the cabin with a weapon. Mr. Rogers testified at Mr. Weaver's trial that his group had never before operated under such rules.</p>
        <p>Mr. Potts and his deputy at the time, Danny O. Coulson, now agent in charge in Dallas, believed that the Ruby Ridge crisis was "the most dangerous situation into which the H.R.T. had ever gone," the report said. Mr. Coulson told investigators, "It was my belief that as soon as H.R.T. personnel arrived at the scene they would be in grave peril."</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Rogers wrote rules that the agents said corresponded to the dangerous situation they confronted.</p>
        <p>The report said Mr. Potts told investigators that he did not discuss the rules with the F.B.I.'s lawyers, contending that a legal review was not usually sought in such a crisis because "rules of engagement are written to fall within the bound of the F.B.I's standard deadly force policy."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
