<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Full Strength Against Ukraine</title>
    <meta content="PL033505" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1070923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PLUS: SOCCER -- U.S. WOMEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ukraine</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EED9163CF93AA25751C1A96E958260" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Full Strength Against Ukraine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States women's national soccer tea will be back at full strength for exhibition rematch with Ukraine (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States women's national team, one of the favorites to win the Women's World Cup next summer, will be back at normal strength for tomorrow's exhibition rematch with Ukraine, four days after a lesser version took the field. The regulars had threatened to skip tomorrow's game unless their two-year-old contract with the United States Soccer Federation was altered.</p>
        <p>The match at Bulldog Stadium in Fresno, Calif., will be the last one of 1998 for the women's team, which has a 20-1-2 record this year. The United States defeated Ukraine, 2-1, on Wednesday at U.C.L.A. in Los Angeles in a game that was closed to spectators and with a roster that included nine women making their first appearances for the United States national team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States women's national team, one of the favorites to win the Women's World Cup next summer, will be back at normal strength for tomorrow's exhibition rematch with Ukraine, four days after a lesser version took the field. The regulars had threatened to skip tomorrow's game unless their two-year-old contract with the United States Soccer Federation was altered.</p>
        <p>The match at Bulldog Stadium in Fresno, Calif., will be the last one of 1998 for the women's team, which has a 20-1-2 record this year. The United States defeated Ukraine, 2-1, on Wednesday at U.C.L.A. in Los Angeles in a game that was closed to spectators and with a roster that included nine women making their first appearances for the United States national team.</p>
        <p>It was the first time in the 186-game history of the American women's program in which a member of the 1991 World Cup championship team did not play. It also marked the end of Kristine Lilly's streak of 63 games started. The roster included none of the team's fixtures, such as Mia Hamm, Julie Foudy or Carla Overbeck.</p>
        <p>Ostensibly, the match was used by Coach Tony DiCicco to fill the three remaining spots on the team's training-camp roster. Early next month, the 26 players will gather in Seminole County, Fla., for the six-month run-up to the first game of the World Cup.</p>
        <p>I have to protect our sponsors and our television partners, so we did the things that were necessary to field a team, said Hank Steinbrecher, the United States Soccer Federation's Secretary General, about the decision to field a team of lesser-known players on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The women's contract with the U.S.S.F. runs through the Pan American Games next August. The federation is the players' sole employer, and without a women's professional league to pay salaries, the federation signs players to bonus-laden contracts that provide incentives for such things as international appearances, goals scored and victories.</p>
        <p>According to Steinbrecher, the federation will spend about $2.1 million on the team as it prepares for the World Cup.</p>
        <p>The players presented a list of things they wanted; not all of them were monetary issues, and we agreed with many of them, Steinbrecher said. Our goal is to be fair-minded. I feel they went about it in a professional way, and we got a new deal. Actually, there are enhancements to the current deal. We never thought that their demands were outrageous; they all seemed to be team oriented.</p>
        <p>Among the enhancements were an increase in living expenses for the players during their six-month stay in Florida, and the settlement of maternity and child-care issues. The agreement was completed last Friday, apparently too late for the federation to alter its plan to field an alternate roster on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The United States, the defending Olympic gold medalist, was one of four nations this week seeded for the four-team, four-group first round in the 16-team event. The others are China, Norway and Germany.</p>
        <p>JACK BELL</p>
        <p>PLUS: SOCCER -- U.S. WOMEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
