<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Philadelphia Journal;   Cries of Poverty in Cradle of Liberty</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="391397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDEPENDENCE NATIONAL HISTORIC PARK (PHILADELPHIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA (PA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL PARK SERVICE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DD153AF937A25753C1A966958260" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Philadelphia Journal;   Cries of Poverty in Cradle of Liberty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL deCOURCY HINDS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Oct. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Stepping into history, possibly to escape the drone of Federal deficit reports, tourists stream into the Cradle of Liberty here at the rate of 14,177 visitors a day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Stepping into history, possibly to escape the drone of Federal deficit reports, tourists stream into the Cradle of Liberty here at the rate of 14,177 visitors a day.</p>
        <p>Stepping into history, possibly to escape the drone of Federal deficit reports, tourists stream into the Cradle of Liberty here at the rate of 14,177 visitors a day.</p>
        <p>But for some that escape turns into confusion and angry outbursts when they see ''Closed Until Further Notice'' signs on nearly half the historic buildings around Independence National Historical Park.</p>
        <p>Isn't the Government back in business? Yes, it is, but the more immediate budget wranglings are not the cause of the proliferation of forbidding signs in the historic area.</p>
        <p>For the past decade National Park Service officials, who mind the cradle, say they have not had enough money to keep it in good repair. And when this lean and uncertain fiscal year began Oct. 1, the rangers had to make a difficult choice on spending. They could either keep all the buildings open and not make repairs, or they could close some of the buildings and lay off employees to come up with the money to pay for the repairs.</p>
        <p>With a porous roof over Independence Hall and squirrels burrowing into 18th century cornices everywhere, the rangers decided to make repairs and lock up buildings.</p>
        <p>''We had to cut visitor services because we're not taking care of the buildings the way we should,'' said Hobart B. Cawood, superintendent of this grassy Colonial oasis that occupies four whole downtown blocks and pieces of 13 others. This summer, he said, almost an entire block of Independence Mall had to be abandoned because of dangerous sidewalks, broken benches, busted street lamps and rotting horse-hitching posts.</p>
        <p>The park's annual budget has stayed at about $7 million for seven years, and despite ever-rising visitor traffic, the Park Service has reduced its staff to 173 people from 226. ''The roof on Independence Hall is in very bad shape,'' said Mr. Cawood, pointing at the shingled roof. He said the park needed $9 million to function normally, but that his best hope was for $8.25 million this year.</p>
        <p>For the past three years, he said, he has appealed in vain for a new roof over the building where the Constitution and the Declaration of Independence were signed, and where Congress met from 1790 to 1800.</p>
        <p>Instead of a $175,000 new roof, Mr. Cawood received $60,000 this year to buy shingles and his short-staffed crew of carpenters fixed half the roof. Another $75,000 has been promised to finish the job next year. ''The Hall should be safe,'' he added, cautiously.</p>
        <p>Independence Hall, the Liberty Bell, Ben Franklin's print shop and other major attractions remain open, but the Park Service closed 8 of its 19 historic buildings, mainly those that attracted fewer visitors.</p>
        <p>''Closed Until Further Notice'' signs were posted Oct. 1 outside the Second Bank of the United States; Old City Hall, where the Supreme Court first convened in 1791; the Graff House, where Thomas Jefferson drafted the Declaration of Independence; the home of Dolley Todd, who married James Madison, the fourth President; three military museums, including one for the Marine Corps, which got its start here in 1775. More than 600,000 people a year used to visit these sites, which Mr. Cawood said would not be reopened until next spring, at the earliest.</p>
        <p>He said other buildings might have to be closed, including Congress Hall, where Congress drafted the First Amendment. That could cause problems for the city's Convention and Visitors Bureau, which plans a bicentennial celebration of the ratification of the Bill of Rights.</p>
        <p>Closing such popular sites may seem penny-wise and pound-foolish, since they are the biggest attraction for tourists and their money in this city, which needs all the money it can get to avert its own fiscal crisis; insolvency is scheduled for Dec. 1 unless the state helps.</p>
        <p>The closings have stirred patriots to anger. ''To me it is absolutely unthinkable that there are not enough funds to keep the Cradle of American Liberty in tip-top condition,'' said Robert J. Williams, an editor at the now-defunct Philadelphia Bulletin. ''When I went to school, we were brought up to look upon this place as the place where it all started, where modern democracy was born, and you get a certain reverence for it.''</p>
        <p>Out-of-towners are also bewildered. ''It's a shame,'' said Jerry Guenther, a visitor from Dallas. ''For a lot of people, it's a once-in-a-lifetime visit.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
