<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PAPERBACK BEST SELLERS: October 14, 1990</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="391879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">LIST</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDC1F26E232BC4852DFB66F958A" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PAPERBACK BEST SELLERS: October 14, 1990</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>$</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Fiction</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>THE DARK HALF, by Stephen King. (Signet, $5.95.) A writer of horror tales kills off his pseudonym, who then goes on a rampage.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>PRESUMED INNOCENT, by Scott Turow. (Warner, $5.95.) A brutal murder creates a crisis among a big city's politicians and lawyers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>$</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Fiction</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>THE DARK HALF, by Stephen King. (Signet, $5.95.) A writer of horror tales kills off his pseudonym, who then goes on a rampage.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>PRESUMED INNOCENT, by Scott Turow. (Warner, $5.95.) A brutal murder creates a crisis among a big city's politicians and lawyers.</p>
        <p>$</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Fiction</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>THE DARK HALF, by Stephen King. (Signet, $5.95.) A writer of horror tales kills off his pseudonym, who then goes on a rampage.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>PRESUMED INNOCENT, by Scott Turow. (Warner, $5.95.) A brutal murder creates a crisis among a big city's politicians and lawyers.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>POSTCARDS FROM THE EDGE, by Carrie Fisher. (Pocket, $4.95.) A drug-addicted actress's battles with her alcoholic mother.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE MINOTAUR, by Stephen Coonts. (Dell, $5.95.) The hunt for a mole in the Pentagon who is giving secrets to the Russians.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>CALIFORNIA GOLD, by John Jakes. (Ballantine, $5.95.) A young man from Pennsylvania makes his fortune in 19th-century California.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>SO WORTHY MY LOVE, by Kathleen E. Woodiwiss. (Avon, $5.95.) The abduction of a woman leads to romance in Elizabethan England.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>OLDEST LIVING CONFEDERATE WIDOW TELLS ALL, by Allan Gurganus. (Ivy, $6.95.) A 99-year-old woman reflects on her past.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>THE SECRET DIARY OF LAURA PALMER, by Jennifer Lynch. (Pocket, $8.95.) The journal of a ''Twin Peaks'' television character.</p>
        <p>9 *</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>ENEMY UNSEEN, by V. E. Mitchell. (Pocket, $4.50.) Captain Kirk on a mission to stop a ruthless assassin; a new ''Star Trek'' adventure.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>THE PILLARS OF THE EARTH, by Ken Follett. (Signet, $5.95.) Murder, arson, treachery, love and lust surround the building of a cathedral in 12th-century England.</p>
        <p>11 *</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>NEMESIS, by Isaac Asimov. (Bantam, $5.95.) A girl on the planet Rotor in the 23d century seeks ways to save Earth from destruction.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>CLEAR AND PRESENT DANGER, by Tom Clancy. (Berkley, $5.95.) The C.I.A.'s Jack Ryan fights Colombian drug lords.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>ISLE OF VIEW, by Piers Anthony. (Avon, $4.95.) Romance and catastrophe beset inhabitants of the fantasy land of Xanth.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>COLD HARBOUR, by Jack Higgins. (Pocket, $5.95.) The O.S.S. agent Craig Osbourne on a perilous mission during World War II.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>THE JOY LUCK CLUB, by Amy Tan. (Ivy, $5.95.) The tensions and bonds shared by Chinese-American women and their immigrant mothers.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Nonfiction</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>47</p>
        <p>ALL I REALLY NEED TO KNOW I LEARNED IN KINDERGARTEN, by Robert Fulghum. (Ivy, $5.95.) Inspirational essays.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>364</p>
        <p>THE ROAD LESS TRAVELED, by M. Scott Peck. (Touchstone/S&amp;S, $10.95.) Psychological and spiritual inspiration by a psychiatrist.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>FROM BEIRUT TO JERUSALEM, by Thomas L. Friedman. (Anchor/Doubleday, $12.95.) The Arab-Israeli conflict as observed by a New York Times correspondent over the past decade.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>19</p>
        <p>A BRIEF HISTORY OF TIME, by Stephen W. Hawking. (Bantam, $9.95.) A scientist reviews efforts to create a unified theory of the universe.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>THE ROAD FROM COORAIN, by Jill Ker Conway. (Vintage, $8.95.) A historian recalls her childhood on an Australian sheep farm.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>AMONG SCHOOLCHILDREN, by Tracy Kidder. (Avon, $9.95.) A year in the life of a fifth-grade teacher in Holyoke, Mass.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>I WANT TO GROW HAIR, I WANT TO GROW UP, I WANT TO GO TO BOISE, by Erma Bombeck. (Harper Paperbacks, $5.50.) Fifteen stories of children surviving cancer.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>EXIT THE RAINMAKER, by Jonathan Coleman. (Dell, $4.95.) The enigmatic case of a successful Maryland college president who disappeared and began a new life.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>LIAR'S POKER, by Michael Lewis. (Penguin, $8.95.) Wall Street's tumultuous 1980's, as witnessed by a young bond trader.</p>
        <p>10 *</p>
        <p>112</p>
        <p>LOVE, MEDICINE, AND MIRACLES, by Bernie S. Siegel. (Perennial/HarperCollins, $8.95.) The importance of a patient's mind and emotions.</p>
        <p>Weeks</p>
        <p>This</p>
        <p>On</p>
        <p>Week</p>
        <p>List</p>
        <p>Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>THE AUTHORITATIVE CALVIN AND HOBBES, by Bill Watterson. (Andrews &amp; McMeel, $12.95.) Cartoons from ''Yukon Ho!'' and ''Weirdos From Another Planet!''</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>TOXIC PARENTS, by Susan Forward with Craig Buck. (Bantam, $5.95.) Ways by which you can improve your relationship with your parents.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>110</p>
        <p>CODEPENDENT NO MORE, by Melody Beattie. (Hazelden/HarperSanFrancisco, $8.95.) Solving your own problems while caring for other people's afflictions.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>THE OLD FARMER'S ALMANAC 1991. (Yankee Publishing, $2.95.) The 199th annual edition.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>THE T-FACTOR FAT GRAM COUNTER, by Jamie Pope-Cordle and Martin Katahn. (Norton, $2.50.) How to reduce fat in one's diet.</p>
        <p>These listings are based on computer-processed sales figures from 3,000 bookstores and from representative wholesalers with more than 38,000 other retail outlets, including variety stores and supermarkets. The figures are statistically adjusted to represent sales in all such outlets across the United States.</p>
        <p>*An asterisk before a book's title indicates that its sales, weighted to reflect the book-selling industry nationally, are barely distinguishable from those of the book above.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
