<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doing In Filthy Jack</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="391882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CRIME/MYSTERY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUBINS, JOSH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARNARD, ROBERT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CITY OF STRANGERS, A (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDA1F26E232BC4852DFB66F958A" item-length="1195" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doing In Filthy Jack</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSH RUBINS; Josh Rubins writes a mystery column for Entertainment Weekly.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RUBINS, JOSH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>A CITY OF STRANGERS</p>
        <p>By Robert Barnard.</p>
        <p>287 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Charles Scribner's Sons. $18.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>A CITY OF STRANGERS</p>
        <p>By Robert Barnard.</p>
        <p>287 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Charles Scribner's Sons. $18.95.</p>
        <p>A CITY OF STRANGERS</p>
        <p>By Robert Barnard.</p>
        <p>287 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Charles Scribner's Sons. $18.95.</p>
        <p>How do you make a murder mystery merry? After all, death by violence is hardly an inherently cheerful topic. Yet from G. K. Chesterton onward, gifted mystery writers (English ones especially) have found ways to bring a genial, even jovial spirit to tales of homicide. One favorite way: make the murder victim as thoroughly loathsome, as unredeemably toxic, as possible - someone, that is, who's virtually begging to be done in. Not only does this remove any hint of tragedy from the central demise, it also guarantees an abundance of likely suspects and juicy motives, since such a vile specimen is sure to have a long list of well-earned enemies.</p>
        <p>Robert Barnard, the most reliable and versatile practitioner of English mystery-comedy on the present scene, is a virtuoso when it comes to this man (or woman)-you-love-to-hate technique. ''Death of a Perfect Mother'' (1981) featured the perfectly hateful Lill Hodsden, whose children were only some of the people with good reason to wish her dead. The title character in ''Death of a Mystery Writer'' (1979), the bullying Sir Oliver Fairleigh-Stubbs, deserved everything he got.</p>
        <p>And now ''A City of Strangers,'' notwithstanding its somber title and its often stark details, presents Mr. Barnard's most exuberantly nasty corpse-to-be thus far. Meet Jack Phelan, the scourge of the Belfield Grove Estate, a working-class development in the bleak suburbs of a contemporary Yorkshire city called Sleate. (Mr. Barnard lives in a contemporary Yorkshire city called Leeds.) A father of six, contentedly unemployed for nearly 20 years, filthy Jack spends his days guzzling beer, insulting the neighbors, picking fights, breaking furniture, hurting people whenever the opportunity arises - ''like a football hooligan grown up.'' (Says the widow next door: ''He never changed, only . . . ripened, you might say.'') He resents having to send his children to school, however briefly. The vicious Phelan teen-agers, Kevin and June, are already hardened criminals; the younger kids, with one miraculous exception, are precociously depraved. When the family descends on a local supermarket, the townsfolk scatter:</p>
        <p>''There were five of them going the rounds of the aisles: the parents, June, Jackie, and Dale. Dale's push-chair and the supermarket trolley made them a formidable group to encounter - practically an armored battalion. Jack pushed the trolley aggressively, shouted instructions, got out of no one's way, cursed old ladies who were peering at prices to save a penny or two on a packet of teabags, and abused one of the shelf-boys who happened to be black. 'I wouldn't go to a Paki shop and I don't expect to see the buggers here,' he shouted ostensibly to his wife, really to all and sundry, and the black youth in particular, who was in fact Caribbean.''</p>
        <p>Imagine the uproar, then, when rumors begin circulating that Jack Phelan has won a fortune ''on the pools'' - and intends to move self and family up the road to quiet, lovely, fiercely middle-class Wynton Lane, where one of the splendid late-Victorian houses is up for sale. Jack, a compulsive mischief-maker, revels in the shock and dismay, the fury, of Wynton Lane's current residents. So does Mr. Barnard, who sketches in the five very different white-collar households involved - hotbeds of neurosis and genteel hypocrisy - with a droll shrewdness and ruthless economy that are reminiscent of Agatha Christie at her very best. (Mr. Barnard's critical study of Christie, ''A Talent to Deceive,'' pays tribute to her underappreciated flair for social comedy.) But though the Wynton Lane dwellers band together in a not-in-my-backyard frenzy, they soon realize that they're powerless to prevent the infamous Phelans (who show up in all their slovenly, derisive glory to ''view'' the property) from buying anything they can afford - which means that when the Phelans' old house is torched, with paterfamilias Jack the sole fatality, Superintendent Mike Oddie has no shortage of possible candidates for the role of arsonist. Up on Wynton Lane there are all those respectable but highly motivated homeowners - including such improbable prospects as Mrs. Rosamund Eastlake, a longtime invalid obsessed with the retired school principal Daphne Bridewell. There are also, given Jack's personality (and his supposed recent windfall), more than a few questions to put to the not-so-grieving widow and other family members.</p>
        <p>Of course, mystery writers who make jolly good use of the monstrous-victim gambit do inevitably encounter one potential drawback. Their most colorful character disappears - permanently - somewhere in the book's first half, and there's always a risk that things may pale noticeably thereafter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barnard, however, canny pro that he is, more than compensates his readers for the loss of Jack Phelan's entertainingly abominable, almost Dickensian presence. In the novel's second half, he sustains the Phelan flavor by shifting attention to the appalling son Kevin, who terrorizes minority merchants, and his sister June, a blase, small-time tart; they, together with parents and siblings, ultimately become a convincing microcosm of Thatcherite Britain's new underclass -''riotous, savage, with nothing to lose.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Barnard deepens his wry portraits of the nervous householders, developing a few of them - studies in hypochondria, sexual repression and male complacency - into tidy, satisfying subplots. (The standout: Mrs. Eastlake, who, roused from her sickbed by the invigorating anti-Phelan fuss, reinvents herself.) And Superintendent Oddie's low-key yet firmly paced sleuthing leads, by way of some bona fide Christie-like twists, to the surprise unmasking of the killer: a monster, no less so than Jack Phelan, but one of a distinctly less amusing sort.</p>
        <p>In the end, in fact, ''A City of Strangers'' turns out to be not quite so merry after all. Having lured us in and cozied us up with Jack Phelan's extravagant (though never cartoonish) awfulness, Mr. Barnard subtly modulates his tone, from jocular to gravely ironic, as the plot's darker, more suspenseful elements take over. The result is as good an example as any of the humorous mystery novel at its unpretentious best: playful but far from giddy, perfectly poised between drollery (part satire, part human comedy) and the stern realities of crime and punishment.</p>
        <p>THE FAMILY THE TOWN LOVED TO HATE</p>
        <p>Coming along Wynton Lane [Rosamund]  saw a little squad of people: a heavy, dirty man who looked as if he had slept in his clothes for the past week; a slatternly woman pushing a push-chair and shoving forward the toddler who belonged in it, but who was instead walking beside her; a teenage girl, deplorably dressed, making a precocious attempt at sexiness; and lastly a smaller girl, maybe just of school age, but still uncertain on her feet. . . . What a gang!</p>
        <p>Suddenly it came to her. The Phelans! This must be the Phelans. With feelings of dread mixed with excitement she watched their progress down the road.</p>
        <p>From ''A City of Strangers.''  CRIME/MYSTERY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
