<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Loneliness of the Last-Chance Canner</title>
    <meta content="26RhomeCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1807363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="HOME WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7D8123EF935A15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Loneliness of the Last-Chance Canner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA SHAINE CUNNINGHAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cunningham, Laura Shaine</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JEWELS. Everyone who cans vegetables or fruits exclaims over those jewel-like jars lining their pantry shelves, or standing in gleaming rows down in the cellar. There is a pioneer pride -- ''I canned those, and they will last me until spring!'' The fantasy is that I will have put up so many jars of tomatoes and plums that they will sustain me through the winter season.</p>
        <p>Part of the dream is that I will share this bounty with family and friends, presenting the Ball jars with beribboned covered lids as au naturel holiday gifts. It's possible, in this fantasy, to believe that the jars themselves are so beautiful that no one ever opens them; in my mind, I see those quart jars as endowed with semi-immortality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JEWELS. Everyone who cans vegetables or fruits exclaims over those jewel-like jars lining their pantry shelves, or standing in gleaming rows down in the cellar. There is a pioneer pride -- ''I canned those, and they will last me until spring!'' The fantasy is that I will have put up so many jars of tomatoes and plums that they will sustain me through the winter season.</p>
        <p>Part of the dream is that I will share this bounty with family and friends, presenting the Ball jars with beribboned covered lids as au naturel holiday gifts. It's possible, in this fantasy, to believe that the jars themselves are so beautiful that no one ever opens them; in my mind, I see those quart jars as endowed with semi-immortality.</p>
        <p>One year -- was it 1999? -- I actually did can 60 quarts of golden heirloom tomatoes for a surefire Golden Pasta Sauce that gave everyone fits of gustatory rapture. But this year I waited too long and had to resort to desperate measures to put up more than a measly half-pint, containing what even I can barely bear to call ''my produce.''</p>
        <p>Produce? I planted late -- ha! I planted when it was almost fall -- so my ''harvest'' was a measly few green cherry tomatoes from a lone drooping vine. I had willed them, ''Ripen, redden,'' but I was too late. I had waited until tomatoes were scarce and more than $3 a pound. I had let the bargain bushels of bursting red and golden tomatoes, featured at the corner farm stand, slip past at 99 cents or less a pound.</p>
        <p>There is always a week, at the very end of harvest time, when the farm stands almost give them away. ''Here,'' they cry, ''take that bushel over there!'' That is the time to grab them, ripe but not rotted, and go into the marathon of canning.</p>
        <p>I should have been hanging over my steaming caldrons in September at the latest. November was pushing the envelope. I dashed around in October on an almost Biblical gleaning, searching the fields of nearby farms for what was left. I spotted a few signs that read ''Fall Raspberries'' and picked the berry canes clean. I could not leave a rubylike raspberry to perish in the bush. Not when it could become jam.</p>
        <p>I ranged far and wide in the final days before frost, gathering the last-minute bounty. Fall actually offers amazing produce: besides autumn raspberries, there are Concord grapes, pears, peppers, apples, pumpkin and squash. At one of my favorite farms in Ulster County, the lady farmer, who is over 80, was still canning herself; I mean that in a literal sense. Her shirt was stiffened with juices; she was steamed into her own Colonial kitchen. Elsa, as she is known, was born in her 1700s stone farmhouse; her father was born in it also. They still have cows and chickens, and fenced areas where you can pick tomatoes, peppers, eggplant, squash and zucchini.</p>
        <p>Elsa cans night and day, putting up jams, tomatoes and whatever else can be sealed in a glass jar. In my panic, I even considered buying Elsa's jars and passing them off as my own. Though she sells jam, Elsa will never sell her plums -- she pointed to 40 gleaming jars and said, ''I am saving those for myself!''</p>
        <p>What I lacked in foresight, I made up in demented desire, driving south to New Jersey and Long Island, scouring fruit stands in warmer climes. (I considered Delaware and Maryland, but ran out of gas.) As a last gasp, leaving work in the city, I snatched imported tomatoes from deluxe Manhattan markets, rationalizing their high prices by telling myself they were at least ripe and juicy, not the desiccated pale, tasteless tomatoes that would confront me by December.</p>
        <p>November found me in a lunatic, insomniac frenzy. I am here to tell you, late autumn is actually a good time to can -- fewer fruit flies, less humidity. The steaming pots heat the kitchen in a cozy manner.</p>
        <p>Admittedly, the enterprise has a desperate, last-chance aspect. ''If I don't can tonight, I will have to settle'' -- for commercial canned, the taste of tin, or too much salt, whatever it is that just makes store-bought not nearly so delectable as even these 11th-hour home-canned goods.</p>
        <p>I set up my kitchen in ''double, double, toil and trouble'' mode. I have a 20-year-old canning kit, nothing fancy. All one really needs is a giant pot (the canner). I have never invested in the pressurized sort; they strike me as too potentially explosive -- a tomato Vesuvius that could erupt. (Still, I eye those canners at yard sales and think, ''maybe someday.'' ) For now, I am content with the giant pot and the gear I love: the quaint jar lifters and racks, strainers, pit removers, ladles and that clever jar neck funnel that saves me from so many splatters and spills. On the side, I have my beloved Ball jars -- I like wide necks -- lids and rings.</p>
        <p>The hardest part is the prep: washing, pitting, possibly peeling. I have simplified this process by only washing. Pits are no problem, I have decided: seeds are great fiber. Peels contain the most vitamins. So I am a Cro-Magnon canner as opposed to a Nigella Lawson. The jars of canned tomatoes and fruit are pithy, but delicious.</p>
        <p>But I made a final serious miscalculation this year; even after all my effort, I wound up with only 10 jars. I considered keeping them all, like Elsa. Then I think, ''Maybe four jars to friends?'' Really good friends, who will appreciate their specialness and that they now cost more than anything in even the most overpriced gourmet deli. Or maybe I should regard the preserves as permanent -- objets d'art to line the kitchen windowsill? But no, they are juicy, and I will crave that taste of the real thing when it is no longer available otherwise.</p>
        <p>Make it through the winter? Even until Christmas? Maybe I should just admit defeat in the immortality department, and eat them now.</p>
        <p>HOME WORK Laura Shaine Cunningham is the author of the memoirs ''Sleeping Arrangements'' and ''A Place in the Country.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Laura Shaine Cunningham is the author of the memoirs ''Sleeping Arrangements'' and ''A Place in the Country.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
