<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heart Bypass Less Risky Last Year, Albany Says</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="658560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGERY AND SURGEONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGERY AND SURGEONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HEALTH DEPARTMENT (NYS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HEALTH DEPARTMENT (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, ELISABETH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, ELISABETH</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HEALTH DEPARTMENT (NYS)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Heart Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D71538F934A15751C1A965958260" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heart Bypass Less Risky Last Year, Albany Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, ELISABETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The risk of dying from heart bypass surgery in New York State continued to drop last year, and was lower than in any other region that collects similar information, according to the State Health Department.</p>
        <p>Those were the conclusions of an annual study by the department, which has been conducted for the last three years. The study calculates the risk of dying from bypass surgery in each hospital and at the hands of each cardiac surgeon who performs more than 200 operations a year. The rating is adjusted to take into account that some institutions and doctors treat sicker patients, who are less likely to survive surgery regardless of its quality. The result is a so-called risk-adjusted mortality rate. Most Rates Similar</p>
        <p>A vast majority of the 31 hospitals in the state licensed to do the surgery had rates statistically indistinguishable from one another. Only New York University Medical Center, with a rate of 1.38 percent, was statistically significantly better than the other hospitals in the state. Only St. Peter's Hospital in Albany, with a rate of 5.78 percent, was significantly worse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The risk of dying from heart bypass surgery in New York State continued to drop last year, and was lower than in any other region that collects similar information, according to the State Health Department.</p>
        <p>Those were the conclusions of an annual study by the department, which has been conducted for the last three years. The study calculates the risk of dying from bypass surgery in each hospital and at the hands of each cardiac surgeon who performs more than 200 operations a year. The rating is adjusted to take into account that some institutions and doctors treat sicker patients, who are less likely to survive surgery regardless of its quality. The result is a so-called risk-adjusted mortality rate. Most Rates Similar</p>
        <p>A vast majority of the 31 hospitals in the state licensed to do the surgery had rates statistically indistinguishable from one another. Only New York University Medical Center, with a rate of 1.38 percent, was statistically significantly better than the other hospitals in the state. Only St. Peter's Hospital in Albany, with a rate of 5.78 percent, was significantly worse.</p>
        <p>Erie County Medical Center, which has the statewide high death rate of 8.78 percent, performed too few operations in 1992 for the rate to be considered reliable for the study. But the hospital "has had a lot of trouble in the past few years and is in the process of reorganizing their program," said Peter Slocum, a spokesman for the Health Department.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mark R. Chassin, the State Commissioner of Health, and others said the report should be extremely useful for the hospitals and surgeons striving to improve the quality of their care, but might be less helpful for an individual trying to choose among the hospitals and surgeons in the middle of the ratings. Health Score Cards</p>
        <p>"I think that these data are most useful for informing and energizing local quality improvement," said Dr. Chassin, noting that such efforts to evaluate care are likely to become increasingly common, since President Clinton has proposed health score cards for hospitals as part of his reform package. Dr. Chassin said that such data encouraged those with below-average rates to re-evaluate and modify their procedures. Over all, the statewide risk-adjusted mortality rate has fallen to 2.5 percent, down from 3.5 in 1990 the first year the survey was performed.</p>
        <p>"I do think it is useful for patients, but you shouldn't use it as the only source on information about where to get your surgery," he said, adding that a relatively poor performance in 1992 might now be irrelevant if the hospital had revamped its cardiac surgery program.</p>
        <p>Indeed, because of statistical shifts as well as improvement efforts, many of the hospitals that were at the extremes of last year's list are now in the middle. Only St. Peter's has been at the bottom for two years running, but it is revising its procedures for taking care of the sickest patients and said it expects improvement in next year's survey. Rating Cardiac Surgeons</p>
        <p>The report also provides weighted death rates for 87 cardiac surgeons based on their performance in the last three years, which range from a low of 0.63 percent to a high of 7.4 percent. Four surgeons had significantly fewer deaths than average and eight had significantly more.</p>
        <p>The Department of Health has prepared a booklet containing all the information that can be obtained through cardiologists or by writing: Cardiac, Box 2000, New York State Department of Health, Albany, N.Y. 12220.</p>
        <p>Except in extreme cases, the state does not use these data to discipline hospitals or surgeons, but relies on the public release of such numbers to spur the professional pride of those with poor records.</p>
        <p>"From the consumer's perspective we think that this kind of disclosure saves lives and allows the consumer to smart-shop," said Blair Horner, legislative director of the New York Public Interest Research Group.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Valentin Fuster, chief of the cardiac unit at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston, warned that the data have the potential for misuse: "I think this is a very constructive process, but it has to be interpreted with caution. I wouldn't want the public to start ranking hospitals since they are all very close and No. 14 this month could be No. 2 next month with new statistics."</p>
        <p>New York is currently planning similar reports on different kinds of procedures, from laparoscopic surgery to breast cancer care. "Our one criticism is that the State Health Department hasn't moved fast enough" Mr. Horner said, noting that Pennsylvania now evaluates 50 different procedures.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
