<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Man Who Loved Chekhov</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="644137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PROSE, FRANCINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OZ, AMOS</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FIMA (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D71239F937A15753C1A965958260" item-length="1025" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Man Who Loved Chekhov</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Francine Prose;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PROSE, FRANCINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIMA By Amos Oz. Translated by Nicholas de Lange. 322 pp. New York: A Helen and Kurt Wolff Book/ Harcourt Brace &amp; Company. $22.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIMA By Amos Oz. Translated by Nicholas de Lange. 322 pp. New York: A Helen and Kurt Wolff Book/ Harcourt Brace &amp; Company. $22.95.</p>
        <p>BEGINNING Amos Oz's new novel, "Fima," we meet Efraim Nisan (Fima) awakening from a troubling dream, and we may think of how Kafka's "Metamorphosis" begins with Gregor Samsa only just awakening from bad dreams of his own. Reading "Fima" has the strange effect of making it seem less awful to wake up, as Gregor Samsa did, transformed into a cockroach. At least that is a transformation, albeit to a lower life-form.</p>
        <p>Fima's existence could hardly be more unchanging or stagnant. At 54, he lives alone in a squalid Jerusalem apartment, eating badly, with dirty clothes and slovenly personal habits: "Not really living. Just existing. Creeping from day to day. . . . Hanging around here like last year's snow." His early promise as a poet has come to nothing; he works as a receptionist at a gynecological clinic, a job that requires the skills of a telephone operator, a triage nurse, a psychologist and a janitor. His sense of involvement in Israeli politics, and in his country's future, has degenerated into tired political arguments with his right-wing father, windy debates with like-minded friends and elaborate Walter Mitty-like fantasies in which Fima summons parliaments and organizes mass movements to realize his brilliantly simple solutions to Israel's most complex problems. His attitude toward his aged father mirrors his feelings about his nation: exasperation, disappointment, worry and fatigue.</p>
        <p>When he's not "fantasizing about seizing power or bringing peace to the land," Fima is kept busy sorting out his many tepid but nonetheless messy personal imbroglios. He's having two dysfunctional love affairs, one with the wife of a close friend and one with a patient at the clinic. He's still involved with his ex-wife, Yael, a woman who knows him well enough to tell him more truth about himself than anyone might want to hear. And he has grown to adore Dimi, Yael's small son by her second husband.</p>
        <p>But despite his worldly entanglements, Fima's real life is, as they say, in his head, where he conducts a nonstop interior monologue that's Talmudic in its intensity and its attention to detail. His obsessions are metaphysics, politics, sex, guilt, ethical obligation, suffering and evil -- and the mystical or concrete ways in which these abstractions connect. Not until "the sad event" we are warned of in the novel's first sentence does Fima truly awaken and start to take responsibility, instead of merely dithering about what the concept means.</p>
        <p>"Fima" is one of those novels in which we begin to suspect that the protagonist is meant to be emblematic of a generation. Surely Fima isn't the only Israeli idealist of a certain age reduced by the current political climate to compulsive newspaper reading and arguing with the radio. But it's one of that smaller, more exclusive group of novels that manage something trickier: it succeeds in making us believe in the particular, individual life of this man of his generation, and sympathize with him.</p>
        <p>Structurally, the novel bumbles along not unlike its hero, whom it follows through the days before "the sad event." So it's with a certain shock that we realize how involved we've become in the fate of a man whom it's hard to admire or like. Partly this is a consequence of Mr. Oz's authorial skill. As the book progresses, Fima's experiences and reflections grow steadily more lyrical, more heartfelt and less clownish. We're startled by the sweetness of Fima's reveries about his mother, who died when he was a child, and by a harrowing scene in which Yael forces Fima to confront the residue of sorrow left over from an abortion she had when they were married. This confrontation sparks, in Fima, a memory of an afternoon he spent with Yael: a passage of beautiful writing about sex that becomes in this context (aided here by Nicholas de Lange's smooth translation) evocative and wrenching.</p>
        <p>Watching Yael and Fima argue, we sympathize with them both. And this evenhandedness, this ability to make us see two sides at once, may have even more to do with the novel's success than its narrative structure or tone. Amos Oz -- the eminent Israeli novelist and essayist best known here for such books as "Black Box" and "Elsewhere, Perhaps" -- is faultlessly patient and tender with his characters. He never judges Fima for what some might see as childishness, laziness and self-indulgence. So, too, he gives his minor characters their dignity and their due. When one of Fima's lovers, an abandoned wife, raves on about her problems, she's not the shrill female hysteric we may recognize from so much contemporary fiction. Rather, we're reminded of Anna Sergeyevna in Chekhov's story "The Lady With the Little Dog," enduring her tearful attack of remorse in Gurov's hotel room.</p>
        <p>IN a discussion with one of his lovers about Latin American literature and magic realism, Fima asserts that "for his money, he would give the whole of this South American circus, with all its fireworks and cotton candy, for a single page of Chekhov. 'A Hundred Years of Solitude' for just one 'Lady With the Little Dog.' " Without sharing Fima's low estimation of Gabriel Garcia Marquez, readers may recognize this as a signal that in case they haven't noticed, the spirit of Chekhov is hovering over these pages. Not only does Mr. Oz strive toward a Chekhovian compassion for his characters, but his novel depends -- as many Chekhov stories do -- on making us believe in the possibility of last-minute grace.</p>
        <p>When tragedy strikes, we watch Fima rise to the occasion and begin to tap his own resources of generosity, humility, common sense, and his sense of purpose. By the novel's end, we're no longer thinking of Kafka's "Metamorphosis" but of more hopeful, autumnal fictions, for example Chekhov's story "The Duel." We no longer feel we're observing a hero who should welcome any change at all -- even transformation into a giant insect -- but rather a man who has been transformed from his former self into something larger, and more fully human.  Francine Prose's most recent book is "The Peaceable Kingdom," a collection of stories.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Francine Prose's most recent book is "The Peaceable Kingdom," a collection of stories.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
