<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Campaign for County Clerk</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="644393"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUNTY CLERKS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WHITE PLAINS (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPANO, LEONARD N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOODY, JAMES P (TOWN SUPERVISOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FERON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D7103FF937A15753C1A965958260" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Campaign for County Clerk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES FERON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FERON, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE office of county clerk is difficult enough to explain, much less attain. What then if the major candidates for this $91,375-a-year post never meet in debate? How are voters to learn the issues or whom to support with their ballots?</p>
        <p>That is the situation that has developed this year between James P. Doody, the Eastchester Town Supervisor, who is seeking the post on the Democratic ticket, and Leonard N. Spano, a long-term member of the Board of Legislators who is running on the Republican and Conservative lines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE office of county clerk is difficult enough to explain, much less attain. What then if the major candidates for this $91,375-a-year post never meet in debate? How are voters to learn the issues or whom to support with their ballots?</p>
        <p>That is the situation that has developed this year between James P. Doody, the Eastchester Town Supervisor, who is seeking the post on the Democratic ticket, and Leonard N. Spano, a long-term member of the Board of Legislators who is running on the Republican and Conservative lines.</p>
        <p>Running may not be the best way to describe Mr. Spano's candidacy, said Mr. Doody, who says Mr. Spano has declined to attend all scheduled debates or joint appearances, "except for one where he showed up but left early," Mr. Doody said. "He has become the phantom of the campaign."</p>
        <p>That is "not true," said Mr. Spano, who maintains that he has made 212 public appearances in the last seven months, none of them with Mr. Doody. "It's really a scheduling problem," Mr. Spano said. "My election committee keeps me on a tight schedule, so I miss some functions." Victim of Democratic Primary</p>
        <p>The county clerk is Westchester's record keeper, filing all real estate and court documents for quick and efficient access. The office is also responsible for issuing various permits, passports and naturalization and notary services.</p>
        <p>The incumbent, Andrew J. Spano (no relation to the candidate), became the first Democrat to win the post this century. Mr. Spano, whose computerization of the office has been widely praised, chose to forego seeking a fourth term in favor of pursuing the Democratic nomination for county executive.</p>
        <p>He had the support of his party's leadership but lost by a narrow margin in a hard-fought primary against Assemblyman Richard L. Brodsky, who is seeking to oust the Republican incumbent, Andrew P. O'Rourke.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doody, a lawyer, said he would advance Mr. Spano's modernization of the clerk's office "through the use of fiber optics, the electronic highways of the future," he said in an interview. "The county clerk database could be extended to municipal buildings, information centers and libraries," Mr. Doody said. An Eye Toward Jobs</p>
        <p>He would also expand the "computer imaging of documents from land records, where the new technique is already available, to court records, enabling law officers and court clerks to get documents in seconds instead of days." He said he favored expansion of the clerk's functions, to include that of an ombudsman, or public advocate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doody and Mr. Brodksy also have proposed making the clerk's office part of a countywide job creations office, specializing in the development of small businesses. The clerk's office handles the filing of new businesses, Mr. Doody said, "so we could accommodate this new role easily and could be particularly helpful in cutting through government red tape."</p>
        <p>Mr. Doody, a graduate of the Columbia University School of Law, has been Eastchester Town Supervisor since 1983, winning re-election handily in a heavily Republican area. The 46-year-old Supervisor lives in Eastchester with his wife, Kathy, and their five children.</p>
        <p>Leonard Spano, a lifelong resident of Yonkers, represents the fifth generation of Spanos in Yonkers. The 63-year-old legislator, who was first elected to the Board of Legislators in 1971, retired seven years ago from a fuel oil and heating business. 'Blueprint for Innovation'</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano and his wife, Josephine, have 16 children, including State Senator Nicholas A. Spano and former Assemblyman Michael J. Spano, who served briefly as an appointee to fill an unexpired term. Michael Spano is a candidate for the Board of Legislators in the 14th District, the seat his father held for 22 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano's extended family has become something of a campaign issue for Mr. Doody, who says there are 17 Spanos, including in-laws, on the county payroll. This, he says, makes his opponent "the king of nepotism." Their combined salary is in excess of $900,000, Mr. Doody said, "and if Len Spano becomes county clerk it would exceed $1 million."</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano's agenda for the office he is seeking, which he calls a "blueprint for innovation," includes the creation of an ombudsman "to guide individuals and businesses through services at all levels of government." Combined Databases Proposed</p>
        <p>He would make information available "to computer users via modems," thus reducing the need to search for records in person. Fees would pay for the installation of "computerized kiosks, perhaps at libraries, for users who want to access information."</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano would also investigate the possibility of combining the database of the clerk's office with those of the County Departments of Health, Environmental Conservation and Motor Vehicles in a geographic information system, which would help in information-gathering and use.</p>
        <p>He has also said he would investigate the possibility of the county's reacquiring the State Department of Motor Vehicles office, which was once handled by the County Clerk's office. The purpose, he said, would be to improve the level of service.</p>
        <p>The Right to Life candidate is Robert Walsh, who says the clerk should be appointed rather than elected.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
