<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Again, Whiff of Syrup Baffles City</title>
    <meta content="09maple" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/09/nyregion/09maple.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1723445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Smell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2D61031F93AA35751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="367" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Again, Whiff of Syrup Baffles City</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Whiff of Maple Syrup Is Back, and New York Smells a Rat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's back and as maddening as ever, or so some noses supposed.</p>
        <p>In October, people all over New York City reported the sweet smell of syrup, like something out of a Vermont diner, only bigger and spreading. ''It's like maple syrup, with Eggos, or pancakes,'' Arturo Padilla said then. ''It's pleasant.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some people have said that the sweet smell of syrup, first reported in October, is back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's back and as maddening as ever, or so some noses supposed.</p>
        <p>In October, people all over New York City reported the sweet smell of syrup, like something out of a Vermont diner, only bigger and spreading. ''It's like maple syrup, with Eggos, or pancakes,'' Arturo Padilla said then. ''It's pleasant.''</p>
        <p>Others said it was caramel, or a freshly baked pie, or Bit-O-Honey candy bars. Still, sweetness seemed sinister to some. Cyanide, you know, smells like almonds.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the city Office of Emergency Management got wind of the return of the mystery smell. And, as it did in October, it investigated.</p>
        <p>The emergency management office has the job of responding to crises, like killer weather or terrorist attacks. Police, fire and environmental protection investigators were sent out with sniffing machines nicknamed ''electronic canaries.''</p>
        <p>Real canaries, sensitive to toxic gases, once served as an early warning system for coal miners. Unlike the mystery smell, however, the mine gases were odorless.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, just as in October, the mystery smell proved elusive.</p>
        <p>''We have no indication that there's anything hazardous,'' said Jarrod Bernstein, a spokesman for the emergency management office. ''Understand it is a lot easier to test if something is not hazardous than it is to figure out exactly what it is.''</p>
        <p>Most of the reports, Mr. Bernstein said, were from above 96th Street in Manhattan, although scattered reports came from Midtown.</p>
        <p>This reporter took his nose for a stroll on 42nd Street between 11th Avenue and Lexington Avenue. Nose in the air, he detected nothing except for a rotten-egg smell midblock at Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>But the Gothamist blog at www.gothamist.com reported a huge maple swath from Greenwich Village to Columbia University. Jen Chung, co-founder of Gothamist, invited readers to add their findings to a Web map she created.</p>
        <p>And did Ms. Chung herself smell the pancakes? Alas, no.</p>
        <p>''I have a cold,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
