<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Virtual Achievement for Hire: It's Only Wrong if You Get Caught</title>
    <meta content="09gameside" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/09/technology/09gameside.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1723555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cheating</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cheating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4DD1131F93AA35751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="563" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Virtual Achievement for Hire: It's Only Wrong if You Get Caught</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Virtual Achievement for Hire: It's Only Wrong if You Get Caught</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Computer games like World of Warcraft require that players start quite unarmed, equipped for killing only lowly opponents, and gradually amass through combat the virtual money to buy weaponry and armor needed to take on more mighty foes, but one can avoid having to work one's way up successive game levels by using services of players who sell virtual money they earn on game for real thing; doing business with these so-called 'farmers' carries social stigma in gaming world akin to cheating at cards; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>So there I was Sunday night, minding my own business in the World of Warcraft online computer game, killing a few rock elementals in the Badlands, when I received two unsolicited private messages from a player with the unlikely name Hfasdlf.</p>
        <p>Both messages said the same thing: ''Hi,plz visit http://www.zlywy.com. The low Price server$9.99=100G $39.99=500G $76.99=1000G.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>So there I was Sunday night, minding my own business in the World of Warcraft online computer game, killing a few rock elementals in the Badlands, when I received two unsolicited private messages from a player with the unlikely name Hfasdlf.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>So there I was Sunday night, minding my own business in the World of Warcraft online computer game, killing a few rock elementals in the Badlands, when I received two unsolicited private messages from a player with the unlikely name Hfasdlf.</p>
        <p>Both messages said the same thing: ''Hi,plz visit http://www.zlywy.com. The low Price server$9.99=100G $39.99=500G $76.99=1000G.''</p>
        <p>Within a minute, a dozen other players in my guild reported receiving the same message offering to sell virtual gold coins in exchange for real-world money. In ''massively multiplayer online games'' like EverQuest and World of Warcraft, a character like Hfasdlf is known as a farmer because all it does is farm for gold (or whatever the game's virtual currency happens to be) rather than play the game in the spirit intended.</p>
        <p>And that intended spirit is very simple: treat the game as a game, not as an entrepreneurial opportunity.</p>
        <p>In most online role-playing games the player's character, or avatar, usually starts out very weak, perhaps only able to kill rats or scrawny kobolds. By killing monsters, the player gains skills, magic equipment and the money to buy still better gear. So enhanced, the player can then kill stronger monsters, like perhaps a troll, which yields even better loot, and so on. Eventually, the character reaches what is known as the endgame, when it is strong enough to take on dragons, demons and other world-threatening foes.</p>
        <p>The catch is that ''eventually'' can be quite some time. In World of Warcraft, for instance, it takes many casual players 25 days (600 hours) or more of playing time before they reach the game's highest power plateau: Level 60. And even once a player reaches Level 60, there is always something to strive for: a stronger piece of magical armor, perhaps an even more lethal enchanted sword. The idea is that the player is supposed to enjoy the journey, exploring the game world and valuing each new piece of treasure as a reward for an obstacle overcome.</p>
        <p>Of course, impatience reigns. And that's where the farmers come in. Don't actually want to work your way up to Level 60? Get a farmer's leveling service to do it for you. Just pay a couple of hundred dollars or more, depending on how many levels you want to skip, wait a week or two, and, voilà!, your character is now at ''max level.'' Don't want to scrounge and scrape for weeks to buy that powerful Krol Blade or Belt of the Archmage that's selling for 500 gold pieces at the in-game auction house? Pay a farmer like Hfasdlf 40 bucks and hook yourself up.</p>
        <p>For any self-respecting gamer, paying for farming services is the easy way out, the ultimate in-game expression of a classic theorem: time equals money. And that is why in most gaming circles, doing business with farmers carries the social stigma of cheating at cards. Among respectable people it is just not done.</p>
        <p>But as in so many other parts of life, temptation often wins out. And as in so many other realms, for many people the only real sin is getting caught.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
