<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Storm Brewing, in the Middle-Aged Soul and at Sea</title>
    <meta content="01SHAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/01/arts/01SHAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1267334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genzlinger, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horovitz, Israel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schreiber, Terry</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Barking Sharks (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E5DB163EF932A35751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Storm Brewing, in the Middle-Aged Soul and at Sea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neil Genzlinger reviews T Schreiber Studio production of Barking Sharks, play by Israel Horovitz, at Maddox Theater; director is Terry Schreiber (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In ''Barking Sharks,'' the playwright Israel Horovitz offers stark proof of how quickly time can wreak its cruel damage. Unfortunately for him, the message is entirely unintentional.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horovitz wrote ''Barking Sharks,'' which is now getting its New York premiere at the T. Schreiber Studio, back in the mid-1990's, before Monicagate, before ''The Perfect Storm,'' before ''American Beauty.'' Now, of course, thinking people everywhere agree that there is absolutely no more insight or pathos to be wrung from the male midlife crisis or the doomed fishing trip. Mr. Horovitz, alas, sought to tap both wells in ''Barking Sharks,'' and as a result, in 2001 the play couldn't possibly feel more unnecessary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In ''Barking Sharks,'' the playwright Israel Horovitz offers stark proof of how quickly time can wreak its cruel damage. Unfortunately for him, the message is entirely unintentional.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horovitz wrote ''Barking Sharks,'' which is now getting its New York premiere at the T. Schreiber Studio, back in the mid-1990's, before Monicagate, before ''The Perfect Storm,'' before ''American Beauty.'' Now, of course, thinking people everywhere agree that there is absolutely no more insight or pathos to be wrung from the male midlife crisis or the doomed fishing trip. Mr. Horovitz, alas, sought to tap both wells in ''Barking Sharks,'' and as a result, in 2001 the play couldn't possibly feel more unnecessary.</p>
        <p>Time, though, need not shoulder all the blame; this drama was undoubtedly a pale piece of work even back in 1995, when it received its world premiere at Mr. Horovitz's Gloucester Stage Company in Massachusetts. The play (set in Gloucester, as are many of Mr. Horovitz's works) tells of Eddie Ciolino (Bob Rogerson), a middle-aged fellow who left Gloucester when he was a teenager and now, many fat New York paychecks later, develops a hankering to return and become a fisherman.</p>
        <p>His wife and son would just as soon he remained an overpaid advertising executive, but Eddie will have none of it; he is, it seems, fixated on a particular moment in his youth, when he and two friends had a band called the Barking Sharks. The term ''band'' is a generous one; the play opens with a flashback scene in which the Sharks sing Neil Young's ''Down by the River,'' and, frankly, they sound like whining cats.</p>
        <p>In any case, Eddie drags his family with him to Gloucester and runs into the other two Sharks, Sara (Mary Beth Kowalski-Twisdale), who was his girlfriend in the old days, and Ted (Jerry Rago), who was his best buddy. Ted and Sara are now married, Ted is a fisherman, the weather's turning ugly, and -- well, you can pretty much guess the rest.</p>
        <p>Which is the problem. The play is wincingly obvious from start to finish: the affair, the trial at sea, the adolescent romance between Eddie's son and Sara and Ted's daughter. It's also full of thudding dialogue, like the line Eddie utters as he foolishly heads out into a storm to try to rescue Ted. ''I know that if I die doing this,'' he says grimly, ''I will have died a man.'' Whatever; just hurry up and die.</p>
        <p>There is not a single character here who can be anything other than self-absorbed for more than a few moments, which means there is not a single character the audience can invest in emotionally. Especially since we've heard it all before, and very recently, at the movies or in the endless hand-wringing brought on by one particularly high-level midlife crisis. Heck, Mr. Rogerson even looks like Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>The actors, burdened with trite material, uniformly fail to impress, though it's not for lack of stage time. Mr. Horovitz, a veteran playwright who should know better, is here afflicted with doesn't-know-when-to-stop disease. Long after the play should have ended, characters are plunging into speeches that begin, ''When I was 4. . .''</p>
        <p>Terry Schreiber compounds the problem by directing at a glacial pace, and as a result the play flirts with the three-hour mark. A long three hours it is. It's like watching the tide go out, only more predictable.</p>
        <p>BARKING SHARKS</p>
        <p>By Israel Horovitz; directed by Terry Schreiber; lighting by Joe Saint; sets by John Pollard; costumes by David Toser; sound designer and musical director, Gib Von Bach; fight choreographer, Randy Kurstin; technical director, Jason Starr; stage manager, Sarah B. Zimmerman. Presented by T. Schreiber Studio. At the Maddox Theater, 151 West 26th Street, Chelsea.</p>
        <p>WITH: Dennis Anderson (Young Ted and Mac Asaro), Alexandra Westmore (Young Sara and Annie Asaro), Rob Dodd (Little Eddie), Bob Rogerson (Eddie Ciolino), J. M. McDonough (Ralph Burke and Busty Ciolino), Quinn Lemley (Alice Ciolino), Jerry Rago (Ted Asaro), Mary Beth Kowalski-Twisdale (Sara Asaro) and Jason Starr and Gib Von Bach (Musicians).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
