<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Notebook;Mayor Giuliani Girds for Battle</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="846965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAYORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLLINS, GAIL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W (MAYOR) RUDOLPH WILLIAM GIULIANI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5D61639F93BA15757C0A960958260" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Notebook;Mayor Giuliani Girds for Battle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COLLINS, GAIL;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of Rudolph Giuliani's big advantages in running for re-election is the fact that not many other people actually want his job. More than a year before the New York mayoral campaign really begins, most of the city's top Democrats have already taken themselves out of the running, eyeing juicier prizes one more year down the line. Both Gov. George Pataki and Senator Alfonse D'Amato seem vulnerable when up for re-election in 1998, despite the fact that former Mayor Ed Koch, in a burst of advance planning, has already endorsed them both.</p>
        <p>The conventional wisdom of New York politics is that Mr. Giuliani's job is not nearly as desirable as Mr. Pataki's or Mr. D'Amato's. It may be true in most professions that if you make it in New York City, you can make it anywhere. But  being elected mayor is regarded as the equivalent of the Academy Award for lifetime achievement -- a very high prestige way of saying your career is over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of Rudolph Giuliani's big advantages in running for re-election is the fact that not many other people actually want his job. More than a year before the New York mayoral campaign really begins, most of the city's top Democrats have already taken themselves out of the running, eyeing juicier prizes one more year down the line. Both Gov. George Pataki and Senator Alfonse D'Amato seem vulnerable when up for re-election in 1998, despite the fact that former Mayor Ed Koch, in a burst of advance planning, has already endorsed them both.</p>
        <p>The conventional wisdom of New York politics is that Mr. Giuliani's job is not nearly as desirable as Mr. Pataki's or Mr. D'Amato's. It may be true in most professions that if you make it in New York City, you can make it anywhere. But  being elected mayor is regarded as the equivalent of the Academy Award for lifetime achievement -- a very high prestige way of saying your career is over.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Giuliani is obviously happy with his present employment and is positioning himself for the next campaign. He has made peace overtures toward David Garth, his estranged campaign adviser. He has managed to get rid of Police Commissioner William Bratton, who, according to the polls, is the man most New Yorkers believe is responsible for bringing down the crime rate. The Mayor apparently did not want to run the risk that next year's opponent would promise  to keep Mr. Bratton on the job, offering voters the option of Giuliani crime control without Giuliani.</p>
        <p>The one thing the Mayor will not do to get re-elected is change his style, since he has neither the talent nor the will for political mutation. That means  he will continue to rely on a circle of advisers so small that his chief of staff serves double duty fighting crime at the fish market, and the head of the Department of Investigation also rode herd on the Columbus Avenue street repairs. He will not learn Mr. Koch's art of self-deprecating humor. During the  campaign he will no doubt defend his best and worst decisions with equal vigor,  and accuse his opponent, no matter who he or she is, of "old thinking."</p>
        <p>The only Democrat who has positively declared he wants to be Mr. Giuliani's opponent is Councilman Sal Albanese of Brooklyn. Mr. Albanese lacks name recognition. But a city that likes to see its Republican Mayor savage other Republicans may feel some sympathy for a Democrat who is equally irritating to his party leaders. Council Speaker Peter Vallone, who has long since deprived Mr. Albanese of all the normal perks of his Council seniority, was once reduced  to disciplining him by throwing him off the Youth Committee.</p>
        <p>Former Congresswoman Geraldine Ferraro has been playing the Colin Powell role of the pre-campaign period. Ms. Ferraro, who has not held public office since 1984 and who has made no overtures toward running for mayor, was the only candidate who could beat Mr. Giuliani in a recent Quinnipiac College poll. But right now, polls can measure little but voters' shifting attitudes toward their  mayor, and their ability to recognize names of opponents. Mr. Giuliani's polls have shown that he was most popular when he endorsed Mario Cuomo and when he displayed a softer side in his statements on child welfare earlier this year. But approval ratings from 40 to 50 percent during most of his term suggest that  the next election will be close and hard-fought.</p>
        <p>The best-known Democrats to express an interest in being mayor are two Borough Presidents, Ruth Messinger of Manhattan and Fernando Ferrer of the Bronx. Although neither is a declared candidate, both have been planning their campaigns for a long time. Ms. Messinger held her first unofficial fund-raiser,  a women-only Super Bowl party, in 1994. Mr. Ferrer has hired Dick Morris, the political strategist who has pushed President Clinton to pre-empt the Republicans on social issues where the conservative stance is popular. It may be a coincidence that Mr. Ferrer, a lifelong opponent of capital punishment, last month demanded the death penalty in the murder of a police officer in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Other Democratic options are dwindling. Public Advocate Mark Green recently announced he will run for the United States Senate. State Comptroller H. Carl McCall and Congressman Charles Schumer seem to be aiming at the governor's race. Mr. Vallone has made it pretty clear that he values his evenings at home too much to run for mayor. "I need a family life, and I don't know whether this city allows you to have one," he told The Times's Joyce Purnick earlier this year. "I think you can as President. I think you can as Governor. I don't think you can do it as Mayor of the City of New York." The nation's chief executive may have a lot on his plate, but Mr. Vallone is presumably impressed that he does not have to leave the dinner table every time there is an electric explosion in the  subways.</p>
        <p>GAIL COLLINS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
