<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dividing Perennials Multiplies Beauty and Neighborliness</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="846696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E3D91639F93BA15757C0A960958260" item-length="894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dividing Perennials Multiplies Beauty and Neighborliness</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRADITION holds that spring-blooming perennials are divided in the fall, while fall-blooming perennials are divided in the spring. This theory is essentially correct, but sometimes gardens do not work out this way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRADITION holds that spring-blooming perennials are divided in the fall, while fall-blooming perennials are divided in the spring. This theory is essentially correct, but sometimes gardens do not work out this way.</p>
        <p>Now that spring is upon us in full glory, gardeners may be noticing that some perennials have grown into massive clumps of roots with a tight colony of sturdy new growth popping up. Division, in this case, makes sense.</p>
        <p>The opposite scenario would be with perennials that have performed beautifully for years and years. There is no need to even think about dividing them.</p>
        <p>Peonies comes to mind. These magnificent May-time bloomers seem to go on forever. There is some debate on whether this old-fashioned standby should ever  be divided. Some gardeners insist division is a must every five years or so, to  make the clump bloom better. And if a family is moving to a new home, there is always the emotional tug to take some favorite peonies along.</p>
        <p>Then there is the school that believes that since the peonies have been growing in place for years and years, why move them? Many people believe a well-established peony planting just becomes more glorious each year. (A ring of well-balanced fertilizer should be applied around the maroon peony clumps now because a peony is a heavy feeder.)</p>
        <p>Certain perennials should be divided now. Among them are the fall-blooming chrysanthemums, asters, and other late daisies like sunflowers and sneezeweeds.  Beebalms, which are mints, grow into thick clumps and can be divided every two years or so. Coral bells (Heucheras) grow into thick clumps, too, and do better  if they are divided up every few years.</p>
        <p>Some of the perennials that should stay in place include indigo (Baptisia) and gas plant (Dictamnus), both huge growers, and the balloon flower (Platycodon), one of the last to show itself in spring.</p>
        <p>Others, including Corydalis, seed themselves everywhere. Instead of dividing  this spreader, look out for seedlings while working around the garden and pull up the unwanted ones.</p>
        <p>Division is one of the grandest ways to share a garden. Before any dividing,  however, it is essential that the locations for the divisions be given some thought.</p>
        <p>If the clump is to be divided, get under it with a spade or a garden fork, and lift the whole clump from the ground for careful examination.</p>
        <p>Usually the center will be hard and aged. It can be discarded. The outer, succulent parts of the clump are the valued divisions and can either be pulled apart with strong hands or cut apart with pruning shears or another implement.</p>
        <p>It is a good idea to work quickly. First, place the clump on an old piece of  burlap. As the divisions are made, they can be separated and easily seen. Cover  the divisions with the burlap, to prevent the roots from drying out.</p>
        <p>Next, plan where the divisions will go, and be sure the soil has been well prepared. Addition of compost in the planting hole helps. The ground is quite moist now and should not need to be soaked before planting. However, watering will be important after the divisions are set in place.</p>
        <p>Sometimes it is not necessary to divide the whole clump, but slices of clumps can be cut off from the plant with little harm. This is especially true for such thick growers as hostas. A good sharp spade can be inserted into the soil around the edge of a clump to get out several divisions. Some gardeners call this method slicing.</p>
        <p>These divisions can then be set in their new space and tucked in gently. The  newer plantings should be watered in well. Although the young hostas may not look elegant their first year, in their second year, they should be magnificent.</p>
        <p>When an established plant grows from a crown and is dug up for division, be careful not to bury the division's crown deeply. Place its basal leaves on the soil, and push the roots to penetrate downward.</p>
        <p>If the division is not a basal grower or crown-forming plant, then plant the  division at the same depth the parent was growing from. Keep an old pair of scissors handy to cut off any straggly torn roots. New ones will grow. When dividing primulas, cut off the older, thick roots to encourage new ones to form.</p>
        <p>A FTER the divisions are in place, it might be helpful to trace a ring of general garden fertilizer around them and work it in lightly with a hand cultivator. Water the divisions in, too, or ideally do the dividing the day before rain is predicted.</p>
        <p>And the leftover divisions that you do not have room to plant? This is where  the sharing with your neighbor comes in. In fact, I know of one gardener whose entire perennial border is made up of divisions from neighbors. The border was not planned this way, but as more and more gardeners shared, this neighborhood garden grew.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
