<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art/Architecture; How Surrealists Made a Movement Of Love and Sex</title>
    <meta content="21RIDI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/21/arts/design/21RIDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1335595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tate Modern (London)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Tate Modern</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E4D9163EF932A15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art/Architecture; How Surrealists Made a Movement Of Love and Sex</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How Surrealists Made a Movement of Love and Sex</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Riding reviews Surrealism: Desire Unbound, new show at Tate Modern in London; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a 1932 letter to André Breton, the autocratic leader of the Surrealist movement, Sigmund Freud made a rather surprising confession: ''Although I have received many testimonies of the interest that you and your friends show for my research,'' Freud wrote, ''I am not able to clarify for myself what surrealism is and what it wants. Perhaps I am not destined to understand it, I who am so distant from art.''</p>
        <p>How could Freud have been stumped by a movement built around dreams and sex? The answer may lie in his final phrase: perhaps he saw Surrealism only as an art movement, one that spoke in the strange new visual language of, say, Max Ernst, Salvador Dali, René Magritte, André Masson and Joan Miró. If so, he was not alone. Today, Surrealism is remembered primarily for its art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Surrealism: Desire Unbound," a new show at the Tate Modern, has done a good job of reminding us that, behind the art, there was always debate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a 1932 letter to André Breton, the autocratic leader of the Surrealist movement, Sigmund Freud made a rather surprising confession: ''Although I have received many testimonies of the interest that you and your friends show for my research,'' Freud wrote, ''I am not able to clarify for myself what surrealism is and what it wants. Perhaps I am not destined to understand it, I who am so distant from art.''</p>
        <p>How could Freud have been stumped by a movement built around dreams and sex? The answer may lie in his final phrase: perhaps he saw Surrealism only as an art movement, one that spoke in the strange new visual language of, say, Max Ernst, Salvador Dali, René Magritte, André Masson and Joan Miró. If so, he was not alone. Today, Surrealism is remembered primarily for its art.</p>
        <p>Indeed, thanks to poaching by advertising, theater and movie directors, and even contemporary artists, many Surrealist images (Magritte's bowler-hatted men, Dali's melting watches, for example) have by now been reworked to the point of cliché. Yet in its heyday between the world wars, Surrealism was primarily about ideas, above all the idea of breaking with all artistic and social conventions. Furthermore, it was a movement born of literature, not of visual art.</p>
        <p>''Surrealism: Desire Unbound,'' a new show at the Tate Modern through Jan. 1, then traveling to the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York, has done a good job of reminding us that, behind the art, there was always debate. Built around the theme of love and sex, a Surrealist obsession, the exhibition not only presents scores of paintings, drawings, photographs and movies, but also accompanies them with books, poems, letters and photographs illustrating how this tightly knit group of intellectuals, poets and artists operated.</p>
        <p>The group approach was central to Breton's control of the movement. Breton himself never ranked as an important poet or artist. Even as an idea man he was not entirely original: it was Apollinaire who coined the term ''surrealism'' in 1917 and who established de Sade, Rimbaud, Baudelaire and Jarry as the movement's first icons; it was Marcel Duchamp who as early as 1912 invented conceptual art; and it was the Dadaists of Zurich under Tristan Tzara whose anarchic happenings first gave intellectual respectability to ''anti-art.''</p>
        <p>But Breton, while infamously humorless, was evidently a strong and charismatic personality. As World War I came to an end, Breton and his fellow poets Louis Aragon and Paul Eluard, inspired by Apollinaire's idea of ''the New Spirit now abroad,'' began experimenting with new literary techniques like automatic writing. At the same time, Duchamp and Francis Picabia were breaking with tradition in art by connecting the hand to the mind and circumventing the eye, as with automatic drawing. By the time the group announced its revolution with the Surrealist Manifesto of 1924, Breton had emerged as its undisputed leader.</p>
        <p>Breton's power was one of the contradictions of a movement that was, after all, devoted to free thinking. Its members borrowed ideas from psychoanalysis, philosophy and politics and then challenged them. They believed in free sex and cheerfully swapped partners. Yet Breton ran the movement like a theocratic dictator, defining the creed, deciding who could belong, holding trials of dissidents and expelling those who crossed him. Magritte, for one, found Breton's methods distasteful and, after a brief visit to Paris, returned home to Brussels. In the end, Breton fell out with almost everyone.</p>
        <p>But it was under his leadership in the late 1920's that the group began an almost-scientific study -- it organized opinion polls and circulated questionnaires -- of the links between the subconscious, dreams, love, eroticism and sex. And in this it was helped by Freud, whose books were belatedly reaching France: ''The Interpretation of Dreams,'' first published in German in 1900, appeared in French only in 1927. As the show demonstrates, apart from political in-fighting, desire was to consume much of the group's attention until its dispersal during World War II.</p>
        <p>One way of testing boundaries was to inject a new sexual explicitness into both poetry -- Breton had banned novels -- and art. (The Tate warns visitors to ''Surrealism: Desire Unbound'' that they may find some works ''challenging.'') But while painters like Dali evidently enjoyed shocking, most artists seemed genuinely interested in deconstructing desire. A path had been cleared for them. Important pre-Surrealist works by Duchamp (''The Bride Stripped Bare by Her Bachelors, Even''), Picabia (''Paroxysm of Suffering'') and Giorgio de Chirico (''The Child's Brain'') were already addressing suppressed sexuality.</p>
        <p>This large exhibition, organized by Jennifer Mundy, a Tate curator, and well received by British art critics, is presented not chronologically but through 13 themes like ''Anatomies,'' ''Imprint of Desires,'' ''Love, Poetry,'' ''Eros'' and ''Erotic Objects,'' which themselves represent a different way of deconstructing desire. Although unavoidably arbitrary, these classifications also illustrate the freedom with which artists confronted desire, from the near-abstract forms of Man Ray's nude photographs to the masturbation, incest and fetishism of Dali's paintings and the violence and blasphemy of his movie work with Luis Buñuel in ''Un Chien Andalou'' and ''L'Age d'Or.''</p>
        <p>Ernst, the handsome young German who was long Breton's most loyal follower, was perhaps the artist whose early work was the most Surrealist, with its often nightmarish blurring of German mysticism and witchcraft with sexual forms and symbols. In contrast, Duchamp, who along with Man Ray kept a healthy distance from Breton, never lost his sense of humor: he added a mustache to a reproduction of Mona Lisa and called the work ''L.H.O.O.Q,'' which when read aloud in French sounds sexy, funny and a tad vulgar; and he had Man Ray photograph him dressed as a woman called Rrose Sélavy, a pun on ''Eros, c'est la vie,'' or ''Eros is life.''</p>
        <p>The place of real women within the movement was more contradictory. They were assigned the role of muses, inspiring poetry and feeding argument and debate. They took off their clothes and served as models. They were even allowed to play off their lovers against one another: Eluard first shared his wife, Gala, with Ernst, then lost her to Dali. Yet Breton, who himself wrote love poetry of some merit, never allowed women to participate in the group's discussions: if a man was doing the desiring, it seems, it sufficed for a woman to be ''That Obscure Object of Desire,'' as Buñuel named his last movie in 1977.</p>
        <p>In art, though, women could find freedom and go their own way. And the Tate exhibition includes several who left their mark on Surrealism. Dora Maar, later traumatized by her relationship with Picasso, was a fine photographer. Frida Kahlo, while unimpressed by Breton during a visit to Paris, carved her own path through Surrealism (Madonna has lent Kahlo's ''Self-Portrait With Monkey'' to the show). Claude Cahun explored gender ambiguity through her own genre of photographic self-portraiture. They were followed by Leonor Fini, Leonora Carrington, Remedios Varo and Dorothea Tanning. And while Louise Bourgeois does not consider herself a Surrealist, the show ends with four of her sculptures that are, if nothing else, sexually charged.</p>
        <p>Still, the exhibition would not be complete without images to ''challenge'' the Tate Modern's visitors. Yet even these seem more Surrealist than erotic or pornographic. From Hans Bellmer, best known for his photographic series of deformed dolls, there are sexually explicit drawings and photographs; from Jindrich Styrsky, there are similar collages; from Masson, a drawing evokes sado-masochism; from Roberto Matta, a sketch portrays ''The 120 Days of Sodom;'' and from Dali, for those who can decode his distorted shapes, there is copulation galore.</p>
        <p>So, one cannot help wondering, what was it that Freud could not understand?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
