<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Happenstance, Not Strategy, Leaves Green Indebted to Few</title>
    <meta content="21GREE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/21/nyregion/21GREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1335878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Political Memo"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Mark (Public Advocate)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koch, Edward I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Liberal Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Green, Mark</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E5DD1E3EF932A15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1453" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Happenstance, Not Strategy, Leaves Green Indebted to Few</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Happenstance, Not Strategy, Leaves Green Indebted to Few</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Green emerges from New York City mayoral primary unexpectedly unencumbered with political debts, having been opposed until now by most of city's influential union leaders and politicians; Green's difficulty in nailing down powerful support is linked to widespread antipathy for his 'obnoxious' personality, in words of former mayor Ed Koch (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His primary contest behind him, Mark Green has emerged, unexpectedly and not by the design of his campaign, as the first Democratic mayoral nominee in memory who appears to owe no obvious debt to the major constituencies that traditionally stake a claim on New York mayors.</p>
        <p>With a few notable exceptions, New York's most influential unions, elected officials and party leaders -- from the teachers to the health care workers; from Representative Charles E. Rangel of Harlem to the Rev. Al Sharpton to former Mayor Edward I. Koch to Raymond B. Harding, the Liberal Party leader -- opposed Mr. Green almost through the end.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mark Green has emerged, as the first Democratic mayoral nominee in memory who appears to owe no debt to groups that traditionally stake a claim on New York mayors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His primary contest behind him, Mark Green has emerged, unexpectedly and not by the design of his campaign, as the first Democratic mayoral nominee in memory who appears to owe no obvious debt to the major constituencies that traditionally stake a claim on New York mayors.</p>
        <p>With a few notable exceptions, New York's most influential unions, elected officials and party leaders -- from the teachers to the health care workers; from Representative Charles E. Rangel of Harlem to the Rev. Al Sharpton to former Mayor Edward I. Koch to Raymond B. Harding, the Liberal Party leader -- opposed Mr. Green almost through the end.</p>
        <p>Until the final weeks of the primary, Mr. Green had the support of only one of the five Democratic county leaders. And the city's most powerful chairman, Roberto Ramirez of the Bronx, who supported Fernando Ferrer in the Democratic primary, said yesterday that he was not supporting Mr. Green in the general election for now, although he said he would not back Michael R. Bloomberg, the Republican candidate, either. Mr. Ramirez said he was not satisfied that Mr. Green went far enough in denouncing his supporters' racially charged attacks on Mr. Ferrer in the primary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green's position in the campaign's final weeks is, his advisers acknowledge, the result of happenstance rather than strategy or the candidate's political fortitude. Mr. Green tried and failed to win the support of most of these groups and figures, and for a long time sought to present himself as the consensus candidate of New York's Democratic establishment</p>
        <p>Mr. Green's difficulty in nailing down much of this support -- when polls showed him the favorite to win his party's nomination -- was noted by critics and supporters alike as additional evidence of antipathy toward a political figure famously described by Mr. Koch as ''obnoxious.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, the result may well turn out to be a welcome turn of events for Mr. Green in the final weeks of this mayoral campaign and, should he win, in a Green mayoralty.</p>
        <p>For one thing, it could complicate the ongoing attempt by Mr. Bloomberg to paint Mr. Green as indebted to Democratic Party constituencies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg's aides had preferred, they said, that he run against Mr. Ferrer, in no small part because his promise to be an advocate for ''the other New York'' had drawn the support of unions as well as most of the city's leading black and Hispanic elected officials.</p>
        <p>More significant, should the often-cautious Mr. Green defeat Mr. Bloomberg, he would have considerable flexibility -- assuming he decided to exercise it -- in parrying the intense, conflicting demands from unions, elected officials and political leaders on how the city should be run over the difficult years ahead. That realization is beginning to sink in with Mr. Green and his advisers as they start considering the contours of a Green mayoralty.</p>
        <p>''He owes nobody nothing -- not that he didn't try,'' said Ken Sunshine, a consultant who is close to Mr. Green. Mr. Sunshine ticked off a list of the union leaders and political officials who turned against Mr. Green, and said: ''He tried damn hard to get all of the above. And it didn't work out in almost every instance.'</p>
        <p>A senior aide to one of Mr. Green's primary opponents said, ''He's unencumbered.''</p>
        <p>According to aides to Mr. Green and Mr. Ferrer, the endorsement discussions between the two and their supporters did not address policy or patronage at City Hall, but rather the distress among Mr. Ferrer's supporters about a last-minute run of telephone calls and leaflets linking Mr. Ferrer to Mr. Sharpton that they described as racially charged.</p>
        <p>''I'll tell you what it doesn't depend on, and that is the question of patronage,'' Mr. Ramirez said on the question of his own support for Mr. Green. ''What I needed yesterday was an acknowledgment and a statement by the leadership of my party that what happened was wrong. That it should not be allowed to happen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramirez said Mr. Green and the state party chairwoman, Judith Hope, had not gone far enough in denouncing the tactic.</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Ferrer's supporters said that since their candidate had endorsed Mr. Green, the discussion would inevitably turn to what kind of role they might play in a Green mayoralty. But advisers to Mr. Green suggested that given the customs of politics, Mr. Green was more likely to reward, at least at first, his earliest and enthusiastic supporters. That is a relatively small list that includes a former police commissioner, William J. Bratton, and former Mayor David N. Dinkins.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green, in an interview, said the absence of support from Democratic leaders during the primary showed that he was not a party insider, his long record as a political candidate and public official notwithstanding.</p>
        <p>''It's true that my history and impulse toward directness and independence has occasionally annoyed some key figures,'' he said. ''I didn't grow up taking the train to Albany or the plane to Washington. I am not regarded by the party leaders as a comfortable old shoe or an insider or a drinking buddy.''</p>
        <p>To underline his point, Mr. Green described a meeting this year with a major labor leader, whom he declined to name, in which the two discussed a possible endorsement. This leader, Mr. Green recounted, turned to him and said, '' 'You're so damn. . . .' Long pause. And I thought, 'Oh God, what is the adjective that's coming?' And the labor leader said: 'independent!' ''</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Green paused. ''I have a witness!'' he said. ''I thought, 'My God, to them it's a curse. To me, it's an asset.' ''</p>
        <p>William Cunningham, a senior Bloomberg adviser, rejected the notion that Mr. Green was politically unencumbered, noting, for example, that he had the support of the police and fire unions. Both unions endorsed Mr. Green in the final days of the runoff.</p>
        <p>''He's making promises and deals all over the place to get the endorsements,'' Mr. Cunningham said. ''How do you think that he got the police and the fire unions? For a police union to endorse Mark Green after basically saying he had no conception of what the job is, and after complaining about him for years, I'd have to ask, 'What turned them around? What 24-hour bit of information made them change?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cunningham declined to elaborate on what he was suggesting. ''I don't want to pick on the cops,'' he said, noting the events of the past five weeks.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. Cunningham noted that Mr. Green had the support of Assemblyman Herman D. Farrell Jr., the chairman of the Manhattan Democratic Party, and that Mr. Farrell had played a very visible role when Mr. Ferrer's supporters began attacking Mr. Green for running a racially charged campaign.</p>
        <p>''I noticed the other day when Mark was being questioned, he rolled out the Manhattan county Democratic chairman on television to defend him,'' Mr. Cunningham said. ''I don't know why that was good strategy, other than the fact that he's an African-American.''</p>
        <p>If the past 10 years in Democratic politics have shown anything, it is that running against what might be perceived as liberal interests is anything but a losing strategy, even in New York. Mr. Green took note of how Bill Clinton won the White House in 1992 by moving the Democratic Party to the center.</p>
        <p>But other than his sometimes awkward attempt to slightly distance himself from Mr. Sharpton, whose support he now says he would welcome, Mr. Green has not done this.</p>
        <p>Even when Mr. Green found himself quarreling with the teachers' union, that was the result not of some strategic move -- like Mr. Clinton's decision to pick a fight with the Rev. Jesse L. Jackson -- but a response to a statement by the union president, Randi Weingarten, that Mr. Green was her last choice when it came to mayoral candidates she might endorse. Ms. Weingarten attended a unity rally Friday with Mr. Green.</p>
        <p>Yesterday Mr. Sharpton said again that he had not decided whether to support Mr. Green. In any event, he said, given the demands Mr. Green would face in trying to govern New York, he is certain that Mr. Green would clearly open the door to all of Mr. Ferrer's supporters, be they Mr. Sharpton, Mr. Ramirez or Dennis Rivera, the head of the health care workers' union, who was also opposed Mr. Green to the end.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Sharpton acknowledged that there might be limits to their influence.</p>
        <p>''We will have to have respectful access,'' Mr. Sharpton said. ''But I don't think we'll run City Hall.''</p>
        <p>Political Memo</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
