<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; Once More at the Crossroads of History</title>
    <meta content="21TR08$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1335863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4D6113EF932A15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1240" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; Once More at the Crossroads of History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>once more at the crossroads of history</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TED ELIOT, a former American ambassador to Afghanistan, remembers standing on a medieval parapet above a desert in this harsh, fiercely beautiful country and seeing a river of red in the sand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TED ELIOT, a former American ambassador to Afghanistan, remembers standing on a medieval parapet above a desert in this harsh, fiercely beautiful country and seeing a river of red in the sand.</p>
        <p>''You'd go down to find out what it was,'' he said, ''and you'd find it was all shards of a civilization that is completely gone.''</p>
        <p>History has been cruel to Afghanistan, but the past left more than pottery shards. For more than 2,000 years, as armies, ancient and modern, swept across its mountains and plains, Afghanistan also absorbed great cultures and religious from virtually every major civilization, East and West.</p>
        <p>Louis Dupree, the late American scholar who wrote the classic history of the place in 1973, said this in the book, simply titled ''Afhanistan'': ''for millennia, the land now called Afghanistan sat in the center of the action, the meeting place of four ecological and cultural areas: the Middle East, Center Asia, the Indian Subcontinent and even the Far East.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Eliot, who was ambassador from 1973 to 1978, when a quarter-century of war and turmoil was just about to begin, said in an interview that ''one of the great attractions of the country was its sense of history.''</p>
        <p>''You couldn't go anywhere in Afghanistan without seeing some marvelous example of Buddhist - or even in some cases Hinu - architecture or art. You could stand on the banks, of the Amu Darya, the former Oxus River, and be in the midst of Greek ruins. You were never, never unaware of these cross-currents.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps history will see the ultimate tragedy in what is happening today, with the arrival of Arab zealots, Osama bin Laden and his lieutenants. Their dominating presence in the Taliban's Afghanistan has brought down on Afhan heads an homes an American war, whose potential ripples could directly affect every land between the Mediterranean and the Ganges. Unhappily this time, Afghanistan again finds itself at the center of the world.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
