<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's a Dance! It's a Play! It's 20 Romanian Gymnasts!</title>
    <meta content="21WBOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="59" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1335848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="FOR YOUNG VIEWERS"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5DA113EF932A15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's a Dance! It's a Play! It's 20 Romanian Gymnasts!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anna Bahney</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even for those involved, defining ''Aeros'' is difficult. An Italian conceived of it, three Americans choreographed it, two Britons refined it, and 20 Romanians performed it. Is it gymnastics? dance? global summit? When Moses Pendleton, one of the choreographers, was asked, his answer was simple: ''It's Aeros. It's flight.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even for those involved, defining ''Aeros'' is difficult. An Italian conceived of it, three Americans choreographed it, two Britons refined it, and 20 Romanians performed it. Is it gymnastics? dance? global summit? When Moses Pendleton, one of the choreographers, was asked, his answer was simple: ''It's Aeros. It's flight.''</p>
        <p>''Aeros: The Illusion of Flight,'' the movement collage that completed its four-month 60-city American tour last year, will have its television premiere Thursday evening at 8 on Bravo, followed by a half-hour documentary at 9:30 describing the collaborative effort.</p>
        <p>The performance taps into the rigorous training and perfect-10 techniques of athletes from the Romanian Gymnastic Federation and teases out the sensibilities of modern dance. Wth more than 15 short pieces - veering from explosive to humorous - the 90-minute performance takes handsprings, back walkovers, pommel horse routines and other gymnastic movements and weaves them into evocative artistic vignettes with titles like ''Machine,'' ''Flower,'' ''Dresses'' and ''The Head.''</p>
        <p>The show's choreographers - Daniel Exralow, David Parsons and Mr. Pendleton - had overlapping experiences in American modern dance companies but had never participated in a project demanding a unified vision until Antonio Gnecchi, an Italian theater agent, brought the three choreographers together to share his dream of gymnasts on stage.</p>
        <p>Working with Luke Cresswell and Steve McNicholas, the creators of the percussion-theater piece ''Stomp,'' the three choreographers set about creating an ''aesthetic on the athletic,'' as Mr. Pendleton put it.</p>
        <p>Not only do the performers appear to fly, but they seem to enjoy it. Mr. Pendleton, who is also the founder and artistic director of the Momix modern dance company, said he was inspired by working with people who had ''no fear.''</p>
        <p>''They have gone through so much in competition,'' he said. ''Performing is nothing for them. It's fun.''</p>
        <p>Anna Bahney</p>
        <p>FOR YOUNG VIEWERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
