<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Blacks, Chef Jobs Finally Call</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="643258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AFRICAN-AMERICAN CHEFS AND COOKBOOK AUTHORS ASSOCIATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMPSON, DOREEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D7163EF933A15753C1A965958260" item-length="1561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Blacks, Chef Jobs Finally Call</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR hundreds of years there have been black cooks in America. Now there are also black chefs.</p>
        <p>In the last few years, more blacks have begun achieving prominence and recognition as professionals in fine restaurants, diversifying a field that was once almost exclusively white, male and, in the most prestigious restaurants, European.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR hundreds of years there have been black cooks in America. Now there are also black chefs.</p>
        <p>In the last few years, more blacks have begun achieving prominence and recognition as professionals in fine restaurants, diversifying a field that was once almost exclusively white, male and, in the most prestigious restaurants, European.</p>
        <p>In the past, few blacks sought admission to the top cooking schools, which funnel graduates into the best restaurants.</p>
        <p>"There was a tendency to look down on being in the kitchen because that's where we were relegated for so many years," said Doreen Thompson, a food-loving lawyer in Washington who founded the African-American Chefs and Cookbook Authors Association last April. "Now, it's being seen as an economically viable profession, and it's percolating up."</p>
        <p>Historically, young blacks have not been able to look around and see many inspiring role models. That is changing, too, as blacks, like members of other minority groups and women, gradually move into jobs that are more visible and more powerful. Ms. Thompson's group is one of a number of new nonprofit organizations that support blacks in the food field through education, financial aid and publicity.</p>
        <p>Significantly, black head chefs in fine restaurants -- like Steve Simmons of One Market, in San Francisco; Patrick Clark of the Hay-Adams Hotel, in Washington; Walter Hinds of Lolabelle, in Manhattan, and Jacqueline Cholmondeley of Livanos, in White Plains -- have generally found restaurant kitchens to be colorblind.</p>
        <p>"When you're in the kitchen trying to turn out the food, there is no time for attitudes," said Mr. Simmons, the chef at One Market, a new restaurant. "In this kitchen we're chefs and cooks first." A graduate of Bates College who has been in the food business for 12 years, Mr. Simmons started as a busboy in San Francisco and eventually attending the restaurant program at City College there.</p>
        <p>At the same time, this generation of chefs is also turning out food that tends to be colorblind. Prominent black chefs are cooking the way their white counterparts are cooking: contemporary American, with French, Italian, Asian and Caribbean influences.</p>
        <p>While a great number of black cooks are still preparing soul food and barbecue, maintaining a culinary tradition for which blacks have long been celebrated, that kind of food does not lead to executive chef positions in top hotels and restaurants. Nor does it lead to the kind of acclaim that is showered on chefs like Mr. Clark, the executive chef at the Hay-Adams, who is regularly invited to cook alongside Wolfgang Puck and Larry Forgione at benefit dinners.</p>
        <p>In the words of Mr. Hinds, the executive chef at Lolabelle, "A black cook is not a chef." A chef, he said, runs a kitchen and is responsible for more than just cooking. As soon as he finds the necessary financial backing, he plans to open his own restaurant, preferably in TriBeCa.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hinds, who was born in Panama -- where his father was a chef -- and grew up in Port Jefferson, L.I., attended Peter Kump's New York Cooking School. His first job was in the kitchen of Safari Grill, a now-defunct restaurant on Third Avenue owned by David Keh. "There were many ethnic groups in that kitchen, so from the beginning, I haven't had any problem with discrimination," he said.</p>
        <p>He calls his food, which features dishes like pepper-seared tuna with stir-fried Asian greens, crisp rice noodles and a soy-tomato vinaigrette, contemporary American. Some of his food also reflects his heritage. He often serves a side dish of mashed plantain and puts dandelion greens in his roast garlic risotto. "But I've gone way beyond any stereotype," he said.</p>
        <p>Lola Bell, the owner of the restaurant where he works, studied at the French Culinary Institute to avoid being stereotyped. "Just because you're black doesn't mean you have to serve curried goat or black-eyed peas and smothered pork chops," she said.</p>
        <p>At One Market, Mr. Simmons's specialties include a fried onion salad with smoked salmon and chervil creme fraiche and a beef tenderloin with a red wine reduction and bone marrow sauce.</p>
        <p>This new group of young black chefs is proving, often to skeptical parents and high school students alike, that becoming a chef or embarking on a career in the food service industry can lead to success and financial independence, not a return to the servitude of generations past.</p>
        <p>Statistics compiled by the National Restaurant Association, a trade group in Washington, show that blacks, who represented 10 percent of the total work force in 1992, held a higher-than-average proportion of jobs in food preparation and service, 13 percent.</p>
        <p>The Bureau of Labor Statistics says that in 1992, blacks held about 44,000, or 13.2 percent, of the 338,000 supervisory positions in food service and preparation. In 1983 they held about 25,000, or 10.6 percent, of 239,000 supervisory positions.</p>
        <p>"Maybe we'll start to bring a sense of the prestige you can have in this field," said Mr. Simmons, who was one of a group of black chefs honored in August at a benefit dinner held by the Sonoma County chapter of 100 Black Men. This group, a national organization, is dedicated to promoting positive role models and raising money for scholarships.</p>
        <p>"The jobs are not just in the kitchen," Mr. Simmons added. "There are also careers in the front of the house, in management, but kids don't know what the opportunities are."</p>
        <p>Ms. Cholmondeley, the executive chef at Livanos, a seafood restaurant, said: "We have to convince people that this is a creditable profession. They think of McDonald's and they're not aware of the possibilities."</p>
        <p>A native of Guyana, Ms. Cholmondeley originally wanted to be a textile designer but became interested in food and decided to attend the Culinary Institute of America in Hyde Park, N.Y. She helped organize a new chapter of black alumni of the school, which is often considered the Harvard of professional cooking schools. The group hopes, among other things, to establish three full-tuition scholarships.</p>
        <p>Jane Wallace, a director of the school who heads the enrollment committee, said blacks make up 4 percent of the student body. Over all, the minority enrollment, including Hispanics, Asians and American Indians, is 12 percent.</p>
        <p>Industry observers also point out that high school guidance counselors need more information about opportunities in the food-service field. "Many of them do not understand that home ec can lead to management positions," said Michael Hurst, a restaurateur in Fort Lauderdale and former president of the National Restaurant Association, who is advising guidance counselors in Florida. The first black president of the restaurant association, Herman Cain, takes office next year. He is also the chief executive of the Godfather's Pizza chain.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bell, the owner of Lolabelle, who started working in restaurants to supplement her income as an actress, regularly talks to high school students.</p>
        <p>"The restaurant business is wonderful because you can be a success without a college degree," she said. "Where else can you start with nothing and wind up owning a business?"</p>
        <p>Ms. Bell has also started an apprenticeship program in her kitchen, a step not without its disheartening aspects. One apprentice, she said, wound up selling drugs in the kitchen. "That was the downside," she said. "But then when I saw the progress made by one young man who could not look you in the eye at first, I knew it's worthwhile."</p>
        <p>Many successful black chefs came from close-knit families. Where the family structure is fragile or nonexistent, mentors become even more essential.</p>
        <p>Susy Davidson, the executive director of the new International Association of Women Chefs and Restaurateurs, said, "You have to have role models and actively network so you can help each other." Her group also plans to reach out to minority men, because they face problems similar to those confronting women.</p>
        <p>Black women have long been professional cooks, a vocational track that evolved from the days when they were domestic employees. A number of them have become extremely successful, like Sylvia Woods, the owner of Sylvia's, a soul-food restaurant in Harlem, and Leah Chase, whose mother opened Dooky Chase, a Creole restaurant in New Orleans, in 1941.</p>
        <p>If today's chefs have broadened their culinary horizons, they have not abandoned tradition. Edna Lewis, for many years the chef at Cafe Nicholson, a restaurant serving Continental food in Manhattan, is now the executive chef at Gage &amp; Tollner in Brooklyn and is serving some Southern specialities.</p>
        <p>Joe C. Randall, who was an instructor at California State Polytechnic Institute and is now promoting black chefs through cable television programs called "Cookin' With Soul," also started a group called A Taste of Heritage Foundation to highlight black contributions to the American table and to raise money for scholarships.</p>
        <p>Ms. Thompson, the founder of the new African-American chef and cookbook author association, is hoping that as blacks become increasingly powerful in the food field, the status of black cooking will also rise.</p>
        <p>"We need greater recognition of the African-American contribution to the American table," Ms. Thompson said. "There are very few upscale restaurants serving African-American food, and we need to encourage them."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
