<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Again, Knicks Squander a Lead</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="398782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DALLAS MAVERICKS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK KNICKERBOCKERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, CLIFTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Dallas Mavericks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA163FF934A35752C1A966958260" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Again, Knicks Squander a Lead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWN, CLIFTON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In their three games this season, the Knicks have let leads slip away as easily as a wet bar of soap.</p>
        <p>Last night, the Knicks lost a 16-point second-quarter lead and suffered a disappointing 96-91 loss to the Dallas Mavericks at Madison Square Garden. It was the Knicks' second consecutive home loss, and in all of their games, they have surrendered double-digit leads in the second half.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In their three games this season, the Knicks have let leads slip away as easily as a wet bar of soap.</p>
        <p>Last night, the Knicks lost a 16-point second-quarter lead and suffered a disappointing 96-91 loss to the Dallas Mavericks at Madison Square Garden. It was the Knicks' second consecutive home loss, and in all of their games, they have surrendered double-digit leads in the second half.</p>
        <p>They had a 16-point lead against Charlotte and needed a rally to win in overtime in their season opener last Friday. They had a 19-point lead against Boston on Saturday and lost. But last night's second-half collapse was the most disheartening of all.</p>
        <p>Playing 48 minutes of good basketball seems something the Knicks are incapable of doing right now. "If we don't change this pattern, it's going to be a long season," said Patrick Ewing, who led the Knicks with 26 points and 10 rebounds.  Defensive Breakdown</p>
        <p>The Mavericks won not only because they rallied, but also because the Knicks broke down defensively. With New York leading, 91-90, Rolando Blackman scored on a layup while being fouled by Gerald Wilkins. Blackman, who ended up with 20 points, was Wilkins's defensive assignment, and the Knick guard let Blackman escape, then compounded the error by fouling.</p>
        <p>"It's a tough play, because in that situation, Blackman has the option to either come off the screen for a jumper, or to cut backdoor," Wilkins said. "He had been so hot shooting the ball, I didn't want to give up the jumper. You almost have to guess, and he did the opposite of what I thought."</p>
        <p>After Blackman missed the free throw, the Knicks needed a basket to go ahead. Most of the 14,056 fans, and most of the Mavericks, probably expected the ball to go to Ewing. It did not. Instead, Stu Jackson, the Knicks' coach, set up a play designed to free either Mark Jackson or Kiki Vandeweghe.</p>
        <p>Mark Jackson backed Derek Harper into the lane, then launched an 8-foot turn-around jumper. The ball kissed the backboard, slid around the rim, and spun out. Ewing could not control the rebound and lost the ball out of bounds with 25 seconds remaining. "I couldn't have asked for a better shot," Jackson said.</p>
        <p>On the next Dallas possession, Vandeweghe was forced to foul James Donaldson with 14 seconds remaining, and the Maverick center made two free throws to give Dallas a 3-point lead. New York's final chance was lost when Wilkins missed a potential game-tying 3-pointer with 8 seconds remaining. Herb Williams rebounded and was fouled, and he made two free throws to clinch the victory for Dallas.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most troubling aspect of this loss for the Knicks was that the Mavericks did most of their damage against New York's starting lineup. Roy Tarpley, who had a game-high 29 points and 10 rebounds, was an inside force. Charles Oakley had 18 rebounds for the Knicks, but committed five fouls trying to contain Tarpley.</p>
        <p>It is becoming clear that the Knicks are not a solid defensive team. They play in spurts. Opponents appear to have the feeling they are never out of a game because New York is susceptible to lapses at any time. After New York went ahead, 49-33, late in the second quarter, the Mavericks regained momentum by scoring the last 7 points of the first half.</p>
        <p>"The difference between the good teams and the very good teams is that the very good teams play well for 48 minutes," said Mark Jackson. "We work hard to get the lead, but we stop attacking."</p>
        <p>How can the Knicks correct the problem? "I think if we execute better offensively down the stretch, we'll be O.K.," Coach Jackson said. "But tonight, we lost our poise down the stretch. That's what was most disheartening."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
