<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talks End, Wait Begins</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="331982"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JAPAN-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAIFU, TOSHIKI (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D91339F936A35750C0A966958260" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talks End, Wait Begins</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>PALM SPRINGS, Calif., March 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In an era in which the cold war is ending, the Germanys are moving toward reunification and the South African Government has legalized the major black opposition, is it possible to resolve trade disputes with Japan?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In an era in which the cold war is ending, the Germanys are moving toward reunification and the South African Government has legalized the major black opposition, is it possible to resolve trade disputes with Japan?</p>
        <p>In an era in which the cold war is ending, the Germanys are moving toward reunification and the South African Government has legalized the major black opposition, is it possible to resolve trade disputes with Japan?</p>
        <p>The grand strategy that President Bush and Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu espoused in their weekend talks was to accelerate the internationalization of Japan - giving it a greater voice in world councils and a greater appetite for the world's goods and services.</p>
        <p>Should the strategy succeed, Japan's surpluses with the United States and other countries would recede, dampening retaliatory sentiments in Washington. And more yen would be plowed into Latin America, Eastern Europe and other areas hungry for capital.</p>
        <p>Vision of the Dangers</p>
        <p>If Mr. Kaifu left Palm Springs with a conceptual framework for greater Japanese political influence in the world, he also had a vision of the dangers if he fails to internationalize his economy.</p>
        <p>The President told White House reporters Saturday, after Mr. Kaifu left for Tokyo: ''I had, in that one-on-one, the opportunity to be just as clear as any Congressman would have liked me to be on what needs to happen to keep this terribly important relationship on track.''</p>
        <p>The President had come to the meeting with letters from lawmakers warning of protectionist reactions if the Japanese, after a decade in which they accumulated $400 billion of trade surpluses with the United States, did not open their markets.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Kaifu said all the right things about his determination to make trade problems ''one of the top priorities of my new Cabinet,'' there is still some healthy skepticism about whether he can deliver.</p>
        <p>As the President himself put it, ''I think the proof of the pudding is in the eating.''</p>
        <p>The House majority leader, Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, who has been a sharp critic of Japan, observed today that over the last decade Japanese prime ministers and American Presidents have had any number of meetings at which trade breakthroughs were supposed to have been made, to little avail.</p>
        <p>''Nothing has changed,'' Mr. Gephardt said on NBC-TV's ''Meet the Press.''</p>
        <p>Taking note of the generalities that both Mr. Kaifu and Mr. Bush used to describe their talks, Senator Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana and chairman of the Senate Finance Committee's trade subcommittee, commented today, ''in trade the devil is in the detail.''</p>
        <p>'U.S. Is Serious About Trade'</p>
        <p>But Mr. Baucus, who has also been highly critical of the Japanese, noted that ''the very fact that the summit was held will send a message that the United States is serious about trade.''</p>
        <p>The President spoke Saturday of a ''trialogue'' among the United States, Japan and the European allies to promote economic development and ''to think about how Japan can more fully play a leading role in the world's political and economic institutions.''</p>
        <p>Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d and Foreign Minister Taro Nakayama have already begun exploring ways to develop the ''trialogue.''</p>
        <p>One possibility would be for a Japanese to become head of either the World Bank or the International Monetary Fund, the two most prestigious global economic institutions, in the next few years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and Mr. Kaifu, in their closing statements after the talks, also hinted at deeper monetary understandings, renewing a pledge to cooperate in foreign exchange markets. The dollar has recently climbed in value against the yen, which threatens improvement of the trade deficit by making Japanese goods less expensive.</p>
        <p>As an export-oriented superpower, Japan has done very well capitalizing on global free trade while restricting foreigners in its market. Powerful industry groups in Japan have a vested interest in maintaining the status quo.</p>
        <p>But in some ways the Japanese consumer has gotten short shrift. Mr. Kaifu is trying to build a power base by allying himself with the consumer.</p>
        <p>His plans for deregulation, increased antitrust enforcement, more effective land use, a more efficient distribution system and other structural changes in Japanese society -all of which would help internationalize the economy - are being sold politically not as concessions to the United States but as essential ingredients to improve the quality of Japanese life.</p>
        <p>President Bush was asked Saturday how confident he was that Mr. Taifu would produce results.</p>
        <p>'I Wish Him Well'</p>
        <p>''Well, he's just won a good victory there,'' he said, referring to the Liberal Democratic Party's victory last month. The President continued: ''He's solidified his party's position. He himself emerges as, I would say, a dynamic new leader. And so we will simply wait and see. But I wish him well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is under pressure from American trade law, which sets deadlines for retaliation against nations that trade unfairly. In coming months, deadlines loom for trade disputes in such sectors as telecommunications, forest products, satellites, supercomputers, shipbuilding and the broader area of structural differences between the United States and Japan.</p>
        <p>The deadlines are the result of stepped-up efforts by Congress in 1988 to deal with mounting business complaints about unfair trade abroad, chiefly in Japan.</p>
        <p>They also reflect frustrations about the rising trade deficits, even though a greater cause of those deficits, most economists agree, is the weak competitive position of the United States, a condition whose causes include low savings, high consumption, high budget deficits and a corporate emphasis on short-term profits.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration does not want to have to retaliate. As the President noted, it is better to resolve trade imbalances by expanding exports, rather than limiting imports.</p>
        <p>Retaliation Less Likely</p>
        <p>Because of Mr. Kaifu's promises, the weekend meeting between the two leaders probably makes retaliation less likely. Despite the deadlines, the President retains flexibility if he can assure Congress that progress is being made.</p>
        <p>Although the business community favors keeping pressure on Japan, it too has little stomach for retaliaion, at least this year. Instead, it is pinning its hopes for trade gains and profits on the international free trade negotiations currently under way that are known as the Uruguay Round.</p>
        <p>These talks, conducted by the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, the world body that oversees trade, are scheduled to end in December. The agenda includes providing international protecton against theft of patents and copyrights, as well as expanding trade in agriculture and in financial and other services.</p>
        <p>Jerry Jasinowski, president of the 13,500-member National Association of Manufacturers, commented, ''I think there is general support for moving ahead with a strong Uruguay Round and a reluctance to have bloody battles with our trading competitors.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
