<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Media: PRESS;In the dance between business journalists and their sources, who is leading whom?</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="821207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORRIS, FLOYD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE2DC1339F93BA35752C0A960958260" item-length="1394" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Media: PRESS;In the dance between business journalists and their sources, who is leading whom?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Floyd Norris</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORRIS, FLOYD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR financial journalists, talking to people who have a stake in what is printed is so ingrained as to seem obvious. The people who think about markets and know what is going on are almost always participants. And they do not often  speak against their own interests.</p>
        <p>In the world of Wall Street, getting favorable publicity for your own position is known as "talking your portfolio." It is a rare money manager who will bad-mouth a stock he owns, or who will forecast plunging bond prices when he owns a lot of bonds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR financial journalists, talking to people who have a stake in what is printed is so ingrained as to seem obvious. The people who think about markets and know what is going on are almost always participants. And they do not often  speak against their own interests.</p>
        <p>In the world of Wall Street, getting favorable publicity for your own position is known as "talking your portfolio." It is a rare money manager who will bad-mouth a stock he owns, or who will forecast plunging bond prices when he owns a lot of bonds.</p>
        <p>For financial reporters, that presents a dilemma. To avoid sources with conflicts of interest is to avoid sources who know what is going on. But to rely on them is to invite criticism that reporters are being used by people trying to make a buck.</p>
        <p>These issues were thrown into harsh relief with the public dismissal of Dan Dorfman from Money magazine last week. Mr. Dorfman, by far the most prominent journalist covering the markets, has long been able to move stocks with a few words, though that is much more likely to happen as a result of his appearances  on the CNBC cable channel than with his monthly column in Money.</p>
        <p>He has been under attack since Business Week reported that a friend of Mr. Dorfman had built a career out of providing access to the columnist and that he  had persuaded Mr. Dorfman to praise some dubious stocks. Business Week added that the Securities and Exchange Commission was looking into the relationship.</p>
        <p>Money says it dismissed Mr. Dorfman for his unwillingness to disclose to his  editor the names of confidential sources cited in his columns for the magazine.  Maybe so, but that explanation also allowed the magazine to get rid of the high-priced columnist without addressing the question of whether he had actually done anything wrong.</p>
        <p>For many financial journalists, the most bothersome question is whether a source is using a journalist for a quick profit. In the 1980's, when the reign of junk bonds made it seem like almost anybody could mount a corporate takeover, there were cases in which a previously unknown raider would be reported to own a sizable stake in a company, with plans to mount a takeover. The stock would leap, but nothing more would be heard of the raid. The suspicion was that the raider used the publicity generated by his leak to find buyers for his stock.</p>
        <p>There is also the case of money managers talking up stocks that they own but  wish they did not, perhaps hoping that the publicity will bring out buyers to take the shares off their hands. That happens fairly often, and does not even involve anonymous sources.</p>
        <p>Such cases explain why some journalists, this one included, sometimes pass up exclusives, fearing that the risk of being used outweighs the marginal benefit of the apparent scoop. There is no easy way to know if a money manager is using  a publication to find buyers for his mistakes, but I routinely warn managers that if I think they are doing that, I will never quote them again.</p>
        <p>Does it work? I'm not sure. But I have had managers, after getting that warning, refuse to talk about stocks they are known to own. I take that as a sign they are selling them, and let it pass.</p>
        <p>Reporters also have a responsibility to know something of the record of the money managers they quote plugging securities. That was illustrated in the last  few weeks by the downfall of S. Jay Goldinger, a much-quoted bond manager who lost big with a poorly timed bet on interest rates and who some clients now maintain misled them. Reporters who used Mr. Goldinger had either not known of or deemed irrelevant the fact that he had been charged by the S.E.C. with insider trading, a charge he beat in court.</p>
        <p>With anonymous sources, the risks grow larger. If an unnamed analyst or money manager is quoted as saying that a certain company is about to report a stunning rise in profits, or has fraudulent accounting, or whatever, that can move the stock price a lot, especially if the company is relatively small.</p>
        <p>The report may or may not be true, but even if it is false there is a possibility that the source who planted it will be able to profit by buying or selling stock in advance, and then reversing the trades as soon as the report is out. And that can be done without the public even knowing who planted the report.</p>
        <p>What is the solution there? First, there is a need to restrict the use of anonymous sources, particularly for information that seems to be very important.</p>
        <p>It is one thing to let a money manager say anonymously that he is shorting semiconductor makers because he thinks a supply glut is coming. That is a forecast based on publicly available information, is clearly an opinion and could be wrong. I'll sometimes use a quote like that. But I won't let some manager say a company is about to get rich off an unannounced contract, or is under investigation by the Government.</p>
        <p>I might try to check out such a tip and run a story if I can confirm it, but  then I am relying on the anonymous source only for a lead, not a fact.</p>
        <p>That kind of reporting is what is often the most needed, and the most difficult. It is the job of a reporter to read and understand financial statements of companies being written about. It is amazing how often a careful analysis of such statements can confirm or deny a report that is being circulated about a company.</p>
        <p>The failure to do that analysis is not illegal; it may not even be unethical. It is a sign of a lack of competence. And there is little doubt that incompetence is a bigger problem than venality in financial journalism.</p>
        <p>In a number of cases over the years, financial journalists have acted in clearly wrong ways, and most publications now have rules against journalists investing in companies they write about.</p>
        <p>There was Alex Campbell, for example, a columnist for The Los Angeles Herald  Examiner in the 1960's, who would buy shares in small companies, tout the companies in his column and then sell the stocks to meet the demand he had generated.</p>
        <p>And there was R. Foster Winans, the columnist for The Wall Street Journal who went to prison for trading in advance of his column.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dorfman vigorously denied having done anything similar, and it would be very surprising if it turned out he had.</p>
        <p>But there is a distinction between not acting illegally and acting responsibly. Mr. Dorfman declined to be interviewed for this column, but in interviews over the years he has indicated a lack of concern about whether he was being used by sources.</p>
        <p>"We're all used," he was quoted as saying to Forbes Media Critic. "If that's  a scandal, it's one at every publication in the industry."</p>
        <p>Any journalist plying this area has been used, this columnist included. If someone points out to me that there is a problem with a company's financial statements, and I determine that there is, the resulting story no doubt pleases  the tipster.</p>
        <p>But part of what financial journalists owe readers is an effort to make sure  that the sources they use are speaking the truth, and to be concerned about the  possibility of being used. That means not printing every rumor that comes along  and it means trying to make clear the interests of those sources that are used,  whether quoted by name or anonymously.</p>
        <p>Those journalists who are not concerned about that are not doing their readers a favor.</p>
        <p>Floyd Norris writes the weekly Market Watch columnfor The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Floyd Norris writes the weekly Market Watch columnfor The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
