<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cornhuskers' Frazier Is a Subtle Player, Maybe a Little Too Subtle</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="810944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ON COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRAZIER, TOMMIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORAN, MALCOLM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0D81339F930A15752C1A963958260" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cornhuskers' Frazier Is a Subtle Player, Maybe a Little Too Subtle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Malcolm Moran</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORAN, MALCOLM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He doesn't pass enough. He doesn't run enough. Just what has Tommie Frazier been doing lately, anyway?</p>
        <p>Frazier's growth into a finished product -- skilled passer, deceptively powerful rusher and the precise leader of Nebraska's so-far unstoppable offense  -- will one day secure him a place in the College Football Hall of Fame. But the emergence of his dominant, disciplined versatility may just be too subtle for most Heisman Award voters to grasp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He doesn't pass enough. He doesn't run enough. Just what has Tommie Frazier been doing lately, anyway?</p>
        <p>Frazier's growth into a finished product -- skilled passer, deceptively powerful rusher and the precise leader of Nebraska's so-far unstoppable offense  -- will one day secure him a place in the College Football Hall of Fame. But the emergence of his dominant, disciplined versatility may just be too subtle for most Heisman Award voters to grasp.</p>
        <p>His play has inspired a chant, "Tommie Heisman," that has become the Midwest version of Donnie Baseball; same rhythm, same inflection, a similar tribute to an unforgettable body of work that will soon become complete. When the regular season ends and the votes are counted, Frazier may discover that his biggest obstacle this season was not across any line of scrimmage, but on the other side of all those sealed envelopes.</p>
        <p>Not that he's complaining. Frazier has been asked, again and again, about his outlook toward the award and his chances in this senior season. His response has been as consistent and direct as his play. "I'm still keeping it to myself," Frazier said this week as the Cornhuskers prepared for the game tomorrow against Oklahoma, his final appearance at Memorial Stadium in Lincoln, Neb. "Maybe after the Oklahoma game I can come out more openly about it. I don't want to jinx myself."</p>
        <p>The chances of Frazier striking a Heisman pose after reaching the Oklahoma end zone would seem roughly equivalent to the possibility of Tom Osborne, the Husker coach, mooning the Sooner sideline. When Frazier was politely pressed on the award, he didn't budge. "I don't know who I'd vote for," he said. "I'm not going to get into the issue. I don't have a vote."</p>
        <p>Frazier is the most important player, by far, on the nation's highest-ranked</p>
        <p>team, a distinction that earned Miami's Gino Torretta a Heisman three years ago. But Frazier does not possess Torretta's passing statistics, and he does not project the drop-back image that remains the standard at quarterback.</p>
        <p>His average of 158.5 passing yards a game, a 58 percent completion rate and just 3 interceptions indicate that Frazier could succeed even if he were limited to nothing but pocket passes. But he's not, and for voters who cling to the first impression of the freshman option quarterback, that versatility becomes a  political weakness. Frazier's pass-efficiency rating of 167.0 would rank third in the nation if he attempted an average of 15 passes a game. He has averaged 13.8 attempts. Voters do not like sorting through "ifs."</p>
        <p>Frazier runs well enough to average 6.5 yards a carry, a figure that is better than 19 of the top 20 rushers in the country. But as much as his running  ability is the focus of an offense that has averaged 412.7 rushing yards, most of those numbers are not attached to his name. Frazier has been responsible for  30 touchdowns this season, 14 on rushes, but he has not produced the kind of Grange-like day that Ohio State's Eddie George had against Illinois. He has not  had the chance.</p>
        <p>"We have not had him throw the ball 35 times a game, which hurts him in passing statistics," Osborne said. "Nor have we had him run 25 times, which hurts him in rushing statistics."</p>
        <p>If the Heisman discussion begins and ends with yards? "If that's the criteria," Osborne said, "he's not going to win."</p>
        <p>Are enough voters that discerning? The Nebraska system has spread the yards evenly enough to diminish Frazier's impact on a perfect season, even as he has made last year's blood clots a distant scare. The memory of last year's once-a-generation offensive line, which seemed to make the identity of the quarterback insignificant, does not help Frazier, either. The image of the Husker factory, producing year after year of outstanding linemen, belies the fact that this season's group was reassembled with no margin for error. After the suspension of Lawrence Phillips, Frazier was operating behind a relatively inexperienced line with a true freshman, Ahman Green, often lining up at tailback. The beat went on.</p>
        <p>Nebraska officials have been left to emphasize the team's 31-3 record with Frazier at quarterback, but the Heisman is not a lifetime achievement award. And who knows how Nebraska's legal problems and deteriorated image will affect voters. The Huskers scored 77 points against Arizona State. Ohio State's John Cooper held starters out of the second half of a rout of Iowa.</p>
        <p>The slights may just be starting. When Frazier was asked about life beyond the degree he will earn in May, he said: "Look for a good job. If pro football comes, I'll give it a shot. If not, I'll find something else to do."</p>
        <p>The decision-makers who shape the professional draft reduced Rodney Peete to  an afterthought and determined that Charlie Ward had no future in football. Tommie Frazier could become one of the finest players in the history of the college game to never win a Heisman and never take a snap in the National Football League. When Frazier stops running from Buffaloes and Sooners -- and maybe Florida Gators, with a second championship on the line -- the obstacles could become serious.</p>
        <p>ON COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
