<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Faces Emerge</title>
    <meta content="16SUN2$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/16/opinion/16SUN2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1325543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">World Trade Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E7DC163BF935A2575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Faces Emerge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Faces Emerge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says terrorist attacks on America should be taken as invitaton to create great new generation and finer country; says in their shared mission to eradicate terrorism, Americans must be careful to protect core of their national culture and remember that they are fighting not for a flag but for system of beliefs that includes basic civil liberties and unyielding tolerance (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It took almost a day, after the bitter shock of Tuesday morning, before it began to become clear who might be missing, who might be presumed dead and who, in the case of the passengers and crew on the four hijacked planes, must certainly have died. The streets around the hospitals near Lower Manhattan began to fill with stricken people trying to locate friends, co-workers or family members who had gotten to work at the usual hour on Tuesday and had not been heard from since midmorning that day. Some people on the streets carried snapshots, wedding photos, graduation pictures. Some had already printed fliers asking, ''Have you seen this person?''</p>
        <p>By Thursday, there were as many fliers across the city as there were American flags. People going about their business stopped to read them again and again wherever they were posted, to touch them sometimes in mute homage. And as the fliers spread, so did the obituaries, which are now, as certainty sets in, beginning to radiate outward from the epicenter of this disaster through big-city and small-town newspapers all across the country. This is an aftershock that has only begun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Collectively, the victims' stories that are emerging provide a remarkably precious opportunity to witness a portrait of this nation assembled out of memories and pictures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It took almost a day, after the bitter shock of Tuesday morning, before it began to become clear who might be missing, who might be presumed dead and who, in the case of the passengers and crew on the four hijacked planes, must certainly have died. The streets around the hospitals near Lower Manhattan began to fill with stricken people trying to locate friends, co-workers or family members who had gotten to work at the usual hour on Tuesday and had not been heard from since midmorning that day. Some people on the streets carried snapshots, wedding photos, graduation pictures. Some had already printed fliers asking, ''Have you seen this person?''</p>
        <p>By Thursday, there were as many fliers across the city as there were American flags. People going about their business stopped to read them again and again wherever they were posted, to touch them sometimes in mute homage. And as the fliers spread, so did the obituaries, which are now, as certainty sets in, beginning to radiate outward from the epicenter of this disaster through big-city and small-town newspapers all across the country. This is an aftershock that has only begun.</p>
        <p>We are just now getting to know these people, the missing and the dead. Their stories carry a weight no one expected because they are such ordinary stories. The people in the World Trade Center on Tuesday morning were bond traders and secretaries, custodians and firefighters, people who had virtually lived at their desks and people who had come to the building only for an appointment that morning.</p>
        <p>Some had been through the 1993 bombing and probably thought about it every day. Some had never gotten over the view from the twin towers, and some no longer saw it at all. You could have found people living in nearly every neighborhood in New York and much of northern New Jersey, people who had grown up or gone to school in nearly every state in this country. The reach of the families they had come from or the families they had raised themselves was truly global.</p>
        <p>No person is interchangeable with another, but we all understand how interchangeable these Tuesday morning stories might have been if the timing of the attacks and the ultimate collapse of the towers had been different. The dividing line between those who made it out and those who didn't is  inexplicable. We are also learning to recognize in the tales the obituaries tell, and in the profiles of the victims we see on television, how interchangeable we might have been with those who died. Their lives resembled ours more closely than we can let ourselves imagine. What we see in those faces and in the lives that ended on Tuesday is the idea of a normality that now belongs to the past.</p>
        <p>Collectively, the stories that are emerging of these lives do not perfectly represent the demographics of America. But they do perfectly represent the elements out of which each of us -- however we differ -- tries to fashion a meaningful existence, one that looks characteristically American whether we mean it to or not.</p>
        <p>The result of Tuesday's destruction is that we have been given a privileged glimpse into the interior of one family after another. It is like walking down the block and being able to see for a moment through the walls of some of the houses. The emotional architecture looks familiar. It is the act of seeing that seems strange.</p>
        <p>This moment of perception will close. The obituaries will run their course, and city workers will  eventually take down the fliers posted all across town, the ones the wind and rain have not taken down first. There will be funerals and memorial services. And just as surely as some people will try to put their grief behind them, there will be others who cannot do so, who will go on believing with a desperate hope that the missing will somehow turn up.</p>
        <p>But for now we have a remarkably precious opportunity to witness a portrait of this nation assembled out of memories and pictures, out of the efforts of everyday people to explain in everyday words who it is they lost on Tuesday. They hold out their photographs to strangers and television cameras. The faces looking out of those pictures could not have imagined knowing what we know now. You can tell it by the way they smile.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
