<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Girl Singing Group Aims for the Stars</title>
    <meta content="24HUCK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1621583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Huckapoo (Music Group)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DA113AF937A15753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Girl Singing Group Aims for the Stars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIAN S. TOY</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles Huckapoo, five-girl band modeled after Spice Girls that has been touring summer camps; three members are from Long Island, one from Rockland County and fifth from rural Pennsylvania; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR as long as Brooke Mori can remember, she has warmed to the glare of stage lights and longed to become a star. Now, at the ripe old age of 13, she can claim to be well on her way to finding the fame she has craved.</p>
        <p>On stage, she is PJ Bardot, a member of Huckapoo, a five-girl band modeled after the Spice Girls that aspires to be the next big thing for the pre-teen set. Back home, though, at least until last year, Brooke was just another student at Bedford Middle School. Three of the other Huckapoo girls also come from the New York City area: two from Long Island and one from Rockland County. The fifth comes from rural Pennsylvania.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR as long as Brooke Mori can remember, she has warmed to the glare of stage lights and longed to become a star. Now, at the ripe old age of 13, she can claim to be well on her way to finding the fame she has craved.</p>
        <p>On stage, she is PJ Bardot, a member of Huckapoo, a five-girl band modeled after the Spice Girls that aspires to be the next big thing for the pre-teen set. Back home, though, at least until last year, Brooke was just another student at Bedford Middle School. Three of the other Huckapoo girls also come from the New York City area: two from Long Island and one from Rockland County. The fifth comes from rural Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Huckapoo spent the summer performing at summer camps in what amounts to a Borscht Belt circuit for tweens youngsters who have outgrown Barney, but who aren't quite mature enough for J. Lo. At each of the 12 camps where they performed, the girls were mobbed by enthusiastic fans who clamored for their autographs and snatched up the group's promotional CDs. A few boys offered their cellphone numbers, original poetry, rings and marriage proposals.</p>
        <p>Even before Huckapoo began its camp tour, the group had already wedged its high-energy teenaged toe into the world of pop stardom. The group has songs on three Disney soundtracks, opened for the tween heartthrob Aaron Carter at a Staten Island concert in June, and are called one of ''today's hottest rising stars'' in the teen magazine, Pop Star!</p>
        <p>When they perform, the girls exude a confidence that comes from years of voice and dance lessons and public performances ranging from community theater to national tours of Broadway and Disney shows. But they also radiate a wholesome youthfulness that stems from the overwhelming sense that they just seem to be having so much fun up onstage.</p>
        <p>So despite missing out on many of the rituals of a ''normal'' childhood, like lazy days at the beach or afternoons hanging out at the local mall, the Huckapoo girls are eager for what might come next. Their parents also are comfortable with the decisions they've made along the way: all the years of talent auditions and dance lessons instead of soccer or field hockey practice and trading regular school for private tutors so Huckapoo can rehearse or perform five, sometimes seven, days a week.</p>
        <p>Brooke, at age 13, is the youngest Huckapoo member, and she admitted to being ''a little sad'' to be missing her freshman year at Staples High School this fall. ''But I'm more excited for this,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Lindsay Nyman, the 14-year-old Long Islander who plays Joey Thunders and would have been a freshman at Long Beach High School in September, shared that sentiment and said, ''There are just so many things to look forward to.''</p>
        <p>The camp shows, in many ways, were merely dress rehearsals for the group's first major show with ticket-buying customers, on Oct. 8 at Town Hall in Manhattan. The girls recorded two songs for a special Christmas CD that will be released next month at Wal-Mart and FYE stores and on which they share billing with Raven and Ashlee Simpson. They will continue recording songs for an album that is scheduled for release in January. And there will be more trips to California in hopes of landing a movie or television deal.</p>
        <p>''All I know right now is they're having such a great time and they're getting great experience,'' said Lori Mori, Brooke's mother, who marvels at how close the girls have gotten. ''Usually when you get five girls together at this age, one day they're inseparable and the next they're crying they hate each other,'' she said. ''But with these girls, I haven't seen a single spat.''</p>
        <p>Nine months ago, Huckapoo was but a concept in the mind of Brian Lukow, a producer who in the late 1990's helped create Dream Street, a boy band that was destined to be the next 'N Sync. Dream Street's first record went gold, with more than 750,000 copies sold, but the band broke up in 2002 after the boys' parents filed a lawsuit against Mr. Lukow and another producer. They charged the producers with creating an atmosphere harmful to minors. The case was dismissed.</p>
        <p>''With Dream Street, the ship came in and then the dock collapsed,'' Mr. Lukow said. ''No one won in that, we all lost.'' Today, only one of the five boys in the band, Jesse McCartney, had hit it big, with a starring role in the WB television drama, Summerland.</p>
        <p>When casting for Huckapoo, Mr. Lukow said he took great care in interviewing the parents as well as the girls. ''I told them they could ask me whatever they wanted about Dream Street, but I had to know that they understood the commitment this was going to take,'' he said.</p>
        <p>So far, he added, everyone has gotten along remarkably well and they have adapted well to the vagaries of a wannabe pop star's life. There are the days when a recording session is unexpectedly delayed for hours, the girls have nothing to pass the time but their iPods and crossword puzzles, and the session winds up running until midnight, or when a camp concert and autograph signing runs late and the girls don't get home until 3 a.m.</p>
        <p>During the school year, the girls would show up at a Manhattan studio five days a week for tutoring from 10:30 a.m. until 1:30 p.m. and then rehearse until 7:30 p.m., learning new songs and dance routines. On weekends, they would put in long hours at a recording studio. Since February, they have recorded more than two dozen songs, many of them originals co-written by Mr. Lukow and songwriters who wrote for Dream Street. They have also taped a music video.</p>
        <p>But the girls insist that none of this feels like work to them. ''It's all new because it's very different from the kinds of things we were doing before,'' said Brittany Lahm, a 15-year-old who plays Twiggy Stardom and is from New City in Rockland County. ''Plus we're like five best friends.''</p>
        <p>Because their schedule can be erratic, the girls often wind up sleeping over at one another's homes. ''I have toothbrushes at everybody's house,'' Brooke said.</p>
        <p>Jordan Price, who plays Groovy Tuesday and is a 15-year-old from Hamburg, Pa., said that it helps that they're all about the same size. ''We don't have to pack ever because we just wear everybody's clothes,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The target audience for Huckapoo is boys and girls ages 6 to 14. Each band member plays a character, a type that might be found in any middle school lunchroom.</p>
        <p>PJ Bardot is into hip-hop and rap music.</p>
        <p>Joey Thunders is punk and favors fishnet stockings and dog collars.</p>
        <p>Twiggy Stardom is the preppy cheerleader.</p>
        <p>Groovy Tuesday is a 1960's-style hippie who wears tie-dye and ripped jeans.</p>
        <p>And finally, Angel Sparks is a biker girl, a character that Mr. Lukow admitted is a little problematic given her age, but his idea was to have someone who favored leather and black, but not the blood and darkness of the Goth crowd. Brittney Segal, the 14-year-old from Jericho who plays Angel, doesn't ride a motorcycle, but has molded the character into someone with a distinct style.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lukow chose the name Huckapoo, he said, because he wanted something that didn't sound ''too girly'' but that also didn't mean anything and could become a topic of conversation. It also helped that www.huckapoo.com was available. Huckapoo, he added, does not derive from Huk-A-Poo, the 70's clothing line.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lukow auditioned more than 200 girls last fall and after a second round of callbacks, he had his cast of five. Each of the girls had an agent, professional training and some professional experience under her belt.</p>
        <p>Brooke had performed with the Kirov Ballet at the Metropolitan Opera House and also was in the national tour of Disney's ''Bear in the Big Blue House.'' Lindsay portrayed the Little Girl in the national tour of Ragtime when she was 9 years old. Coincidentally, Brittney played the same role the next year, when she was 10. Jordan was in the American Girls Revue at American Girl Place, the retail store devoted to the popular line of dolls. And Brittany had done several television commercials, including one for Dimetapp, Barbie Generation Girl and Nix Lice Shampoo. (She was the friend of the girl who had lice.)</p>
        <p>Each of the girls had some trouble getting used to the idea that they had to completely adopt the personalities of their characters whenever in public.</p>
        <p>But early on, Mr. Lukow laid down the law. ''I told them this is not a democracy and this is the way it is,'' he said. ''The girls have to be larger than life and they have to buy into these characters if Huckapoo is going to succeed as a business for us. And God bless them, because after our talk, they got it.''</p>
        <p>The idea of five very different girls coming together to make music and sing about the things that girls care about boys, crushes, boys, being misunderstood, and boys seems to resonate with their target audience.</p>
        <p>''I like them because they're original and I can relate to their songs,'' said Hillary Rapport, a 13-year-old from Harrison, N.Y. who was at Huckapoo's last camp concert at Indian Head Camp in Lookout, Pa. ''You don't really see girls our age singing, so it's kind of cool.''</p>
        <p>Jeremy Ferris, 13, of Syosset, N.Y., who was also in the Indian Head audience, said, ''They have a great sound and I liked their dance moves and how they move together.'' He added that he thought Huckapoo appeals more to boys than girls because ''You know,'' he shrugged. Then, after struggling for words, he finally said, ''They're cute.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lukow would not talk about Huckapoo's expenses. But to make the group a success, he and his partner will likely have to lay out millions of dollars to get the exposure they need. Each girl collects a salary, and operating costs have included everything from private tutors and studio time to hotel bills and the fee for Camplified, the Manhattan company that produced the camp tour.</p>
        <p>''I push the girls hard because, basically, the entire business is based on five girls becoming superstars or the business fails,'' Mr. Lukow said. ''I guess that makes me nuts, but there's no way to say it differently. They have to be nothing short of amazing.''</p>
        <p>The girls' parents said they believed that Huckapoo just might have a shot at real success because the girls are talented, the concept is different and Mr. Lukow seems to have the right show business connections.</p>
        <p>''I figure she's got the rest of her life to be miserable in some job,'' said Lindsay's father, Bruce Nyman. ''But even if they don't become the next Spice Girls, it's been a heckuva ride for Lindsay and the other girls. We'll have no regrets.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
