<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New (Age) American</title>
    <meta content="24NJDI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1621631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chakra (Paramus, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corcoran, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EED7113AF937A15753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New (Age) American</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CORCORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Corcoran, David</byline>
      <dateline>PARAMUS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Corcoran reviews Chakra restaurant in Paramus, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''THE name Chakra, inspired by the ancient yoga systems of India,'' says a press release for this eight-month-old restaurant, ''refers to spinning vortices of energy created within us by the interpenetration of consciousness and physical body . . . a connection to the mind, body and spirit, subtly channeled through the senses.''</p>
        <p>Goodness. Is this a restaurant or a New Age massage? In truth, neither the name nor the public relations blather gives any clue to what Chakra is all about. And this is a good thing, because its pleasures turn out to be unexpected and many.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''THE name Chakra, inspired by the ancient yoga systems of India,'' says a press release for this eight-month-old restaurant, ''refers to spinning vortices of energy created within us by the interpenetration of consciousness and physical body . . . a connection to the mind, body and spirit, subtly channeled through the senses.''</p>
        <p>Goodness. Is this a restaurant or a New Age massage? In truth, neither the name nor the public relations blather gives any clue to what Chakra is all about. And this is a good thing, because its pleasures turn out to be unexpected and many.</p>
        <p>It inhabits a big, anonymous-looking box of a building that used to be Bisque, an ambitious but underpowered New American restaurant that never gained traction here in mall country. Michael Heiden, a 34-year-old restaurant entrepreneur from Florida, acquired it two years ago with a group of partners and proceeded to remake it in his own vision. He poured in money by the carload -- $3 million, he told me the other day -- and while lavish spending is no guarantee of good taste, he has succeeded to a stunning degree.</p>
        <p>The place is enormous, with 187 seats -- a vast, dark cavern with pools of light and shadow. It has palm trees and teak tables and lush, gauze-curtained banquettes strewn with velvet pillows. Two tall, long walls are made of bricks salvaged from a 120-year-old kiln in Illinois; inset are fake windows and Cambodian bas-relief panels depicting Buddhist prayer rites. Off to one side is a long mahogany bar, with low-slung tables and ottomans for a purposeful singles crowd. At the center, lighted like a stage, is a wall of falling water, its colors constantly changing.</p>
        <p>If it all sounds like a garish theme park -- ''Phantom of the Opera'' meets ''Kon-Tiki'' -- I can only try to reassure you that seeing is believing. Somehow it works. And the food, happily, does not come across as an afterthought.</p>
        <p>The menu has very little to do with the restaurant's name. The chef, Edward Lake, 35, comes to Chakra after five years as executive chef in the delegates' dining room at the United Nations. Despite the international pedigree, his style is resolutely New American, focusing on seasonal ingredients assembled in creative ways and plated to look gorgeous under dramatic lighting. What his United Nations tenure seems to have taught him is how to cook impressive food for a great many people without wilting under the stress.</p>
        <p>Smoked salmon belly, for example, offered one recent Sunday as the chef's daily sashimi, could well become a signature dish. Three slices of salty, unctuous fish, edged with a pepper-and-spice crust, were each topped with flying-fish roe, as varicolored as that water wall: red, infused with aged soy sauce; orange, with mirin; and green, with wasabi.</p>
        <p>Prices, not surprisingly, are high. That particular appetizer was $18, and it is easy to spend $60 or more per person, especially if you take advantage of the smartly chosen, well-balanced wine list (which the companionable young black-clad servers will happily deconstruct for you).</p>
        <p>Mr. Lake's fried calamari takes the lead in this year's squid derby. It was crisp, minimally greasy and beautifully complemented by a deep, dark roasted-garlic aioli.</p>
        <p>Surmounting another cliché, four jumbo coconut shrimp were perfectly cooked and enlivened by their crunchy, peppery batter. Washington State oysters were glisteningly fresh despite their 3,000-mile journey. Steak tartare was almost creamy, especially given its topping of chopped hard-cooked egg, but an infusion of mustard and capers gave it energy and life; it came with a bonus, a paper cone filled with herbed potato straws. The only mild disappointment among the starters was the tough pastry crust under a buttery tart of artichokes and wild mushrooms.</p>
        <p>And the only disappointment among main courses was mahi-mahi (listed on the menu as the market-priced ''day boat'' fish), which came to the table overcooked and dry. The day boat offering on another night, wild king salmon, had no such problems. It was succulent, and admirably set off by wild mushrooms and risotto. Pan-roasted duck breast was gamy and juicy, with wilted watercress and a splendid purée of potatoes and green olives. Strip steak was ample and tender, set off by sharp broccoli rabe and a chive-potato purée.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lake has a good time with pasta. Tagliatelle, boiled and then deep-fried, made an intriguing base for littleneck clams in a delicious lemony broth mellowed by tomato concassé. Homemade ravioli were filled with shredded short ribs and served over a terrific, multilayered sauce that incorporated cream, wine and foie gras trimmings but somehow stopped short of punishing richness.</p>
        <p>Short ribs, properly meaty and fatty, came with a nice counterintuitive touch: a potato salad whose infusions of vinegar and dill made a cooling, tangy contrast to the beef. Next to that dish, grilled diver scallops with shaved fennel, orange sections and mizuna greens amounted to spa cuisine.</p>
        <p>Desserts do not flag. A tall, pyramidal napoleon of fresh berries and goat cheese was the most spectacular, but crème brûlée was first rate, and so were a Meyer lemon tart and a dark, intense Valrhona chocolate cake. A chocolate-and-vanilla ice-cream sandwich with all sorts of caloric bells and whistles struck me as over the top, and so did a malted-milk-ball mousse.</p>
        <p>But sorbets and gelatos, cut into cubes and presented in whimsical architectural stacks, were light, smooth and filled with character. They may not have had chakra, but they sent us home happy. And regardless of the name, that's the point.</p>
        <p>Chakra  W-144 Route 4 (eastbound)  Paramus  (201) 556-1530  www.chakrarestaurant.com</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- A tour de force of a restaurant, big, dark and dramatic.  SERVICE -- Eager to please, but often confused. Prepare to be double-teamed.  SMOKING -- Cigarettes are allowed in the bar, and smoke drifts into the dining area.  WINE LIST -- Long and varied, with good choices even in the $20's and $30's. Wines by the glass (mostly $7 to $10) are particularly well chosen.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Oysters, sashimi, coconut shrimp, calamari, steak tartare; pastas of the day, salmon (roasted or grilled), grilled scallops, duck breast, strip steak, short ribs; berry napoleon, crème brûlée, chocolate cake, lemon tart, sorbets and gelatos.  PRICE RANGE -- Dinner appetizers: $6 to $18; entrees: $19 to $34; desserts: $6 to $10.  HOURS -- Open daily. Lunch: Monday through Friday, and Sunday jazz brunch, 11:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m. Dinner: Monday through Thursday, 6 to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 6 to 11 p.m.; Sunday, 5 to 9 p.m.  CREDIT CARDS -- American Express, Diners' Club, MasterCard, Visa.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Fully accessible.  IF YOU GO -- The restaurant is just west of the Garden State Plaza shopping center and the intersection of Routes 4 and 17. Detailed directions are on its Web site.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
