<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bronx Politics Is Complicated As Politician Pledges to Run</title>
    <meta content="13BRON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1024106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bronx (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hicks, Jonathan P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Espada, Pedro Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Espada, Pedro Gautier (Councilman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E4DB163DF930A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bronx Politics Is Complicated As Politician Pledges to Run</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pedro Espada Jr, two weeks after dropping out of State Senate race in the Bronx, says he has changed his mind and will run in Democratic primary to regain seat he once held; when he withdrew from race, Espada said that it would help promote party unity while also helping his son, Councilman Pedro Gautier Espada, mend his relationship with Democratic Party officials; Espada says he reversed his decision because Bronx Democratic officials had reneged on what he says were promises to stop investigation of his healthcare business if he withdrew (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two weeks after he dropped out of the State Senate race in the Bronx, Pedro Espada Jr. said yesterday that he had changed his mind and would run in the Democratic primary to regain the seat he once held.</p>
        <p>The decision is certain to inject a new round of turbulence into the political landscape in the Bronx. When he withdrew from the race, Mr. Espada had said that it would help promote party unity while also helping his son, Councilman Pedro Gautier Espada, mend his relationship with Democratic Party officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two weeks after he dropped out of the State Senate race in the Bronx, Pedro Espada Jr. said yesterday that he had changed his mind and would run in the Democratic primary to regain the seat he once held.</p>
        <p>The decision is certain to inject a new round of turbulence into the political landscape in the Bronx. When he withdrew from the race, Mr. Espada had said that it would help promote party unity while also helping his son, Councilman Pedro Gautier Espada, mend his relationship with Democratic Party officials.</p>
        <p>But yesterday, Mr. Espada said he had reversed his decision because Bronx Democratic officials had reneged on what he said were promises to stop an investigation of his health-care business if he withdrew.</p>
        <p>Mr. Espada said that the Bronx Democratic leader, Assemblyman Roberto Ramirez, had indicated two weeks ago that he would ask Robert T. Johnson, the Bronx District Attorney, to end investigations of Mr. Espada's finances at the Soundview Health Clinic if he did not oppose State Senator David Rosado.</p>
        <p>Mr. Espada and his son have had a volatile, on-again off-again relationship with the Bronx Democratic organization for the last two years. But it seemed that the two sides were mending fences with Mr. Espada's decision not to seek his old seat.</p>
        <p>That decision was viewed as a victory for Mr. Ramirez, since it would have reduced the number of Democratic officials facing opponents in the party's primary in September. Instead, Mr. Ramirez and the Democratic organization now seem destined for a highly charged primary season.</p>
        <p>Mr. Espada said that his brother, Jose Espada, the owner of an ambulance company, would now run for the Assembly against Ruben Diaz Jr., who holds the seat once held by Pedro Gautier Espada, the Councilman. Also, Mr. Espada said, his son will oppose Mr. Rosado for the position of Democratic leader in that district.</p>
        <p>The Daily News reported yesterday that it had obtained audio and video tapes from Mr. Espada of a secretly recorded meeting between Mr. Espada and Mr. Rosado as well as a meeting between Mr. Rosado and his son, the Councilman, two weeks ago. In the tapes, the paper said, Mr. Rosado boasted of the Democratic Party's ability to influence the Bronx District Attorney to investigate or call off investigations of Mr. Espada's business, based on the former Senator's political decisions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramirez denied that there was any truth to what Mr. Rosado was saying, calling it the most ''ludicrous statement I would have possibly heard.'' Asked if there had been any deal offered by the organization to persuade Mr. Espada to stay out of the race, Mr. Ramirez said: ''Absolutely not.''</p>
        <p>Steven R. Reed, a spokesman for the Bronx District Attorney, declined to comment on what investigations, if any, his office was conducting into Mr. Espada and his business.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
