<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Politics Keeps New York State Mental Unit Open</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="560461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MENTAL HEALTH AND DISORDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOSPITALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GOWANDA (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GOWANDA PSYCHIATRIC CENTER (NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DD1E3BF937A35753C1A964958260" item-length="1654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Politics Keeps New York State Mental Unit Open</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GOWANDA, N.Y., Oct. 1 --</p>
        <p>A rattling wind slams against the red-brick facade of Building 86 of the Gowanda Psychiatric Center, then whistles down the hallways of what was once a ward in one of New York's state-run mental hospitals.</p>
        <p>Like many of the other structures at the sprawling complex here, Building 86 is empty. But Gowanda, which in its heyday in the 1950's had 3,710 patients on grounds surrounded by farmland, is not closed. On the second floor of Building 67, amid wall stencils of horses, sunsets and a space shuttle, 14 mentally ill people live on a single ward. They are the only patients here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GOWANDA, N.Y., Oct. 1 --</p>
        <p>A rattling wind slams against the red-brick facade of Building 86 of the Gowanda Psychiatric Center, then whistles down the hallways of what was once a ward in one of New York's state-run mental hospitals.</p>
        <p>Like many of the other structures at the sprawling complex here, Building 86 is empty. But Gowanda, which in its heyday in the 1950's had 3,710 patients on grounds surrounded by farmland, is not closed. On the second floor of Building 67, amid wall stencils of horses, sunsets and a space shuttle, 14 mentally ill people live on a single ward. They are the only patients here.</p>
        <p>With local lawmakers fighting fiercely to preserve the hospital and the jobs it provides, the state continues to spend $2.9 million a year to keep Gowanda open -- paying for a round-the-clock admissions center, a staff of 44 including full-time psychiatrists and services ranging from physical therapy to ceramics classes.</p>
        <p>It is an amount that many mental-health advocates call frighteningly high, because it could pay for more than a hundred beds in community residences at a time when thousands of the mentally ill are homeless in the streets of New York City.</p>
        <p>But so far, the Legislature has not provided the legal authorization for the center to be closed.</p>
        <p>So Gowanda has become a sort of Love Canal of state mental-health policy, a ghostly setting that lingers while the bureaucracy fights over what to do with it. And like Love Canal, it is perhaps even more potent as a symbol than for the actual dollars spent here: what is happening at Gowanda, 40 miles south of Buffalo, is likely to happen elsewhere in New York as the state tries to close or reduce services at several other large mental hospitals upstate that are vestiges of another era.</p>
        <p>In each case, a powerful combination of community leaders, local lawmakers and unions are fighting off the planned closures of the mental hospitals, which often have been the dominant employer in their area.</p>
        <p>Their campaigns provide an oddly direct contrast to the "not in my backyard" phenomenon that has stymied attempts downstate to build many of the community residences for the mentally ill, which are far cheaper and considered by experts to be more humane and more effective in treating most sick people. While almost everybody agrees that some of the hospitals need to be phased out, the local groups plead against closing the one in their backyard.</p>
        <p>What has happened, in essence, is that the debate over how best to spend the state's mental-health dollars has been overwhelmed by a classic political struggle over how to fairly divide money between upstate and downstate.</p>
        <p>"There is tremendous pressure on lawmakers to keep these hospitals open until they can find other employment for the people who work there, and I can sympathize with that," said Steven Greenfield, the executive director of the Association of Community Living Agencies in Mental Health, a nonprofit advocacy group. "But to some extent," he said, "mentally ill patients are being held hostage for the sake of economic development."</p>
        <p>Although the vast move to deinstitutionalize the mentally ill has emptied New York's mental hospitals of all but 11,000 patients, there are nonetheless 22 hospitals in the system -- four more than there were even in 1953, when the mental-hospital population hit its peak of 93,000. Nearly two-thirds of the state's mental-health budget is spent on the hospitals, even though the goal of deinstitutionalization was to channel most spending to the community programs.</p>
        <p>So while New York continues to lead every state in per-capita spending on the mentally ill, there is nowhere near enough money for the estimated 170,000 mentally ill people outside the hospitals. And up to half of the patients in the hospitals could themselves be treated in community residences if there were rooms available, state officials say.</p>
        <p>As the patients at Gowanda wander the silent grounds on a chilly fall afternoon, the physical isolation here only magnifies the sense that some are trapped in worlds of their own. "Do you feel that?" asks a woman named Carol, her eyes brimming with tears. "Do you feel the winter feeling coming on?"</p>
        <p>Others say that if there is nobody around, they like it that way. "You know that when all these buildings are empty it's good -- you don't have to look around for anybody looking at you," said Douglas, a bearded 34-year-old man who was committed to Gowanda after the police found him ripping paneling from a house he had formerly lived in. (He said he still considered the wood his.) 'It's Eerie'</p>
        <p>Outside of Building 67, which houses the ward and staff offices and an outpatient treatment center nearby, Gowanda is a virtual ghost town.</p>
        <p>"It's eerie, it's strange," said Peter L. Smith, who started working here as a mental-therapy aide in 1966. Now, as the sergeant in charge of safety and security, he makes the rounds of the empty buildings, guarding against water leaks or cracked pipes.</p>
        <p>"Imagine coming through here at midnight," Mr. Smith said as he took a visitor through the abandoned Building 86. "Just you and a flashlight and your shadows."</p>
        <p>For most workers at Gowanda, there is a lingering sense of bitterness that the hospital, rated among the state's best, was the first to be phased out, and many are convinced that the action has led directly to more homelessness.</p>
        <p>"We opened the back door and closed the front door," said Wayne Jones, a mental-health-therapy aide and the president of the union local. "That's all the state did."</p>
        <p>The state Office of Mental Health announced plans last year to close Gowanda and three other hospitals and cut services at seven other hospitals. The long-term savings would be $420 million a year, or enough to nearly double the budget for community programs.</p>
        <p>But the policy has run into political roadblocks. "It's very easy to stop things in New York State," said Richard C. Surles, the state's Commissioner of Mental Health. "It can be very hard to do them." Foes See a Ploy</p>
        <p>State lawmakers from western New York, however, have an entirely different perspective on the situation at Gowanda. They say that the problem is not that the institution has stayed open too long, but that it was emptied too fast. And they contend that by keeping an almost absurdly small number of patients there, mental-health officials have deliberately created a white elephant in a bid to increase the public pressure to close Gowanda entirely.</p>
        <p>Under the state's Mental Hygiene Law, none of the hospitals can be closed without specific legislative authorization. But the Office of Mental Health is legally able to curtail services to an absolute minimum, which is what has happened at Gowanda.</p>
        <p>"It galls me that the system is being manipulated this way," said State Senator Dale M. Volker, an Erie County Republican. "They decided to close Gowanda down, come what may, and they decided to blame the Legislature. Now they're saying it's costing us a ton of money, and it's your guys' fault."</p>
        <p>Mr. Volker and other lawmakers from the area have declared that they will not let Gowanda close until they are persuaded that the Department of Mental Health has a workable plan for providing acute-care and emergency services for the mentally ill in local hospitals in southwestern New York.</p>
        <p>The state has committed itself to such a plan and says it should be in full operation within the year. John R. Collier, the executive director at Gowanda, warned that it would be a mistake to shut Gowanda down before the state had demonstrated that it would follow through on the alternatives.</p>
        <p>"The stupidest thing we could do is renege on our promises," said Mr. Collier. "The Legislature will say forget it, if this is the way you play ball, then you won't close Willard, you won't close Harlem Valley, you won't close anything else." He was referring to two other mental hospitals slated for closure, in Seneca and Dutchess counties. Inmates Are Jobs</p>
        <p>Assuming the dispute is settled, Gowanda will most likely become a prison. Indeed, half of the original grounds has already been turned into one, the Collins Correctional Center.  But there is also some reluctance among upstate lawmakers in Albany to develop a widespread policy of turning mental hospitals into prisons, since it could jeopardize a separate agreement to build five new prisons in upstate areas. Prisons are a major source of jobs in many rural areas.</p>
        <p>In any case, there is no question that the closings and the up to 9,000 jobs that would be lost, could represent a devastating economic blow to areas that have already been through tough times. The Willard center in Romulus, for instance, is the third-largest employer in Seneca County, which is also facing the prospect of losing another of its largest employers, an Army depot.</p>
        <p>"There are economic reasons why communities don't want to give up the hospitals," said David Mechanic, the director of the Institute for Health, Health Care Policy and Aging Research at Rutgers University. But, he added, "From the point of view of mental health, it's totally irrational to have small numbers of patients in outmoded physical plants that are extremely costly to keep up."</p>
        <p>That is nonetheless exactly what is happening at Gowanda now, where the average spent per patient last year was $192,833, and the costs could grow even more exorbitant.</p>
        <p>And C. Richard Orndoff, the regional director in western New York for the Office of Mental Health, said that as long as the Legislature refused to close the hospital, the law would require that it maintain its accreditation with full staff, doctors, services and an admissions unit -- even if it was not treating anyone.</p>
        <p>"It's not beyond the realm of possibility that we could be sitting here a year from now with 44 staff and 20 empty beds," he said. "We might be open, but with no patients at all."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
