<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crime</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="560596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STASIO, MARILYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAIN, W EDWARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALTERS, MINETTE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAUTER, ERIC</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLY, SUSAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADY, JOHN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LOVE COOLS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ICE HOUSE, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BACKFIRE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">OUT OF THE DARKNESS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">KADDISH IN DUBLIN (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DC153FF937A35753C1A964958260" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marilyn Stasio</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STASIO, MARILYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Would a joke about Northrop Frye make you (a) laugh or (b) cringe? Do you agree with the following statement: "Nowhere was a place more cold-blooded than a graduate English department"? Have you ever wanted to strangle your (a) faculty adviser, (b) graduate assistant or (c) college-age child? If you liked this little quiz, then have I got a book for you.</p>
        <p>LOVE COOLS (Putnam, $19.95), W. Edward Blain's second campus mystery, after "Passion Play," delivers a devious murder plot that catches the conscience, or lack of it, of the summer faculty at the Stone Mountain Theater in Virginia's Shenandoah Valley. Fierce professional rivalries break out among this cutthroat gang of teachers after an esteemed Shakespearean scholar dies in a fire. Although her last manuscript was presumably destroyed, two thematically different versions surface, giving rise to grave charges of fraud.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Would a joke about Northrop Frye make you (a) laugh or (b) cringe? Do you agree with the following statement: "Nowhere was a place more cold-blooded than a graduate English department"? Have you ever wanted to strangle your (a) faculty adviser, (b) graduate assistant or (c) college-age child? If you liked this little quiz, then have I got a book for you.</p>
        <p>LOVE COOLS (Putnam, $19.95), W. Edward Blain's second campus mystery, after "Passion Play," delivers a devious murder plot that catches the conscience, or lack of it, of the summer faculty at the Stone Mountain Theater in Virginia's Shenandoah Valley. Fierce professional rivalries break out among this cutthroat gang of teachers after an esteemed Shakespearean scholar dies in a fire. Although her last manuscript was presumably destroyed, two thematically different versions surface, giving rise to grave charges of fraud.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blain, who is chairman of the English department at Woodberry Forest School in Virginia, creates a wonderfully poisonous atmosphere in which his articulate characters wage their vendettas, along plot lines that cunningly parallel those of the two shows in rehearsal. Leaving the unethical grown-ups to play at the dirty tricks of "A Midsummer Night's Dream," the director's sensitive adolescent son wraps himself in young Hamlet's black mantle of revenge to get back at a sadistic teacher. For all the palpable hits he scores with his satirical thrusts at academe, Mr. Blain takes Hamlet's theme -- the alienation and betrayal of children by their parents -- very much to heart.</p>
        <p>The three friends named Phoebe, Anne and Diana who give themselves such enigmatic airs in Minette Walters's intriguing first mystery, THE ICE HOUSE (St. Martin's, $18.95), have lived in the manor house of Streech Grange since Phoebe's husband disappeared 10 years earlier. Young hoodlums torment them for being lesbians or even witches. Everyone in the village suspected them of having murdered Phoebe's husband. And now that a decayed, mutilated corpse has turned up in the old icehouse, people suspect them all over again.</p>
        <p>"God knows what it is, but there's something very attractive about us," says Anne, the cynical one. "Perhaps it's the uncertainty."</p>
        <p>Ms. Walters makes an art of uncertainty by twisting familiar conventions of the traditional British mystery (the tramp in the woods, the prowler in the dark, the secret in the safe) into a stylish, nontraditional mystery in which ambiguity abounds. Like the reader, Sgt. Andy McLoughlin doesn't know what to make of the three fascinating sphinxes at Streech Grange. Is their eccentric reclusiveness a show of guilt or defiance, or is it simple pigheaded loyalty to an old friendship?</p>
        <p>Or is Anne right when she says, "Life is pure farce from beginning to end, with a little black comedy thrown in for shade"? After much mulling, Sergeant McLoughlin decides to enjoy the farce, and the reader is advised to do likewise.</p>
        <p>If they gave an Academy Award for best videotape of an armed robbery, it would have to go to the stunt pulled off by Bobby Radcliff, the oddly endearing psychopath in Eric Sauter's BACKFIRE (Dutton, $19). A killer with keen cinematic instincts, Bobby follows a script for his liquor store robberies and uses lost, mixed-up children as expendable extras. The former film student also makes pornographic blackmail tapes for an unscrupulous Philadelphia lawyer involved in the shady re-election campaign of a state senator. After casually killing one of his young accomplices, Bobby defies the laws of probability by kidnapping a teen-age runaway who chances to be the senator's daughter. As further proof that it's a small world in Philadelphia, both cases fall to the same detective.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sauter's police procedures may be full of air, but he methodically fills in all the gory details of the extravagantly violent action. Equally attentive to the psyches of his characters, he examines both victims and victimizers for the generational patterns of abuse that can produce a monster like Bobby. "Everyone was raised wrong," a more subtle villain notes. "That's one of the nice things about growing up. You finally realize it." And if you don't, you make movies.</p>
        <p>Susan Kelly's solidly researched plots give her Liz Connors mysteries backbone and guarantee that her heroine, a crime reporter from Cambridge, Mass., is not your ordinary 5-foot-10-inch redheaded amateur sleuth. Once again, the plot's the thing in OUT OF THE DARKNESS (Villard, $18), which finds Liz doing the legwork for a best-selling author of true-crime books who has blown in from the Coast to write up a local serial killer case. Griffin Marcus is sure he knows who has been strangling women and dumping their bodies along the Merrimack River; but when Liz starts investigating his leads, she sees things he's overlooked. Pursuing her own ideas after Marcus brushes them aside (too cavalierly to make the story entirely convincing), Liz also analyzes the special terror that this kind of killer holds for women. "Smart, ambitious, hard-working women tend not to be passive and obedient," she observes. "And what's a serial killer doing but imposing the ultimate form of obedience and passivity on the women he kills?"</p>
        <p>She's smart, Liz is, and so is Ms. Kelly. Too smart to drag in too many red herrings or to overwork the romantic angle -- although series fans will note that Liz and her long-term lover are on the rocks. You just can't trust those smooth West Coast authors.</p>
        <p>It's said, in John Brady's KADDISH IN DUBLIN (St. Martin's, $18.95), that there are only about 2,000 Jews in all of Ireland. One of these is an Irish Supreme Court justice. Another was his son, whose body washes up on a beach in Killiney with three bullet holes in the head, execution-style. Matt Min ogue, an inspector with Dublin's Garda Murder Squad and the magnetic center of this superb series, shudders at the political implications when a group calling itself the League for Solidarity With the Palestinian People claims credit, or perhaps damnation, for the deed.</p>
        <p>"There are extremists everywhere, aren't there?" says Justice Fine, who senses a kindred soul in Minogue. "It's that simple." Simple but also disillusioning for both men, whose dedication to legal justice can't survive without their deeper belief in human tolerance. Shaken by another murder that confirms the existence of a new extremist group ("Catholic, nationalist, conservative"), Minogue despairs even more of his countrymen.</p>
        <p>Although he writes with realistic precision of Irish police procedures, Mr. Brady adopts a tone of battered lyricism for Minogue's keening thoughts about the spiritual corruption he sees around him. It's a sad sound, the lamentations of a decent man's conscience, but it's the music that keeps drawing us back to this haunting series.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
