<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debating The Merits Of Debate</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="560446"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICAL NOTES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGAL AID FOR THE POOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC WORKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, KIRK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEZER, PAULINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REGAN, EDWARD V (COMPTROLLER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Aid for the Poor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Works</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DE1F38F937A35753C1A964958260" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debating The Merits Of Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, KIRK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While Bush and Clinton negotiators were debating the issue of Presidential debates this week, an even odder scenario was playing out in New York between Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and State Comptroller Edward V. Regan. Neither man is up for re-election this year, but Mr. Regan wants to debate Mr. Cuomo anyway, and this week threw down the gauntlet.</p>
        <p>The ostensible topics would be an $800 million job-creation bond act that will be on the Nov. 3 ballot, along with what Mr. Regan, a Republican, has called New York's "shabby" borrowing practices under the administration of Mr. Cuomo, a Democrat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While Bush and Clinton negotiators were debating the issue of Presidential debates this week, an even odder scenario was playing out in New York between Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and State Comptroller Edward V. Regan. Neither man is up for re-election this year, but Mr. Regan wants to debate Mr. Cuomo anyway, and this week threw down the gauntlet.</p>
        <p>The ostensible topics would be an $800 million job-creation bond act that will be on the Nov. 3 ballot, along with what Mr. Regan, a Republican, has called New York's "shabby" borrowing practices under the administration of Mr. Cuomo, a Democrat.</p>
        <p>It isn't that Mr. Regan is against the bond act, which he has called a "laudable goal." The point of the debate, the Comptroller said, was to try to exact a public pledge from the Governor and the leaders in the Legislature that reforms in how New York borrows money would be seriously pursued next year along with the new bond money.</p>
        <p>Officials in Mr. Cuomo's office, however, immediately said they perceived a hidden agenda in the challenge -- clued in, they said, in part by the fact that Mr. Cuomo agrees with the comptroller about the need for the bond act and the need for debt reform, and in part by the fact that Mr. Regan is seen in his party as a potential gubernatorial candidate in 1994.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Mr. Cuomo, Anne W. Crowley, called the challenge simply a "publicity stunt," because she said, "there's really nothing for the Governor and the comptroller to debate."</p>
        <p>Mr. Regan, meanwhile, has vowed to press ahead with his plan, although so far he has not followed Bill Clinton's example and had his potential debate opponent taunted by costumed supporters.</p>
        <p>No "Chicken Mario" suits have been seen. On the Book Circuit</p>
        <p>Connecticut's Secretary of the State, Pauline R. Kezer, wants people to be excited about things like civic duty and voting. To that end she was seen at a recent charity event belting out the lyrics to "Take Me Out to the Polling Place," (to the tune of "Take Me Out to the Ball Game").</p>
        <p>But now Ms. Kezer, who is the only Republican holding statewide elected office in Connecticut, may well have met her match in trying to make Democracy fun.</p>
        <p>On Saturday Ms. Kezer sat for two hours at Westfarms Mall in Farmington, signing copies of one of the dullest books in print: The Connecticut State Register and Manual. At 873 fine-print pages -- listing, for instance, the name of every member of every local zoning board in the state -- the guide is very important to lawmakers, lobbyists and journalists, and roundly ignored by just about everybody else. The book has traditionally been sold through an obscure office in the Secretary of the State's headquarters and nowhere else.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, however, the General Assembly voted to push a wider distribution of the guide, through book stores, and Ms. Kezer gamely signed on to promote it. The book went on sale last month in eight book stores around the state for $10 for the soft-cover and $19 for the hard-cover version.</p>
        <p>"Not everybody needs or wants this," Ms. Kezer said after her book-signing. And most people are not even sure</p>
        <p>why</p>
        <p>they would want it. "A couple of people came in and knew exactly what it was," she said. Eight copies were sold. Political Ping-Pong</p>
        <p>When the brand new Republican Legislature cut New Jersey's budget by a billion dollars this year, one of the agencies that was hit hard was the innocuously named Department of the Public Advocate. The agency has sweeping powers to bring lawsuits "in the public interest" against parties, including the state, and had made more than a few Republican enemies over the years.</p>
        <p>Republicans had already been seeking the resignation of the Public Advocate, Wilfredo Caraballo, for among other things recommending that students be shuffled across district lines to achieve racial integration. When the budget cuts hit, Mr. Caraballo did resign, saying the Legislature had politicized the fiscal process.</p>
        <p>His office then announced what it said were the implications of the cuts: a reduction in the staff of public defenders, whose services for indigent criminal defendants are required by the United States Constitution. County budgets would have to pick up the slack, the advocate's office said.</p>
        <p>That promptly threw the matter into the courts, and this week the State Supreme Court threw it right back into the arena of politics.</p>
        <p>But with a threat: The court said in a terse statement that it would wait only 45 days before deciding how the public-defender system should be financed in New Jersey, unless the issue was "resolved by the other branches of government."  POLITICAL NOTES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
