<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WESTCHESTER GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="820854"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEFD61239F934A35752C0A960958260" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WESTCHESTER GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIFE BY THE FRAME</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIFE BY THE FRAME</p>
        <p>Mary Engel, daughter of the photographer Ruth Orkin and director of the Ruth  Orkin Photo Archives, will give a talk about her mother's work at the Ground Glass meeting tomorrow at 7:30 P.M. in the Rye Arts Center, 51 Milton Road. A short video narrated by Julie Harris and titled "Ruth Orkin: Frames of Life," will be shown, before its screening at the Sundance Film Festival in Utah.</p>
        <p>In addition to her achievements as a photographer, Ruth Orkin produced two movies with her husband, Morris Engel. One of them, "The Little Fugitive" won first prize at the Venice Film Festival in 1953.</p>
        <p>The Ground Glass Inc. is a group of Westchester photographers, photo-journalists, professors and amateur photographers who get together to discuss mutual interests and concerns, and who sponsor workshops, exhibitions, demonstrations and lectures like Ms. Engle's.</p>
        <p>The meeting is open to the public free of charge. For more information call 632-4211.</p>
        <p>DRILLS ON ICE</p>
        <p>Hockey fans have an opportunity to watch the New York Rangers in practice today if they get to the Playland Ice Casino in Rye as soon as possible. Doors open at 9 A.M. and practice begins at 11 A.M. Admission is $6 at the door, seating is limited and parking is free.</p>
        <p>Public skating resumes at 1:30 and continues to 5:30 P.M. Skating tickets are $4.75 for adults, $3.50 for children younger than 13. The casino is in Playland  Park off I-95, Exit 19. Call 921-0370 for more information.</p>
        <p>ANTI-CARTWRIGHTS</p>
        <p>"The Geldings," opening at the Schoolhouse Theater in Croton Falls on Thursday and continuing through Sunday, carries America's mythic West to its comic outer edge, streaking off on a tangent from the "Bonanza" television series.</p>
        <p>Three Gelding brothers and the requisite desperado, singing cowboy, luscious  widow, and a horse named Bucky play out a machismatic scenario against a background of the Gelding's falling-apart ranch and the local saloon.</p>
        <p>William Seebring, the play's author and a narrative cartoonist whose work has appeared in The Village Voice and National Lampoon, won the New American Comedy  Festival Award in 1988 in Ukiah, Calif., for "The Geldings." He is expected to direct a workshop production at the Harold Clurman Theater in Manhattan later this year.</p>
        <p>Curtain times are 8 P.M. on Thursday through Saturday, and 3 P.M. on Sunday.  Tickets are $12. Call 277-8477 for reservations or information.</p>
        <p>BRONZ ON KING</p>
        <p>Lois Bronz, the first black woman to be elected to the County Board of Legislators, will deliver a lecture titled "Martin Luther King's Impact on America" on Friday at 8:30 P.M. at the Community Synagogue in Rye.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bronz, a Democrat whose district covers parts of New Rochelle and White Plains, and the towns of Greenburgh and Scarsdale, was elected in November 1993  and took her seat on Jan. 1 of last year. She is listed in "Who's Who Among American Women" and in 1990 she was named Westchester County's Woman of the Year. She has been active in organizations promoting understanding among black,  Jewish and Italian Westchester residents.</p>
        <p>The synagogue is at 200 Forest Avenue in Rye, admission is free and people of all ethnic and religious backgrounds are welcome.</p>
        <p>BIT OF GOLD LEAF</p>
        <p>Karen Gorst has displayed her calligraphy and manuscript illuminations and held workshops at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Cloisters, in schools, galleries and professional societies, and at the New York Public Library at 42d  Street and Fifth Avenue. An exhibition of her work, titled "Divine Gifts" is on  display in the Madeleine Gutman Gallery of the Greenburgh Town Hall through Jan. 30.</p>
        <p>A co-founder of the Gabriel Guild, dedicated to keeping alive the medieval illumination arts through teaching and producing, Ms. Gorst hews to the use of traditional hand-ground paints, inks, and 22 karat gold leaf, but occasionally switches to contemporary materials. The exhibition has examples of both methods.</p>
        <p>Greenburgh Town Hall, at the Tarrytown Road and Hartsdale Avenue in Elmsford, is open Mondays through Fridays from 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission to the exhibition is free. For information, call 422-1038.</p>
        <p>QUILTS ON THE FARM</p>
        <p>A display of quilts dating from 1900 to the present -- handmade and machine made -- are on view at Muscoot Farm today from noon to 3 P.M. During that time Jamie Friedenberg, a folk artist, will demonstrate the preparation of fabric for quilting, and a so-called quick-quilting technique using a special cutter. Admission to the farm, off Exit 6 of I-684 in Somers, is free, and the phone number is 232-7118.</p>
        <p>ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
