<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chant, Taken Back to Its Roots</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="820729"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="RECORDINGS VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, SARAH BRYAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D71239F934A35752C0A960958260" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chant, Taken Back to Its Roots</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH BRYAN MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MILLER, SARAH BRYAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHANT SELLS. Whether in the traditional Gregorian forms intoned by cloistered monks or in the derivatives lately composed by the likes of Arvo Part and Henryk Gorecki, chant is hot, and knockoffs abound. Anglican chant is making a comeback in the Episcopal Church, and recent recordings have explored variants within the Roman Catholic tradition.</p>
        <p>It was only a matter of time before someone thought of marketing what may be  the most ancient form of chant still practiced, in the Jewish tradition. And now someone has, with "Chants Mystique: Hidden Treasures of a Living Tradition" (Polygram Special Markets 314 520 340-2; CD), a survey of Hebrew liturgical music from the distant past to the present, cleverly disguised as a vehicle for  New Age navel-gazing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHANT SELLS. Whether in the traditional Gregorian forms intoned by cloistered monks or in the derivatives lately composed by the likes of Arvo Part and Henryk Gorecki, chant is hot, and knockoffs abound. Anglican chant is making a comeback in the Episcopal Church, and recent recordings have explored variants within the Roman Catholic tradition.</p>
        <p>It was only a matter of time before someone thought of marketing what may be  the most ancient form of chant still practiced, in the Jewish tradition. And now someone has, with "Chants Mystique: Hidden Treasures of a Living Tradition" (Polygram Special Markets 314 520 340-2; CD), a survey of Hebrew liturgical music from the distant past to the present, cleverly disguised as a vehicle for  New Age navel-gazing.</p>
        <p>The current popularity of chant confounds many listeners, who find it irredeemably boring, compared to, say, Mahler. But the music seems to appeal to  two large and distinct constituencies, serving as high-class aural wallpaper for easy-listening purposes, and resonating with a search for meaning in a culture that has rejected much of its spirituality and now feels the loss. (Is it surprising that the mystical Minimalism of the Polish Mr. Gorecki and the Estonian Mr. Part originated in countries ruled for decades by a regime that espoused the doctrine of dialectical materialism?) Even the most earthbound baby-boomers must eventually long for something deeper than the Beach Boys and less pretentious than Simon and Garfunkel, and chant seems to provide one answer to such yearnings.</p>
        <p>Chanting began for the most practical of reasons. The singing voice carries better than the speaking voice, and you can sing without strain for a lot longer than you can shout. Black street vendors in Charleston, S.C., had known this for generations by the time George Gershwin came along to borrow their distinctive calls for "Porgy and Bess." Before acoustics became a science or electronics boosted the volume of the whispery-voiced, chant got the message out.</p>
        <p>Because its primary purpose was to put across a text, chant originally used simple lines that could barely be called melodies. With time, these became more  elaborate, but they remained sufficiently plain that many different texts could  be adapted to any specific setting.</p>
        <p>Oral traditions, like those of early chant, are prone to constant alteration, and little ancient Jewish chant has survived to the present. For many centuries, religious singing styles moved back and forth between church and synagogue or synagogue and mosque. And given a natural tendency toward musical assimilation,  Jewish worship tunes often came to sound like the music of the surrounding culture.</p>
        <p>"Chants Mystiques" chronicles those changes, offering Hebrew chants from a variety of times and places (Yemen, Spain, Vienna). Though it is saddled with tacky, pseudo-mystical cover art, and it sounds in places like the standard cantor-with-droning-choir compilations available in synagogue bookshops everywhere, it has enough unique and inspired moments to lift it well above the  ordinary.</p>
        <p>Particularly effective is the "circular chanting," in the opening selection and elsewhere: the choristers form a circle, and their entrances are staggered to achieve an unmanicured sound close to what might actually be heard during congregational chanting in a synagogue. At other times the choral sound is seamless, but the irregularity at the beginning sets the mood.</p>
        <p>"Mi Al Har Chorev," the oldest extant example of notated Jewish music, holds  the greatest musicological interest. Discovered in Cairo in the last century, the scrap was set down by one Obadiah, a Norman monk who converted to Judaism in the 12th century. The text is a panegyric to Moses, and the music sounds much like Catholic chant of the same time, except for the improvisational cadenzas, performed by the cantor in a wild Middle Eastern style.</p>
        <p>The production underlines the similarities among chant forms by presenting Psalm 114 ("When Israel went forth from Egypt") by moving between Latin and Hebrew on the same tune, one still heard in Anglican and Roman Catholic churches. The Sephardic tradition of Spain and the Mediterranean is represented in a haunting setting of "Sh'ma Yisroel" ("Hear, O Israel") from Turin, and the Islamic influences of northern Africa also appear. There is a lovely example of pure Renaissance polyphony in an exquisite setting of Psalm 146 ("Praise the Lord, O my soul!") by the Mantuan Salomone Rossi.</p>
        <p>A couple of typical examples from the 19th-century school of cantor-with-lush-choir are followed by a contemporary piece from Israel. And the finale, "Ki Lo No'e" ("For to Him praise is proper"), a Passover prayer set to an Eastern European folk tune, offers some rousing extemporizations by the cantor.</p>
        <p>Ricardo Rosenkranz is the producer. A Mexican-born, Chicago-based neonatologist, he conceived of the recording as a Jewish answer to the "chant" phenomenon and enlisted Matthew Lazar as conductor and Alberto Mizrahi as cantor. The Greek-born Mr. Mizrahi, who can be dreadfully annoying to ear and eye when working as an operatic tenor, is much more at home as a cantor, and he  displays a virtuosic command of various styles of Jewish liturgical music. The pickup choir, Chorale Mystique, sings splendidly under Mr. Lazar's direction.</p>
        <p>RECORDINGS VIEW Sarah Bryan Miller is a freelance writer andsinger in Chicago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Sarah Bryan Miller is a freelance writer andsinger in Chicago.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
