<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Choosing Berries for Eating or for Show</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="GARDENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAUST, JOAN LEE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DC113CF932A25753C1A964958260" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Choosing Berries for Eating or for Show</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FAUST, JOAN LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S berry time not only for the delicious ones that are eaten but also for the ornamental ones that are decorating many shrubs, vines and trees.</p>
        <p>The most obvious cultivated shrub that is a big showoff now is Pyracantha or firethorn. Its gorgeous orange berries can be seen for blocks. The plant is stiff and lends itself nicely to training along chimneys or fences. The summer flowers are not too significant and most gardeners grow the plant for the gorgeous orange berries, which are favorites with birds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S berry time not only for the delicious ones that are eaten but also for the ornamental ones that are decorating many shrubs, vines and trees.</p>
        <p>The most obvious cultivated shrub that is a big showoff now is Pyracantha or firethorn. Its gorgeous orange berries can be seen for blocks. The plant is stiff and lends itself nicely to training along chimneys or fences. The summer flowers are not too significant and most gardeners grow the plant for the gorgeous orange berries, which are favorites with birds.</p>
        <p>The cultivar Lalandei has been around since the turn of the century. It is the pyracantha most widely available, and with good reason. The berries are particularly showy and the plant is tough and can live through rugged winters. This cultivar is also popular because it is upright and can be readily trained to a trellis or wall. Pruning is best done in the spring, just after the first growth. Be careful when pruning: the common firethorn is realistic and sometimes those thorny branches can be wicked.</p>
        <p>Another shrub, called sapphireberry, is a large grower and when planted in full sun with space to grow it can be dramatic. The shrub is well named since the berries are an intense deep blue. The birds relish them as well and this shrub is often recommended for planting in large gardens where attracting birds is a goal. Botanically Symplocos paniculata, the shrub came to the United States from Japan and was introduced by Thomas Hogg, who was appointed by President Lincoln as a United States marshal. The Hogg nursery, which existed in New York City during the 19th century, was noted for its stock of Japanese plants.</p>
        <p>Of course, the dogwoods always put on a good show at this time of year. Curiously, the squirrels seem to wait until the dogwood berries are perfectly ripe, bright red, and then go to work. In a day's time they can strip a dogwood tree of its ornamental crown and leave nothing but the leaves. The birds are not innocent, either, and they do have a good time devouring dogwood berries. This sort of ruination is characteristic of the common native dogwood, Cornus florida. But squirrels and birds seem to leave alone the beautiful strawberry-like fruit of the Cornus kousa, which is becoming popular for the suburbs since the species shows some resistance to the dogwood's troubles.</p>
        <p>The hollies should also be at the top of the berry list. Although the traditional red-berry hollies are cut for the Christmas season, there are several hollies that are beginning to show berry color now and are more deserving of garden space.</p>
        <p>A particular favorite is the native winterberry, Ilex verticillata. The foliage will drop in a few more weeks to leave the colorful display of red berries in place, if the birds do not get to them first.</p>
        <p>Although it would appear that hollies are prickly and not appetizing to the deer population, it has been said that, when hungry, deer will even eat holly. One bright note, a list of deer-resistant plants appears in the back of the catalogue from the Twombly Nursery in Monroe. One of them is inkberry (Ilex glabra), another deciduous native holly. The berries are black and not as showy. This may be the holly to consider if the deer are devastating the landscape.</p>
        <p>Berry talk cannot omit a most spectacular native shrub, the American cranberrybush (Viburnum trilobum). It is a truly excellent shrub for several seasons. It has lovely white flowers in spring followed by the brilliant red fruits now. These can be traffic stoppers and, in many cases, cars do stop and their passengers eagerly gather the fruit, which is edible, for a delicious jam.</p>
        <p>Barberries are showing off at this time of year, too, and it is with some hesitation that this shrub is recommended. Birds do cherish the fruit and their feeding is one sure way of spreading this species about. The barberry fruit contain seeds and pass through the birds' digestive system and grow in the fertile ground wherever they are dropped.</p>
        <p>Japanese barberry does have the thorns as do almost all of the barberries, but botanists have tamed the wildness and created several cultivars with better habits. Even though the flowers are a golden yellow, the fruits do attain the brilliant red color. Two of the most popular cultivars are Crimson Pygmy, a Dutch selection, and Aurea with its showy yellow leaves but limited fruit appeal.</p>
        <p>Although the berry talk has been positive to this point, a warning should go out that there are two berry-bearing vines that do not belong in a garden. They are takeover plants with extremely aggressive tendencies. As beautiful as its fruit is, the porcelainberry vine (Ampelopsis brevipedunculata) is a nuisance. The berries are beautiful and can range from soft blue to sapphire blue to almost purple. When seen in the wild, admire the berries but never try to gather them for home. Just as handsome is pokeweed (Phytolacca americana) but it is poisonous. For cultivation, stick with the tried and true berry-bearing plants.  GARDENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
