<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Knuckleball Captures Prime Time</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562030"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PITTSBURGH PIRATES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ATLANTA BRAVES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL LEAGUE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WAKEFIELD, TIM</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Pittsburgh Pirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D8113BF932A25753C1A964958260" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Knuckleball Captures Prime Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU could envision it all over America yes terday little children, grown men, women who think their time has come. All of them out in backyards and playgrounds, digging their fingertips into the stitches of a baseball.</p>
        <p>In one glorious prime-time display, the knuckleball has become fashionable, the ticket to the major leagues, to fame and fortune. Boxers are throwing away their gloves. Musicians are hocking their guitars. Savings and loan officials and investment brokers and other scam artists left over from the 80's are putting their clients on hold while filing their fingernails. The knuckleball will be the get-rich scheme of the 90's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU could envision it all over America yes terday little children, grown men, women who think their time has come. All of them out in backyards and playgrounds, digging their fingertips into the stitches of a baseball.</p>
        <p>In one glorious prime-time display, the knuckleball has become fashionable, the ticket to the major leagues, to fame and fortune. Boxers are throwing away their gloves. Musicians are hocking their guitars. Savings and loan officials and investment brokers and other scam artists left over from the 80's are putting their clients on hold while filing their fingernails. The knuckleball will be the get-rich scheme of the 90's.</p>
        <p>"From what I hear, I've started a fad," Tim Wakefield said after stopping the Braves, 3-2, Friday night.</p>
        <p>Until the Braves stomped all over the home team, 6-4, last night, Wakefield was looming over the Braves like some giant inflatable monster balloon, leering and fluttering in the night air.</p>
        <p>The knuckleball has been the star of the series, but it may turn out to be a fascinating footnote to a quickie weekend that saw Deion Sanders razzed for striking out before his midnight run to Florida and Barry Bonds booed at home for his dismal three-year post-season slump.</p>
        <p>With the Pirates down, three games to one, Manager Jim Leyland could have shown some imagination and come back with the rookie tonight on only one full day off. After all, the knuckler does not put the usual stress on a pitcher's body, and Wakefield has said, "I've pitched with one day's rest before."</p>
        <p>After the loss, Leyland said, "I could use him if I had to, but it would be pushing it a bit to come back that quick."</p>
        <p>Earlier, somebody said Wilbur Wood used to pitch with one day off, and Leyland said, "Yeah, and look at his record," which was 164-156.</p>
        <p>Instead, Leyland will come back tonight with Bob Walk rather than Danny Jackson, who was hammered in the second game. The manager has been second-guessed for not starting Wakefield in that game, but Leyland did not want the knuckler dancing in the sunlight at 3 P.M. in Atlanta. Hard to hit but harder to catch. Plus, Wakefield is a rookie, albeit a poised, 26-year-old rookie.</p>
        <p>The Braves still may not have seen the last of him. One can only hope Leyland saw a vision in his sleep overnight.</p>
        <p>All of this intrigue because of a pitch that dips and soars and takes preposterous routes toward home plate. Up to now, Wakefield was only an interesting statistic to casual fans, eight victories and one loss after he was called up from the minors. But he did it in a relatively small publicity mill, with both newspapers shut down, in a summer when not many people had much stomach for baseball.</p>
        <p>Wakefield's story is intriguing because he learned the pitch fooling around with his father, and he only switched to pitching when he could not hit in the minors. He stands sideways to the batter, rocking backward slightly, cranking his elbow and flicking the ball plateward like some darts player.</p>
        <p>Anybody with an ounce of spunk could watch the tube Friday and think, "Hmmm, I could do that." Female athletes, emboldened by the presence of Manon Rheaume, the goalkeeper in the Tampa Bay hockey organization, could see themselves lobbing a knuckler past the Braves.</p>
        <p>Of course, it ain't that easy, as Wakefield points out: "But once you get on the hill, can you throw strikes? Can you field your position? Can you hold runners on base?"</p>
        <p>"Timmy came with the whole package because of Spin Williams, our minor league pitching coach," said Ray Miller, the Pittsburgh varsity pitching coach.</p>
        <p>"Timmy beat the odds because he was quick to the plate. He can also field his position. And minor league managers want to help themselves by winning a lot of games," Miller added, meaning that managers do not normally have much patience for experiments with freak pitches.</p>
        <p>"I know some scientist could write a paper that this is impossible," said Don Slaught, the bruised and battered catcher. "But sometimes the ball does a spiral. Some of them are just nasty. I'd never call one of them.</p>
        <p>"Some scientist could also tell you it is physically impossible for a ball to go 47 miles per hour for 60 feet, but it does," Slaught added.</p>
        <p>Actually, Wakefield's velocity never fell below 53, but whatever the speed, Slaught can never, ever, assume where the ball is going. That is his problem. It takes some skill to stop a knuckleball, much less catch it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
