<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tchaikovsky and 'Mambo Madness'</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHERMAN, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDC103CF932A25753C1A964958260" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tchaikovsky and 'Mambo Madness'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHERMAN, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are so many fine events planned for next weekend that making a decision as to which one to attend might not be easy.</p>
        <p>First, on Friday at 8 P.M., Feld Ballets/NY begins the "Dance!" series at the Performing Arts Center of the State University of New York at Purchase; the event will be held in Theater A. On Saturday, the center has scheduled two programs for 8 P.M. One is the American debut of Dance Collective, a much-acclaimed company from Winnipeg, Manitoba; this event will be in Theater C.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are so many fine events planned for next weekend that making a decision as to which one to attend might not be easy.</p>
        <p>First, on Friday at 8 P.M., Feld Ballets/NY begins the "Dance!" series at the Performing Arts Center of the State University of New York at Purchase; the event will be held in Theater A. On Saturday, the center has scheduled two programs for 8 P.M. One is the American debut of Dance Collective, a much-acclaimed company from Winnipeg, Manitoba; this event will be in Theater C.</p>
        <p>The other will be taking place across the lobby in Theater B, where the front seats are going to be removed so that members of the audience can dance, if they like, to the "Mambo Madness" of Mario Bauza and his Afro-Cuban Jazz Orchestra. Reservations for any of these performances may be obtained by calling the Performing Arts Center box office at 251-6200.</p>
        <p>Also at the center on Saturday at 8 P.M. will be a concert by the Westchester Symphony, which begins its 67th season with an all-Tchaikovsky program in Theater A. Two of the composer's most popular scores will be included: the "Romeo and Juliet" Overture and the Violin Concerto, with Aaron Rosand as the distinguished guest soloist. Another item on the program is the rarely encountered Symphony No. 1, subtitled "Winter Dreams." The orchestra's music director, Anthony Aibel, said this early work "contains one of the more brilliant finales and triumphant codas in any Tchaikovsky work." The number to call for single-ticket or subscription information is 835-8481.</p>
        <p>The first of four Saturday recitals scheduled for Caramoor's Music Room in Katonah will be held this Saturday at 8:30 P.M. The resident Cassatt String Quartet, which has temporarily become a trio because one member is ill, will play Dohnanyi's Serenade, Schubert's Trio in B flat, and the Mozart Divertimento in E flat (K. 471).</p>
        <p>Appearing at later Caramoor concerts are the cellist Daniel Gaisford (Oct. 24), the Saint Lawrence String Quartet (Oct. 31) and the pianist-composer Neely Bruce (Nov. 7). Further information can be obtained by calling the box office at 232-1252.</p>
        <p>The Friends of Music will present a recital by the New York Woodwind Quintet on Saturday at 8:30 P.M. at the Ossining High School Auditorium. On the program: Hindemith's "Kleine Kammermusik" No. 2, Mozart's Quintet in E flat (K. 452) and Poulenc's Sextet, the last two with the guest pianist Robert Levin. The number to call for more information is 271-4657 or 271- 4800.</p>
        <p>The husband-and-wife team of Mark Reynolds and Kathen Cowan will offer an assortment of old ballads, contemporary folk songs and instrumentals on guitar, harp, banjo, violin and hammered dulcimer as the headliners next Saturday at 8 P.M. at the Treestar Coffeehouse in Mount Kisco's Presbyterian Church. The number to call for information is (203) 438-6102.</p>
        <p>At the Tarrytown Music Hall, also next Saturday at 8 P.M., there will be plenty of folk fiddling. The multiple-Grammy winner Allison Krauss will perform with her bluegrass band Union Station; also on the agenda is Chanting House, a vocal-instrumental quartet headed by the all-Ireland Fiddle Champion, Eileen Ivers. The number to call for information is 332-8497.</p>
        <p>A benefit both for and at the New Rochelle Public Library is scheduled next Saturday at 8 P.M. The Queen City Singers and Dancers will offer a musical revue, "All That Jazz: A Salute to the Great Choreographers of Broadway." The show will be repeated next Sunday at 3 P.M. More information can be obtained by calling 632-7878.</p>
        <p>The concert pace does not slow down next Sunday either. The Rye Arts Center opens its Performing Arts Series with a 3 P.M. recital at Rye Country Day School by the American pianist Eugen Indjic, who was born in Belgrade and now lives in Paris. And at 4 P.M., Johannes Somary makes his debut as the new music director of the Taghkanic Chorale at Manhattanville College in Purchase. The program, highlighted by the Faure Requiem, is a benefit for the college's Music Scholarship Fund. The Rye Arts Center's number is 967-0700; the Manhattanville music department number is 694-2200, Extension 260.</p>
        <p>The Westchester Chamber Music Society will present an evening with the Emerson Quartet next Sunday at 8 o'clock at Congregation Emanu El of Rye. The quartet will play Schubert, Shostakovich, Bartok and Beethoven. The chamber society's number is 948-6533 or 967-7399.</p>
        <p>Two cabaret/jazz programs are scheduled next Sunday. Departing from its usual classical roster, Downtown Music at Grace is presenting the Broadway and pop singer Gail Nelson, with the pianist-arranger Danny Holgate and his trio at the Episcopal church in White Plains. The first part of the 4 P.M. program focuses on show music of Gershwin, Kern and Rodgers; after intermission comes music by Fats Waller, Duke Ellington, Chick Corea and Thad Jones. The number to call for information and ticket reservations is 949-0384.</p>
        <p>Jazz is also on the program at the Tarrytown Music Hall next Sunday at 8 P.M. when the Ed Polcer Quartet of Westchester warms up the crowd for the appearance of the singer-pianist Diane Schuur.</p>
        <p>Thom Wolke, head of the presenting group, Twin Cloud Concerts, said that Ms. Schur, who is blind, is known for "the uplifting spirit and vitality" of her performances. Like the Nelson-Holgate Duo, Ms. Schur will sample the repertory of earlier jazz with songs popularized by Ella Fitzgerald, Dinah Washington and Sarah Vaughan, among others. More information can be obtained by calling 332-8497.  MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
