<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Weary R.E.M. Seems Stuck in Midtempo</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562062"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="RECORDINGS VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">REM (BAND)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">POWERS, ANN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D9153AF932A25753C1A964958260" item-length="999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Weary R.E.M. Seems Stuck in Midtempo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POWERS, ANN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pop music fans often treat their favorite songs like piggy banks, turning words and melody upside down until the coin of meaning drops into their hands. They can get it all wrong, transforming a lyricist's scribbles into Proustian reflections. Michael Stipe, singer for R.E.M. and hero to a decade's worth of moody college kids, expresses his frustration over such misunderstandings on "Drive," the first single from the group's 10th album, "Automatic for the People" (Warner Brothers 4-44505; CD and cassette).</p>
        <p>The song echoes with the weariness of lamentation. Peter Buck's acoustic guitar weaves a gentle ring around accordion, strings and ponderous drums as Stipe grumbles a canticle of dismissive phrases. "Hey, kids, rock-and-roll, nobody tells you where to go," he sings, sure that if he were to disappear, the song would go on as before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pop music fans often treat their favorite songs like piggy banks, turning words and melody upside down until the coin of meaning drops into their hands. They can get it all wrong, transforming a lyricist's scribbles into Proustian reflections. Michael Stipe, singer for R.E.M. and hero to a decade's worth of moody college kids, expresses his frustration over such misunderstandings on "Drive," the first single from the group's 10th album, "Automatic for the People" (Warner Brothers 4-44505; CD and cassette).</p>
        <p>The song echoes with the weariness of lamentation. Peter Buck's acoustic guitar weaves a gentle ring around accordion, strings and ponderous drums as Stipe grumbles a canticle of dismissive phrases. "Hey, kids, rock-and-roll, nobody tells you where to go," he sings, sure that if he were to disappear, the song would go on as before.</p>
        <p>It's a grim start for the follow-up to R.E.M.'s artistic and popular breakthrough, which came with the video and single "Losing My Religion" from last year's "Out of Time." But it's perfectly in step with the band's current elegiac mood. A sense of exhaustion permeates this album of acoustic meditations. A muted string section (arranged by the former Led Zeppelin bassist John Paul Jones) and occasional oboe or accordion provide subtle elaborations on the band's stripped-down ensemble work. Of 12 songs, only 3 go beyond midtempo. Stipe's lyrics, elliptical as always, evoke disconnection, failure and loss.</p>
        <p>Only "Man on the Moon" shines with a wit that balances R.E.M.'s somber tendencies -- and that song pays ironic homage to the late comic Andy Kaufman, known for his odd obsessions and confusing performances.  Mentioning Kaufman in the same breath as Moses and Sir Isaac Newton, Stipe makes a game of human endeavor, insisting that it all ends in dust. "Let's play Twister, let's play Risk," Stipe jokes to the notables he's invoked. "I'll see you in heaven if you make the list." Buck's slippery guitar lines render Stipe's skepticism whimsical, but bitterness stirs beneath the song's surface.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, "Automatic for the People" confronts mortality in a more solemn mode. Knox Chandler's cello bears the rhythm of "Sweetness Follows" like a dark angel, as Stipe explores the need for rituals of grief. As the music dims, Stipe recalls a community torn apart by persistent misfortune. "It's these little things, they can pull you under," he murmurs. This painful story turns specific in "Monty Got a Raw Deal," which addresses an unspecified friend (perhaps Montgomery Clift, a patron saint for sensitive boys of another era) whom Stipe's words cannot save from violence. "You don't want this sympathy," Stipe sighs as Buck's mandolin rings over a quickening drumbeat. The beauty of the song struggles against the singer's sense of its pointlessness.</p>
        <p>The sentiment is gray, but not entirely surprising. Stipe has, after all, always been wary of the role of pop sage. From the band's early years as the flagship of alternative rock to its current eminence as a hit group that has maintained its integrity, R.E.M. has kept its image unpretentious and its ambitions obscure.</p>
        <p>In 10 albums, Stipe's dense lyrics melded with the radiant musicianship of Buck, the drummer Bill Berry and the bassist Mike Mills, recasting the American pastoral in a post-punk mode. Buck, a record collector, brought a slew of influences to the band, which soon came to represent alternative rock at its most lyrical. The band members' continued allegiance to the college town of Athens, Ga., further enhanced their image as pop Romantics.</p>
        <p>As the group's music grew into a more radio-friendly sound and Stipe replaced his famous mumble with clearly enunciated phrases, a larger audience found significance in R.E.M.'s ambiguities. Stipe became an unglamorous icon, shunning the excesses of the arena-rock crowd in favor of the direct-action politics of organizations like Greenpeace and Act Up. Many consider him to be a highly successful celebrity activist. "Automatic" reveals Stipe's own disillusionment with this role, as he leads R.E.M. back toward the shelter of musical obscurity.</p>
        <p>The litanies collected here bear dreams of retreat -- from the political arena in "Ignoreland," fame in "The Sidewinder Sleeps Tonight" and life itself in the unfinished suicide note "Try Not to Breathe." Stipe never clearly names the forces that drive him toward despair, but the album's tone of bereavement suggests that the AIDS crisis is at its heart. As friends and lovers lose their lives to a creeping illness that will not be coerced into making sense, and as a new generation of fans comes of age with their sexuality already under siege, pop artists like Stipe and R.E.M. intimately realize the limits to which art can change the world.  Even the ability to communicate seems limited; words and music can only suggest, and never encompass, such sorrow. After all, even Orpheus finally failed to raise the dead Eurydice with his song. And pop music fans can't even seem to get the lyrics right.</p>
        <p>Even in the midst of such disenchantment, R.E.M. can't resist its own talent for creating beautiful and moving sounds. "Automatic" never comes close to the epiphany of "Losing My Religion," but Buck, Mills and Berry can still conjure melodies that fall like summer sunlight. And Stipe still possesses a gorgeous voice that cannot shake its own gift for meaning. His self-doubt and evasiveness never completely squelch its evocative power.</p>
        <p>Once on "Automatic," in the song "Everybody Hurts," he allows that strength to overcome his caution. Simple words run over a sing-along melody as Stipe assures a friend that he can survive his anguish. In such a sad world, the song concludes, mourning is precisely what we share. "If you think you've had too much of this life, hang on," Stipe whispers as Buck's arpeggios carry him toward a rousing finale. The song is "Automatic"s spark of hope, a nod to tomorrow on an album heavy with doubts about today.</p>
        <p>RECORDINGS VIEW Ann Powers writes about pop music for SF Weekly, The Village Voice and L.A. Weekly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ann Powers writes about pop music for SF Weekly, The Village Voice and L.A. Weekly.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
