<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Venice Journal; Dying Art: Building a Crooked Boat to Go Straight</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="459986"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOATS AND BOATING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VENICE (ITALY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Venice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED6173DF936A25754C0A967958260" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Venice Journal; Dying Art: Building a Crooked Boat to Go Straight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>VENICE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The men of the Tramontin family seem ideally qualified to perpetuate the history of Venice as they work in their dark, messy boatyard, making wooden vessels as elegant as a swan, nimble as a reed and finely carved as a violin.</p>
        <p>Nevis and Roberto Tramontin are gondola builders, and by verdict of Venetian nautical historians, they are the best and among the last of a vanishing breed. Jeopardizing their ancient skill are the haste of modern man, the motorboats, the labor laws and a shortage of youngsters willing to spend 10 years learning how to make one of the world's most complex boats -- a craft that is built crooked so it will glide straight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The men of the Tramontin family seem ideally qualified to perpetuate the history of Venice as they work in their dark, messy boatyard, making wooden vessels as elegant as a swan, nimble as a reed and finely carved as a violin.</p>
        <p>Nevis and Roberto Tramontin are gondola builders, and by verdict of Venetian nautical historians, they are the best and among the last of a vanishing breed. Jeopardizing their ancient skill are the haste of modern man, the motorboats, the labor laws and a shortage of youngsters willing to spend 10 years learning how to make one of the world's most complex boats -- a craft that is built crooked so it will glide straight.</p>
        <p>At the Tramontin yard, father and son were still at work on a recent evening as a storm darkened the Grand Canal, both men laughing and shouting in Venetian dialect.</p>
        <p>"The best age for a gondola is seven years," proclaimed Nevis Tramontin, looking well below his 70 years. "Then she is like a woman of 35, polished, well-curved and settled into herself."  A Variety of Woods</p>
        <p>His son, Roberto, was running his hand over a kind of gondola embryo, its ribs still showing, its prow and stern naked without their metal finishings. Scattered around the yard were more pieces of the giant puzzle: staves of cherry wood waiting to stiffen the hull, mahogany planks ready to become the deck and sheets of oak curved to form a perfect starboard.</p>
        <p>The Tramontins use no sketches, diagrams or prefabricated parts to build one of the oldest surviving forms of transport. They keep the knowledge of how to season, cut, fit and assemble a gondola's 280 pieces in their heads and hands.</p>
        <p>"Only in the last five years I started to understand the work," Roberto, who has spent 22 of his 37 years in the yard. "Each tree is different. Each gondola is different. It's made like a balance to fit the gondolier. If he is heavy, you make the stern higher. If he is light, you compensate at the bow."</p>
        <p>Nevis Tramontin, paintbrush in hand, was finishing another slender craft that would soon join the Venetian fleet, these days numbering about 400 gondolas. No, he said, the Tramontins did not mind applying their skills to a vessel now virtually reduced to ferrying tourists. The family had a reputation to keep up, one that includes his grandfather, Domenica, who began working in this same boatyard in 1884.</p>
        <p>For the Tramontins, as for many other Venetians, the gondola is still a time machine.</p>
        <p>Once, more than 10,000 of the flat-bottom crafts plied the canals of Venice, and for more than 10 centuries they were crucial to the city's life.</p>
        <p>Like limousines today, companies sent them around town, and thousands of private gondoliers would take the men to work, the women on their outings and the staff to shop. Even Venetians of modest means would traveled to baptisms, weddings and funerals in a gondola. And everyone loved to gossip about the goings-on behind the velvet and brocade curtains of the little gondola cabins, reputed to be a favorite spot for secret love affairs.</p>
        <p>Today's gondolas, though stripped of privacy, still have some imprints of the Venetians' love for splendor -- the velvet cushions, the bas-reliefs, their lacquered shine. They are still black, though, because a decree four centuries ago banned the use of gold-leaf paint to discourage showiness.</p>
        <p>But the classic boat is now threatened, says the Society for the Preservation of the Gondola. Although everyone has scoffed at the suggestion of making plastic gondolas, there has been talk of making far simpler, cheaper boats. It now takes two people about 40 days to build one at a cost of some $20,000, without trims and furnishings.</p>
        <p>Gondoliers blame the motorlaunches now serving as buses and taxis for the decline of their trade. The noisy launches have not only replaced the silent but slow gondolas, but they also make waves that rudely bounce the delicate vessels against mooring poles and canal walls. The increased water motion degrades the wood, and is reducing the life of a gondola from 30 to 15 years.  Labor Laws Blamed</p>
        <p>For several years now, the Preservation Society and town hall officials have lobbied for a training school for craftsmen before the old art disappears, but it has not opened for lack of funds. The dozens of boatyards of old have dwindled to three, which build a total of about 10 gondolas a year, not enough to maintain the current Venetian fleet. The Tramontins are booked till the year 2010, and exports have virtually stopped. An order from Japan for 50 gondolas to be delivered in one year was turned down.</p>
        <p>Roberto Tramontin blames the labor laws and the unions for the fact that he cannot afford to train an apprentice because of high wages and social benefits. "The unions are the troublemakers," he says. "They expect me to pay a lot to someone who cannot produce and takes my time while I train him. I refuse. When I went to school, I had to pay."</p>
        <p>Over the years, Mr. Tramontin has learned to build almost every part of the 36-foot boat. He meticulously cures the eight kinds of wood he needs, planes it, drenches some pieces and curves them over the heat of burning reeds. The parts he does not make are the extras like the oar and the oarlock.</p>
        <p>The main secret of the Tramontin gondola, though, is that it is built to be asymmetrical to make up for the pull of the gondolier, who rows only on one side. Mr. Tramontin explains that the flat bottom is skewed 13 degrees to the right and that the left side of the hull is more deeply curved, lower and wider. The intricate design has baffled visiting naval engineers.</p>
        <p>"The great thing is, I can make any gondola you want, longer, wider or higher," Mr. Tramontin sai. "But I won't change the color. I say like Henry Ford, you can have any car you like, as long as it's black."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
