<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Games Go Hollywood, Do the Players Lose?</title>
    <meta content="30HOLLY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/30/technology/30HOLLY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1251302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marriott, Michel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D6153DF933A05752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Games Go Hollywood, Do the Players Lose?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHEL MARRIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marriott, Michel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many new computer and video games are displying increasingly movielike design, tone and texture, taking advantage of more muscular game hardware like high-performance microprocessors and greatly improved graphics capabilities; some game players are complaining that cinematic moments can seriously stall game play, making games more fun to watch than play; developers find production costs and times are rising; some star designers are demanding star-status salaries; photos (M)o</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE stone and steel towers of Manhattan loom large across the screen, appearing at once contemporary yet oddly quaint. Then suddenly, out of the morning mist, exotic fighter planes roar into view. They swoop and fire wing-mounted cannons in aerial dogfights set to a full orchestral score that quickens the pulse and accents the action.</p>
        <p>Heard over the din of combat are the voices of actors portraying flying aces and villains taunting their foes or screaming their last words as cockpits fill with smoke and their bullet-riddled aircraft spiral to earth. And every scene is shown from more camera angles and with more tracking shots and close-ups than most established filmmakers would dare to use even with Titanic budgets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE stone and steel towers of Manhattan loom large across the screen, appearing at once contemporary yet oddly quaint. Then suddenly, out of the morning mist, exotic fighter planes roar into view. They swoop and fire wing-mounted cannons in aerial dogfights set to a full orchestral score that quickens the pulse and accents the action.</p>
        <p>Heard over the din of combat are the voices of actors portraying flying aces and villains taunting their foes or screaming their last words as cockpits fill with smoke and their bullet-riddled aircraft spiral to earth. And every scene is shown from more camera angles and with more tracking shots and close-ups than most established filmmakers would dare to use even with Titanic budgets.</p>
        <p>The scenes might go well with hot, buttered popcorn, but they are not taken from the latest action-adventure film starring flesh-and-blood actors like Arnold Schwarzenegger. These rapid-fire sequences belong to Crimson Skies, a new computer game by Microsoft.</p>
        <p>Crimson Skies is one of a number of new computer games intended for personal computers and game consoles like Sega's Dreamcast and Sony's new PlayStation 2 that are recasting what is possible for a game. Instead of stilted backgrounds, limited mobility and cartoonish characters that typified many computer games on the market just a couple of years ago, a whole new class of games is displaying increasingly movielike design, tone and texture. They are taking advantage of more muscular game hardware like high-performance microprocessors and greatly improved graphics capabilities.</p>
        <p>None of this, however, guarantees a good game. Too many extraordinarily cinematic moments can seriously stall game play and make the overall experience of playing them more passive than interactive. Some of these powerfully cinematic games are raising a question about video games in general: should they be more fun to watch than to play?</p>
        <p>Not necessarily, said Eric Scheirer, a media and entertainment analyst for the Forrester Research consulting group. As the video game industry tries to become a more mass-market business, Mr. Scheirer said, it makes sense that games adopt more Hollywood production values to appeal to broad tastes. But, he cautioned, there is a danger. ''The artistic value is in the interactive experience itself,'' Mr. Scheirer said, ''not so much in the production values.''</p>
        <p>Some game players are already complaining that too many new games have excessive visual elements -- filmlike introductions and short movies spread through the game -- that slow down play.</p>
        <p>''Every time you go into the game, a movie starts,'' said a 15-year-old video game player who identified himself only as Aaron. ''And it shows again and again. I don't want to see it a second time.''  Some game players, like Aaron and his friends, simply press their computer's Escape key to skip the ''movie'' and just play the game.</p>
        <p>And for the game developers, the making of video games is becoming more like the making of movies, with some of the same problems. Production costs are rising and production schedules are getting longer. The newly released Star Trek: Deep Space Nine computer game, titled The Fallen, took developers 22 months to complete for Simon &amp; Schuster Interactive, longer than it took Paramount Studios to complete some ''Star Trek'' movies for theatrical release.</p>
        <p>There are even a few star game designers who, based on their reputations for creating best-selling games, can demand star-status salaries to develop new games.</p>
        <p>And as with movies, said Robert Kotick, co-chairman and chief executive of Activision Inc., one of the world's largest computer and video game developers, the game industry is more likely now to bet on potential blockbusters than on the small, more cheaply produced games.</p>
        <p>''Instead of doing five titles for $800,000 each, people are focused more on doing one title for $4 million,'' Mr. Kotick said.</p>
        <p>An A-level computer game, industry experts say, can easily cost as much as $10 million to $15 million and take 18 months to 2 years to finish. Of course the potential for great profit is there. In the United States, video game revenue approached movie-business levels last year, bringing in $7.4 billion compared with $7.5 billion in box office sales, according to the National Association of Theater Owners and PC Data, a company that tracks electronics sales.</p>
        <p>''Parallels between the movie market and the game market are so amazing that they have almost become one and the same,'' said Chris Mike, vice president for marketing at Konami of America, a major video and computer game maker in Redwood City, Calif.</p>
        <p>Already, game developers and executives routinely talk about trying to create a prerelease buzz for their games and then nervously anticipating the first round of reviews, just like Hollywood studio executives.</p>
        <p>Like movies, Mr. Mike added, ''games are a hit-driven business.''</p>
        <p>One of the new games is Kassen, a military conquest game by EA and Koei designed for PlayStation 2, with its improved processing might. It plunges players into 17th-century Japan and seemingly endless battlefields. Perfect rows of Samurai archers reach for their bows as horses snort and colorful banners snap in the wind moments before a cavalry charges in a clash of vast armies fighting for glory and territory.</p>
        <p>In Halo, a futuristic Earth-versus-Them shooter and strategy game scheduled for release early next year by Bungie, the computer-generated preview that sets up the game lasts for nine minutes.</p>
        <p>Leaked snippets of the cinematic elements of the yet-to-be-released PlayStation 2 game Metal Gear Solid 2: The Sons of Liberty, by Konami,  have been showing up on Web sites. In Japan, a DVD of the game's computer-generated action scenes is being sold on the street. Bootleg copies have made their way to the United States.</p>
        <p>''Our whole goal is to give the player the kind of role of being Errol Flynn in a 1930's, 1940's great pirate adventure film of the air,'' said Jordan Weisman, the creative director of Crimson Skies, which was released this fall. Players take the role of Nathan Zachary, a dashing ace, and the action is built around no only shooting down opponents, but also accomplishing missions that give the game a sort of dramatic arch.</p>
        <p>Crimson Skies is spawning an official line of novels, aircraft manuals, maps and other accessories made in the Art Deco style of the late 1920's and 1930's, just as a hit film might.  The game even opens with a grainy, black-and-white newsreel a la ''Citizen Kane,'' to establish an air of an authentic time and place that permeates the game.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scheirer, of Forrester Research, said that the spate of posters, action figures and other products tied to movielike video games is further proof that the games are becoming more realistic, so much so that they are becoming ''emotionally resonant'' with players.</p>
        <p>But the new creative freedom comes with its own liabilities, said Doug Hare, production project director of The Fallen. Scripts must be written as they are for a film, except they must be much longer because games are not linear, meaning that they have no clear middle or end. Game producers often point out that a movie might last two hours, while a game is often crammed with enough material to last for as long as 60 hours to 80 hours.</p>
        <p>Games are becoming more like movies in another way. Mr. Weisman, who invented the Crimson Skies universe, said game makers feel pressure to begin recovering a game's production costs as soon as it is released. Game industry executives don't have opening box office receipts to study, but they do have weekly sales reports from major chain stores.</p>
        <p>Then there are the sequels. Final Fantasy, by Squaresoft, has just been released in its ninth incarnation, and Microsoft's MechWarrior 4 and D.O.A. 2: Hardcore, by Tecmo, recently reached stores. Mr. Hare is already promising a sequel to The Fallen.</p>
        <p>''As our budgets grow there is similar pressure, like in Hollywood, to be able to follow on a success,'' Mr. Weisman said.</p>
        <p>''Studios need to have the right balance to continue with franchises -- there are fans that love them and demand more and they are a good financial bet -- and be willing to risk capital on a brand-new, clean slate and start a new franchise like Microsoft was willing to do with Crimson Skies.''</p>
        <p>The actor Mark Hamill, who has been working to complete The Black Pearl, a computer-game version of a script he originally wrote for a film, lamented that the computer-game world had become so wedded to movie action.</p>
        <p>''The trouble with my game is that it is more of a thinking man's game,'' he said. ''It has less action and rewards nonconfrontation, which I think is an important element in this time.</p>
        <p>''My biggest problem is that with the type of gaming consoles and technology that can handle so much action, where you have so much memory available to you, sometimes you're not looking at the product as a whole.</p>
        <p>''You wonder why in the game you are being chased by 38 helicopters. Is it because it is possible?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
