<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reporter's Murder Leads to Wide Speculation</title>
    <meta content="09russiansumm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/09/world/europe/09russiansumm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1796086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EED81330F93AA35753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reporter's Murder Leads to Wide Speculation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reporter’s Murder Leads to Wide Speculation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL SCHWIRTZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A summary of the top stories in Russian newspapers on Monday.</p>
        <p>TODAY'S TOP STORY</p>
        <p>JOURNALIST, GOVERNMENT CRITIC MURDERED: The murder of Anna Politkovskaya, possibly the strongest journalistic voice in opposition to the government of President Vladimir V. Putin and Russia's war in Chechnya led all the major newspapers today. Ms. Politkovskaya, a contributor to the independent Novaya Gazeta newspaper, was shot three or four times in the stairwell of her apartment in Moscow on Saturday afternoon. Novaya Gazeta's front page today displayed a simple photograph of Ms. Politkovskaya framed in thick black borders with Anya, the diminutive of her name, printed in block letters above.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A summary of the top stories in Russian newspapers on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A summary of the top stories in Russian newspapers on Monday.</p>
        <p>TODAY'S TOP STORY</p>
        <p>JOURNALIST, GOVERNMENT CRITIC MURDERED: The murder of Anna Politkovskaya, possibly the strongest journalistic voice in opposition to the government of President Vladimir V. Putin and Russia's war in Chechnya led all the major newspapers today. Ms. Politkovskaya, a contributor to the independent Novaya Gazeta newspaper, was shot three or four times in the stairwell of her apartment in Moscow on Saturday afternoon. Novaya Gazeta's front page today displayed a simple photograph of Ms. Politkovskaya framed in thick black borders with Anya, the diminutive of her name, printed in block letters above.</p>
        <p>It is most likely that Ms. Politkovskaya's journalistic endeavors led to her murder, today's papers wrote. Novaya Gazeta devoted three full pages to excerpts from some of her most controversial pieces of 2006. Most are critical of the Russian military's continued operations in Chechnya and of the leadership of the Chechen prime minister, Ramzan A. Kadyrov. In her last public appearance on Oct. 5, Kommersant reported, she told Radio Liberty that her wish was to see Mr. Kadyrov on the defendant's bench in court. If investigators did link the murder to the current leadership in Chechnya, Kommersant wrote, the region's government officials and military officers could lose their positions. Chechnya's president, Alu Alkhanov, along with Mr. Kadyrov strongly condemned the murder, Kommersant reported.</p>
        <p>One of Ms. Politkovskaya's colleagues at Novaya Gazeta told Kommersant that anyone could have been behind the murder: members of Russia's intelligence services, Chechens associated with Mr. Kadyrov, the police, or pseudo-patriots and fascists.</p>
        <p>A few newspapers provided speculations, seemingly without basis in fact. Izvestia suggested that one of Russia's high-profile exiles, like Boris A. Berezovsky, could have arranged Ms. Politkovskaya's murder as a way to destabilize Russia. Komsomolskaya Pravda wrote that the liberal opposition in Russia -- which, incidentally, Ms. Politkovskaya vocally supported -- could have carried out the murder as a way to undermine the Kremlin and spark public protests.</p>
        <p>Government officials have been largely silent on the case. Rossiiskaya Gazeta, Russia's government-run newspaper, wrote that the prosecutor general had taken personal control of the investigation, but said little else beyond a straightforward recounting of the details. Novaya Gazeta said that it will conduct its own investigation, wrote Nezavisimaya Gazeta. Its editor in chief said that his newspaper will have greater access to useful information than law enforcement agencies. The newspaper wrote that Ms. Politkovskaya had no connections to ''political intrigues'' or ''financial interests.'' It said that either Mr. Kadyrov or someone hoping to replace him was probably behind the murder.</p>
        <p>Gazeta wrote that the murder had already resonated strongly in Russian society. Novye Izvestia said that, despite the lack of information from Russia's main news agencies, the murder has startled the country. The newspaper wrote that Ms. Politkovskaya was one of the last hopes for the thousands of victims of state tyranny, terror and illegality in Russia. Novaya Gazeta wrote on its front page, under Ms. Politkovskaya's photograph, that ''as long as there is a Novaya Gazeta, her killers will not sleep soundly.''</p>
        <p>IN OTHER NEWS</p>
        <p>KOMMERSANT  RUSSIA, GEORGIA IN CITIZEN EXCHANGE: Russia and Georgia continued to exchange evacuated and deported citizens today. The Russian emergency situations ministry sent two planes with Georgian deportees to Tbilisi today, adding to the 140 deported from Russia on Friday. Those same planes were expected to pick up about 245 Russian citizens for ''evacuation'' to Moscow. Meanwhile, Russian riot police conducted ''mass document checks'' around the Georgia embassy in Moscow on Saturday, detaining several Georgians. Georgia's government called the detentions a ''provocation'' and a ''xenophobic step.''</p>
        <p>VEDOMOSTI  FOREIGNERS PAID MORE THAN RUSSIANS: Russian businesses, reacting to a decrease in the number of Russian workers, are hiring greater numbers of foreigners. According to the Central Bank, in the first half of 2006, foreigners in Russia earned about $3.2 billion in wages compared with $789 million paid to Russian citizens. The Central Bank attributed this wage gap mostly to workers from the former soviet states, while wages paid to specialists from other countries have been slowly declining.</p>
        <p>VREMYA NOVOSTEI  PRESIDENT PRESSES FOR STRONGER MIGRATION LAW: In a closed-door meeting with members from the Federation Council, Russia's upper house of Parliament, President Putin pressed senators on the need to develop a comprehensive migration plan. He also reminded them of a plan to attract Russian citizens living abroad back to the motherland. According to senators, Mr. Putin said that Russia's migration law should conform to international standards and strictly control the flow of migrants in order to enable a civilized labor market.</p>
        <p>NEZAVISIMAYA GAZETA  ELECTIONS IMPORTANT, BUT RESULTS STILL UNKNOWN: Municipal elections were held in nine Russian regions on Sunday, amid accusations of fraud and irregularities. A representative from a Russian nongovernmental organization focused on elections said that the campaign leading up to Sunday's elections was devoid of any platform articulation. While the newspaper did not publish the results, experts said that the elections will play a significant role in the alignment of forces for federal elections in 2007.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
