<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In South, Prayer Is a Form of Protest</title>
    <meta content="Y08ALA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="971321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prayers and Prayer Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alabama</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DeMent, Ira (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prayers and Prayer Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E0D71439F93BA35752C1A961958260" item-length="1226" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In South, Prayer Is a Form of Protest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>BOAZ, Ala., Nov. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Judge Ira DeMent's order barring student-led voluntary prayer in Alabama public schools is spurring protests by students and politicians; prayer remains common in many north Alabama hill country schools, despite decades of Federal court rulings against practice; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The students are demonstrating here.</p>
        <p>They walked out of Boaz High School by the hundreds at the beginning of class on Tuesday to form a ring of prayer on the tennis courts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The students are demonstrating here.</p>
        <p>They walked out of Boaz High School by the hundreds at the beginning of class on Tuesday to form a ring of prayer on the tennis courts.</p>
        <p>The next day, 59 students at Alabama Avenue Middle School in nearby Albertville left their classes and marched to City Hall. They prayed there too.</p>
        <p>After the football game between Boaz and Crossville on Thursday night, students from both schools met at midfield to pray. There have been similar displays at Sardis High, Glencoe High and other schools across the north Alabama hill country known as Sand Mountain.</p>
        <p>The turmoil is not limited to the schools. Ever since Oct. 30, when a Federal judge issued an injunction against a 1993 state law allowing student-led, nonproselytizing, voluntary prayer in the public schools, politicians around the state have railed against the decision. Gov. Fob James Jr., a Republican, has harshly criticized the judge and says he will do all he can to restore prayer to the schools. The State Attorney General, Bill Pryor, also a Republican, plans to appeal the ruling.</p>
        <p>Judge Roy S. Moore of Etowah County Circuit Court in nearby Gadsden has become something of a celebrity for fighting, both in court and in the news, to keep a tablet of the Ten Commandments hanging behind his bench. He issued an order from his court this week that said the injunction on the prayer law by the Federal District Court Judge, Ira DeMent of Montgomery, was not the law of Etowah County, and was an ''unconstitutional abuse of power'' by the Federal judiciary.</p>
        <p>Governor James, for his part, issued a statement on Tuesday pledging to ''resist Judge DeMent's order by every legal and political means, with every ounce of strength I possess.'' He declined in a news conference to disclose how he might resist the order, but Alabamians are mindful that the Governor threatened earlier this year to call out the National Guard to protect Judge Moore's Ten Commandments tablet. Told at the news conference about the student prayer walkouts, Mr. James responded, ''I don't blame them at all.''</p>
        <p>Mr. James's opponents accuse him of provoking disobedience, and they maintain that he is once again evoking the imagery of previous confrontations between the state of Alabama and the Federal courts. The only difference, they say, is that the subject now is religion, not race.</p>
        <p>''For the Governor of a state to do this is exactly like George Wallace standing in the schoolhouse door,'' said Pamela L. Sumners, the lawyer for the plaintiffs who are seeking to invalidate the 1993 school prayer law.</p>
        <p>With the help of Governor James and Judge Moore, the Sand Mountain region of Alabama has become the nexus of the latest crusade for the reparation of church and state. But it is by no means the only battleground in the South these days.</p>
        <p>In Decatur, Ga., last month, school officials allowed the pastor of New Missionary Baptist Church to conduct a service at Southwest DeKalb High School during school hours after a student had been stabbed to death. The county's public safety commissioner, Tom Brown, a member of the church, told the students, ''We are here in defiance of the Supreme Court, calling the name of Jesus Christ.'' And in Greenville, S.C., this week, a group of evangelicals announced that it was giving up on public education altogether and was beginning a campaign to urge Christian parents to pull their children out of public schools.</p>
        <p>In this part of Alabama, prayer has remained as common as pop quizzes in many schools, despite decades of Federal court rulings against the practice. Until Judge DeMent issued his injunction, sectarian prayers were commonly recited over public address systems at the beginning of the day, and at athletic events, assemblies and commencement ceremonies, said a number of school administrators and students.</p>
        <p>''Everyone around here is God-believing,'' said Jermaine Davis, an 18-year-old senior at Boaz High. ''Everyone around here believes in Christ, as far as I know. Having Jesus in our school is something that we need. It gives us strength.''</p>
        <p>At Boaz, where a prayer was recited over the public address system before Thursday night's game, nearly 500 of the school's 636 students protested Judge DeMent's ruling by walking out of class on Tuesday for the prayer vigil on the tennis courts.  One student told the crowd, ''We can't let this judge keep us from praying,'' the assistant principal,  Tommy Plunkett, said. A much smaller number, perhaps 60, repeated the protest on Wednesday. Three students were suspended for not returning to class.</p>
        <p>J. Randall Morton, the principal, said, ''We announced that they had made their statement and they had been heard and now their responsibility was to be in the classroom.''</p>
        <p>Judge DeMent's highly detailed injunction prohibits the Governor, the Attorney General, the State Board of Education and the Board of Education in DeKalb County, Ala., where the lawsuit was filed, from permitting any school-organized or officially sanctioned religious activity in the classroom, including vocal prayer, readings of the Scripture, devotional discussions, and distribution of religious materials. It also bans publicly broadcast prayers and invocations at commencement exercises, assemblies and sporting events.</p>
        <p>It does not prohibit private, personal prayer, the wearing of religious symbols or clothing, the use of religious texts in class for academic purposes, voluntary expression of religious beliefs by students in school assignments, or participation in religious activities during noninstructional time.</p>
        <p>The ruling also provides for the appointment of a monitor to patrol DeKalb County schools in search of violations.</p>
        <p>Governor James, who had previously sent Judge DeMent a 34-page letter arguing that the Bill of Rights does not apply to the states, likened the monitor to ''secret police.''</p>
        <p>The monitor, he said in his statement, ''will comb the schools looking for 'these dangerous criminals' who might, in a public setting, pray for the Father's blessing on this nation.'' He also warned that the judge would fine or jail teachers and students who pray for the safety of soldiers during times of war.</p>
        <p>In making his attempt to keep the Federal court's injunction from taking effect in Etowah County, Judge Moore wrote: ''It is neither the prerogative of nor within the province of a court to dictate how, when and where a child may acknowledge God. This is the essence of freedom of religion under the First Amendment.''</p>
        <p>That led Ms. Sumners, whose case is being financed by the American Civil Liberties Union and by Americans United for Separation of Church and State, to petition Judge DeMent to block Judge Moore's ruling.</p>
        <p>It is well-established, she wrote, that Federal courts have supremacy over state courts. ''This court cannot allow Etowah County,'' she argued, ''to set up a law until itself, to be a constitutional republic unto itself.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
