<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When an Italian Place Moves Upscale</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="671156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MARE E MONTE (GREENWICH, CONN, RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1D91E3BF934A15751C0A962958260" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When an Italian Place Moves Upscale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, PATRICIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANOTHER Italian restaurant? Yes, indeed, and when it is as good as Mare e Monte in Greenwich, there's reason to cheer. The newcomer, subtitled "Ristorante Toscano," is on the site of Da Vinci's, an old-fashioned family-style pizza place and has the same ownership. But the sweeping changes are all for the better.</p>
        <p>Mare e Monte is stylishly cool looking, with white walls, black trim, mirrors, murals and deep-blue touches in chairs, table aprons and draperies. The smoking and non-smoking sections seem to fluctuate as demand dictates, from the large main dining room to a smaller, cozy room near the bar. Softly lighted at night, the main room is bright, light and cheery by day, with sunshine flooding in from the large front windows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANOTHER Italian restaurant? Yes, indeed, and when it is as good as Mare e Monte in Greenwich, there's reason to cheer. The newcomer, subtitled "Ristorante Toscano," is on the site of Da Vinci's, an old-fashioned family-style pizza place and has the same ownership. But the sweeping changes are all for the better.</p>
        <p>Mare e Monte is stylishly cool looking, with white walls, black trim, mirrors, murals and deep-blue touches in chairs, table aprons and draperies. The smoking and non-smoking sections seem to fluctuate as demand dictates, from the large main dining room to a smaller, cozy room near the bar. Softly lighted at night, the main room is bright, light and cheery by day, with sunshine flooding in from the large front windows.</p>
        <p>The menu, tilting toward the Italian north, is modish as well. While the name Mare e Monte (Sea and Mountain) suggests a menu of seafood and game, the concentration is on pasta and meat, with just a few fish and shellfish dishes. Prices are on the high side in what seems typical of Greenwich.</p>
        <p>One of the most appealing entrees can be found listed under appetizers: seafood antipasto platter at $15.95. The diversity and generosity of the warm contents -- a plethora of shrimp, scallops, smoked salmon, calamari, octopus, crab claws, marinated anchovies and mushroom caps, served on a bed of linguine with tomato sauce -- make this appropriate as a main course, or easily shared by two or three as a starter.</p>
        <p>An appetite-sparking first course is salad, either misticanza (mixed baby greens lightly dressed), tricolore (arugula, radicchio and endive) or the seductive arugula con i funghi selvaggi (a special of arugula and wild mushrooms).</p>
        <p>As for non-salad starters, calamari fritti was just as expected -- greaseless, crisply fried and bountiful. Less satisfying was polenta con salsicce -- two large, thick triangles of mealy polenta in a bland marinara sauce accompanied by two sausages, one of which was dense and blackened.</p>
        <p>Entrees fared better, from calamari con fagioli (an expert rendering of fork-tender squid and beans in a succulent white wine sauce with tomato, garlic and a nip of sage) to scaloppine di vitello alla zingara (three exquisite escalopes, layered with prosciutto, in a subtle, well-seasoned Madeira sauce, served with a salty new potato and wood-scented slices of grilled eggplant, mushrooms, squash and fennel).</p>
        <p>There is a risotto of the day, and at one lunch it was made with fresh asparagus tips and saffron -- a golden, creamy creation that was superb. Less appealing was ravioloni all' olio di tartufo -- large, round cheese-filled ravioli bathed in butter, truffle oil and a touch of saffron -- delicate but rather boring, with minimal saucing.</p>
        <p>The lunch and dinner menus share several dishes but there are differences, notably the inclusion of pizza or focaccia as a noontime option. Pizza quattro stagioni was a medley of mushrooms, bits of artichoke hearts, prosciutto, salty and delicious ripe Gaeta olives and mozzarella, spread generously over the thinnest of pizza crusts.</p>
        <p>Focaccia Toscana, brushed with olive oil, tomato, fresh basil and rosemary, had a crust as skinny as that on the pizza.</p>
        <p>Actually, the first delight at Mare e Monte was the crusty, triangular rolls, called panini, made on the premises and served oven hot. Dipped in high quality extra-virgin olive oil, the rolls made a delicious preprandial warm-up.</p>
        <p>A small, separate menu lists dessert, coffee, liqueurs and digestifs. Three desserts were richly rewarding. The tiramisu was a creamy prize, a blend of textures and flavors. Mascarpone cheesecake was properly light and fluffy with a tantalizing whisper of Triple Sec, while an order of biscotti brought three different types studded with almonds, hazelnuts and aromatic spices.</p>
        <p>We spent $62.70 for two, which included three courses each before tax, tip and beverages. A well-priced wine list includes 46 choices, 29 Italian, with a few French and the remainder American, many in the $15 to $30 range.</p>
        <p>A mundane beer list sports two Italian choices and Samuel Adams, but little else of interest to the suds aficionado.</p>
        <p>Mare e Monte's transformation into a first-class establishment adds another upscale choice to Greenwich's restaurant scene. Mare e Monte</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>235 Greenwich Avenue (corner of East Elm Street), Greenwich. 661-5831.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: A large dining room stylishly decorated in black, white and deep blue, plus a smaller room near the bar.</p>
        <p>Service: Cordial, correct, professional.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: Padellata di cozzi a piacere, calamari fritti, arugula con i funghi selvaggi, misticanza, tricolore, calamari con fagioli, scaloppine di'vitello alla zingara, risotto with asparagus and saffron, seafood antipasto platter, pizza quattro stagioni, focaccia Toscana, tiramisu, biscotti, mascarpone cheesecake.</p>
        <p>Price range: Lunch entrees $8.50 to $17.50, dinner entrees $13.50 to $23.50.</p>
        <p>Credit cards: American Express, Diners Club, Mastercard and Visa.</p>
        <p>Hours: 11:30 A.M. to 3 P.M. Monday through Friday, 3 to 10 P.M. Monday through Friday, 11:30 A.M. to 11 P.M. Saturday, 11:30 A.M. to 10 P.M. Sunday.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Accepted.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility: Ground-level access.  DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
