<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Darfur Crisis Defies Even Redoubled U.S. Peace Efforts</title>
    <meta content="13sudan" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1717308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5DA133EF930A25752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Darfur Crisis Defies Even Redoubled U.S. Peace Efforts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL BRINKLEY</byline>
      <dateline>JUBA, Sudan, Nov. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As three white helicopters carrying Robert B. Zoellick and his traveling party began descending over the Kalma refugee camp in the Darfur region of Sudan on Thursday afternoon, crowds of refugees -- thousands of them -- stopped what they were doing, then ran to the camp's central square.</p>
        <p>The refugees ringed the square. Mr. Zoellick, the deputy secretary of state, waved and smiled. On his left wrist that day, he had chosen to wear a blue jelly plastic bracelet bearing the slogan, ''Not on our watch.'' But even with all his attention on Sudan, the population of this camp, and of others across Darfur, grows daily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As three white helicopters carrying Robert B. Zoellick and his traveling party began descending over the Kalma refugee camp in the Darfur region of Sudan on Thursday afternoon, crowds of refugees -- thousands of them -- stopped what they were doing, then ran to the camp's central square.</p>
        <p>The refugees ringed the square. Mr. Zoellick, the deputy secretary of state, waved and smiled. On his left wrist that day, he had chosen to wear a blue jelly plastic bracelet bearing the slogan, ''Not on our watch.'' But even with all his attention on Sudan, the population of this camp, and of others across Darfur, grows daily.</p>
        <p>Asked in Khartoum on Wednesday about America's intentions toward Sudan, Mr. Zoellick bristled a bit when he noted that this was his fourth visit in the past seven months. ''I haven't been to any other country four times this year,'' he said. ''I haven't even been to New York four times this year.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zoellick has thrown the full power and prestige of his office into his mission in Sudan: to end the violence in Darfur that has claimed more than 200,000 lives and to consummate the peace agreement between southern rebels and the government in Khartoum.</p>
        <p>But by almost any measure the situation has only worsened. Perhaps, he said, Sudan is impervious to outside pressure and entreaty.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zoellick had been in the deputy secretary's job only a couple of months when he made his first trip here in April. Since then, Sudan has taught him the limits of diplomacy.</p>
        <p>''If people are determined to kill each other,'' he said, ''there's not a lot the United States can do.''</p>
        <p>If nothing else, Mr. Zoellick understands the Sudanese better. He can recite tribal names, affiliations and political leanings and recount the nation's blood-spattered history. So he knows that Western political leaders have seldom fared well here.</p>
        <p>In 1885, Gen. Charles George Gordon, the British administrator of Khartoum, was beheaded on the very palace steps Mr. Zoellick climbed Wednesday afternoon, on his way to the office of Sudan's current president, Omar Hassan al-Bashir to urge him yet again to end the violence.</p>
        <p>The next day, government-backed militiamen on horseback galloped into the Kalma refugee camp, just hours before Mr. Zoellick arrived. They shot a refugee dead.</p>
        <p>Violence in Darfur has worsened, after a relatively calm summer. Darfur's rebel leaders have split in a bitter feud, seriously complicating sputtering peace negotiations. And after the death in July of John Garang, the charismatic southern leader, movement toward carrying out the terms of the north-south peace treaty has slowed.</p>
        <p>About all Mr. Zoellick and the Sudanese can cite as significant progress are the recent announcements that Sudan intends soon to appoint members to several commissions that will oversee the details of the treaty.</p>
        <p>''I didn't start out starry-eyed about this,'' he said in an interview. ''Yes, this causes some frustration.'' But, he added, Sudan is a harsh place, where citizens live by ''a culture of retribution.''</p>
        <p>Officials in Washington, including 109 members of Congress who wrote to the State Department last month accusing Mr. Bush of appeasing Sudan, want to find a simple villain in the Sudanese government, he said. ''But there are no angels here.''</p>
        <p>The Darfur rebels hold much of the responsibility for the surge in violence, though American officials say the government's typical response is brutal and indiscriminate, leading to the deaths of hundreds of civilians not involved in the conflict.</p>
        <p>Asked last week why Sudan should listen to what Americans say, Jendayi Frazer, the assistant secretary of state for African affairs, said, ''Because it affects their relations with the United States.''</p>
        <p>But after months of high-level attention by American officials and only token responses, the administration must be wondering whether Sudan really cares.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zoellick insisted he was undeterred. ''I'm persistent,'' he said. But then he quoted a man he respects: J. B. Kazura, the Rwandan general who is acting commander of the African Union peacekeeping forces in Sudan.</p>
        <p>The road ahead is ''very difficult,'' the general told him. ''Very difficult.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
