<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats' Broom Sweeps Out Many Republicans; Treading Where Denis Dillon Wouldn't</title>
    <meta content="13lielect" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1717135"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E5DC123EF930A25752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats' Broom Sweeps Out Many Republicans; Treading Where Denis Dillon Wouldn't</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL VITELLO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY the time he had served for 31 years as district attorney of Nassau County, Denis Dillon was probably known as much for the kinds of things he did not do as for those he did.</p>
        <p>For example, he did not seek the death penalty in any murder trial, and he refused to handle cases involving abortion-clinic protesters, farming them out to neighboring jurisdictions. Mr. Dillon, 71, attributed both of those policies to his personal convictions and to the tenets of his Roman Catholic faith.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY the time he had served for 31 years as district attorney of Nassau County, Denis Dillon was probably known as much for the kinds of things he did not do as for those he did.</p>
        <p>For example, he did not seek the death penalty in any murder trial, and he refused to handle cases involving abortion-clinic protesters, farming them out to neighboring jurisdictions. Mr. Dillon, 71, attributed both of those policies to his personal convictions and to the tenets of his Roman Catholic faith.</p>
        <p>Then, for reasons less clear-cut, Mr. Dillon was also seen by critics as a district attorney who maintained a prosecutorial no-fly zone over swaths of criminal territory involving the abuse of institutional power: he seemed reluctant to investigate political corruption during the long period of Republican machine control in Nassau. He rarely pursued cases of brutality by police or correction officers, though brutality problems plagued the county for decades. He was slow to prosecute priests accused of sexually molesting children.</p>
        <p>As a result of Mr. Dillon's self-imposed proscriptions, Kathleen Rice, the former federal prosecutor who defeated him Tuesday to become the first woman elected to the office in Nassau, will probably be defined, at least initially, by how willing she is to tread where Mr. Dillon would not.</p>
        <p>Among some, hopes are high that she'll be willing.</p>
        <p>''I'm confident now that the Diocese of Rockville Centre will no longer have a safe haven in the Nassau County district attorney's office,'' said Laura Ahearn, the director of Parents for Megan's Law, a Long Island advocacy group that has been critical of the church's failure to protect children from sexually predatory priests. ''In my experience, Dillon was more concerned with expediency than with thorough prosecution,'' she said. ''We are looking forward to a fresh approach.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dillon's office did bring several pedophile priests and church workers to trial and secured prison terms in a few cases, though victims complained that the sentences were too short. But in public perception, his approach suffered by comparison with his counterpart in Suffolk County, Thomas J. Spota. Though Mr. Spota prosecuted about the same number of cases as Mr. Dillon did, he also conducted a yearlong grand jury investigation into the history of predatory priests in the diocese, which encompasses both counties of Long Island. The grand jury produced a report in 2004 that detailed a pattern of official neglect and cover-ups in the diocese that went far beyond the handful of prosecuted cases. Mr. Dillon criticized the report as ''salacious'' and without legal basis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spota said he hopes to have better relations with his new counterpart in Nassau, and to share priorities as prosecutors. ''After my investigation of the diocese, I had virtually no contact with Dillon's office,'' Mr. Spota said. ''He wouldn't speak to me.''</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Dillon nor the diocese responded to requests for comment for this article.</p>
        <p>''I think it's important for district attorneys of contiguous counties to have a solid relationship,'' Mr. Spota said. ''Many of our investigations cross over county lines -- gambling, organized crime, in the area of governmental corruption. It will be refreshing to be able to interact.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spota's prosecution of political corruption in the last few years was seen as partly responsible for the widespread election losses Suffolk Republicans suffered on Tuesday, especially in the Town of Brookhaven. Whether Ms. Rice pursues a complementary path into the realm of official corruption or steers clear, people in both parties said her political finesse would be tested early and often when she assumes office in January. She will take charge of a staff of 150 lawyers, many of whom have worked for Mr. Dillon for years and revere him.</p>
        <p>She will inherit several public corruption cases involving former midlevel aides to Thomas R. Suozzi, the county executive, whose popularity at the top of the Democratic ticket helped elect her. She will also take over part of a continuing investigation of circulation fraud at Newsday. Not least of all, Ms. Rice's own campaign promise to cut down on plea bargains in criminal cases could raise a political problem of its own.</p>
        <p>''I have two reactions to her election, and they are opposite,'' said Barbara Bernstein, the director of the Civil Liberties Union of Nassau County. ''I am thrilled that somebody will be there to enforce the law when anti-abortion demonstrators block clinics. But I am also concerned that when she faults Dillon for using plea bargaining, she may end up with thousands of cases backed up, which means people can sit in jail forever. That's not justice either.''</p>
        <p>Stephen Scaring, a former assistant district attorney under Mr. Dillon, said that whatever differences emerge between the administration of the current district attorney and his successor, they would most likely play out at the margins.</p>
        <p>''A D.A.'s office is an institution that functions pretty much the same, regardless of who is in charge,'' said Mr. Scaring, now a lawyer in private practice in Garden City. ''For the most part, the burglars are going to commit their burglaries, the police are going to arrest them, and the D.A.'s are going to prosecute them, just like they have always done.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
