<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Italians Take German Side in Spat</title>
    <meta content="20GERM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/20/international/europe/20GERM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1505975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bochum (Germany)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schroder, Gerhard (Chancellor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berlusconi, Silvio (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Berlusconi, Silvio</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schroder, Gerhard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EED61E3CF933A15754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Italians Take German Side in Spat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Some Italians Take German Side in Spat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>BOCHUM, Germany, July 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recent war of words between German Chancellor Gerhard Schroder and Italy's Prime Min Silvio Berlusconi is cause for concern among residents of Bochum, Germany; many in this Ruhr Valley town, where tens of thousands of Italians migrated after World War II in search of work, worry that spat will revive old prejudices on both sides; in strange coincidence, museum has just opened exhibit devoted to vast, but uneasy, two-way traffic between Germany and Italy, documenting wave of guest workers in both countries and illustrating evolution of relationship; today, Germany is home to 610,000 Italians; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To Celso Curzi, it was deplorable enough that Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi of Italy likened a German member of the European Parliament to a guard in a Nazi camp. ''We have our own little Benito problem,'' he said, referring to Mussolini.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Curzi, an Italian who immigrated to Germany, really got upset when he heard that a junior tourism minister in Italy had described Germans as ''hypernationalistic blonds'' who invaded Italian beaches and held ''noisy burping contests.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For an immigrant enclave the Ruhr Valley, the fallout from the recent war of words between Germany and Italy has been both economic and emotional.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To Celso Curzi, it was deplorable enough that Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi of Italy likened a German member of the European Parliament to a guard in a Nazi camp. ''We have our own little Benito problem,'' he said, referring to Mussolini.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Curzi, an Italian who immigrated to Germany, really got upset when he heard that a junior tourism minister in Italy had described Germans as ''hypernationalistic blonds'' who invaded Italian beaches and held ''noisy burping contests.''</p>
        <p>''He didn't just damage Italian tourism,'' said Mr. Curzi, as two old Italian friends nodded gravely. ''He damaged every Italian business in Germany -- every pizzeria, every ice cream shop. When you say things like this minister, you stir up the same kind of prejudice we faced when we got here.''</p>
        <p>In Berlin and Rome, the recent war of words between Germany and Italy has been portrayed as a sort of summer theater, with Mr. Berlusconi and Chancellor Gerhard Schröder kicking sand at each other like unruly teenagers at the beach. Actually, not at the beach, since Mr. Schröder canceled his vacation in a resort town on the Italian coast to register his anger at the anti-German remarks.</p>
        <p>Here in the Ruhr Valley, however, the tiff has touched a nerve. Tens of thousands of Italians immigrated to industrial cities like Bochum after World War II, in search of work. An unsung part of Germany's postwar economic miracle, they toiled in coal mines, steel mills or on the railroad.</p>
        <p>Now many are pensioners like Mr. Curzi, with German wives and children -- and a hard-won sense of belonging to their adopted land.</p>
        <p>They worry that the spat will revive old prejudices on both sides, which Mr. Curzi sums up with an old cliché about the right-brain, left-brain relationship between the countries. ''Germans love Italians, but don't admire them. Italians admire Germans, but don't love them.''</p>
        <p>In a strange coincidence, a museum here just opened an exhibit devoted to the vast, but uneasy, two-way traffic between Germany and Italy. Titled ''Naples-Bochum-Rimini,'' it documents the wave of Gastarbeiters, or guest workers, who came to the Ruhr Valley from Italy, as well as the Germans who chose Italy as their first playground after shaking off the ashes of war.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to trace how this relationship has evolved,'' said Dietmar Osses, the director of the museum. ''We show German prejudices toward Italians, but also the German longing for Italian beaches, for laughter, for the lightness of the culture.''</p>
        <p>Among the items on exhibit are faded family photographs, employment contracts yellowed with age and a pair of woolen socks sent by an Italian mother fretting about her son's first winter in ice-bound Germany.</p>
        <p>Some were donated by Mr. Curzi and his friends Giuseppe La Torre and Antonio Colabella. Mr. Colabella, 72, showed a visitor a clunky, battery-powered head lamp he had used in the mines. The son of a penniless farmer in central Italy, he answered the German government's call for guest workers in 1957.</p>
        <p>Life was often rude for these new arrivals. Mr. Curzi, who emigrated from Pesaro, a coastal town south of the Adriatic resort Rimini, said his German bosses initially treated him as shiftless and unreliable.</p>
        <p>''They always said they would put a stamp on my backside that said, 'Go back to Pesaro,' '' said Mr. Curzi, who is now 64.</p>
        <p>Germans also nursed the stereotype that Italians were hot-blooded and prone to violence. Mr. La Torre, who emigrated from a mountainous farming village east of Naples, recalled how he was almost fired when his boss claimed that Mr. La Torre had tried to stab him with a mining pick during an argument.</p>
        <p>These men persevered, however, and by the mid-1960's, when Turkish immigrants began to stream into Germany, Italians had become favored workers. Today, 610,000 Italians live in Germany, second among immigrants only to the 1.9 million Turks. Many of the Italians own restaurants, flower shops and gelato parlors.</p>
        <p>Still, more recent Italian immigrants have had problems. Nearly 8 percent of Italian children have been assigned to schools for students with learning problems, a higher percentage than Turkish children. Educators surmise that the Italians assimilate less well because their families plan to stay here only briefly.</p>
        <p>Such thinking seems odd to a longtimer like Mr. Colabella. When he married a German in 1960, he gave up any dreams of returning to Italy. He brought up his six children to speak only German, though he still speaks it with a sing-song accent that is unmistakably Mediterranean.</p>
        <p>Far from rejecting the stereotype of blond Germans, Mr. Colabella fell in love with one. ''When I saw this beautiful blonde, I thought, 'My God,' '' he said, recalling his first glimpse of his wife.</p>
        <p>Mr. La Torre arrived here in September 1957 thinking he would be back in Italy by the following Easter. He even bought a house in his village to keep the home fires burning. In 1994, however, he finally sold it, concluding that he would rather spend his retirement in the Ruhr.</p>
        <p>''The nostalgia for Italy was there,'' he said, ''but over the years it faded. Now when I go there, I miss my kids.''</p>
        <p>In a closing of the circle, these aging Italians and their German families are now part of Germany's annual holiday exodus to Italy. Mr. Curzi and his children plan to spend three weeks in August in Pesaro, where Mr. Schröder had planned to take his summer holiday.</p>
        <p>Despite his worries, Mr. Curzi is hopeful that the storm will soon blow over. He said his brother in Pesaro called to tell him that there were so many banners outside restaurants welcoming Germans, and promising a German-speaking staff, that he wondered whether Italians were still welcome. ''At least I won't have a problem,'' Mr. Curzi said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
