<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOTLIGHTS</title>
    <meta content="05WEFOOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1524971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kornel, Ezriel (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershenson, Roberta</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fiction of Reality, The: The Man Who Shouted Teresa (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E7D6123CF936A35753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOTLIGHTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA HERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershenson, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Footlights column on White Plains neurosurgeon and actor Dr Ezriel Kornel, who will perform solo show The Fiction of Reality: The Man Who Shouted Teresa at Northern Westchester Center for the Arts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doctor in the House, But Onstage</p>
        <p>Precision reigns in the operating room, where ruminations on the nature of reality could cause a mind to wander.</p>
        <p>So it is good that Dr. Ezriel Kornel, a White Plains neurosurgeon, gets to ponder metaphysical questions in his after-hours life as an actor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Doctor in the House, But Onstage</p>
        <p>Precision reigns in the operating room, where ruminations on the nature of reality could cause a mind to wander.</p>
        <p>So it is good that Dr. Ezriel Kornel, a White Plains neurosurgeon, gets to ponder metaphysical questions in his after-hours life as an actor.</p>
        <p>His passion for acting has landed him at the South Salem Library theater, Wainwright House in Rye and several Off Off Broadway theaters during the last nine years. He aims high, studying with the same coach that luminaries like Glenn Close use.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kornel, 50, is interested in the role fantasy plays in perception. He will explore the subject in a solo show, ''The Fiction of Reality: The Man Who Shouted Teresa,'' at the Northern Westchester Center for the Arts in Mount Kisco on Wednesday and Thursday at 7:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>The piece combines stories by Italo Calvino and David Lefkowitz and is directed by Lazaro Perez.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to write in the program that everyone has their own version of reality,'' Dr. Kornel said. ''How much they bend the world to fit that version, or bend their own sense of reality to fit the real world, is the art of living.''</p>
        <p>Tickets are $20. Dr. Kornel said he would donate any profits to the arts center.</p>
        <p>Information: (914) 241-6922.</p>
        <p>Gracing Yonkers, A Sculpture Park</p>
        <p>The idea for a sculpture meadow on the banks of the Hudson River arose five years ago when the sculptor Barbara Segal held a ''stone symposium'' along the waterfront in Yonkers, backed by the city.</p>
        <p>Sculptors worked in stone and marble while the public watched, promoting the role of the arts in downtown redevelopment.</p>
        <p>Now Yonkers not only has a slick full-color newsletter devoted to its recent accomplishments (a new riverfront apartment building, restaurants and retail growth, an arts center, a new library), it also has a stunning new sculpture park, a result of the symposium.</p>
        <p>The Yonkers Sculpture Meadow will be inaugurated on Wednesday from 5 p.m. to 7 p.m. with a free public cocktail party on the waterfront.</p>
        <p>Entertainment includes music by the Yonkers-based Youth Theater Interaction and the Jan Leder Quartet, with a dance performance by students from Sarah Lawrence College.</p>
        <p>Lorraine Altamura Siegel, chairwoman of Yonkers Friends of the Arts, sponsor of the event, says the college's participation is a sign of the city's new cachet.</p>
        <p>''Sarah Lawrence historically wouldn't even admit they were in Yonkers,'' she said. ''This is a big step for them.'' (In the fractured manner of Westchester addresses, the college has a Bronxville address, though it is located in Yonkers.)</p>
        <p>The sculpture park is a joint project of the city and Segal Fine Arts, which is run by Ms. Segal.</p>
        <p>It features whimsical and stately marble and limestone furniture representing rooms without walls: a ''Cloud Living Room'' by Ms. Segal, a ''River Bedroom'' by Susan Abraham; a ''Meditation Circle'' by Paul Greco; an ''Early American Dining Room'' by Alfredo Cardenas. and a ''Fish Loveseat'' by Lou Lalli.</p>
        <p>Information: (914)949-6007.</p>
        <p>Pianist's Solo Show Of Photographs</p>
        <p>The concert pianist Robert Preston developed a friendship with Ansel Adams when the photographer, who was also a pianist, heard one of Mr. Preston's recordings. Adams invited Mr. Preston, who studied as a child at the Music Conservatory of Westchester in White Plains, to his home in Carmel, Calif., and offered suggestions about the black and white photographs by Mr. Preston that were used on his record cover. Soon the power of photography wrestled the force of music and in 1997 Mr. Preston switched professions.</p>
        <p>A longtime Westchester resident, Mr. Preston now lives in Stamford, where he works in a ''really sophisticated darkroom.'' An exhibition of 16 of his photographs, ''The Earth and Other Sacred Places,'' will be on view in the conservatory's Stadther Recital Hall from Wednesday through Nov. 25. A public reception will take place Wednesday from 7 to 10 p.m. Information: (914)761-3900.</p>
        <p>ROBERTA HERSHENSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
