<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Metaphysical Poets, Recited on the Fens</title>
    <meta content="05WOLF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/05/arts/theater/05WOLF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1524687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butterworth, Jez</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolf, Matt</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Night Heron (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (Eng)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Royal Court Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Butterworth, Jez</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DF1F3DF936A35753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Metaphysical Poets, Recited on the Fens</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Metaphysical Poets, Recited on the Fens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT WOLF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wolf, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matt Wolf article previews Jez Butterworth play Night Heron; play comes to New York after run in London; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME plays write their meanings large, with bald-faced thesis statements or characters that are clear stand-ins for the author. Jez Butterworth's ''Night Heron,'' on the other hand, works by allusion, ellipses and an appeal to the imagination. It left a good many British critics bewildered when it opened at the Royal Court Theater in London some 18 months ago.</p>
        <p>''I'd say I was 30 percent gripped, 30 percent entertained and 40 percent baffled,'' wrote John Gross in The Sunday Telegraph. John Peter, in The Sunday Times, thought Mr. Butterworth's play ''has a story, sort of, but it works like poetry'' -- which makes sense, insofar as the play liberally quotes poetry, including the ending to the first act: an unexpected and poignant recitation of ''The Garden,'' the celebrated 1681 poem by Andrew Marvell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bewildering a good many critics when it opened 18 months ago in London, Jez Butterworths "Night Heron" works by allusion, ellipses and an appeal to the imagination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME plays write their meanings large, with bald-faced thesis statements or characters that are clear stand-ins for the author. Jez Butterworth's ''Night Heron,'' on the other hand, works by allusion, ellipses and an appeal to the imagination. It left a good many British critics bewildered when it opened at the Royal Court Theater in London some 18 months ago.</p>
        <p>''I'd say I was 30 percent gripped, 30 percent entertained and 40 percent baffled,'' wrote John Gross in The Sunday Telegraph. John Peter, in The Sunday Times, thought Mr. Butterworth's play ''has a story, sort of, but it works like poetry'' -- which makes sense, insofar as the play liberally quotes poetry, including the ending to the first act: an unexpected and poignant recitation of ''The Garden,'' the celebrated 1681 poem by Andrew Marvell.</p>
        <p>New York theatergoers can make what they will of ''The Night Heron'' when it opens on Tuesday at the Atlantic Theater Company, the same stage on which Mr. Butterworth's first play, the scabrous underworld comedy ''Mojo,'' opened to buoyant reviews in 1997. As was true of ''Mojo,'' ''The Night Heron'' is directed by Neil Pepe, the Atlantic's artistic director; among the American cast are three members of the ''Mojo'' company -- Chris Bauer, Clark Gregg and Jordan Lage -- and Mary McCann, a founding member of the Atlantic who is married to Mr. Pepe.</p>
        <p>It is Ms. McCann, playing a bulky jailbird with the wonderful name of Bolla Fogg, who gets the Marvell poem that closes Act I. (She wears a fat suit for the role, her hair cut short, almost to the skin.) The other characters include a pair of out-of-work gardeners subsisting on rabbits in England's marshy fenlands, east of Cambridge, who take in Bolla Fogg as a paying boarder, and a naked Cambridge undergraduate who, near the end of the play, delivers a passage from John Donne. In the London production, he quoted Percy Bysshe Shelley.</p>
        <p>Why the change of poet? ''To see the effect it has on the play,'' said Mr. Butterworth, 34, speaking by telephone from New York six days into previews of the Atlantic production.</p>
        <p>Presumably it's no accident that Mr. Butterworth has shifted from a Romantic poet (Shelley) to a Metaphysical one (Donne), in keeping with the particular metaphysics of his play, which has an almost supernatural tone as it celebrates the order of the natural world while depicting the struggle of human beings to exist in it and with one another. ''What comes out of the boy's mouth could be one of many poems,'' said Mr. Butterworth, who was an English major at Cambridge. ''He had a choice of about five; what I would love to do is rotate them.''</p>
        <p>More important than the specific poet was the feeling imparted by poetry of ''a dream logic,'' Mr. Butterworth said. ''I was after a conscious thing, which is very hard to achieve -- where the effects are almost intangible, like the effects of a dream.''</p>
        <p>His goal with ''The Night Heron'' represents a considerable contrast with Mr. Butterworth's determinedly cool, hip ''Mojo,'' a play -- first seen at the Royal Court here in 1995 -- that displayed a definably aggressive urban attitude. ''There were all kinds of things I felt I could write after 'Mojo,' '' he explained of the earlier work, which is set in London's seamy 1958 Soho. ''They were all similar to 'Mojo,' when the last thing I wanted was to come out with three or four plays that were the same.''</p>
        <p>In London, where ''The Night Heron'' was directed beautifully by the Court's artistic director, Ian Rickson, some saw echoes of Harold Pinter, whom Mr. Butterworth directed in his 1998 movie version of ''Mojo.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pepe said he thinks of the play ''in the tradition of Beckett.''</p>
        <p>''It's about telling a story,'' he said, ''without explaining but by doing and not pandering to an audience.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Butterworth said he writes plays ''to lose an audience, initially.''</p>
        <p>''I love that feeling when a play opens and you don't know where you are and what's going on,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THEATER Matt Wolf is the London theater critic for Variety.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Matt Wolf is the London theater critic for Variety.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
