<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Pressures Threaten A Romanian Pastime: Graft</title>
    <meta content="05ROMA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/05/international/europe/05ROMA-L.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1524911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Europe</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Romania</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tudor, Corneliu Vadim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Romania</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Tudor, Corneliu Vadim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1D8123CF936A35753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Pressures Threaten A Romanian Pastime: Graft</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Diplomat Is Criticized by Romanian</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>BUCHAREST, Romania</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Romania, which has long been hotbed of corruption, is facing several dynamics that may bring change; presidential candidate Corneliu Vadim Tudor seeks to harness national seething over corruption; US wants to build military bases as alternative to bases in Germany and is concerned how money will be spent; European Union is demanding changes and reforms without which Romania's entry into union will be in jeopardy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Relations between Michael Guest, the American ambassador here, and Corneliu Vadim Tudor, a poet and far-right nationalist with ambitions to be president, are scarcely diplomatic.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Guest says something critical, Mr. Tudor clubs back with an attack -- often crude, and largely unprintable -- on the unhidden fact that Mr. Guest is gay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American ambassador and a far-right nationalist are, quite separately, and each with a wary eye on the other, tackling the issue of corruption.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Relations between Michael Guest, the American ambassador here, and Corneliu Vadim Tudor, a poet and far-right nationalist with ambitions to be president, are scarcely diplomatic.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Guest says something critical, Mr. Tudor clubs back with an attack -- often crude, and largely unprintable -- on the unhidden fact that Mr. Guest is gay.</p>
        <p>Yet the two men, quite separately, and each with a wary eye on the other, are pushing to the front of Romanian politics the same concern: the extraordinary mire of corruption here, regarded by some as the worst of any country seeking to join the European Union.</p>
        <p>As a result, some experts say that corruption may finally become an issue that Romanian politicians ignore at their peril.</p>
        <p>Tales of corruption fill the pages of newspapers every day, with scandals ranging from the disappearance of profits from the sale of Romania's shipping fleet to a more recent fraud involving illegal gasoline shipments, a case in which the country's prime minister, Adrian Nastase, intervened on behalf of a defendant.</p>
        <p>Romanians complain of everything from having to pay off bureaucrats to huge companies that pay little income tax.</p>
        <p>For years, people here seemed resigned to accept corruption quietly, even though Romania has developed far more slowly than many other former Communist nations. But now pressures from both inside and outside seem to be changing that.</p>
        <p>There is a presidential election next year, and Mr. Tudor, often considered a fringe political figure, wants a repeat of the 2000 race, when he ran surprisingly better than expected on the strength of a protest vote against politics as usual. Then, as now, he sought to harness the national seething over corruption: he even promised -- in jest, he says now -- to round up corrupt politicians in a stadium and gun them down.</p>
        <p>Since then, another dynamic has pushed the issue to the fore: this Balkan nation of 23 million suddenly became more relevant to the outside world. The United States wants to build military bases here as an alternative to bases in Germany, and it is concerned how its money will be spent -- or lost, as the case may be.</p>
        <p>The European Union is also demanding changes, particularly the reform of the judiciary responsible for prosecuting corruption cases. Without those changes, Romania is unlikely to join by the already optimistic date of 2007 that it has set.</p>
        <p>In this atmosphere, Mr. Guest gave a blistering speech on the issue in April. He took shots at ''businessmen with inside connections'' who profit from the privatization of state companies. He charged that AIDS drugs cost hospitals here 50 percent more than they do in the United States, saying that ''if you look hard enough you can even find out who benefits.''</p>
        <p>''At times I have urged, publicly and privately, that stronger steps need to be taken against corruption,'' Mr. Guest said. ''Almost invariably, someone says to me, 'Mr. Ambassador, you don't understand.' Well, my friends, I do understand. I understand too well.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Tudor claims not to understand why Mr. Guest does not support him more, given their shared concerns about corruption. Nonetheless, he sees it as a potent issue in next year's elections.</p>
        <p>''Romanians are tired of the lack of medicines, the lack of food, in general, of the very low level of life,'' Mr. Tudor said. ''This can be the starting point of revolution.''</p>
        <p>During the summer, the government did pass a conflict of interest law, which drew praise as a first step as well as criticism for being weak and vague. It followed the establishment last year of a national prosecutor of corruption.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor, Ioan Amarie, has been lauded for his energetic work, investigating more than 2,200 complaints since took office in September 2002 and winning indictments in hundreds of those cases.</p>
        <p>NATO has agreed to accept Romania as a member next year, but there are mixed feelings among political experts here about the role the United States and Europe might play in cracking down on corruption.</p>
        <p>On the one hand, expectations are high that Western institutions will continue to demand change; on the other, there is concern that the United States may decide corruption is just too hard to excise and will cut a deal to make it easier to put military bases here.</p>
        <p>The European Union, meanwhile, may overlook such shortcomings and make Romania a member as a way to check America's growing interest in Eastern Europe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
