<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Singh Has Eight Birdies To Put Heat on Woods</title>
    <meta content="05GOLF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/05/sports/golf/05golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1525089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">American Express Championship (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Singh, Vijay</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7DE133CF936A35753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Singh Has Eight Birdies To Put Heat on Woods</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Singh Gets Eight Birdies in Third Round as Woods Stumbles</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>WOODSTOCK, Ga., Oct. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tiger Woods takes third-round lead at American Express Championship (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vijay Singh never captured the lead Saturday, but he definitely got Tiger Woods's attention.</p>
        <p>Setting up a showdown that could have a big impact on this year's PGA Tour money race, Singh pulled to two strokes behind Woods heading into Sunday's final round of the American Express Championship. Singh produced the best round of the tournament, a six-under-par 64, in a commanding display of ball-striking on the difficult Capital City Club course.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vijay Singh pulled to two strokes behind Tiger Woods heading into Sundays final round of the American Express Championship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vijay Singh never captured the lead Saturday, but he definitely got Tiger Woods's attention.</p>
        <p>Setting up a showdown that could have a big impact on this year's PGA Tour money race, Singh pulled to two strokes behind Woods heading into Sunday's final round of the American Express Championship. Singh produced the best round of the tournament, a six-under-par 64, in a commanding display of ball-striking on the difficult Capital City Club course.</p>
        <p>Woods, who held a five-stroke lead when the round began, finished it at eight-under 202 after shooting a 69, with Singh next at 204, then Tim Herron (67) at 205 and K.J. Choi (68) at 206.</p>
        <p>The third-round charge by Singh put heat on Woods, and they will be paired in the last group of the final round.</p>
        <p>''A lot of things are up for grabs tomorrow,'' said Woods, who can snatch the lead from Singh on the money list by winning the $1.05 million first-place check Sunday. ''It's going to be a lot of fun.''</p>
        <p>Singh had the most fun Saturday in a superb round that featured eight birdies and two bogeys on a day when only 8 of the 72 players remained under par. Singh could have gone even lower but missed a 4-foot attempt for birdie at No. 13 and a 5-foot attempt for par on No. 14.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Singh preferred to focus on the positive. After a 64, who could blame him?</p>
        <p>''I don't know if I can swing the club any better,'' Singh, who has three victories this year, said. ''If I can keep doing this, I'm going to shoot low numbers.''</p>
        <p>Singh is first on the money list with $5.7 million, ahead of Davis Love III ($5.5 million) and Woods ($5.2 million). But with Love out of contention at 11 over par, either Singh or Woods will hold the money lead after Sunday with five weeks left in the season.</p>
        <p>A victory by either Singh or Woods could wind up deciding the player of the year award, voted on by Tour players.</p>
        <p>While the player of the year award and money title are clearly up for grabs, this was clearly Singh's day. Tour officials watered the greens Friday night after some players grumbled that they were too firm, and Singh took full advantage of the more receptive conditions.</p>
        <p>''I don't think anybody wants to play this kind of golf course every week,'' Singh said. ''You'll go into an asylum if you have to do that.''</p>
        <p>Herron and Choi are also in striking distance, partly because Woods was not at his best Saturday.</p>
        <p>After a splendid start, with birdies on three of his first seven holes, Woods three-putted for bogey at No. 8. He missed the green with a sand wedge at No. 11, leading to another bogey. Suddenly, with Singh making four consecutive birdies on Nos. 9-12, Woods had only a one-stroke lead.</p>
        <p>Woods birdied the par-5 No. 12. Then Singh, playing two groups ahead, bogeyed No. 14 and Woods made a 9-foot birdie putt at No. 13. That gave Woods a four-stroke lead again heading to the 16th tee, but Woods made another mistake, his first double bogey of the tournament.</p>
        <p>Woods hooked his drive at No. 16 into the left fairway bunker, and the ball landed next to a clump of sand, giving him no chance to reach the green. After blasting out into the fairway, Woods hit a poor approach shot into the right greenside bunker. His bunker shot flew across the green almost 60 feet past the pin, and after a poor lag putt, Woods still had to make an 8-footer for double bogey.</p>
        <p>But Woods made the putt, and Singh had a bogey at No. 18, giving Woods a two-stroke lead to work with.</p>
        <p>Having won 29 of 31 Tour events when he has held or shared the 54-hole lead, Woods has proved he is one of golf's best closers. On a course like Capital City, however, where any hole could lead to a potential bogey, the playing conditions and Singh will present a serious challenge.</p>
        <p>''I just made two mistakes today that I don't normally make -- three-putted 8, then made bogey with a sand wedge in my hand on No. 11,'' Woods said. ''It was kind of frustrating, but I got in the clubhouse and still have the lead.</p>
        <p>''It's not easy going out there with a lead -- everyone is coming after you. But the great thing is, you always have those shots to play with. If I shoot the same score they do, then obviously I win. It doesn't take a rocket scientist to figure that out.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
