<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Share a Cab, Get a New Job: Taking Advantage of Chance</title>
    <meta content="13JMAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/13/jobs/13jmar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1656732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, Coeli</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Employment Agencies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Employment Agencies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Little Brown &amp; Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E6DC143CF930A25750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1309" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Share a Cab, Get a New Job: Taking Advantage of Chance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Share a Cab, Get a New Job: Taking Advantage of Chance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COELI CARR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carr, Coeli</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chance meeting on airplane results in job offer for woman coming to New York without employment; other serendipitous hirings discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a Sunday night last May, sitting in a window seat waiting for the plane to take off, Megan Ferington had no idea the skies that awaited her would be so friendly or auspicious.</p>
        <p>She had spent the previous year working at an advertising agency in Salt Lake City, her first job after receiving a master's degree in public relations from the S.I. Newhouse School of Public Communications at Syracuse University. But a desire for a new professional challenge had prompted her to sell her furniture and car and buy a one-way ticket to New York City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sitting in her seat waiting for the plane to take off, Megan Ferington had no idea the skies that awaited her would be so auspicious.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a Sunday night last May, sitting in a window seat waiting for the plane to take off, Megan Ferington had no idea the skies that awaited her would be so friendly or auspicious.</p>
        <p>She had spent the previous year working at an advertising agency in Salt Lake City, her first job after receiving a master's degree in public relations from the S.I. Newhouse School of Public Communications at Syracuse University. But a desire for a new professional challenge had prompted her to sell her furniture and car and buy a one-way ticket to New York City.</p>
        <p>''Everyone in Salt Lake thought I was completely nuts, because I was moving here without a job, without a place to stay, and I had only been to the city once before, as a tourist,'' said Ms. Ferington, 24.</p>
        <p>She noticed that the man sitting next to her was reading a media-related story that she thought might come in handy for the several job interviews she had lined up for the next day. She asked him if she could have a look after he finished, leading to a conversation about her career aspirations. ''He had a kind of a grin on his face that led me to believe this guy might know something,'' she said. Her instincts turned out to be on the money.</p>
        <p>Unknown to Ms. Ferington, Stan Bratskeir, the owner and president of his own public relations firm, Bratskeir &amp; Company, in New York -- and a friend of the man in the middle seat -- had been listening in from the aisle seat.</p>
        <p>Impressed with her independence and confidence in coming to New York with no real prospects -- that rated high in the ''moxie box,'' he said -- Mr. Bratskeir introduced himself, said he would be happy to take a look at her résumé and suggested she stop by for an interview, which she did, two days later.</p>
        <p>Four days after that, she was offered an account executive position, which she accepted right away. Within two weeks, she was at her desk, a full-fledged employee at Bratskeir. ''I think people are really amazed with my story because it has an element of fate to it,'' Ms. Ferington said.</p>
        <p>Her in-flight conversation was probably about as long as a typical corporate interview, but was much less formal and probably more revealing. ''I felt like he knew me as a person and liked my character,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She added that she found it hard to believe that anyone who listened to intuition and believed in the synchronicity of being in the right place at the right time could discount the significance of finding a potential business connection outside the office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bratskeir is no stranger to the benefits of chance meetings. ''I've met a lot of people whom I've ultimately hired in unusual ways, like while sitting in restaurants,'' he said. ''You have a much better opportunity to really learn about somebody, because their defenses are down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bratskeir talked openly with his staff about the uncanny meeting with Ms. Ferington, but other employers are reluctant to discuss such serendipitous hires. One person, who spoke on condition of anonymity, described sharing a short cab ride with a stranger who happened to have a departmental opening. That connection led to a job, after a battery of tests and formal interviews.</p>
        <p>The company's employees were not told about the cab ride, probably ''because it was such a chance encounter,'' the new employee said. He suggested that the circumstances might be interpreted as not taking the hiring process seriously.</p>
        <p>This reluctance to honor chance does not surprise Malcolm Gladwell, author of the best seller ''Blink: The Power of Thinking Without Thinking'' (Little, Brown, 2005), which describes the phenomenon of very quick decision-making.</p>
        <p>''That's one of the truths about decisions we make instinctively -- we are embarrassed by them,'' said Mr. Gladwell, who said it was ''highly typical'' to cover up decisions made this way. ''I wish we were a little more honest about how we make decisions. But the fact remains that in these kinds of workplace settings, there's a culture that's very hostile to the idea that we make up our minds on the spur of the moment.''</p>
        <p>Job seekers, however, tend to be less concerned with corporate opinion of the process than in being hired, by whatever means necessary. These people may be happy to know that they can greatly improve their odds of turning chance meetings into opportunities.</p>
        <p>The answer lies in understanding the configuration of the brain. The limbic system is involved with intuition, hunches and emotion, and the frontal lobe is the part that censors emotions and discourages impulsive behavior, said Mona Lisa Schulz, a neuropsychiatrist in Yarmouth, Me., whose clientele includes people who want to know how to use their intuition more productively.</p>
        <p>Dr. Schulz, the author of ''Awakening Intuition: Using Your Mind-Body Network for Insight and Healing'' (Three Rivers Press, 1999) and ''The New Feminine Brain,'' to be published this summer by Free Press, said that people with ''double-D frontal lobes'' would never have initiated a conversation, as Ms. Ferington did, even if their instinct told them to.</p>
        <p>''Your frontal lobe would say, 'I can't do that, he'll think I'm a nut,''' said Dr. Schulz, who suggested ways for people to counteract those fears. ''You push your edge, try to break a bit of your former rules about how to engage, and notice your discomfort and anxiety. Go to someone in a restaurant and ask them what they're eating. You're stretching the limit of what you consider politeness and social comportment. You experience the anxiety, but acknowledge this is truly not a dangerous situation.''</p>
        <p>Networking to find a job is increasingly hard work, so it is easy to understand the appeal of landing a job interview while standing in line for a movie or over a steam table at lunch time. But for Andrea R. Nierenberg, president of the Nierenberg Group, a Manhattan marketing consultancy, taking advantage of any chance meeting is a form of networking.</p>
        <p>''Networking is a state of mind,'' said Ms. Nierenberg, author of ''Nonstop Networking: How to Improve Your Life, Luck and Career'' (Capital Books, 2002) and the forthcoming ''Million Dollar Networking.''</p>
        <p>''Someone can be in a cab and just say, 'Nice weather we're having,' but could also take the bull by the horns and say, 'So, what do you do?' and get into a discussion and a rapport,'' Ms. Nierenberg said.</p>
        <p>If you conceal too many of your needs, she said, people will not know what you want, and they will leave the meeting none the wiser.</p>
        <p>''I've made connections getting my nails done, on the top of the Tokyo Tower and standing by the ladies' room,'' she said. ''You never know where that connection could lead.''</p>
        <p>There is evidence that subjugating the fears of your frontal lobe may help your career. ''There are many people in corporate culture who are Type A's, driven, impulsive and risk-taking,'' Dr. Schulz said.</p>
        <p>''They have less frontal-lobe censoring and are more likely to act on their limbic system hunches. They are very much rewarded. Donald Trump is a perfect example.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
