<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Start Piecing Together Gunman's Path</title>
    <meta content="13SHOO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1656850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nichols, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnes, Rowland W (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDD153CF930A25750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Start Piecing Together Gunman's Path</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>DULUTH, Ga., March 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article follows tentative police reconstruction of Brian Nichols's activities from killing of Judge Rowland W Barnes to his capture on following day (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Brian Nichols walked out of his hostage's suburban Atlanta apartment at 11:24 a.m. on Saturday, waving a white piece of cloth in surrender, he ended just over 24 hours of bloodshed, fear and furious police activity.</p>
        <p>The end came after a spree in which Mr. Nichols is accused of overpowering the deputy who was escorting him to his rape trial, stealing her gun, injuring her, running into the courtroom where his trial was being held, killing the judge and court reporter, fleeing and fatally shooting a deputy, hijacking a series of vehicles, assaulting a couple, shooting a federal customs agent, stealing the agent's truck and taking a woman hostage in her suburban apartment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Brian Nichols walked out of his hostage's suburban Atlanta apartment at 11:24 a.m. on Saturday, waving a white piece of cloth in surrender, he ended just over 24 hours of bloodshed, fear and furious police activity.</p>
        <p>The end came after a spree in which Mr. Nichols is accused of overpowering the deputy who was escorting him to his rape trial, stealing her gun, injuring her, running into the courtroom where his trial was being held, killing the judge and court reporter, fleeing and fatally shooting a deputy, hijacking a series of vehicles, assaulting a couple, shooting a federal customs agent, stealing the agent's truck and taking a woman hostage in her suburban apartment.</p>
        <p>Some major gaps remain in the authorities' knowledge of Mr. Nichols's movements after he fled the Fulton County Courthouse on Friday.</p>
        <p>Still, a clearer picture of Mr. Nichols's day was emerging.</p>
        <p>At 8:45 a.m. on Friday, Judge Rowland W. Barnes of Superior Court opened a civil trial in his eighth-floor courtroom. The civil trial was unrelated to the rape trial of Mr. Nichols, which the judge was also hearing.</p>
        <p>Around the same time, Mr. Nichols was taken from the detention area and escorted by Deputy Cynthia Hall to a holding area to change into civilian clothes for his trial.</p>
        <p>Somehow, Mr. Nichols overcame the deputy, stole her weapon and injured her, the police said.</p>
        <p>Instead of fleeing the courthouse, Mr. Nichols made his way to Judge Barnes's chambers, where he took a second weapon from a deputy.</p>
        <p>Richard L. Robbins, a lawyer who was part of the civil case, said Mr. Nichols appeared around 9 a.m. and quickly shot the judge from behind. The judge's court reporter, Julie Ann Brandau, was also shot and killed.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Nichols raced down to the sidewalk on Martin Luther King Jr. Drive. Officials said another deputy, Sgt. Hoyt Teasley, chased Mr. Nichols, who shot Sergeant Teasley in the stomach, killing him.</p>
        <p>A witness saw Mr. Nichols run across the street and commandeer a passing car. Shortly afterward, the police believe, he hijacked a white tow truck several blocks north of the courthouse.</p>
        <p>Driving south, past the State Capitol and away from the courthouse, Mr. Nichols pulled the tow truck into another parking garage and hijacked a silver Mercury Sable owned by Almeta Kilgo, who works for Atlanta's major daily newspaper, The Journal-Constitution.</p>
        <p>Shortly afterward, Mr. Nichols drove to yet another parking lot a few blocks away and approached a reporter for The Journal-Constitution, Don O'Briant, who had just parked his green Honda. Mr. O'Briant turned to run and was hit on the head with the gun by Mr. Nichols.</p>
        <p>The police said Saturday afternoon that they still did not know precisely what Mr. Nichols did between 9:30 a.m., when he abandoned the Honda, and 10:40 p.m., when he accosted Iman Adan outside her apartment just east of the Lenox Square Mall.</p>
        <p>But they believe that Mr. Nichols took a commuter train to a station near the mall. Ms. Adan said Mr. Nichols demanded to be let into her home. Inside, Ms. Adan's boyfriend, Shelton Warren, wrestled with Mr. Nichols, who hit him and fled.</p>
        <p>Almost immediately afterward, he headed two blocks to the south and shot and killed David Wilhelm, the assistant agent in charge of the federal customs office in Atlanta, and stole his badge, gun and truck, the police said. Sometime later, Mr. Nichols came up behind a woman entering her apartment at Bridgewater Luxury Apartment Homes, 20 miles northeast of Mr. Wilhelm's home.</p>
        <p>All indications were he did not know the woman, whom the police did not identify. He kept her hostage through the night, following the manhunt on television.</p>
        <p>At 9:50 a.m., the police received a 911 call from the woman. The police were unsure whether she had escaped or been freed.</p>
        <p>An officer on patrol responded, and the SWAT team followed, arriving on the scene about 10:30 a.m.</p>
        <p>Before the police even tried to contact him, Mr. Nichols came out of the building waving the white cloth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
