<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="03TRAN$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1306652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4D61139F930A35754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Placed OF Tim Salmon on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled OF Jeff DaVanon from Salt Lake of the PCL. Activated C Jose Molina from the 15-day DL and optioned him to Salt Lake.  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Recalled RHP Danys Baez from Buffalo of the International League. Optioned RHP Roy Smith to Buffalo.  YANKEES--Placed OF David Justice on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled INF-OF Clay Bellinger from Columbus of the International League.  TEXAS RANGERS--Placed 3B Ken Caminiti on irrevocable waivers for the purpose of giving him his unconditional release. Placed RHP J.D. Smart on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to July 1. Recalled RHP Aaron Myette from Oklahoma of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Agreed to terms with RHP Brandon League, OF Tyrell Godwin, SS Michael Rouse and LHP Christopher Neylan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Placed OF Tim Salmon on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled OF Jeff DaVanon from Salt Lake of the PCL. Activated C Jose Molina from the 15-day DL and optioned him to Salt Lake.  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Recalled RHP Danys Baez from Buffalo of the International League. Optioned RHP Roy Smith to Buffalo.  YANKEES--Placed OF David Justice on the 15-day disabled list. Recalled INF-OF Clay Bellinger from Columbus of the International League.  TEXAS RANGERS--Placed 3B Ken Caminiti on irrevocable waivers for the purpose of giving him his unconditional release. Placed RHP J.D. Smart on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to July 1. Recalled RHP Aaron Myette from Oklahoma of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Agreed to terms with RHP Brandon League, OF Tyrell Godwin, SS Michael Rouse and LHP Christopher Neylan.</p>
        <p>National League  CINCINANTI REDS--Activated LHP Dennys Reyes off 15-day disabled list and optioned him to Louisville of the International League. Assigned RHP Osvaldo Fernandez outright to Louisville. Signed RHP Jose Rijo to a minor league contract.  COLORADO ROCKIES--Signed RHP Dan Miceli to a minor league contract.  FLORIDA MARLINS -- Placed CF Preston Wilson on the 15-day disabled list.</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES DODGERS--Agreed to terms with SS Irvin Joel Guzman.  MILWAUKEE BREWERS--Placed RHP Paul Rigdon on 15-day disabled list. Recalled OF Alex Sanchez from Indianapolis of the International League.  METS--Signed RHP Jason Weintraub and C Tyler Beuerlein. Assigned Weintraub to Kingsport of the Appalachian League and Beuerlein to Brooklyn of the New York-Penn League.  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Agreed to terms with OF Cedric Brooks.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  BUFFALO BILLS--Released WR Stephen Campbell, WR Teddy Johnson and C Ryan Diepenbrock.  NEW ENGLAND PATRIOTS--Signed CB Leonard Myers.  TENNESSEE TITANS--Agreed to terms with CB Michael Booker.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  ANAHEIM MIGHTY DUCKS--Acquired LW Denny Lambert from Atlanta for future considerations.  ATLANTA THRASHERS--Agreed to terms with F Hnat Domenichelli.  BOSTON BRUINS--Signed RW Martin Lapointe to a four-year contract and D Sean O'Donnell to a three-year contract.  CALGARY FLAMES--Signed D Bob Boughner to a three-year contract.  DALLAS STARS--Signed RW Donald Audette to a four-year contract.  LOS ANGELES KINGS--Re-signed D Mathieu Schneider to a three-year contract, and signed LW Ken Belanger and D Brett Hauer to two-year contracts.  MINNESOTA WILD--Signed C Darby Hendrickson to a three-year contract.  NASHVILLE PREDATORS--Signed LW Stu Grimson to a two-year contract.  OTTAWA SENATORS--Re-signed D Curtis Leschyshyn to a multiyear contract.  PHILADELPHIA FLYERS--Signed C Jeremy Roenick to a five-year contract.  PHOENIX COYOTES--Acquired C Daymond Langkow from Philadelphia for two future draft choices.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
