<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conversations/Cajuste Carelus; A Haitian Refugee Wonders When He'll Return</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="532442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFUGEES AND EXPATRIATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASYLUM (POLITICAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHEMO, DIANA JEAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARELUS, CAJUSTE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARISTIDE, JEAN-BERTRAND (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D61339F932A05756C0A964958260" item-length="1246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conversations/Cajuste Carelus; A Haitian Refugee Wonders When He'll Return</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA JEAN SCHEMO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHEMO, DIANA JEAN</byline>
      <dateline>HUNTINGTON, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cajuste Carelus, who is in the 12th year of exile from his native Haiti, can speak freely. He has no plans to return home anytime soon.</p>
        <p>President of the Haitian Community Association in Huntington, N.Y., and chairman of its Multi-Cultural Center, Mr. Carelus has pledged not to return to Port-au-Prince until democracy does. "I work for change from here," he said. His association tracks Haiti's faltering attempts at democracy, helping scores of the casualties: refugees who land here without money, housing or friends. Mr. Carelus and a friend feed and shelter the newcomers, and provide a lawyer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cajuste Carelus, who is in the 12th year of exile from his native Haiti, can speak freely. He has no plans to return home anytime soon.</p>
        <p>President of the Haitian Community Association in Huntington, N.Y., and chairman of its Multi-Cultural Center, Mr. Carelus has pledged not to return to Port-au-Prince until democracy does. "I work for change from here," he said. His association tracks Haiti's faltering attempts at democracy, helping scores of the casualties: refugees who land here without money, housing or friends. Mr. Carelus and a friend feed and shelter the newcomers, and provide a lawyer.</p>
        <p>The friend sits by, listening closely as Mr. Carelus speaks, but says little. He clings to his anonymity because he intends to go home sometime soon.</p>
        <p>Through their work, the two men have encountered the fear and desperation of Haitians who have fled the military takeover of their country. They are incensed by President Bush's decision to turn back the rattletrap boats bearing Haitians bound for America, and believe Washington would only have to place one tersely worded phone call to Port-au-Prince to restore to power Haiti's democratically elected President, Jean-Bertrand Aristide.</p>
        <p>"I don't believe in military intervention from America," said Mr. Carelus, "but if Bush wanted it, Aristide would be sleeping in Haiti tonight." Mr. Aristide left Haiti after a military coup Sept. 30. Since then, thousands of Haitians have escaped the country, and filled the holding camps at the American naval base at Guantanamo Bay, Cuba, in their quest to reach Miami.</p>
        <p>Citing overcrowding at Guantanamo Bay, the Bush Administration announced last week that to discourage more Haitians from striking out for America, the Coast Guard would escort back to Haiti any boats not in imminent danger of sinking.</p>
        <p>Those seeking political asylum would have to do so at the American embassy in Port-au-Prince, Washington said. At the same time, the United States is applying economic pressure against the military regime run by Gen. Raoul Cedras through an embargo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carelus's friend, who had refrained from speaking, now addressed him in Creole. The two agreed that the American-backed embargo of Haiti amounted to little more than an attempt to hedge political bets. Casual Racism</p>
        <p>"There's a big hole in the economic embargo," Mr. Carelus said, switching to English. "We do have the Dominican Republic next to us. Anything can go through there. The embargo would be good if any ship or plane couldn't travel to Haiti, and if the people of the O.A.S.  [ Organization of American States ]  enforced it."</p>
        <p>He maintains that most of the refugees bobbing over the Caribbean are escaping military repression rather than poverty. "They are political refugees, because before Aristide, a lot refused to come by sea because it was so dangerous," Mr. Carelus said. "But we see this real flow after Aristide lost power, when the military took over."</p>
        <p>At 42 years of age, Mr. Carelus, a high school science teacher when he left Haiti, now works in Syosset as a school maintenance man. His 62-year-old friend founded an elementary school in Haiti in the 1950's. The Tontons Macoute blew it up a few years later. Defying a presidential order to remain in Haiti, the principal fled. Now he paints boats for a living in Port Washington, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Their Haitian Community Association has also tried to improve the quality of education that the Huntington schools provide for immigrant children. An investigation by the New York State Department of Education found that the schools offered minimal instruction in English as a second language, and placed a disproportionate number of foreign and minority children into special-education classes.</p>
        <p>"I had a meeting with the superintendent right here in this room," said Mr. Carelus. "We offered to talk to the children a few times a week, to translate, to work with the school district. I said, 'We have teachers in the district from Haiti.' They smile when we talk, but they definitely don't want us."</p>
        <p>The superintendent, Richard B. Stock, did not return a reporter's phone call seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Their lives on Long Island are not marked by the harshness faced by Haitians in New York City. Perhaps because the minority population is smaller than in New York, the racism is more overt here, said Mr. Carelus.  "You live with it. You see it. You touch it."</p>
        <p>The battles Mr. Carelus fought in Haiti were more dangerous than casual racism in Long Island. There he had spoken to his students against the regime of Jean-Claude Duvalier. One April night, the Tontons Macoute took Mr. Carelus to a cafeteria-style restaurant turned torture chamber. "I was there just because I was caught talking to a few people. Some of them were big officers in the regime.</p>
        <p>"From 5 P.M. to the next morning, all night, they made me watch. I saw two men beating another man with sticks and then poking him in the ribs with sticks. A woman was so shocked and frightened, she fell on the floor and had her period right there from the emotion. I saw them beat a man so hard until there was blood, just because he sold somebody's painting for $25 and kept a few dollars for himself." Mr. Carelus shook his head as if to empty out the memory. "He was a student of mine."</p>
        <p>He was on his feet, acting out the horrors, and glanced over at his friend: "I see all of that. I saw things must change, and the only way to change was to leave the country," he said. 'Time to Go Back'</p>
        <p>The men have differing ideas about how to bring change to their homeland. "This is a good time to go back to Haiti," his friend replied. He believes that if he waits for democracy, he may never get back.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carelus is troubled that Haitians are being denied hearings to determine whether they are in danger of political persecution. He believes that the United States has not been complying with the United Nations' 1951 Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees, which guarantees political asylum to victims of persecution.</p>
        <p>He mentioned the Russian Jews who have been taken in by the United States without severe scrutiny. The policy towards Haitians is different. "They're going by our skin."</p>
        <p>The abrupt shift in United States policy toward the Haitian boat refugees could spread to people escaping persecution in other countries as well, he cautioned. "Today it's the Haitians, tomorrow it's somebody else."</p>
        <p>Neither of the men believed that Mr. Bush's policy, requiring Haitians to apply for political asylum at the embassy in Port-au-Prince, would succeed. Mr. Carelus's friend could not contain his feelings. "If one or two go," he said, "it's no big deal. But if it's 400 or 500, the military won't let them go.</p>
        <p>"Those military like to see blood. They like to see bodies on the floor. They don't even think about the consequences," he said.</p>
        <p>The educator looked down at his hands as he spoke. A week before, his nephew disappeared. His family in Haiti searched for two days, only to find him dead, an electrical cord around his neck.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he plans to return home this summer. He speaks of building a school, a clinic, a canteen, a tool bank for farmers. It is because he wants to go back so urgently that he restrained himself during the conversation. For when he has spoken publicly about the plight of Haitians, chilling phone calls followed: "You're going to die tonight," unnamed voices warn. Until now, they have never been able to silence him.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
