<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Redistricting Decision Puts Elections in Doubt</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="461579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITY COUNCILS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPANISH-SPEAKING GROUPS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REAPPORTIONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOARD OF ELECTIONS (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEFRANCESCO, DANIEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reapportionment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDD143FF933A15754C0A967958260" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Redistricting Decision Puts Elections in Doubt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTIN GOTTLIEB</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City's political leaders scrambled last night to salvage this fall's City Council elections in the face of a Justice Department decision that Hispanic residents were unfairly represented in 3 of 51 new districts.</p>
        <p>But with the city up against a back-to-the-wall deadline, the director of the city's Board of Elections said the decision made it "extremely unlikely" that the elections could be held as scheduled. And the city's highest-ranking elected Hispanic officials and representatives of the Hispanic groups that challenged the plan before the Justice Department vowed to seek a postponement of the election and to send the entire redistricting plan back to the drawing board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City's political leaders scrambled last night to salvage this fall's City Council elections in the face of a Justice Department decision that Hispanic residents were unfairly represented in 3 of 51 new districts.</p>
        <p>But with the city up against a back-to-the-wall deadline, the director of the city's Board of Elections said the decision made it "extremely unlikely" that the elections could be held as scheduled. And the city's highest-ranking elected Hispanic officials and representatives of the Hispanic groups that challenged the plan before the Justice Department vowed to seek a postponement of the election and to send the entire redistricting plan back to the drawing board.</p>
        <p>With Mayor David N. Dinkins and Council Speaker Peter F. Vallone calling for fast action, staff members of the Council Districting Commission tried last night to locate the 15 commissioners to schedule a meeting quickly on what to do about redrawing the lines for an important part of the most fundamental reformation of city government since the turn of the century.</p>
        <p>But Daniel DeFrancesco, the Executive Director of the Elections Board, cautioned that the tight timetable for petitioning, legal challenges and primaries leading up to Election Day on Nov. 5 was already in motion and would likely have to be torn up because of the decision. Monday Petition Deadline</p>
        <p>Under the schedule, Council candidates have until Monday to file petitions requiring 900 valid signatures to qualify for election. Eighty-one candidates, including two in one of the invalidated districts, have already filed petitions and Mr. DeFrancesco said he had expected at least that many additional candidates to file before Monday's deadline.</p>
        <p>Any postponement could create a need for a new 30-day petitioning period and a new sequence of dates for challenges before the board and in the courts, he said. This year's primary date, Sept. 12, is already late because of Jewish holidays on the first two Tuesdays in September, he said, and further delay would make it all but impossible to send ballots in timely fashion to service women and men around the world.</p>
        <p>Complicating matters further, lawyers for Councilwoman Susan Alter of Brooklyn, who was moved out of her current district and put into one represented by Noach Dear, said that if the commission did not redraw her lines as well she would press her challenge to the plan in Federal court based on language in the Justice Department decision that she viewed as favorable to her case. Ms. Alter, who is white, asserts she was unfairly cut out from an overwhelmingly black district that she had represented for decades. Concerns Called 'Reasonable'</p>
        <p>Against this backdrop, it was clear that Mayor Dinkins and Mr. Vallone, usually fierce political rivals, were united in wanting to see the elections take place. Deputy Mayor Bill Lynch, the Mayor's chief political operative, urged the commissioners to meet quickly and to limit their actions to rectifying the problems the Department pointed to in the three districts, the 34th and 37th in Brooklyn, and the Eighth in the South Bronx and East Harlem.</p>
        <p>"When you open the door again a lot of people try to run in it," he said. Speaking in particular about the Eighth district, he described the Justice Department's concerns as "reasonable" and said, "I don't think it will take very much to fix those concerns."</p>
        <p>In a statement, Mr. Dinkins pointed to praise for the commission that was contained in the decision by Assistant Attorney General John Dunne, the head of the Justice Department's Civil Rights Division. Mr. Dunne had said the commission "made great strides in drawing Council district lines which greatly enhance minority voting strength overall."</p>
        <p>He described the changes required to satisfy the Department as "modest."</p>
        <p>The city's Corporation Counsel, Victor A. Kovner, said the city could help bring off the elections by asking the Justice Department and a three-judge Federal panel to permit the present petitions even if some election districts are added or deleted from council districts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vallone also called for the commission to meet quickly. People close to the Council leadership said it is particularly interested in seeing the lines upheld because the overwhelming number of incumbents -- who support Mr. Vallone in his leadership role -- have well-protected seats under the commission plan. Problems Elsewhere</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, the drawing of legislative district lines was turned over to experts appointed by Federal judges after the Justice Department invalidated initial redistricting plans. The danger to a legislature is that the judicial appointees do not have the same interest in protecting incumbents.</p>
        <p>Ruben Franco, chief counsel of the Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, a principal challenger of the plan, said that asking that an expert be appointed to oversee the redistricting "is one of the things we are tossing around."</p>
        <p>In the swirl of confusion last night, it was unclear what the redistricting commission might do and how it could legally go about doing it. While the Justice Department invalidated three districts, it strongly criticized the lines of a fourth, District 21 in Queens, as the product of a process which "consistently disfavored the Hispanic voters, causing the Hispanic voting strength in the city to be unnecessarily limited overall." However, the provisions of the Voting Rights Act only cover Manhattan, the Bronx, and Brooklyn in New York City, boroughs where it had been determined that there has been a pattern of minority disenfranchisement.</p>
        <p>While not ruling that the redrawing of District 45 in Brooklyn, Ms. Alter's district, or several other unnamed districts was invalid, Assistant Attorney General John R. Dunne, head of the Civil Rights Division, wrote that "the commission appears to have made its decisions about these districts based upon a misunderstanding of the law."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
