<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A VOTE DEADLINE IN FLORIDA IS SET FOR TODAY</title>
    <meta content="14ELEC$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/14/politics/14ELEC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1247295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COUNTING THE VOTE: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Broward County (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seminole County (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Katherine (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, Karen P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7DE1F38F937A25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A VOTE DEADLINE IN FLORIDA IS SET FOR TODAY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM and DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Firestone, David; Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>TALLAHASSEE, Fla., Nov. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Disputed presidential election results are thrown into new uncertainty after Florida's Republican secretary of state Katherine Harris declares she will enforce legal November 14 deadline for certifying statewide vote; announcement comes as predominantly Democratic counties press ahead with hand counts of ballots that may not be completed on time; officials from two mainly Democratic counties and campaign of Vice Pres Al Gore appear in court seeking to extend deadline; argue that Florida law is flexible enough to allow most to complete tally; Vice Pres Al Gore makes first public comment since election; says it is important to 'spend days necessary' to determine winner; says he would not wish to win presidency by few votes cast in error, misinterpreted or not counted; Bush remains in seclusion in Texas; chief spokeswoman Karen Hughes condemns Gore campaign for pressing ahead with hand recounts; Broward County officials vote not to proceed with full recount after sample of precincts found gain of only four votes for Gore; Democratic officials say they will sue to overturn decision; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The disputed presidential election results were thrown into new uncertainty today when Florida's Republican secretary of state declared that she would enforce a legal Tuesday evening deadline for certifying the statewide vote, even as predominantly Democratic counties moved forward with hand recounts of ballots that might not be finished in time and both sides wrangled in court.</p>
        <p>At midday, a federal judge in Miami denied a Republican request for an injunction to block the manual recounts as unconstitutional. After hearing two hours of arguments from teams of lawyers, the judge, Donald M. Middlebrooks, paused only a moment before ruling that the federal court had no jurisdiction and putting the matter back in state hands. [Article, Page A15, and text, Page A20.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The disputed presidential election results were thrown into new uncertainty today when Florida's Republican secretary of state declared that she would enforce a legal Tuesday evening deadline for certifying the statewide vote, even as predominantly Democratic counties moved forward with hand recounts of ballots that might not be finished in time and both sides wrangled in court.</p>
        <p>At midday, a federal judge in Miami denied a Republican request for an injunction to block the manual recounts as unconstitutional. After hearing two hours of arguments from teams of lawyers, the judge, Donald M. Middlebrooks, paused only a moment before ruling that the federal court had no jurisdiction and putting the matter back in state hands. [Article, Page A15, and text, Page A20.]</p>
        <p>At virtually the same time, two mainly Democratic counties and the campaign of Vice President Al Gore were in state court here, seeking to extend the Tuesday deadline until the hand recounts can be finished and arguing that Florida law is flexible enough to allow the most complete possible tally. The judge in that case put off a ruling until Tuesday but asked pointed questions that suggested he might extend the deadline.</p>
        <p>Nearly a week after the election to choose the 43rd president, Mr. Gore made his first public comment about the Florida situation, addressing reporters outside the West Wing of the White House this afternoon. He said it was important to ''spend the days necessary'' to determine the winner in his bitterly close race against Gov. George W. Bush of Texas.</p>
        <p>''I would not want to win the presidency by a few votes cast in error or misinterpreted or not counted, and I don't think Governor Bush wants that either,'' Mr. Gore said, adding: ''While time is important, it is even more important that every vote is counted and counted accurately.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush remained in relative seclusion at his ranch near Waco, Tex., and made no public appearances. But his camp has suggested that it would carry its fight to block the hand recounts all the way to the United States Supreme Court if necessary. Mr. Bush's lawyers said a formal decision on an appeal would be made soon, and his chief spokeswoman, Karen P. Hughes, condemned the Gore camp's efforts to press ahead with hand recounts in four counties.</p>
        <p>''To produce a fair and accurate count, votes need to be counted fairly and accurately,'' Ms. Hughes told reporters in Austin, Tex. ''Because there are no uniform standards governing this manual recount in four heavily Democratic areas, the votes in these four selective counties are not being counted accurately or fairly. They are being counted subjectively and selectively.''</p>
        <p>Tonight, election officials in one of those counties, Broward, voted not to proceed with a full recount after a count of sample precincts found a gain of just four votes for Mr. Gore. Gore aides said that they would file suit seeking to overturn the decision on the ground that the sample count could translate into 400 additional votes for Mr. Gore in the whole county and that local officials may have acted on an erroneous opinion by the secretary of state's office.</p>
        <p>In the swirling atmosphere of recriminations, each side turned familiar arguments against the other. The Bush partisans accused the Gore camp of seeking loopholes in the Florida laws it had cited as controlling the situation in federal court just this morning. Top Gore advisers rebutted the Bush camp's repeated assertions that the vice president wants to keep counting until he likes the result by accusing the Bush forces of trying to cut off the count while Mr. Bush is ahead, in an effort to guarantee their desired outcome.</p>
        <p>The Florida secretary of state, Katherine Harris, a co-chairwoman of Mr. Bush's state campaign, met briefly with both camps this morning and then issued a two-page statement that she presented as a simple recitation of her duties under the law.</p>
        <p>But in the politically charged reality here, where George Bush's younger brother, Jeb, is the Republican governor, Ms. Harris's statement also amounted to a tactical line in the sand, one that the Texas governor's legal advisers hope could force the Democrats to finish whatever recounting they hope to do in less than 36 hours and freeze the official results in the Republicans' favor.</p>
        <p>A running tally by The Associated Press of the recounts to date showed Mr. Bush with a lead of 388 votes out of some 6 million cast statewide.</p>
        <p>Democrats argued that Florida law gave Ms. Harris flexibility to wait at least until Friday, when the deadline expires for overseas absentee ballots to arrive in Florida.</p>
        <p>''Her plan, I'm afraid, has the look of an effort to produce a particular result in the election rather than to ensure that the voice of all the citizens of the state would be heard,'' Mr. Gore's chief representative here, former Secretary of State Warren M. Christopher, said this afternoon. ''It also looks like a move in the direction of partisan politics and away from the nonpartisan administration of the election laws.''</p>
        <p>Jeb Bush recused himself last week from serving on the three-member state Election Canvassing Commission, which includes Ms. Harris and the state director of elections, Clay Richards, a Republican appointee, and is responsible for certifying the final vote. But the governor's replacement, Robert Crawford, the Democratic agriculture commissioner, is a Bush ally who said today that he was required to enforce the deadline.</p>
        <p>One senior Republican official with close ties to the Bush campaign said Bush strategists, including former Secretary of State James A. Baker III, had known all along that a federal court might decline to intervene in a case involving state election law. But the official said the Bush camp believed that was a risk worth taking and that Judge Middlebrooks's ruling might have tied the Democrats' hands.</p>
        <p>''The judge essentially ruled that the state law has to be followed,'' the official said. ''And part of that state law was that the recounts have to be done by 5 p.m. Tuesday, and Baker always had his eye on that, and now there's a federal judge who says Florida law has to be followed.''</p>
        <p>In fact, there was considerable confusion about just what would happen if a county's tallies were not finished by the Tuesday deadline. One section of the state's election law, governing the canvassing board, stipulates that all counties missing by the deadline ''shall be ignored, and the results shown by the returns on file shall be certified.'' The following section of the statute, adopted subsequently, states that such returns ''may be ignored'' by the Department of State ''and the results on file at that time may be certified.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Harris said the law gave her no discretion to extend the deadline, except possibly in the event of a natural disaster like Hurricane Andrew, when compliance would be impossible, though the law makes no such specific exception.</p>
        <p>Her statement said, ''But a close election, regardless of the identity of the candidates, is not such a circumstance; the law provides for automatic recounts, protests, and manual recounts, and it plainly states when this process must end.''</p>
        <p>But this afternoon, lawyers for Palm Beach and Volusia Counties, Democratic strongholds where Mr. Gore is ahead in the vote, told Judge Terry P. Lewis of Circuit Court that Ms. Harris was arbitrarily imposing a deadline even as the hand count went on, and Dexter Douglass, a lawyer for the Gore campaign, ridiculed Ms. Harris's reasoning.</p>
        <p>''Let me tell you,'' Mr. Douglass said. ''This is not only a hurricane, this is a bark-splitting North Florida cyclone with a hurricane tailing on the end of it.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''The issue is, does Florida stand up for an honest vote, that people in other countries can look to and say that the United States has honest elections, or are there elections where some bureaucrat writes a letter and says, you lose, your vote doesn't count.''</p>
        <p>Under sharp questioning from Judge Lewis, lawyers for Ms. Harris acknowledged that the second section of the law did give the state some leeway in the timing of the certification. The judge expressed a good deal of skepticism that there was any point in certifying the results on Tuesday, while waiting until Friday to certify a winner.</p>
        <p>Although Judge Lewis gave no indication of how he would rule, his questions made it clear that he saw no reason a county should not have enough time for a manual recount.</p>
        <p>''How could you conceivably do a manual recount in a large county without enough time?'' he asked a Bush campaign lawyer. ''It seems kind of futile to give someone an option for a manual recount, but no opportunity to do it.''</p>
        <p>Barry Richards, a lawyer for the Bush camp, responded, ''It's not our place to question the wisdom of the legislature.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Douglass told the judge, ''My client, Vice President Gore, is prepared to lose this election based on an honest count, he is prepared to accept the finality within a reasonable time.''</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign is pursuing hand recounts in two other counties, Broward and Miami-Dade, and Mr. Christopher said it had joined the counties' suit in an effort to ensure such counts could be completed, even if that took longer than Friday.</p>
        <p>Ron Labasky, general counsel of the state Association of Supervisors of Elections, said that individual county canvassing boards generally had discretion over certifying their own vote tallies. He said he did not believe the process envisioned tallies that would be an amalgam of machine-counted and manually recounted ballots, but he acknowledged that the situation was unclear.</p>
        <p>''I think the process would be that the count would be the count,'' Mr. Labasky said.</p>
        <p>Election officials in Volusia County, a largely Democratic area in the east-central part of the state, began a manual recount on Sunday, with officials saying they were not sure it could be completed by the Tuesday deadline. They filed suit in Circuit Court here today seeking an injunction barring Ms. Harris from ignoring results they might submit after Tuesday at 5 p.m., though county officials also said they hoped to finish in time, perhaps as soon as tonight.</p>
        <p>Palm Beach County, which has been enmeshed in a recount of its own and is the only county yet to file any formal tally with the secretary of state's office, is to begin a full manual recount on Tuesday. It joined the suit, as did the Gore campaign.</p>
        <p>Broward County officials began their hand recount today, and Miami-Dade officials are to meet on Tuesday to discuss how to proceed with one there.</p>
        <p>For her part, Ms. Harris sent workers from her office to election supervisors' officers in each of the state's 67 counties, so they would be available to receive the latest returns by the Tuesday deadline.</p>
        <p>''They will remain in the offices of those supervisors of elections until 5 p.m. tomorrow in order to be available to officially receive the certified returns of that county until the last moment, thus providing the maximum possible time for recounting and certification,'' she said in her statement.</p>
        <p>Ms. Harris also said she would ask county election officials to certify the results of the overseas absentee ballots by Saturday morning at the latest. ''Therefore, I anticipate that the presidential election in Florida will be officially certified by Saturday afternoon, barring judicial intervention,'' she said.</p>
        <p>That is clearly what the Bush campaign hopes. Senior Republican officials with ties to the campaign said it had several options as the specter of manual recounts in Democratic counties loomed. One was to demand manual recounts in Republican counties, an option that may still exist in some counties. But they believed they had a stronger case that the manual counts were flawed.</p>
        <p>COUNTING THE VOTE: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
