<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opinions to Spare? Click Here</title>
    <meta content="03SURV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/03/technology/circuits/03surv.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1501812"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Market Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consumer Reports (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Inside Research (Newsletter)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zogby International</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Nancy Beth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Laurence N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Market Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Zogby International</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E6DF113AF930A35754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opinions to Spare? Click Here</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Opinions to Spare? Click Here</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NANCY BETH JACKSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jackson, Nancy Beth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Market researchers are increasingly relying on online questionnaires; surveys are intended to be simple and entertaining to entice people to return to share more opinions; findings do not represent cross-section of nation because they are all people with Internet access and are self-selected; Laurence N Gold of Inside Research newsletter anticipates online market research will account for 33 percent by 2006, compared to 10 percent in 2000; potential is intriguing to long-established Zogby International, which predicts it will become most efficient tool for surveys; Consumer Reports conducted part of its annual survey of products and services online last year; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A PENNY for your thoughts? These days your online opinion may be worth $1 or more as market researchers try to reach consumers who have grown increasingly reluctant to respond to surveys conducted by telephone, by mail or in person. In the process, they are changing the way research is done and raising questions about whose voice is being heard.</p>
        <p>For the participants, the cost is 5 to 20 minutes spent filling out a questionnaire at a Web site. The incentives are as little as a few dollars or the chance to win flat-screen monitors and spa vacations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Your online opinion may be worth $1 or more as market researchers try to reach consumers increasingly reluctant to respond to surveys.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A PENNY for your thoughts? These days your online opinion may be worth $1 or more as market researchers try to reach consumers who have grown increasingly reluctant to respond to surveys conducted by telephone, by mail or in person. In the process, they are changing the way research is done and raising questions about whose voice is being heard.</p>
        <p>For the participants, the cost is 5 to 20 minutes spent filling out a questionnaire at a Web site. The incentives are as little as a few dollars or the chance to win flat-screen monitors and spa vacations.</p>
        <p>The surveys are intended to be simple and entertaining so respondents will return to share more opinions. It is unclear how many are answering the call. But one firm, Greenfield Online, has signed up 1.2 million people by advertising at Web sites.</p>
        <p>Over the last six months, responding to invitations from various research firms, I have sounded off dozens of times about casino resorts, business travel, automobiles, bakery products, commercials, snack foods, movies, toothbrushes, winter sports and coffee beans. Occasionally I felt so ill informed about a topic that I cribbed an answer, pausing to do a Google search, for example, to help on a couple of sports surveys even though nothing but my ego was riding on an informed response. Petless, I did skip the pet survey that popped up when I was checking Italian temperatures at www.weather.com.</p>
        <p>For my effort, I have pocketed all of $12 and won no prizes -- I missed a $50 payout for a 500-question survey because my computer froze -- but I've kept clicking because I became obsessed. The surveys are more engaging than computer solitaire and leave me feeling that I have done a civic duty. My answers will ''directly impact the products and services that everyone enjoys,'' one assured me.</p>
        <p>Yet the findings are certainly flawed because those responding do not represent a cross-section of the nation. For one thing, they are all people with Internet access; for another, they are self-selected. And those who do take part are generally recruited for panels, pools from which respondents are chosen again and again on various topics. (Even then, you sometimes have to act fast to join: after entering my age, sex and ZIP code, I have been turned away because too many like me had already volunteered.)</p>
        <p>Online surveys began appearing in academic and marketing circles about a decade ago, first as scattered e-mail messages and then in online focus groups. Early participants were predominantly male, like the Internet population at the time, but now women are overrepresented on many panels, particularly those involving shopping.</p>
        <p>''It's wondrous how fast Internet research is growing,'' said Laurence N. Gold, editor and publisher of Inside Research, a newsletter for the market research industry. Mr. Gold said that in 2000, only 10 percent of all market research spending involved Internet surveys, compared with a projected 23.6 percent this year. By 2006, he anticipates, online market research will account for 33 percent, or about $900 million. About three-quarters of all market research firms already have some online presence, he said.</p>
        <p>The Internet has yet to penetrate households to the extent that would allow it to reflect broad public opinion in the way the random telephone surveys traditionally used in political polling do. But its potential for plumbing the attitudes, behavior and desires of consumers -- if not voters -- intrigues long-established research firms. Zogby International, which does market research surveys and public opinion polling, predicts at its Web site that ''the computer will gradually replace the telephone as the most efficient vehicle for survey research.''</p>
        <p>Driving the growth are the limitations of the old technology and the promise of the new. Everyone wants to know what's on the consumer's mind, but traditional survey methods have become more expensive and time-consuming. People beg off from face-to-face interviews and discard mail questionnaires as junk. Consumers often decline to respond to phone surveys as well, or pre-empt them with caller ID and other devices. (The new federal do-not-call list for telemarketing exempts telephone surveys and polls.) Moreover, cellphone numbers are not included in random surveys.</p>
        <p>One reason online surveys are finding a receptive audience is that they are less intrusive than telephone surveys, allowing people to reply when convenient. Firms can prompt laggards with e-mail reminders. While neither online surveys nor telephone surveys can convey the smell, taste and texture of products, the Internet's potential is only beginning to be explored with the advent of streaming audio and video and virtual grocery shelves and shopping baskets.</p>
        <p>''We do the old things better, but what's left to be done is to invest the new things the medium allows you to do,'' said Eric J. Johnson, a Columbia University marketing professor who began organizing online panels in 1996. ''We can experiment with what makes survey completion easy for people, the order and kinds of questions, and how long it takes for a respondent to answer a question.''</p>
        <p>Consumer Reports is among the research organizations seeking to shift much of their work to the Internet. Its research staff, made up of psychologists, sociologists, statisticians and other social scientists, wanted to learn faster and at less cost about the experiences its constituency -- generally well-educated consumers -- has had with cars, DVD players, dishwashers, lawn mowers and so on.</p>
        <p>Last year the magazine's annual survey of products and services went out by regular mail to almost four million subscribers. Paper, printing and postage amounted to $700,000, the most expensive research effort to date in its reporting program. Respondents were asked (but not required) to contribute $6 to Consumers Union, the magazine's nonprofit publisher, to help defray the cost.</p>
        <p>In April, nearly 900,000 people subscribing to the magazine's online edition received the 2003 survey by e-mail. Charles Daviet, director of survey research for Consumers Union and a veteran of 30 years of surveys, said the response rate to the online questionnaire was 25 percent, compared with 13 to 14 percent for the mail survey in recent years.</p>
        <p>Each e-mailed survey cost roughly half of its postal counterpart. Mr. Daviet expects even greater savings next year because some of the expenses covered basic programming.</p>
        <p>What's more, nobody has to transfer the answers into a database. ''You have offloaded all the work to the customers,'' said Donna Hoffman, a co-founder of the eLab research center at Vanderbilt University and a psychologist specializing in electronic commerce.</p>
        <p>Although professional organizations like the American Association for Public Opinion Research express concern that online surveys will be used as to sell products, I was never asked to buy anything during or after any of the surveys. That is not to say that my behavior was not influenced. As if playing a game, I tried to guess what company or industry was sponsoring the study, and I generally knew by the time the survey was over. I started paying more attention to television commercials, sports events sponsors, casinos and cars. I bought my first battery-powered toothbrush some weeks after the toothbrush survey. I paused during a coffee survey to brew a cup.</p>
        <p>That was a classic reaction, Dr. Hoffman said. ''We know from years of experiments in psychology research that experiments influence behavior,'' she said. ''When you are asked what do you think about X, then you start thinking about X.''</p>
        <p>Manipulation or priming during the study could taint the results, she said, but respondents may benefit by becoming aware of issues and products they had not considered, leading to ''a generation of consumers who have never been better informed.''</p>
        <p>Yet some researchers fear that online surveys exclude voices, raise issues about sampling techniques and accuracy, train people to become professional respondents, and devalue surveys by making them a new form of electronic junk mail.</p>
        <p>Despite the expansion of the Internet, some social and economic groups are still vastly underrepresented online, said John Stevenson, associate director of the University of Wisconsin Survey Center. Unlike random phone surveys, in which far more people would have a chance to be contacted, an Internet panel does not represent ''average'' Americans.</p>
        <p>The self-selected participant is set apart first by having an e-mail address and secondly by signing up at a Web site or clicking on a pop-up window. Faster modems and more powerful computers may encourage proportionately more participation from yet another subgroup.</p>
        <p>''The challenge of Web surveys is who are we getting, who does this represent, are we getting who we think we're getting,'' Mr. Stevenson said. ''Even when you know, it's a challenge. When we've been successful, it's working with fixed audiences, not in general public surveys.''</p>
        <p>One thing is certain: with papers on Web surveys surfacing at academic conferences, there is ''a whole body of research waiting to happen,'' Mr. Stevenson said. Research on research, that is.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
