<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Advanced Chip Offered By Texas Instruments</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="399084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TEXAS INSTRUMENTS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD9153CF93BA35752C1A966958260" item-length="555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Advanced Chip Offered By Texas Instruments</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS C. HAYES, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, Nov. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Restoring a touch of pride for American makers of computer chips, Texas Instruments Inc. said today that it was delivering limited supplies of its model of the world's most advanced memory chip to some of its largest customers.</p>
        <p>Samsung of South Korea and Hitachi and Toshiba of Japan have made similar announcements within the last two months, and NEC of Japan said it would begin small shipments of its dynamic random access memory chip that stores 16 million bits or two million characters before the end of the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Restoring a touch of pride for American makers of computer chips, Texas Instruments Inc. said today that it was delivering limited supplies of its model of the world's most advanced memory chip to some of its largest customers.</p>
        <p>Samsung of South Korea and Hitachi and Toshiba of Japan have made similar announcements within the last two months, and NEC of Japan said it would begin small shipments of its dynamic random access memory chip that stores 16 million bits or two million characters before the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Texas Instruments, one of the few American chip makers that did not quit making memory chips in the early 1980's, accounts for a big share of the nation's memory chip output. Japanese companies held 69 percent of worldwide memory chip sales in 1989, and American producers had 16 percent, according to Dataquest Inc., a research firm in San Jose, Calif.  'Perseverance Has Paid Off'</p>
        <p>"It's nice to know that Texas Instruments' perseverance has paid off in being able to compete," said Ione Ishii, a Dataquest analyst who follows the industry. She said worldwide sales of 16-megabit memory chips would exceed $5 billion in 1994.</p>
        <p>The executive directing Texas Instruments' production of the advanced memory chips, Lionel White, said in a statement that design engineers and computer industry managers say Texas Instruments has a slight lead over its foreign competitors in the race for high-volume production.</p>
        <p>"According to our customers, these 16-megabit samples are the first they've seen that are based on a design developed for high-volume production," he said. Initial output of the chips will be from the company's newest semiconductor plant, in Avezzano, Italy. Other Texas Instruments plants in Dallas; Miho, Japan, and Taiwan will be equipped later to make the chip.</p>
        <p>The International Business Machines Corporation and American Telephone and Telegraph Company have also spent heavily to develop and produce the 16-megabit chip, but virtually all of their output would be for their own products.</p>
        <p>The 16-megabit memory chip is certain to lead to smaller and more powerful products in the computer and telecommunications industries, as well as find broader uses in aircraft, automobiles and other products. It is also a crucial technology being developed for high-definition television.</p>
        <p>A single 16-megabit D-RAM chip the size of a fingernail can provide two million characters of storage in computers. That is about four times the total capacity of the I.B.M. and similar personal computers in the mid-1980's using as many as 20 chips.</p>
        <p>Agreement With Hitachi</p>
        <p>Texas Instruments has shared research in developing the 16-megabit chip with Hitachi through an agreement the companies signed in 1988. Stan Victor, a spokesman, said the Texas Instruments' chip was based on the company's own designs and manufacturing process.</p>
        <p>In mastering the high-volume production process, Texas Instruments reduced the width of electronic circuits in the new chip to less than a one-hundredth of the width of a human hair, or nearly six-tenths of a micron.</p>
        <p>Texas Instruments' shares gained 12.5 cents, to $25.75, in trading on the New York Stock Exchange today. The shares traded as high as $27.375 during the session but retreated during the market's broad selloff later in the day.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
