<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Atlanta Journal; Its Bloom Is the World's Largest, but Its Smell Is an Eye-Opener</title>
    <meta content="07BLOO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1030113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Odors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Botanical Garden</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Odors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4D6133EF934A35754C0A96E958260" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Atlanta Journal; Its Bloom Is the World's Largest, but Its Smell Is an Eye-Opener</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, July 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amorphophallus titanum, world's largest and perhaps rarest flowering plant, blooms at Atlanta Botanical Garden, marking only sixth time in history that plant has flowered in cultivation in US; curators believe none of previous blooms matched current 6-foot-2-inch height; plant emits its notorious odor, which has earned it the name 'corpse flower' in its native Sumatra; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the Atlanta Botanical Garden, they have been anticipating this event like the flight of Kahoutek. Curators and security guards have been standing watch around the clock. Web sites and telephone lines have been updated daily to keep the citizenry informed. For more than a week, enthusiasts have trekked through the lobby of the Fuqua Conservatory, cameras in hand, in order to monitor and record the progress.</p>
        <p>And then on Saturday afternoon, days before anyone expected it to happen, the world's largest and perhaps rarest flowering plant, the Amorphophallus titanum, began to bloom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the Atlanta Botanical Garden, they have been anticipating this event like the flight of Kahoutek. Curators and security guards have been standing watch around the clock. Web sites and telephone lines have been updated daily to keep the citizenry informed. For more than a week, enthusiasts have trekked through the lobby of the Fuqua Conservatory, cameras in hand, in order to monitor and record the progress.</p>
        <p>And then on Saturday afternoon, days before anyone expected it to happen, the world's largest and perhaps rarest flowering plant, the Amorphophallus titanum, began to bloom.</p>
        <p>In botanical terms, this is not unlike the birth of a giant panda at the National Zoo. Only six times in history, including once last month at the Fairchild Tropical Garden in Miami, has the plant flowered in cultivation in this country. And the curators here believe that none of the previous phallus-shaped plants has matched the 6-foot-2-inch heighth of this one.</p>
        <p>That explains why officials at the botanical garden here plan to lord it over their competitors by printing T-shirts proclaiming, ''Our Amorphophallus is way bigger than yours.'' Horticultural humor.</p>
        <p>Size, of course, is not everything. And with the Amorphophallus titanum, a native of Sumatra that is also known as the titan arum, it is the stench that counts as well.</p>
        <p>Upon blooming, the flower emits an odor that is most frequently compared to that of rotting flesh, all in a ploy to convince beetles and flies that the plant is carrion. Once lured to the titan arum, the bugs pick up pollen and transport it to other flowers. Not for nothing is the plant known in Sumatra as bunga bangui, or corpse flower.</p>
        <p>''When I came in yesterday it smelled like a cross between a dead animal and a rotting pumpkin,'' said Ron Gagliardo, the botanical garden's curator of tropical plants and the man who nurtured the titan arum from a seedling with a diet of bone meal and chicken manure. ''You get used to it, but in the first few minutes it was a little nauseating even for me.''</p>
        <p>The smell today, while noticeable, was far from repugnant, at least partly because the conservatory was ventilated with a constant flow of cooled air. Carolyn White, a security guard, did her best to console those who seemed disappointed that the smell was bearable. ''It was really bad yesterday,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The botanical garden is normally closed on Mondays, but opened today so that visitors could view the titan arum before the flower curled and shed, a process that is usually completed only two or three days after the blooming begins. As parents lined their children in front of the plant, the youngsters pinched their nostrils with their fingers and made disgusting gagging sounds.</p>
        <p>Many visitors noted that in an era when the other side of the planet is only a Web site away, it was refreshing to be astounded by a work of nature. ''There's so much in the world that we're unaware of,'' said Sister Marian, 49, a bespectacled Dominican nun who carried a Canon camera. ''How many times in your lifetime do you get to see something like this?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gagliardo, who was certain that his ward would not bloom until Wednesday or Thursday, was visiting friends in Denver, some 1,200 miles away, when he received the blessed news in a telephone call on Saturday night. Like a father absent for the birth of his child, he sped to the Denver airport early Sunday morning and talked his way on to a crowded flight.</p>
        <p>''I went up to the desk and showed them a picture and said, 'Have you ever seen this plant?' '' the 33-year-old Mr. Gagliardo recounted. ''They said, 'Why are you showing us this?' And I said, 'Because it's my plant and it's blooming and I've got to get back to Atlanta'. ''</p>
        <p>Technically, the Amorphophallus titanum is a compound flower with a series of small flowers hidden within a vast vase-like spathe. The grayish spadix shoots skyward from the base of the spathe.</p>
        <p>At any rate, the Amorphophallus titanum is larger than the largest single flower, the Rafflesia arnoldii, also from Sumatra. And its mystique is only enhanced by the difficulty of its cultivation, the unpredictability of its flowering, and the remarkable speed of its growth. Since the bud of the Atlanta plant emerged from the soil on June 12, it has grown an average of five to six inches a day.</p>
        <p>While pleased with today's show, officials at the botanical garden were disappointed that they were not able to artificially pollinate the plant, an unprecedented feat. Officials at the Fairchild garden in Miami collected pollen from their plant last month and supposedly sent it to Atlanta, but it never arrived. ''The pollen,'' Mr. Gagliardo said dejectedly, ''seems to be lost in the mail.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
