<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan Would Revise Farm Subsidies</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE BUDGET BATTLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CROP CONTROLS AND SUBSIDIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crop Controls and Subsidies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D71130F934A25753C1A966958260" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan Would Revise Farm Subsidies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: House and Senate conferees reached agreement today on a $41 billion, five-year farm policy that changes the structure of commodity price supports and includes the strongest environmental provisions of any farm legislation in history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: House and Senate conferees reached agreement today on a $41 billion, five-year farm policy that changes the structure of commodity price supports and includes the strongest environmental provisions of any farm legislation in history.</p>
        <p>House and Senate conferees reached agreement today on a $41 billion, five-year farm policy that changes the structure of commodity price supports and includes the strongest environmental provisions of any farm legislation in history.</p>
        <p>The changes in rules that have provided subsidies to producers of grain, cotton, rice and other commodities for more than five decades are intended to save the Government $13.6 billion over the next five fiscal years.</p>
        <p>The conferees estimated that, at $41 billion, farm program spending from fiscal 1991 through fiscal 1995 would cost slightly more each year than the $7.8 billion that was spent in fiscal 1990. Before the agreed changes, conferees estimated that the five-year cost of the bill would be $54 billion to $56 billion.</p>
        <p>New Course for Agriculture</p>
        <p>Over the long-term, experts in both parties said, the broad package of economic, scientific and environmental provisions agreed to today is intended to set a new course for American agriculture, making the farm sector less costly to the Government and less threatening to the environment.</p>
        <p>The agreement on programs to protect the environment come after both committees for decades rejected the notion that farm chemicals needed to be closely regulated to reduce contamination.</p>
        <p>Edward Madigan, Republican of Illinois and the ranking minority member of the House Agriculture Committee, said today that the provisions had been adopted by the House committee to head off even more stringent regulations that were being proposed.</p>
        <p>The legislation is expected to be considered and approved later this week or early next week by both houses of Congress and signed by President Bush. ''It is a respectable work product that balances well inumerable sensitive, often divergent, interests,'' Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter said today.</p>
        <p>The most significant change was introduced late last week to respond to the demand by Congressional leaders that farm program spending be cut by more than 25 percent to reduce the Federal deficit. The conferees said they met the demand by agreeing to change the structure of the price support programs.</p>
        <p>Decades of Control</p>
        <p>Since the program was established in the 1930's, the supply of grain, cotton, rice and other commodities has been controlled by the Government through contracts with hundreds of thousands of farmers.</p>
        <p>In exchange for letting a specified amount of land lay fallow each year, typically 5 percent to 15 percent of their tillable land, farmers who signed up for the program are paid for every bushel of grain, bale of cotton or pound of rice they produce. Under the new bill, the amount of land on which farmers can grow crops eligible for payments would be reduced by 15 percent.</p>
        <p>The conferees also agreed to set a limit of $100,000 on payments to any farmer.</p>
        <p>According to an analysis by an economist at Oklahoma State University, a farmer who has a 1,000-acre wheat farm in Kansas could lose nearly $13,000 as a result of the change.</p>
        <p>The reduction in the amount of a farmer's harvest that is eligible for Government support, together with the $100,000 limit on payments, opens the commodity price support programs more than ever before to market forces.</p>
        <p>Some Might Drop Out</p>
        <p>Experts in both parties said today that under the proposed new program, farmers might be eligible in some years to grow crops that receive Government payments on just 70 percent of their land. If market prices are high enough, thousands might drop out of the program, they said. If farmers abandoned the program, Congressional support could diminish and lead to more substantial structural changes, even elimination of the programs as early as 1995.</p>
        <p>''You have a farm bill where farmers now can make a real choice about whether to farm on the program or off,'' said Senator Patrick J. Leahy, a Democrat of Vermont and chairman of the conference committee. ''In the past, you really didn't have a choice. The programs were the only game in town.''</p>
        <p>Several conferees said that they were anxious about the rule changes and that they might vote against the final bill. ''It will cause in the short-term a reduction in net farm incomes at a time when costs are up. It's going to squeeze cash,'' said Senator Bob Kerrey, a Democrat of Nebraska. ''It's going to have a negative impact and it's apt to be felt the worst in the Great Plains because it's drier and farmers don't have the same options'' as farmers in other parts of the country.</p>
        <p>Several farm groups said today they were very unhappy with the proposed reduction in harvests that are eligible for payments. They also criticized fees that producers of milk, sugar, tobacco, peanuts, honey and wool are expected to pay when they market their crops in a new plan expected to raise $1 billion or more.</p>
        <p>''Congress has gone tax crazy,'' said Wayne Cryts, a spokesman in Missouri for the American Agriculture Movement, one of the nation's largest farm groups. ''It is our opinion that we have enough tax writing committees in Washington, but it appears now that we have two more in the Senate and House Ag committees.''</p>
        <p>New Enrivonmental Provisions</p>
        <p>The 1990 farm policy law also contains an array of new provisions that the conferees believe will make farming less polluting and result in safer food for consumers.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most significant is a ten-fold increase in the amount of money that Congress wants the Department of Agriculture to spend on research into cultivation practices that use little or no toxic chemicals. The department spent $5 million in fiscal 1990 to develop such practices; the conferees authorized the department to spend $80 million a year.</p>
        <p>The conferees also established rules that require farmers to keep records on how they use 125 toxic pesticides. The records could be reviewed by the department for studies on pesticide use across the United States and must be made available for review by medical specialists in the investigation of poisoning accidents.</p>
        <p>One provision sought by environmental groups to bar the export of pesticides outlawed for use in the United States was dropped from the bill after the White House, the Environmental Protection Agency and the Department of Agriculture agreed with the pesticide industry that it was unnecessary and would cost hundreds of jobs.</p>
        <p>THE BUDGET BATTLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
