<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hackett Stars in Goal; Sutter Sparks Offense</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK ISLANDERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WINNIPEG JETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DB1E39F934A25753C1A966958260" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hackett Stars in Goal; Sutter Sparks Offense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I., Oct. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The struggling Islanders played like world-beaters tonight. The struggling Winnipeg Jets played as if they would rather be watching the World Series on television. The result was a 4-1 Islander victory that featured notable performances by several members of the home team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The struggling Islanders played like world-beaters tonight. The struggling Winnipeg Jets played as if they would rather be watching the World Series on television. The result was a 4-1 Islander victory that featured notable performances by several members of the home team.</p>
        <p>The struggling Islanders played like world-beaters tonight. The struggling Winnipeg Jets played as if they would rather be watching the World Series on television. The result was a 4-1 Islander victory that featured notable performances by several members of the home team.</p>
        <p>Greg Parks, called up from the minor leagues to replace the injured Pat LaFontaine, scored his first National Hockey League goal in his first N.H.L. game. Jeff Hackett, the Islanders' rookie goalie, made 41 saves, almost had his first N.H.L. shutout and heard the sparse gathering of fans at the Nassau Coliseum chanting his name even after he gave up a late goal.</p>
        <p>And Brent Sutter, the veteran captain, scored twice for the Islanders, who dominated in all phases of the game despite the absence of seven regular players.</p>
        <p>''It's something you dream about since you were knee high,'' said Parks, who joined the Islander organization as a free agent. ''Just to get in a game.''</p>
        <p>Rebound Ruins Shutout</p>
        <p>Hackett is now the team's first-string goalie because Mark Fitzpatrick and Glenn Healy are out with illness and injury, respectively. His shutout was spoiled at 16 minutes 20 seconds of the third period when Thomas Steen beat him on a rebound.</p>
        <p>''Of course I was thinking about it, I'd be lying if I said I wasn't,'' Hackett said of the shutout bid. He has started two games and won them both. The other was a 4-2 victory at Chicago.</p>
        <p>Among the Islanders' top performers was Randy Wood, who had five shots on goal but failed on one breakaway and fired high and wide on another setup directly in front.</p>
        <p>''We'll have to get him a wider stick,'' said Al Arbour, the coach, ''or a small shovel.''</p>
        <p>Arbour was beaming because, he said, his team - now 2-3 for the season - had ''no passengers'' tonight. The same couldn't be said for the Jets.</p>
        <p>''I don't know how you can go four games without a win and not have the proper frame of mind,'' said Bob Murdoch, the Winnipeg coach.</p>
        <p>The Jets came into the season with high expectations after finishing third in the Smythe Division last season with 85 points and extending the Edmonton Oilers, the eventual Stanley Cup champions, to seven games in the first round of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Winnipeg is said to be led by a Fab Four defensive group made up of Dave Ellett, Fredrik Olausson, Phil Housley and Teppo Numminen. But they looked like a Drab Four tonight as the Jets fell behind, 3-0, after one period, stayed behind by the same margain after two and saw the deficit increase early in the third. The Jets' record is 1-5-1, good for last place in the Smythe. ''We have not had a good work ethic and a total team effort,'' said Genral Manager Mike Smith before the game. ''We have shown no discipline. I'm not sure what the trouble is. A number of players are off to horrible starts.''</p>
        <p>The Jets, rarely a good draw on the road, attracted only 9,805 tonight to the Coliseum, whose official capacity is 16,297. Winnipeg is scheduled to face the Rangers Wednesday night at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Rough Season Debut</p>
        <p>Bob Essensa, Winnipeg's starting goalie, was making his first N.H.L. appearance of the season after suffering a groin injury in training camp and playing briefly in the minor leagues. Essensa gave up the first three goals and was removed at the first intermission in favor of Richard Tabaracci.</p>
        <p>The Islanders opened the scoring at 8:11 on Derek King's second goal of the season. It came moments after the Islanders had killed the second of two penalties that overlapped for 32 seconds. King stole the puck, worked a passing combination with Sutter and shot low from the circle to the right of the goalie.</p>
        <p>They went up, 2-0, at 15:02 when Sutter rebounded Wood's shot for his first goal of the game and they built the lead to 3-0 at 16:07 when Parks took a feed from David Volek and got two swipes at the puck from the edge of the crease.</p>
        <p>Sutter made it 4-0 in the first minute of the third period by racing down the left side and firing a low slap shot shortly after crossing the blue line.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
