<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sandra Auerback, Victor Scheinman</title>
    <meta content="06auerback" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/06/fashion/weddings/06auerback.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1781070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Auerback, Sandra Jean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scheinman, Victor David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E0DA113FF935A3575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="438" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sandra Auerback, Victor Scheinman</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sandra Auerback and Victor Scheinman</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sandra Jean Auerback and Victor David Scheinman were married last evening. Rabbi Mikki Bourne officiated at the Stanford Faculty Club.</p>
        <p>Ms. Auerback, 60, is keeping her name. She is a clinical social worker who has a psychotherapy practice in San Francisco. She graduated from the University of California, Berkeley, and received a master's degree in social work from Hunter College.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The couple were married Saturday evening at the Stanford Faculty Club.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sandra Jean Auerback and Victor David Scheinman were married last evening. Rabbi Mikki Bourne officiated at the Stanford Faculty Club.</p>
        <p>Ms. Auerback, 60, is keeping her name. She is a clinical social worker who has a psychotherapy practice in San Francisco. She graduated from the University of California, Berkeley, and received a master's degree in social work from Hunter College.</p>
        <p>She is a daughter of the late Molly Auerback and Dr. Alfred Auerback, who lived in San Francisco. Her father was a psychiatrist with a private practice in San Francisco, where her mother worked as a registered nurse.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scheinman, 63, is a consulting professor of mechanical engineering at Stanford. He developed the original commercial robot, the programmable universal machine for assembly, known as PUMA, and was a founder of Automatix, a maker of robotic automation and artificial-vision systems that was in Billerica, Mass. He graduated from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and received a master's degree in mechanical engineering and a graduate engineer's degree from Stanford.</p>
        <p>He is a son of the late Sera Scheinman and Dr. Leonard Scheinman, who lived in Riverdale, the Bronx. His mother was a Hebrew teacher at the Riverdale Temple religious school. His father was a clinical professor of psychiatry and neurology at Columbia and had a private psychiatry practice in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Ms. Auerback and Mr. Scheinman, who were both divorced, met in December 1989 at a singles party sponsored by Stanford Bachelors, a group of university alumni.</p>
        <p>Each was fascinated to find out that the other's father was a psychiatrist, and they became so engrossed in conversation that they didn't notice the party was ending until the coat-check attendant, wanting to go home, interrupted them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Auerback remembers saying: ''This has been really great. We'll have to get together sometime.'' His response was not what she expected. ''He said he'd have to think about it.''</p>
        <p>''Stanford bachelors are in high demand,'' Mr. Scheinman said with a laugh, recalling that evening. ''Can't be too easy.''</p>
        <p>That wasn't the reason he had initially given her, though. ''He said I lived too far away,'' Ms. Auerback said.</p>
        <p>''I used to say I didn't want to drive more than 15 minutes to see a woman,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>Ms. Auerback was 40 minutes away. ''So he had to think about it,'' she said. ''He's a ponderer.''</p>
        <p>He called her the next day.</p>
        <p>Last February, when Ms. Auerback's birthday neared, she made a suggestion. ''Instead of having a 60th birthday party,'' she asked, ''why don't we get married and have a wedding party?''</p>
        <p>His response: ''Why not?''</p>
        <p>''You're talking to an engineer,'' he added, ''not a romanticist.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
