<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reorganizing the Yankees;   Vincent Directive and Steinbrenner Response</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="372979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAJOR LEAGUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VINCENT, FAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINBRENNER, GEORGE M 3D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD103CF932A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="1408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reorganizing the Yankees;   Vincent Directive and Steinbrenner Response</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Following are excerpts from the documents released by Commissioner Fay Vincent yesterday and the four-paragraph statement issued by George Steinbrenner.</p>
        <p>Agreement And Resolution</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Following are excerpts from the documents released by Commissioner Fay Vincent yesterday and the four-paragraph statement issued by George Steinbrenner.</p>
        <p>Agreement And Resolution</p>
        <p>Following are excerpts from the documents released by Commissioner Fay Vincent yesterday and the four-paragraph statement issued by George Steinbrenner.</p>
        <p>Agreement And Resolution</p>
        <p>The Commissioner, recognizing the benefits to Baseball from a resolution of this matter, orders and directs that Mr. Steinbrenner be subject to the following sanctions, and Mr. Steinbrenner, recognizing the sole and exclusive authority of the Commissioner and recognizing the benefits to Baseball from a resolution of this matter without further proceedings, agrees to accept the following sanctions imposed by the Commissioner:</p>
        <p>Mr. Steinbrenner recognizes, agrees and submits to the sole and exclusive jurisdiction of the Commissioner. . . .</p>
        <p>Mr. Steinbrenner acknowledges and accepts the findings of the Decision to which this Agreement is attached and, specifically, that his conduct as described in the Decision was not in the best interests of Baseball. Mr. Steinbrenner further accepts the sanctions imposed on him by the Commissioner and agrees not to challenge the sanctions in court or otherwise. . . .</p>
        <p>On or before August 20, 1990, Mr. Steinbrenner will resign as General Partner of the New York Yankees; within twelve months after that date, he will reduce his ownership interest to less than 50 percent. . . .The Commissioner will approve any transfer to any member of the Steinbrenner family.</p>
        <p>On or before August 20, 1990, consistent with the terms of the New York Yankees Partnership Limited Partnership Agreement and subject to the subsequent approval of the Major League Clubs, a new General Partner will be appointed for the New York Yankees. The Commissioner will approve the appointment of either of Mr. Steinbrenner's sons as general partner.</p>
        <p>Bound by the Order</p>
        <p>Any of Mr. Steinbrenner's family members who become involved in the operations of the New York Yankees or become a General Partner of the New York Yankees shall be bound by the terms of the Supplemental Order governing the conduct of New York Yankees officials, which is attached hereto and incorporated herein by reference.</p>
        <p>Effective August 20, 1990, Mr. Steinbrenner will be treated, for all purposes, as if he were on the Ineligible List (although he will not actually be placed on the Ineligible List). Accordingly, until further notice from the Commissioner, Mr. Steinbrenner shall not (a) visit or be physically present in the clubhouse, offices, owners box, or press box at Yankee Stadium or the Yankees' spring training facility, or any other area not generally open to the public at either location, without the prior approval of the Commissioner, or the clubhouse, offices or press box at any other Major League Club; or (b) associate or communicate with any Major League Club (including the New York Yankees) or its personnel or any person having business or financial dealings with the New York Yankees, in connection with any matter involving the New York Yankees or Baseball.</p>
        <p>Written Request Needed</p>
        <p>It is recognized that circumstances may arise involving material and extraordinary financial or business affairs of the New York Yankees in which Mr. Steinbrenner may feel his participation is necessary. On these occasions, a written request may be submitted to the Commissioner seeking permission for Mr. Steinbrenner to attend business meetings or otherwise communicate regarding financial or business matters affecting the Club. Unless and until such permission is granted by the Commissioner, Mr. Steinbrenner shall not attend such a meeting or otherwise become involved in such matters. . . .</p>
        <p>With respect to any request pursuant to the preceding paragraph, if the matter involved falls within any of the four categories enumerated below, then the Commissioner shall approve such request: (i) negotiations or disputes concerning television or radio contracts; (ii) negotiations or disputes concerning concession agreements; (iii) governmental negotiations or agreements, including lease agreements; or (iv) banking relationships, including financial arrangements.</p>
        <p>It is clearly understood by Mr. Steinbrenner and all Yankees officials that it is the intention of the Commissioner to monitor closely their behavior to insure full compliance with this Agreement. Any noncompliance with this Agreement by Mr. Steinbrenner shall be deemed conduct not in the best interests of Baseball and shall subject Mr. Steinbrenner to further discipline, up to and including permanent placement on the Ineligible List.</p>
        <p>Supplemental Order</p>
        <p>The conduct which gave rise to my Decision of July 30, 1990 and the accompanying Agreement and Resolution bearing the same date also raised issues with regard to certain practices of the New York Yankees. To address these issues, and to further implement my Decision, I am hereby imposing the following restrictions on the New York Yankees and all officials of the Club, pursuant to the Commissioner's power under the Major League Agreement. 1. Except as otherwise provided for in the Agreement and Resolution to which this Supplemental Order is attached, no Yankee officials or employees shall confer, consult, advise or otherwise communicate, either directly or indirectly, with George M. Steinbrenner III on any matter involving the New York Yankees or Baseball until further order of the Commissioner. If such communication, either direct or indirect, occurs, a responsible Club official shall immediately notify the American League President. Furthermore, six months from the date hereof and each six months thereafter, a responsible Club official, after making reasonable inquiry of other Club officials and employees, shall certify in writing to the American League President that no such communications occurred during the preceding six months period, or if such communications did occur, shall fully disclose all details. 2. The New York Yankees, and all officials of the Club, shall not conduct any investigation of allegations involving any Major League player or Club employee regarding any matter without adhering to the following procedure: any such allegations coming to the attention of Club officials, and which those officials believe may warrant further investigation, shall promptly be reported to the Director of Security in the Commissioner's Office, who shall advise the Club as to the extent to which the Yankees may conduct further investigation into the matter, if at all. 3. For the period of 5 years, the following actions by the New York Yankees shall not be undertaken without prior notice to, and approval of, the American League President, which approval shall not be unreasonably withheld: a. The hiring, firing, promotion, demotion or reassignment of any officer of the Club. b. The assertion of any claims in court litigation or arbitration proceedings against a Major League player (other than a salary arbitration pursuant to the Basic Agreement). c. The retention of outside counsel or private investigators in connection with any matter relating to a Major League player. In this regard, under no circumstances shall Philip McNiff perform any services for, or maintain any contact with, the Yankees, or any employee of the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Statement By Steinbrenner</p>
        <p>As I said yesterday, I have no comment on the Commissioner's decision. I am, however, satisfied with the resolution of the matter.</p>
        <p>For some years now I have been preparing to turn over the operation of the Yankees to my sons and sons-in-law. My son Hank, subject to league approvals, will become general partner at this time.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, I may be involved in material and extraordinary financial or business affairs of the team. In addition, I will be involved in negotiations in matters concerning radio-TV agreements, concessions agreements, governmental, state/ city agreements and all banking relationships. These are the areas which I feel require my attention.</p>
        <p>As for the baseball side, after 17 years, 14 of which were winning seasons, I think it's time to turn that over to the young blood in the family. We are presently blessed with an awful lot of fine young ballplayers joining the team and it's exciting to watch them. The future appears bright and it seems an appropriate time for change. I have no desire to return as general partner. That will rest with my sons. I have other endeavors which I plan to devote most of my available time to now, which are very important to me.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
