<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Job Losses Continued In October</title>
    <meta content="Y02ECO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/02/business/02ECON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1436940"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E7DC163EF931A35752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1321" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Job Losses Continued In October</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Job Losses Continued in October</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The economy lost jobs in October for the second consecutive month, the government said yesterday, in a sign that economic growth, after accelerating over the summer, has recently slowed to a crawl.</p>
        <p>The unemployment rate rose slightly last month to 5.7 percent, and the nation's payrolls shrunk by 5,000 jobs, largely because of layoffs in manufacturing and construction. Companies also cut their workers' hours for the first time since July, suggesting that large-scale hiring is unlikely in the immediate future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The economy lost jobs in October for the second straight month in a sign that economic growth, after accelerating over the summer, has now slowed to a crawl.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The economy lost jobs in October for the second consecutive month, the government said yesterday, in a sign that economic growth, after accelerating over the summer, has recently slowed to a crawl.</p>
        <p>The unemployment rate rose slightly last month to 5.7 percent, and the nation's payrolls shrunk by 5,000 jobs, largely because of layoffs in manufacturing and construction. Companies also cut their workers' hours for the first time since July, suggesting that large-scale hiring is unlikely in the immediate future.</p>
        <p>The report, released just days before the midterm election, provided evidence of the worst job losses in the economy during a two-year Congressional cycle since 1981-82, when Republicans lost ground on Capitol Hill two years after the Reagan landslide.</p>
        <p>Coming after several weeks of discouraging economic signs, the Labor Department report also led most economists to predict that the Federal Reserve would cut its benchmark interest rate when it meets on Wednesday, probably by a quarter point but perhaps by as much as a half percentage point.</p>
        <p>Last year, the Fed reduced the rate -- currently at 1.75 percent -- 11 times to lower the cost of borrowing and encourage new spending by businesses and consumers. The Fed has kept the rate steady this year in the hope, now fading, that the economy was solidly recovering from last year's recession.</p>
        <p>Hoping to make the kind of gains opposition parties often do during economic slowdowns, Democrats used yesterday's report to criticize President Bush's economic leadership. Republicans responded that they could best improve job growth by capturing control of the Senate as well as the House, enabling them to pass a new round of tax cuts.</p>
        <p>With terrorism and a possible war in Iraq occupying much of the political debate, however, the economy might not prove to be as important an issue as it has in the past, members of both parties said.</p>
        <p>''It hasn't gotten to that kind of red-hot issue yet, but the mood is one of foreboding,'' said Senator Jack Reed, Democrat of Rhode Island.</p>
        <p>R. Glenn Hubbard, a top economic adviser to Mr. Bush, commented: ''Things aren't getting worse, but they aren't getting noticeably better.''</p>
        <p>Adding to the concerns, weekly earnings fell in October for the first time since July and only the second time in the last year. Consumer spending already dropped 0.4 percent in September, the Commerce Department said yesterday, and many companies, worried that spending may slow further, have cut production recently.</p>
        <p>Last month, manufacturers eliminated 49,000 jobs, the 27th straight monthly cut by the sector, which now employs fewer workers than it has at any point since 1961. Reinforcing a sense that the industrial sector is suffering more than it was during the summer, a survey of supply-chain managers released yesterday indicated that manufacturing activity fell in October for the second month in a row.</p>
        <p>''The economy has lost considerable momentum,'' said Chris Varvares, president of Macroeconomic Advisers, a forecasting firm in St. Louis. ''It's clearly taking longer for it to rebound than a lot of people had thought initially.''</p>
        <p>Still, the addition of 70,000 workers across the broad service sector last month helped keep the nation's payrolls nearly flat and suggested that the economy, while weak, did not appear headed for a new recession. Hospitals, hotels, law firms, mortgage brokers and restaurants all added workers in October, the Labor Department said. Government agencies helped, too, adding 24,000 employees.</p>
        <p>Also, the Labor Department's regular data revisions showed that the economy had created more jobs in August and eliminated fewer in September than previously reported.</p>
        <p>''It's still hard to find jobs,'' said Richard D. Rippe, the chief economist at Prudential Securities, ''but we haven't seen a collapse in the labor market.''</p>
        <p>Stocks rose yesterday, with the Dow Jones industrial average up more than 120 points, or 1.44 percent, to close at 8,517.64. Investors seemed to take the poor job performance and the rise in the jobless rate, which had been 5.6 percent in September, as an indication that the economy was weak enough to encourage the Fed to reduce interest rates, but not so weak as to harm corporate profits severely.</p>
        <p>Some analysts argue that the Fed should act more aggressively and cut rates by a half-point next week, rather than taking small steps that might fail to jump-start the economy. Alan Greenspan, the Fed chairman, and many of his colleagues have been reluctant to act again, believing that last year's cuts will continue to help growth in coming months.</p>
        <p>Since the beginning of last year, the economy has lost 1.7 million jobs, or about 1 percent of the nation's total, according to the Labor Department. In the last 60 years, only the Congressional elections of 1954, 1958 and 1982 came after a two-year period with larger job losses, relative to the size of the labor force.</p>
        <p>Those three elections happened in the middle of a Republican president's term, as is the case this year, and Democrats gained even more seats in those elections than is typical for the opposition party in a midterm election.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's jobs report offered them one more opportunity to fault Mr. Bush for this job downturn.</p>
        <p>''The administration tends to ignore these economic issues,'' said Mr. Reed, the senior Democrat on the Joint Economic Committee. ''The same effort and imagination he applies to other areas should be applied to the economy.''</p>
        <p>Representative John M. Spratt Jr., Democrat of South Carolina, said the party would extend unemployment insurance and consider cutting taxes and increasing public works spending if it gained control of the House and kept control of the Senate. Most Republicans oppose new spending, including the extension of jobless benefits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hubbard said the president was responsible for the two most significant pieces of economic legislation during the last two years: last year's tax cut and the stimulus package early this year. A Republican-controlled Congress could create jobs by passing more tax cuts and a terrorism-insurance bill, he said.</p>
        <p>Either way, however, ''we are in for a bumpy next few months,'' Mr. Hubbard said.</p>
        <p>Beyond the overall numbers, the jobs report was filled with evidence of the economy's deterioration since the summer.</p>
        <p>The average weekly earnings of hourly workers, who make up about 80 percent of the work force, fell 46 cents, to $507.75, according to the Labor Department, which adjusts the numbers to account for normal seasonal variations. The number of people who said they could find only part-time work increased to 4.3 million, from 3.9 million in June. More of the unemployed last month were people who had lost their jobs, and fewer were people entering the labor force.</p>
        <p>Employment at temporary-help firms also fell by 56,000, the biggest drop in a year. Before companies begin hiring large numbers of permanent workers, they often add to their temporary work force.</p>
        <p>''There's no indication the economy is getting liftoff speed,'' said Edward F. McKelvey, a senior economist at Goldman, Sachs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
