<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Radio Stations Enjoy Rising Ratings as Music Purists Fume</title>
    <meta content="05LITE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Jazz Is 'Lite,' the Profits Heavy" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="934770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="The Jazz Is 'Lite,' the Profits Heavy"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watrous, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EFD8103DF936A35755C0A961958260" item-length="1852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Radio Stations Enjoy Rising Ratings as Music Purists Fume</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER WATROUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Watrous, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some of fastest-growing radio stations in country have adopted format usually referred to as 'smooth jazz'; it is mostly instrumental, mostly polite, geared for people who do not like rap or contemporary pop; critics condemn it as 'easy listening' music, but it is attracting kinds of listeners that advertisers want to reach: between ages of 35 and 50, and with disposable incomes; fans of this music suggest that class, education and affluence are powerful bonds that can transcend racial boundaries; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The music is mostly instrumental, and mostly polite. It is often music for people who don't like rap or contemporary pop. It is the music of solid citizens, most of them between the ages of 35 and 50, people with disposable income who are tired of listening to oldies. It gets solid boos from critics, who condemn it as ''easy listening'' or ''lite jazz,'' music for people who like the idea of jazz but don't really like jazz. They may be black or white, women or men: the radio format is almost astonishingly democratic.</p>
        <p>As a result, the 160 radio stations around the country that have adopted the format, usually referred to as ''smooth jazz,'' include some of the fastest-growing in the business. One such station, WQCD (101.9 FM) in New York City -- the one that calls itself CD 101 and runs the advertising campaign promising ''the smoothest place on earth'' -- is being bought by Emmis Broadcasting for some $160 million, a figure that raised eyebrows in the radio industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The music is mostly instrumental, and mostly polite. It is often music for people who don't like rap or contemporary pop. It is the music of solid citizens, most of them between the ages of 35 and 50, people with disposable income who are tired of listening to oldies. It gets solid boos from critics, who condemn it as ''easy listening'' or ''lite jazz,'' music for people who like the idea of jazz but don't really like jazz. They may be black or white, women or men: the radio format is almost astonishingly democratic.</p>
        <p>As a result, the 160 radio stations around the country that have adopted the format, usually referred to as ''smooth jazz,'' include some of the fastest-growing in the business. One such station, WQCD (101.9 FM) in New York City -- the one that calls itself CD 101 and runs the advertising campaign promising ''the smoothest place on earth'' -- is being bought by Emmis Broadcasting for some $160 million, a figure that raised eyebrows in the radio industry.</p>
        <p>Advertisers, no fools, are listening, too. They realize that this audience has big money. But that audience also suggests that the radio format, in its search for the largest possible base to sell advertising, is creating an unlikely constituency. A recent sold-out concert at Carnegie Hall supported by CD 101 and featuring the singer Diane Reeves and the saxophonist Gerald Albright was surprisingly interracial, even in a city where races mingle more freely than in many other parts of the country.</p>
        <p>If music is always identity, then the concert and the music being sold suggested that class, education and affluence are powerful bonds that can create subcultures that move beyond racial boundaries. The style is the musical version of ''Oprah,'' beyond ethnicity.</p>
        <p>''It's rare to find a format that's even slightly multiethnic,'' said Pierre Bouvard, the general manager of Arbitron, the radio rating service.</p>
        <p>Smooth jazz stations have figured out the demographic complexities of each city, tailoring what they play to draw as many people as possible. And performers like the saxophonist Kenny G and the singers Luther Vandross and Anita Baker make music that appeals across traditional race, age and gender lines.</p>
        <p>''This is one of the success stories of the 1990's,'' Mr. Bouvard said. ''As you look at the adult demographic, between the age of 25 and 54, the age group that has money and spends it, it is performing very, very well. And between the ages of 35 and 64, it's often the leading station in an area.''</p>
        <p>The national statistics chatter about money. Forty-two percent of the listening households have an income above $50,000, a rate 26 percent higher than the national average. Some 2 percent drive BMW's, 78 percent higher than the average, while only 22 percent own Chevrolets, 15 percent lower than the average. People who listen to the music like to drink Beck's and alcohol-free beer. And they like sparkling water. The top 50 smooth jazz stations have projected combined advertising revenues of $190 million this year.</p>
        <p>Moving Into The Daylight</p>
        <p>All this began in the early 80's in California -- where else? -- with stations in Los Angeles and San Diego that had gone broke playing something else. At KIFM (98.1) in San Diego, the smooth jazz, which at the time was the mixture of jazz and rock called fusion, was being played from 10 P.M. to midnight. But the listener response was exceptional, and it was moved to daytime.</p>
        <p>In its own quiet way, the new format was mildly experimental. It mixed instrumental music, by people like the guitarists George Benson and Pat Metheny and the saxophonist Grover Washington Jr. with vocalists like Sade, Luther Vandross or Vanessa Williams, and finally, the innocuousness of New Age music.</p>
        <p>''It really took off,'' said Bob O'Conner, a consultant who was the programmer at KIFM at the time. ''It was sexy music, and spiritual, and it spread by word of mouth. Remember that it was really free-form radio, with a lot of freedom and not much pressure on the D.J.'s. It was adult music for adults who were smart, and the word got around, and finally we moved it to the daytime.''</p>
        <p>For the last decade the format, octupus-like, has been reaching out and stealing listeners. Programmers have been looking beyond instrumental pop and adjusting their play lists to fit local tastes. In New York that means touches of rhythm and blues; on the West Coast, the New Age guitarist Ottmar Liebert still shows up a bit. (Serious jazz has no commercial radio outlet anywhere in the country; its devotees turn instead to public radio and college stations.)</p>
        <p>Though smooth jazz has become a fixed format, it is still one of the most flexible in commercial radio. Some critics take this to mean that there is no center or character to it.</p>
        <p>In cities like New York and Chicago, with larger black populations, the stations program more black vocal pop, pulling audiences away from stations that play rap. On the West Coast, New Age and even Hispanic-influenced music lure listeners away from their niche radio stations.</p>
        <p>''I think the plate just gets bigger and bigger for us,'' said Steve Williams, the program director for CD 101 in New York. ''We know that our listeners appreciate pop and jazz, but just like anything else, the rock-dog listener of the 70's -- they're 40 now -- they're listening to Kenny G or David Sanborn. It's their life style. They're not going out to hear Rod Stewart. But they are interested in hearing things they've never heard before.''</p>
        <p>One Career Revitalized</p>
        <p>Peter White, a guitarist who is having big success in smooth jazz, mimics the audience. He spent a decade with the rock singer Al Stewart, then worked for several years with the pop singer Basia.</p>
        <p>''Rock, which is the music I grew up playing, just became tiring,'' said Mr. White. ''In the late 1980's, I listened to the Wave, the smooth jazz station in Los Angeles, and I heard all these guitarists playing melodic pop, and I knew I could do that. So I've started a new career, and at 42 I feel completely revitalized. And my audience, which is my age and tired of the same 20-year-old rock singers singing about how much they hate their parents, is coming along for the ride. It's great.''</p>
        <p>And members of that audience are active record buyers. The baby boomers' experience is one of an affiliation to music; loyalties change, but the instinct to find new music has not.</p>
        <p>''Advertisers love this demographic because the audience is willing to spend money,'' said Frank Cody, the general manager of Broadcast Architecture, a consulting company for the format, and a man widely considered be its father for helping to introduce it in Los Angeles at KTWV (94.7), called the Wave. ''They have sophisticated, really high-end stereo systems, and they'll go into a record store with a long list of things they heard on the radio or read about and walk out with a stack of 10 CD's every month. Kids can't afford that.''</p>
        <p>For Kevin Gore, who runs the jazz marketing department for Columbia Records, smooth jazz is shaping how companies are acting.</p>
        <p>''We're very happy about the success of our smooth jazz artists,'' he said. ''If an average jazz album sells around 5,000 copies, a smooth jazz artist will be selling 125,000. So the signing and release of a new record by Gato Barbieri for us means big business.''</p>
        <p>''Que Pasa,'' Mr. Barbieri's first release in nearly 20 years, fits right into the smooth jazz format but is a long way from his roots as an avant-garde saxophonist. The recording has been greeted with general euphoria in smooth jazz circles, partly because it brings a distinctive personality and pedigree to an idiom that is seen, even by its fans, as being devoid of personalities.</p>
        <p>That lack of a distinctive sound plagues programmers, who concede that listeners often don't know what they're listening to. So the programmers have begun to institute pop-radio-style play lists, in which certain songs are repeated more often than others. And they have run tests to judge the reactions to individual tracks. Broadcast Architecture brings in an auditorium full of listeners who rate the desirability of new material on the basis of 7- to 15-second bursts of a tune.</p>
        <p>''The main problem with smooth jazz radio was that it traditionally played too many different songs, so the listener identification of material wasn't high,'' said Mr. Cody. ''By doing tests, we've been able to find out what listeners want, and by playing the songs in heavier rotation, the songs get noticed.''</p>
        <p>To devotees, smooth jazz is considered a step up in sophistication from pop music. But the lack of definition in the sound opens it up to attack by critics and serious jazz fans. Smooth jazz programmers say they see themselves as crusaders, softening up the defenses of listeners who do not necessarily like jazz. Some stations throw a little serious jazz into the mix, or create special time slots for ''real'' jazz.</p>
        <p>More Than A Rhythm Section</p>
        <p>Stanley Crouch, a columnist for The Daily News in New York and the artistic consultant for Jazz at Lincoln Center, dismisses the music.</p>
        <p>''The problem emerged with fusion music in the 1960's, which made it difficult for people to tell the difference between jazz and instrumental pop music,'' he said. ''Now, because of the title, some people are led to believe that jazz is anything with a pop rhythm section and an instrumental improvisation. Smooth jazz makes it more difficult to know what jazz is for the average person, and when people finally hear real jazz, they always say, 'Why did I spend so much time listening to garbage?' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams of CD 101 said: ''Smooth jazz is a marketing term. It works for us. We're not the epitome of an art form. We take the interest of the public, and we examine it and try and support it. But we're also public trustees: we start people off with instrumental-based music, and from there they can move on to more complex intellectual forms of improvisational music.''</p>
        <p>No matter how the music is validated or explained, for Mr. Bouvard at Arbitron, smooth jazz is just the 90's version of easy listening, once dismissed as ''elevator music.''</p>
        <p>''In the 1960's and 1970's, we had easy listening stations,'' he said. ''They played relaxing music. It was often instrumental versions of pop songs. It was heard in offices and it was meant to make people relax. Today smooth jazz stations play relaxing music. They play instrumental versions of pop songs. It's heard in offices. Smooth jazz is just a fancy name for easy listening.''</p>
        <p>The Jazz Is 'Lite,' the Profits Heavy</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
