<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Other Unbeatens Look for B.C.S. Chance</title>
    <meta content="31colleges" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/31/sports/ncaafootball/31colleges.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1713946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bowl Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bowl Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Stanford University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of California</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Virginia Tech</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bowl Championship Series</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Southern California</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Texas</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7D91F3FF932A05753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1067" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Other Unbeatens Look for B.C.S. Chance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Other Unbeatens Look for a Chance in the B.C.S.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Pete Thamel</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By scoring 21 points in the final seven minutes of regulation, then beating Stanford in overtime Saturday night, U.C.L.A. pulled off one of the most improbable victories of this college football season.</p>
        <p>When quarterback Drew Olson lobbed a 23-yard touchdown pass to Brandon Breazell in overtime, the Bruins completed their fourth comeback of 10 or more points this season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With just a few weeks left in the season, No. 7 U.C.L.A., No. 3 Virginia Tech and No. 4 Alabama face daunting odds of dislodging U.S.C. or Texas from the top spots in the B.C.S. standings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By scoring 21 points in the final seven minutes of regulation, then beating Stanford in overtime Saturday night, U.C.L.A. pulled off one of the most improbable victories of this college football season.</p>
        <p>When quarterback Drew Olson lobbed a 23-yard touchdown pass to Brandon Breazell in overtime, the Bruins completed their fourth comeback of 10 or more points this season.</p>
        <p>That frenetic finish kept U.C.L.A. (8-0) on the fringe of the race for the national title; it is one of five unbeaten teams.</p>
        <p>With just a few weeks left in the season, seventh-ranked U.C.L.A., No. 3 Virginia Tech and No. 4 Alabama face daunting odds of dislodging Southern California or Texas from the top spots in the Bowl Championship Series standings. The team with the best chance for a late-season run to the Rose Bowl may be the Cardiac Bruins, who have a chance to topple U.S.C. in their regular-season finale on Dec. 3.</p>
        <p>There is a good chance that U.S.C. and U.C.L.A. will each enter that game undefeated.</p>
        <p>Jerry Palm, an independent B.C.S. analyst, said that voters would have the greatest impact on the formula that decides the outcome of the B.C.S.</p>
        <p>''Voters are a fickle bunch and difficult to predict,'' Palm said. ''But wouldn't it be surprising to vote the Bruins behind any other undefeated teams if they ended Southern Cal's winning streak and finished undefeated?''</p>
        <p>Perhaps Virginia Tech is a more likely candidate to reach the B.C.S. title game if U.S.C. or Texas drops out of the top places. The Hokies are a consensus No. 3, and their difficult schedule down the stretch -- starting with a game at No. 5 Miami on Saturday night -- will help them in the computer rankings. That is, of course, if they win the remainder of their games.</p>
        <p>The blend of six computer formulas counts for only a third of the B.C.S. formula. The Harris Poll and the USA Today coaches' poll make up the other two-thirds.</p>
        <p>Boston College was ranked No. 13 last week, and Virginia Tech blew out the Eagles on Thursday night, 30-10. After playing Miami, the Hokies will play at Virginia, at home against North Carolina, then probably against No. 9 Florida State in the inaugural Atlantic Coast Conference title game, in Jacksonville, Fla.</p>
        <p>Texas took over the No. 1 spot in the B.C.S. standings last week, but its weak schedule the rest of the season will probably cause it to fall to No. 2 behind U.S.C.</p>
        <p>If the Hokies win the rest of their games, they will have a chance to leap over Texas for the No. 2 spot. Virginia Tech Coach Frank Beamer said last week that he believed things would work out for the Hokies if they went undefeated.</p>
        <p>''That's a pretty strong finishing schedule,'' Palm said of Virginia Tech. ''If they're able to do that, they have a chance to be the No. 1 overall team in the computers. That gives them a chance to let those computers go to work for them and against Texas.''</p>
        <p>A weak schedule down the stretch and a generally weak Big 12 improve the chances of Texas finishing undefeated, but those factors could hurt it in the computer rankings. The Longhorns play at Baylor, at home against Kansas, then at Texas A&amp;M for their regular-season finale. Then they will almost certainly play in the Big 12 title game in Houston. None of the Longhorns' remaining opponents are strong enough to give them a boost in the computer rankings.</p>
        <p>But Palm said, ''Virginia Tech still is going to have to close the gap in the polls.''</p>
        <p>Finally, there is Alabama. The combination of the Crimson Tide's impotent offense and its grueling schedule makes it perhaps the least likely of the undefeated teams to reach the B.C.S. title game.</p>
        <p>Alabama has scored just one offensive touchdown in its past two conference victories, and it may have to face three more top-20 teams before a bowl game. After a trip to lowly Mississippi State on Saturday, the Tide will play No. 6 Louisiana State and at No. 17 Auburn. Alabama would then face Georgia or Florida in the Southeastern Conference title game in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>With so many games remaining before the B.C.S. bids are determined, the possibilities are endless. And as U.C.L.A. demonstrated Saturday night, almost anything can happen when a team finishes with a strong closing kick.</p>
        <p>Changing Offenses</p>
        <p>The spread offense is sputtering for many teams this season.</p>
        <p>Purdue traditionally has a productive spread, but the Boilermakers are 2-6 this season, 0-5 in the Big Ten. Bowling Green entered the season billed as a potential Bowl Championship Series challenger, but its star quarterback, Omar Jacobs, has a shoulder injury, and the Falcons (4-4) have two losses in the Mid-American Conference.</p>
        <p>Even Missouri and Texas A&amp;M, with seemingly ideal quarterbacks to run a spread-option system, have struggled. Brad Smith and Missouri managed just 3 points in a loss to Kansas on Saturday. Reggie McNeal and Texas A&amp;M were trounced, 42-14, at home against Iowa State.</p>
        <p>Florida essentially ditched its base spread-option offense for a power game in its 14-10 victory over Georgia on Saturday. The move caught the Bulldogs off guard, and the Gators scored touchdowns on their first two possessions. The shift in strategy allowed the Gators to play to their strengths, and it debunked some of the hype surrounding Coach Urban Meyer's offense.</p>
        <p>''There's no secret offense, or everyone would run it,'' Meyer said Sunday. ''It's the personnel running the offense.''</p>
        <p>Meyer's switch indicated that the Gators were conceding that SEC teams like L.S.U., Alabama and Georgia have too much speed on defense for Florida to try to run plays laterally. So Meyer has altered his philosophy to emphasize field position and rely on the Gators' sturdy defense. It is a far cry from the 500 yards a game his Utah team averaged last season.</p>
        <p>''Am I comfortable with this?'' Meyer said. ''I'm comfortable with winning and giving players the opportunity to win.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
