<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China's State Catholic Church Honors John Paul</title>
    <meta content="05CHIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/05/international/worldspecial2/05china.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1662533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="JOHN PAUL II: BEIJING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">John Paul II (Pope)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Popes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Popes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E7DD1F3FF936A35757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China's State Catholic Church Honors John Paul</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">China's State Catholic Church Honors John Paul</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More than 300 Chinese parishioners fill downtown cathedral in Beijing to honor Pope John Paul II in public Mass held by Communist Party's state-controlled Catholic Church; memorial Mass captures contradictions of Catholicism in China, where church acknowledges pope as spiritual leader but rejects authority of Vatican over church affairs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 300 Chinese parishioners filled a downtown cathedral Monday morning to honor Pope John Paul II in a public Mass held by the Communist Party's state-controlled Catholic Church.</p>
        <p>The memorial Mass held at Southern Cathedral here captured the contradictions of Catholicism in China, where the church, officially known as the Catholic Patriotic Association, acknowledges the pope as a spiritual leader but rejects the authority of the Vatican over church affairs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 300 parishioners filled a cathedral in Beijing in a Mass held by the Communist Party's state-controlled Catholic church.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than 300 Chinese parishioners filled a downtown cathedral Monday morning to honor Pope John Paul II in a public Mass held by the Communist Party's state-controlled Catholic Church.</p>
        <p>The memorial Mass held at Southern Cathedral here captured the contradictions of Catholicism in China, where the church, officially known as the Catholic Patriotic Association, acknowledges the pope as a spiritual leader but rejects the authority of the Vatican over church affairs.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Song Shang'en offered a short eulogy that was notable for not mentioning the pope's lifelong fight against Communism. Instead, the priest praised John Paul as ''a man of peace; he made a great contribution to the church.''</p>
        <p>The priest also alluded to the political tension between China and the Vatican, which severed diplomatic relations in 1951. The Vatican is the last government in Europe to maintain diplomatic relations with Taiwan, which China considers a breakaway province. Father Song said Rome's ties to Taiwan ''make it impossible to improve relations between China and the Vatican.''</p>
        <p>Experts estimate that China has 12 million Catholics, many of them worshiping in ''underground'' churches that pledge fealty to the Vatican and are banned by the government. In recent weeks, two underground priests have been arrested, according to the Cardinal Kung Foundation, a group based in Stamford, Conn., that monitors religious persecution in China.</p>
        <p>After the Mass on Monday, several parishioners spoke of their love for John Paul. Many people noted with sadness that the pope had never fulfilled his lifelong wish to visit China, though they seemed ignorant of the political split that prevented his coming.</p>
        <p>''That is a huge regret, and we always hoped and prayed he would come here,'' said Zhang Mingqiang, 70, who described himself as a lifelong Catholic. ''We didn't understand the ins and outs of it, but it never came about.''</p>
        <p>Another memorial Mass is scheduled for Tuesday morning at a different state-approved Catholic cathedral in Beijing. Meanwhile, underground churches scattered around China also have been holding secret memorial services, according to the Cardinal Kung Foundation.</p>
        <p>''To us in the underground church, Pope John Paul II's death is not only the death of our pontiff, but also the loss of a great father and friend of Roman Catholics in China,'' Joseph Kung, president of the foundation, wrote in a statement. ''He loved the underground church in China from the very beginning of his pontificate.''</p>
        <p>JOHN PAUL II: BEIJING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
