<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Florida State Tumbles To No. 3 in Its State</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="490880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTHERN STATES (US)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D71631F932A35751C1A967958260" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Florida State Tumbles To No. 3 in Its State</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>GAINESVILLE, Fla., Nov. 30 (AP)</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Florida State, the preseason favorite to win the unofficial national championship and the nation's top team in the polls for nearly three months, today became only the third best in its state.</p>
        <p>Florida, No. 4 in The New York Times's computer ranking and No. 5 in the Associated Press poll of broadcasters and writers, handed the Seminoles their second consecutive loss by harassing Casey Weldon into a subpar performance and riding the passing of Shane Matthews to a 14-9 victory. That ended a four-game losing streak in the rivalry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Florida State, the preseason favorite to win the unofficial national championship and the nation's top team in the polls for nearly three months, today became only the third best in its state.</p>
        <p>Florida, No. 4 in The New York Times's computer ranking and No. 5 in the Associated Press poll of broadcasters and writers, handed the Seminoles their second consecutive loss by harassing Casey Weldon into a subpar performance and riding the passing of Shane Matthews to a 14-9 victory. That ended a four-game losing streak in the rivalry.</p>
        <p>Florida State was No. 3 in the A.P. poll and No. 5 in the Times ranking.</p>
        <p>The triumph was the eighth straight since a loss at Syracuse for Florida (10-1), which won its first official Southeastern Conference championship this season and is headed to the Sugar Bowl to play Notre Dame on Jan. 1. Florida State (10-2) lost the polls' No. 1 ranking to Miami two weeks ago and finished last in the state by virtue of its 0-2 record against intrastate rivals.</p>
        <p>Matthews, who completed 12 of 30 passes for 208 yards, gave Florida a 14-3 lead when he rolled to his right to avoid a heavy rush and found Harrison Houston streaking downfield against linebacker Reggie Freeman on a 72-yard touchdown play.</p>
        <p>The 11-point lead appeared safe until late in the fourth quarter when Weldon, who lost one fumble and threw an interception, finally got Florida State's offense on track.</p>
        <p>Florida State, which twice failed to score a touchdown on possessions inside the Florida 5, drove 80 yards to cut the deficit to 6 points when Amp Lee scored on a 25-yard pass play with 5 minutes 24 seconds left. The Seminoles got the ball back a minute later, but Florida State was stopped on downs at the Gators' 14.</p>
        <p>Weldon, who completed 24 of 51 passes for 305 yards, had similar problems producing points in the 17-16 loss to Miami. The Seminoles failed to score touchdowns on three possessions inside the 20 against the Hurricanes.</p>
        <p>Florida State, averaging nearly 460 yards and 39 points a game, was held to 18 yards net offense in the opening quarter and did not make a first down until two minutes into the second period.</p>
        <p>The Seminoles settled for a 19-yard field goal by Gerry Thomas on their most promising drive of the first half, failing to get into the end zone after Weldon's 8-yard completion to Kez McCorvey gave Florida State at first down a the Florida 1.</p>
        <p>Errict Rhett, who rushed for 109 yards on 24 carries, scored Florida's first touchdown on a 3-yard run. No. 12 Tennessee 45, Vanderbilt 0</p>
        <p>KNOXVILLE, Tenn. (AP) -- Andy Kelly threw for two touchdowns, including one to defensive tackle Shazzon Bradley on a fake field goal, and Tennessee rushed for 415 yards in the Southeastern Conference game.</p>
        <p>Tennessee (9-2 over all, 5-2 in the conference) beat Vanderbilt (5-6, 3-4) with three rushers exceeding 100 yards for the first time in school history.</p>
        <p>The Vols got 145 yards and 2 touchdowns from James Stewart, 115 yards from backup Aaron Hayden, and 107 from third-team tailback Mose Phillips. Wide receiver Ronald Davis scored from 32 yards out on a reverse.</p>
        <p>Vanderbilt, which has been primarily a running team, gained only 150 rushing yards and a total of 231. Tennessee gained 507 total yards.</p>
        <p>The two teams got into a fight before the game even started. Then Tennessee came up with a knockout punch in the first half to lead at the half, 24-0. No. 13 Alabama 13, Auburn 6</p>
        <p>BIRMINGHAM, Ala. (AP) -- Freshman David Palmer's running and receiving led Alabama over Auburn, saddling the Tigers with their first losing season since 1981.</p>
        <p>Alabama (10-1), which beat Auburn for the second straight year, will play No. 19 Colorado in the Blockbuster Bowl on Dec. 28. Auburn (5-6) won't be going to a bowl game for the first time since 1982.</p>
        <p>Palmer lined up for one play at quarterback and made it good, dodging three defenders at the end of a 10-yard scoring run to the right corner. A 68-yard pass play from Jay Barker to Kevin Turner preceded Palmer's touchdown. Southern 31, Grambling 30</p>
        <p>NEW ORLEANS (AP) -- Malcolm Picou blocked an extra point attempt, and Nathaniel Harrison threw a 70-yard touchdown pass to Bryan Thomas in the fourth quarter to lead Southern University to a victory over Grambling in a Southwestern Athletic Conference game.</p>
        <p>Grambling (5-6, 3-4) had pulled within one point, 24-23, on Nate Singleton's second touchdown of the afternoon on a 3-yard wingback reverse, but Gilad Landau missed the kick for the extra point.</p>
        <p>Southern was penalized for roughing the kicker and Landau got another chance to tie it. But Picou broke through and blocked it.</p>
        <p>Grambling took a 30-24 lead on a 9-yard touchdown pass from reserve quarterback Eric Bryant to Derrick Ned as the fourth quarter began. Southern (4-7, 4-3) scored the winning touchdown with 6:27 left in the game on the 70-yard pass from Harrison to Thomas. Georgia 18, Georgia Tech 15</p>
        <p>ATLANTA (AP) -- Garrison Hearst scored on a 69-yard run and set up the winning field goal with a 30-yard run. Hearst ran for 175 yards against the nation's seventh-best rushing defense, which had been allowing only 100 yards per game on the ground. Georgia (8-3) snapped a two-game losing streak in the series and ended Tech's 17-game home winning streak. Georgia Tech, which last year finished No. 1 in the United Press International poll, fell to 7-5.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
