<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Workers, a Winter Lull</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="496621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTMAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW YEAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCTIVITY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYERS, STEVEN LEE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Productivity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD7133DF93BA15751C1A967958260" item-length="884" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Workers, a Winter Lull</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYERS, STEVEN LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everything about work the last couple of days has been all wrong. Noah Rosenblum, an engineer at J. P. Morgan &amp; Co. on Wall Street, noticed it. The phones rang less. He found a seat during his coffee break.</p>
        <p>His co-worker Patrick McAleer said he felt it, too. A lot of people had brought their kids to work. "The funny thing," he said, sitting with Mr. Rosenblum yesterday in the atrium of the J. P. Morgan Building, lushly decorated for the holidays, "is that they're off for a day and they bring their family into the office."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everything about work the last couple of days has been all wrong. Noah Rosenblum, an engineer at J. P. Morgan &amp; Co. on Wall Street, noticed it. The phones rang less. He found a seat during his coffee break.</p>
        <p>His co-worker Patrick McAleer said he felt it, too. A lot of people had brought their kids to work. "The funny thing," he said, sitting with Mr. Rosenblum yesterday in the atrium of the J. P. Morgan Building, lushly decorated for the holidays, "is that they're off for a day and they bring their family into the office."</p>
        <p>With Christmas and New Year's Day falling in the middle of the last two weeks of the year, offices throughout the New York metropolitan region have drifted through the last two days in a sort of a holiday Twilight Zone.  An Outer-Office Experience</p>
        <p>"After Christmas, it's an interregnum," said Samuel M. Ehrenhalt, the regional commissioner in New York City for the Federal Bureau of Labor Statistics. "The old king is gone and the new one has not yet come. It's close-out time. The pace of activity begins to wind down, and it stays wound down until after the New Year."</p>
        <p>While few offices have actually closed, few have had more than skeletal staffs. All but the most essential employees sawthis week and next as the perfect opportunity to stretch the two midweek holidays into a vacation -- what Irwin Kellner, the chief economist for Manufacturers Hanover Trust, called "white-collar holidays."</p>
        <p>And yet those who did work found the office vacuum a vacation in itself. The commute has been a breeze, the office mood casual, almost festive. And while it has been nearly impossible to get anyone on the phone, some said it was the best time of the year to actually get some work done.</p>
        <p>"You can accomplish more now, because there's not so many people harassing you," said Mr. Rosenblum, who said his office was in a "California state of mind."</p>
        <p>Delos R. Smith, the senior business analyst for the Conference Board, a economic research organization in Manhattan, said "very little gets done" during these half-holidays, half-workdays.</p>
        <p>"I'm not even bothering to make phone calls," he said. "Nobody's returning them."</p>
        <p>Making the best of it, Mr. Smith took half the day off so he could take his wife and daughter to the movies. "At 1:30, goodbye," he said.</p>
        <p>In Somers, N.Y., at the world headquarters of Pepsico Inc., a spokesman, Gary Gedermann, said a few workers had to be on hand "just in case Coke changes their formula again or something."</p>
        <p>Mr. Gedermann said he believed the semiholidays gain momentum in a sort of ripple effect.</p>
        <p>"Everyone figures, 'No one else is in, so I'm not going to go in,' " he said. "The assumption cascades and becomes a reality."</p>
        <p>Jeanette Sivak went to work yesterday at the St. Andrews Textile Company at 135 West 50th Street in Manhattan, but wearing a "Guess University" sweatshirt and towing a 6-year-old "helper," her son Matthew. Not Much Work</p>
        <p>The import company had virtually no business, so Ms. Sivak, a computer operator, spent the day with 8 of the company's 27 employees doing such things as sorting out "the things I've thrown in the drawer for the last year."</p>
        <p>The office's casual mood aside, she said, "Every time I wake up at 7:30, it feels like a workday."</p>
        <p>In some cases, the boss's absence alone was enough to make the week feel like a holiday.</p>
        <p>"Both of my bosses are out -- one officially, one sick," said Jonathan Feinberg, a computer programming analyst at Columbia House in midtown Manhattan. "This is when I get all my computer-game-playing in."</p>
        <p>Larry Cooperman, a case administrator at the American Arbitration Association, also in midtown, found another benefit. His commute on Long Island Rail Road this week has been something it very rarely is: a pleasure. "I wish I had a camcorder," he said. "All the seats were empty." Professionals' Holiday</p>
        <p>Many of those who took off were professionals -- lawyers, accountants and advertisers. They could stay home anticipating a year-end slowdown, but others could not. Retail stores, restaurants, hotels, theaters and other businesses that cater to those on vacation were as busy as ever.</p>
        <p>"I'm just grateful I'm working," said Michel Silva, a lobby receptionist in the Worldwide Plaza office tower on Eighth Avenue at 49th Street.</p>
        <p>Raju Sewani waited all day in his gift store and newsstand in the same building for a mere trickle of customers. The tower is usually bustling with workers from Microsoft, the Polygram record company, and the advertising agencies N .W. Ayer Inc. and Olgilvy &amp; Mather. 'Bad for Business'</p>
        <p>"The building told me 75 percent of the people who work here are off," said Mr. Sewani, who opened the shop just four months ago. "This whole week it's like this. It's bad for business."</p>
        <p>Glenn Weiner, an actor, was working, too. Painted silver and wearing only a Speedo swimsuit and Nike sneakers, he walked along 49th Street in the Theater District, filming scenes for a multimedia production called "Power of Dreams."</p>
        <p>Mr. Weiner, who was obviously cold, disrupted traffic as he posed with a large wooden heart smudged with dirt. "It's a man carrying his heart, with crud on it," explained David Niles, the director.</p>
        <p>With opening night planned for January, Mr. Niles said, "We're working straight through."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
