<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Welcoming Arafat, Clinton Rebukes Israel</title>
    <meta content="04PREX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="913237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Agency for International Development (Aid)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Robert E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Atwood, Brian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DB1730F937A35750C0A961958260" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Welcoming Arafat, Clinton Rebukes Israel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton and Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat meet at White House, where Clinton delivers mild but relatively rare rebuke of Israel for decision to proceed with construction of thousands of new homes for Jews in East Jerusalem; Clinton says action has created mistrust that could damage peace effort in region; Arafat meets with Sec of State Madeleine K Albright, Treas Sec Robert E Rubin and Brian Atwood, director of Agency for International Development (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Yasir Arafat at his side, President Clinton delivered a mild but relatively rare rebuke of Israel today, saying the Israeli Government's decision last week to allow construction of thousands of new homes for Jews in East Jerusalem had created ''mistrust'' and could damage the peace effort in the region.</p>
        <p>The President made his remarks as he began an extended meeting this morning with Mr. Arafat, the Palestinian leader, who raised the subject of the new Jewish housing in a tone that Mr. Clinton's spokesman, Michael D. McCurry, later described as ''very concerned and emotional.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With Yasir Arafat at his side, President Clinton delivered a mild but relatively rare rebuke of Israel today, saying the Israeli Government's decision last week to allow construction of thousands of new homes for Jews in East Jerusalem had created ''mistrust'' and could damage the peace effort in the region.</p>
        <p>The President made his remarks as he began an extended meeting this morning with Mr. Arafat, the Palestinian leader, who raised the subject of the new Jewish housing in a tone that Mr. Clinton's spokesman, Michael D. McCurry, later described as ''very concerned and emotional.''</p>
        <p>Today's meeting was the sixth between Mr. Clinton and Mr. Arafat, but it had added significance as the first meeting held directly between the two men without the presence of other Middle East leaders, or, as Mr. McCurry put it, ''in the context of some other gathering.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat's meeting at the White House came on a day when Palestinians in the West Bank and Gaza Strip, as well as in East Jerusalem, took part in a general strike to protest the Israeli decision to build the first of 2,500 of 6,500 homes on a hill in East Jerusalem known in Arabic as Jabal Abu Ghneim and in Hebrew as Har Homa.</p>
        <p>Sitting beside Mr. Arafat in the Oval Office, Mr. Clinton said it was important for the Israelis and Palestinians ''to be building confidence and working together'' as the peace talks move forward and then lent his voice to the chorus of international criticism of the new housing.</p>
        <p>''I would prefer the decision not have been made, because I don't think it builds confidence,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''I think it builds mistrust, and I wish that it had not been made.''</p>
        <p>In meetings with Mr. Arafat and in public remarks, the White House seemed eager to lend its support and encouragement to the Palestinian leader -- in part to shore up the peace effort, which has lagged again since the brief burst of enthusiasm after the agreement in January that led to the withdrawal of Israeli forces from Hebron.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat went on to meet separately with Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, as well as Secretary of Treasury Robert E. Rubin and the director of the Agency for International Development, Brian Atwood. At lunch at the State Department, the Americans and Mr. Arafat's delegations held lengthy discussions on increasing investments in the Palestinian territories.</p>
        <p>The State Department then announced the creation of a joint committee -- like the ones the United States has with Russia, South Africa and Egypt -- that is to meet regularly to discuss diplomatic, economic and cultural concerns.</p>
        <p>Neither the President nor his aides discussed what the United States would do -- or could do -- to reverse the decision by the Government of Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu. The Clinton Administration, like those those before it, has opposed Jewish settlements in the territories captured by Israel in 1967. And Administration officials had quietly urged Mr. Netanyahu's cabinet beforehand not to move ahead with the housing project in East Jerusalem, which Israeli seized from Jordan in the 1967 war.</p>
        <p>While he delivered a rebuke, Mr. Clinton also made clear that the United States' role was that of mediator, helping but not taking sides. In answering another question -- on whether the United States should, as many in Congress have demanded, recognize Jerusalem as Israel's capital -- Mr. Clinton said the United States should avoid staking a position on a matter that will be part of the ''final status'' talks between the Israelis and Palestinians.</p>
        <p>''I think that would be a big mistake,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But officials portrayed Mr. Clinton's remarks on the housing project, which echoed those made by White House and State Department spokesmen last week, as a subtle but significant warning to the Israelis not to take steps to provoke the Palestinians or throw up obstacles to the peace effort.</p>
        <p>''We really rolled out the carpet for Arafat,'' an Administration official said, speaking on condition of anonymity. At the same time, the official said, the President's remarks were an effort to show ''that we're a little frustrated with Netanyahu.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat, for his part, said the new Israeli construction in East Jerusalem, which the Palestinians hope to make the capital of a Palestinian state, was intended ''to squeeze and to isolate Jerusalem.'' But he stopped short of warnings by other Palestinian leaders that the housing in East Jerusalem could lead to violent protests.</p>
        <p>Today's meeting with Mr. Arafat followed one the President had with Mr. Netanyahu last month. And it precedes a series of meetings with Middle Eastern leaders in which the Administration hopes to restore momentum to the peace effort. President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt and King Hussein of Jordan are scheduled to come for meetings with Mr. Clinton and others later this month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
