<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; Lonely, and Then Still Lonelier</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="462109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKNER, ANITA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BRIEF LIVES (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DB133EF931A15754C0A967958260" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; Lonely, and Then Still Lonelier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brief Lives By Anita Brookner  260 pages. Random House. $20.</p>
        <p>Fay Langdon, the elderly first-person narrator of Anita Brookner's latest novel, "Brief Lives" (her 10th), was a singer of popular songs on the wireless in her youth. Among her favorites were "You Are My Heart's Delight" and "Always."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brief Lives By Anita Brookner  260 pages. Random House. $20.</p>
        <p>Fay Langdon, the elderly first-person narrator of Anita Brookner's latest novel, "Brief Lives" (her 10th), was a singer of popular songs on the wireless in her youth. Among her favorites were "You Are My Heart's Delight" and "Always."</p>
        <p>"Sometimes the words come back to me, even now," Fay reports, "but I try not to think about the melodies, which, since I have grown older, strike me as unbearably sad, plaintive, modest, wistful, redolent of everyday disappointments, even tragedies. I try not to brood, although I suppose I have as much to brood over as anyone else. So much gone. So much lost." So depressing.</p>
        <p>"I'll be loving you always, with a love that's true always," go the words of "Always." Hardly could the sentiments of a song be more at odds with a life than they are with Fay's.</p>
        <p>As a young woman, Fay falls in love with and marries Owen Langdon, a former Battle of Britain pilot who works for a London firm. Though Owen has made Fay give up her singing career, he is away on business much of the time, selling real estate to wealthy buyers on the French Riviera, and even when he's home with Fay he's not always quite there.</p>
        <p>"Intimacy, I see now, was what he feared the most; intimacy made him uneasy, as if he had forfeited or lost part of himself in the process, as if it had made him vulnerable to criticism, to attack. I had seen his face after I had once, in the early days, prevailed on him to love me; it was fretful, pained, resentful. All this I saw in one terrible moment, as he turned away from me. He sat on the edge of the bed, naked, his clasped hands hanging between his knees.  Poor Tom's a-cold, I thought. I was so frightened then that I vowed I would keep my distance. For that was what he wanted, and I still loved him enough to try to please him."</p>
        <p>As the song goes: "When the things you plan need a helping hand, I will understand always."</p>
        <p>Fay's mother dies, filling her with "such despair that I suffered in a very physical sense. . . ." Then she gets news that Owen has been killed in a car crash. On her way to claim his corpse, she braces herself for the rest of her life. "No one would ever meet me again," she recalls. "I was alone, and now, at last, I knew the true meaning of loneliness."</p>
        <p>The novel gets steadily more painful to read.</p>
        <p>For a while you think Fay's bleak despair is a setup. At the darkest point, when Fay has sold the house she shared with Owen and moved into a flat by herself, a friend's husband shows up and begins an affair with her. But this hopeful development quickly turns to ashes. First, Fay grows dependent on her lover, building her lonely days around the moment when he may show up. Then she learns he has died of a stroke.</p>
        <p>She is plunged back into her isolation. "Eventually I would become an object of pity," she thinks, "if I were lucky enough not to become an object of derision, one of those mad old women in broken shoes who mutter to themselves in public places."</p>
        <p>I will spare you the other terrible things that happen to Fay.</p>
        <p>In truth, I've cheated slightly in this summary. The point of "Brief Lives" is not to drive the reader to suicide. The plot is actually a variation on Anita Brookner's familiar theme of the conflict between humble innocence and cynical knowing.</p>
        <p>The one constant in Fay's life -- the person she introduces with the opening words of "Brief Lives" -- is the beautiful Margaret Julia Wilberforce, a once popular actress whose condescendingly aristocratic ways have gone out of fashion. Fay dislikes Julia, as does Julia Fay, but their attraction to each other, particularly Julia's hold over Fay, is what "Brief Lives" is essentially about.</p>
        <p>Julia is skillfully drawn by Ms. Brookner. "I would come into that drawing-room, with flowers, or some little trifle -- one always brought an offering -- which she would take from me with a gesture of palpitating gratitude, and then pause to consider.  'Oh,' she would say, on a note of dwindling enthusiasm, pretending to examine it or them more closely. 'Oh.  How charming.' She would mark a pause, and then the eyelids would fall to half-mast, at which anyone in attendance . . . would burst into delighted laughter. 'Quite charming,' she would go on, losing interest. 'Put them there, would you? I'll see to them later.' "</p>
        <p>And there is surprising depth and complexity to the way the novel resolves Fay's attachment to Julia, contradicting everything Fay thinks she understands about people.</p>
        <p>In fact, "Brief Lives" is full of the intelligence and artistry one takes for granted from Ms. Brookner, who won the Booker Prize for her novel "Hotel du Lac" (1985) and is also a renowned authority on 18th-century painting.</p>
        <p>But none of this relieves the oppressiveness of Fay Langdon's interminable threnody, ironic though it may be.  "I dread the weekends," she reports in the final pages. "I dread the pretense that drives me to the shops on a Saturday morning, and the shame of buying a solitary chop and few vegetables, which I cook for my lunch. I feel the burden then. I dread the calm of Saturday afternoons, punctuated only by the distant roar from the football terraces. Something stops me from going out, as if I might be in danger of missing a visitor, though no one comes. I sit by the window, with my hands in my lap, looking out and waiting."</p>
        <p>Perhaps Fay deserves such a fate for believing in the lyrics of songs like "Always." But her monumental gloom makes you wish certain lives in "Brief Lives" were briefer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
