<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turgeon Exits As Isles Make Their Move</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="753399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRADES (SPORTS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK ISLANDERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MONTREAL CANADIENS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAMOS, JASON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TURGEON, PIERRE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALAKHOV, VLADIMIR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MULLER, KIRK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, MATTHIEU</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Montreal Canadiens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D8113EF935A35757C0A963958260" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turgeon Exits As Isles Make Their Move</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAMOS, JASON</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I., April 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Don Maloney finally did it. He finally pulled the trigger on a trade, a five-player deal with Montreal that involved the Islanders' most recognizable name, Pierre Turgeon.</p>
        <p>Now the question is: Is it too late -- if not to turn around this 10-20-4 season, then to save Maloney's job as general manager?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Don Maloney finally did it. He finally pulled the trigger on a trade, a five-player deal with Montreal that involved the Islanders' most recognizable name, Pierre Turgeon.</p>
        <p>Now the question is: Is it too late -- if not to turn around this 10-20-4 season, then to save Maloney's job as general manager?</p>
        <p>What Maloney gave up in addition to Turgeon, two years removed from a 132-point season, was Vladimir Malakhov, perhaps the player with the most potential on the team, but one the Islanders got tired of waiting for to deliver on his promise.</p>
        <p>What the Islanders received in return was the Canadiens' captain, Kirk Muller, a hard worker, proven scorer and two-way center who spent seven productive seasons with the Devils; Mathieu Schneider, a gifted defenseman who can score, but who was all but run out of Montreal by the French-speaking news media; and a 22-year-old prospect in center Craig Darby.</p>
        <p>"From a casual fan's point of view, they're probably wondering how the heck we could ever trade Pierre Turgeon," Maloney said tonight, after returning from a three-day trip to Montreal and one day after his team had lost for the 10th time in its last 12 games. "But you know, we're trying to set a new course here."</p>
        <p>Apparently there is already a new one in Montreal, where Turgeon stepped right into the spotlight tonight by scoring the tying goal for the Canadiens and assisting on the winning one in a 6-5 victory over the Quebec Nordiques.</p>
        <p>Maloney's remarks tonight, though, made it clear that the moves were made with next season in mind.</p>
        <p>Expect a major overhaul. Goaltender Jamie McLennan was demoted to Denver of the International Hockey League this morning, one day after giving up 5 goals on the first 15 shots he faced during the Islanders' 5-4 loss to Washington on Tuesday night. Tommy Salo, who had a 45-14-4 record at Denver, was recalled to take McLennan's place. And there is still plenty of time to make another trade before Friday's deadline passes.</p>
        <p>"We're certainly still talking," said Coach Lorne Henning. "There are still some areas we're trying to shore up."</p>
        <p>But even if Maloney does nothing more, today's deal was the Islanders' most significant one since, Oct. 25, 1991, when Turgeon, Hogue, Uwe Krupp and Dave McLlwain were acquired from Buffalo for Pat LaFontaine, Randy Hiller, Randy Wood and a draft choice.</p>
        <p>Bill Torrey, the former Islander general manager, engineered that blockbuster. In his almost three years in the position, Maloney has been criticized for not being able to pull off a major trade, especially last season, when the Rangers improved themselves at the deadline and Maloney came away empty-handed, then watched his team lose four straight to the Rangers in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>"I know there's been a knock here personally because we haven't made any deals," he said. But today, Maloney came through, although the deal looks to be unpopular at first.</p>
        <p>"If there wasn't a risk in any deal, if you're afraid of making a deal, you should be a librarian or something," Maloney said.</p>
        <p>The major reasons given for trading Turgeon and Malakhov were inconsistency and lack of leadership. The term "attitude adjustment" was frequently used by Maloney.</p>
        <p>"I think it was as much that we have to demand that all our players play," he said. "If you let your top players off the hook, then what kind of message does that send?"</p>
        <p>The departure of Malakhov, a 26-year-old Russian defenseman who is in the option year of his contract, was not a surprise. The swap of the 25-year-old Turgeon (34 games, 13 goals, 27 points) certainly was.</p>
        <p>"I look at our last two years here with our No. 1 go-to weapon, and it hasn't been very good," said Maloney, who signed Turgeon to a four-year, $11 million contract two summers ago. "He was coming off a 132-point season. We had landed in the semifinals and it was all hugs and kisses. That seems like a long time ago. Now I have to come in the cloak of darkness and leave in the cloak of darkness."</p>
        <p>Schneider, 25, was born in Manhattan, and said he welcomed the change. Muller, 29, who was named the Canadiens' captain this season, seemed more shocked, though he averaged nearly 27 goals a season with the Devils from 1984-91 before helping the Canadiens win the Stanley Cup in 1993.</p>
        <p>As for Turgeon, he returns to his native Quebec with his best years ahead of him and the blessing of General Manager Serge Savard, who sees Turgeon as the nifty, play-making center that his team has long sought.</p>
        <p>Malakhov has never quite lived up to expectations.</p>
        <p>"Very few guys in the league can play at Vlady's level when he's playing," said Maloney. "But let's face it, the question is when does that come out and can you count on it? One thing with Schneider, he plays hard every night. We cannot continue to accept losing and be happy about it and say, 'Well, we worked hard, we don't have defense, our goaltending's poor, I got checked, I fell down.'</p>
        <p>"We need to find competitive people and leaders here. And we're willing to sacrifice skill at this point, thinking that we can re-acquire what we're losing at a certain time. Are we going to be able to re-acquire a potential superstar? That may be tough."  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
