<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FIVE QUESTIONS for DR. RAYMOND L. WOOSLEY; Terror Adds to Safety Issues Awaiting New F.D.A. Chief</title>
    <meta content="29FIVE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/29/business/yourmoney/29FIVE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1427586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Five Questions for Dr. Raymond L. Woosley"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flaherty, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woosley, Raymond (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcclellan, Mark B (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Fitness and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Food and Drug Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7D81F39F93AA1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FIVE QUESTIONS for DR. RAYMOND L. WOOSLEY; Terror Adds to Safety Issues Awaiting New F.D.A. Chief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Terror Adds to Safety Issues Awaiting New F.D.A. Chief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE FLAHERTY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flaherty, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Raymond L Woosley, pharmacologist and vice president for health sciences at University of Arizona, answers questions on challenges facing Dr Mark B McClellan, newly nominated chief of Food and Drug Administration, whose job has been expanded to include review and approval of drugs for protection from terrorism (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER 20 months without a leader, the Food and Drug Administration may be getting one. Last Wednesday, President Bush nominated Dr. Mark B. McClellan, a White House adviser who is an expert in health care economics, to the position. Dr. McClellan, whose confirmation by the Senate is widely expected, would be in charge of one of the biggest and most wide-ranging agencies in Washington, with jurisdiction over products representing 20 percent of every consumer dollar spent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush nominated Dr. Mark B. McClellan, a White House adviser who is an expert in health care economics, to lead the Food and Drug Administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER 20 months without a leader, the Food and Drug Administration may be getting one. Last Wednesday, President Bush nominated Dr. Mark B. McClellan, a White House adviser who is an expert in health care economics, to the position. Dr. McClellan, whose confirmation by the Senate is widely expected, would be in charge of one of the biggest and most wide-ranging agencies in Washington, with jurisdiction over products representing 20 percent of every consumer dollar spent.</p>
        <p>The appointment of a new commissioner has been eagerly awaited by food and medical safety experts. Dr. Raymond L. Woosley, a pharmacologist and vice president for health sciences at the University of Arizona, is known for his research into the safe use of medicine. He spoke on Thursday about the challenges facing Dr. McClellan.</p>
        <p>JULIE FLAHERTY</p>
        <p>Q. What do you see as the most important priority for Dr. McClellan at the F.D.A.?</p>
        <p>A. There is a whole new range of priorities after 9/11, so No. 1 has to be an expedited review and approval of drugs for the protection from terrorism. The whole related question of food safety is a critical part of this. Even before 9/11, food safety was a serious problem, and continues to be, with mad cow disease and E. coli and other concerns.</p>
        <p>Another major priority, I hope, will be addressing the problems of regulating the dietary supplements that really aren't dietary supplements. The F.D.A. is going to have to start reviewing and regulating them as drugs to protect the public.</p>
        <p>Q. Dr. McClellan's background is primarily in Medicare and other health care financing issues that are not part of the F.D.A.'s jurisdiction, and he has little experience in drug safety and food contamination issues. Does that present a problem?</p>
        <p>A. Not really. The scope of the responsibilities for this position is so immense. Something like 75 to 80 percent of everything we contact in our day is under the purview and review of the F.D.A. There is no way anyone in that position is going to have the full coverage of expertise needed for that job. So he has to think about what team he needs to assemble to help him fill in the strengths he needs.</p>
        <p>The most important thing for this position is the medical background. It will come down to him to say, ''Is this drug ready to go to the public?''; to know the medical use of those devices, those drugs, firsthand; the risk-benefit ratio that you learn about in medical school; knowing that medicines can be life-saving but they can also be harmful. Those really have to weigh heavily on the person making those decisions.</p>
        <p>Q. How will Dr. McClellan's strength in economics and health policy help him?</p>
        <p>A. The agency in the past has operated very much in isolation, but Secretary Thompson [Tommy G. Thompson, secretary of health and human services] has expressed interest in having the agency be more a member of the team that addresses the needs of the health of the public. The prescription drug benefit discussions -- the commissioner will probably not play a role in those decisions, but by being a spokesperson for the agency, it will help inform the economic decisions that have to take place. And vice versa. If the agency is going to review a drug that will be covered by Medicare, it's going to be exposed to elderly patients in large numbers very quickly, and that has to be part of the safety plan.</p>
        <p>Q. A growing number of drugs have been taken off the market, suggesting that the F.D.A. might have been too hasty in approving them. What should the new commissioner be doing about that?</p>
        <p>A. I don't think it means they were too hasty. Drugs will always need to be taken off the market. Every drug that goes on the market is an experiment, because you will never know all you need to know about a medication until it is in broad public use. Even if you could study 30,000 patients before a drug goes on the market, you will still have the possibility that there is one in 50,000 that are going to be harmed and the drug will have to come off the market. I've often said we know more about a drug before it goes on the market than we ever have before. Our failing has been what we do once it's on the market. The agency has not been given the resources to adequately monitor and evaluate post-marketing safety of drugs and devices, and that's been the problem. If we had a better safety system we would have drugs approved more quickly.</p>
        <p>Q. This appointment comes at a time when the F.D.A. is under growing drug industry pressure to broaden the rules on how drug makers can market their products. How should the new commissioner respond?</p>
        <p>A. Marketing affects risk, because marketing affects the people who are exposed to a medication. Drugs are approved with a certain type and pattern of population exposure, so when a drug goes on the market it is approved for use in that population as it was in the studies. But marketing can sometimes drive the drug into new uses, new populations where we don't have any evidence that it will be safe and effective. Good marketing should follow good drug development and not get out in front of it.</p>
        <p>Five Questions for Dr. Raymond L. Woosley</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
