<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women's Shelter Wants Women Only on Its Board</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="379437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BATTERED SPOUSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMELESS PERSONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSTON (MASS)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROSIE'S PLACE (BOSTON)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DC153CF935A1575BC0A966958260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women's Shelter Wants Women Only on Its Board</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Aug. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Every day more than 100 women drop in at Rosie's Place because they are homeless and hungry, and in most cases because they have been abused at the hands of men. At Rosie's, the first homeless shelter in the country for females only, women are always welcome.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Every day more than 100 women drop in at Rosie's Place because they are homeless and hungry, and in most cases because they have been abused at the hands of men. At Rosie's, the first homeless shelter in the country for females only, women are always welcome.</p>
        <p>Every day more than 100 women drop in at Rosie's Place because they are homeless and hungry, and in most cases because they have been abused at the hands of men. At Rosie's, the first homeless shelter in the country for females only, women are always welcome.</p>
        <p>But men are not so welcome, and a recent decision to ban them from the board of directors has divided the shelter's corps of 250 volunteers, the people often described as the heart of the 16-year-old organization.</p>
        <p>Although men have volunteered at Rosie's since the privately financed shelter opened, a male volunteer who wanted to run for the board in July learned he was not qualified because of his sex.</p>
        <p>No man had sought a seat on the 19-member board until January, when Howard Ostar, a longtime volunteer, decided to run in the board election that month. Volunteers who have worked at Rosie's for at least six months are eligible for board seats and can vote in elections.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Ostar lost, Randy Bluffstone, a volunteer for more than two years, decided to run in the July election. But Mr. Bluffstone's bid was thwarted when the board amended its bylaws in March to exclude men.</p>
        <p>Today three seats remain vacant because no female candidates have sought them. Agnes Cahill, president of the board, said the directors were considering eliminating the vacant seats or filling them with homeless women.</p>
        <p>'The Normal Dirty Jobs'</p>
        <p>Mr. Bluffstone, a graduate student in economics at Boston University, said he was shocked by what appeared to be deliberate discrimination by people who are keenly aware of bias. ''The male volunteers work in the kitchen and do the normal dirty jobs like all the volunteers, but we're barred from any position of control because of our gender,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The board's policy has divided the shelter's 250 volunteers, at least 10 of whom are men. While Mr. Bluffstone continues to volunteer at the shelter, serving meals, washing dishes and socializing with the guests, Mr. Ostar left, saying he was frustrated at being excluded from managerial decisions.</p>
        <p>Rosie's officials say the rule is not meant to discriminate, but rather to formalize the shelter's goal of providing female role models for women. About 90 percent of the women who come to Rosie's have been abused by men. Many are chemicallyepepdedent, and nearly 25 percent veve beeininfefected witththAIAI v vusus ililsoso s sltlts s veveununededofof beds, Rosie's has limited its overnight capacity to 20 so it can attend to each woman individually. ''Rosie's has led the way in how to provide a service to people in need without robbing them of their diginity,'' said Sue Marsh, executive director of the Massachusetts Coalition for the Homeless.</p>
        <p>Not the 'Shelter Industry'</p>
        <p>Kip Tiernan, the shelter's founder, who is known for her commitment to the plight of poor women, said Rosie's was determined not to join the ''shelter industry'' by expanding capacity to accommodate a growing homeless population. Instead, the board decided last year to concentrate on helping a limited number of women find permanent homes and steady jobs. To that end, the directors created two managerial positions, which were filled by women. Given the shelter's focus on women, supporters of the board argue that reserving board seats for women is appropriate. ''It is within the spirit of affirmative action that a place whose entire mission is steeped in the conviction to empower women has a policy for board membership that reflects this commitment,'' said Lisa Price, a volunteer for more than two years.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bluffstone argues that men can also provide important role models for the women who come to Rosie's. ''I thought I could make a contribution to the empowerment of poor women by showing them on the spot that I value their ideas and opinions,'' he said. ''But the board members are sending the message that men are not to be trusted. I think they're seriously misguided.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
