<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Poland, Reveries of 1980 Give Way to Reality</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="379662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">POLAND</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOLIDARITY UNION (POLAND)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF1E3EF935A1575BC0A966958260" item-length="545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Poland, Reveries of 1980 Give Way to Reality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN ENGELBERG, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>WARSAW, Aug. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Poland is awash in nostalgia this month as the nation revisits those simpler times of a decade ago, when an August strike at the Gdansk shipyard gave birth to the Solidarity union. To Solidarity's leaders, this anniversary has been an occasion for pleasant reminiscenses about the years when their lives were a straightforward morality play: dissidence against</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Poland is awash in nostalgia this month as the nation revisits those simpler times of a decade ago, when an August strike at the Gdansk shipyard gave birth to the Solidarity union. To Solidarity's leaders, this anniversary has been an occasion for pleasant reminiscenses about the years when their lives were a straightforward morality play: dissidence against</p>
        <p>Poland is awash in nostalgia this month as the nation revisits those simpler times of a decade ago, when an August strike at the Gdansk shipyard gave birth to the Solidarity union. To Solidarity's leaders, this anniversary has been an occasion for pleasant reminiscenses about the years when their lives were a straightforward morality play: dissidence against Communist oppressors.</p>
        <p>But such reveries are often interrupted these days by the more ambiguous realities of democratic Poland, where former Solidarity colleagues are organizing rival political parties for the national elections.</p>
        <p>Throughout the month, Polish television has been showing the grainy black-and-white footage of Solidarity's heady early days, when a young and trim Lech Walesa joined with the intellectuals of Warsaw to found a powerful national movement and shake the ruling Communist Party. Today many of those intellectuals, their hairlines receding and their waistlines expanding, gathered at the Warsaw University to mark the anniversary. In the end it appeared that this attempt to rekindle the spirit of 1980, when the electrician and the professor joined together against a common enemy, had fallen on deaf ears.</p>
        <p>''Ten years ago there was a strong alliance between workers and intellectuals,'' Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki said to the crowded auditorium. ''We should not lose this value in the new conditions.''</p>
        <p>The Events of 1980</p>
        <p>Mr. Mazowiecki played a significant role in the events of 1980 that led to the creation of the Solidarity Trade Union. Shortly after the workers at the Gdansk shipyard went on strike on Aug. 14, 1980, Mr. Mazowiecki delivered a letter of support signed by intellectuals in Warsaw and Krakow. Within weeks Mr. Mazowiecki, a journalist, and Bronislav Geremek, a professor, had become advisers to a new union led by Mr. Walesa, an electrician.</p>
        <p>After the Communists gave up power in 1989, Mr. Mazowiecki was the Solidarity chairman's hand-picked choice as Prime Minister. Since then, the two men have parted ways as Mr. Walesa has staked his claim for the presidency of Poland and its potential powers for ruling by decree.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walesa was invited to today's meeting in Warsaw, which was largely attended by Mr. Mazowiecki's political supporters. Mr. Walesa did not go and instead sent a letter that touched on one of his key criticisms of Mr. Mazowiecki's Government: its failure to develop popular involvement in politics.</p>
        <p>''We have conquered it,'' Mr. Walesa said of the Communist system,'' and we have accomplished much, but we have not worked out a way of restoring the social vigor of 1980, which was stifled by the imposition of martial law.''</p>
        <p>The Polish Constitution does not provide for parliamentary elections until 1993. Gen. Wojciech Jaruzelski, the President, began his six-year term only last year. Still it is believed that Poland will have elections within the next year, perhaps this fall.</p>
        <p>In a statement earlier this month, Mr. Walesa tried to allay some hurt feelings that resulted from his criticisms of the Mazowiecki Government. He endorsed national elections of the President, even though his supporters have been urging his immediate election by the Parliament, as is possible under the present Polish Constitution.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
