<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pact Raises Few Hopes Among Those Long Schooled in Chaos</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="846531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="MIDEAST ACCORD: IN LEBANON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LEBANON</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LEBANON</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PARTY OF GOD (HEZBOLLAH)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JEHL, DOUGLAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1DB1639F934A15757C0A960958260" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pact Raises Few Hopes Among Those Long Schooled in Chaos</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JEHL, DOUGLAS</byline>
      <dateline>BEIRUT, Lebanon, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This country has been pounded by more than 24,000 Israeli shells and nearly 600 air raids in the last 16 days, and their effect will be felt long after the  guns fall silent early Saturday.</p>
        <p>Across the hills of southern Lebanon, which bore the brunt of Israel's military campaign against Hezbollah guerrillas, roads and water pipelines have been severed and villages shattered. More than 400,000 refugees remain separated from their homes, some of which are no longer standing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This country has been pounded by more than 24,000 Israeli shells and nearly 600 air raids in the last 16 days, and their effect will be felt long after the  guns fall silent early Saturday.</p>
        <p>Across the hills of southern Lebanon, which bore the brunt of Israel's military campaign against Hezbollah guerrillas, roads and water pipelines have been severed and villages shattered. More than 400,000 refugees remain separated from their homes, some of which are no longer standing.</p>
        <p>And Lebanon, so flush with pride at its recovery from long years of civil war, must once again pick up the pieces -- at a cost that officials say has soared into the hundreds of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Even this afternoon, as the agreement to halt the fighting was announced, electric power flickered in the capital, which came under Israeli bombardment this month for the first time in 13 years. Officials said schools and universities would remain closed for a week and probably longer, leaving education a victim as it has so often been over Lebanon's history.</p>
        <p>"We have only just rebuilt, and now they are wrecking everything," said Michel Iddi, the Minister of Higher Education.</p>
        <p>It has been five years since Syria's intervention ended the sectarian violence that had rocked Lebanon since 1975. But in a sign that war has once again touched quarters far removed from the battle front, dozens of refugees sat sprawled this afternoon in a Lebanese University classroom where first-year  architecture students should have been laboring over blueprints. And some were asking whether this country will ever again know what normal means.</p>
        <p>"Who knows what the Israelis will do," said Zana Ajani, 29, who said she and  her family would be in no hurry to return home to Nabatiye, a main target of the Israeli attacks. "They have no humanity. They say they won't shoot. But we've been shot at by them before."</p>
        <p>All 40,000 Lebanese University students have been forced outside since the Israeli campaign unloosed the flood of refugees from the south. Uprooted by the  civil war, and shut countless times by violence, the university and other schools in Lebanon have been closed since the Israeli attacks began on April 11.</p>
        <p>"We are used to getting by without," said Nisreen Itani, an 18-year-old architecture student, who has also been coping with a home overflowing with relatives who fled the fighting. "And what this month has reminded us is that what we have been living is a false peace."</p>
        <p>Outside many of Beirut's shops this afternoon, gasoline-powered generators remained ready to roar into action in anticipation of the power failures that have come half a dozen times a day since Israeli bombs hit two compounds on outskirts of Beirut last week.</p>
        <p>And instead of classes, the Lebanese University's School of Fine Arts, in its temporary headquarters, housed nearly 400 displaced people.</p>
        <p>Some said they hoped to hurry home as soon as it became clear that the agreement today would hold. But with so much of southern Lebanon's infrastructure wrecked by the bombardment, a delegation from the Health Ministry was sketching plans for a prolonged period in which the Government may still need to provide care for refugees, who United Nations officials say amount to 90 percent of the region's population.</p>
        <p>Among those waiting bitterly for an end to the fighting in one university classroom was Sara Hamoud, 50, who fled her village in southern Lebanon and who  said she had no idea what she will find when she returns.</p>
        <p>"I lost this leg in 1978," Mrs. Hamoud said, showing a withered stump that she said was a casualty of another Israeli incursion. "And they're still bombing our land."</p>
        <p>Once located in a historic building in central Beirut, the fine arts school has had to settle for temporary quarters for nearly 20 years, ever since its old structure and others like it were destroyed in sectarian fighting at the outset  of Lebanon's civil war.</p>
        <p>It was partitioned during the war years, along with the rest of the university, into four equal branches to accommodate a country rigidly divided along religious lines.</p>
        <p>Now that a civil peace has taken hold, many still harbor hopes that the institution can become an undivided Lebanese University again.</p>
        <p>But outside the fine arts school's latest site, students and some professors  also spoke with some frustration about what fate has dealt to Lebanon. They remembered the dozens of times in which classes were halted and spoke of their hopes that someone might somehow force Israel to reimburse Lebanon for the damage it has caused.</p>
        <p>The Lebanese are accustomed to disruption. But along with causing widespread  damage, the Israeli military campaign has compounded the level of dismay felt here, in part because this time the Lebanese do not believe they are at fault.</p>
        <p>"In the past, we felt that we were responsible for the damage, and that we were destroying ourselves," said Assad Deab, president of the Lebanese University. "Now we have a common enemy."</p>
        <p>MIDEAST ACCORD: IN LEBANON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
