<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marathoner's Mental Map Leads to the Olympic Trials</title>
    <meta content="08TRAC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1174898"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Columbia (Sc)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Lena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Anne Marie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DC143EF93BA35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marathoner's Mental Map Leads to the Olympic Trials</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LENA WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Lena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Anne Marie Lauck preparing for Olympic trials for women's marathon which will take place Feb 26 in Columbia, SC (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Olympic trials for the women's marathon will take place Feb. 26 in Columbia, S.C. But Anne Marie Lauck, who finished 10th in the 1996 Summer Olympics in Atlanta, has already run the 26.2-mile course over and over in her mind.</p>
        <p>She has played out the different and situations she will need to react to in the race and has mapped out the varying strategies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Olympic trials for the women's marathon will take place Feb. 26 in Columbia, S.C. But Anne Marie Lauck, who finished 10th in the 1996 Summer Olympics in Atlanta, has already run the 26.2-mile course over and over in her mind.</p>
        <p>She has played out the different and situations she will need to react to in the race and has mapped out the varying strategies.</p>
        <p>''I have a bunch of situations that I constantly play through my head,'' Lauck said yesterday at a luncheon of the New York Track Writers Association. ''I was just going over the course this weekend and playing out things in my head: where the different mile points are in the race and if I'm feeling good or not feeling good at this point.''</p>
        <p>Her head tells her that about the last six miles may be the toughest because the ''last 10K's of most marathons are,'' and that she should not worry about the competition but stick to what is best for her.</p>
        <p>Lauck's mental games have been necessitated by bad weather that has kept her from training outdoors. She has been running on a treadmill in her home of Hampton, N.J., for the last few weeks.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, she flew to South Carolina to examine the course. Running the last 22 miles Saturday helped put her mind at ease.</p>
        <p>''It got me excited because it felt very easy,'' the 30-year-old Lauck said. ''I really like this course, which is unusual because a lot of people are intimidated by it because it isn't a quick course. But I'm comfortable with it.''</p>
        <p>More than 200 women have qualified for the trials by running a marathon faster than 2 hours 50 minutes in the last two years, yet few have a realistic chance of earning one of the three spots available for the Summer Games in Sydney, Australia, in September. The winner of the trials will make the United States team regardless of her finish time, but the others must have met the Olympic standard of 2:33 at some point since last June.</p>
        <p>Entering the trials, Libbie Hickman, 35, of Fort Collins, Colo., has the fastest career time of 2:28:34, followed by Kristy Johnson, 34, of Shepherdstown, W.Va., at 2:29:05.</p>
        <p>Lauck ran a 2:37:59 qualifying time -- the 10th fastest -- last November to win the Philadelphia Marathon. She set her personal best of 2:30:19 with a third-place finish in the 1994 New York City Marathon.</p>
        <p>Lauck has had a difficult time in marathons since the 1996 Olympics. In 1997, Lauck broke her collarbone in a rock slide while vacationing with her husband, Jim, in Hawaii. The injury led to biomechanical problems that compromised her career. She dropped out of the Chicago Marathon that year and experienced problems in the 1998 New York City Marathon. Because of her injuries, Lauck contemplated retirement.</p>
        <p>But now she is feeling like her old aggressive self once again.</p>
        <p>''I know I can run between 2:30 and 2:32 on that course right now,'' Lauck said. ''And there are others who can do it too.''</p>
        <p>Lauck would not say how the images in her mind played out in the end, but said she was relaxed and remained focused.</p>
        <p>''I want to be able to react to certain moves and maybe to initiate some important moves and carry on my ability from '96,'' she said. ''That's a huge advantage for me, having made the team in 1996 and having that positive experience. I want to use that to my advantage.''</p>
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
