<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conservative Leader Says G.O.P. Can Do Better Than Mayor</title>
    <meta content="08CONS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1174929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Long, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7DB143EF93BA35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conservative Leader Says G.O.P. Can Do Better Than Mayor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>COLONIE, N.Y., Feb. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Conservative Party leader Michael Long, all but ruling out his party's support for Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani's Senate run, says that he would prefer that mayor drop out of race; says his party would readily nominate Representative Rick Lazio; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All but ruling out his party's support for Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's Senate run, the Conservative Party leader said today that he would prefer that the mayor drop out of the race, and said his party would readily nominate Representative Rick A. Lazio.</p>
        <p>''I think I would rather that he didn't run,'' the party chairman, Michael Long, said at a news conference at the party's annual conference here, near Albany.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All but ruling out his party's support for Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's Senate run, the Conservative Party leader said today that he would prefer that the mayor drop out of the race, and said his party would readily nominate Representative Rick A. Lazio.</p>
        <p>''I think I would rather that he didn't run,'' the party chairman, Michael Long, said at a news conference at the party's annual conference here, near Albany.</p>
        <p>Mr. Long, who has clashed with the mayor over abortion and other issues, also pointed out that Public Advocate Mark Green, a liberal Democrat, would become mayor if Mr. Giuliani was elected to the Senate with a year left in the mayoral term. ''He'd be doing the voters and the taxpayers a favor if he stayed as mayor,'' Mr. Long said.</p>
        <p>He argued that any number of other Republicans, like Mr. Lazio, who are more conservative but less polarizing than the mayor, would fare better against the Democratic candidate, Hillary Rodham Clinton. ''I submit to you if Rudy got out of the race and someone like, for instance, Congressman Lazio, got into the race, she loses,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio, who also attended the Conservative conference, had considered entering the Senate race earlier, and said today that he had not ruled out doing so, but added that if he did, he would want to be on the Republican line as well as the Conservative line.</p>
        <p>The mayor deflected questions today about Mr. Long's comments, and declined to say whether he would seek the Conservative Party nomination. ''Generally, what I am interested in is not what a political party thinks,'' he said. ''It is what the people in the state think.''</p>
        <p>While the Conservative Party is small -- its 170,000 registered voters are 1.6 percent of the state total -- it wields a disproportionate influence in state politics. In statewide elections, Republicans who also have the Conservative nomination can count on getting about 300,000 votes on that line, or 4 percent to 8 percent of the total vote, often enough to decide a close race.</p>
        <p>The dispute between Mr. Long and Mr. Giuliani has been simmering for months, as Mr. Long repeatedly complained that the mayor had not called him or met with him to discuss a possible endorsement. But their rift was deepened by many of the mayor's comments on television news programs on Sunday morning, the day of Mrs. Clinton's official announcement of her candidacy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani said on television that he would not change his position and support a ban on the abortion procedure that opponents call partial-birth abortion, although the Conservative Party has called such a  change in position a minimum condition for  considering endorsing him. If he is elected to the Senate, Mr. Giuliani said Sunday on ''Meet the Press'' on NBC, ''I would vote to preserve the option for women.''</p>
        <p>Appearing the same day on ABC's ''This Week,'' the mayor said: ''I'd like to run on all the lines. I'd like to run on the Liberal line, the Conservative line. I'd like to run on the Democratic line, if I could figure out how to do it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Long said today that if the mayor stood fast on the abortion issue, ''he doesn't get a ticket to the dance,'' meaning that party leaders would not even discuss backing him. But he also suggested that Mr. Giuliani would never make a long-awaited pitch for Conservative support, the closest Mr. Long has come to saying outright that his party would not nominate the mayor.</p>
        <p>Ever since Mr. Long and Mr. Giuliani talked briefly in March last year, Conservative Party leaders have been increasingly frustrated with Mr. Giuliani's refusal even to discuss the possibility of a pact. And several people close to Mr. Long said the mayor's comments on the Sunday talk shows might have been the final insult. Aside from Mr. Giuliani's unwillingness to compromise on abortion, his suggestion that party identity and party ideology are meaningless sounded to Conservatives like an attack on their reason for being.</p>
        <p>Mr. Long repeatedly used the word ''liberal'' to describe Mr. Giuliani, who has taken a range of positions, from supporting abortion rights to endorsing gay rights, that the Conservative Party opposes. And several times, Mr. Long questioned whether the mayor really planned to run, noting that Mr. Giuliani has not definitively stated his intentions.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Giuliani said: ''I have not given up anyone's endorsement. But the reality is I don't think that endorsements really matter, particularly in my case. I am well known. I have a record that people can look at and they can judge whether they like that record and they would like to see that kind of dedication, that kind of conscientiousness, that kind of hard work that I put out on behalf of people in the city done for the people of the state.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Giuliani narrowly leads Mrs. Clinton in public opinion polls, those surveys have reflected a two-way race, without a third, Conservative candidate. In any case, it is expected to be a close contest, and no Republican has won statewide office in New York without the Conservative nomination since Senator Jacob K. Javits and Attorney General Louis J. Lefkowitz were re-elected in 1974.</p>
        <p>New York is the only state that allows a candidate to be nominated by more than one party and to compile the votes received on the ballot lines of separate parties.</p>
        <p>The Conservatives have shown that by running their own candidates, they can play havoc with the Republicans. In 1990, when Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, a Democrat, might  have been vulnerable to a strong Republican challenge, the Conservatives nominated their own candidate, Herbert London, drawing more than 800,000 votes and helping assure Mr. Cuomo an easy victory.</p>
        <p>For months, Mr. Long has said that he was talking with a handful of people who might run on the Conservative line, though he has refused to name any of them.</p>
        <p>But today, he went out of his way to talk up the prospects of Representative Lazio as a more acceptable, more conservative Republican; it was intentionally provocative talk meant in part to tweak the Republican establishment. Mr. Lazio, from Suffolk County, had wanted to run for the Senate, and Gov. George E. Pataki was at first seen as promoting his candidacy. But in August, Mr. Pataki and others pressured him into stepping aside to clear the primary field for Mr. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>The governor and other party leaders have had rocky relations with Mr. Giuliani, but most consider him their party's best hope to capture a seat now held by a Democrat, Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, who is retiring. While many would prefer Mr. Lazio, they see him as a weaker candidate against Mrs. Clinton, and they want to avoid a primary fight and a party split in November.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's appearance here last night, playing host at a dessert reception for Conservative leaders, ''certainly raises speculation'' that the congressman still might run, Mr. Long said.</p>
        <p>''I think if he made a phone call, we're ready to move,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio said today, as he has before, that he has still not ruled out a run. ''I am thinking it through, and I have not closed the door,'' he said. But, he added, ''I would not pursue the Conservative nomination without pursuing the Republican nomination at the same time.''</p>
        <p>At the Conservative Party gathering, ''There was what I would characterize as overwhelming support for me to get into the Senate race,'' he said. ''It is very clear to me that if it is not me, there will be some other Conservative candidate,'' running to the mayor's right in November.</p>
        <p>Mr. Long revealed today that his party, which opposes abortion in all forms, has been conferring with the Right to Life Party about the possibility of both parties nominating the same candidate for Senate. ''Hopefully, we're going to do that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Conservative Party has laid down two conditions for considering a nomination of Mr. Giuliani: that he change his position on partial-birth abortion, and that he not accept Liberal Party support. The Liberal Party has been a crucial source of support for the mayor, but he and the party's leader, Raymond B. Harding, have refused to say what relationship they will have this year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harding said today that his party would decide this spring whom to support.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
