<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Quattrone Juror Says Three Wouldn't Budge</title>
    <meta content="27STAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/27/business/27star.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1530607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Credit Suisse First Boston</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Quattrone, Frank P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Credit Suisse</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Quattrone, Frank</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E3DA1131F934A15753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Quattrone Juror Says Three Wouldn't Budge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Quattrone Juror Says Three Wouldnt Budge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jurors comment on deliberations that led to hung jury in trial of former Credit Suisse First Boston official Frank P Quattrone on charges he obstructed justice and tampered with witnesses in government probe of way bank allocated stock offerings; suggest new trial would likely lead to another hung jury because of scant evidence in case (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the case of the United States v. Frank P. Quattrone, juror No.4 would not budge.</p>
        <p>At around noon on Friday, the juror, Michael Roman, a silver-haired graphic artist from Ossining, N.Y., told his fellow jurors for the final time that he and two others were not prepared to find Mr. Quattrone guilty of obstruction of justice and tampering with witnesses. Continuing deliberations in the case ''would be pointless,'' he argued, according to jurors who reconstructed the deliberations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the mistrial of Frank P. Quattrone, the former banker, prosecutors are considering whether to try him again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the case of the United States v. Frank P. Quattrone, juror No.4 would not budge.</p>
        <p>At around noon on Friday, the juror, Michael Roman, a silver-haired graphic artist from Ossining, N.Y., told his fellow jurors for the final time that he and two others were not prepared to find Mr. Quattrone guilty of obstruction of justice and tampering with witnesses. Continuing deliberations in the case ''would be pointless,'' he argued, according to jurors who reconstructed the deliberations.</p>
        <p>Later that afternoon, as Judge Richard Owen of Federal District Court in Manhattan declared a mistrial in Mr. Quattrone's trial, the immediate question became: Will the United States attorney's office in Manhattan retry the case?</p>
        <p>Prosecutors indicated during the trial that they would retry Mr. Quattrone in the event of a mistrial, but in interviews after the trial, some jurors suggested that the likelihood of another hung jury would be high because the scant evidence the case was based on would make it difficult for jurors to reach a unanimous verdict.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Roman's announcement kept the 11-member jury deadlocked after nearly six days of deliberations, Kenneth Shook, a retired architect who said he planned to find Mr. Quattrone guilty, wanted to keep debating. In just the previous two days, he and two other jurors, Peter H. Goodwin and Arlene Vrabel, had persuaded three other jurors to find Mr. Quattrone guilty, Mr. Shook said.</p>
        <p>Some jurors had seesawed on their vote from one day to the next as they tried to determine whether Mr. Quattrone obstructed justice and tampered with witnesses when he sent a one-line e-mail message on Dec. 5, 2000, to the investment bankers on his staff at Credit Suisse First Boston instructing them to follow the company's document retention policy, just days after learning of a government investigation into the way the bank allocated stock offerings.</p>
        <p>''Given his background, his education and his position, Quattrone would have had all his fingers on the buttons,'' Mr. Shook said in an interview yesterday that he had told his fellow jurors.</p>
        <p>But some jurors contended Mr. Quattrone was too smart to obstruct an investigation so overtly. To persuade them otherwise, some jury members mentioned scandals from the presidencies of Bill Clinton and Richard M. Nixon to show ''how a supposedly smart person could do something so stupid,'' Mr. Shook said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Roman and two other jurors, Mayo Villalona and Joyce James, were not convinced, according to the jurors. They stuck to their position throughout the deliberations because ''the evidence wasn't strong enough,'' Mr. Roman said as he left the courthouse on Friday. ''You had to make a leap.''</p>
        <p>Each side is likely to approach a second trial differently because each has seen the other's arguments.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quattrone's testimony appeared to create a major credibility problem with at least one juror when he denied under questioning by his lawyers that he had anything to do with the allocation of stock offerings, only to acknowledge under cross-examination that he did play a role.</p>
        <p>''He did a bad job going up there,'' said Mr. Villalona, a 26-year-old Manhattan resident who works at HSBC Holdings. ''I heard a lot of jurors say if he hadn't been a witness, it would have been 'not guilty' the first day.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Quattrone's testimony from the trial could be entered into evidence in a new trail.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors, on the other hand, may want to focus more on Mr. Quattrone's $120 million salary in 2000. ''Anyone making that kind of salary would be in a position to know anything and everything,'' Mr. Shook said he and other jury members felt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quattrone's lawyer, John W. Keker, had argued during his closing argument that the reason prosecutors mentioned Mr. Quattrone's salary was because they were ''trying to tap into the hatred and suspicion that people feel about corporate executives these days.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Quattrone would likely still face Judge Owen, who has repeatedly made rulings against him and made disparaging remarks about his lawyers. In a new trial, Judge Owen could be expected to narrow the evidence and testimony even more.</p>
        <p>Even then, it might be a difficult case to make, acknowledged Mr. Shook, who said he would like to see Mr. Quattrone retried. ''You had to put a lot of circumstantial evidence together,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
