<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Jewish Family's Stolen Legacy; Heirs Seek Restitution for Retail Empire Lost to Nazis</title>
    <meta content="24NAZI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/24/nyregion/24NAZI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1394916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Berlin (Germany)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Worth, Robert F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Principe, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany/Berlin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World War II</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E4DA163BF937A15756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1285" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Jewish Family's Stolen Legacy; Heirs Seek Restitution for Retail Empire Lost to Nazis</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Jewish Family's Stolen Legacy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT F. WORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Worth, Robert F</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barbara Principe of Newfield, NJ, who discovered only two years ago that her family controlled Wertheim department store empire in Berlin until Nazis forced family to give up everything they owned, sues current German owners of property for unspecified compensation and damages; parcels of land in Berlin that are now worth hundreds of millions of dollars; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barbara Principe remembers little of her early childhood in Nazi Germany. After her parents fled with her in 1939, traveling through Britain and Cuba to a chicken farm in South Jersey, they spoke only fleetingly of her Jewish family's old life in an opulent home outside Berlin.</p>
        <p>It was not until two years ago, at the age of 67, that she discovered that her family once controlled a profitable department-store empire in the heart of Berlin. She also discovered that the Nazis had forced the family to give up everything they owned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heirs to a Berlin retail empire have filed suit to regain restitution for what was lost to Nazis during World War II.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barbara Principe remembers little of her early childhood in Nazi Germany. After her parents fled with her in 1939, traveling through Britain and Cuba to a chicken farm in South Jersey, they spoke only fleetingly of her Jewish family's old life in an opulent home outside Berlin.</p>
        <p>It was not until two years ago, at the age of 67, that she discovered that her family once controlled a profitable department-store empire in the heart of Berlin. She also discovered that the Nazis had forced the family to give up everything they owned.</p>
        <p>Now Mrs. Principe and her nephew are suing the current German owners of the property for unspecified compensation and damages in Federal District Court in Manhattan, in what may be the largest single-family Holocaust-related suit ever. It is a legal battle over parcels of land in Berlin that are now worth hundreds of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the main defendant, KarstadtQuelle AG, Germany's largest retailer, say the suit should be dismissed because of prior Holocaust-related settlements. The United States State Department is deciding whether to ask the court to dismiss the suit on that basis, and is expected to issue a statement in the next few weeks.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Principe's father, Gunther Wertheim, who was struggling to make a new life in 1951, came to Manhattan to sign away all his rights to restitution for the property he had lost.</p>
        <p>He did so after he and his brother Fritz began the process to seek restitution in 1950, a lawyer for Mrs. Principe said. A lawyer and former adviser to the Wertheim family, Arthur Lindgens, traveled to New York from Germany and paid Gunther and Fritz Wertheim $9,200 each for the rights to their shares, insisting that the Wertheim department stores were ruined and the company's properties in East Berlin had been seized by Communist authorities. Mr. Lindgens's estate is also being sued by Mrs. Principe and her nephew; the lawyer for the estate would not comment.</p>
        <p>Using those shares, Mr. Lindgens, who was chairman of the company, and other German owners of Wertheim then quickly merged it with its main competitor, Hertie, another Jewish retailer that had also been taken over under the Nazis. KarstadtQuelle bought the merged companies in 1994. The company says it had $15 billion in sales in 2001.</p>
        <p>The 1951 deal came to light just two years ago because of the dogged sleuthing of Mrs. Principe's lawyers and a German graduate student at the Free University in Berlin who chose the Wertheim family as her Ph.D. subject. It formed the basis of the lawsuit, first filed in March 2001.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Principe, who lives in Newfield, N.J., a few miles from the farm where her parents settled half a century ago, stands to win hundreds of millions of dollars if her case succeeds. Her lawyers would retain one-third, but receive nothing if she loses.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for KarstadtQuelle filed a motion to dismiss the suit in early May. They contend that it is pre-empted by an agreement reached two years ago by the German government and major German companies to settle earlier suits brought by victims of Nazi slave labor.</p>
        <p>That agreement obligated the United States government to request the dismissal of future suits against German companies ''arising from the National Socialist era and World War II.'' Although the agreement included a fund to compensate some Nazi victims and their heirs, Mrs. Principe's lawyers say she would not be eligible under the law.</p>
        <p>But in a letter to American officials, the Jewish Claims Conference, which helped negotiate the slave-labor settlement, has said it does not apply to the Wertheim suit. ''This is not a claim arising from World War II, because the fraud alleged took place in 1951 and afterward,'' said Gideon Taylor, the executive vice president of the conference.</p>
        <p>Several legal scholars familiar with recent Holocaust claims say they agree. ''Given the facts of the case, the family should have their day in court,'' said Ruti Teitel, a professor at New York Law School who has written on international restitution law.</p>
        <p>Whatever the outcome, it is clear that the Wertheims, like so many European Jews, were cheated of their legacy. They founded the Wertheim corporation in 1875, which expanded until the 1930's.</p>
        <p>After taking power in 1933, the Nazis passed laws making it difficult, and eventually impossible, for Jews to own or operate businesses. The Wertheim empire, with eight large stores in Berlin, was a special target. The family was forced to give up its shares in the company to businessmen deemed Aryan.</p>
        <p>Several Wertheim family members died in concentration camps. Gunther Wertheim and his family survived, but he was in poor health and virtually penniless when they arrived in New Jersey in the early 1940's. He died in 1954. His brother Fritz, a death camp survivor, found a job as a cook in a mental institution.</p>
        <p>The loss of the stores might easily have been forgotten. Although Mrs. Principe's mother successfully sought restitution for the family's house outside Berlin, she did not tell her daughter the full story of the company. Her father was too bitter over his losses to say much about them, Mrs. Principe said.</p>
        <p>But in the early 1990's, Simone Ladwig-Winters, a graduate student at the Free University, discovered documents in an archive in Potsdam that showed how the Wertheim company's original Jewish owners were forced to give up their shares. In 1998, the Berlin Restitution Authority, which had issued compensation rulings on many East German properties stolen in the Nazi era, made her research part of its archive.</p>
        <p>In early 2000, one of Mrs. Principe's lawyers, Gary M. Osen, stumbled onto Ms. Ladwig-Winters's findings. The idea for the lawsuit was born when he found what he considers the most damning evidence: an agreement written by hand in New York City on Aug. 12, 1951, describing the anticipated merging of the Wertheim company and its major competitor, Hertie. That was several days before Mr. Lindgens, the former family adviser, persuaded Gunther and Fritz Wertheim to give up their shares.</p>
        <p>Mr. Osen said the company's new owners had kept that and other documents from seeing light because they prove that Gunther and Fritz Wertheim were cheated. It is true that no one knew how profitable the company would become in later decades. But even in 1951 dollars, the shares were worth far more than the brothers were paid, Mr. Osen said.</p>
        <p>It is far from clear that Mr. Osen will prevail. But Mrs. Principe and her nephew, Martin G. Wortham, say the battle will be half won if the suit is allowed to proceed in an American court so that the full truth of their family's betrayal can emerge. (The family changed the spelling of its name to Wortham after coming to the United States.)</p>
        <p>''These people are still making money off our family's name, and my father was told there was nothing left,'' said Mrs. Principe, who has 7 children and 16 grandchildren. She returned to Berlin last year and was astounded to find a vast department store with her parents' last name on it. ''It leaves you feeling not only flabbergasted but really angry.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
