<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pope Banishes a Shadow Left By Bulgaria's Tie to Shooting</title>
    <meta content="Y24POP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/24/international/europe/24POPE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1394888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bulgaria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sofia (Bulgaria)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanley, Alessandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">John Paul II (Pope)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weakland, Rembert G (Abp)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bulgaria/Sofia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Popes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Popes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bulgaria</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="online_producer">John Paul II</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E0DB163BF937A15756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pope Banishes a Shadow Left By Bulgaria's Tie to Shooting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pope Banishes a Shadow Left by Bulgaria's Tie to Shooting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
      <dateline>SOFIA, Bulgaria, May 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pope John Paul II tells throng of well-wishers in crowded square in Sofia, Bulgaria, that he bears no grudge over accusations that Bulgarian secret service may have tried to have him killed in 1981; says he loves Bulgarian people; his presence in Bulgaria provides kind of absolution government has long sought; even some Bulgarians doubt that men acquitted in pope's attempted murder were entirely innocent; pope's efforts to return attention to his peace-seeking missions in Eastern Orthodox territory are dimmed by news that Rembert G Weakland, another American bishop, is under suspicion in sex abuse scandal that is engulfing Roman Catholic Church in US: photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Paul II reassured Bulgarians this evening that he bore no grudge over accusations that the Bulgarian secret service may have tried to have him killed in 1981.</p>
        <p>''I say to all that I have never ceased to love the Bulgarian people,'' the pope told a throng of well-wishers crowding the square outside Alexander Nevsky Cathedral immediately after arriving from Baku, Azerbaijan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Paul II said he bore no grudge over accusations that the Bulgarian secret service may have tried to have him killed in 1981.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Paul II reassured Bulgarians this evening that he bore no grudge over accusations that the Bulgarian secret service may have tried to have him killed in 1981.</p>
        <p>''I say to all that I have never ceased to love the Bulgarian people,'' the pope told a throng of well-wishers crowding the square outside Alexander Nevsky Cathedral immediately after arriving from Baku, Azerbaijan.</p>
        <p>The ailing pope, who took language lessons in the Vatican before he left, began his speech in Bulgarian, but his quavering voice was hard to follow. When he reached the allusion to the 1981 assassination attempt, the pope turned his text over to an interpreter. The crowd responded with cheers.</p>
        <p>Three Bulgarians were charged with aiding the Turkish gunman, Mehmet Ali Agca, but were acquitted by an Italian court for lack of evidence. The verdict, in falling short of a clear ''not guilty,'' has cast a shadow on Bulgaria ever since.</p>
        <p>John Paul's five-day tour of Bulgaria and Azerbaijan is his first foreign trip since sex abuse scandals began engulfing the Roman Catholic Church in the United States.</p>
        <p>But the pope's efforts to return attention to his peace-seeking missions in Eastern Orthodox territory were dimmed by news that yet another American bishop, Rembert G. Weakland, archbishop of Milwaukee, is under suspicion.</p>
        <p>Archbishop Weakland acknowledged he paid $450,000 to settle a sexual assault complaint against him by an adult male student 20 years ago, though he denied the charges.</p>
        <p>The pope did not mention the matter tonight, and his press secretary made it clear the Vatican did not want the scandal to seep into the papal journey. ''As a matter of procedure, we do not comment on topics, even big ones, while we are away from the Vatican out of courtesy for the country we are visiting,'' the spokesman, Joaquin Navarro-Valls, said tonight. ''When we return to the Holy See, a comment is possible.''</p>
        <p>Once a Communist state, Bulgaria wants a Vatican stamp of approval as it seeks entry to the European Union and NATO. The pope's presence in Bulgaria provides the kind of absolution the government has long sought. Even some Bulgarians doubt the acquitted men were entirely innocent.</p>
        <p>''We want to apologize that it happened and show him that the Bulgarian people did not have anything to do with his attempted murder,'' Venka Misteva, 65, an economist, explained as she waited for a glimpse of the first pope ever to visit Bulgaria.</p>
        <p>The pope wants another chance to visit a mostly Eastern Orthodox country after previous trips to Romania, Georgia and Ukraine, steppingstones in his lifelong goal of mending the 1,000 year rift between Roman Catholicism and Eastern Orthodoxy.</p>
        <p>In Baku earlier today, the pope tried to show his good intentions by promising $20,000 toward the million-dollar ransom that Chechen bandits have demanded from Azeri Orthodox Church leaders for the return of one of their clerics.</p>
        <p>Patriarch Maxim of Bulgaria attended the welcome ceremony today, led by Bulgarian President Georgi Parvanov, but kept an icy distance.</p>
        <p>The two religious leaders will meet when the pope pays a courtesy call on Friday, but no joint prayer services are planned. ''We did not invite him,'' the patriarch said recently. ''We only responded to his desire to visit us.''</p>
        <p>Orthodox leaders fear that the wealthier, more powerful Catholic church is using reconciliation as a Trojan horse to push into Orthodox territory and convert their believers.</p>
        <p>The pope got a warmer response from Orthodox believers in Azerbaijan, where they form a tiny minority of that mostly Muslim nation and find common cause with the even tinier Catholic community of 120 people, including expatriates.</p>
        <p>It took many hundreds of foreign visitors and Muslim guests to fill the 5,000 seats in the Palace of Hard Ball Games where the pope celebrated mass this morning. ''Thrilled and flabbergasted,'' is how James Tilley, an Oklahoma oilman in Baku who assisted at the altar, said he felt when he heard the pope was coming so far for so few.</p>
        <p>During the service, the Baku congregation also felt a moment of fear when a man on crutches scuttled through the crowds and came within 15 feet of the pope before security guards grabbed him. After determining that the man, Kazim Azizov, an addled Azeri refugee from Armenia, was harmless, security guards escorted him back to the altar so he could kiss the pope's hand and receive a papal blessing.</p>
        <p>Tamara Akhundova, an Azeri Muslim, said she was moved. ''To me the pope looks like a very old, sick man who has a lot of love in his heart.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
