<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Talent Cradled in London And Nourished by New York</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="805201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONDON, ENGLAND, UK</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKS, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEWART, PATRICK</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">TEMPEST, THE (PLAY)CITY:  LONDON, ENGLAND, UK</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E3DF1639F933A05753C1A963958260" item-length="1253" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Talent Cradled in London And Nourished by New York</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKS, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1993, Patrick Stewart went to London to perform his one-man version of "A  Christmas Carol" for the hometown crowd. In New York, his performances of the work over the two previous Christmas holidays had been sold-out sensations, the  audiences so thrilled at watching him act out an entire Dickens novel that they  laughed even before the punch lines.</p>
        <p>But at the Old Vic theater in London, there were no waves of love or laughter radiating from the audience on opening night. The crowd sat stone-faced as Mr. Stewart anxiously went through his paces as Tiny Tim and Bob Cratchit and Scrooge, material that had seemed sure-fire on the other side of the Atlantic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1993, Patrick Stewart went to London to perform his one-man version of "A  Christmas Carol" for the hometown crowd. In New York, his performances of the work over the two previous Christmas holidays had been sold-out sensations, the  audiences so thrilled at watching him act out an entire Dickens novel that they  laughed even before the punch lines.</p>
        <p>But at the Old Vic theater in London, there were no waves of love or laughter radiating from the audience on opening night. The crowd sat stone-faced as Mr. Stewart anxiously went through his paces as Tiny Tim and Bob Cratchit and Scrooge, material that had seemed sure-fire on the other side of the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>I played to almost total silence," said Mr. Stewart, who is to star in "The Tempest," which opens on Wednesday at the Broadhurst Theater. "I was in a total  state of panic. There was no indulgence, no overt generosity. I felt I was on trial."</p>
        <p>And of course, he was. Theater is to London what fine red burgundy is to, well, Burgundy. So when Mr. Stewart returned to the British stage after years in the United States as a performer on "Star Trek: The Next Generation," he was instantly reminded of how much more demanding audiences there could be. The only thing to do, he said, was to raise the level of his performance and win over the crowd.</p>
        <p>"In London, they make you work for it," Mr. Stewart said the other day as he  sat in his Manhattan apartment high above Third Avenue. "I just think that acting here in New York is more fun. When I think of London, I think of drama. When I think of New York, I think of show biz."</p>
        <p>Few actors working today have bridged the worlds of drama and show biz more successfully than the 55-year-old Mr. Stewart, who spent years playing classical roles with the Royal Shakespeare Company in England before finding huge commercial success in the United States as Capt. Jean-Luc Picard on "Star Trek." Now, armed with the technique acquired in London and the money and fame earned in Hollywood, Mr. Stewart has the skill and the following to bring the two worlds together. Which is precisely what he is doing this season, as the star of a Shakespeare play on Broadway.</p>
        <p>And not one of Shakespeare's traditional crowd-pleasers. Not a zippy "As You  Like It" or a bloody "Macbeth" or a raucous "Taming of the Shrew." Mr. Stewart is Prospero in the New York Shakespeare Festival's production of "The Tempest,"  an esoteric work that scholars describe as one of Shakespeare's "problem" plays. It was such a critical and popular success during its run in Central Park last summer, however, that George C. Wolfe, who heads the festival and directed the play, decided to move it to Broadway.</p>
        <p>"Watching 1,900 people rise to applaud and cheer 'The Tempest'!" Mr. Stewart  marveled as he recalled his summer in the park. "It's not 'Hamlet.' And they were reacting like it was 'Sunset Boulevard.' "</p>
        <p>That the festival finds itself on Broadway with Shakespeare for the first time since 1972, when Sam Waterston and Kathleen Widdoes starred in "Much Ado About Nothing," is in no small measure due to Mr. Stewart. The transfer, in fact, was predicated on his participation. It is a strange and gratifying turn of events for an actor who was unknown in this country a few years ago. And odder still that an interlude on television should be a major factor in how a classically trained English actor gets to Broadway in a classical role.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart is a bit ambivalent about his television success: pleased at the  economic freedom it has provided ("That's 'Star Trek,' " he said, showing a picture of a 315-year-old farmhouse in the north of England that he bought with  earnings from the show) but worried that the impression he made in seven seasons as the Star Fleet captain will obscure his stage accomplishments. Because Mr. Stewart, despite his television experience and a growing film career -- he managed to steal a scene or two in the recent "Jeffrey" -- still thinks of himself as a stage actor. And it is on the stage, always the stage, where English actors prove themselves.</p>
        <p>He has been doing the classics since his boyhood in Mirfield, a village in Yorkshire where theater was as ubiquitous as pick-up rugby matches. "In my small town, there were 9,000 people and 11 fully active drama societies," Mr. Stewart said. By the age of 15 he had played Richard III, Leontes and Prospero.  "Every church, every chapel, you had plays," he added. "Those were possibly the  most idyllic days of acting, and it was all just for fun."</p>
        <p>After training at the Bristol Old Vic, Mr. Stewart joined the Royal Shakespeare Company. In 1968 he came to New York for the first time, appearing with the renowned company in "As You Like It" and "The Taming of the Shrew." Two years later, he returned to the United States in another Shakespeare production  that some theatergoers regard as one of the most memorable theater nights in their lives: Peter Brook's legendary 1970 staging of "A Midsummer Night's Dream."</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart had a small part in "Dream," that of Snout, the tinker. He would  work again with Mr. Brook in the mid-1970's, playing Enobarbus in "Antony and Cleopatra," a production he remembers better for what happened during rehearsals than for the performances.</p>
        <p>"The aura of mystique and magic around Brook I found to be unfounded," Mr. Stewart said. "I felt his technique was based on absolute common sense." He recalled a rehearsal period with the five other principal actors, including Alan Howard and Glenda Jackson, in which they were called on to perform all the parts in the play. Mr. Brook had placed a script on a carpet; anyone could pick  it up and start to read. "It was one of the most thrilling experiences of a play that I've ever seen," he said. "It was as if I was experiencing the play for the first time."</p>
        <p>But little in Mr. Stewart's theatrical training had prepared him for Hollywood. Having come from a society obsessed with status by birthright, he was stunned to discover that he was entering a subculture with almost as rigid a hierarchy. "A New York producer once said to me, 'In Hollywood, people define themselves by what they won't do,' " Mr. Stewart said. "Like, 'I don't do TV daytime.' " As an actor in a syndicated series, Mr. Stewart learned that his rung on the ladder was lower than that of feature film and prime-time network television stars.</p>
        <p>But in New York, Mr. Stewart has never felt anything less than a celebrity with a permanent key to the city. Just as New Yorkers seem to have embraced his  performances, so has Mr. Stewart embraced New York.</p>
        <p>"I feel, as a performer, for the first time in my life I'm understood," he said, gazing out the kitchen window at the rooftops of the Upper East Side. "I think America is good for me."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
