<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Fashion;The Old World via the Bay Area</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="805188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITE, CONSTANCE C R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GALINDO, CESAR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, WYNN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DF1639F933A05753C1A963958260" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Fashion;The Old World via the Bay Area</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE C. R. WHITE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITE, CONSTANCE C R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a study of successful entertainers a few years ago, it was determined that one thing they shared was the chance to develop their skill away from the hubs of their profession. The implication was that creativity was best nurtured away  from potentially crushing competition and in an environment conducive to developing an individual point of view.</p>
        <p>Such may be the case with Wynn Smith, who staged his first show at the Linda  Dresner boutique, at 484 Park Avenue (59th Street). Based in San Francisco, Mr.  Smith turns out the most unlikely clothes for a West Coast designer. The support of Ms. Dresner, who is known for her store's stern presentation of cutting-edge  European high fashion, says as much.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a study of successful entertainers a few years ago, it was determined that one thing they shared was the chance to develop their skill away from the hubs of their profession. The implication was that creativity was best nurtured away  from potentially crushing competition and in an environment conducive to developing an individual point of view.</p>
        <p>Such may be the case with Wynn Smith, who staged his first show at the Linda  Dresner boutique, at 484 Park Avenue (59th Street). Based in San Francisco, Mr.  Smith turns out the most unlikely clothes for a West Coast designer. The support of Ms. Dresner, who is known for her store's stern presentation of cutting-edge  European high fashion, says as much.</p>
        <p>There is something Old World European about the approach of the 31-year-old  Mr. Smith. The interpretation, however, is an original hybrid affected no doubt  by his decision to set up shop in San Francisco, though he could easily fit into any leading fashion city.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith presented both his signature collection and Wink, a new secondary line. Ms. Dresner and some models in the show wore T-shirts provided by Mr. Smith that had the word "Wuss" printed on them, suggesting the clothes were either a sendup of wimpy ladylike fashion or a glorification of such. Well, if you're going to dress like a wuss, do it Mr. Smith's way.</p>
        <p>He teamed an asymetrically cut jacket of proper Prince of Wales plaid with a  knee-length leather python-print skirt. A boxy black reptile-print jacket had no fasteners, its matching bell-leg pants slung insolently below. White denim bootleg jeans sat below a fitted couturelike double-breasted crop peacoat. Mr. Smith finished off a ladylike navy cotton sateen skirt suit with latex gloves: perhaps the perfect accessory for the busy urban woman who goes straight from lunch to perform an operation in the surgical room?</p>
        <p>Though one might want to skip the gloves and the five-and-dime bedroom slippers with which Mr. Smith accessorized many outfits, they were a great improvisation for a designer long on ideas and short on cash.</p>
        <p>Cesar Galindo refined his Latin mode this season with delectable tea dresses  and pistol-sharp cocktail pants suits worthy of any samba-tinged soiree. There were even confectionary names for the hues the designer used for his most sugary styles, like candy pink for a satin pouf dress fitted in the bodice and belling  gently over the legs.</p>
        <p>A key-lime satin dance dress was festooned with one big bow in the front at the waist. A glazed pink gown's shimmery polka dots on closer inspection turned  out to be constellations of clear sequins.</p>
        <p>At the Westcott-Fenasci show yesterday, a large video screen projected a serene blue seascape filmed entirely underwater. A lone diver was depicted swimming balletically in one languid dress after another. It was the perfect backdrop for the simple evening dresses presented on mannequins by the design team of Carla Westcott and Eugene Fenasci. The two promote a philosophy of minimal detail, one in which a woman does not wear her fashion sense on her sleeve.</p>
        <p>Tiny, piquant bows sat on either side at the hip of an ink-blue V-neck gown in silk charmeuse. Minute Swarovski crystals ringed the empire seam and waist-high seam on a style in white silk georgette.</p>
        <p>Christian Blanken has moved from an otherworldly esthetic into the wider world of fashion trends. And there is no bigger trend right now than color. Mr.  Blanken had loads of it -- cobalt, orange, chartreuse. He twice melded them with other trends -- ski-inspired ribbed knits and ultrasuede sportswear.</p>
        <p>In taking the commercial-trend approach, Mr. Blanken faces an important challenge: preserving his nascent identity as a distinctive designer. Since in the past, some of Mr. Blanken's work has been overly eccentric, next season holds real hope that he may find the right balance.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
