<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets Turn to a Rookie to Back Up Martin</title>
    <meta content="15jets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/15/sports/football/15jets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1709697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Buffalo Bills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Bills</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Houston, Cedric</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Martin, Curtis</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EEDC143FF936A25753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets Turn to a Rookie to Back Up Martin</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jets Turn to a Rookie to Back Up Martin</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Oct. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rookie Cedric Houston has to be prepared to step into the spotlight Sunday and play like Curtis Martin when the Jets face the Buffalo Bills on the road.</p>
        <p>With the fifth-year running back Derrick Blaylock sidelined for six to eight weeks with a broken right foot, Houston assumes the role of backup to Martin, who led the National Football League in rushing last season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cedric Houston has to be prepared to step into the spotlight Sunday and play like Curtis Martin when the Jets face the Buffalo Bills on the road.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The rookie Cedric Houston has to be prepared to step into the spotlight Sunday and play like Curtis Martin when the Jets face the Buffalo Bills on the road.</p>
        <p>With the fifth-year running back Derrick Blaylock sidelined for six to eight weeks with a broken right foot, Houston assumes the role of backup to Martin, who led the National Football League in rushing last season.</p>
        <p>''That's his role for the weekend,'' Coach Herman Edwards said. ''If something should happen to Curtis, he's going to play. And if something doesn't happen to Curtis, he's going to give him a breather, at least.''</p>
        <p>It is a formidable assignment, especially considering that Houston, 23, was inactive for the first three games and does not have a regular-season carry.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Edwards pronounced Houston ready, and perhaps for good reason; Edwards saw how well Houston was able to step into the shoes of someone else during the rookie talent show last month, when Houston did a dead-on impersonation of Edwards.</p>
        <p>Houston imitated Edwards delivering one of his motivational speeches, and also told jokes as if he were auditioning to be Cedric the Entertainer.</p>
        <p>''He was really good,'' Edwards said. ''I was like, 'Is that Cedric Houston talking?' because he never says anything. He was a pretty good comedian. He had some pretty good one-liners. He was on a roll.''</p>
        <p>Houston, whom the Jets selected in the sixth round of the draft in April, is a different player than the one who barely made an impression during the Jets' minicamp. That Houston was chubby, to use Edwards's word, and unable to practice because of a thyroid condition that was uncovered during a physical examination at the N.F.L. combine in Indianapolis in February.</p>
        <p>The diagnosis explained why Houston tired easily throughout his collegiate career at Tennessee. Despite frequently having to go to the sideline during games to catch his breath, Houston ran for 1,005 yards and averaged 5.6 yards a carry as a senior.</p>
        <p>He started taking medication for his thyroid condition under the supervision of the Jets' medical staff. By the start of training camp in late July, Houston said he was feeling better than he had in years. ''I feel like I'm in the best shape of my life,'' he said recently, and added, ''I'm not even on medication any more.''</p>
        <p>Houston is a power runner who spent a lot of time this week on goal-line running and pass-blocking drills.</p>
        <p>''When you bring a young guy in, everyone always wonders, well, how is he going to run?'' Edwards said. ''That's not my concern. It's how does he pick up the protections, the blitz? That's what you always worry about with young running backs. Can he pick up the protection when they start bringing those guys off the edge and we get a pass?''</p>
        <p>Houston conceded that ''my blocking schemes have been pretty tough,'' but said he was not concerned. ''You've just got to get up there and know what you're doing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He earned laughter and applause in the talent show with that attitude. On Sunday, he will be trying to win his teammates' approval on a much bigger stage.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
