<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Caracas Asks U.S. to Help On Oil Output</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="385565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VENEZUELA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEREZ, CARLOS ANDRES (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DC1431F932A1575AC0A966958260" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Caracas Asks U.S. to Help On Oil Output</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela, Sept. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The President of Venezuela, citing an ''inevitability of confrontation'' in the Middle East, is urging the United States to invest in increased oil production in this South American nation, which holds the largest proven oil reserves outside the Middle East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The President of Venezuela, citing an ''inevitability of confrontation'' in the Middle East, is urging the United States to invest in increased oil production in this South American nation, which holds the largest proven oil reserves outside the Middle East.</p>
        <p>The President of Venezuela, citing an ''inevitability of confrontation'' in the Middle East, is urging the United States to invest in increased oil production in this South American nation, which holds the largest proven oil reserves outside the Middle East.</p>
        <p>''Venezuela is the safe, sufficient and reliable bridge towards energy self-sufficiency for the Americas,'' Carlos Andres Perez said in an interview on Monday at the presidential palace here. ''With the Orinoco Belt, Venezuela has the second-largest oil reserves in the world, after Saudi Arabia.''</p>
        <p>Venezuela's light-to-heavy reserves - those that are easily refined - are 59 billion barrels. But the Orinoco Belt, a 20,000-square-mile area north of the Orinoco River in eastern Venezuela, contains 270 billion barrels of extra-heavy bitumen oil, which is less economical to refine but is now being tapped with an experimental technology. A Leading Source for U.S.  Venezuela has alternated with Saudi Arabia as a leading source of foreign oil for the United States, which buys two-thirds of Venezuela's production. To help the world market cope with the current oil crisis, Mr. Perez has ordered a 25 percent increase in production, to 2.5 million barrels a day, by December.</p>
        <p>But he said that with American private and public investment, he could almost double Venezuela's production capacity to five million barrels a day by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, if the crisis in the Middle East explodes in a conflagration that damages the oil wells of the region, the energy crisis will convert into an energy catastrophe,'' Mr. Perez said. ''We can produce more, but we don't have the wells to pump out the oil.''</p>
        <p>In contrast to Venezuela's ambitious expansion plans, Mexico, the other large exporter to the Americas, is experiencing a decline in output and is expected to become a net importer within 15 years.</p>
        <p>''The hemisphere should see the oil problem with a strategic vision,'' said Mr. Perez, who plans to pursue his proposal on a visit to New York in 10 days.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, Venezuela's Minister of Energy and Mines, Celestino Armas, visited Washington and proposed to American officials and business executives the creation of ''a hemispheric strategic oil production capacity.''</p>
        <p>U.S. Concerns Bought Out</p>
        <p>In a change of policy, Mr. Armas encouraged American oil companies to invest in refining and production in his country, which has the lowest production costs of any nation in the Western Hemisphere. American oil companies operating in Venezuela were bought out in 1975 under a nationalization program.</p>
        <p>With a tight budget in Washington, American officials have said they favor increasing Venezuelan production through private investment.</p>
        <p>Talks to discuss the proposed plan have been hampered because of bureaucratic reasons in Washington. The United States has not had an ambassador accredited here since July 1989. Confirmation hearings for the new Ambassador-designate, Michael M. Skol, are to be held next week.</p>
        <p>At the palace, Mr. Perez played down reports here that with oil prices almost tripling in three months, Venezuela had hit a jackpot. He estimated that his country would earn an extra $800 million this fall - money that would go to servicing foreign debt and for increasing oil production. The country's total foreign debt is around $34 billion.</p>
        <p>No Discouts to Cuba</p>
        <p>In recent days, Government officials have battled reports that international development banks are using high oil prices to justify reducing low-interest loans to Venezuela.</p>
        <p>The President also ruled out selling oil at a discount to Cuba. Evidently lured by rising world oil prices, the Soviet Union said last month that it would cut by 20 percent its shipments of inexpensive oil to Cuba. In response, the Cuban Government announced last week the purchase of hundreds of thousands of bicycles to help Cubans get around without cars and buses.</p>
        <p>''Even though Cuba is from our region, it does not share our system,'' said Mr. Perez, who heads one of Latin America's longest-running democracies.</p>
        <p>Returning to his vision of oil-rich Venezuela guaranteeing the hemisphere's self-sufficiency in energy, Mr. Perez said his proposal was congruent with President Bush's plan for a hemispheric free-trade zone.</p>
        <p>''With the creation of the European Common Market, of the Asian market around Japan, the United States needs an alliance with Latin America,'' Mr. Perez said. ''This is a market of 500 million people, with tremendous natural resources.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
