<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Justices Say Suspects Can Be Held Up to 48 Hours Without Warrant</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="445395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARREST WITHOUT WARRANT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFUGEES AND EXPATRIATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASYLUM, POLITICAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED SPECIES ACT (1973)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RIVERSIDE COUNTY (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDA133FF937A25756C0A967958260" item-length="1428" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Justices Say Suspects Can Be Held Up to 48 Hours Without Warrant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court ruled today that people who are arrested without a warrant may be imprisoned for as long as 48 hours while awaiting a judicial determination of whether the arrest was proper.</p>
        <p>The 5-to-4 decision set aside a Federal court order, issued in a lawsuit brought by prisoners against Riverside County, Calif., that had established a 36-hour deadline for a judicial determination of whether the police had probable cause to arrest someone without a warrant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court ruled today that people who are arrested without a warrant may be imprisoned for as long as 48 hours while awaiting a judicial determination of whether the arrest was proper.</p>
        <p>The 5-to-4 decision set aside a Federal court order, issued in a lawsuit brought by prisoners against Riverside County, Calif., that had established a 36-hour deadline for a judicial determination of whether the police had probable cause to arrest someone without a warrant.</p>
        <p>Under the California county's policy, the determination was supposed to be made within 48 hours, not counting weekends and holidays. But delays of three or four days were common if an arrest occurred on the eve of a weekend or holiday.</p>
        <p>The ruling today may not have a sweeping effect nationwide, since many states already meet the standard set by the Court.</p>
        <p>Writing for the majority, Justice Sandra Day O'Connor said that while delays of three or four days were unreasonable, the lower courts' choice of a 36-hour deadline was not required by the Constitution. "In our view," she said, "the Fourth Amendment permits a reasonable postponement of a probable-cause determination while the police cope with the everyday problems of processing suspects through an overly burdened criminal justice system."</p>
        <p>In a dissenting opinion, Justice Antonin Scalia said a 24-hour delay was the most that could be tolerated without violating common-law traditions and the Fourth Amendment's prohibition against "unreasonable" seizures.</p>
        <p>Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and Justices Byron R. White, Anthony M. Kennedy and David H. Souter joined the majority opinion. Justices Thurgood Marshall, Harry A. Blackmun and John Paul Stevens dissented in another opinion.</p>
        <p>Most states appear to have handled probable-cause determinations more expeditiously than the Court required today. New York law, as interpreted by the state courts, forbids a delay of more than 24 hours from arrest to arraignment. Most states have laws that bar "unnecessary delay."</p>
        <p>While those states are now theoretically free to relax their current procedures, there is no indication of widespread eagerness to do so. The American Bar Association has recently recommended a delay of no more than six hours during the day, with a longer delay permitted if the arrest takes place at night.</p>
        <p>Two legal scholars said the decision, coming from a Court increasingly deferential to police concerns, was not surprising. "This Court gives weight to the needs, convenience and practical problems of law enforcement officials," said Yale Kamisar of the University of Michigan Law School.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Kamisar and Barry C. Scheck of Cardozo Law School in New York found the spirit of the case disturbing. "Pulling someone off the streets and putting him in jail for 36 hours without any showing of probable cause goes against basic American principles," Mr. Scheck said. "But as they become overburdened, criminal justice systems are willing to cheat at the margins."</p>
        <p>Justice O'Connor said a 48-hour deadline was an appropriate balance between "important competing interests," which she identified as the states' concern for public safety and the individual's interest in not being subject to "prolonged detention based on incorrect or unfounded suspicion."</p>
        <p>A delay of more than 48 hours could be justified in the case of an emergency or "other extraordinary circumstance," Justice O'Connor said. On the other hand, she added, a determination that could have been made sooner but that is delayed for 48 hours out of "ill will" or for the illegitimate purpose of "gathering additional evidence to justify the arrest" might be unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>Arrests made without warrants are common occurrences as, for example, when the police witness what appears to be a crime in progress.</p>
        <p>In a 1975 decision, Gerstein v. Pugh, the Supreme Court ruled that arrests without warrants were not necessarily unconstitutional as long as they were followed by a "prompt" judicial determination of whether the police had probable cause to believe that a crime had been committed. The 1975 decision did not define the word "prompt."</p>
        <p>The decision today, County of Riverside v. McLaughlin, No. 89-1817, vacated a ruling by the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit, in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The decision was notable for both for Justice Souter's vote with the majority and Justice Scalia's departure from his usual allies in a vigorously worded dissenting opinion.</p>
        <p>Justice Souter's views are still sufficiently unknown that his vote in contested cases is of particular interest. So far this term, he has written only one opinion. There is little doubt that this case would have come out the other way had Justice Souter's predecessor, William J. Brennan Jr., still been on the Court.</p>
        <p>In fact, there were some indications that the case would come out the other way when the Justices cast their preliminary votes after the argument on Jan. 7. It is possible that Justice Scalia or one of the other dissenters was originally writing a majority opinion, but that Justice O'Connor picked up a fifth vote. She has written two other majority opinions in cases argued the week of Jan. 7, an unusual assignment pattern for the Court.</p>
        <p>In his dissenting opinion, Justice Scalia traced the history of arrests without warrants in support of his conclusion that a minimal delay was all that was permitted both in English common law and at the time the Fourth Amendment was drafted.</p>
        <p>"While in recent years we have invented novel applications of the Fourth Amendment to release the unquestionably guilty, we today repudiate one of its core applications so that the presumptively innocent may be left in jail," Justice Scalia said.</p>
        <p>The Court was unanimous on one significant portion of the opinion. The county had argued that the prisoners who brought the class-action lawsuit in 1988 did not have legal standing to do so, because they would be either released or held on a determination of probable cause by the time a court could decide the case. But all Justices agreed today that the case was not moot, and that the class-action procedure had been the proper way to obtain a ruling on the merits of the constitutional argument.</p>
        <p>The Court accepted eight new cases for decision today, including these:  Refugee Status</p>
        <p>The Court agreed to decide whether foreigners who flee their countries to avoid forced service in the ranks of guerrilla armies qualify for asylum in the United States under the Refugee Act of 1980.</p>
        <p>The case is an appeal by the Bush Administration from a ruling last year by the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit. The appeals court ruled that a Guatemalan man, Jairo J. E. Zacarias, was eligible for asylum because he faced persecution for his political beliefs if he returned to his village.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zacarias had fled at the age of 19 after two masked men carrying machine guns had come to his home to recruit him to their effort to overthrow the Guatemalan Government. When he refused, they told him to "think it over well" because they would be back.</p>
        <p>To qualify for asylum under the Refugee Act, an alien must demonstrate a "well-founded fear of persecution on account of race, religion, nationality, membership in a particular social group, or political opinion."</p>
        <p>In its appeal, Immigration and Naturalization Service v. Zacarias, No. 90-1342, the Adminstration is arguing that the Ninth Circuit had given too broad a reading to the term "political opinion."  Endangered Species</p>
        <p>Accepting an appeal by the Bush Administration, the Court agreed to decide whether the Endangered Species Act applies overseas. The United States Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit, in St. Louis, ruled last year that Federal agencies financing a project in foreign countries must insure that the project is not likely to harm any endangered or threatened species.</p>
        <p>The Departments of Interior and Commerce, which administer the Endangered Species Act, had at one point taken the view that the law did apply overseas. But the Government's official position changed in 1981. This case, Lujan v. Defenders of Wildlife, No. 90-1424, is the result of a lawsuit brought in 1986 by several environmental groups seeking a declaration that the new regulations were erroneous.</p>
        <p>In its appeal, the Administration is arguing that the organizations did not have standing to bring the lawsuit, and that the Eighth Circuit's ruling would cause "serious injury to the nation's foreign relations and foreign aid programs."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
