<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In 'Rugrats,' Babies Know Best</title>
    <meta content="30SCHM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1042569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmuckler, Eric</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rugrats (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6DA143CF933A0575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In 'Rugrats,' Babies Know Best</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMUCKLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmuckler, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Schmuckler reviews Rugrats, animated Nickelodeon television series popular among children 2 to 11; cartoon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOUR babies are sitting in a playpen, and 1-year-old Tommy Pickles is trying to persuade his scaredy-cat pal Chuckie to jump the fence in search of adventure. ''Someday you'll be 6 years old,'' Tommy says with his usual bravado. ''Do you want to look back then and say you never really lived?''</p>
        <p>As most American parents of young children know, Tommy and Chuckie are the heroes of ''Rugrats,'' the animated Nickelodeon series that is the most popular television show among children 2 to 11, according to Nielsen Media Research provided by Nickelodeon. Created to appeal across the board to young and old children as well as families, it is a quirkily drawn show that describes the world from a child's-eye-view, a vantage that is often uncomprehending but always slyly observant. Along the way, the show makes good-natured but biting fun of career-obsessed working moms, daydreaming dads, cranky grandparents and our media-driven consumer culture.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOUR babies are sitting in a playpen, and 1-year-old Tommy Pickles is trying to persuade his scaredy-cat pal Chuckie to jump the fence in search of adventure. ''Someday you'll be 6 years old,'' Tommy says with his usual bravado. ''Do you want to look back then and say you never really lived?''</p>
        <p>As most American parents of young children know, Tommy and Chuckie are the heroes of ''Rugrats,'' the animated Nickelodeon series that is the most popular television show among children 2 to 11, according to Nielsen Media Research provided by Nickelodeon. Created to appeal across the board to young and old children as well as families, it is a quirkily drawn show that describes the world from a child's-eye-view, a vantage that is often uncomprehending but always slyly observant. Along the way, the show makes good-natured but biting fun of career-obsessed working moms, daydreaming dads, cranky grandparents and our media-driven consumer culture.</p>
        <p>''Rugrats'' has catapulted Nickelodeon to its current dominance of children's television. Its premiere made a decent showing in 1991, just as the 11-year-old channel was gaining a foothold; when it later went into daily reruns, its ratings jumped, much to the surprise of network executives. In contrast to quick-burning kiddie crazes like ''Mighty Morphin Power Rangers'' and ''Goosebumps,'' ''Rugrats'' shows remarkable staying power; after seven seasons, ratings are higher than ever. Nickelodeon deals its ace as often as possible: the series is shown weekdays at 8:30 A.M. and 7:30 P.M, Saturdays at 8 P.M. and Sundays at 10 A.M. A dozen or more episodes routinely place in the top-50-cable-shows rankings each week, helping make Nickelodeon the nation's top-rated basic cable network.Inevitably, the series has developed all the trappings of a full-fledged, cash-spouting franchise: everything from T-shirts to toothpaste, a touring stage show, a daily comic strip and, in November, a feature film, which is already generating heavy playground buzz.</p>
        <p>''It's reached a kind of phenomenon status,'' says Nickelodeon's president, Herb Scannell. ''We think in some ways this is our Mickey Mouse.''</p>
        <p>Like ''Sesame Street'' and ''Animaniacs,'' ''Rugrats'' is one of those rare shows that works for both children and grown-ups.</p>
        <p>''Kids appreciate the way kids get confronted by the adult world and adults are amused by the lampooning of the harried life of parents today,'' says Mr. Scannell. The show's theme: ''It's tough to be a kid in an adult world. Kids don't always get it right and adults don't always have all the answers. In that sense, it's a manifesto of the Nickelodeon philosophy.''</p>
        <p>The rugrats are led by Tommy, a bald, scrappy underdog, and fretful Chuckie, who sports a tangle of orange-red hair and Buddy Holly-esque square-framed glasses. The twins Lil and Phil function as a Greek chorus. Then there's Angelica, the bratty, bossy know-it-all who lords it over the babies from her lofty 3-year-old perch but invariably gets her comic comeuppance.</p>
        <p>The babies don't talk in front of grown-ups but hold marvelously skewed discussions about the mysterious adult world. For instance, Lil and Phil have deduced that a wristwatch is actually called a ''time'' because the grown-ups are always pointing to their wrists and saying, ''Look at the time!''</p>
        <p>The show is filled with child-friendly slapstick. In one episode, Tommy joins Grandpa for a supermarket run in search of a box of Reptar cereal (Reptar is the faux-Godzilla toy craze within the series). Tommy sneaks off and accidentally clears off shelves, turns a huge pile of watermelons into a tsunami and sleds down a crumbling display on a cereal box, laying waste to the store.</p>
        <p>Many throwaways gags are aimed at baby-boomer parents watching with their children. Tommy's mother, Didi, frequents a frozen yogurt and antique emporium named Cold 'n' Oldies. At the mention of ''Dances With Wolves,'' one slow-witted dad says, ''I didn't see it; I don't really like musicals.'' And what other children's show would refer to the Velvet Underground in a punch line?</p>
        <p>The satire is more pointed in sending up modern-day family issues, like overauthoritative parenting experts (''These pop-up books foster delusional behavior!'' one barks). Angelica's mother, Charlotte, is a go-go corporate raider with a cell phone glued to her ear and pet fish named Vesco and Boesky. She explains her work to Angelica this way: ''A corporation is like a big, hungry monster. My job is to find plenty of smaller, weaker monsters for it to eat.''</p>
        <p>After wrecking a big deal (by destroying the presentation props), Angelica tremulously asks, ''Mommy, are you going to fire me?''</p>
        <p>In a medium of overgrown animals and jumpsuited superheroes, ''Rugrats'' goes for authenticity in its setting and concerns.</p>
        <p>''It's about a contemporary American family that lives in the real world; it just happens to be animated,'' says Mr. Scannell.</p>
        <p>Tommy's father, Stu, and Angelica's father, Drew, are brothers with a vigorous sibling rivalry. Grandparents squabble over cards. The Pickles family is half-Jewish, with a set of grandparents who speak with a thick Yiddish accent. Special episodes about Hanukkah and Passover -- the latter featuring Angelica as the Pharaoh and Tommy proclaiming ''Let my babies go!'' -- were highly praised as holiday primers.</p>
        <p>The show's tone is always sunny and usually silly but can also be poignant. A Mother's Day special last spring delved into the story of why Chuckie doesn't have a mother. The comedy revolved around the children's efforts to find him a suitable mom. First they tried the dog. Then Angelica took charge and changed his name to Blaine, because it sounded like a ''TV name.'' In the end, Chuckie found a box of his mother's things and his father told him an age-appropriate version of the loss of his mother, ending with a beautiful poem she had written for him from the hospital.</p>
        <p>''Rugrats'' was created by Arlene Klasky; her then-husband, Gabor Csupo (pronounced SHOO-po), and Paul Germain. (The couple have since divorced but remain amicable partners in Klasky-Csupo and produce ''The Wild Thornberrys,'' Nick's new animated series about a family on safari.) Ms. Klasky remembers her own years as a working mother as ''part of my inspiration.''</p>
        <p>''I didn't know what I was doing,'' she explained. ''I used all the childhood development books.'' She sees some of herself in Didi, the gentle former schoolteacher, but adds, ''If you ask my kids now, I may be becoming Charlotte.''</p>
        <p>Discussing the series' runaway success, Ms. Klasky cites the appeal of the characters and the show's unique look. The authentic, childlike voices and the acting also have a great deal to do with it. And the writing, of course. The stories are simple and deal with basic children's issues like friendship or overcoming simple fears.</p>
        <p>About the only criticism of ''Rugrats'' that Nickelodeon has heard is that the parents seem to leave their progeny unattended a lot. But Mr. Scannell says that is simply a device to give the children a chance to talk. Children's-television observers also give the show a thumbs-up. Peggy Charren, founder of Action for Children's Television, an advocacy group, says: ''It's fun. It has a little edge, but not a bad edge. I wouldn't call it educational in the narrow sense, but it's warm and friendly and kids love it.''</p>
        <p>Katharine Heintz-Knowles, a former assistant professor of communications at the University of Washington who studies the effects of children's television, praises the show but prefers to watch with her 5-year-old daughter ''in order to help put it in context.''</p>
        <p>''There's some stuff very young kids might take as literal, like when the babies crawl into the mailman's bag to be delivered or pile up pieces of furniture to reach the cookie jar, and sometimes Angelica's language is not the kind of thing I'd want to hear in my house,'' Ms. Heintz-Knowles continues. ''Overall, though, it's very clever and very creative, and I'm glad they've got some new episodes. We could recite the old ones by heart.''</p>
        <p>Having conquered television, this gang is headed for the multiplex with ''The Rugrats Movie,'' opening at Thanksgiving. Regular viewers already know the Pickles family is going to have a new baby, Dylan (Dil Pickles, for short). The film offers  wilder action than the series, as well as a soundtrack featuring hip ''Rugrats'' fans like Beck, Jakob Dylan, Patti Smith and Elvis Costello. The sequel is already in the works.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION Eric Schmuckler writes for various publications about the mass media, particularly television.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Eric Schmuckler writes for various publications about the mass media, particularly television.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
