<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patterns</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="750027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITE, CONSTANCE C R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDF1739F932A15750C0A963958260" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patterns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Constance C. R. White</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITE, CONSTANCE C R</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ellin Saltzman Keeps Busy</p>
        <p>Ellin Saltzman has been very much in evidence at the European collections on her first foray into the ready-to-wear shows as corporate fashion director for the Limited Inc. There had been speculation that Ms. Saltzman, who has been fashion director of some of America's most expensive stores, would be unwelcome representing a lower-price retailer with a mammoth private-label business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ellin Saltzman Keeps Busy</p>
        <p>Ellin Saltzman has been very much in evidence at the European collections on her first foray into the ready-to-wear shows as corporate fashion director for the Limited Inc. There had been speculation that Ms. Saltzman, who has been fashion director of some of America's most expensive stores, would be unwelcome representing a lower-price retailer with a mammoth private-label business.</p>
        <p>Ms. Saltzman said she was viewing the shows in her capacity as fashion adviser to Henri Bendel, which is owned by the Limited. "I'm here functioning for Henri Bendel in much the same way I functioned at Macy's in relation to I. Magnin," said Ms. Saltzman, who was at most of the shows with Ted Marlow, who was named president of Henri Bendel earlier this year.</p>
        <p>While Ms. Saltzman's road in Paris appears to have been smooth, there were bumps in Milan. She acknowledged that she was not invited to Gianni Versace's show; her understanding was that the house does not invite nonclients. Zoran, a key Bendel resource, said Ms. Saltzman did not attend his presentation because he would not accommodate her request to bring along the Bendel team. Ms. Saltzman said her presence was unnecessary since other Bendel executives were on hand.</p>
        <p>She said she would be working with Mr. Marlow to develop new resources for the store, starting with Dolce &amp; Gabbana and Lawrence Steele, which were picked up on this trip. Azzedine Alaia Prepares</p>
        <p>As the ready-to-wear shows here began winding down, the contrarian Azzedine Alaia was in his atelier above his store on Monday preparing a new line. As usual, he was vague on when it would be finished and when it might hit stores.</p>
        <p>He was serving lunch to a small coterie, including Regis Pagniez, publication director of Elle; Franca Sozzani, editor in chief of Italian Vogue; Ingrid Sischy, editor of Interview, and the designer Vivienne Westwood. But he took time out to provide a small preview.</p>
        <p>Leather worked in intricate new ways will be prominent in the new collection. One creation begins with horsehair-like fiber looped and stitched onto layers of leather in red, aqua and black. The leather inside the loops is cut out, to be filled with transparent plastic or mirrors. An unfinished black wool dress fitted through the bust and waist had satin insets down the back, descending below the ankle with a grand sweep. Faces Become Softer</p>
        <p>As clothes on the runways of Europe lose their vixen edge, the face is softening up, too. The look is still feminine, but ruby-red lips and harsh eyeliner have been returned to the makeup kits of drag queens. Eyes this season were lined faintly, if at all; lips were frosted and foundations sheer. Cheeks bore the slightest hint of blush. "The idea is to have faces that look very pure," Karl Lagerfeld said. "We used a lot of mother-of-pearl in the makeup."</p>
        <p>Francois Nars, a makeup artist who worked on the shows of Gianni Versace, Valentino and Rifat Ozbek, among others, said he and others were borrowing from different decades to come up with something new. He achieved the toned-down look with whitewashed colors on the lips, translucent powder and blush and short, feathered false eyelashes instead of eyeliner.</p>
        <p>Like several makeup artists who are becoming stars in their own right on the fashion circuit these days, Mr. Nars has his own line of cosmetics, at Barneys. Several of the lipstick shades he will introduce in April will be in the pale frosted tones evident on the runways here. A Feraud Introduction</p>
        <p>As the grand old names of French fashion age, so do customers who grew up with them. The key is to expand the customer base before the name loses value. And so for fall, Louis Feraud will introduce Expressions by Louis Feraud in the United States. "This collection is closer to the body, a little sexier, a little more feminine," said Gloria Gelfand, president of Louis Feraud U.S.A. Expressions -- the name is pending legal approval -- is designed by Judi Jordan, an American living in Paris, and will be manufactured in France.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
