<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEHIND THE WHEEL/2007 Lexus LS 460; A Luxury Liner, Not a Love Boat</title>
    <meta content="10AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/10/automobiles/autoreviews/10AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20061217T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1810875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Behind the Wheel"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lexus Division of Toyota Motor Sales Usa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ulrich, Lawrence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE1DD1731F933A25751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEHIND THE WHEEL/2007 Lexus LS 460; A Luxury Liner, Not a Love Boat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It’s a Luxury Liner, Not a Love Boat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE ULRICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ulrich, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Behind the Wheel review of 2007 Lexus LS 460; photos; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS history buffs are fond of saying, you can lose the battle but win the war.</p>
        <p>That bromide surely describes the Lexus LS sedan, now entering its fourth generation as the LS 460. Since its inaugural year of 1989, this Japanese flagship has received its share of cannonballs from auto critics. Its styling has been dismissed as a Mercedes knockoff. Its soothing driving experience, a bit like doing the breaststroke in a gravy boat, can't match the athletic moves of a BMW 7 Series. For design panache, it's no Audi A8. And with Toyota on its coat of arms, it lacks the pedigree of Jaguar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Lexus LS sedan, now entering its fourth generation as the LS 460, keeps rolling while its trouble-prone rivals are stuck in the shop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS history buffs are fond of saying, you can lose the battle but win the war.</p>
        <p>That bromide surely describes the Lexus LS sedan, now entering its fourth generation as the LS 460. Since its inaugural year of 1989, this Japanese flagship has received its share of cannonballs from auto critics. Its styling has been dismissed as a Mercedes knockoff. Its soothing driving experience, a bit like doing the breaststroke in a gravy boat, can't match the athletic moves of a BMW 7 Series. For design panache, it's no Audi A8. And with Toyota on its coat of arms, it lacks the pedigree of Jaguar.</p>
        <p>But every year, when the smoke clears, a funny thing happens: the Lexus LS handily outsells them all, in part because it keeps rolling while its trouble-prone rivals are stuck in the shop.</p>
        <p>The LS 460 is more of the same, easily the most user-friendly of the big luxury cars and a magnificent long-distance tourer. But despite its endless virtues, the Lexus still isn't the stuff of executive daydreams or nightclub fantasies.</p>
        <p>For the first time, buyers can choose two sizes: the LS 460, starting at $61,715, or the $71,715 LS 460 L, which gets a nearly five-inch stretch for a roomier back seat.</p>
        <p>The V-8 engine, the first all-new design since Lexus' opening year, delivers the cruise-ship power expected in this class: 380 horsepower and 367 pound-feet of torque from a mere 4.6 liters.</p>
        <p>This silken, sophisticated engine is joined to the world's first eight-speed automatic transmission, one-upping Mercedes's seven speeds. The gearbox shifts almost imperceptibly and helps the LS hum from 0 to 60 miles an hour in just 5.4 seconds. Yet cruising at 65 m.p.h. in eighth gear -- with the engine loafing at a near-silent 1,600 r.p.m. -- the Lexus returned 30 miles a gallon, remarkable for such a big, mighty machine. My mileage exceeded the federal highway rating of 27 m.p.g. (18 in town). Over all, I got 21 m.p.g. in my test car.</p>
        <p>An adaptive air suspension and optional variable-ratio steering deliver effortless comfort and control. As ever, the LS isn't especially sporty. In this class, if you want hot handling, you go with BMW or, one better, with a Maserati Quattroporte.</p>
        <p>Instead of thrills, it's all about chill: The LS 460 L I tested was reading-room quiet, as relaxing as a four-star resort. Visually, the cabin may lack the boutique dazzle of Audi or Mercedes, but the materials and finishes are fully on par. For instance, the LS's steering wheel leather is buffed twice and gets a special water-based dye for a pleasing look and feel. Outside, the flawless paint is hand-sanded twice.</p>
        <p>The latest edition of the fabulous, optional Mark Levinson audio system features 19 speakers and 450 watts, plus a hard drive that holds up to 2,000 songs from CD's -- though the drive cannot store tunes from an iPod. (You can play your iPod through the system, however.)</p>
        <p>Except for one gimmicky feature, not one function required a trip to the owner's manual -- or the maddening trial and error required on some German models just to find the ballgame on the radio. (Isn't that the point of a luxury car, to make life easier rather than harder?) The Lexus touch screen, which controls the navigation, climate and audio systems, remains the class benchmark for intuitive operation.</p>
        <p>The one unconvincing feature is the ''advanced parking guidance system.'' This $1,200 option lets the car parallel-park itself or back into a space between two cars. A screen displays a camera view of the intended space, overlaid with a rectangular grid that you adjust to confirm the final destination. After that, you simply feather the brake and the car steers itself into place. Theoretically.</p>
        <p>In practice, the system often took multiple tries over several minutes before docking successfully. It struggled to identify curbs and regularly asked me to realign the car before trying to park. The parking space has to be huge, at least five feet longer than the car, calling the entire exercise into question. And the system shuts down if you back up too fast.</p>
        <p>My advice: If your parking skills are so bad that you need a robotic rescue, hire a driver and take the executive seating package instead.</p>
        <p>This $12,675 option (available only on the stretch version) comes closest to giving the Lexus the cachet it covets. Both its rear seats can be reclined, heated or cooled. And the right-side chair features a deeper, 45-degree recline plus an extending ottoman -- imagine a first-class airliner seat, complete with a remote control for ''shiatsu,'' or stretch massage, in varying strengths.</p>
        <p>Sensors measure rear passengers' body temperatures in three zones and adjust the climate control accordingly. The package also adds a DVD entertainment system with a vivid nine-inch display; fancier leather and headliner; power sunshades for the rear doors; a box that cools beverages; and a center console with a Bentleyesque folding table of polished wood.</p>
        <p>The only thing missing, my wife suggested, was a power pedicure.</p>
        <p>The fixed center console limits riders to two in back, and the package significantly reduces trunk space to 12 cubic feet, down from 18 in cars without it, to accommodate a separate rear air-conditioner. And there's only one V.I.P. seat, because fully extending the ottoman requires pivoting the front passenger chair forward via a rear console control.</p>
        <p>Parents be warned: Plopping siblings in back will be sheer fratricide as they vie for the junior V.I.P. chair. But the real-deal executive could indeed hire a chauffeur and simulate the Roll-Royce or Maybach experience for a fraction of the price.</p>
        <p>Laden with options, the LS 460 L test car checked in at $92,120.</p>
        <p>This powerhouse of luxury, quality and technology demands respect, but it still doesn't spark much lust. Blame the styling again, a letdown considering the momentum Lexus showed with its handsome IS and GS. Those sedans are perhaps the most distinctive Lexuses yet, but the LS takes a safer approach. The result is another apologetic Asian design, a doughy blend of BMW 7 Series and Toyota Avalon.</p>
        <p>The look is so, well, acceptable -- and you expect a grander adjective for a car that can top $90,000. (The hybrid LS 600h arrives in spring with a price that can hit six figures.)</p>
        <p>Like a brain surgeon who dreams of being a rock star, Lexus imagines its new LS as a hotter, more desirable machine. But really, what's wrong with being a brain surgeon? Once again, men and women unmoved by flash will happily settle down with this brilliant, sensible and successful Lexus.</p>
        <p>INSIDE TRACK: A thrilla in vanilla.</p>
        <p>Behind the Wheel</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 17, 2006, Sunday  A chart with a review of the Lexus LS 460 L last Sunday misstated some specifications of the car. Its weight is 4,332 pounds, not 4,475; its highway mileage rating is 27 m.p.g., not 25; and its peak torque is 367 pound-feet, not 370. In addition, it is a shorter model, the LS 460, that has a base price of $61,715. As noted in the review, the LS 460 L starts at $71,715.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 17, 2006, Sunday</p>
        <p>A chart with a review of the Lexus LS 460 L last Sunday misstated some specifications of the car. Its weight is 4,332 pounds, not 4,475; its highway mileage rating is 27 m.p.g., not 25; and its peak torque is 367 pound-feet, not 370. In addition, it is a shorter model, the LS 460, that has a base price of $61,715. As noted in the review, the LS 460 L starts at $71,715.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
