<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Girl Stricken With Rare Form of Encephalitis</title>
    <meta content="31DISE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1058251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilogoren, Jodi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Neal L (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2DE153FF932A05753C1A96E958260" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Girl Stricken With Rare Form of Encephalitis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JODI WILGOREN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bronx teen-ager has contracted rare and often fatal disease, Eastern equine encephalitis, first such case reported in New York City and only third time a person in New York State has been afflicted with virus; Dr Neal L Cohen, city's Health Commissioner, says girl is improving (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Bronx teen-ager has contracted a rare and often fatal disease, Eastern equine encephalitis, the first such case reported in New York City and only the third time a person in New York State has been afflicted with the virus, health officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The 16-year-old girl, whom the authorities would not identify, has returned home after 12 days in a Bronx hospital. She has been ill since late September, but her condition has improved, said Dr. Neal L. Cohen, the city's Health Commissioner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Bronx teen-ager has contracted a rare and often fatal disease, Eastern equine encephalitis, the first such case reported in New York City and only the third time a person in New York State has been afflicted with the virus, health officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The 16-year-old girl, whom the authorities would not identify, has returned home after 12 days in a Bronx hospital. She has been ill since late September, but her condition has improved, said Dr. Neal L. Cohen, the city's Health Commissioner.</p>
        <p>''She's out of the woods,'' Dr. Cohen said. ''We can't speak to whether she's 100 percent, or 90 percent, or so-and-so, but she's much better.''</p>
        <p>Medical literature indicates that this strand of encephalitis, known as EEE, has a 30 percent to 60 percent mortality rate. It is extremely rare. Dr. Cohen said there have been only 172 cases nationwide in the last 35 years.</p>
        <p>A Rhode Island man died of the disease in June. The two previous New York State cases were also fatal; the most recent was in 1983, when the virus killed a 7-year-old boy from Onondaga County.</p>
        <p>The virus is transmitted by mosquitoes and wild birds and cannot be passed from human to human. The mosquitoes that carry the virus are not common in New York City, though two Long Island parks were closed briefly in September 1997 when the mosquitoes carrying the virus were found there. They have also been discovered in recent years in Connecticut and New Jersey, and a 69-year-old man in Plainville, Mass., contracted the disease last year.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cohen said the potential danger was low, noting that the mosquito season had passed. On Friday, he said, city officials set four mosquito traps in Bronx neighborhoods and came up with just one mosquito, but it was not yet known whether the mosquito was a carrier.</p>
        <p>''The likelihood now is that with the colder weather, we may not find any mosquitoes with the potential to carry this virus,'' Dr. Cohen said. ''If there were mosquitoes that were carrying the virus, the period of greatest risk of infection would have been last month, not currently.</p>
        <p>''As the weather gets even colder, it will eliminate even the low index of suspicion we would have that there could be any potential risk,'' he added.</p>
        <p>City officials said the unusually mild winter and hot summer may have brought the rare mosquitoes here. Other New Yorkers would most likely have contracted the virus around Labor Day, if at all, they said.</p>
        <p>Though the Bronx girl has been sick for more than a month, city officials said they were notified of the diagnosis only yesterday. In addition to searching for mosquitoes throughout the city, Dr. Cohen said officials would check hospitals for any other potential cases.</p>
        <p>Encephalitis, a swelling of the brain, typically starts with a high fever, stiff neck and headaches, but often leads to brain damage or death. City health officials would not provide any further details of the Bronx girl's condition or identify her doctors or the hospital she stayed in.</p>
        <p>There is a vaccine to treat the disease in horses, but none for humans. Only the symptoms can be addressed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
