<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tourism Thrives on the Coattails of Kykuit</title>
    <meta content="TOURISM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1017513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kykuit (Rockefeller Mansion)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River Valley (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tarrytown (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rockefeller Family</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Singer, Penny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Hudson Valley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E2D61630F934A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tourism Thrives on the Coattails of Kykuit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PENNY SINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Singer, Penny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kykuit, Rockefeller family estate in Tarrytown, NY, has become national and international tourist destination and catalyst for revival of tourism in Hudson Valley; economic implications described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE jewel in the crown, the magnificent mansion, the big fish, the cash cow. No matter how Kykuit is described, the Rockefeller family estate in Tarrytown has become a national and international tourist destination, bringing economic benefit in its wake.</p>
        <p>''Kykuit, opened on May 1 for its fifth season, has become the catalyst for an unprecedented revival of interest in tourism in the Hudson Valley, which translates into an increase in revenue for businesses in the region,'' said Burns Patterson, marketing director for Historic Hudson Valley, the nonprofit organization that administer Kykuit, a property of the National Trust for Historic Preservation, and five other sites in the Hudson Valley.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE jewel in the crown, the magnificent mansion, the big fish, the cash cow. No matter how Kykuit is described, the Rockefeller family estate in Tarrytown has become a national and international tourist destination, bringing economic benefit in its wake.</p>
        <p>''Kykuit, opened on May 1 for its fifth season, has become the catalyst for an unprecedented revival of interest in tourism in the Hudson Valley, which translates into an increase in revenue for businesses in the region,'' said Burns Patterson, marketing director for Historic Hudson Valley, the nonprofit organization that administer Kykuit, a property of the National Trust for Historic Preservation, and five other sites in the Hudson Valley.</p>
        <p>Kykuit has been so successful in attracting visitors, Mr. Patterson said, that the site has become a victim of its own success. ''During our first year of operation, we had 116,000 visitors,'' he said. ''Last year the number more than doubled to 243,000, and since each tour is limited to a fairly small number of visitors, getting reservations was difficult. But this year we've expanded in several directions in order to accommodate more people.''</p>
        <p>This season at Kykuit, Mr. Patterson said, visitors have two tour options, one of which is the special garden and sculpture tour, introduced last year on a limited basis. It is now available full time through Nov. 1, expanding the site's capability to handle more visitors. The other is the house and garden tour.</p>
        <p>Susan T. Greenstein, Kykuit's new  program director and formerly with the New York Botanical Garden, said the Garden and Sculpture tour is a guided walk through the gardens, fountains and modern sculpture on the estate. ''The focus is on the fabulous sculpture, breathtaking landscape and the Beaux-Arts garden design of William Welles Bosworth, which is one of the few intact Beaux-Arts gardens in America,'' Ms. Greenstein said. ''The Rockefeller family were very involved with the planning of the gardens, and the evolution of the gardens is illustrated during the tour.''</p>
        <p>Parts of the estate, which were not available on the original tour but are now open, include the Morning Garden, the Grand Staircase and the Italian Garden, she said.</p>
        <p>As for the art on display, it is remarkable.</p>
        <p>''Gov. Nelson Rockefeller's extraordinary collection of 20th-century sculpture, including the works of Picasso, Alexander Calder, Henry Moore and Louise Nevelson, are on display throughout the gardens,'' Mr. Patterson said. ''Some pieces, including Picasso's 'Bathers,' Isa Noguchi's 'Black Sun' and Karel Appel's 'Mouse on Table' have never been shown in public before, a real feast for art lovers.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Greenstein recommends the house and garden tour for first-time visitors.</p>
        <p>''The rooms are furnished with fine English and American pieces, portraits and family photographs,'' she said. ''However, it is apparent that this is a family home, not a museum. Visitors, especially those from overseas, often are surprised that the house is so livable.''</p>
        <p>Tourism has been growing in importance every year as a source of revenue in the county, said Georgia G. Kalayjian, president of the Westchester Convention and Visitors Bureau in White Plains.</p>
        <p>Efforts to attract European tourists who have a penchant for visiting gardens and historic houses have been increased, Ms. Kalayjian said.</p>
        <p>''We're gong to promote Kykuit at an upcoming meeting of select foreign tour operators in Chicago,'' she said.''We're also going to market the site at a world travel meeting in London.</p>
        <p>''The Rockefeller name is known around the world.'' People want to see their home. Kykuit is the big fish that draws tourists in, and the smaller fish eventually benefit. Larger numbers of European and Asian tourists are now eager to travel outside Manhattan. They want to see the countryside. They visit our attractions, stay at our hotels, eat in our restaurants, shop at our stores. They bring in new dollars, which are very good for our economy,''</p>
        <p>Estimates show the average Kykuit day tripper spends $59 in the county on gas, restaurants, and the like, Ms. Kalayjian said. And for every overnight hotel stay, $189 is the average amount spent besides the cost of the room.</p>
        <p>This season, for the first time, the Castle at Tarrytown is offering two getaway tie-in packages, the Sleepy Hollow and Rockefeller tours to Kykuit and Sunnyside, the home of Washington Irving, combined with a two-night stay at the authentic turn-of-the-century castle, now a hotel.</p>
        <p>Rates range from $770 for a king-size double room to $1,490 for a large suite with a living room and a wood-burning fireplace. Packages include  a Continental breakfast each morning, a dinner for two at the Equus restaurant in the hotel, a picnic lunch for two on the day of the tours and admission to the historic sites. The package is available until Oct. 31, but it must be reserved in advance.</p>
        <p>The Castle also has a lunch-lecture package tie-in with Kykuit, which is new this year. The package, titled ''Relive the Golden Age,'' is available on May 27 and June 3. On those days, the tour of Kykuit will be followed by lunch and a lecture by Ms. Greenstein at the Equus restaurant in the Castle. For reservations for all events, the number to call at the Castle is 631-1980.</p>
        <p>The Renaissance Westchester Hotel in White Plains is also offering  promotional tie-ins with Historic Hudson Valley. ''We're advertising with them, and we're hooked up to their Web site,'' said Fred J. Heintz, director of marketing of the Renaissance Westchester Hotel. ''During the week our occupancy rates are good, running about 80 percent. But weekends are slow, averaging about  55 to 60 percent. We'd like to bring that up to 70 percent. Maybe the expanded program at Kykuit will  stimulate business.''</p>
        <p>For ease in obtaining reservations to Kykuit, Mr. Patterson said: ''Visitors can now reserve tickets on the Internet rather than by phone. And they will get a saving of 10 percent or more when they do.''</p>
        <p>Tickets to Kykuit may also be bought through New York Waterway, which offers a combination package including a Kykuit tour and a Hudson River cruise. Ticket prices, which include Kykuit and admission to Philipsburg Manor in Sleepy Hollow, the round-trip cruise and ground transportation, are $60. The number to call for information on the New York Waterway packages is (800) 533-3779.</p>
        <p>Kykuit is open every day except Tuesdays through Nov. 1. Each tour costs $18, $17 for people older that 65 and $16 for children 12 and older.  Tours are not recommended for children younger than 12. Tickets are available by phone at 631-9491 or on line at www.hudsonvalley.org.</p>
        <p>''I hope those who come to see Kykuit will also visit our other historic sites,'' Mr. Patterson said. ''Sunnyside, Philipsburg Manor, Van Cortlandt Manor, Montgomery Place and the Union Church are all unique and wonderful in their own way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
