<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children's Books in Brief</title>
    <meta content="RV103904" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1017467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Jan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jordan, Sandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spires, Elizabeth</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Chuck Close Up Close (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E2D91331F934A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children's Books in Brief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Elizabeth Spires</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spires, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elizabeth Spires reviews book Chuck Close Up Close by Jan Greenberg and Sandra Jordan (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chuck Close Up Close</p>
        <p>By Jan Greenberg and Sandra Jordan.</p>
        <p>DK Ink/DK Publishing, $19.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 8 and up)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chuck Close Up Close</p>
        <p>By Jan Greenberg and Sandra Jordan.</p>
        <p>DK Ink/DK Publishing, $19.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 8 and up)</p>
        <p>In the late 1960's the New York artist Chuck Close came to prominence by painting monumental heads -- his own and those of good friends -- in an intensely photorealistic manner. The 7-by-9-foot paintings were aggressive and, at times, almost unpleasant, but Close's technique quickly captured the art world's attention.</p>
        <p>Now Jan Greenberg and Sandra Jordan have written an inspiring biography of Close, published recently to coincide with a retrospective exhibition of his work at the Museum of Modern Art in New York (continuing through May 26). The authors chronicle Close's struggles as a child with a severe learning disability, detailing the ridicule he was subjected to from unkind teachers and children, and his retreat into art, magic and puppetry. Full-page color illustrations detail Close's evolution as a painter over the past 30 years, from his early gargantuan heads in stark black and white to ones of varying sizes, some in color, in which he employed different media and materials, using an airbrush and even his own fingertips to apply the paint.</p>
        <p>When Close was suddenly paralyzed from the chest down 10 years ago by the collapse of a spinal artery, his doctors and friends thought he would never paint again. But after months of intense rehabilitation, Close overcame a disability more severe than anything he had experienced as a child. Seen up close, his recent portraits are complex grids composed of tiny swirling squares, circles and ovals of color within color -- small abstractions pulsing and vibrating with life, like giant amoebas, or blown-up pixels from a television screen. Viewed from across a room, the multiplicity of vibrant forms coalesces into the recognizable likenesses of the same friends and family members he has been painting all these years. The resulting images are more compelling and approachable than Close's early work ever was.</p>
        <p>''Chuck Close Up Close'' is a simply written yet fascinating account of how nearly insurmountable obstacles can often spur artistic growth. A helpful glossary, a bibliography and a brief discussion of other artists' portrait styles over the centuries are included at the end of the book -- all useful in giving young readers a context for Close's own work. His story is sure to interest not only those children who possess an imaginative, artistic bent, but also the many who have ever felt themselves to be unhappily different from the herd.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Spires</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
