<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stewart Keeps His Points Lead in the Rain</title>
    <meta content="Y28AUT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/28/sports/othersports/28AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1435807"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Napa 500 (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nobles, Charlie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Busch, Kurt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stewart, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEEDA173FF93BA15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stewart Keeps His Points Lead in the Rain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Stewart Keeps His Points Lead in the Rain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nobles, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>HAMPTON, Ga., Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kurt Busch wins Napa 500 auto race; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Atlanta Motor Speedway officials persuaded Nascar this year to change the date of the NAPA 500 from its spot as the final race on the Winston Cup schedule, where it had been since 1996, to today because of recurring rain problems. It did not help.</p>
        <p>On a day turned so nightmarish by rain that there was a delay of 2 hours 26 minutes and the race finished under the lights, Tony Stewart moved closer to the Winston Cup Series points championship as 24-year-old Kurt Busch won his second straight race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tony Stewart moved closer to the Winston Cup Series points championship as 24-year-old Kurt Busch won the NAPA 500.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Atlanta Motor Speedway officials persuaded Nascar this year to change the date of the NAPA 500 from its spot as the final race on the Winston Cup schedule, where it had been since 1996, to today because of recurring rain problems. It did not help.</p>
        <p>On a day turned so nightmarish by rain that there was a delay of 2 hours 26 minutes and the race finished under the lights, Tony Stewart moved closer to the Winston Cup Series points championship as 24-year-old Kurt Busch won his second straight race.</p>
        <p>Busch, among four drivers in Winston Cup history to win more than once by age 25, took the lead on Lap 206 and edged Joe Nemechek in a race shortened by rain to 248 laps from 325.</p>
        <p>Officials feared for the drivers' safety, so they shortened the race. ''It always makes your mind think twice when you've got raindrops coming down,'' Nemechek said.</p>
        <p>Busch, who drives a Ford, also won at Martinsville, Va., last week in joining Bill Elliott as the only drivers this year who have won back-to-back races.</p>
        <p>Stewart, meanwhile, used a fourth-place finish to expand his points lead to 146 with three races to go, at Rockingham, N.C., Phoenix and Homestead, Fla. Mark Martin eased into second with his eighth-place finish, while the rookie Jimmie Johnson, 22nd today, dropped to third, 150 points back. He had trailed Stewart by 82 points.</p>
        <p>Stewart has been frequently asked in recent weeks whether he has gone conservative in trying to protect the points lead. That line of questioning does not make him happy.</p>
        <p>''There still isn't anyone out there who can say I'm points racing,'' he said. ''I could've cruised and just rode in, but I was going for the win today.''</p>
        <p>Stewart could have been in trouble when he suddenly pitted during a caution flag on the 35th lap, concerned about two loose lug nuts on his left front wheel. His crew had left the lug nuts loose earlier when it performed a complete tire change in less than 13 seconds, considered a remarkable turnaround.</p>
        <p>''We didn't want to take any chance because there was still a lot of racing to go,'' said Greg Zipadelli, Stewart's crew chief. ''It's better to take care of it.''</p>
        <p>Returning to the track from the unscheduled stop, Stewart found himself in 35th as the drivers were under the caution for another 10 laps.</p>
        <p>But once the green flag was waved, Stewart quickly threaded his way through traffic and back into contention. He was 11th after 66 laps, fifth after 89 and then gained a spot a lap until he reached the front after 93 laps. Stewart lost that perch when he pitted for four tires and fuel on Lap 96, but he had clearly reasserted himself.</p>
        <p>''We earned that,'' he said of his comeback. ''There was nothing easy about it. We drove to the front.''</p>
        <p>Later, on Lap 188, when Stewart regained the lead for 16 laps, he playfully implored his pit crew to show a little enthusiasm the next time he passed them on the track. And they did, cheering wildly.</p>
        <p>Yet the long rain delay set the tone at this track, considered the series' fastest where restrictor plates are not used and normally capable of handling speeds of more than 190 miles per hour. Busch's average speed was only 127.519 m.p.h.</p>
        <p>The race was stopped because of rain after 26 laps around the 1.54-mile oval. At the time, Kyle Petty led because he was the only racer who had not made a pit stop. Stewart, the pole-sitter, was second.</p>
        <p>''Tony was probably saying, 'Who was that idiot that didn't pit?' '' said Petty, a distant 21st in the points standings. '' 'Oh, that's Kyle. It's all right.' ''</p>
        <p>Petty, delighted at securing bonus points for leading the race, surrendered the top spot in a stop for tires, as the race continued under caution for the next 19 laps.</p>
        <p>Johnson spun out twice in trying vainly to keep his Chevrolet in contention. ''We just had a loose race car today,'' he said. ''But at least we didn't hit anything.''</p>
        <p>The trouble started with his spin on Turn 4 of Lap 139, badly damaging three tires and putting the race under a caution. Still, through his pit crew's heady and quick work, Johnson was able to stay on the lead lap.</p>
        <p>The crew changed his left-side tires on Lap 140 and the right-side tires on the following lap just before the caution was removed. But the car continued to handle poorly.</p>
        <p>For Busch, who did not even participate in last year's fall race here, the consecutive victories gave him three for the season and portended a bright future.</p>
        <p>''You never know if you're going to be staying in Winston Cup -- if you've got the stuff, so to speak, to cut the mustard,'' he said. ''But I am starting to get a better feeling about it.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
