<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Diary of a Wordsmith, Or Is That Wordjones?</title>
    <meta content="12HAUP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1001557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lehmann-Haupt, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gelbart, Larry</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Laughing Matters (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0D81130F931A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Diary of a Wordsmith, Or Is That Wordjones?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lehmann-Haupt, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Christopher Lehmann-Haupt reviews book Laughing Matters: On Writing 'M*A*S*H,' 'Tootsie,' 'Oh, God!' and a Few Other Funny Things by Larry Gelbart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAUGHING MATTERS  On Writing 'M*A*S*H,' 'Tootsie,' 'Oh, God!' and a Few Other Funny Things  By Larry Gelbart  276 pages. Random House. $24.</p>
        <p>''I love to play with language; make it do tricks, turn a word inside out to see if it's got a hidden meaning tucked away somewhere, or perhaps find that it's capable of an extra entendre or two.'' So writes Larry Gelbart, the writer, in his combination memoir-sampler, ''Laughing Matters: On Writing 'M*A*S*H,' 'Tootsie,' 'Oh, God!' and a Few Other Funny Things.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAUGHING MATTERS  On Writing 'M*A*S*H,' 'Tootsie,' 'Oh, God!' and a Few Other Funny Things  By Larry Gelbart  276 pages. Random House. $24.</p>
        <p>''I love to play with language; make it do tricks, turn a word inside out to see if it's got a hidden meaning tucked away somewhere, or perhaps find that it's capable of an extra entendre or two.'' So writes Larry Gelbart, the writer, in his combination memoir-sampler, ''Laughing Matters: On Writing 'M*A*S*H,' 'Tootsie,' 'Oh, God!' and a Few Other Funny Things.''</p>
        <p>And it shows, this verbal sportiveness of Mr. Gelbart's, not only in the prose of his book -- ''To make a long story short he made a short story long,'' he writes of the comedian Danny Thomas -- but also in the trajectory of his career. The child of Yiddish-speaking immigrants from Eastern Europe, Mr. Gelbart did not start speaking English until he was 5.  Only 11 years later, in 1944, he was being paid to write gags for Mr. Thomas in his role as Jerry Dingle, the mailman on the Maxwell House Coffee Time radio show, starring Fanny Brice as Baby Snooks.</p>
        <p>From there Mr. Gelbart went on to write for other comedians, other media: for Eddie Cantor, Bob Hope and Sid Caesar, among others; for television (''M*A*S*H,'' ''United States''), for cinema (''Oh, God!'' ''Barbarians at the Gate'') and for theater (''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum,'' ''Sly Fox,'' ''City of Angels''). He helpfully says, ''Asked once whether there was a reason why all of Sid's writers tended to be 'young and Jewish,' I said it was probably because all of our parents were old and Jewish.''</p>
        <p>Yet what is engaging about ''Laughing Matters'' is not so much the verbal friskiness that went into its writing as the stories Mr. Gelbart tells of overcoming the handicap it gave him. ''In truth, I tend to overwrite,'' he confesses, ''to write too many jokes. That's Bob Hope 101.  Always leave 'em laughing. Always meet 'em laughing. Always keep 'em laughing.''</p>
        <p>This tendency proved a drawback when it came to writing longer material, he admits. On one of the first movie scripts he was assigned to improve, the producer told him he loved what he was doing. But when he heard gales of laughter and put ''a drinking-glass to our common wall, a primitive but time-tested way of eavesdropping,'' he learned that other writers were ''improving my improvements.''</p>
        <p>''Plotting is nothing I did, or do, naturally,'' he writes. ''It is the hardest part of the writing process. No matter how many times you plot a script successfully, the next one, representing new and uncharted territory, convinces you that you were merely lucky the last time out, that you really don't know how to do it at all.'' Or as he likes to quote the German novelist Thomas Mann, ''A writer is someone for whom writing is more difficult than it is for other people.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Gelbart did overcome such difficulties eventually. So the most diverting parts of ''Laughing Matters'' are the ones that tell how he did it: for instance, how he helped pioneer a ''multitiered storytelling technique'' in the ''M*A*S*H'' series.  How he learned from his master, the Roman comic playwright Plautus, in writing ''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum.'' And how he depended on Stefan Zweig's version of ''Volpone'' in preparing his successful Broadway version, ''Sly Fox'' (which starred George C. Scott), and never bothered to read the Ben Jonson original.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the rest of ''Laughing Matters'' is mostly filling. From the looks of it, his editor, Sam Vaughan, who has written brief bridging essays along with an introduction, had a hard time pulling material out of Mr. Gelbart. Beyond a few of the essays, the book never works up much momentum. Instead it improvises with lists of the author's favorite things on television (Milton Berle's ''Texaco Star Theater,'' Edward R. Murrow, Richard M. Nixon), excerpts from the author's best scripts (''Barbarians at the Gate,'' ''Mastergate''), praise for people he admires (of ''the diminutive agent and producer Irving Lazar,'' he writes, ''good things came in small packagers'') and damnation for those he feels have crossed him (of the actor Dustin Hoffman he remarks, ''Never work with an Oscar winner who is shorter than the statue'').</p>
        <p>After a while, all you can hope for are more clever one-liners. Happily, they keep coming. ''My own definition of a friend is someone who has the decency not to send you a thank-you note after you've had a failure.''  ''Contrary to popular belief, it's not the legs that go first; it's remembering the word for legs.'' ''Over a lifetime I've produced more drafts than the north wind.'' ''I carry no childhood scars; I was an amused rather than an abused child.''</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Gelbart would be the first to admit, when you start to depend on funny lines, you know you are in trouble. In the end, ''Laughing Matters'' leaves the reader wishing that the author had exercised his evident talent for mastering new media and learned the art of writing memoir as skillfully as he does everything else.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
