<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weary Knicks Misfire Against Hornets</title>
    <meta content="12KNIC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1001595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Charlotte Hornets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Orleans Hornets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DF1E30F931A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weary Knicks Misfire Against Hornets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLOTTE, N.C., March 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charlotte Hornets defeat New York Knickerbockers, 85-78; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Starks stood in front of a mirror after the game, fidgeting with his tie for 10 minutes or more. He was twisting it and tightening it over and over in search of the perfect knot.</p>
        <p>Finding perfection is a chore for Starks these days, no matter how many times he has completed the same simple routine before. Tying knots, taking shots. Nothing is easy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Starks stood in front of a mirror after the game, fidgeting with his tie for 10 minutes or more. He was twisting it and tightening it over and over in search of the perfect knot.</p>
        <p>Finding perfection is a chore for Starks these days, no matter how many times he has completed the same simple routine before. Tying knots, taking shots. Nothing is easy.</p>
        <p>The frustration of Starks and Coach Jeff Van Gundy bubbled to the surface tonight as the Knicks lost to the Hornets, 85-78, at Charlotte Coliseum. It was not enough for Charles Oakley to bounce around like a kid on a hopscotch grid. His surprising spring -- he grabbed 22 rebounds -- could not push the Knicks past what has become a mental and physical block.</p>
        <p>Whether they are weary of body or mind, the Knicks are not making the snap decisions and snap shots needed  to win the second games when they play on back-to-back nights. The Hornets won their ninth game in a row, as Glen Rice escaped the Knicks' defense for the first time this season to score 22 points and Anthony Mason added 21 points. The Knicks, meanwhile, lost for the fifth time in a row on the back end of back-to-back games.</p>
        <p>New York shot just 34.9 percent. The prime example of the Knicks' futility was Allan Houston, who had a team-high 25 points but made just 9 of 24 shots. But he was not alone. Charlie Ward was 1 of 7 and Terry Cummings was 1 of 5. And there were times when the slumping Starks, who was 4 of 10, was firing like a tank spinning out of control. He was 1 of 4 from 3-point range, and rarely looked to go inside. But Starks was not alone in his undisciplined shot selection; the Knicks made 3 of 17 from behind the arc, with Ward and Houston each 1 of 5.</p>
        <p>''Our shot selection at the end of the first half was pitiful,'' Van Gundy said. ''We had Larry Johnson down low with a guard on his back and we go down and jack up a long jumper. The ball did not go inside.''</p>
        <p>The ball did not go in at all to start the third quarter, when the Knicks hit just 1 of their first 13 shots. They managed to lean on their defense to stay close, as they had all night.</p>
        <p>''The game was there to win if we wanted it,'' said Oakley, who had a layup to tie the game with 5 minutes 31 seconds left. ''Charlotte made the big plays and we didn't. They came in on an 8-0 streak, and left 9-0.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks (35-27) have a streak of another kind going. They are a team unable to find a way to win the second of consecutive games. Often, those games have come on the road, where the Knicks are 12-19 this year.</p>
        <p>''Something mentally must go wrong when we go on the road,'' Houston said. ''There is no way you can win a ball game without making shots.''</p>
        <p>Starks has to make his share in order for the Knicks to win. He has talked about how his energy level takes a dip on the road and how he can find the sizzle only at the Garden. But even at home, Starks has been off the mark.</p>
        <p>Over the last nine games, Starks has hit just 30 of 93 shots. It is no coincidence that the Knicks have lost four of their last five games.</p>
        <p>In the past, he has been the perfect lift for the Knicks. But tonight, in a tight game that was tied in the fourth quarter, Van Gundy took Starks off the floor, relying on a more energetic Anthony Bowie instead. In the fourth quarter, Starks played less than a minute. He came in with 10:49 left in the game and was pulled by Van Gundy 30 seconds later, after he lost control of the ball. That was it. He never returned.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to talk today,'' Starks said, walking away from questions.</p>
        <p>As unpredictable as Starks is, the Knicks rely on him and need the return of his game.</p>
        <p>''We need him to win,'' Van Gundy said. ''Not playing him is not an option. We can't have subpar performances from our main guys.''</p>
        <p>There is not enough room for error on a team that has been wiped out because of injuries. Chris Mills, who sprained his left toe against the Orlando Magic on Tuesday night, only played because the team had to have him. He was hardly able to function, starting and playing just 16 minutes while shooting 0 for 5. ''It definitely affected me,'' Mills said.</p>
        <p>The Knicks are a banged-up bunch, and their depth is just one more factor that weighs them down in back-to-back situations.</p>
        <p>''We have struggled with offensive energy and have failed to make shots in those situations,'' Van Gundy said. ''We have failed to create shots against quality teams. And most of our problems have been on the road as well. So, you couple those things together, and we've really struggled.''</p>
        <p>Nothing is easy. Starks knows that as well as anyone.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>CHRIS CHILDS (sprained ankle) missed his ninth game. ''Same old, same old,'' said Coach JEFF VAN GUNDY when asked about Childs's progress in his recovery.  PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
