<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turf; When Banks Step Back, Middlemen Rush In</title>
    <meta content="12TURF$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1001577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rozhon, Tracie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Turf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEED61130F931A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="2253" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turf; When Banks Step Back, Middlemen Rush In</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mortgage brokers are playing increasingly large role in helping consumers get best rates on residential mortgages and complete paperwork; brokers now do much of work formerly done by bank officers, often taking their fees from lenders; drawings; table (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Lorraine Altman arrived for her first meeting with a mortgage broker, she came armed. From her perusal of the Internet the night before, she knew the current interest rates. From discussions with her real estate agent, she knew what type of loan she wanted. And from talking with her accountant, she knew exactly how much she wanted to spend on the monthly mortgage payment for the new $165,000 Upper East Side one-bedroom apartment she had picked out.</p>
        <p>The only thing this savvy 52-year-old Long Islander didn't know -- and was relying on the mortgage broker to tell her -- was where her mortgage would be coming from: a bank, a small investment group, an insurance company or a giant mortgage conglomerate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Lorraine Altman arrived for her first meeting with a mortgage broker, she came armed. From her perusal of the Internet the night before, she knew the current interest rates. From discussions with her real estate agent, she knew what type of loan she wanted. And from talking with her accountant, she knew exactly how much she wanted to spend on the monthly mortgage payment for the new $165,000 Upper East Side one-bedroom apartment she had picked out.</p>
        <p>The only thing this savvy 52-year-old Long Islander didn't know -- and was relying on the mortgage broker to tell her -- was where her mortgage would be coming from: a bank, a small investment group, an insurance company or a giant mortgage conglomerate.</p>
        <p>Ms. Altman, a job-training executive in Manhattan, found that getting a mortgage these days is a lot different from the way it was 17 years ago, when she bought a co-op in Great Neck, N.Y. ''I never even heard of a mortgage broker when I bought my last co-op,'' she said. ''I just walked into the Dime Savings around the corner.''</p>
        <p>Times have changed. Real estate agents, brokers and bankers say that these days, home buyers are more inquiring, the old-line banks are more reluctant to lend and the mortgage brokers are a lot more reputable. In a decade, the number of mortgage brokers has tripled; the use of mortgage brokers has soared, from less than 20 percent to 52 percent. In Manhattan, the percentage is probably higher; experts estimate that mortgage brokers handle as much as 75 percent of all co-op loans.</p>
        <p>''Ten years ago, all top 10 lenders in the country were banks,'' said Neil Bader, the chief executive of Skyscraper Mortgage, one of the largest mortgage brokerage companies in New York City. ''Now, there's only two or three.''</p>
        <p>Not only that, but customers are also more technologically plugged in. ''Consumers are more adept at using the Internet, and bankers and mortgage brokers are, too,'' said Barbara Kent, a lawyer at the New York State Banking Department. In response to dozens of requests from buyers, lawyers and brokers, she said, the state has proposed a new rule to allow mortgage applications to be filed over the World Wide Web. ''New York is the first state to address using the Internet to get a mortgage,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Banking Department is currently gathering comments on the rule -- which contains the same protections for consumers as the old-fashioned transactions -- and said it might release the new rule sometime in April or May.</p>
        <p>It used to be a lot simpler. In the early 1980's, when Ms. Altman was getting her first mortgage, the prospective home buyer would stroll into a bank, brandishing a contract to buy a house. The banker might even know the place. There wouldn't be too much discussion about rates -- the percentage the bank charges to make the loan. There would be lots of forms, lots of hand-shaking, an appraisal and, finally, at the closing, the bank officer would appear with a check.</p>
        <p>The idea of a mortgage broker -- a middleman who would scout the market, find the best rate (even if it was from a lender in San Diego or Dallas), counsel and advise, and then do all the paperwork -- was almost unheard of.</p>
        <p>In the past, mortgage brokers often took their fees from the customer -- occasionally opening themselves to criticism that they were gouging the home buyer. Now, they increasingly take their commissions from the lender. In effect, the lender offers the broker a discount to do what the bank officers once did: things like filling out applications, scanning credit reports and arranging appraisals. For his fee, the broker takes the difference between the discount rate for the loan and the retail rate. (Regardless of how the fee is figured, reputable brokers say a customer should never pay more than if he walked into a bank.)</p>
        <p>Most of these changes have occurred since the mid-80's, when the states started registering mortgage brokers and many banks switched their focus away from residential mortgage lending. Now, customers complain that the banks have abandoned the off-the-street mortgage customer.</p>
        <p>The change, New York Banking Department officials say, may be most noticeable in the savings banks. ''Savings and loans did a tremendous mortgage business, and that definitely has lessened after the S.&amp; L. crisis of the 80's,'' Mrs. Kent said. ''They were encouraged to diversify, and the business that has left the savings banks has gone to mortgage brokers.'' (In 1987, those banks did 41 percent of the country's mortgage business; two years ago, they were down to 19 percent.)</p>
        <p>Banks still give mortgages, but many would rather let the mortgage broker stand between them and the customer. Even if a loyal bank customer gets a mortgage through his bank, he may find that his mortgage is sold shortly afterward to a different bank or a large consolidator.</p>
        <p>The March 2 issue of The National Mortgage News lists the top 50 mortgage lenders; only a handful can be considered old-fashioned banks in the sense that they have branches. Norwest Mortgage, based in Des Moines, is first, followed by Countrywide Home Loans of Pasadena, Calif. Chase Manhattan Mortgage of Edison, N.J., is third. In the New York region, the only old-fashioned banks listed are Marine Midland (No. 29), in Depew, N.Y., and the Long Island Savings Bank (No. 45). To tie in to the big, out-of-state lenders, a customer probably needs a broker.</p>
        <p>''You can usually get a better deal from the mortgage brokers than from the banks; they'll generally write the business faster because they'll draw on all those sources,'' said R. Marshall Kneeland, a building contractor from Winsted, Conn., who used to be a real estate agent. Five years ago, when he was selling houses, he said, many people thought of mortgage brokers as ''kind of slimy specimens who took out small ads in the classifieds, like: 'Refused by your bank? Come see us.' ''</p>
        <p>Now, he said, mortgage brokers are ''taking out giant billboards on I-91.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kneeland, who is currently using a mortgage broker to help him shop for his own mortgage, pointed out that many borrowers don't keep track of who holds their mortgages. ''It might be the bank you signed up with -- or it might be the ABC Finance Company in Albuquerque,'' he said. ''You might as well go for the best deal.''</p>
        <p>Getting the best deal has become an obsession for many of today's home buyers, some of whom are comparison shopping on the Internet, a tool that wasn't even available 10 years ago. Refinancing, which allows borrowers to better the interest rates they got in the past, now makes up 55 percent of today's mortgage business.</p>
        <p>All of this points to an increasingly investigative shopper. Yet, even the best informed home buyer may need help with the paperwork involved in applying. That's where a broker -- or even the Internet -- can help.</p>
        <p>Richard Hodos, a commercial real estate broker, figured there would be no snags in applying for a $300,000 loan to buy a huge 1,000-square-foot one-bedroom apartment in an elegant prewar co-op building in Greenwich Village. After all, he was putting up 40 percent of the $499,000 price.</p>
        <p>But despite Mr. Hodos's sterling credit report, Bruce G. Maasbach, the broker at Skyscraper Mortgage, was concerned about two recent credit inquiries from banks. ''They want to make sure you're not taking out any other mortgages on different properties,'' he explained. So Mr. Hodos, an enthusiastic and affable man of 37, gave reasons for the credit inquiries, including his request to one credit card company for an increased limit this past Christmas.</p>
        <p>AT their first face-to-face meeting, Mr. Maasbach -- who had drafted a pile of forms after a brief telephone interview -- laid out for Mr. Hodos what he would be charged, above and beyond the monthly payment and the up-front money that would be required, including an application fee of $290, a credit check for $10 and the appraisal fee of $275.</p>
        <p>By the end of the session, Mr. Hodos had filled out all the paperwork and had a tentative rate -- 7 3/8 percent, from the Astoria Federal Savings and Loan Association in Lake Success, N.Y. -- and a tentative monthly payment: $2,072.</p>
        <p>These days, the banks rely on brokers like Mr. Maasbach and Elise Leve Wittenberg at Manhattan Mortgage, who met with Ms. Altman, to funnel clients and paperwork to them. But it wasn't always that way. In fact, before the mid-1980's, the banks didn't usually deal with mortgage brokers at all.</p>
        <p>When the business of mortgage brokering began, ''we were the lender of the last resort,'' said Tuck Marshall, who will become the president of the National Association of Mortgage Brokers in June. He continued: ''The mortgage broker helped you clean up your credit and found you a loan -- but not through a bank. It was seen as slightly shady business.''</p>
        <p>From 1990 to the present, there was an even greater shift, away from commercial and savings banks to mega-lenders like Countrywide, which last year lent $45 billion. ''No one knows these big mortgage conglomerates' names -- they don't even have branches,'' Mr. Bader said. ''They're using the mortgage brokers as conduits.''</p>
        <p>This all gets a bit heady for a consumer who wants to research the rates on his own, and confusing for those who are not yet ready to spend their spare time hunkered down over a computer keyboard, trying to surf the Web.</p>
        <p>L. Daniel Rawitch is the chief executive of Finet, the parent company of I Qualify, a mortgage brokerage company on the Internet. Mr. Rawitch says his company (at www.iqualify.com) will give a preliminary approval in six minutes, based on a quick, fill-in-the blanks application, to prospective homeowners for only $39. If the applicant  gets the preliminary approval, he or she can take the results to any lender, the company says, or use Monument Mortgage, the mortgage company Finet also owns.</p>
        <p>The Web site may be helpful in spotting weak areas; applicants may be told to explain late payments on credit cards, for instance. After a client pays a fee, I Qualify  will also mail him the current percentage rate for a mortgage and the monthly payment. But Manhattanites beware: the company does not handle loans on co-ops. And, as it states in bold type, ''This is not a commitment to lend.''</p>
        <p>To Mr. Rawitch and his competitors, the Internet is the wave of the future. Others are not so sure.</p>
        <p>''The Internet isn't there yet,'' said Mark E. Zimmerman, a real estate lawyer in Manhattan. ''People want personal service, plain and simple. The banks are really missing the boat.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bader, whose mortgage brokerage company has three Web sites, grumbled, ''The Internet will be there for my children.''</p>
        <p>Still, there are plenty of people already betting that Mr. Zimmerman and Mr. Bader are wrong.</p>
        <p>Defining the Terms  FOR the novice searching for a mortgage, here are a few terms to throw around so you can sound like a pro.  ADJUSTABLE RATE MORTGAGE -- Often called an ARM in the ads, it means that the interest rate changes at specified intervals; for example, ''10/1'' means the rate will stay fixed for 10 years, then will change each year for the duration of the mortgage.  LIFE CAP -- The limit on the interest rate on an adjustable rate loan.  POINTS -- A one-time charge by a lender: each point equals 1 percent of the loan amount.  CLOSING COSTS -- Costs incurred in buying real estate, which can include points, attorney's fees, the cost of a lien search, filing fees and more.  LOAN COMMITMENT -- An agreement to lend. Synonym: Loan approval.  REFINANCE, OR REFI -- Money borrowed by the owner of real estate to replace an existing loan on the same real estate.</p>
        <p>TRACIE ROZHON</p>
        <p>Proceed With Caution</p>
        <p>ALTHOUGH a lot of the uncertainty when dealing with a mortgage broker is gone -- New York State and the surrounding states have some of the toughest rules around -- the smart home buyer always comes to the first meeting well prepared.</p>
        <p>Get a recommendation from a friend or colleague who has used a good broker in the past. Failing that, get several names from your real estate broker.</p>
        <p>Check newspapers or the Internet to learn the most current rates for the kind of mortgage you want. Last month, the New York State Banking Department began posting the latest interest rates for mortgages on the World Wide Web, at www.banking.state.ny.us. (Look under the section called Interest Rate Surveys.) For the Web-challenged, hard copies of the reports can be obtained from (800) 518-8866.</p>
        <p>Remember to ask the mortgage broker to go over every one of the charges you will have to pay. You shouldn't pay more for a mortgage through a broker -- including all preparation costs -- than you would pay if you walked in to a bank. (Brokers say you will often pay less, because of their ability to comparison shop.)</p>
        <p>TRACIE ROZHON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
