<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Factory Orders Up Sharp 2.9%</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="457179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FACTORS AND FACTORING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMMERCE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DF153AF930A35754C0A967958260" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Factory Orders Up Sharp 2.9%</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a compelling report of economic rebound, new orders to American factories surged 2.9 percent in May, the biggest increase in more than a year, the Commerce Department reported today.</p>
        <p>It was also the second straight substantial rise after five months in which factory orders declined. The April gain, moreover, was revised upward to 2.1 percent from the 1.8 percent initially reported.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a compelling report of economic rebound, new orders to American factories surged 2.9 percent in May, the biggest increase in more than a year, the Commerce Department reported today.</p>
        <p>It was also the second straight substantial rise after five months in which factory orders declined. The April gain, moreover, was revised upward to 2.1 percent from the 1.8 percent initially reported.</p>
        <p>Today's report seemed to extinguish any remaining hopes that the Federal Reserve would find it necessary to cut interest rates again to spur the economy, which is widely believed to be climbing out of the recession that began a year ago. The central bank's Open Market Committee began a two-day meeting today to set monetary targets for the balance of the year.</p>
        <p>"I think we're in a classic recovery environment now," said Edward Yardeni, an economist at C. J. Lawrence Inc., a New York securities firm. He noted that not only have new orders turned up -- a predictive indicator -- but that shipments of factory goods have now advanced for two straight months. Consumer Confidence Up</p>
        <p>In another report, the University of Michigan said its widely followed consumer survey showed a sharp jump in confidence in June.  [ Page D2. ]</p>
        <p>The report on factory orders covered the entire range of factory goods -- $120.1 billion of durables, which are designed to last a minimum of three years, and $117.9 billion of nondurables. A preliminary report on orders for durable goods last Tuesday showed these surging 3.8 percent in May, a gain trimmed today to 3.4 percent, mainly because of a lower order level for fabricated metals.</p>
        <p>Orders for nondurables rose 2.5 percent, with all major industries except rubber and plastics posting increases, the department said. For nondurables, orders are generally filled so quickly as to be regarded essentially the same as shipments.</p>
        <p>Shipments of food products rose 1.3 percent, textile mill products rose 2.2 percent, chemicals and allied products rose 1.9 percent and petroleum and coal products rose 3.6 percent.</p>
        <p>Tobacco products, which are highly erratic for tax and other reasons, soared 22.6 percent. Rubber and plastics fell 1.5 percent while paper and related products edged down one-tenth of 1 percent, the report showed.</p>
        <p>In all, shipments climbed 1.3 percent in May after a 2.7 percent April increase, but backlogs of unfilled orders were essentially unchanged at $521.1 billion, the lowest level since February 1990.</p>
        <p>Declines in orders for durables offset increases in nondurables.</p>
        <p>Inventories, meanwhile, fell eight-tenths of 1 percent, to $382 billion, declining for the fifth time in six months since reaching a November 1990 peak of $392.4 billion. It appeared that these inventory reductions were involuntary, as sales have outpaced production rather than representing deliberate retrenchment by anxious executives.</p>
        <p>By the stage of fabrication, inventories of finished goods eased 1.6 percent for durables and five-tenths of 1 percent for nondurables. Work-in-process was down seven-tenths of 1 percent and five-tenths of 1 percent, respectively, for these categories while materials and supplies fell 1 percent and four-tenths of 1 percent. Unfilled Orders Rise</p>
        <p>Unfilled orders for nondurables in May rose 4.1 percent, to $21.2 billion, the biggest increase since February 1987 and the highest level since May 1990, the Department reported.</p>
        <p>Over all, the 2.9 percent gain in factory orders reflected a gain of $6.8 billion for the month. This followed a 2.1 percent gain in April and a 2.9 percent decline for March. Orders, however, remain 2.2 percent below the level of May 1990.</p>
        <p>By market categories, orders were up 5.5 percent for automotive equipment, 3.2 percent for consumer, 3.7 percent for machinery and equipment, 1.9 percent for business supplies, 1.5 percent for construction materials and supplies, 3.7 percent for information technology industries and 6.1 percent for health care products.</p>
        <p>Orders for military goods, on the other hand, tumbled 18.1 percent, and home goods and apparel eased nine-tenths of 1 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
