<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CRITIC'S CHOICE/Film; A Retrospective Examines Kurosawa and His Star</title>
    <meta content="26CHOI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/26/movies/26CHOI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1411060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Critic's Choice | 'Kurosawa &amp; Mifune'"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kurosawa, Akira (1910-98)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Throne of Blood (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Film Forum</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kurosawa, Akira</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mifune, Toshiro</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E4DD1138F935A15754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CRITIC'S CHOICE/Film; A Retrospective Examines Kurosawa and His Star</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Retrospective Examines Kurosawa and His Star</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews Throne of Blood, 1957 film by Akira Kurosawa now re-released; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It should be enough to get you into Film Forum to say that the theater begins a 12-picture retrospective today of the work of the director Akira Kurosawa and his star Toshiro Mifune, with all new prints.</p>
        <p>And it's more than satisfying to see ''Seven Samurai'' (Aug. 30-Sept. 12) and ''Hidden Fortress'' (Aug. 16-20) after the last mess of a ''Star Wars.'' Both of Kurosawa's samurai action spectacles were chief among George Lucas's many inspirations. (And ''Samurai'' also was the source of ''The Magnificent Seven.'') At least Kurosawa doesn't give his samurai hairstyles that make them look like drug dealers from some intergalactic trailer park, as Mr. Lucas did with Obi-Wan Kenobi and Anakin Skywalker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Film Forum offers a 12-picture retrospective of the work of the director Akira Kurosawa and his star Toshiro Mifune, with all new prints.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It should be enough to get you into Film Forum to say that the theater begins a 12-picture retrospective today of the work of the director Akira Kurosawa and his star Toshiro Mifune, with all new prints.</p>
        <p>And it's more than satisfying to see ''Seven Samurai'' (Aug. 30-Sept. 12) and ''Hidden Fortress'' (Aug. 16-20) after the last mess of a ''Star Wars.'' Both of Kurosawa's samurai action spectacles were chief among George Lucas's many inspirations. (And ''Samurai'' also was the source of ''The Magnificent Seven.'') At least Kurosawa doesn't give his samurai hairstyles that make them look like drug dealers from some intergalactic trailer park, as Mr. Lucas did with Obi-Wan Kenobi and Anakin Skywalker.</p>
        <p>Kurosawa used the action genre more luxuriantly than any other director because he unleashed Mifune as a force of nature -- the havoc he wrought was as frightening as we could imagine because the director allowed us to understand what Mifune's victims were up against. Despite all the derring-do of Hong Kong martial-arts films, none of their directors ever lingered on the deadly physicality of the stars. Kurosawa let Mifune's oaken arms say as much about his ruined amoral samurai in ''Sanjuro'' (Aug. 27-29) as the actor's murderously swift shifts of facial expression did.</p>
        <p>In the first of the series, tonight's ''Throne of Blood,'' Kurosawa's adaptation of ''Macbeth,'' director and star clarify the action in a way that's simultaneously furtive and bold. This catalyzing work, as well as ''The Bad Sleep Well'' (Aug. 14 and 15), sparked the imagination of directors from Aki Kaurismaki to Peter Sellars in recasting their own versions of Shakespeare.</p>
        <p>But it's the films that are rarely revived that cast a far more potent spell. In ''Drunken Angel'' (Aug. 4-6), the first of the Kurosawa-Mifune collaborations, a pitilessly impatient Mifune commandeers the picture as a gangster who ruins the life of a back-street doctor (Takashi Shimura). (The power struggle between the director and actor is detailed in Stuart Galbraith IV's book ''The Emperor and the Wolf,'' a continent-size overview of the pair's careers together.)</p>
        <p>And there's also the psychologically brutal ''I Live in Fear'' (Tuesday and Wednesday) and ''Stray Dog'' (Wednesday through next Friday), one of the greatest detective films ever made.</p>
        <p>Certainly ''Sanjuro'' and ''Yojimbo'' (Aug. 21-24) gave us Clint Eastwood as seen in Sergio Leone's ''Fistful of Dollars.'' Yet it's Kurosawa's films ''High and Low'' (Aug. 11-13) and ''Stray Dog'' that gave Mr. Eastwood the second calling card of his career: Dirty Harry, a shell casing of a man who wasn't much different from the criminals he pursued. If only Harry had remained true to this conception -- which clearly influenced the director Don Siegel -- instead of becoming a squinting superhero incapable of doing wrong. Then, the ''Dirty Harry'' movies might have danced in the region between immorality and amorality, as both ''Stray Dog'' and ''High and Low'' manage to.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Eastwood, left to his own devices, is a man incapable of offering complication -- something that Kurosawa and Mifune did exceptionally well.</p>
        <p>''Kurosawa &amp; Mifune'' opens today at the Film Forum, 209 West Houston Street, South Village, and runs through Sept. 12. Tickets: $9.75; $5 for members. Box office: (212) 727-8110.</p>
        <p>Critic's Choice | 'Kurosawa &amp; Mifune'</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
