<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As More People Take to Personal Watercraft, Dangers Increase</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="370740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JET SKIS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D6173BF930A15754C0A966958260" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As More People Take to Personal Watercraft, Dangers Increase</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your July 8 article on personal watercraft as pleasure or nuisance neglects to mention that these new ''toys'' can be not only disturbing but also dangerous, and some vehicles may be more dangerous than others. Safety in the use of these vehicles has become a public-policy issue because increasing numbers of people have been killed or injured in their use.</p>
        <p>The House of Representatives Commerce, Consumer and Monetary Affairs Subcommittee, which I head, has investigated the safety and regulation of these vehicles for more than two years. The Coast Guard, which collects statistics from state authorities on all boating-related deaths and injuries, reports to me that it knows of 55 deaths and more than 1,000 serious injuries since 1985 connected with use of personal watercraft. The figures may be incomplete because the Coast Guard estimates it receives reports on only 5 percent to 10 percent of all nonfatal accidents. One purpose of my investigation is to determine if more precise data collection should be required.</p>
        <p>People have been killed in collisions with personal watercraft. A woman in a rubber raft on vacation in Hawaii was killed by a fast-moving motor craft driven by a 6-year-old boy. Most often, collisions result, in the Coast Guard's words, from ''the deliberate desire of the operators to use the maneuverability of the craft to the utmost - by riding in very close proximity to other boats, either making sudden but deliberate turns when riding in close formation with other personal watercraft or when 'wake jumping' behind other boats.''</p>
        <p>Many users of these craft are young, and state laws differ tremendously on age limits and training before they may be sold or rented. Young people rent these craft because they are relatively expensive. An industry publication states, ''the statistics show that when you're out there cruising this summer and a personal watercraft comes whizzing toward you at 35 or 40 m.p.h., the odds are that the rider is young, inexperienced (perhaps it's his first time up on a rented craft, and he doesn't even know how to stop or turn it), and he knows even less about the rules of the road or anything else about boating.'' Young users have been disproportionately killed and injured by them.</p>
        <p>The dramatic increase in personal watercraft makes this a public-policy issue. The industry estimates about 250,000 vehicles have been sold. Other estimates put the number in the United States at up to 500,000.</p>
        <p>Finally, not all personal watercraft require the operator to stand or kneel. It has been alleged that the stand-up model encourages more dangerous maneuvers. Thus, another object of my investigation is to determine if there is a relation between accidents and deaths among different models.</p>
        <p>DOUG BARNARD JR.</p>
        <p>Member of Congress, 10th Dist., Ga.</p>
        <p>Washington, July 9, 1990</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
