<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SOME PRICES JUMP DESPITE A PATTERN OF LOW INFLATION</title>
    <meta content="22INFL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uchitelle, Louis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DB153CF931A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SOME PRICES JUMP DESPITE A PATTERN OF LOW INFLATION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Uchitelle, Louis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US inflation rate stays persistently low, but prices are rising noticeably for variety of everyday items, sharply enough in some cases to catch attention and provoke annoyance; prices of commodities and manufactured goods remain steady--partly from pressures of global competition--but prices are rising smartly for growing number of items in service sector, including fast-food hamburgers, auto maintenance and dental care; increases are seen as reflection of robust economy, in which people become more ambitious in purchases and more tolerant of costs, as incomes rise and unemployment falls; Consumer Price Index has risen only 1.7 percent in past year; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While the national inflation rate stays persistently low, reminiscent of the 1950's and 60's, prices have been rising noticeably in recent months for a variety of everyday items -- from fast-food hamburgers to auto maintenance to dental care.</p>
        <p>The increases have been sharp enough in some cases not only to catch people's attention but to provoke their annoyance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While the national inflation rate stays persistently low, reminiscent of the 1950's and 60's, prices have been rising noticeably in recent months for a variety of everyday items -- from fast-food hamburgers to auto maintenance to dental care.</p>
        <p>The increases have been sharp enough in some cases not only to catch people's attention but to provoke their annoyance.</p>
        <p>Consider the experience of John Gachelin, a 28-year-old marketing executive, who moved with his wife to Dallas from Chicago, in part to lower their living costs. Unlike Illinois, Texas has no state income tax. And houses cost less. But in the seven months since the move, the Gachelins have been hit with steep price increases to rent videos, change the oil in their two cars, buy cigarettes (he smokes), use a pay phone and buy hardcover books.</p>
        <p>''The pay phone really surprised me,'' said Mr. Gachelin, who earns $40,000 a year. ''I put in a quarter one day, and I found that I had to deposit 35 cents. But, hey, what can you do about it?''</p>
        <p>What softens the blow for the Gachelins and many others are the prices that are not rising. Most of the essentials -- food, gasoline, cars, furniture, appliances, most apparel -- are holding steady in price or becoming cheaper. That is why the Consumer Price Index, which is an average of the prices of thousands of goods and services, has risen by only 1.7 percent over the last year.</p>
        <p>It is the extras in life -- along with a few striking essentials, like home prices and rents -- that are becoming noticeably more expensive, and that is raising eyebrows. The University of Michigan's weekly consumer surveys may be registering the smallest percentage of Americans in 30 years worried about inflation, but they are also registering a growing annoyance.</p>
        <p>''Almost everyone has this asymmetric reaction,'' said Richard Curtin, director of the surveys. ''When prices go down or don't rise much, people don't say, 'On average, inflation is 1 or 2 percent.' Their attention is drawn to the items that went up in price, and they are annoyed. When prices go down or hold steady, they don't pay special attention; they just think that was a good buy.''</p>
        <p>Just how can the overall inflation rate remain so low while so many individual prices seem to be rising smartly? The answer lies in the way the Consumer Price Index is calculated. The Government checks 80,000 different prices each month, many of them for manufactured goods and commodities -- toys and cars, for example, and gasoline and food. These prices figure heavily in the averaging process that produces the Consumer Price Index. But over the last year, the prices of manufactured goods and commodities have remained steady, in part because of the pressure of global competition, and that has held down the overall index.</p>
        <p>The price increases these days are centered in the service sector, where prices are rising rather smartly for a growing number of items. These increases, however, are not widespread enough to pull up the overall index beyond its current low level.</p>
        <p>''The price increases in services have certainly outpaced those for products and commodities in the Consumer Price Index,'' said Patrick Jackman, chief of the group at the Bureau of Labor Statistics that compiles the index. If the trend continues, the index could edge up gradually. That, in fact, has happened in the last two months.</p>
        <p>The expanding list of rising prices is partly a reflection of the robust economy. As incomes rise and unemployment falls, people become more ambitious in their purchases and more tolerant of price increases, even while complaining. So they go along with a Manhattan merchant, for example, who has raised the price of his custom-made suits by $100, to between $750 and $1,095.</p>
        <p>''I needed to be at this level three or four years ago,'' said Andrew Kozinn, the third-generation owner of Saint Laurie Merchant Tailors on Broadway near 19th Street. He recently opened his first uptown store, on Park Avenue at 51st Street, to draw more customers from the banks, investment houses and office towers in the area. ''I could not have raised my prices or opened that store,'' Mr. Kozinn said, ''without this feeling of prosperity among so many people.''</p>
        <p>Merchants in general have become bolder in pushing up prices. That is particularly the case if what they sell is much in demand these days and short in supply, like custom-made men's suits or rental apartments. Or they are services available from no one else -- Walt Disney's theme parks, for example, and the state-run ferry system that carries 25 million riders a year between Seattle and the numerous island communities in Puget Sound.</p>
        <p>Disney's admission price to its theme parks in Orlando, Fla., rose nearly 5 percent in April, to $42, and the state-run ferry system's tickets went up 7 percent, on average, in May. The new fares range up to $30 on the longest route. The state ferry commission said the increases were required to finance expansion of the fleet; the service is heavily used by tourists and commuters. The commuters expressed resignation. Many said, in a questionnaire, that they had no reasonable alternative to the ferry.</p>
        <p>The ferry price increase, the first since 1994, reflects an increasingly common practice in the private sector. ''Our clients have been struggling with price resistance for so long that any cunning they can use to grab an extra price, they use,'' said Daniel Yankelovich, chairman of the polling company DYG, whose clients are mostly corporations. ''The list of significant increases is almost a profile of what people can get away with.''</p>
        <p>Prices in the last year have gone up significantly more than the inflation rate in more than 30 categories. This is evident in the data collected by the Bureau of Labor Statistics and in more than two dozen interviews with company executives and representatives of trade and consumer organizations.</p>
        <p>The list includes price increases already much in the news: fees for using automated-teller machines, for example, car rentals, airline fares for last-minute travelers, hotel rates, monthly apartment rentals and housing prices, although the cost of running a house has gone down for those who have refinanced mortgages.</p>
        <p>Other increases run the gamut of services: legal fees, dental care, H.M.O. insurance premiums, parking lot rates, some fast-food restaurant prices, long-distance phone calls made within a state, accountants' fees, school tuition at all levels and charges for vehicle maintenance.</p>
        <p>Entertainment is also more expensive -- cable television rates are up, as are tickets to most theme parks and sports events, entrance fees for some national parks and even wine. The price of a funeral also keeps going up.</p>
        <p>Rising costs are sometimes cited as justification for the price increases. The Boston Red Sox, in announcing a ticket price increase at Fenway Park, argued that the money would go in part to pay the salaries of expensive baseball players. Procter &amp; Gamble invoked higher paper costs as the reason for a 6 percent increase in the prices of bath and facial tissues in January. And Burger King blamed the rising minimum wage, which has pushed up the earnings of many of its employees, as a reason for cutting back sharply on the discounting of its Whopper hamburger.</p>
        <p>Since March, the Whopper has been sold increasingly at its full price of $1.99 to $2.19, and the once-frequent discounts, to 99 cents, have been gradually eliminated, said Kim Miller, a Burger King spokeswoman. ''We have decided consciously to shift the battle to taste, not price,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Still, there is the problem of getting customers in the door. Americans have grown accustomed to discounts and bargains, and Burger King still offers 99-cent specials. But now it generally features less costly food than the Whopper -- a small milkshake, for example, or onion rings or fries. The hope is that once in the door, customers will spring for the Whopper.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Kozinn, the Manhattan clothier, has, as a lure, a giant yellow tape measure placed decorously in the window of his Park Avenue store. In red ink, the word ''sale'' stands out against the yellow background. John Lynch, a lawyer, sometimes has suits made at Mr. Kozinn's establishment for the sale price; usually they feature less expensive fabric. But last winter, he picked out a pricey British cloth, a blue woolen, and paid $795 for it. That same suit, six months earlier, had sold for $695.</p>
        <p>''I am very thin and I have no seat,'' he said, ''and I would have to spend almost as much to properly tailor a suit purchased off the rack. Still, $795 is a stretch and I would probably draw the line if the price went up another $100, or if I got concerned about the economy.''</p>
        <p>That same sort of ceiling seemed to govern an increase in pay phone rates in many states. Deregulation permitted the increase, but an attempt by local phone companies, which own many of the pay phones, to impose a 50-cent minimum in some Midwestern states resulted in a sharp decline in use. The customer resistance disappeared at a 35-cent minimum, and that became the norm in many states starting last October, although not in New York, which still charges 25 cents.</p>
        <p>''The notion was that the market should set the price,'' said James Smith, a spokesman for Bell Atlantic, which provides service in the Northeast, ''and 35 cents has turned out to be the market price.''</p>
        <p>Sooner or later, of course, the market will have something else to say about prices. ''It will be interesting,'' said Mr. Jackman of the Bureau of Labor Statistics, ''to see what happens when the economy slows down.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
