<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adventure of Pirates, Pashas and Virtuosos</title>
    <meta content="22CORS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026562"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BALLET REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Ballet Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD6143CF931A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adventure of Pirates, Pashas and Virtuosos</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews American Ballet Theater new full-length version of Le Corsaire with two casts; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Too many cooks usually spoil the bouillabaisse and borscht. But ''Le Corsaire,'' an adventure yarn of a 19th-century French-Russian ballet, turned into an overnight hit for American Ballet Theater, thanks to a felicitous gaggle of producers and coaches from two continents.</p>
        <p>It is easy to see why the work looked so spectacular on Friday night at the Metropolitan Opera House when the company presented its first staging of a three-act ''Corsaire.'' The production, based on a 1997 Boston Ballet version, is a fabulous machine for dancing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Too many cooks usually spoil the bouillabaisse and borscht. But ''Le Corsaire,'' an adventure yarn of a 19th-century French-Russian ballet, turned into an overnight hit for American Ballet Theater, thanks to a felicitous gaggle of producers and coaches from two continents.</p>
        <p>It is easy to see why the work looked so spectacular on Friday night at the Metropolitan Opera House when the company presented its first staging of a three-act ''Corsaire.'' The production, based on a 1997 Boston Ballet version, is a fabulous machine for dancing.</p>
        <p>Not even the Kirov Ballet from Russia could field such depth of talent in all the leading roles in its own full-evening ''Corsaire'' here in 1989 as Ballet Theater did this weekend.</p>
        <p>The first cast on Friday was led by Nina Ananiashvili as Medora, the Greek girl abducted by a slave dealer, and Giuseppe Picone, a revelation in his dancing as Conrad, Medora's pirate lover.</p>
        <p>Wonderfully assertive but careful to keep a clean classical line, Mr. Picone was all flair and flourish. Trained in his native Italy and most recently a member of the English National Ballet, he has slowly worked up to his matinee-idol image in this, his first season with Ballet Theater. Sex appeal is the secret here. But as with Rudolph Valentino in the tango, it's the dancing that counts.</p>
        <p>A pirate who points his toes perfectly? Not to worry. The story is less important in ''Le Corsaire'' than the choreography, whose most classical vestiges are derived from Marius Petipa's 1899 version for the Maryinsky Ballet in St. Petersburg, Russia.</p>
        <p>The jewel-like pas de trois for three odalisqes in pale blue tutus and bare midriffs is the supreme example and featured Gillian Murphy, a corps member who brought the house down on Saturday night with her triple and quadruple pirouettes as well as her astonishingly precise leg beats.</p>
        <p>But from the moment the curtain rose on Vladimir Malakhov, as the slave dealer bursting with energy in a Turkish bazaar, it was clear that this was to be an all-star evening. Angel Corella was Birbanto, a fiery pirate in a character-dance role that has been enhanced with extra bravura. Ashley Tuttle had the supporting classical role as Gulnare, another slave captive, and Jose Manuel Carreno, was splendid in the role Rudolf Nureyev made famous as the slave lying at Margot Fonteyn's feet in the pas de deux known for short as ''Le Corsaire.'' But, as the Kirov taught us, this pas de deux was originally a pas de trois, and here again Medora was alternately partnered by Conrad, who gets an extra solo, and Mr. Carreno, dancing the familiar choreography as Ali, Conrad's slave.</p>
        <p>To get through the web of characters has not been easy, even for 19th-century choreographers. The Ballet Theater ''Corsaire'' is the latest of many versions. The Boston Ballet production is itself based on a 1992 version for the Bolshoi Ballet by Konstantin Sergeyev, onetime star and director of the Kirov.</p>
        <p>Kevin McKenzie, Ballet Theater's artistic director, requested that the Boston production be tightened and made more dramatically coherent. Anna-Marie Holmes, the Boston Ballet's new director, has restaged that production with past or present members of the Kirov: Tatyana Legat, Tatyana Terekhova and Serge Berejnoi (now a ballet master at the Boston Ballet).</p>
        <p>One result is that more dancing gets crammed into Act I, and the evening gets off to an uplifting start that telegraphs the virtue of this version: entertainment pure and simple. Mr. Malakhov, as Lankendem, the slave dealer, makes something major of a potentially minor role, never overdoing the comic potential of his villain, always giving his solos an extraordinary flexibility and lightness. This was especially true in the ''Pas d'Esclave'' pas de deux where Miss Tuttle, initially veiled, shielded her face from him while showing off first-class classical form. ''Le Corsaire'' very loosely derived from a poem by Byron, has the same mix of character and classical dancing of all 19th-century spectaculars. This eclecticism was clear from the start when Mr. Corella's power came to the fore. His energy never flagged even when he and Elizabeth Ferrell, dancing excellently, led two ensembles in what looked like a hodgepodge of various ethnic dances.</p>
        <p>Pride of place belongs nonetheless to the classical set pieces. Ms. Ananiashvili, carried in veiled and sold to a pasha, danced with customary amplitude but she could also tease the same resident pasha, subtly acted by Michael Owen, with delightfully detailed small steps.</p>
        <p>Oksana Konobeyeva and Sandra Brown did well enough on Friday as two of the odalisqes and came closer to Ms. Murphy's stunning level on Saturday night. When Conrad rescued Medora and took her to his pirate lair, Mr. Carreno was his magnificent virtuoso self in the pas de trois with Ms. Ananiashvili, dancing in full ballerina mode, and Mr. Picone.</p>
        <p>To suggest the choreography is all Petipa is to forget the many Soviet ballet masters who changed the ballet over the decades. The love duet for Medora and Conrad in the grotto is in a fluent Soviet style, and even most of the male choreography was created in the Soviet era. But when Birbanto leads a mutiny and Medora is returned to the pasha, one can believe that Petipa's choreography is still visible in the pasha's dream. Here Ms. Ananiashvili and Miss Tuttle led units of little girls and a female corps in a symmetrical floral arrangement, the divertissement known as ''Jardin Anime.'' It was lovely.</p>
        <p>And so was Julie Kent, leading Saturday night's cast and hitting her stride in Act II with an unexpectedly subdued Mr. Carreno as Conrad and a polished Mr. Picone as Ali. John Selya as Birbanto, was splendid in his exceptional vigor and Paloma Herrera gave Gulnare a superbly girlish dazzle. Charles Barker conducted the eclectic score by five 19th-century composers.</p>
        <p>LE CORSAIRE</p>
        <p>BALLET REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
