<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Enmity Past, U.S. Meets Iran And Suffers Bitter 2-1 Defeat</title>
    <meta content="22SOCC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Washington; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iran-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0D8153CF931A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Enmity Past, U.S. Meets Iran And Suffers Bitter 2-1 Defeat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>LYONS, France, June 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iran defeats US, 2-1, in World Cup soccer championships in Lyons, France; historic victory, which was Iran's first in its two World Cup appearances, knocks Americans out of competition; game is characterized by displays of friendship and without disruptions, as had been feared by soccer officials, despite vigorous but peaceful demonstration in stands against Islamic regime; Iranian players say victory was significant, and not necessarily for political reasons, since it shows things said about Iran are not true; say it was greatest game they ever played; thousands celebrate in streets of Teheran; Iran's conservative leaders praise team's defeat of strong and arrogant opponents; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Iranian players shook hands with the Americans before tonight's game, handed them white flowers symbolizing peace and even posed together for a picture. But friendship extended only so far. There was a soccer game to win, and not only did Iran prevail, 2-1, but this historic victory also knocked the United States out of contention in the World Cup.</p>
        <p>This was the first time that Iran and the United States had met in soccer and the first time that Iran had won a game in two trips to the World Cup. The countries exchanged visits by their Olympic-style wrestling teams this year, and have participated in the Summer Games, but this was the most visible head-to-head sporting event between the two countries since the Islamic revolution in 1979.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Iranian players shook hands with the Americans before tonight's game, handed them white flowers symbolizing peace and even posed together for a picture. But friendship extended only so far. There was a soccer game to win, and not only did Iran prevail, 2-1, but this historic victory also knocked the United States out of contention in the World Cup.</p>
        <p>This was the first time that Iran and the United States had met in soccer and the first time that Iran had won a game in two trips to the World Cup. The countries exchanged visits by their Olympic-style wrestling teams this year, and have participated in the Summer Games, but this was the most visible head-to-head sporting event between the two countries since the Islamic revolution in 1979.</p>
        <p>In victory tonight, Iranian players said it was significant to have defeated the Americans, and not necessarily for political reasons.</p>
        <p>''I think it is important after 20 years of situations to show that the things said about Iranians are not true,'' said goalkeeper Ahmadreza Abedzadeh. ''We were courageous and we played fair. That is very important.''</p>
        <p>In Teheran, thousands of celebrating fans took to the streets, some women without their scarves, despite efforts by the Islamic regime to make sure that the celebration was not as vociferous as it had been last November when millions took to the streets in spontaneous celebration after Iran qualified for the World Cup for the first time in 20 years. [Page C9.]</p>
        <p>The Iranian players said they knew the people of Iran would be exultant. ''It was the greatest game we ever played,'' said the star forward Khodadad Azizi. ''The whole nation was waiting for this game and expecting us to win.''</p>
        <p>Although soccer's world governing body had feared that protesters would try to disrupt the game, the opposite happened, as fans of both teams seemed to go out of their way to show that they could be friendly even if their governments could not.</p>
        <p>The only demonstration was a vigorous but peaceful protest against Iran's Islamic regime, launched by several thousand Iranian expatriates who smuggled T-shirts and banners into Gerland Stadium showing the pictures of two leaders of a Paris-based opposition group called the National Council of Resistance.</p>
        <p>The match was played several days after President Clinton called for improved relations with Iran after 19 years of enmity between the two countries, and followed a call in January by Iranian President Mohammad Khatami for cultural exchanges between the two countries.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Iran's conservative religious leaders attempted to use the victory for political purposes. Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, who is Iran's ultimate leader, said in a statement broadcast by state television, ''Tonight again the strong and arrogant opponents felt the bitter taste of defeat at your hands.''</p>
        <p>Dissidents also tried to capitalize on the forum by promoting their resistance group. The French police rushed into the stands several times to confiscate banners and pictures celebrating the two leaders of the National Council of Resistance, but new banners and pictures kept popping up like mushrooms. The opposition group's influence is considered limited inside Iran, but the size of the protest was undoubtedly an embarrassment to the Islamic regime.</p>
        <p>In the game's most surreal moment, the protesters waved their T-shirts and banners jubilantly at halftime as the public-address system played the macarena. About 75 French policemen in riot gear marched to one side of the field 10 minutes before the game ended, but the Iranian fans left peacefully and ecstatically.</p>
        <p>While Iran (1-1) is expected to have its hopes of advancing to the second round dashed on Thursday when it faces powerful Germany, at least it can dream. The United States, which has lost both its matches and has scored but one goal in the two games, will now play Yugoslavia on Thursday in a game that will have meaning only to the Yugoslavs.</p>
        <p>Only the top two teams in the group will advance to the next round, and Germany and Yugoslavia each have 4 points, with each winning a game -- for 3 points -- and tying one -- for 1 point. Iran now has 3 points. With no points and a game left, the United States has no hope.</p>
        <p>The Americans cannot match their accomplishment in 1994 of having advanced to the second round. Given their generally poor play and inability to put the ball into the net, the 1998 World Cup will be regarded as a complete failure. Alan I. Rothenberg, president of the United States Soccer Federation, called tonight's defeat a ''bitter disappointment.''</p>
        <p>If the United States were a serious soccer country, Coach Steve Sampson might have lost his job tonight, just as the coaches from Saudi Arabia and South Korea did in recent days. But Rothenberg said Sampson would coach the team against Yugoslavia. Sampson made five lineup changes tonight, scrapping the 3-6-1 formation he had used in the opening 2-0 loss to Germany for a 3-5-2 formation, with Brian McBride and Roy Wegerle at forwards and Tab Ramos, Frankie Hejduk and Joe-Max Moore assuming roles in midfield.</p>
        <p>Sampson wanted assertive play in attack after Monday's tentative loss to Germany and tonight the Americans hit the goal post twice and the crossbar once and outshot Iran, 27-15, but could not score until McBride's header for a goal in the 88th minute. In fact, the Americans came forward so aggressively, took so many risks, that they were left completely out of shape on defense.</p>
        <p>In the 40th minute, with Claudio Reyna giving him far too much room, Iran's Hamid Estili headed a ball past the American goalkeeper Kasey Keller to give his team a 1-0 lead. As the crowd of 35,500, made up largely of Iranian fans, erupted, Estili kissed the ground in celebration.</p>
        <p>In the 83d minute, Mehdi Mahdavikia sprinted past the disheveled American defense and blasted another shot past Keller.</p>
        <p>Sampson faced stern questions about why he kept Eric Wynalda, the Americans' leading career scorer, on the bench, but he said, ''I wouldn't change a thing.''</p>
        <p>Neither would Jalal Talebi, the Iranian coach who has lived for 17 years in Palo Alto, Calif., and who took his current job only four weeks ago after his team floundered with a defensive style. ''This is a big victory,'' he said. ''I don't think the people were celebrating because we played against the United States. They were happy because this is the first time we won a game in the World Cup. Everyone has pride and hope for the future. This was a unity game.''</p>
        <p>Before the game, players from both teams shook hands and stood together for pictures, draped in each other's flags, both in Lyons' sun-baked plazas and outside Gerland Stadium. In a gesture of friendship, some fans even wore red, white and blue hats celebrating the United States and red, green and white jerseys hats celebrating Iran.</p>
        <p>''I never thought I'd be wearing an Iranian flag in my cap,'' said David Mebane, 22, an accountant from Austin, Tex., as he posed with Iranian fans. ''This has changed my attitude toward the people of Iran, from an image of uneducated guys chanting and flag burning to an image of people who are peaceful and more than friendly. I'm thoroughly impressed.''</p>
        <p>Henry Jalali, a native of Iran who has lived for 25 years in San Francisco, where he works as a civil engineer said any victory would be for the Iranian people, not the Islamic regime. Today he wore an American handkerchief flag for a cap and an Iranian jersey.</p>
        <p>''The Islamic regime has deprived Iranians of every moment of joy and happiness,'' Jalali said. ''This shows we are still alive, we are humans. My children in the past were humiliated to say they were Iranian. Now they are proud. This happiness has been brought by the soccer team. ''</p>
        <p>Security was heavy in the blocks surrounding the stadium. And French police confiscated flags of the Iranian opposition, which showed a lion and a sun in the white field of the tricolor instead of the religious symbol of Allah. The National Council of Resistance called the confiscations insulting and criticized governments of both Iran and the United States of attempting to use the game for political benefit.</p>
        <p>Abedzadeh, the Iranian goalkeeper, said of the demonstrators: ''We respect everyone. They were there to give us energy.''</p>
        <p>Talebi, Iran's coach, said: ''Maybe I saw, but I did not care. I was not looking at the protesters; I was looking at my team. It is not good to ask a sportsman a political question.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
