<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Everything for Camp But the Mosquitoes</title>
    <meta content="24SHOP$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/24/technology/24SHOP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1295914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Online Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario/Toronto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Toronto (Ontario)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Red Lodge (Montana)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Outward Bound</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7DF103DF937A15756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Everything for Camp But the Mosquitoes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla Online Shopper column describes shopping online to outfit her two daughters for camp; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the final weeks before my two oldest daughters went away to camp for the first time last summer, it became impossible to walk through their bedroom. Stacks of clothes -- a million pairs of underwear, a billion pairs of socks, a zillion pairs of shorts -- covered the floor in heaps so high that we had to hop from one bare spot to another like frogs on a lily pond.</p>
        <p>Piles of paraphernalia were not what I had in mind when I signed up Zoe, 12, and Ella, 10, for camp. I had envisioned sweet-faced bunkmates, sitting in a circle around a campfire singing hokey songs with wholesome refrains. Accompanied by ukulele. And I imagined them awakening to the same kind of hazy mornings that once prompted E. B. White to write of his childhood summers in Maine, ''The bedroom smelled of the lumber it was made of and of the wet woods whose scent entered through the screen.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the final weeks before my two oldest daughters went away to camp for the first time last summer, it became impossible to walk through their bedroom. Stacks of clothes -- a million pairs of underwear, a billion pairs of socks, a zillion pairs of shorts -- covered the floor in heaps so high that we had to hop from one bare spot to another like frogs on a lily pond.</p>
        <p>Piles of paraphernalia were not what I had in mind when I signed up Zoe, 12, and Ella, 10, for camp. I had envisioned sweet-faced bunkmates, sitting in a circle around a campfire singing hokey songs with wholesome refrains. Accompanied by ukulele. And I imagined them awakening to the same kind of hazy mornings that once prompted E. B. White to write of his childhood summers in Maine, ''The bedroom smelled of the lumber it was made of and of the wet woods whose scent entered through the screen.''</p>
        <p>I was not mentally prepared for the daunting ''Camp Packing List'' that arrived in the mail and sent us scurrying from store to store in a precamp scavenger hunt, accumulating stashes of plastic toothbrush holders, mesh laundry bags and disposable, four-drawer cardboard dressers (apparently a must for bedside storage).</p>
        <p>Upon my daughters' return from camp last year, I took inventory. Here is a list of the items each girl actually used at camp: (1) a bathing suit, (2) a pair of sneakers and (3) sunscreen (although some troubling photographic evidence of sunburned noses suggests a weak commitment).</p>
        <p>Last week, as I pulled the dusty duffels off the laundry room shelf in preparation for next month's return to summer camp, my impulse was to impose a moratorium on purchases. Isn't that the point of summer camp, after all -- to remove kids from the daily temptations of the consumer culture and expose them to more important and timeless values?</p>
        <p>''O.K., but I need just one pair of sweatpants because I know you don't want to worry about how I might be freezing to death,'' said Ella, exhibiting all the qualities of a future trial lawyer. She then shivered delicately, to invoke the cold northern nights. Before I knew it, I found myself reading her list of a ''few small necessities.'' Item: ''lip balm (need three-pack, should be cherry flavor).''</p>
        <p>I savored one victory. This year, instead of wasting hours driving from store to store, I ordered supplies from the Bunkline site (www.bunkline.com), one of a growing number of Web retailers with names like Campsupplies (www  .campsupplies.com) and WolfHead Athletic (www.wolfheadathletic  .com) that specialize in selling all the ''few small necessities'' you can think of, like canteens and flashlights and After Bite insect itch eraser. And you can even ship the order directly to camp, to bypass the bottleneck in your child's bedroom.</p>
        <p>If that sounds too good to be true, listen to this: ''We will even sew in the labels on the clothes before we send them,'' said Ruth Barnett, owner of Bunkline. (Which, come to think of it, might have averted last year's tragedy of having the baby scribble all over her tummy with the indelible marker we bought to write names in shirt collars.)</p>
        <p>Some sites offer free shipping. The Camp Connection site (www  .campstore.com), based in Toronto, offers free ground shipping on orders of more than $150. But order early or you may need to pay to upgrade. Jonathan Silver, the Camp Connection site's general manager, said that ''ground shipping'' is a euphemism for ''it can take two to four weeks to get to the States.''</p>
        <p>At Bunkline, which carries more than 300 items in categories from trunks to toiletries, Ella craved (don't ask me why) a small plastic ''shower tote'' to carry toiletries ($9.95). That prompted Zoe to invoke Subparagraph 3, Line 11 of the equal-treatment clause of the Sibling Bill of Rights, the provisions of which were satisfied by adding a second tote to my shopping basket. The site was behaving poorly, however, and would not display images of the items or let me complete the sale online. I called the toll-free number and placed the order over the phone. The total set me back $24.40, including shipping.</p>
        <p>It could have been worse. In case this is the first year your children will go to summer camp, I would like to warn you about a popular item known as the Crazy Creek camp chair. If you have not already heard about this lightweight, foldable marvel, you soon will. An Outward Bound instructor invented the Crazy Creek nearly 15 years ago to make it possible for campers to sit on the ground without actually making contact with the ground. Prices vary, from  $46.95 at Bunkline.com, to $45 at Campsupplies.com to $38.50 direct from the manufacturer at Crazy Creek (www.crazycreek.com).</p>
        <p>I learned of the chair's existence only last summer via a breathless collect call from camp: ''Everyone  has one so I am the only one with wet shorts from sitting in the grass.''</p>
        <p>When I phoned Walter Goldstein, a spokesman for Crazy Creek Products of Red Lodge, Mont., to complain about the addictive quality of the product, he said: ''It's based on the design of an old canoe chair, and over the last 15 years, millions have been sold. Millions.''</p>
        <p>I know. Two were sold to me. And yes, Zoe and Ella also have ''unbreakable plastic soap dishes'' ($1.49 apiece at Camp Connection) to carry back and forth to their disposable, four-drawer cardboard dressers.</p>
        <p>There may be one bright spot in this buying frenzy: I learned that there might be a tangible emotional benefit in the accumulation of all this stuff. ''Kids who get to help shop and pack for camp,'' said Dr. Christopher Thurber, a clinical psychologist, ''feel like they're taking part in the decision-making process and are much less likely to be as homesick as the ones who don't.'' Dr. Thurber is co-author of ''The Summer Camp Handbook: Everything You Need to Find, Choose and Get Ready for Overnight Camp -- and Skip the Homesickness'' (Perspective Publishing, 2000).</p>
        <p>But no matter what your camp's ''Camp Packing List'' may suggest,  you do not need to go crazy and buy 411 pairs of pajamas.</p>
        <p>''The important thing is the interaction, to let the kid make some of the shopping decisions,'' Dr. Thurber said. ''Even if you're shopping for something as small as toothpaste, if you let the kid pick out the bubble-gum flavor, that's a way of making the kid feel in control.''</p>
        <p>That is a nice way of rationalizing why we now have a pile of lip balm on the floor in the bedroom. And why all of it is labeled ''cherry flavor.''</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
