<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Boy's Slaying Resonates in a Bedroom City of Immigrant Workers</title>
    <meta content="24BOY.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/24/nyregion/24BOY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1296047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Morristown (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valenzuela, Walter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Uruguay</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Morris County (New Jersey)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Morristown (New Jersey)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Central America</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Mount Kisco (New York)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (New Jersey)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Farmingville (New York)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Suffolk</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Madison</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Colombia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Whippany (New Jersey)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Normandy Park</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Uruguay</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Westin Hotel</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cole, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0DE113DF937A15756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Boy's Slaying Resonates in a Bedroom City of Immigrant Workers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS and ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert; Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Morris County, NJ, authorities appeal to Hispanic neighbors of slain 10-year-old Walter Valenzuela to come forward with any information that might aid investigation without worrying about being deported or other penalties if they are illegal aliens; map; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Morris County, N.J., prosecutor urged Hispanic neighbors of a slain 10-year-old Guatemalan boy yesterday to come forward with any information that might aid the investigation, without worrying about deportation or other penalties if they are illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>''We've got a murder to solve,'' said John B. Dangler, the prosecutor, standing outside the home in Morristown of Walter Contreras Valenzuela, whose battered body was found Tuesday morning near railroad tracks less than a mile from the house he shared with his parents and 9-year-old sister. The authorities had been looking for Walter since early Monday, when he failed to return home from a local church carnival.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Morris County, N.J., prosecutor urged Hispanic neighbors of a slain 10-year-old Guatemalan boy yesterday to come forward with any information that might aid the investigation, without worrying about deportation or other penalties if they are illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>''We've got a murder to solve,'' said John B. Dangler, the prosecutor, standing outside the home in Morristown of Walter Contreras Valenzuela, whose battered body was found Tuesday morning near railroad tracks less than a mile from the house he shared with his parents and 9-year-old sister. The authorities had been looking for Walter since early Monday, when he failed to return home from a local church carnival.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor's appeal, on Spanish-language radio and television stations, was one of many indicators of how much the historic city of richly restored Victorians and humble two-family homes, has changed in recent years as Hispanic immigrants flock there in growing numbers. Latinos, including a recent influx of immigrants from Central America, now make up nearly 30 percent of the town's 18,500 residents, up from 5 percent in 1980 and 14 percent a decade ago.</p>
        <p>Morristown, the seat of Morris County, one of the wealthiest counties in the nation, has been partly reborn as a dormitory town for the men and women who trim suburban lawns, pave the driveways and clean the area's corporate office parks. In that regard, it resembles Mount Kisco in Westchester County and Farmingville in Suffolk, other suburbs among many in the region transformed by immigration in the last decade.</p>
        <p>''Because it is located at the center of one of the state's more robust economies, Morristown offers immigrants access to opportunities and provides them with affordable places to live,'' said James W. Hughes, a professor of urban planning and policy at Rutgers.</p>
        <p>Walter's parents -- his mother is a housekeeper at the Westin Hotel in Morristown and his stepfather a waiter at the nearby Madison Hotel -- were comforted yesterday by the Rev. Brando Ibarra, a priest at St. Margaret's Roman Catholic Church.</p>
        <p>''The family is poor,'' Father Ibarra, who is from Colombia, said outside the family's home on Abbett Street, wedged between a gas station and a Baptist church. ''They don't have money for his funeral.''</p>
        <p>But that burden was partly lifted,  Father Ibarra said, by two neighborhood men who went door-to-door collecting money for the family. As of this afternoon, they had raised $640, the priest said, one dollar at a time.</p>
        <p>Eleodora Contreras, the boy's mother, had not realized her son was missing for several hours on Sunday because she collapsed into bed for a nap after a long day of changing sheets and cleaning bathrooms. ''The only thing they were doing was working, working very hard,'' Father Ibarra said of the Valenzuelas and, by implication, others like them. ''But sometimes they can't take care of their kids as well.''</p>
        <p>When Walter's mother woke up  around 8 p.m. and could not find Walter, she started a frantic, door-to-door search in the largely Hispanic neighborhood. ''She was in tears when she came here,'' said Rosa Murillo, 39, whose 11-year-old-son, José, often played video games and soccer with Walter.</p>
        <p>At midnight, Ms. Contreras called the police, who began searching the brush-choked banks of the Whippany River, where Walter sometimes went to fish, and the nearby woods at Historic Speedwell Village, the place where Samuel Morse perfected the telegraph in 1838.</p>
        <p>With tears streaming down her face, Ms. Contreras, 37, told reporters this morning that her son's face had been so badly disfigured that the police had to use fingerprints to make a positive identification. Although investigators would not discuss how the boy had been killed, Mr. Dangler said he had not been sexually assaulted. ''We've got some significant leads,'' is all he would say.</p>
        <p>Those who knew Walter described him as energetic and independent minded, a tree-climbing adventurer who excelled at soccer and enjoyed collecting turtles and minnows from the Whippany River.</p>
        <p>''He was a happy kid, always having fun, always playing,'' said Eddie Gonzales, a neighbor. ''He was just a normal boy.''</p>
        <p>At Normandy Park Elementary School, eight crisis counselors were on hand yesterday to help Walter's classmates grapple with his death. ''There were some pretty devastated kids,'' said Bill Cole, a school psychologist. '' 'Why' was the biggest question -- and 'how.' ''</p>
        <p>Although they were careful not to cast blame on his parents, many residents said they were distressed to learn that Walter had gone to the carnival alone on Sunday night.</p>
        <p>Lester Walker, 44, a neighbor, said Ms. Contreras had tried to set rules about where Walter could and could not go, but that she and her husband were not always around to enforce them. ''I guess they were always out working and he had a lot of free time,'' Mr. Walker said.</p>
        <p>Ruth Klineman, a social worker for the Morris County Office of Hispanic Affairs, said that many immigrant parents in Morristown lacked the English-language skills to help them find better jobs. ''They try to be good parents but it's tragic that their work often keeps them away from their children,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Klineman, a native of Uruguay, said that many Hispanics are accustomed to life in small villages, where people look out for one another's children. ''They come here and they live the same way because they do not know about the dangers,'' she said. ''They shouldn't do that here. But at the same time, they have to feed their kids.''</p>
        <p>Speaking to reporters yesterday, Ms. Contreras expressed regret that she was not always able to watch her son and made a plea for parents to keep an eye on their children. With grief in her voice, she recounted a conversation she had had with Walter the day before he disappeared, with her son saying how he would one day ease her burden. ''He said how much he loved me,'' she said, ''and that one day he'll be able to make a good living and then I won't have to work so hard.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
