<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Broadway Beacon Set to Glow Again</title>
    <meta content="17XPAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="981104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paramount Building (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Times Square and 42d Street (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunlap, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stonbely, George N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D6123FF934A25751C1A961958260" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Broadway Beacon Set to Glow Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunlap, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Great glass globe atop Paramount Building, which was darkened during World War II and later neglected as Times Sqare ebbed, will light skis again, this time with music; rooftop loudspeakers will chime 'Give My Regards to Broadway' 15 minutes before curtain time at surrounding theaters; star-studded dial of four-sided tower clock will be illuminated, and 19-foot sphere at its peak will take on 24,000-watt glow; George N Stonbely, whose company managed $600,000 repair and restoration project, calls it one of final touches validating renaissance of Times Square (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ignited in the incandescent Jazz Age, darkened by the fearful years of war and neglected as Times Square ebbed, the great glass globe atop the Paramount Building will light the skies again. This time, with music.</p>
        <p>Tonight, the craggy summit of the building, between 43d and 44th Streets, is to come glittering back to life. Rooftop loudspeakers will chime ''Give My Regards to Broadway'' 15 minutes before curtain time at surrounding theaters. The star-studded dial of the four-sided tower clock will be illuminated, and the 19-foot sphere at its peak will take on a 24,000-watt glow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ignited in the incandescent Jazz Age, darkened by the fearful years of war and neglected as Times Square ebbed, the great glass globe atop the Paramount Building will light the skies again. This time, with music.</p>
        <p>Tonight, the craggy summit of the building, between 43d and 44th Streets, is to come glittering back to life. Rooftop loudspeakers will chime ''Give My Regards to Broadway'' 15 minutes before curtain time at surrounding theaters. The star-studded dial of the four-sided tower clock will be illuminated, and the 19-foot sphere at its peak will take on a 24,000-watt glow.</p>
        <p>While no match for the candlepower of modern billboards, the globe and clock held their own last night in a test run. On the clock, ruby red tick marks formed a delicate necklace. And when the globe itself turned red, it looked as if a planet-sized blood orange had been suspended in the night sky. Or as if the giant ''i'' of the Paramount Building had at last been dotted.</p>
        <p>''This is one of the final touches validating the renaissance of Times Square,'' said George N. Stonbely, president of Spectacolor Communications, the Manhattan sign company that managed the $600,000 repair and restoration project.</p>
        <p>While the Paramount Theater on the ground floor is long gone, the return of the beacon conjures the squeal of bobby-soxers waiting for Frank Sinatra under the bow-shaped marquee or the infectious swing of Benny Goodman's band as patrons jitterbugged in the aisles.</p>
        <p>''Bringing it back is a sheer joy for the neighborhood,'' said Gretchen Dykstra, president of the Times Square Business Improvement District.</p>
        <p>The Paramount Building was developed by Adolph Zukor, chairman of the Paramount Pictures Corporation, to designs by the Chicago firm Rapp &amp; Rapp. When it opened in 1927, the 33-story tower was the tallest on Broadway north of the Woolworth Building. Its copper and glass globe, symbolizing the worldwide reach of Paramount, enjoyed a prime spot in Manhattan's firmament.</p>
        <p>Five-pointed stars on the clock face, 25 feet in diameter, evoked the stellar halo over Paramount's trademark mountain peak. Across the Hudson River, New Jersey residents could set their watches by the globe, which flashed every quarter hour.</p>
        <p>But in 1942, all illumination was extinguished in Times Square above street level. Those too young to recall the Second World War might imagine that the ''dim out'' was a needless precaution against air raids that never materialized. But the danger posed by a blazing cityscape was very real.</p>
        <p>''German submarines lurking along the ship channels could draw a bead on an Allied freighter with the help of Times Square,'' wrote William Laas in ''Crossroads of the World'' (1965), a history of Times Square. ''Although running without lights, the victim vessel would become clearly silhouetted against the glow.''</p>
        <p>After the war, the lights came on again, but not in the Paramount tower. The theater was closed in 1964 and replaced by office space. The clock sputtered in the 70's and was disconnected. But enough architectural distinction remained in 1988 to warrant landmark designation.</p>
        <p>The Paramount Building is now owned by Janice H. Levin, an art collector and philanthropist, and others. Jeffrey R. Gural, the president of Newmark &amp; Company Real Estate, which manages the property, said the relighting was not needed to attract tenants because the building was fully rented. Rather, he said, Mrs. Levin and the other owners love the city and hope to leave a legacy.</p>
        <p>Jennifer J. Raab, chairwoman of the Landmarks Preservation Commission, believes they will. ''My children will never dance under the stars on the Astor Hotel rooftop, as their grandparents did,'' she said. ''But they'll be able to gaze at the Paramount clock.''</p>
        <p>Even the Paramount marquee will return next year, at least as a reproduction. It will serve as the entrance to a new restaurant to be owned by Robert Earl, the chief executive of Planet Hollywood.</p>
        <p>Overhead, the globe will glow steadily white every night after dusk, Mr. Stonbely said. There will be one red pulse on the quarter hour, two on the half hour, three on the three-quarters hour and four on the hour.</p>
        <p>Broadway's trade association, the League of American Theaters and Producers, said the chime would serve as a sonic nudge to Broadway theatergoers as curtain time nears.</p>
        <p>''If you could flick the lights twice in Times Square, that would be most appropriate,'' said the league's executive director, Jed Bernstein. ''But if you can't, this is the next best thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
