<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dresdner Bank Head to Quit in 2 Weeks</title>
    <meta content="Y17DRES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="981057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dresdner Bank Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sarrazin, Jurgen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DB123FF934A25751C1A961958260" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dresdner Bank Head to Quit in 2 Weeks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, Dec. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jurgen Sarrazin, chief executive of Dresdner Bank AG, announces that he will quit in two weeks, months earlier than he originally planned, apparently because of widening scandal over tax avoidance that has already engulfed several top bank executives; Sarrazin has not been charged with wrongdoing; unexpectedly early resignation is clearest sign yet of turmoil in top ranks of Germany's third-largest bank; it also raises questions about Dresdner's push to become world-class competitor in investment banking (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The chief executive of Dresdner Bank A.G. announced today that he would quit in two weeks, months earlier than he had originally planned, apparently because of a widening scandal over tax avoidance that has already engulfed several top bank executives.</p>
        <p>The executive, Jurgen Sarrazin, has not been charged with wrongdoing, but two top executives have already admitted to evading taxes on millions of dollars of income and government investigators have searched the homes of numerous others -- including that of Mr. Sarrazin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The chief executive of Dresdner Bank A.G. announced today that he would quit in two weeks, months earlier than he had originally planned, apparently because of a widening scandal over tax avoidance that has already engulfed several top bank executives.</p>
        <p>The executive, Jurgen Sarrazin, has not been charged with wrongdoing, but two top executives have already admitted to evading taxes on millions of dollars of income and government investigators have searched the homes of numerous others -- including that of Mr. Sarrazin.</p>
        <p>The unexpectedly early resignation is the clearest sign yet of turmoil in the top ranks of Germany's third-largest bank. It comes at a time when all German banks are under enormous pressure, thanks to a wave of mergers sweeping over Europe and to cutthroat competition as the Continent moves toward introducing a single currency.</p>
        <p>It also raised questions about Dresdner's push to become a world-class competitor in investment banking. Two days ago, Der Spiegel magazine reported that the man in charge of those operations, Hans-Georg Hofmann, had confessed to avoiding taxes on millions of dollars he had made outside Germany. Mr. Hofmann recently stepped down from Dresdner's management board, though he remains in charge of Dresdner's investment banking subsidiary, Dresdner Kleinwort Benson, in London.</p>
        <p>In a brief statement, Mr. Sarrazin said today that ''further controversial personal speculation'' must be put to an end -- an apparent reference to a barrage of reports in the German media over reported tax avoidance. ''The current public discussion does not help the daily service of our workers and the success of our bank,'' Mr. Sarrazin said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarrazin had already startled Germany's still-decorous banking community several months ago when he announced that he would retire in May and defied tradition by rejecting the somewhat honorific post as chairman of the bank's supervisory board. Industry executives say Mr. Sarrazin had run afoul of board room politics and been pushed by board members into early retirement. Bernhard Walter, who currently oversees Dresdner's overseas corporate banking, will succeed him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarrazin's decision to leave even sooner, on Dec. 31, came just two days after the latest blast of bad publicity about Dresdner. According to Der Spiegel, Dresdner's Mr. Hofmann had quietly approached tax investigators earlier this year in the wealthy Frankfurt suburb of Bad Homburg and admitted that he had failed to pay taxes on at least $500,000 of income a year between 1989 and 1996. Mr. Hofmann had earned the money through stock trading profits and other sources outside of Germany -- mostly in Switzerland -- according to the magazine.</p>
        <p>Dresdner executives have emphasized repeatedly that Mr. Hofmann remained a key figure and was in full charge of investment banking activities. But most executives here viewed the move as a step down for Mr. Hofmann, a blunt-spoken and colorful rival to the phlegmatic and aloof Mr. Sarrazin.</p>
        <p>Dresdner had already been embarrassed by a string of other revelations about tax avoidance among top executives.</p>
        <p>Hans Gunther Adenauer, the great-nephew of Germany's first postwar Chancellor, resigned from Dresdner's management board in early October after admitting to the authorities that he had evaded paying hundreds of thousands of dollars in taxes.</p>
        <p>Just a few weeks before that,  Dresdner's former chief executive and the chairman of its supervisory board announced that he too would resign. The former chief executive, Wolfgang Roller, had denied any wrongdoing, and said that he was merely resigning to help end the media's fixation on personal issues.</p>
        <p>The board room antics may indeed prove to be little more than a huge embarrassment at an otherwise solid bank. But they come at a time when bankers here are under enormous pressure to set strategy in a marketplace that is changing at warp speed.</p>
        <p>Dresdner and most other German banks have profit margins that are far lower than those of banks in the United States and Britain. They are saddled by far too many bank branches, while losing lucrative corporate business to Wall Street investment banks. Those pressures have stoked the latest passion for mergers.</p>
        <p>Less than two weeks ago, Union Bank of Switzerland and the Swiss Bank Corporation rocked the industry worldwide by announcing a  merger that will create the world's second-biggest bank, a behemoth with $632 billion in assets and a formidable investment banking presence on Wall Street as well as in Europe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
