<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pro Hockey; Islanders Win With Defense</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="396146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK ISLANDERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA FLYERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL HOCKEY LEAGUE (NHL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FINN, ROBIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D6143CF93BA15753C1A966958260" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pro Hockey; Islanders Win With Defense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FINN, ROBIN</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I. Oct. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was not quite a case of mass soul-searching, said the Islander coach, Al Arbour, but it seemed to work for his world-weary players. They took one meeting, and then another, and tonight, liberated by all the talk and united by a simple, shared conclusion, the Islanders put up a defensive front that flummoxed the Flyers and delivered a 5-2 victory.</p>
        <p>"We had those meetings yesterday and today and realized what kind of team we are," Craig Ludwig said. "If we worry about defense, we can frustrate any other team, and tonight we went into this game with just one thing on our mind. As far as we're concerned, our regular-season opener was tonight."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was not quite a case of mass soul-searching, said the Islander coach, Al Arbour, but it seemed to work for his world-weary players. They took one meeting, and then another, and tonight, liberated by all the talk and united by a simple, shared conclusion, the Islanders put up a defensive front that flummoxed the Flyers and delivered a 5-2 victory.</p>
        <p>"We had those meetings yesterday and today and realized what kind of team we are," Craig Ludwig said. "If we worry about defense, we can frustrate any other team, and tonight we went into this game with just one thing on our mind. As far as we're concerned, our regular-season opener was tonight."</p>
        <p>The Islanders played so carefully in front of the rookie goaltender George Maneluk that not even two early goals from the Flyers dissuaded him or them from their mission of terminating a four-game losing streak. 'George Kept His Composure'</p>
        <p>"We got down by two but nothing changed," Arbour said, "and George kept his composure."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Pat LaFontaine, who had never lost his, supplemented the defensive game plan by scoring his seventh career hat trick, with all three goals the product of power plays.</p>
        <p>Composure had been a commodity in short supply on the club in the course of its losing streak; lately a one-goal deficit had been enough to send the players into a collective cringe from which recovery seemed impossible. But even after falling behind by 2-0 tonight, the Islanders persevered and, with just 30 seconds left in the opening period, managed to regain equal footing with the Flyers.</p>
        <p>"Tonight we fought back, we didn't get down," said LaFontaine, whose three goals were reason enough for the Islanders to experience a buoyancy not yet felt this season.</p>
        <p>"We need Patty to go like that every game for us," Arbour said.</p>
        <p>The evening began eerily for Maneluk, who was beaten in his first N.H.L. start by Philadelphia's very first shot, a glove-high chip from the defenseman Kjell Samuelsson. When Murray Craven made the score 2-0 for the Flyers with Maneluk screened on Philadelphia's fourth shot of the night during a power play at 11:56, another Islander demise seemed imminent. 'I Was Getting Worried'</p>
        <p>"I was getting worried," said Maneluk, who expects to be thrust into the spotlight again on Sunday in Pittsburgh due to injuries to the club's three regular goaltenders. "I was pretty nervous at first."</p>
        <p>But when the Islanders went on the power play just a minute later, LaFontaine had one more dance step than did Ron Hextall, and his pirouette put him behind the goalie with ample net space to aim for at 13:32. Hextall had a clearer confrontation with Bill Berg's blast from the top of the left circle at 19:30, and seemed in the proper position to stop it, but the puck glanced off his stick and drifted into the net to even things at 2-2.</p>
        <p>The Islanders, who had managed all of three goals in their last two outings while yielding 16, took their first period recovery as a positive omen and hastened to embellish it in the second. The activity even got so boisterous around the Flyer net that Hextall eventually surrendered his spot in it to Ken Wreggett.</p>
        <p>LaFontaine, toe-to-toe with Hextall during a power play, gave the Islanders a 3-2 lead at 7:36. Hextall left the game for the solitude of the trainer's room just over a minute later after Randy Wood's shorthanded break-in attempt catapulted him and defenseman Jiri Latal skates first into the crouching goaltender. Hextall suffered a strained left knee in the collision and the Flyers estimated that he will be sidelined for three weeks.</p>
        <p>But LaFontaine was just as unforgiving to Wregget, and, getting the full grasp on a 5-on-3 Islander advantage, the center completed his hat trick with a brisk one-timer from the left circle at 10:42.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
