<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ivory Coast Faces First Free Elections Today</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="396085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IVORY COAST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOBLE, KENNETH B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOUPHOUET-BOIGNY, FELIX (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ivory Coast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Ivory Coast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DA1F3AF93BA15753C1A966958260" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ivory Coast Faces First Free Elections Today</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH B. NOBLE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NOBLE, KENNETH B</byline>
      <dateline>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast, Oct. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a brief and bitter campaign, voters of the Ivory Coast will choose a president on Sunday in their first free elections in nearly three decades.</p>
        <p>Most political commentators believe that the incumbent, Felix Houphouet-Boigny, will almost certainly come out ahead of his challenger, Laurent Gbabgo, a history professor and leader of the Ivorian People's Front.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a brief and bitter campaign, voters of the Ivory Coast will choose a president on Sunday in their first free elections in nearly three decades.</p>
        <p>Most political commentators believe that the incumbent, Felix Houphouet-Boigny, will almost certainly come out ahead of his challenger, Laurent Gbabgo, a history professor and leader of the Ivorian People's Front.</p>
        <p>But victory will not necessarily reflect a public vote of confidence in President Houphouet-Boigny, the only man who has governed this country since it became independent from France in 1960. It is more likely to be based on other factors: an electoral system skewed toward the governing Democratic Party and the often disorganized and ineffectual campaign waged by opposition forces.</p>
        <p>The election here marks the end of the first act of democracy's dramatic comeback in Africa. At least 13 governments have said they will lift bans on opposition parties: Angola, Benin, Cameroon, Cape Verde, Congo, Gabon, Guinea-Bissau, the Ivory Coast, Mozambigue, Sao Tome and Principe, Somalia, Zaire and Zambia. Such action would give millions of people their first chance since independence to choose their leaders freely.  Stark Choice for Voters</p>
        <p>But of all the options to have emerged in Africa, the choice put before Ivorian voters will be among the most stark: to continue with the present leadership or to break with the past and reverse years of authoritarian rule. Mr. Houphouet-Boigny is Africa's longest-serving leader and the third-longest-serving in the world, after Presidents Fidel Castro of Cuba and Kim Il Sung of North Korea.</p>
        <p>In the early 1970's, when opposition parties were still banned, Mr. Gbagbo spent two years in jail for advocating democracy in the Ivory Coast. He later spent seven years of exile in France, where he wrote political tracts and gave speeches lambasting Mr. Houphouet-Boigny and his Government as dictatorial and corrupt.</p>
        <p>In May, bowing to rising demands for social and political change, Mr. Houphouet-Boigy lifted the ban on opposition parties, opening the possibility of a multiparty government. Within weeks, some 25 parties were born.</p>
        <p>But in recent weeks, as it appeared that Mr. Gbagbo would become the standard-bearer for a coalition of opposition parties, leaders of the governing party have attacked him and his supporters with increasing venom, denouncing them as political dilettantes who have aggravated ethnic tensions.</p>
        <p>Given the personal antagonism between the two men, the brief campaign has been often been bitter, but strangely short of substance. Image of Father Figure</p>
        <p>Mr. Houphouet-Boigny has cast himself as a kind of national father figure above the fray, who will serve more as a arbiter than as a chief executive if elected to a sixth five-year term.</p>
        <p>The governing party, moreover, has spent freely and warned that there can be no political stability unless it wins. Leaders of the People's Front, by contrast, have hinted that if they lose it will be a result of Government vote-buying and outright rigging. And they have theatened to retailiate.</p>
        <p>"If we are beaten honestly, we will withdraw with dignity," Mr. Gbagbo told a rally earlier this week, "but if we are robbed, will will act accordingly."</p>
        <p>Politicans concur that the most pressing problem facing the Ivory Coast, the world's largest producer of cocoa, is how to remedy its sinking economy.</p>
        <p>Since becoming President of what had been one of France's more backward African colonies in 1960, Mr. Houphouet-Boigny has presided over a tenfold increase in per capita income, to about $750 today. Of sub-Saharan African countries that do not export oil, the Ivory Coast has a per capita income second only to South Africa's.</p>
        <p>But after four years of slumping agricultural prices, this nation of 11 million people has been plunged into the worst recession since records were first kept at the turn of the country.  Opposition's Economic Program</p>
        <p>Mr. Gbagbo has loosely sketched out a program based on reducing the enormous power of business conglomerates and distributing the national wealth more evenly, but he has given scant detail. The 46-year-old art history specialist has also suggested that Mr. Houphouet-Boigny is too old for another five-year term.</p>
        <p>At a party congress earlier this month, Mr. Houphouet-Boigny was lucid and appeared relatively robust at what he says is the age of 85. But many people insist that he is closer to 90, and there have been persistent rumors that his health is failing. Since the congress, the President has rarely appeared in public and has declined requests for interviews from the press. He has left his campaigning to Laurent Dona Fologo, a senior party official and former Minister of Communication.</p>
        <p>The opposition leader, who has conducted a much more arduous and visible campaign with frequent rallies, has also made an issue of Mr. Houphouet-Boigny's decision to build a Roman Catholic basilica, Our Lady of Peace of Yamoussoukro, the laregst Christian church in the world.</p>
        <p>The President has said he built the church in his native village with his personal funds. But Mr. Gbagbo has called it a "manifestation of presidential megalomania," and said it illustrated a key lesson of modern Africa: the absence of checks and balances.</p>
        <p>Although there are no reliable polls to guide them, most political observers predict that the President will win handily. A key reason is a decision by the governing party to give African foreign nationals the vote.</p>
        <p>Between three and four million Africans -- mostly from neighboring Burkina Faso, Ghana, Mali and Guinea -- live in the Ivory Coast, and most of them are expected to vote for the President.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
