<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Cover</title>
    <meta content="0529COVER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1676291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="HIGHLIGHTS"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E1DB1E39F93AA15756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="472" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Cover</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eagles Farewell I Tour  Wednesday at 8 p.m. on NBC</p>
        <p>THERE seems to be a rule that anyone writing about the Eagles must at some point refer to the band or its music as ''quintessentially American.'' So it may appear incongruous that the group's two-hour concert special on NBC this week was filmed about as far away from the United States as it's possible to get, in Melbourne, Australia. But Don Henley (right), who has been with the group since its beginning, more than three decades ago, said years of touring had created fans all over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eagles Farewell I Tour  Wednesday at 8 p.m. on NBC</p>
        <p>THERE seems to be a rule that anyone writing about the Eagles must at some point refer to the band or its music as ''quintessentially American.'' So it may appear incongruous that the group's two-hour concert special on NBC this week was filmed about as far away from the United States as it's possible to get, in Melbourne, Australia. But Don Henley (right), who has been with the group since its beginning, more than three decades ago, said years of touring had created fans all over.</p>
        <p>''I think we embody for the Japanese, and perhaps for the Australians as well, some of the Western mythology that has been part and parcel of America for quite some time,'' he said, mentioning two countries where the band has especially strong followings. These nations may not be as dependent on the cultural exports of the United States as they once were, since they have developed their own vibrant cultural scenes, but Mr. Henley said the band was still benefiting from the fan base and good will it built up during its hit-making years in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>The NBC special, which includes highlights of three of the group's five concerts in Melbourne, is thick with those well-known hits: ''Take It Easy,'' ''Peaceful Easy Feeling,'' ''Tequila Sunrise'' and more.</p>
        <p>''The key thing with music specials is that there needs to be artists or groups that have a song list that people really know, that they can relate to, and you can remember where you were, and so on,'' said Doug Vaughan, NBC's vice president for special programs. ''There's just a handful, really, that have had that kind of staying power.''</p>
        <p>How have the Eagles (on the cover, from left, Timothy B. Schmidt, Mr. Henley, Glenn Frey and Joe Walsh) managed to mine that body of hits but not become a tiresome nostalgia act?</p>
        <p>''Well, breaking up for 14 years helped,'' said Mr. Henley, referring to the band's long hiatus, which ended in 1994. ''That and the fact that a lot of our songs are well crafted. Songwriting is not just an art, it's a craft.''</p>
        <p>One song in particular continues to surprise him with its reach, he said, remembering a trip he took with CARE to a remote mountaintop in Honduras. To identify the visitor to the rest of the villagers, a local man went into a hut and returned with a cassette player; out of it came the strains of a familiar tune, and the man pointed to the machine, then to Mr. Henley. ''I'm beginning to understand that there's really almost no place you can go on the planet where they're not familiar with the song 'Hotel California,''' Mr. Henley said.</p>
        <p>NEIL GENZLINGER</p>
        <p>HIGHLIGHTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
