<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Accident, Japan Rethinks Its Nuclear Hopes</title>
    <meta content="25JAPA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="918121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plutonium</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tokai (Japan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plutonium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EFDD113BF936A15750C0A961958260" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Accident, Japan Rethinks Its Nuclear Hopes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollack, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>TOKAI, Japan, March 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recent fire and explosion at Japan's only nuclear waste processing plant at Tokai have raised public concern about safety of atomic power and cast cloud over nation's already controversial program to harnesss deadly plutonium as source of energy; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A plaque in front of the village hall proclaims that people here live with ''the fire of the atom.'' This town was the birthplace of atomic energy in Japan -- site of the country's first research reactor and first commercial nuclear power plant -- but in the future it might be remembered more as a place where Japan's nuclear ambitions took a severe blow.</p>
        <p>A fire and explosion here at the country's only nuclear waste reprocessing plant have raised public concern about the safety of atomic power and cast a cloud over Japan's already controversial program to harness deadly plutonium as a source of energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A plaque in front of the village hall proclaims that people here live with ''the fire of the atom.'' This town was the birthplace of atomic energy in Japan -- site of the country's first research reactor and first commercial nuclear power plant -- but in the future it might be remembered more as a place where Japan's nuclear ambitions took a severe blow.</p>
        <p>A fire and explosion here at the country's only nuclear waste reprocessing plant have raised public concern about the safety of atomic power and cast a cloud over Japan's already controversial program to harness deadly plutonium as a source of energy.</p>
        <p>The incident, on March 11, has been classified as the worst nuclear accident in the nation's history.</p>
        <p>Some 37 workers were exposed to radiation, although it was far below levels that would be harmful, the plant's managers said. Some radioactive materials, including plutonium, escaped into the atmosphere and were detected as far as 23 miles away, though at levels that the Government insisted posed no danger.</p>
        <p>But some experts say it is worrisome that any radiation leaked at all. ''I think the accident is technically very serious even if it's not environmentally serious,'' said Atsuyuki Suzuki, professor of nuclear engineering at the University of Tokyo.</p>
        <p>A seeming comedy of errors in responding to the fire and informing the public was more disturbing to some than the amount of radiation released.</p>
        <p>The missteps were committed by the Power Reactor and Nuclear Fuel Development Corporation, a Government-run company that also was in charge of an experimental reactor at which a serious accident occurred in December 1995.</p>
        <p>Japan is banking heavily on conventional uranium-based nuclear power and on advanced systems using plutonium to relieve its almost complete dependence on imported oil and coal.</p>
        <p>Plutonium can be extracted from the spent fuel of nuclear power plants and then used as fuel itself, either in conventional reactors or in fast breeder reactors, which can create more plutonium than they consume.</p>
        <p>The plant in Tokai, a Pacific coast town 70 miles northeast of Tokyo, handles about 12 percent of Japan's spent fuel, with the rest sent to France or Britain for reprocessing. The Tokai plant and the adjacent plutonium fuel fabrication factory now contain about 4.4 tons of plutonium, which is toxic and in some forms can be used to make nuclear warheads.</p>
        <p>Even before the latest accident, Japan's plan was facing a cloudy future because of the December 1995 leak of sodium coolant at the country's prototype fast breeder reactor, known as Monju. No date has been set for reactivating Monju, which has been closed since the accident.</p>
        <p>The Government-run nuclear energy company was harshly criticized for its slow response to the Monju accident and for its attempts to cover it up. The company's top executive was replaced, safety manuals were revised and other reforms were supposedly introduced. But many of the same types of mistakes were made in the Tokai accident.</p>
        <p>The sprinkler system to put out the fire was left on for only one minute. It is believed that failure to extinguish the blaze completely led to the subsequent explosion.</p>
        <p>Containment systems did not function effectively, so that radiation from the room with the fire leaked into an adjacent building, exposing workers, who were not evacuated until 24 minutes after the fire was noticed.</p>
        <p>Although the nuclear energy company reported the initial fire quickly to local governments, it took hours to report that radiation had leaked, and then continually revised upward the amount of leakage and the number of workers exposed. People in Tokai did not know of the explosion, which took place about 8 P.M., until the next morning, in part because the local government withheld the news.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, several officials in the department in charge of repairs at Tokai took part in a golf tournament on the day of the accident and subsequent days as well.</p>
        <p>''The lessons from Monju were not learned,'' conceded Junichi Kurakami, a spokesman for the Tokai works. ''My own mother was asking, 'What's going on with your company?' ''</p>
        <p>The fire started shortly after 10 A.M. in a chamber in which low-level liquid waste from the plutonium extraction process is mixed with asphalt and poured into metal drums for eventual disposal. The waste is so dangerous that people are not allowed in the chamber and all of the work is done by remote-controlled machines.</p>
        <p>The explosion, 10 hours later, blew out most of the windows in the four-story concrete building, as well as some thick shutters and doors, allowing radiation to escape.</p>
        <p>The cause of the fire is still not known. But it is known that asphalt can become combustible when it gets hot enough. One theory is that a contaminant in one of the drums reacted with the nuclear waste, producing heat. A Belgian reprocessing plant had a similar accident in 1981.</p>
        <p>Government officials vowed to continue Japan's nuclear program, saying that while the accident had damaged public confidence, the basic technology was sound.</p>
        <p>''If we judge the accident from only the technical point of view, we don't have a severe problem,'' said Yoichi Fujiie, a member of Japan's Atomic Energy Commission, which makes nuclear policy.</p>
        <p>But it is becoming harder for the Government to find places willing to accept the many more nuclear power plants that it wants to build.</p>
        <p>And in Rokkasho, where a new, larger reprocessing plant is planned, ''We can no longer welcome the facility as warmheartedly as before,'' said Yasuhiro Kobayashi, a local official.</p>
        <p>Even in Tokai, some people are having second thoughts -- something new in the town that became the site of Japan's first research reactor in 1959 and first commercial nuclear power plant in 1965. About a third of the 33,000 residents are dependent on the nuclear industry, and about 40 percent of the municipal tax revenue comes from the industry.</p>
        <p>''For the first time, my anger just exploded,'' said Yoko Owada, 59, who runs a vegetable stand. ''I no longer trust them.''</p>
        <p>Katsuhiro Terunuma, a food wholesaler, said orders from elsewhere in Japan for dried sweet potatoes, the local specialty, dropped 40 percent in the days after the accident.</p>
        <p>Still, if Tokai is any indication, opposition will not be strong enough to stall Japan's nuclear plans.</p>
        <p>''The people from outside the area are more worried than the local people,'' said Tetsuji Fujita, 60, who works at the local agricultural co-op. ''My daughter, who lives elsewhere, called me in the middle of the night saying I shouldn't go outside.''</p>
        <p>''People have lived with the facility for decades,'' said Akiko Kawano, 19, a cashier in a toy store. The store's name is Atom.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
