<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Retailers Fill a New Apparel Niche</title>
    <meta content="30KIDS$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Letting Out the Seams For Chubby Children" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="933416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Letting Out the Seams For Chubby Children"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Penney, J C, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Center for Health Statistics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Canedy, Dana</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2DD103AF933A05756C0A961958260" item-length="2050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Retailers Fill a New Apparel Niche</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANA CANEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Canedy, Dana</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Apparel industry is recognizing that overweight children make up increasing segment of fashion market, and major retail chains are rushing to add larger sizes to their clothing lines and special departments for pudgy preadolescents; National Center for Health Statistics calculates that 4.7 million children aged 6 to 17 were overweight in 1991, latest year for which statistics are available; that was 10.9 percent of total school-age population, more than double 5 percent recorded in 1965; graph; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like many young girls, Jenna Sheffield likes to keep her fashion statements simple: shirts with kittens on them, pink and blue overalls and loose-fitting skirts that she can swirl around in like a dancer.</p>
        <p>''I don't wear dresses much, the top part doesn't fit me,'' said Jenna, who is 8 years old and overweight. ''I just like colored shirts with a pretty design.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like many young girls, Jenna Sheffield likes to keep her fashion statements simple: shirts with kittens on them, pink and blue overalls and loose-fitting skirts that she can swirl around in like a dancer.</p>
        <p>''I don't wear dresses much, the top part doesn't fit me,'' said Jenna, who is 8 years old and overweight. ''I just like colored shirts with a pretty design.''</p>
        <p>Simple desires. But her mother, Shirley Sheffield, says that only recently have stores in the Oakland, Calif., area, where the family lives, begun to carry Jenna's sizes in the same brands and styles that skinnier playmates are wearing.</p>
        <p>''They just started to realize that there must be kids out there who are fat just like they started to realize there are women who are fat,'' Mrs. Sheffield said.</p>
        <p>While consumers still complain that heavier children must pick from dowdy pants and skirts with elastic waistbands that stores stock behind last season's fashion flops, the apparel industry is moving fast to change all that.</p>
        <p>After years of neglect, the industry is recognizing that overweight children make up an increasing segment of the fashion market, and retail chains from the J. C. Penney Company to Kids ''R'' Us are rushing to add larger sizes to their repertoires and special departments for pudgy pre-adolescents.</p>
        <p>The reason for their solicitousness is simple: America's youth, addicted to fast food and computer games they can play from the comfort of a couch, are getting fatter. The National Center for Health Statistics calculates that 4.7 million children aged 6 to 17 were overweight in 1991, the latest year for which statistics are available. That was 10.9 percent of the total school-age population, more than double the 5 percent recorded in 1965.  Under a broader definition of obesity that the Government uses to measure adults, the center said that 22 percent of children and adolescents were overweight in 1991, up from 15 percent in just 10 years.</p>
        <p>''American children over the past decade have been getting significantly heavier,'' said Dr. William J. Klish, a professor of pediatrics at Baylor College of Medicine in Houston and chairman of the American Academy of Pediatrics' nutrition committee. ''We have an epidemic going on in terms of obesity. It is increasing at a rate of about 1 percent a year.''</p>
        <p>Nor is the sheer increase in the number of overweight children the only reason retailers are filling their racks with bigger garments. Baggy is fashionable, with even slender youngsters sporting pants so loose the waistline sags to the knees. Manufacturers of children's wear are stocking larger sizes to keep children in their brands for a year or two longer before they switch to, say, Tommy Hilfiger. And retailers who cater to a youthful market want to keep them from graduating to stores popular with older teen-agers, like Limited Express.</p>
        <p>''It's the manufacturer and retailer holding on to that child in the so-called kids' department longer,'' said Stanley Kaye, an executive with the Larkin Group, which produces the International Kids' Fashion Show in New York.</p>
        <p>That suits many parents just fine, allowing them to postpone for as long as possible their sons' and daughters' switch to the funkier, and more revealing, fashions prevalent among high schoolers. For overweight children, the trend is heaven-sent because it lets them blend in with the crowd.</p>
        <p>For decades, clothing sizes for children aged 7 to 12 ranged from 7 to 14, but size 16 is now increasingly considered the cutoff. In some cases the specifications for standard-size garments are being redefined to make them larger. And some companies have added plus-sizes beyond size 16.</p>
        <p>''Generally, retailers like ourselves are trying to take care of the most important size segment, so the special size segment becomes very under-served in the marketplace,'' said Mary Kwan, vice president and general merchandise manager for the children's division of Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company. ''There is a really good opportunity for us to capture that market.''</p>
        <p>The quandary for retailers, though, is how to market their oversized garments without offending their overweight customers. Sears takes the direct approach, pitching a frequent-shopper program for its Pretty Plus line of girls' clothing in brochures that feature plump young models wearing its larger dresses and jeans.</p>
        <p>Sears introduced Pretty Plus in some of its stores in the late 1980's, and has since added it to 675 stores across the country. So, where Sears's jeans and dresses once only fitted girls aged 7 to about 12 who weighed up to 110 pounds and who had a 33-inch waist, the retailer now sells those items for girls who weigh as much as 145 pounds and whose waists are up to 36 1/2 inches around. (The average weight for 12-year-old girls is 101 pounds, according to Federal data.) Sears said sales of its Pretty Plus clothing have increased strongly in each of the last two years, but declined to give specific figures.</p>
        <p>Julissa Aranda, a Pretty Plus sales clerk at the Rego Park Sears in Queens, says her job requires a certain delicacy of expression. ''You can't say, 'Your daughter is big,' '' Ms. Aranda said. ''I just say that the bigger clothes are built better for their shape, that the clothes won't cut into their waist, because little girls complain about that a lot.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Aranda is convinced the wider variety of apparel for her overweight customers has bolstered their self-confidence. ''Everybody wants to be in style, especially little kids,'' she said. ''It helps them feel better.''</p>
        <p>Kids ''R'' Us has taken the opposite tack to Sears, quietly adding the larger clothes to racks alongside standard-size items rather than promoting them as a separate collection. Kids ''R'' Us, the children's clothing division of Toys ''R'' Us Inc., added girls' plus sizes in 100 stores last year and is in the process of expanding them to all of its 276 stores. And the chain this fall is adding plus sizes for boys to its private-label brand.</p>
        <p>Even retailers who have traditionally sold ''husky'' lines of larger clothing for boys are seeing a need to bulk up. J. C. Penney, for instance, increased the sizes in its ''husky'' line for boys two years ago because of the demand for even roomier garments.</p>
        <p>At the Kmart Corporation, buyers added size 16 to children's clothing orders for the first time this year so its stores would have the larger size on shelves in time for back-to-school shopping this summer. And the Dayton Hudson Corporation, which added a plus size to its children's lines a year ago at its Target Stores, is increasing its assortment, from shorts to jeans, because of customer demand.</p>
        <p>''Typically we have sizes through 16,'' said Susan Eich, a spokesman for Dayton Hudson. ''What we have now is a 16 plus. It's not longer, but it's wider around the middle.''</p>
        <p>None of this came too soon for Rachel James, an overweight 14-year-old who lives on the Upper West Side of New York City. Rachel, who likes to read fashion magazines and shop for ''vintage stuff, like bell bottoms,'' says that finding large-size fashions can still be frustrating, but adds that she has noticed a change at some stores that sell clothes for children and teen-agers.</p>
        <p>''I keep finding these places that have plus-size clothing, which is really nice,'' Rachel said.</p>
        <p>For a lot of larger children, the wider assortment of clothes is taking the trauma out of trips to the mall. Jody Savage, who works for a pharmaceutical company in Oakland, Calif., says it has made a big difference in the outlook of her overweight 12-year-old daughter.</p>
        <p>''She is only now getting to the point where she feels comfortable going into a store,'' Ms. Savage said. ''It used to be an ordeal for her. She had to try on so many things to find something that fit. Very few styles were cut in a way to fit her. Whoever made these clothes made an assumption about body types of the children they are serving. There was an assumption that young girls will be thinner.</p>
        <p>''Now when you go into some stores you do see the larger sizes. We just go to the mall and there are several stores that work out really well for her.''</p>
        <p>It is not just fat children to whom merchants are catering. Health experts point out that children's bodies are maturing faster than they did decades ago and that children are simply bigger overall. Physicians cite better prenatal care that results in bigger babies at birth; diets that while heavy on the fat also include more protein and vegetables, and advances in pediatric medicine as factors.</p>
        <p>Still, it is overweight children who present the most delicate marketing issues. Some companies have even assembled focus groups to seek out  the sources of parental angst and threats to children's self esteem when they shop for plus-size clothes. The findings are not too surprising.</p>
        <p>''We've done some focus studies and found that large children are not really pleased to shop where the word 'chubby' is used,'' said Andrew L. Kahn, chief executive of Kahn-Lucas-Lancaster Inc., a children's clothing manufacturer in New York.</p>
        <p>Recognizing that overweight children do not like being singled out with their own line of clothing, some manufacturers are simply making their garments bigger without changing the numbers on the labels. ''Our 7 to 14 sizes, if anything, are being made more generous and are fitting children only up to 8 or 9 years old,'' said Justin Israel of Knitwaves Inc. in Manhattan, a manufacturer of sportswear for girls. ''Seven to 14 traditionally fit a 7-to-12-year-old child.''</p>
        <p>Some retailers, notably the same upscale department stores that have been criticized for being slow to offer more variety to overweight women, seem to be ignoring the market for large children. Neiman Marcus and Saks Fifth Avenue, for instance, both said they did not offer plus-sizes for children, while Bloomingdale's said it was unaware of the trend.</p>
        <p>Janis Prado, who lives in the San Francisco suburbs with her overweight daughter, said that the lack of variety in children's departments often forced her to shop in junior departments -- even though the clothing costs more and she considers the styles too mature. ''She's only 10,'' Ms. Prado said. ''I don't want her looking older yet. That comes soon enough.''</p>
        <p>Laura White-Mohseni says she has been frustrated by the lack of selection for her overweight son, even at stores that carry larger sizes. ''Now that he is getting older, he wants to look like other kids and not have things that are all elastic in the waist,'' said Mrs. White-Mohseni, who lives in Ruston, La.</p>
        <p>Her son, Shahene Mohseni, 8, said he likes ''regular clothes'' like jeans and jerseys. He also prefers ''sort of baggy stuff. It just feels comfortable,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Letting Out the Seams For Chubby Children</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
