<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="30DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="933453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EED9103AF933A05756C0A961958260" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mutual Fund Inflows Rise; Dow Average Loses 27.05  With investors bullish, cash flows to mutual funds have gained strength in the last two months -- with inflows to stock funds reported at $15.7 billion in April and estimated at $19 billion in May. But fund managers have been cautious, leaving two-thirds of April's new stock money in cash.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mutual Fund Inflows Rise; Dow Average Loses 27.05  With investors bullish, cash flows to mutual funds have gained strength in the last two months -- with inflows to stock funds reported at $15.7 billion in April and estimated at $19 billion in May. But fund managers have been cautious, leaving two-thirds of April's new stock money in cash.</p>
        <p>Stocks fell yesterday, weakened by slack demand for technology issues and a disappointing earnings forecast by Nike. The Dow industrials lost 27.05 points, closing at 7,330.18. $(Page D4.$)</p>
        <p>Nike shares fell 13 percent after the company said that its quarterly earnings would be below expectations because of disappointing sales and the shutdown of a factory in Canada that makes skates. $(D3.$)</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities rose, helped by foreign purchases and reinforced by a better-than-expected auction of five-year notes. The yield on the 30-year bond fell to 6.97 percent, from 7.02 percent on Wednesday. $(D14.$)</p>
        <p>Former Nomura President Arrested Nomura Securities' former president, Hideo Sakamaki, has been arrested in connection with a widening scandal involving suspected illegal payoffs to a racketeer. $(D14.$)</p>
        <p>Scholastic Cutbacks Bolster Shares</p>
        <p>Scholastic announced cost cuts that include the elimination of 400 jobs, intended to save at least $25 million annually. The company's battered stock rose by 11.4 percent. $(D2.$)</p>
        <p>2 Suitors Pursue Bozell</p>
        <p>A sale of Bozell, Jacobs, Kenyon &amp; Eckhardt, the world's 14th-largest advertising agency company, may be near as two bigger competitors, Omnicom and True North Communications, pursue acquisition bids. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. $(D2.$)</p>
        <p>Another Shift in Marvel Fight</p>
        <p>Toy Biz, a company at the heart of the battle for control of Marvel Entertainment, has changed sides again, backing away from an agreement with Marvel bondholders. $(D4.$)</p>
        <p>20 State Securities Regulators Act</p>
        <p>Securities regulators from 20 states, led by Attorney General Dennis C. Vacco of New York, filed lawsuits and took other actions against stockbrokers pushing penny stocks by phone. They acted just as Congress, responding to securities industry pressure, is attacking state enforcement efforts. $(D2.$)</p>
        <p>Trouble at Boston Chicken Unit</p>
        <p>Boston Chicken said that it was unhappy with results in its restaurant division and that the president of the unit, Laurence M. Zwain, had resigned. The announcement sent the company's shares down sharply. $(D4.$)</p>
        <p>American Airlines Seeks Shuttle</p>
        <p>American Airlines moved to buy the U S Airways Shuttle, but its bid is expected to encounter heavy resistance. $(D2.$)</p>
        <p>Sybase Executive Leaves</p>
        <p>The turnaround of Sybase, a maker of data base software that has been struggling to regain its former luster, ran into another hurdle when a key executive left. $(D14.$)</p>
        <p>Kravis Fund Invests in Hospitals</p>
        <p>A venture capital fund established last year by the financier Henry R. Kravis to encourage economic development in New York City is investing $2 million with two troubled hospitals to help them expand a company that will go head-to-head with giant health maintenance organizations. $(B5.$)</p>
        <p>Suit Over Secondhand Smoke</p>
        <p>A lawsuit brought by an American Airlines flight attendant and nonsmoker who has lung cancer could present another front -- the health consequences of secondhand smoke -- in the broadening legal assault on cigarette companies. $(A14.$)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
