<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Decide if Car Leasing Is for You</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Your Money Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="578998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERRING, HUBERT B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDE1E39F935A15751C1A964958260" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Decide if Car Leasing Is for You</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HUBERT B. HERRING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERRING, HUBERT B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Car leasing has joined Santa Claus as a fixture of life: expectations about its gifts may be excessive, but it is here to stay. Nearly a quarter of those who drove off in new cars this year had lease contracts in hand -- and, for a few years, more money in their wallets. Are they making a wise long-term choice?</p>
        <p>Here are a few quick answers:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Car leasing has joined Santa Claus as a fixture of life: expectations about its gifts may be excessive, but it is here to stay. Nearly a quarter of those who drove off in new cars this year had lease contracts in hand -- and, for a few years, more money in their wallets. Are they making a wise long-term choice?</p>
        <p>Here are a few quick answers:</p>
        <p>*If the important thing is driving the best car for a few years at the lowest monthly cost -- lease.</p>
        <p>*If you are able to pay for a car in cash or by taking out a (tax-deductible) home equity loan -- buy.</p>
        <p>*If you expect to keep a car more than a few years, you are probably still better off buying, though some lease deals may be good enough to be exceptions.</p>
        <p>*If you drive long distances, or expect the seats to be adorned with peanut butter and apple juice within weeks -- buy.</p>
        <p>*If a lease has terms far wide of the norm, pass it by. For instance, most leases, before penalties kick in, allow 12,000 to 15,000 miles a year -- plenty for most people. Some offer far less.</p>
        <p>*Read the fine print. Then read it again.</p>
        <p>Beyond this, it gets harder to figure. You must examine the facts and your budget, weigh various intangibles and huddle with your calculator.</p>
        <p>Be aware that in terms of your commitment, leasing differs little from buying. If you lease for, say, four years, you are essentially buying the first four years of a car's life and promising to deliver later a cream puff of a used car -- 1 ownr, lo mlge, exc cond.</p>
        <p>So to look solely at monthly payments is shortsighted. You do not buy a house just because payments fit your budget; you study the market and decide whether the price is right.</p>
        <p>One variable you can predict is interest costs. If you lease, you are borrowing a car's entire value from the first day, so borrowing costs are built in. But as with an auto loan, that interest is not deductible. So if you use a home equity loan, your after-tax interest will be lower. And if you pay cash, your interest cost becomes the return you passed up, which is probably lower still.</p>
        <p>But what are a car's first years worth? Depreciation varies widely, with a Mercedes retaining a far higher percentage of its initial value than, say, a Chrysler Le Baron.</p>
        <p>So your basic calculation is this. Add up all leasing costs. Then add up the purchase costs over the same years. The difference is what you will have paid for that used car. Is that a good price?</p>
        <p>That could depend on whether you keep it, because the price of a good used car is far higher if you're buying than if you're selling. If you sell a used car, you either get the lower price a dealer will pay or face the headache of selling it yourself, so leasing would often have made more sense. But if you expect to buy after leasing, which you can usually do, either at a preset price or a "fair market value," you may be better off buying. You will get the best possible used car -- one you took care of yourself -- and you will not have to plunk down $10,000 or so to get it.</p>
        <p>For some, leasing fits. Patrick Molt of Irvington, N.Y., recently decided on a Volvo 850. After studying the numbers, he estimated that the interest rate built into the lease was 8 percent, compared with 8.5 percent for financing. That decided it.</p>
        <p>But others run into problems. Thomas Sanzillo and Theresa Funiciello of New York City tried to end two leases early and faced $5,000 in penalties, not the $500 they expected. They sued the lessor, asserting that the terms were lost in small print.</p>
        <p>Oh yes, the small print: excavate it thoroughly. If an ad trumpets dazzlingly low payments, read on for an often-hefty "capital cost reduction" -- fancy words for a down payment. BMW recently ran afoul of New York's Attorney General, who called its lease offer misleading, saying it obscured that payment. Ending a Lease Agreement</p>
        <p>New York City's Consumer Affairs Department warns that terms for ending a lease early vary widely and advises consumers to pin down any penalties ahead of time. Also, most buyers "heave a sigh of relief when they make their last car payment," the agency says. But "with leasing, this is often where the trouble starts." Are you just responsible for "excess wear and tear," or must the car be showroom-clean? You had better find out; the difference can be thousands of dollars.</p>
        <p>In any case, leasing is definitely on the rise. In 1992, 24 percent of new cars were leased, up from 12 percent in 1986, according to Art Spinella of CNW Marketing/Research, which tracks car leasing. In explaining that rise, he cites the escalating battle for consumer dollars.</p>
        <p>"Car companies are no longer competing only with each other," he said, "but with makers of home computers and other products." He estimates that 20 percent of people who lease should not do so and half the people who buy should probably lease.</p>
        <p>But he stresses that for leasing to make long-term sense, the money saved month by month should be invested or used for some lasting purpose, like adding on to a home.</p>
        <p>Tax considerations should not be a factor. You may get a slightly larger deduction for business use if you lease, "but the little bit you may save will not outweigh a bad lease," says Shelley Martin, a partner at Weikart Tax Associates in New York.</p>
        <p>Still not sure? Maybe the deciding factor is this: You simply do not want the feeling that the new car in your driveway belongs to a leasing company. On the other hand, leasing may make you feel just a bit less anxious with that expensive piece of metal sitting all alone out there.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
