<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russians Dazzle And Take The Gold</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="866723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="ATLANTA: DAY 4 -- GYMNASTICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1996)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GYMNASTICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UKRAINE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLAREY, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NEMOV, ALEKSEI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED91639F930A15754C0A960958260" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russians Dazzle And Take The Gold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLAREY, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, July 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The record book will show that Russia won its first Olympic gymnastics gold medal in the team competition tonight.</p>
        <p>The record book will be slightly misleading.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The record book will show that Russia won its first Olympic gymnastics gold medal in the team competition tonight.</p>
        <p>The record book will be slightly misleading.</p>
        <p>What the comprehensive Russian victory over the Chinese represented was continuity, not novelty. The Soviet Union may no longer exist, but the gymnasts  it identified as youngsters and trained are still capable of excelling on the world stage.</p>
        <p>And though some now excel for Ukraine or Belarus or even Germany, there were  enough left representing Russia to win yet another gold for Coach Leonid Arkaev, the driving and often Draconian force behind the Soviet dominance of the sport from the late 1970's until the dissolution of the nation in 1991.</p>
        <p>Arkaev, with his closely cropped gray hair and imperious bearing, was ubiquitous during training and competition in the Georgia Dome, rearranging lineups, attitudes and even rubber landing mats.</p>
        <p>Despite, or perhaps because of, the tight rein, the Russian team performed brilliantly. It has a fine mix of talent with two familiar stars, Aleksei Voropaev and Sergei Charkov, and one brilliant new one: the 20-year-old Aleksei  Nemov, now the favorite for the all-around gold medal. And when the last giant swing had been swung and the last landing had been "stuck," the Russian gymnasts and coaches exchanged hugs and kisses (on the lips, Russian style).</p>
        <p>"There is a difference," said Voropaev, part of the so-called Unified Team that won gold at the 1992 Olympics. "Before, it was very difficult to make the team, and you felt a huge responsibility when you did. I had Vitaly Shcherbo and Igor Korobchinski next to me. Now, I have Nemov and others. It is good now, but  I think it was stronger then."</p>
        <p>The Russians came into the optional round with a lead of 1 point over the two-time defending world champion Chinese. After three of the six rotations, the Chinese had cut the lead nearly in half, but the Russians reversed the trend on  vault and then took command on the next rotation when three Chinese fell while performing on the horizontal bar: Shen Jian, Huang Huadong and Huang Liping.</p>
        <p>The Russians won with 576.778 points. China, a silver medalist in 1984 and 1992, finished second again with 575.539 points. Ukraine, which has three former Soviet stars including Korobchinski, held on for the bronze with 571.541. Belarus was fourth with 571.381 and the United States a respectable fifth with 570.618.</p>
        <p>The Americans, fifth after compulsories, had dreamed of winning the bronze at home, and the crowd of 30,788 did its best to egg them on, but after a promising start on the parallel bars and the horizontal bar, Peter Kormann's team fell back with major mistakes on the floor exercise and, more predictably, the pommel horse, its weakest event.</p>
        <p>The consolation prize was that fifth was considerably better than the American men's ninth-place finish at the last two world championships. It also was the best result for an American men's team at the Olympics since Bart Conner, Peter Vidmar and their charismatic cohorts won the gold in 1984 at the Los Angeles Games the Soviets boycotted. Also encouraging was the performance of John Roethlisberger, who finished with the fifth-highest combined score after compulsories and optionals. If not for his fall on the pommel horse, which cost  him half a point, Roethlisberger would have been second behind Nemov. Two Americans qualified for event finals: Blaine Wilson on rings and Jair Lynch on parallel bars.</p>
        <p>"We are the most improved team in the world," Kormann said. "We had some rough spots, but we were in the hunt for the medal the whole way. One year ago,  no one would have thought we'd be in the hunt."</p>
        <p>Less than one year ago, it looked unlikely that the Russians would be in position to win the gold. They finished 11th in compulsory exercises at the world championships in Sabae, Japan, last October and ended up fourth over all,  which was fine for most nations but not for one that was supposed to carry the Soviet gymnastics torch. But the Russians and the once-flighty Nemov have made great leaps in a sport where improvement is incremental.</p>
        <p>"We have a saying in Russia: Tough luck makes you luckier," Arkaev said. "After Sabae, we had to search deep and start thinking of what we are and who we are. We did a lot of soul-searching."</p>
        <p>Arkaev took risks. He left Yevgeny Shabaev, last year's world all-around bronze medalist, at home because he believed Shabaev's injured shoulder was still suspect. He left another top gymnast, Dmitri Karbonenko, at home in France and picked 17-year-old Nikolai Krukov, the silver medalist at last year's world  championships and the youngest men's gymnast in Atlanta. Krukov never broke. Nor did Charkov, a member of the Soviet team that won gold in 1988.</p>
        <p>Charkov was coaching in Germany last year, but after watching the Russians struggle in Japan, he called Arkaev and asked to return to the famous and now slightly crumbling Round Lake training complex near Moscow. The Russians' lowest score in tonight's 36 routines was a 9.225 from Yevgeny Podgorny on parallel bars; they were able to drop that because only the top five scores on each apparatus count.</p>
        <p>Nemov has been there since age 14, and tonight he put all his training to good use. His lowest score was a 9.65 on rings, but he qualified for the five other event finals. His overall total was 116.361 points, more than a point better than Vitaly Shcherbo of Belarus, the winner of six Olympic gold medals in 1992, who fell on the pommel horse tonight. In third was Voropaev, followed by Jordan Jovtchev of Bulgaria, Roethlisberger and the defending world all-around champion, Li Xiaoshuang.</p>
        <p>Wilson and his fellow American John Macready finished 12th and 33d and qualified with Roethlisberger for Wednesday's all-around final.</p>
        <p>"We competed our hearts out," said a teary Roethlisberger.</p>
        <p>ATLANTA: DAY 4 -- GYMNASTICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
