<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Martha Stewart Uses Web to Tell Her Side of Story</title>
    <meta content="Y06ADC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/06/business/media/06ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1494832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insider Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Erbitux (Drug)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Imclone Systems</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Martha</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Erbitux (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insider Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Stewart, Martha</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D61F30F935A35755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Martha Stewart Uses Web to Tell Her Side of Story</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Martha Stewart Uses Web to Tell Her Side of Story</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martha Stewart uses her Website to declare her innocence, arguing that government, after more than year, has decided to bring charges against her for matters that are personal and unrelated to business of Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia; asserts she will fight to clear her name; also pays for full-page advertisement in USA Today in which she says she is innocent of crimes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>She has been indicted and deposed and made to march before tabloid paparazzi, but Martha Stewart is now taking her case to the people, electronically.</p>
        <p>''After more than a year, the government has decided to bring charges against me for matters that are personal and entirely unrelated to the business of Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia,'' Ms. Stewart wrote in an open letter posted on a Web site that began operating early yesterday. ''I want you to know that I am innocent -- and that I will fight to clear my name.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>She has been indicted and deposed and made to march before tabloid paparazzi, but Martha Stewart is now taking her case to the people, electronically.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>She has been indicted and deposed and made to march before tabloid paparazzi, but Martha Stewart is now taking her case to the people, electronically.</p>
        <p>''After more than a year, the government has decided to bring charges against me for matters that are personal and entirely unrelated to the business of Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia,'' Ms. Stewart wrote in an open letter posted on a Web site that began operating early yesterday. ''I want you to know that I am innocent -- and that I will fight to clear my name.''</p>
        <p>The site, www.marthatalks.com, is part of an offensive by Ms. Stewart in the wake of her indictment on conspiracy, obstruction of justice and securities fraud charges.</p>
        <p>She also paid for a full-page advertisement in USA Today yesterday. In it she said she was innocent of the crimes that the Justice Department and the Securities and Exchange Commission say she committed in the course of selling nearly 4,000 shares of ImClone Systems in late December 2001.</p>
        <p>The Web site, a novel use of the Internet for a defendant in a high-profile criminal case, is her way to ''stay in direct touch with her public,'' said a spokesman. The direct communication might help her image and initially seemed to bring out support.</p>
        <p>A statement from her lawyers that was issued after the indictment on Wednesday is posted on the site, and visitors can send her e-mail. In its first 16 hours or so, the Web site received more than a million hits and about 12,000 e-mail messages, the spokesman said, including one from a federal agent who wrote encouraging Ms. Stewart not to settle.</p>
        <p>''This entire charade smells like a railroad job to me,'' he wrote, according to a message provided by a public relations firm, Citigate Sard Verbinnen, that began representing Ms. Stewart in recent weeks. ''Somebody's grandstanding and using you to get their name into the press. I'm really sorry about that. These folks are wasting precious time, sweat and treasure for what amounts to (if it even happened) a really trivial offense.'' The writer admits he is a longtime fan: ''I've followed your career over the years and I've always been an admirer. I learned how to roast corn from you, a skill which continues to impress my friends.''</p>
        <p>The investigation of the circumstances surrounding Ms. Stewart's sale of Imclone stock culminated in the criminal indictment against Ms. Stewart and her stockbroker, Peter E. Bacanovic, who are accused of lying about the reasons for the trade.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stewart and her broker have said they had prearranged to sell if the share price fell below $60, but the government says she sold after learning that ImClone's top officer was selling his shares. The S.E.C. has sued them both for insider trading and is seeking to bar Ms. Stewart from serving as a director of any public company and to limit any executive role.</p>
        <p>On the Web site, Ms. Stewart does not mention that $60-a-share explanation, writing instead that ''I simply returned a call from my stockbroker.''</p>
        <p>''Based in large part on prior discussions with my broker about price, I authorized a sale of my remaining shares in a biotech company called ImClone,'' she writes.</p>
        <p>After she and Mr. Bacanovic pleaded not guilty to all the criminal charges, Ms. Stewart stepped down as chairwoman and chief executive of her media and merchandising company. She remains a director and chief creative officer and is certainly the face of the company.</p>
        <p>The e-mailer's suggestion that Ms. Stewart was somehow singled out has been contradicted by the government.</p>
        <p>Wayne M. Carlin, regional director of the S.E.C., noted that the agency had brought insider-trading charges that involved smaller gains than Ms. Stewart's against people less well known than she is. ''There would be something very wrong, if we're bringing those cases, and we gave Martha Stewart a pass because she's famous,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Several people said that starting a Web site could improve her image, badly tarnished by the events of the last 12 months.</p>
        <p>''It's something she should have done earlier,'' said Jennifer Openshaw, host of the public-television show ''What's Your Net Worth?'' ''She needs to be connecting with the public.''</p>
        <p>Joe Lockhart, a former Clinton administration spokesman who is now a Washington image consultant, said communicating directly with people -- via ads, the Web or other means -- can be more effective than relying on television and newspaper coverage. ''In a situation like this, you've got to use every tool you can,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Others say there could be a downside. ''It's a mixed bag,'' said Jim Cohen, a professor at the Fordham University School of Law, who frequently defends clients in federal court. ''The short-term gain for her is that she will level the playing field a little bit after all the negative publicity. The short-term negative is that the U.S. attorney's office will react as if they have been poked in the eye.''</p>
        <p>Once Ms. Stewart's case comes to trial, as her lawyers have vowed it will, the Web site may produce other benefits. ''It's interesting because it is arguably an attempt to influence the jury pool,'' said Roman Darmer, a former federal prosecutor in Manhattan. ''If her side is putting out information on the site, that's fairly significant.'' At the same time, doing so may give away the defense's strategy. And then again, ''people may disagree with you,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, admiration seems to flow from every quarter.</p>
        <p>''You don't know me, but I've watched your show for years, in a 2-bedroom, 1-bath trailer with my husband and my 3 children,'' wrote a woman named Wendy Yockey. ''While we busted our butts, managing 3 kids, work, and a budget, I watched my inspiration shows. Which of course included yours.'' Today, Ms. Yockey added, the family lives in a large house with a garden. She closed her message: ''Fight Martha, Fight!!''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
