<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MediaTalk; Magazine Rivals in Tug of War Over Star</title>
    <meta content="14BRIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/14/business/14BRIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1293275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vogue (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harper's Bazaar (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuczynski, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wintour, Anna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spears, Britney</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Audit Bureau of Circulations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Spears, Britney</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bundchen, Gisele</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, Laura</person>
        <person class="online_producer">O'Connell, Patrick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EEDC163AF937A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="449" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MediaTalk; Magazine Rivals in Tug of War Over Star</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX KUCZYNSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kuczynski, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vogue magazine editor in chief, Anna Wintour, reconsiders plan to feature Britney Spears on November cover after learning singer will be on August cover of Harper's Bazaar; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oops! Britney Spears might have done it again.</p>
        <p>The magazine wars between Harper's Bazaar and Vogue magazine continue at full tilt, and Ms. Spears is at the heart of the latest battle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oops! Britney Spears might have done it again.</p>
        <p>The magazine wars between Harper's Bazaar and Vogue magazine continue at full tilt, and Ms. Spears is at the heart of the latest battle.</p>
        <p>Last month, sparks flew when Katherine Betts, the editor in chief of Harper's Bazaar, and Anna Wintour, her former mentor and current archrival, the editor in chief of Vogue, discovered that their magazines had not only featured the same model -- Gisele Bundchen -- on their June covers, but also featured interviews with the first lady, Laura Bush.</p>
        <p>Now the magazines are at odds again, but this time it is over the bubblegum-pop star Ms. Spears, the bellybutton-baring teenager behind hits like ''Oops! I Did it Again'' and ''What U See (Is What U Get).''</p>
        <p>Executives at Condé Nast, which owns Vogue, said Ms. Wintour had planned to feature Ms. Spears on the magazine's November cover, but that she had learned that Ms. Spears would be on the August cover of Harper's Bazaar, and was reconsidering giving Ms. Spears the Vogue cover, one of the most coveted pieces of real estate for stars on the rise.</p>
        <p>Ms. Betts at Harper's Bazaar said that her cover for August had been planned for a long time. ''We have been thinking about her for a while,'' she said. ''And we wanted to make sure it was the right moment. August happens to be 'our women in power in entertainment' issue, so we figured that was the right moment.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Vogue, Patrick O'Connell, said that Ms. Spears had not been taken off the cover schedule. He would not say what month she was scheduled to appear.</p>
        <p>The battle over Ms. Spears comes at a time of depressed newsstand sales. Vogue's single-copy sales dropped 9.1 percent, to 430,942, on average during the last six-month period audited by the Audit Bureau of Circulations, which ended Dec. 31. Total circulation rose 1 percent, to 1.1 million. Harper's Bazaar's dropped 2.5 percent, to 169,301, with overall circulation dropping 5.7 percent, to 708,104.</p>
        <p>Lisa Kasteler, Ms. Spears's spokeswoman, said that as far as she knew, Ms. Spears was still confirmed for both covers.</p>
        <p>When asked what her game plan would be if Ms. Spears was no longer welcome at Vogue, Ms. Kasteler said she had no such plan. ''Come on, she's Britney Spears,'' she said. ''Vogue would have to be idiots to throw her off the cover.''</p>
        <p>ALEX KUCZYNSKI</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
