<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baseball's Antitrust Exemption Suffers a Setback</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="780153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTITRUST ACTIONS AND LAWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAJOR LEAGUES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DA123EF937A3575BC0A963958260" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baseball's Antitrust Exemption Suffers a Setback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball's 73-year-old exemption from antitrust laws sustained at least a temporary jolt yesterday when the Senate Judiciary Committee, for the first time ever, sent to the full Senate a bill calling for partial repeal of the exemption.</p>
        <p>The legislation, approved by a 9-8 vote, would repeal the antitrust exemption in labor matters, freeing the players to use the courts as players in other sports have done. It would not affect the minor leagues, the amateur draft or franchise relocation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Baseball's 73-year-old exemption from antitrust laws sustained at least a temporary jolt yesterday when the Senate Judiciary Committee, for the first time ever, sent to the full Senate a bill calling for partial repeal of the exemption.</p>
        <p>The legislation, approved by a 9-8 vote, would repeal the antitrust exemption in labor matters, freeing the players to use the courts as players in other sports have done. It would not affect the minor leagues, the amateur draft or franchise relocation.</p>
        <p>Committee members said afterward that a vote in the full Senate would be close, but that the measure might pass.</p>
        <p>"It stands a very good chance, partly because the people in baseball today are their own worst enemies," said Senator Patrick Leahy, Democrat of Vermont, who voted in favor of the bill. "The argument I made was very simple: If we didn't have an antitrust exemption and they came to Congress today asking for it, do you think they'd get more than five votes?"</p>
        <p>Dianne Feinstein, Democrat of California, and an opponent of the bill, said only, "It's got a good chance."</p>
        <p>There was no immediate indication of when the bill would reach the Senate floor. When it does, it will be the target of an intensive lobbying effort by the major league owners, who desperately want to retain the exemption the United States Supreme Court granted baseball in 1922.</p>
        <p>The owners have aggressively lobbied members of the judiciary committee since the bill was introduced last January. One person familiar with their campaign quoted some Senators as saying they might be inclined to vote for the bill but were feeling "too much political heat."</p>
        <p>A similar bill was rejected by the committee, 10-7, in June 1994. Three members who voted for the bill last year and two who voted against it no longer are on the committee. Three other members switched their votes. Orrin Hatch, Republican of Utah, who became the committee chairman last November and became a co-sponsor of the bill, and Edward Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts, voted for the bill this time. Charles Grassley, Republican of Iowa, changed to a no vote.</p>
        <p>Herbert Kohl, Democrat of Wisconsin, abstained from yesterday's vote because he owns the Milwaukee Bucks basketball team. He is also a lifelong friend of Bud Selig, baseball's acting commissioner.</p>
        <p>Deprived of the chance that Kohl's vote would have created a 9-9 deadlock and stalled the bill, Selig said in a statement, "The game of baseball was not positively served by the Senate committee action today," adding, "We are confident that the full Senate will see the wisdom of our arguments."</p>
        <p>The Players Association, which has conducted a lobbying campaign of its own, adopted a low-key approach in its reaction to the committee vote. The executive director, Donald Fehr, spoke, like Selig, of the need for a new labor agreement and the promotion of the game.</p>
        <p>"Removing the antitrust exemption," he said in a statement, "is a significant push in the right direction. We urge the full Senate and the House of Representatives to pass this bill promptly."</p>
        <p>In approving the legislation, the committee produced a split party vote: three Democrats and six Republicans in favor, four Democrats and four Republicans opposed.</p>
        <p>Joining Hatch, Kennedy and Leahy in voting yes were Russ Feingold, Democrat of Wisconsin, and Strom Thurmond of South Carolina, Alan Simpson of Wyoming, Michael DeWine of Ohio, Spencer Abraham of Michigan and Fred Thompson of Tennessee, Republicans.</p>
        <p>Voting no with Grassley and Feinstein were Joseph Biden of Delaware, Paul Simon of Illinois and Howell Heflin of Alabama, Democrats, and Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania, Hank Brown of Colorado and Jon Kyl of Arizona, Republicans.</p>
        <p>When the committee rejected the bill last year, future prospects for legislation to repeal the exemption looked bleak. Howard Metzenbaum, Democrat of Ohio, who was the moving force behind the bill, was retiring from the Senate and no other Senator on the committee appeared ready to pick up where Metzenbaum left off.</p>
        <p>But as the labor dispute between the players and the owners wore on and the players' strike seemed endless, Hatch became the bill's champion on the Republican side.</p>
        <p>"A limited repeal of the antitrust immunity for baseball is now in order," Hatch said yesterday before the vote. "The immunity has distorted labor relations in major league baseball and has sheltered baseball from the market forces that have allowed the other professional sports, such as football and basketball, to thrive."</p>
        <p>Biden, the Senate's ranking minority member, said of his opposition to the bill: "I'm on the side of staying out of it. On the side that says don't intervene. I'm beginning to think baseball's not worth it."</p>
        <p>Before the vote, Simpson introduced an amendment linked to the naming of an independent commissioner, which baseball has not had for nearly three years. If an independent commissioner with authority in labor relations were appointed within 90 days, the amendment stipulated, the exemption would remain intact. Furthermore, the amendment provided for joint election of a commissioner by owners and players and Presidential involvement in the process if the two sides failed to agree on a commissioner. But the committee rejected the amendment by a 10-6 vote.</p>
        <p>Last September, a bill to lift the exemption was voted out of the House Judiciary Committee, but the term ended before it reached the House floor.  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
