<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Upstate Race for House Seat Turns Into a Nasty Fight</title>
    <meta content="11sweeney" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/11/nyregion/11sweeney.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1796404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DF1030F932A25753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Upstate Race for House Seat Turns Into a Nasty Fight</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Upstate Race for a Seat in Congress Turns Nasty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Locked in one of the costliest and nastiest House races in New York State, Representative John Sweeney, a four-term Republican from the Albany region, and his Democratic challenger traded pointed accusations yesterday over each other's character and fitness for office.</p>
        <p>The day of charges and countercharges began when the Democrat, Kirsten Gillibrand, called on Mr. Sweeney to release records stemming from any ''run-ins with the law you may be hiding from voters.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative John Sweeney of New York, who is a Republican, and his Democratic challenger, Kirsten Gillibrand, attacked each other’s character and fitness for Congressional office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Locked in one of the costliest and nastiest House races in New York State, Representative John Sweeney, a four-term Republican from the Albany region, and his Democratic challenger traded pointed accusations yesterday over each other's character and fitness for office.</p>
        <p>The day of charges and countercharges began when the Democrat, Kirsten Gillibrand, called on Mr. Sweeney to release records stemming from any ''run-ins with the law you may be hiding from voters.''</p>
        <p>In issuing the call, she cited two incidents that resulted in Mr. Sweeney's arrest nearly 30 years ago -- one in 1977 for turning in a false fire alarm and another a year later for driving while intoxicated. Ms. Gillibrand also seized on a 2001 incident in which Mr. Sweeney drove his car into a utility pole after, he said, he had had two glasses of wine. While he was not charged or issued a ticket, questions about whether he received preferential treatment by the local police have surrounded the case.</p>
        <p>''Your decision to release any and all records related to your arrests and other incidents with law enforcement will send an important signal about your willingness to come clean with voters,'' Ms. Gillibrand said in a letter to Mr. Sweeney that her campaign distributed to reporters. ''Failure to do so will send the message that you have something to hide.''</p>
        <p>The Sweeney camp said that the congressman had nothing to hide and that all records involving the incident were publicly available from the authorities -- a claim that the Gillibrand camp denied.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney's campaign staff accused Ms. Gillibrand of dredging up 30-year-old incidents as part of a ''desperate'' campaign ploy. ''It's all old news,'' said Maureen O'Brien Donovan, a spokeswoman for the Sweeney campaign. ''This stuff has been in the paper. It's been talked about before. Ms. Gillibrand is trying to win a race and she's brought the campaign down to the gutter.''</p>
        <p>While several polls have shown Mr. Sweeney holding a lead in the heavily Republican district, some Democrats believe that he is potentially vulnerable, given the war in Iraq and President Bush's ratings. Mr. Sweeney has spent more than $1.6 million and Ms. Gillibrand more than $800,000, according to the most recent statements.</p>
        <p>The attacks by Ms. Gillibrand are just the latest example of how Democrats have tried to use ethics issues to club Republicans, after a string of damaging revelations, particularly that Republican leaders failed to act on initial signals that a colleague was sexually harassing male teenage pages. In her letter, for example, Ms. Gillibrand seemed to make reference to claims that Republican leaders had deliberately ignored signs that that colleague, Representative Mark Foley, a Florida Republican who resigned last month, was having inappropriate exchanges with the pages.</p>
        <p>''Now more than ever, voters need to be assured that their member of Congress is not involved in any sort of legal cover-up or is above the law in any way,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The bitter tone of the exchange is nothing new in the contest in New York's 20th Congressional District, which stretches from Dutchess County to near the Canadian border in the eastern part of the state, and also includes counties southwest of Albany. As it enters its final weeks, the race has become dominated by a barrage of nasty charges from both candidates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney, for example, has sought to portray Ms. Gillibrand as a wealthy Manhattan lawyer who moved to the district to run for Congress. In one recent television spot, the Sweeney camp accuses Ms. Gillibrand, who grew up in the district, of ''living the high life,'' of refusing to release her tax returns and of war profiteering stemming from ownership of stock in defense contractors.</p>
        <p>Mrs. O'Brien Donovan pursued that line of attack again yesterday, suggesting that Ms. Gillibrand was refusing to release her tax returns because she had something to hide.</p>
        <p>''If Kirsten Gillibrand wants the voters to have the necessary information to determine who they want to support, she will release her tax records immediately and prove once and for all that she does not pay New York City resident income taxes,'' Mrs. O'Brien Donovan said. ''The voters deserve to know if she is paying Social Security taxes for her child care staff and if her personal financial investments will serve as a conflict of interest when she votes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
