<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gift to Beth Israel Is Just Part of a Family Tradition</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="678612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GIFTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BETH ISRAEL MEDICAL CENTER (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TELTSCH, KATHLEEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PHILLIPS, LAWRENCE S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EED8113FF936A35757C0A962958260" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gift to Beth Israel Is Just Part of a Family Tradition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHLEEN TELTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TELTSCH, KATHLEEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It began with a pushcart more than a century ago in the busy warren of streets on the Lower East Side, all crowded with immigrants, many of them Polish and Russian Jews who had come to America fleeing the pogroms. One was a peddler named Moses Phillips, who set out mornings pushing a cart piled high with shirts sewn by his wife, Endel, in their one-room loft.</p>
        <p>At first he sold shirts solely to support his family, but soon he had a bigger cause: to scrape together enough money to open a medical dispensary, because new immigrants did not meet the residency requirements imposed by local hospitals. Neighbors helped, going door-to-door collecting anything offered -- pennies, nickels, pillow cases, candles and even a few chickens. These efforts made it possible to transform a Henry Street tenement into a clinic, which later grew into Beth Israel Medical Center, one of the country's leading hospitals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It began with a pushcart more than a century ago in the busy warren of streets on the Lower East Side, all crowded with immigrants, many of them Polish and Russian Jews who had come to America fleeing the pogroms. One was a peddler named Moses Phillips, who set out mornings pushing a cart piled high with shirts sewn by his wife, Endel, in their one-room loft.</p>
        <p>At first he sold shirts solely to support his family, but soon he had a bigger cause: to scrape together enough money to open a medical dispensary, because new immigrants did not meet the residency requirements imposed by local hospitals. Neighbors helped, going door-to-door collecting anything offered -- pennies, nickels, pillow cases, candles and even a few chickens. These efforts made it possible to transform a Henry Street tenement into a clinic, which later grew into Beth Israel Medical Center, one of the country's leading hospitals.</p>
        <p>Now, 105 years and three generations later, Moses Phillips's great-grandson, Lawrence S. Phillips, is giving $5 million to Beth Israel for a new outpatient care center at Union Square.</p>
        <p>In the years between, there have been other Phillips family gifts.</p>
        <p>When the downtown dispensary outgrew its cramped quarters early in the century, a building committee headed by Moses's son, Isaac, raised money for a 17-story hospital building on 17th Street between First and Second Avenues. And later Isaac's son, Seymour, was a hospital trustee who rescued the nursing school when it was in danger of closing for lack of financing -- it is now the Phillips Beth Israel School of Nursing.</p>
        <p>"This contribution," said Mr. Phillips of his $5 million gift, "is made as a way of giving back to the community, just like my great-grandfather, grandfather and father did."</p>
        <p>He enjoys drawing a parallel between the hospital's expansion and the Phillips family's prosperous growth from a pushcart business to primary stockholder of the Phillips-Van Heusen Corporation, one of the country's leading apparel concerns.</p>
        <p>"Moses in his first year sold $250 in shirts from his pushcart; the company's sales this year will total $1.3 billion," said Mr. Phillips, who retired last year as president and is now chairman of the board.</p>
        <p>The family's story is proudly preserved in a prominent display at the company offices at 1260 Avenue of the Americas. There, in a room with three glass walls, are the photographs of Moses and Endel, taken in 1881 soon after they left their home in Suwalki in Poland and traveled to New York. The display includes the citizenship papers of Isaac, who was 18 when the family immigrated, and also a copy of the statement he made at the cornerstone-laying ceremony for Beth Israel's new quarters on Oct. 22, 1922.</p>
        <p>"Hospitals which are built for the sick are usually so managed that the sick are the only ones not at home there," he said. "It is difficult to cure the body if the spirit is depressed." At Beth Israel, he said, each patient was to be treated as if he were in his own home, "treated as a friend, not a 'case.' "</p>
        <p>The $5 million Phillips gift will go toward the $34 million purchase of space in the Zeckendorf Towers complex on Union Square. It will be used to develop ambulatory services and to expand outpatient care.</p>
        <p>The family's personal involvement remains strong, even though Mr. Phillips now makes his home in Florida. His mother, Madelyn Phillips, recently gave $1 million to help renovate the hospital's Family Practice Unit. A sister, Carol P. Green, is a member of the trustee board's Phillips Beth Israel School of Nursing committee.</p>
        <p>All of the family members assembled this week at the mother's home for the Passover observance. Will there be a fifth generation involved in Beth Israel?</p>
        <p>Brother and sister, who have five children between them, looked at each other, weighing the prospects. "Children become scattered and assimilate," said Mr. Phillips.</p>
        <p>"One day, hopefully," the sister added.</p>
        <p>For now, both are enthusiastic about the involvement of Phillips-Van Heusen in supporting assistance to the poor in third world countries through the American Jewish World Service, founded in 1985 by Mr. Phillips because he wanted a Jewish charity to have a visible presence abroad as did other religious groups. The World Service has rebuilt earthquake-destroyed homes in Colombia, provided housing in El Salvador, and flown food to famine areas in Africa.</p>
        <p>Phillips-Van Heusen, formed in 1919 when the Phillips family company signed a contract with John M. Van Heusen, has contributed to six schools in the highlands of Guatemala, where the company has three plants. Mr. Phillips will be succeeded as chairman in June by Bruce Klatsky, currently the president. Mr. Klatsky recently became a Beth Israel trustee.</p>
        <p>At the company's entrance stands a wooden cart piled with shirts. It is a decorative piece of highly polished oak, nothing like the humble vehicle pushed by the great-grandfather along Hester and Orchard Streets. But clearly, it is a pushcart.</p>
        <p>"We never forget where we came from," said Mr. Phillips.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
