<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Medicare Paying Doctors 59% of Insurers' Rate, Panel Finds</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="678627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCTORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PHYSICIANS PAYMENT REVIEW COMMISSION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7D6113FF936A35757C0A962958260" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Medicare Paying Doctors 59% of Insurers' Rate, Panel Finds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Medicare, the Federal health insurance program for the elderly, pays doctors only 59 percent of what private insurance companies pay, and this gap may "compromise access to care for Medicare beneficiaries," a Federal advisory commission said today.</p>
        <p>The gap has increased in the last five years, and President Clinton's health plan could widen it further, said the panel, the Physician Payment Review Commission. In 1989, Medicare paid doctors 68 percent as much as private insurers paid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Medicare, the Federal health insurance program for the elderly, pays doctors only 59 percent of what private insurance companies pay, and this gap may "compromise access to care for Medicare beneficiaries," a Federal advisory commission said today.</p>
        <p>The gap has increased in the last five years, and President Clinton's health plan could widen it further, said the panel, the Physician Payment Review Commission. In 1989, Medicare paid doctors 68 percent as much as private insurers paid.</p>
        <p>The 13-member commission, created in 1986, advises Congress on payment of doctors under Medicare and Medicaid, which together serve more than 65 million people. Recommendations of the commission are taken seriously by Congress, which has approved many of its past suggestions.</p>
        <p>Judith N. Brown, chairwoman of the American Association of Retired Persons, said: "When retirees move into a new area, they often have difficulty finding a physician who will take them. It's becoming more difficult to find doctors who will take people if they're on Medicare." Long Viewed as Inadequate</p>
        <p>Medicare has always been less generous than private insurers in paying doctors. But Government data show that Medicare was paying 85 percent as much as private insurers in 1970's.</p>
        <p>Howard B. Shapiro, director of public policy at the American College of Physicians, which represents 80,000 internists, said the trend documented by the commission was worrisome. "Medicare payment levels are beginning to approach Medicaid payment levels," which have long been viewed as inadequate, he said.</p>
        <p>Doctors' fees under Medicaid, the Federal-state program for low-income people, vary widely from state to state. On the average, the commission said, Medicaid pays doctors 47 percent of what private insurers pay.</p>
        <p>Medicaid payments to doctors have increased in the last few years, mainly because of a Federal law that forced states to raise payments for pediatric and obstetric services. A Widening Gap</p>
        <p>"Physicians continue to serve new Medicare patients," the commission said. But it added, "The gap between Medicare payments and those of private insurers is widening," and these disparities may reduce access to care for some patients, as doctors take patients with private insurance in preference to Medicare beneficiaries. Black, Hispanic and disabled people already report difficulties getting care under Medicare, the panel said.</p>
        <p>The gap between Medicare and private insurance is partly a result of the Government's success in slowing the growth of Medicare spending for doctors' services. Such spending rose 4.8 percent a year from 1989 to 1993, as against 12.1 percent a year from 1980 to 1989. In recent years, private insurers have allowed much larger increases in doctors' fees than Medicare permitted.</p>
        <p>The commission said that stringent limits on Medicare payments proposed by President Clinton would widen the gap, so that by the year 2000, Medicare would pay doctors only 43 percent to 52 percent of what private insurers pay. Ups and Downs of Fees</p>
        <p>In its report to Congress, the commission also made these points:</p>
        <p>*A Medicare fee schedule that took effect in 1992 has redistributed doctors' income. Payments per service increased 17 percent for family doctors and general practitioners, but only 2 percent for internists. For surgeons, payment rates dropped 8 percent.</p>
        <p>*Medicare pays doctors 54 percent of what commercial insurance companies pay and 69 percent of the fees paid by Blue Cross and Blue Shield plans.</p>
        <p>*The volume of doctors' services for each Medicare beneficiary increased, on the average, about 50 percent from 1986 to 1993. Variations in Payments</p>
        <p>Dr. John M. Eisenberg, chairman of the commission, said that some of the increase occurred because of new technology and was "definitely appropriate." For example, he said, doctors are performing more endoscopy procedures, to screen patients for colon cancer, and more angioplasty procedures, using small balloons to open up coronary arteries.</p>
        <p>The study found huge variations in Medicaid payments to doctors in various states. In New York, New Jersey and Rhode Island, it said, Medicaid fee levels are about half the national average. In Alaska, Arizona and Wyoming, Medicaid fees are at least 25 percent above the national average. In Connecticut, Medicaid payments to doctors are about the same as the national average.</p>
        <p>Comparison of Medicaid fees in 1990 and 1993 shows a mixed picture. Payments to doctors in West Virginia, which had been among the lowest in the country, nearly tripled and now match the national average. Fees in seven other states -- Alaska, Connecticut, Kentucky, Mississippi, Montana, New Hampshire and Washington -- increased by 30 percent or more in this period. But fees in California, Indiana, Massachusetts and South Carolina declined slightly from 1990 to 1993. Concern Over Proposals</p>
        <p>The commission welcomed efforts by Mr. Clinton and members of Congress to guarantee health insurance for all Americans. But it expressed concern about the complexity of proposals for regional health insurance purchasing groups, or alliances.</p>
        <p>Instead, the commission urged Congress to create a national alliance, which would offer consumers a variety of health plans. The plans would include one that is run by the Government, like Medicare, and pays doctors a separate fee for each service performed.</p>
        <p>This public plan would guarantee that low-income people have access to a full range of doctors, and it could compete with private plans, the commission said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
