<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dutch Rescuer to Give Talk</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="751216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAZI ERA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HOLLAND</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER PSYCHOANALYTIC SOCIETY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STROBOS, TINA (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHENSON, ROBERTA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DC133FF935A15750C0A963958260" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dutch Rescuer to Give Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA HERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHENSON, ROBERTA</byline>
      <dateline>LARCHMONT</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE 50-year-old photographs show smiling friends and a group clustered around a table. Dr. Tina Strobos, a psychiatrist here, points at different faces. This one died in a concentration camp, she says. That one was never heard from again. This one moved to Israel, where she still visits the woman's grandchildren.</p>
        <p>The pictures represent Dr. Strobos's youth in the Netherlands, a youth she said she feels homesick for, a youth cut short by the five-year occupation by the Nazis beginning in 1940. Dr. Strobos was then a 20-year-old medical student, and pictures of her show a strikingly beautiful, dark-haired young woman. Along with her mother and grandmother, Dr. Strobos, whose family consisted of Social Democrats and atheists, sheltered more than 100 Jews in their house in Amsterdam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE 50-year-old photographs show smiling friends and a group clustered around a table. Dr. Tina Strobos, a psychiatrist here, points at different faces. This one died in a concentration camp, she says. That one was never heard from again. This one moved to Israel, where she still visits the woman's grandchildren.</p>
        <p>The pictures represent Dr. Strobos's youth in the Netherlands, a youth she said she feels homesick for, a youth cut short by the five-year occupation by the Nazis beginning in 1940. Dr. Strobos was then a 20-year-old medical student, and pictures of her show a strikingly beautiful, dark-haired young woman. Along with her mother and grandmother, Dr. Strobos, whose family consisted of Social Democrats and atheists, sheltered more than 100 Jews in their house in Amsterdam.</p>
        <p>Dr. Strobos says she cannot be called a Christian rescuer, because she, too, is an atheist. But she is included in every book about non-Jewish rescuers during the Holocaust, and her name, along with her mother's name, is inscribed in the Garden of the Righteous at Yad Vashem, the Holocaust memorial in Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Still a striking woman who was dressed in a bright red shirt, a man's striped tie and pearls for a recent interview, Dr. Strobos practices family therapy in a home office overlooking an inlet. She is still immersed in the details of events that happened long ago, although she says she refuses to live in the past. Although it was decades before Dr. Strobos could bear to tell her story, she now speaks often about the Holocaust. Dr. M. Donald Coleman, a psychiatrist and psychoanalyst who practices in Mamaroneck, said he was astonished to learn of his colleague's background. He asked Dr. Strobos to address the Westchester Psychoanalytic Society, where she will speak on April 3 at 8:15 P.M. about "Courage and Decency During the Nazi Occupation of Holland in World War II."</p>
        <p>The meeting, which is free and open to the public, will be held in the second-floor auditorium of the main administration building of New York Hospital-Westchester Division in White Plains. Reservations, which are required, can be made by calling 939-2085.</p>
        <p>"Psychoanalysis has provided us with invaluable knowledge about the darker side of man's nature," Dr. Coleman said. But "our field knows so little about qualities like courage and decency. Perhaps we can only listen to people like Tina and hope to learn, certainly to be inspired."</p>
        <p>Dr. Strobos said she doesn't cry anymore or have nightmares about her nine arrests by the Gestapo or the eight heart-stopping times her house was searched. "You repress those awful, terrifying memories," she said. "I avoided reading Anne Frank until 20 years after the war. I still do it in spurts."</p>
        <p>Dr. Strobos's activities in the Dutch Resistance intensified in 1942, when the university at which she was studying was closed because students refused to sign a Nazi loyalty oath. Although she was opposed to violence, she hid and transported stolen weapons and also obtained forbidden radio transmitters to communicate with Britain. She risked her life many times, not only by hiding Jews but by distributing underground newspapers and helping ailing or pregnant Jews get hospital care.</p>
        <p>Dr. Eva Fogelman, a Manhattan social psychologist and psychotherapist who included Dr. Strobos in her 1994 book "Conscience and Courage: Rescuers of Jews during the Holocaust," published by Anchor Books, spoke of Dr. Strobos's "real ingenuity" in stealing people's identification cards at social gatherings so the underground could turn them into life-saving documents for Jews. The young woman also obtained the release from prison of a friend, Dr. Abraham Pais, by pleading in person with a high Nazi official.</p>
        <p>Dr. Pais, now an American citizen and a theoretical physicist, and author, mentioned Dr. Strobos's "moral nobility" in a chapter of his autobiography that appeared in The Hudson Review.</p>
        <p>Only once, Dr. Strobos said, did she and her mother, whom she saw manhandled by the police during a protest against anti-Semitism in 1933, speak about the mortal danger they were courting. "My mother said, 'You know, we could both get killed this way,' " she said. But for Dr. Strobos, the worst fear was that she would not rescue enough Jews. Like Schindler, she said she felt guilty that she had not done more.</p>
        <p>Dr. Coleman called such feelings astonishing in light of the rescuers' courage. "One way of seeing it is that if the conscience gets exercised, it gets stronger," he said. "Like a muscle, the more you exercise it, the stronger it becomes. Many people started out with one small act of decency that grew and grew. It suggests something that might be used in education: small acts of conscience might lead to larger ones."</p>
        <p>He said the Psychoanalytic Society will try to shed some light on those who transcend their fears to do what Dr. Strobos calls "the right thing, your duty." Dr. Arthur Lew, president of the society, will lead a discussion after her talk.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
