<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oven Does the Trick for Impromptu Dining</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="751271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DB153EF935A15750C0A963958260" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oven Does the Trick for Impromptu Dining</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOIRA HODGSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OFTEN on weekends I find myself putting together an impromptu lunch or dinner for which the food is bought at the last minute. As a result, I have to keep it simple. One solution is to cook as much as possible in the oven.</p>
        <p>The other day I came across an interesting recipe by the celebrated French chef Joel Robuchon: just the sort of thing I had in mind -- a pork loin roasted with fresh sage leaves over several different kinds of vegetables. It sounded delicious, but the recipe had an enormous amount of fat in it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OFTEN on weekends I find myself putting together an impromptu lunch or dinner for which the food is bought at the last minute. As a result, I have to keep it simple. One solution is to cook as much as possible in the oven.</p>
        <p>The other day I came across an interesting recipe by the celebrated French chef Joel Robuchon: just the sort of thing I had in mind -- a pork loin roasted with fresh sage leaves over several different kinds of vegetables. It sounded delicious, but the recipe had an enormous amount of fat in it.</p>
        <p>First, it involved frying the vegetables -- onion, plum tomatoes and carrots -- in butter. Then they were to finish cooking in olive oil under the loin of pork, which was covered in a layer of fat.</p>
        <p>I decided to use the same vegetables but roast them separately -- skipping the butter altogether -- in just a little oil. The vegetables came out almost caramelized, their flavors emphasized by the roasting process. The pork was cooked on its own in a Dutch oven in a couple of inches of chicken stock to keep it moist, and the fat was poured off before the cooking juices were reduced for the sauce.</p>
        <p>In another pan I roasted potatoes the Italian way, the skins partly peeled, with whole cloves of garlic and herbs. Everything was put in the oven, and all I had to worry about was string beans, which were steamed, and salad.</p>
        <p>For dessert we had strawberries and ice cream, with chocolate cookies on the side. Roast Loin of Pork With Sage Total time: 2 hours  2cloves garlic, peeled and minced  13-pound boneless pork loin, rolled and tied in one piece  6sprigs fresh sage  Juice of 1/2 lemon  Coarse salt and freshly ground pepper to taste  2tablespoons of olive oil  1medium onion, sliced  3sprigs thyme  2 1/2cups strong chicken stock  1/2cup white wine.  Sprigs of sage to garnish</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Chop the garlic and half the sage and insert it in the center of the pork. Squeeze a half lemon over the pork and season the meat with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>2. Heat the olive oil in a heavy casserole or Dutch oven just large enough to hold the loin. Brown the loin on all sides and drain off the fat.</p>
        <p>3. Arrange the onion over the bottom of the pan and sprinkle with remaining sage leaves and thyme sprigs. Put the loin on top and add the chicken stock and wine. Cover and cook for an hour. Uncover, turn the oven up to 375 degrees, and let the meat brown for 20 to 30 minutes. Test to see if the meat is done. (It is cooked when an internal temperature of 155 degrees on a meat thermometer is registered.)</p>
        <p>4. Remove the pork loin to a serving dish and keep it warm. (You can put it back in the oven, leaving the door ajar.) Skim the fat from the cooking juices and reduce them until thick. Season to taste with salt and pepper. Serve in a warmed sauce boat. Decorate the pork with sprigs of sage and thyme and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: Dried sage does not work for this recipe. If you cannot find fresh sage, fresh rosemary can be used. Dried rosemary may also be used, but sparingly since it is twice as strong.</p>
        <p>Roast Carrots, Tomatoes And Onions With Thyme Total time: 2 hours  1 1/2pounds carrots  12plum tomatoes 2large onions  2tablespoons olive oil  2teaspoons fresh thyme leaves  (or one teaspoon dried)  Coarse salt and freshly ground pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Slice the carrots into one-inch pieces. Peel the tomatoes by dropping them into boiling water, leaving them for a minute and then draining them and slipping off their skins. Cut them in half and scrape out the seeds. Cut the onions in thick slices.</p>
        <p>2. Pour the oil over the bottom of a baking dish about 9 by 13 inches and spread out the onions, tomatoes and thyme. Season with salt and pepper and stir the vegetables lightly to make sure they are coated with the oil. Bake for 30 minutes, stirring from time to time.</p>
        <p>3. Add carrots, stir to coat with oil and continue roasting for one hour.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: If you are cooking these vegetables at the same time as the pork, the oven temperature should be turned up for the last 20 to 30 minutes. Check the vegetables to make sure they will not be overcooked; if they are cooking too fast, remove them from the oven and keep them warm on the back of the stove, returning them to the oven for the last 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>Roast Potatoes With Garlic And Rosemary Total time: 2 hours  2pounds red-skinned or Yukon gold potatoes  3tablespoons olive oil  1tablespoon rosemary  12cloves garlic, with their skins intact  Coarse salt and freshly ground pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat the oven to 350 degrees. Peel away any damaged bits from the potatoes, leaving a generous amount of skin. Cut the potatoes in half, or quarters if they are large.</p>
        <p>2. Pour the oil over the bottom of a baking dish large enough to hold the potatoes without crowding them in one layer. (You may need two dishes; a cast-iron pan will also do.) Add the potatoes, rosemary and garlic, season them with salt and pepper and stir them so they are coated with the oil. Bake for one to one-and-a-half hours, turning the potatoes from time to time.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: If you are cooking the potatoes at the same time as the pork, the temperature should be turned up for the last 20 to 30 minutes. Check to make sure they will not be overcooked.  FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
