<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is That Deion Sanders Poking Around Giants?</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="707834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, MIKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANDERS, DEION</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DE1539F931A1575BC0A962958260" item-length="884" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is That Deion Sanders Poking Around Giants?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREEMAN, MIKE</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Aug. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Time in New York?</p>
        <p>It may seem farfetched that the free agent cornerback Deion (Prime Time) Sanders would become a member of the Giants and their thin secondary. But Sanders would apparently like the Giants to think long and hard about that prospect. Sanders has told some National Football League players and team officials that he would like to at least talk with the Giants about joining the team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Time in New York?</p>
        <p>It may seem farfetched that the free agent cornerback Deion (Prime Time) Sanders would become a member of the Giants and their thin secondary. But Sanders would apparently like the Giants to think long and hard about that prospect. Sanders has told some National Football League players and team officials that he would like to at least talk with the Giants about joining the team.</p>
        <p>According to players and team officials from the San Francisco 49ers and Miami Dolphins -- clubs Sanders has already visited on his free agent tour -- Sanders wants to add the Giants to his list of potential employers.</p>
        <p>The problem, the Sanders camp feels, is a perceived lack of interest on the Giants' part. But is there a lack of interest in the two-sport star? It depends on whom you talk to in the Giant organization.</p>
        <p>"I think we should be interested in him," said Robert Tisch, chairman and co-chief executive officer of the Giants. "I think he is someone we should think about. But he hasn't been discussed. We haven't talked about Deion Sanders yet. That doesn't mean we won't, it just means he hasn't come up yet."</p>
        <p>Giant thoughts of Prime Time don't end there. Perhaps the heart and soul of the team, running back Rodney Hampton, said that if several other high-paid Giants joined him he would be willing to renegotiate his three-year, $6.8 million contract so the team could fit Sanders's $3 million-a- year salary under the cap.</p>
        <p>The Giants are now about $2 million under the cap; teams like to have about $1 million of maneuvering room to sign players in case of injury.</p>
        <p>"I would love to have him here," Hampton said. "He would be a great addition to this team. We need some spice around here. I think he could help us in three different areas, defense first, then some on offense and on special teams. You can't beat that. If he came here, we'd compete for the conference title.</p>
        <p>"If a couple of guys offered to restructure things, I would do it. I would be in the front of the line. I don't know if I could afford to do it by myself, but if two or three guys did it with me I'd do it. I think it would be worth it." Ouch!</p>
        <p>The Giants are concerned about their secondary. In their 13-10 loss to the Jets on Saturday night, the rookie cornerback Tito Wooten was burned so badly on the 80-yard touchdown pass from Jack Trudeau to Stevie Anderson that it looked as if Wooten still had jet lag from the team's Berlin trip.</p>
        <p>The secondary is full of rookies and first-year players, and with the third-year veteran, Phillippi Sparks, out for at least another week with a knee injury that makes things worse.</p>
        <p>Giants General Manager George Young declined to comment about Sanders, while Coach Dan Reeves has been asked about Sanders before and laughed it off. A Bidding Ploy</p>
        <p>Some in the organization feel that Sanders's tour is nothing but an attempt to get teams to outbid each other. Others on the team clearly feel differently, thinking Sanders would be a great addition -- as long as the salary he would earn didn't bankrupt the team.</p>
        <p>Hampton's suggestion is shared by other highly visible players in the league. Already, quarterback Steve Young of the 49ers (who earns $5.3 million a season), Dan Marino of the Dolphins ($4.2 million) and Joe Montana of the Kansas City Chiefs ($3.4 million) have offered to restructure their deals to get Sanders.</p>
        <p>Sanders is scheduled to visit Kansas City, Atlanta and New Orleans this week. His story is one of many for the Giants, coming off their loss to the Jets, the story being that players and now even Tisch would love to have the Pro Bowl player.</p>
        <p>Sanders is intriguing, but the Giants do have more immediate concerns: Quarterback Kent Graham.</p>
        <p>It appears that Graham will not be available in the team's final preseason game against the Chicago Bears because of a deep back bruise, courtesy of Jets linebacker Marvin Jones on a hit Graham called a cheap shot. Reeves called it definitely questionable. In Need of a Safety Net</p>
        <p>Graham is the backup to Dave Brown, so it's not a major blow to the team, but it does mean that Brown will be exposed more. And, at least for this week, there is no safety net should Brown get hurt. Stan White moves into the No. 2 slot and Brian Fox to No. 3.</p>
        <p>Reeves was also upset by the number of mental and technique errors the Giants made.</p>
        <p>The Giants had six penalties for 30 yards, and bad tackling as well as bad reads led to the Jets rushing for 155 yards and gaining 5.7 yards a rush. Offensive line missing blocks. Defensive linemen not getting off blocks. Linebackers over-pursuing. All these things contributed to Reeves having a bad Sunday morning.</p>
        <p>"Way too many mistakes," he said. "For us to be the best we can be, we've got to do things better technique-wise and assignment-wise. Probably the worse we've done technique-wise and assignment-wise all preseason." Alert Is Sounded</p>
        <p>You get the feeling that Reeves is sounding an all-points bulletin, letting the team know that this week will be a tough one, possibly the toughest one of camp.</p>
        <p>Reeves was asked whether the errors could be corrected in two weeks, in time for the Sept. 4 opener against Philadelphia. He said the problems "better be corrected in one."</p>
        <p>"We don't have time to wait," he said.  PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
