<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Sounds of Spanish Grate</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="707803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="FLIGHT FROM CUBA: FLORIDA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CUBA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORDHEIMER, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE6D61439F931A1575BC0A962958260" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Sounds of Spanish Grate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON NORDHEIMER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORDHEIMER, JON</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Aug. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the edge of the Everglades, where new housing tracts thin out into palmetto scrubland and a marshy saw-grass horizon, two cultural forces gathered today at a corner highway truck stop called Dade Corners.</p>
        <p>On one side were a few hundred Cuban-Americans waiting in the summer heat under a threatening sky to board shuttle buses for a one-mile trip to the Krome Detention Center, where family members or old friends who had just crossed the Florida Straits in boats were being held by immigration authorities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the edge of the Everglades, where new housing tracts thin out into palmetto scrubland and a marshy saw-grass horizon, two cultural forces gathered today at a corner highway truck stop called Dade Corners.</p>
        <p>On one side were a few hundred Cuban-Americans waiting in the summer heat under a threatening sky to board shuttle buses for a one-mile trip to the Krome Detention Center, where family members or old friends who had just crossed the Florida Straits in boats were being held by immigration authorities.</p>
        <p>On the other side were the regulars inside the Frog Pond, a restaurant that serves alligator steaks and fried rabbit and caters to non-Hispanic whites who live in houses or trailer parks 15 miles from downtown Miami.</p>
        <p>The view from the Frog Pond was not a happy one for Tom Ross and the other regulars as they watched the parking lot and adjoining fields fill up, to the sound of spoken Spanish.</p>
        <p>"Cubans I work with are some of the warmest people I know," said Mr. Ross, a rangy 51-year-old who is head of an excavating business. "But every time I start talking about Cubans it comes out sounding like hate.</p>
        <p>"They come here and walk right into a giveaway system that hands them more medical and housing benefits than the average workingman enjoys."</p>
        <p>Along the polyurethane counter top, which is inlaid with $246 worth of coins, there were grunts of agreement.</p>
        <p>It is a workingman's place, the walls studded with signs like "Kitchen Closed Due to Illness (Sick of Cookin)," the down-homey pride pervasive. But the views heard here can be heard in suburban living rooms and beach-front cafes, wherever non-Hispanic people gather who feel dispossessed by yet another wave of Cuban migration to Miami.</p>
        <p>On the line to the shuttle bus, the conversation, in Spanish, was of changing immigration policy and the immediacy of the moment. If the non-Cubans resent Cubans, a few of the speakers offered, it is resentment of hard work and of the family ties that fuel a will to succeed in a new country.</p>
        <p>Non-Hispanic whites are now a minority population in metropolitan Miami, putting a harder edge to the language used at places like the Frog Pond.</p>
        <p>"Things have gotten so out of hand that if you express your true feelings, it's now a hate crime," said Larry Funk, 34, finishing off eggs and home fries with his wife, Pam, 38.</p>
        <p>Added Mrs. Funk, "The politicians are so busy giving away our tax money to Cubans, Haitians and anyone else who feels like coming here, there won't be anything left for us and our children."</p>
        <p>Looking out the glass entrance to the Frog Pond, the regulars saw more cars filled with Cuban-Americans pull up and fill Frog Pond parking spaces. Sally Jackson-Smith, a waitress with a commanding glare, went to the door to shoo them away. Escaping 'a Long Sleep'</p>
        <p>At the edge of the parking lot, where the line for the shuttle buses snaked 40 yards in the dust, Pedro Cuadra waited patiently. He had come to the United States in the 1980 Mariel boatlift, and now he hoped to find his cousin and other relatives among the refugees at the detention center.</p>
        <p>He said that although he was glad he made the decision to flee Cuba, his 14 years in the United States had not been easy.</p>
        <p>Shortly after arriving in this country, Mr. Cuadra went to live with the only Cuban he knew, an older friend of his parents who lived 50 miles from Duluth, Minn. Mr. Cuadra winced, as if words could not express the cold of a Minnesota winter. After two years, he went with another Mariel refugee to fish for king salmon in Alaska. "It was good money but ----" Again, the eyes were slits.</p>
        <p>In 1983 Mr. Cuadra went to Tampa and landed a cook's job in a Spanish kitchen. He and his wife, with one baby at home and three bedrooms, figure they can take in seven relatives and find them kitchen work. "Leaving Cuba was like waking up from a long sleep," he said quietly. Life in the United States, while not a dream, was like walking among the living, he said as the line crawled forward.</p>
        <p>Down the line stood 18-year-old Nancy Santalo and her mother, Maria. They were going to the detention center to meet Orlando Lopez, 28, her former brother-in-law.</p>
        <p>Nancy and her parents also came to Florida in the 1980 boatlift, an event that led to concern that Fidel Castro was sending thousands of undesirables here.</p>
        <p>"My parents both went to work in shoe factories two weeks after arriving in Miami," said the young woman, now a student at the Institute of Fine Arts in Miami, studying fashion. Both parents now work for a building maintenance company, she said. Along the Counter</p>
        <p>Back inside the Frog Pond, Tom Ross checked the sky and figured it had better rain before the simmering heat from the asphalt of Krome Road spawned fights among those in the parking lot.</p>
        <p>A man who would identify himself only by first name, Stuart, drifted by the counter. He had a gray beard and wore a denim jacket and jeans. He said he had lived in Miami since 1949.</p>
        <p>"There's absolutely no difference between these new Cuban refugees and the Haitians trying to get here by boat," he intoned in a soft voice free of malice. "They're all coming here for jobs. The only real difference is 99 percent of the Haitians are black so no one cuts them a break."</p>
        <p>Heads along the counter bobbed in agreement. But David Casey, who had a little bit of a wild look, started going on about how Miami was a great place before Cubans and Haitians brought disease and drugs and disorder with them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross had heard it all before, but he kept quiet. "Trouble is," he said later, "we are not a melting pot in Miami, and there are a lot of cultural differences between us. People can't look at the cultural differences and separate out the hate that builds up."</p>
        <p>At the truck stop's gas pumps, two big tour buses braked with a hiss. Out of the buses filed Italian, German and French tourists on their way to Key West. They mingled with the Spanish-speaking Cubans, and the lot was filled with a cacophony of foreign voices, like a nightmare vision for the regulars inside the Frog Pond.</p>
        <p>Soon, rain danced down the highway, drenching those lined up for the shuttle bus as thunder boomed. Tom Ross decided to have that beer as the rest of the regulars scattered for home.  FLIGHT FROM CUBA: FLORIDA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
