<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Working Up a Broad Street Mood</title>
    <meta content="01RANG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HOCKEY" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="905694"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Flyers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6DA123DF932A35751C0A961958260" item-length="527" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Working Up a Broad Street Mood</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>RYE, N.Y., Jan. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Preview of New York Rangers' game against Philadelphia Flyers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ulf Samuelsson seemed a little antsy this afternoon. It was Day 4 without a game, and with the Philadelphia Flyers more than 24 hours away, he had only his teammates to take on.</p>
        <p>He exchanged shoves with Brian Noonan and jousted with Sylvain Blouin. When Blouin slashed him, Samuelsson yelped. Then Samuelsson intercepted a pass by Niklas Sundstrom, a deed that left Sundstrom slamming his stick on the glass in anger. And when Samuelsson beat Mike Richter with a shot, he celebrated with an elaborate raising of his arms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ulf Samuelsson seemed a little antsy this afternoon. It was Day 4 without a game, and with the Philadelphia Flyers more than 24 hours away, he had only his teammates to take on.</p>
        <p>He exchanged shoves with Brian Noonan and jousted with Sylvain Blouin. When Blouin slashed him, Samuelsson yelped. Then Samuelsson intercepted a pass by Niklas Sundstrom, a deed that left Sundstrom slamming his stick on the glass in anger. And when Samuelsson beat Mike Richter with a shot, he celebrated with an elaborate raising of his arms.</p>
        <p>If today's practice is a reliable indicator, Samuelsson might be in the mood for a combative effort against the Flyers, who have beaten the Rangers by 2-1 and tied them, 1-1, in two meetings so far this season.</p>
        <p>''It will be perfect for us to face one of the better teams in the league,'' Samuelsson said. ''I had a good time in practice. Glad to be back.''</p>
        <p>Chances are good that Samuelsson and his defense partner Aleksandr Karpovtsev will play against Eric Lindros and his Legion of Doom line that includes John LeClair on left wing and either Dainius Zubrus or Mikael Renberg on the right.</p>
        <p>''It's almost an honor to play against a line like that if you get the assignment,'' Samuelsson said.</p>
        <p>In 27 games this season, since returning from a serious groin injury, Lindros has 14 goals and 21 assists. LeClair leads the Flyers in goals with 29 and in points with 53. Zubrus, a rookie, has replaced the struggling Renberg, at least temporarily, on that first line.</p>
        <p>''The Flyers skate better than they did last year,'' Mark Messier said. ''It should be a good game.'' Among Philadelphia's recent additions: Paul Coffey, the swift, attacking defenseman, who has 20 points in 31 games.</p>
        <p>Since the Flyers swept the Rangers in the second round of the 1995 playoffs, the Rangers have considered Philadelphia a key rival. Last season, in five games, the Flyers won three, the Rangers won once and one game was tied.</p>
        <p>Against Atlantic Division teams, the Rangers are 5-12-4, worst among their divisional rivals. The Flyers are 8-8-2 in the division and are ''a real in-your-face team,'' according to Ranger Coach Colin Campbell.</p>
        <p>''They are a hard team to match up against,'' he said. Along with Lindros, the Flyers' centers include Joel Otto and Rod Brind'Amour. The Rangers counter with Messier, Wayne Gretzky, Sergei Nemchinov and, possibly, Adam Graves, if Graves moves from left wing to a checking-line role as center.</p>
        <p>''Grit has been a question,'' Campbell said of his team. ''We've been searching for that center iceman who is a gritty, in-your-face tough guy. It will be a good challenge to see how we match up.''</p>
        <p>In two games against Philadelphia, Gretzky has no goals and one assist. He is scoreless in the last 12 games. He said he hopes this week's idle days will help.</p>
        <p>''The break for me, mentally, came at the right time,'' he said. ''It was a good time, not physically, but mentally, to get a refresher and walk away from the game for a few days and come back recharged.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
