<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Needs Gretzky? Robitaille Keeps the Streak Alive</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="830437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MONTREAL CANADIENS NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAMOS, JASON WAYNE GRETZKY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Montreal Canadiens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2D71239F935A25751C0A960958260" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Needs Gretzky? Robitaille Keeps the Streak Alive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAMOS, JASON WAYNE GRETZKY;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No Gretzky. But thanks to Luc Robitaille, there is still a streak.</p>
        <p>With a heavy accent on irony.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No Gretzky. But thanks to Luc Robitaille, there is still a streak.</p>
        <p>With a heavy accent on irony.</p>
        <p>Robitaille -- more than anybody else -- was the reason the Rangers will have a chance to break their 25-season-old franchise-record 24-game home unbeaten streak next Thursday night against the Islanders.</p>
        <p>The left wing came through with a pair of goals, one from a seemingly impossible angle, in the final 5 minutes 37 seconds to rally the Rangers to a 2-2 tie against the Montreal Canadiens last night. The goals made the Rangers 18-0-6 in their last 24 games at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>It was a game the Rangers had all but lost, but Robitaille turned the sellout crowd's second-period boos into a chorus of "Luuuuuc!"</p>
        <p>The irony? Robitaille and Ray Ferraro have been the subject of intensive rumors concerning a trade for Wayne Gretzky of the Los Angeles Kings.</p>
        <p>"He seemed to be mad," said Neil Smith, the Rangers' president. "I'll make one up about him every week."</p>
        <p>Smith smiled. He could afford to.</p>
        <p>Smith had held a news conference before last night's game to say that no deal is in the works. Robitaille, however, did not find out about Smith's comments until after his heroics.</p>
        <p>And he was a little skeptical when he heard about them.</p>
        <p>"Usually when they say nothing's happening, that's when something happens," said Robitaille. "But I think Neil has always been real honest with me, with everybody. If he says it, he usually means it."</p>
        <p>And the streak?</p>
        <p>"It's a good thing," said Robitaille. "The more you keep winning, the harder  it is to make trades. And that's all I want to do. Make it real hard for them."</p>
        <p>Perhaps distracted by all the rumors, the Rangers made things real hard on themselves last night. They woke up after killing a 5-on-3 Canadiens advantage for 1:09 that began with 8:05 left in the game.</p>
        <p>Then Robitaille began the comeback. Standing near the sideboards and looking  almost straight on at the left post, Robitaille flicked an Aleksei Kovalev rebound in the general direction of the net. The puck caromed off Pat Jablonski, who was late in getting his right skate to the post, and into the net at 14:23.  And the Rangers had life.</p>
        <p>But it was almost a short one. After a Vladimir Malakhov penalty gave the Rangers their fifth power-play of the evening, Glenn Healy, with help from Bruce Driver, had to make an excellent save on Vincent Damphousse after the goalie had failed to clear the puck past Damphousse at what seemed like miles away from the Ranger net.</p>
        <p>That play kept it a one-goal game.</p>
        <p>Then, with the Rangers still on the power play, Robitaille scored his 19th of the season on a rebound of a Driver blast at 17:24 after Driver had held in the  puck at the left point. Healy (35 saves) did the rest. And the streak, 2 minutes 26 seconds shy of extinction, lives on.</p>
        <p>As does Robitaille -- in a Ranger uniform.</p>
        <p>"I think that was apropos," Coach Colin Campbell said.</p>
        <p>Between periods, Robitaille had said that the Garden ice was sloppy. The Rangers were nearly as sloppy over the first two periods and trailed by two goals entering the final 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>By that time, Ferraro wasn't around. He left after one period after aggravating a groin strain. The rest of the Rangers were physically present, but many didn't seem to be there mentally.</p>
        <p>Healy, making his 16th consecutive start in goal, was given little help early on.</p>
        <p>Damphousse made up for an earlier breakaway miss with a short-handed breakaway goal 9:15 into the game. One minute 34 seconds later, Martin Rucinsky  made it 2-0 with his 13th goal in Montreal's last 14 games, a power-play one-timer.</p>
        <p>And though they headed into the dressing room down only a pair of goals, boos could be heard from the Garden crowd, perhaps a bit spoiled by a streak.</p>
        <p>By the end of regulation, those boos had turned into a standing ovation -- much of it directed at Robitaille.</p>
        <p>"I'll be relieved after March 20," Robitaille said of the trading deadline. "Or whenever he gets traded."</p>
        <p>Nobody had to ask Robitaille whom he was referring to.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>MIKE RICHTER dressed for the first time since suffering a groin strain in Edmonton on Dec. 30. Richter said before the game that he would probably make his return on Saturday night in Ottawa. COLIN CAMPBELL said it would either be in Ottawa or in Pittsburgh on Sunday night. . . . DOUG LIDSTER played for the first time in 13 games after suffering multiple facial fractures on Jan. 5 at Washington.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
