<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Staten I., New Use For Gracious Landmark</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="60" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Lifestyle Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="401679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY OUTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DC1438F93BA25752C1A966958260" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Staten I., New Use For Gracious Landmark</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For almost 150 years, the winds from the Kill van Kull must have evoked memories of the violent seas for thousands of homeless sailors who took shelter at Sailors Snug Harbor, a self-contained community for retired seamen on Staten Island.</p>
        <p>The community moved to North Carolina in 1976, but the winds are still blowing through Snug Harbor's iron gates, carrying with them a strong sense of history. The 80-acrecompound is now a thriving cultural center, but it is easy to imagine what the place might have been like a century ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For almost 150 years, the winds from the Kill van Kull must have evoked memories of the violent seas for thousands of homeless sailors who took shelter at Sailors Snug Harbor, a self-contained community for retired seamen on Staten Island.</p>
        <p>The community moved to North Carolina in 1976, but the winds are still blowing through Snug Harbor's iron gates, carrying with them a strong sense of history. The 80-acrecompound is now a thriving cultural center, but it is easy to imagine what the place might have been like a century ago.</p>
        <p>The maritime hospital and retirement community just a block from the water's edge opened in 1831. It was endowed by a wealthy mariner named Robert Richard Randall, who came from a family of privateers and died in 1801. Legend has it that Alexander Hamilton drafted Captain Randall's will, which endured 30 years of legal challenges before Snug Harbor was finally able to open.</p>
        <p>In the next 50 years, as the community thrived, graceful Victorian cottages were built for staff members, imposing Greek Revival halls for the seamen's medical and social needs, and dormitories for the seamen.</p>
        <p>By the beginning of this century, a thousand men lived at Snug Harbor with all their needs taken care of. They had a chapel, a music hall where visiting vaudevillians performed, shops and their own government complete with a governor appointed by the trustees who lived in a mansion on the property.</p>
        <p>New York City bought the property after the seamen moved away and set about converting it into a cultural center in what Helen Kodadek, assistant to the director for marketing, described as "an ongoing process."</p>
        <p>Today 28 historic buildings are still on the site, and the 13 that have been restored house an array of attractions. Perhaps the most popular is the Staten Island Children's Museum, which, in addition to an extensive toy collection, has several educational exhibits including, currently, one on insects.</p>
        <p>Parents who fret that younger children won't be interested in the same exhibits as their older brothers and sisters don't have to worry; the museum has a supervised play area for preschoolers.</p>
        <p>The children's museum is open Wednesday through Friday from 1 to 5 P.M. and on weekends from 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission is $2. Tours and special events can be arranged by calling (718) 273-2060.</p>
        <p>A few buildings away, in one of the Greek Revival halls, is the Newhouse Center for Contemporary Art. Although its exhibitions are varied, the museum takes pains to show the works of local artists or art that reflects the history of Staten Island or Snug Harbor.</p>
        <p>The Newhouse Center is open Wednesday through Sunday from noon to 5 P.M. Admission is $2. For more information call (718) 448-2500.  Current exhibitions include the paintings of two islanders, Alfredo Arcia and Robyn Ellenbogen. Also on display is a collection of photographs by Alan Michelson, the artist in residence, who lives in one of the cottages and uses Snug Harbor studio space.</p>
        <p>Fred Loessel, assistant director of the gallery, said the center rents studio space to artists and musicians, and hopes to expand the artist-in-residence program.</p>
        <p>"It's kind of a weird, unique place that artists like," he said. "It's close to Manhattan, yet removed."</p>
        <p>Indeed, the skyscrapers of Manhattan, as well as the oil refineries of New Jersey, are visible from most parts of the grounds. But a different kind of view is available at the Staten Island Botanical Garden, which is also on the Snug Harbor grounds. A holiday plant and tree sale will begin Dec. 6 at the Botanical Garden Gift Shop. The grounds are open daily from 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. There is no admission fee. For information, call (718) 273-8200. GETTING THERE</p>
        <p>Snug Harbor is at 1000 Richmond Terrace, two miles from the Staten Island Ferry terminal in St. George. Snug Harbor offers an old-style trolley powered by natural gas that runs from the ferry to the grounds. On Wednesday and Thursday the trolley leaves the terminal every half hour from 1 to 5 P.M.; Friday through Sunday, every half hour from 1 to 8 P.M. The one-way fare is $1; children ride free.</p>
        <p>A city bus, the S40, leaves the ferry terminal two or three times an hour and passes Snug Harbor along Richmond Terrace. HOLIDAY CALENDAR</p>
        <p>Nov. 23: "The Kid Brother," a 1927 silent film starring Harold Lloyd, Veterans Memorial Hall, 3 P.M. Admission $6; $4 for people older than 62 and children under 12.</p>
        <p>Nov. 24: Concert by a gospel choir, the Institutional Radio Choir, Veterans Memorial Hall, 7 P.M.; $10.</p>
        <p>Nov. 25: Harpsichord recital by Ronald Cross, Veterans Memorial Hall, 7 P.M.; $3.</p>
        <p>Dec. 2: "Day Without Art," readings by writers in response to the AIDS crisis, Newhouse Center, 2 P.M.; $5; $4 for children and the elderly.</p>
        <p>Dec. 6: Opening of "Merry Christmas, Darling," a musical holiday celebration, Veterans Memorial Hall, 8 P.M.; $12; $7 for children. Also on Dec. 8 and 14 at 8 P.M., Dec. 15 at 3 P.M. and Dec. 9 and 16 at 7 P.M.</p>
        <p>Dec. 7-8: Gift gathering. From noon to 7 P.M. on Friday and from 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. on Saturday, several New York City cultural institutions will be displaying their gift shop wares in the Great Hall. Admission $2; children free.</p>
        <p>Information, (718) 448-2500.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY OUTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
