<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Executive Computer; More and More Portables, With More and More Power</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="401648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSONAL COMPUTERS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PETER H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DC1439F93BA25752C1A966958260" item-length="1154" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Executive Computer; More and More Portables, With More and More Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter H. Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PETER H</byline>
      <dateline>LAS VEGAS, Nev.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE personal computer industry is getting carried away these days, literally and figuratively. The flurry of new portable machines fall into two broad categories: smaller and more powerful, or larger and more exotic, and scores of them were on display last week at the annual Comdex/Fall computer trade show here. Manufacturers clearly expect portables to become standard equipment in businesses in the years ahead and many types of portables have emerged:</p>
        <p>* Hand-held information managers, like the Sharp Wizard, that weigh less than a pound and act as an executive secretary. "It doesn't make sense to kill a mosquito with a sledgehammer," said Gilbert J. DeLiso, national marketing manager for the Sharp Electronics Corporation, based in Mahwah, N.J. He said the Prudential Insurance Company of America had bought 10,000 of the units for its sales force.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE personal computer industry is getting carried away these days, literally and figuratively. The flurry of new portable machines fall into two broad categories: smaller and more powerful, or larger and more exotic, and scores of them were on display last week at the annual Comdex/Fall computer trade show here. Manufacturers clearly expect portables to become standard equipment in businesses in the years ahead and many types of portables have emerged:</p>
        <p>* Hand-held information managers, like the Sharp Wizard, that weigh less than a pound and act as an executive secretary. "It doesn't make sense to kill a mosquito with a sledgehammer," said Gilbert J. DeLiso, national marketing manager for the Sharp Electronics Corporation, based in Mahwah, N.J. He said the Prudential Insurance Company of America had bought 10,000 of the units for its sales force.</p>
        <p>* Coat-pocket PC's, like the $1,995, 1.5-pound Poqet computer, which offer full MS-DOS compatibility. Stav Prodromou, vice chairman of the Poqet Corporation, of Sunnyvale, Calif., said his customers include Warner Brothers and Chevron.</p>
        <p>* Laptops with brilliant and expensive color screens, like the Toshiba T3200SXC, with a list price of $8,995, and the Sharp Colorstar PC8501, which is expected to sell for less than $10,000. In general, color screens add $2,000 to $2,500 to the price of comparable monochrome models. They are likely to find a home with executives who need to make presentations on the road.</p>
        <p>* Portables powered by the Intel Corporation's 486 processor that can hold their own with any desktop system. The International Business Machines Corporation showed off its PS/2 Model 75, at 20 pounds more "luggable" than truly portable, that comes with either a gas-plasma or color display. When it becomes available in March, the price will be heavy, too -- $16,000 to $19,000.</p>
        <p>In addition, companies at Comdex showed a variety of other machines: "palm-top" units that can receive facsimile messages and electronic mail; portables with cellular modems that can bypass the wired telephone network to send and receive information through the cellular phone system; portables with removable hard disks; portables that attach to desktop "docking stations"; portables that use a pen-like stylus instead of a keyboard, and even portables that run software designed for scientific and engineering work stations. In short, there are portables in virtually any size, shape and configuration the user wants.</p>
        <p>Even so, some industry observers say we ain't seen nothing yet. They probably have in mind machines like an intriguing 14-pound portable, called the Britelite, that was demonstrated here by Research Development and Innovations Inc., of San Diego. The Britelite, manufactured by the Korean computer maker Trigem, is one of the first portables based on the Sparc processor, which relies on RISC, reduced instruction set computing.  The Sparc chip is used in work stations made by Sun Microsystems Inc., as well as by an increasing number of clone companies.</p>
        <p>Research Development asserts that the Britelite, which will cost $10,000 to $12,000 when it becomes available next month, will run not one, not two, but three of the most popular operating systems used by businesses: Sun OS, Macintosh and MS-DOS. It will come with 8 megabytes of memory, a 100-megabyte hard drive and a 13-inch monitor with a resolution of 1,152 by 900.</p>
        <p>The Britelite is believed to be the first machine of any type that "emulates" Macintosh software without using Apple Computer Inc.'s proprietary, jealously guarded codes. The Macintosh emulation feature was not demonstrated here, said Rick Schrameck, the president of Research Development, because his company was awaiting final clearance from its lawyers. In the past, Apple has threatened to sue any company that encroaches on its Mac monopoly, but Mr. Schrameck contended that the Mac feature was legally bulletproof.</p>
        <p>An Apple spokesman declined to comment, saying the company has not had a chance to see the Britelite. Sun, meanwhile, has endorsed the Britelite.</p>
        <p>On a theoretical level, at least, the Britelite represents the first major step toward computers that can run software from a variety of operating systems. The user would not have to worry whether the applications were based on DOS or Macintosh or Unix; he or she would plug it in and the machine would sort out the underlying conflicts. Such a system is seen by many frustrated users as the Holy Grail of computing. The Britelite is a dramatic advance, although it cannot run all operating systems and runs MS-DOS only at the speed of a 286-based system.</p>
        <p>What remains to be seen is whether there is a market for a Sparc-Unix laptop. The Toshiba Corporation of Japan believes there is; it has introduced a Sparc-based laptop in Japan but not in the United States. It is also unclear how many Unix users really need to run Macintosh and DOS software.</p>
        <p>Unix is usually depicted as a daunting operating system, and it has traditionally been used in scientific and engineering applications, as well as for software development. Because it is better suited than any other current operating system for large workgroup applications and for jobs where the user needs to perform several tasks at once, many people believe Unix will capture a larger share of the business PC market in coming years.</p>
        <p>Unix is already making significant inroads in the financial community, where traders must monitor several sources of information and send information over a network at high speed. Sun, with its Sparc-based workstations, is the leading advocate of desktop Unix systems, and a half-dozen companies at Comdex were demonstrating Sparc clones.</p>
        <p>It stands to reason that if Unix becomes a significant player in standard business envirnments, and if portability is truly important to business executives, then eventually there will be a market for Unix portables.</p>
        <p>So what will be the role of the portable computer? Some analysts envision portables as replacements for a large number of today's desktop machines, allowing an executive to have one machine that contains all his information and to take it with him wherever he goes. "I've just come back from Japan, and that is clearly the direction the Japanese companies are following," said Tim Bajarin, executive vice president of Creative Strategies International Inc., of San Jose, Calif. "I think they are going to take a lot of the desktop computer companies by surprise."</p>
        <p>Others say the main use of the portables will continue to be as supplementary devices, when executives are away from their primary desktop machines. "I look at these as second computers, so price is important," said Ruthann Quindlen, vice president of Alex. Brown &amp; Sons in San Francisco. "These people aren't looking for leading-edge technologies. They want them smaller, faster, with better keyboards, and so on."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
