<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Off to Good Start, Ewing Is Aiming Higher</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="402064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK KNICKERBOCKERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EWING, PATRICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, CLIFTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D91E31F93BA25752C1A966958260" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Off to Good Start, Ewing Is Aiming Higher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWN, CLIFTON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the Knicks' locker-room door opened after the game on Thursday night in Portland, Ore., Patrick Ewing braced himself for the inevitable group of reporters waiting. He had ice bags on both knees, a few scars on his body, but fewer concerns about the Knicks on his mind.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' eight-day West Coast trip was over with a 3-1 record, a morale booster for Ewing and the Knicks. And Ewing had continued to play at a level that makes him arguably the best center in the National Basketball Association, and definitely one of the league's best players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the Knicks' locker-room door opened after the game on Thursday night in Portland, Ore., Patrick Ewing braced himself for the inevitable group of reporters waiting. He had ice bags on both knees, a few scars on his body, but fewer concerns about the Knicks on his mind.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' eight-day West Coast trip was over with a 3-1 record, a morale booster for Ewing and the Knicks. And Ewing had continued to play at a level that makes him arguably the best center in the National Basketball Association, and definitely one of the league's best players.</p>
        <p>Heading into last night's game against Philadelphia in Madison Square Garden, Ewing was among the league leaders in scoring (28.6), rebounding (12.6) and blocked shots (4.88).</p>
        <p>Many people thought it would be impossible for Ewing to improve over last season, when he averaged 28.6 points, 10.9 rebounds and 3.99 blocks. But so far he has been better, a tribute to the intense work he does every summer as well as during the season. Ewing often arrives at practice 90 minutes early to lift weights, even on the mornings after games.</p>
        <p>Yet, the Knicks' early season has already had its highs and lows. When New York got off to a 1-2 start, Ewing appeared frustrated, and commented publicly for the first time that he was unhappy with the progress of contract negotiations with the Knicks.</p>
        <p>Ewing, who is eligible to become a restricted free agent at the end of this season, is seeking a new multimillion-dollar contract that would allow him to finish his career in New York. Neither the Knicks, nor David Falk, Ewing's attorney, have said much about the negotiations, hoping to keep the details private.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Ewing's main objective is to help the Knicks be the best team possible, a team good enough to contend for the championship. A private individual, Ewing prefers to let his play do the talking. And right now, his play reflects a determined and confident man. The following is a look back at Ewing's week on the West Coast.</p>
        <p>Sacramento, Calif., Nov. 9-10 -- When the Knicks arrived on a Friday afternoon, the weather was picturesque, 80 degrees and a cloudless sky. Yet after flying for more than five hours, the players grabbed a quick bite, then boarded a bus to practice at a local gym. The floor was slippery and practice was not good. Stu Jackson, the coach, allowed Ewing and Charles Oakley to sit out practice. Because they are physical players, because they play a lot of minutes, and because they spend most of their time in the low post, Ewing and Oakley take more punishment than anyone else on the team. So occasionally, Jackson gives them a day off.</p>
        <p>That logic looked like a stroke of genius the next night when New York played the Sacramento Kings. It was obvious after the opening quarter that Ewing and Oakley would have to play long minutes if the Knicks were going to win. Perhaps affected by the long trip, the Knicks lacked crispness offensively, missing shots and fumbling passes. They committed 23 turnovers. The Kings were no better, shooting 38.8 percent and missing 10 of 32 free throws. It was an ugly game.</p>
        <p>But in the fourth quarter, Ewing was at his best, scoring 8 of his 24 points to help squeeze out a 93-88 victory. He also contributed 13 rebounds and 5 blocked shots.</p>
        <p>After the game, a reporter asked Jackson where the Knicks would be without Ewing. Jackson rolled his eyes and said, "I don't even want to think about that."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, two young boys who wanted to meet Ewing were escorted into the locker room. Ewing shook hands with both, then playfully asked which one was the better basketball player. The taller youngster raised his hand, but the other youngster said, "I'm pretty good, too." Ewing laughed.</p>
        <p>The Knicks' victory also brightened his mood, but there was no time to celebrate. Less than 24 hours later, New York would be in Los Angeles playing the Lakers.</p>
        <p>Inglewood, Calif, Nov. 11-12 -- Playing the Lakers brought out the best in the Knicks. They played poised and confident basketball and won, 109-103. Ewing was typically outstanding: 27 points, 14 rebounds, 6 assists and 3 blocked shots. But he had plenty of assistance from his teammates, particularly Kiki Vandeweghe, who scored 10 of his 22 points in the final five and a half minutes.</p>
        <p>After the game, a subdued Magic Johnson was trying to explain the Lakers' third loss in four games. In the other locker room, Ewing was begining to feel good about the Knicks, not only because they won, but also because so many people played well.</p>
        <p>"The Lakers may be having problems, but they still have Magic Johnson and James Worthy," Ewing said. "Anytime we can beat a team with those two guys on it, especially on the road, I feel good. This was a big win. It's a good sign for us."</p>
        <p>Seattle, Nov. 13 -- Xavier McDaniel, the SuperSonics' outstanding forward, had this to say in The Seattle Times about what he expected from Ewing and the Knicks' offense:</p>
        <p>"Pat's going to be the focal point. Pat goes from one block to the other, and everybody else watches. It's like Gladys Knight and the Pips."</p>
        <p>It was a clever line by McDaniel, but he found it to be untrue. The Knicks won an emotional game in overtime, 116-110, giving them a perfect 3-0 record on the trip.</p>
        <p>Despite 28 points, 8 rebounds and 3 blocks, Ewing said after the game, "I don't think I had a good game, but the rest of the team played real well."</p>
        <p>Ewing was half right, because the rest of the team did play well, especially Gerald Wilkins (22 points) and the entire bench, which combined for 34 points.</p>
        <p>"One more game and we can go home," Ewing said. "No matter what happens in Portland, we can say this trip has been a success."</p>
        <p>Portland, Nov. 14-15 -- Jackson gave the entire team a day off on Wednesday. It did not help. Portland rolled to a 141-125 victory, the undefeated Trail Blazers' seventh triumph. Ewing had 27 points and 9 rebounds, but with the game out of reach, he did not play most of the final period.</p>
        <p>As he thought about the long trip home, Ewing has this to say about the state of the Knicks:</p>
        <p>"The trip was great, but we have a lot of work to do. The season is still young. Last year we were killing people in the first half of the season, then we took a nose dive. We have to stay focused and keep working.</p>
        <p>'We're going to try not to let what happened last year happen again. All the talk and the media and the controversy last year were distractions. We're going to try and stay away from that."</p>
        <p>When asked if the chemistry on this year's team had improved, Ewing said: "I'm not sure yet because it's too early. But we're playing very well for the most part. We're hitting the open man. Kiki has been playing tremendously. Everybody has been contributing."</p>
        <p>Does he think the Knicks depend on him too much to win? Ewing smiled as he prepared to leave the locker room, perhaps keeping his innermost thoughts to himself.</p>
        <p>"Some people are always going to find fault with any situation," Ewing said. "I just worry about playing, to do the best that I possibly can to win. That's all I can do. My goal is to win. If we keep winning, I'll be happy."  PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
