<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Angry Investors Of Eurotunnel Move to Replace Its Directors</title>
    <meta content="07TUNN$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/07/business/worldbusiness/07tunnel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1572431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eurotunnel Plc and Eurotunnel Sa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miguet, Nicolas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shirrefs, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Voting Requirements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Voter Registration and Requirements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Eurotunnel</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7DA1738F934A35757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1084" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Angry Investors Of Eurotunnel Move to Replace Its Directors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Angry Investors of Eurotunnel Move to Replace Its Directors</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Incumbent board of Eurotunnel, in stunning shareholder revolt, concedes defeat to uprising organized by French populist politician Nicolas Miguet; Miguet solicited shareholder votes to throw out current directors and replace them with slate of his choosing; campaigned on platform that tunnel should be run for benefit of shareholders, whose investment has been withering in value for years, with creditors being forced to make large concessions; chief executive Richard Shirrefs has been unable to turn around company; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a stunning shareholder revolt, the incumbent board of Eurotunnel, the financially struggling project that has provided a rail link between France and Britain for 10 years, conceded defeat to an uprising organized by a French populist politician, Nicolas Miguet.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Miguet has won the day,'' Ann Leva, a spokeswoman for the company, said Tuesday night, on the eve of a shareholders meeting. Mr. Miguet had solicited shareholder votes to throw out the current directors and replace them with a slate of his choosing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The board of Eurotunnel, the financially struggling project that has provided a rail link between France and Britain, conceded defeat to a shareholder uprising.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a stunning shareholder revolt, the incumbent board of Eurotunnel, the financially struggling project that has provided a rail link between France and Britain for 10 years, conceded defeat to an uprising organized by a French populist politician, Nicolas Miguet.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Miguet has won the day,'' Ann Leva, a spokeswoman for the company, said Tuesday night, on the eve of a shareholders meeting. Mr. Miguet had solicited shareholder votes to throw out the current directors and replace them with a slate of his choosing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miguet was exultant after the company conceded. ''It's an historic victory,'' he said in a telephone interview. ''Democracy prevailed. It is a first in the world. I am very proud of helping to make it possible.''</p>
        <p>He campaigned on a platform that the tunnel should be run for the benefit of shareholders, whose investment has been withering in value for years, with creditors being forced to make large concessions. But Tuesday night he declined to offer details on what concessions he expected creditors to make.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miguet, the founder of the French Taxpayers Party, had been contemptuous of management, and it of him. ''We are morality. They are vice and crime,'' he said earlier Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Eurotunnel was plagued by cost overruns in construction and revenues have consistently been below expectations since it opened in 1994. Since the debt was restructured in 1997, Mr. Miguet said in arguments sent to shareholders, ''Eurotunnel's situation has not stopped getting worse and successive managements, creditors and public bodies have not reacted.''</p>
        <p>The company's management proposed a vague restructuring plan earlier this year, but the plan has made little progress and appeared to hold out little hope for shareholders to realize much of anything.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miguet said Tuesday that creditors should be willing take large losses from the original loans because much of the debt was now owned by hedge funds, which had purchased it at deep discounts.</p>
        <p>The company has been fighting Mr. Miguet vigorously and in its presentations to shareholders it accused him of ''repeated attempts to destabilize the company'' and called his proposals ''incredibly naïve, if not dishonest.''</p>
        <p>But as the company's situation has worsened, more and more institutional investors have sold their shares -- and thus their votes -- largely to French individuals. The company says it has 1.1 million shareholders, up from 700,000 a year ago.</p>
        <p>Most of them did not vote, and some of the largest ones -- the remaining institutional shareholders -- appear to have stuck with management. But the company said its management had received proxies representing just 8.3 percent of the shares, while the Miguet forces had more than 20 percent.</p>
        <p>Other shares came in either by paper ballots, not yet counted, or belong to the 4,222 shareholders who are registered to attend the shareholders meeting at a conference center near Charles de Gaulle Airport. Most of these shareholders are expected to support Mr. Miguet.</p>
        <p>While only 39 percent of the shares were expected to vote, the company said only 25 percent were needed for a quorum. There had been speculation that the company would challenge the legality of some proxies given to Mr. Miguet and his supporters, but Allison Bourgeois, the company's director for communications, seemed to rule that out.</p>
        <p>''We have no reason to believe a vote is not a vote,'' she said Tuesday night. ''You can't appeal against it.''</p>
        <p>Shares of Eurotunnel fell 0.02 euros to 0.56 euros (68 cents) in Paris trading before the management conceded defeat. Mr. Miguet said he expected the price to rise to above 2 euros in coming years as a result of good management from ''the new team, the dream team.''</p>
        <p>Just how he can accomplish that is far from clear. There is little doubt that the company will be unable to pay its debts when they start coming due in 2006, particularly because it had been collecting revenues from rail operators based on optimistic traffic guarantees that are due to expire that year. That would lead to a sharp reduction in revenue.</p>
        <p>Eurotunnel's chief executive, Richard Shirrefs, said earlier this year that the company was in ''a stable equilibrium of failure,'' but the restructuring plan he proposed seemed to offer little tangible hope for shareholders. But the British and French governments appeared to be unwilling to admit that the shares were likely to be worthless in any reorganization, and the company was unwilling to say how badly shareholders might fare in any debt reorganization.</p>
        <p>The shareholders have been suffering for years. When the tunnel was initially financed in 1987 -- without overt public financing, a requirement for approval by Margaret Thatcher, then the British prime minister -- shareholders were told that dividends were likely by 1995. At the last restructuring, in 1997, dividends were expected in 2006.</p>
        <p>Instead, the shares have fallen to the point that they are trading at barely 10 percent of the original issue price from 1987. Shareholders put up more money through rights offerings in 1990, 1994 and 1999, and while the prices at each offering were successively lower, buyers at any of the offerings have lost money.</p>
        <p>The proportion of trading volume in London has fallen from 47 percent in 1991 to 12 percent last year and 9 percent last month, as French individual investors bought while others sold.</p>
        <p>As a politician, Mr. Miguet has not proven wildly popular. He said his party received 3.45 percent of the vote in races it entered in last month's French regional elections. But he and his allies did win the right to try to run a company that operates one of the most famous feats of engineering in European history but has been unable to make money doing it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
