<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Secret History of Birth Control</title>
    <meta content="22KEVLEST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/22/books/review/22KEVLEST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1311100"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kevles, Daniel J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tone, Andrea</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Lara V</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Devices and Desires (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sexual Chemistry (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Food and Drug Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0DB173BF931A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Secret History of Birth Control</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Secret History of Birth Control</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Daniel J. Kevles</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kevles, Daniel J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel J Kevles reviews following books: Devices and Desires: A History of Contraceptives in America by Andrea Tone; and Sexual Chemistry: A History of the Contraceptive Pill by Lara V Marks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEVICES AND DESIRES</p>
        <p>A History of Contraceptives in America.</p>
        <p>By Andrea Tone.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 366 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Hill &amp; Wang. $30.</p>
        <p>SEXUAL CHEMISTRY</p>
        <p>A History of the Contraceptive Pill.</p>
        <p>By Lara V. Marks.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 372 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press. $29.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two new books show the resilience of the American contraceptive industry in the face of militant attempts to suppress it</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEVICES AND DESIRES</p>
        <p>A History of Contraceptives in America.</p>
        <p>By Andrea Tone.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 366 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Hill &amp; Wang. $30.</p>
        <p>SEXUAL CHEMISTRY</p>
        <p>A History of the Contraceptive Pill.</p>
        <p>By Lara V. Marks.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 372 pp. New Haven:</p>
        <p>Yale University Press. $29.95.</p>
        <p>In 1982, a French pharmaceutical company announced that it had developed a pill that would end a pregnancy if taken within seven weeks of conception. Advocates of reproductive freedom hailed the news, because the pill, known as RU-486, meant that abortions could be induced soon after conception in a doctor's office, without surgery. By the early 1990's, RU-486 was available in France, Britain and Sweden. But protests by antiabortionists were driving its European manufacturers to quit making it, and opponents in the United States helped block its introduction here by threatening to boycott the products of any drug company that sold it. In the face of such intimidation, virtually no American company was willing to supply it in commercial quantities. Since its approval for sale by the Food and Drug Administration last fall, RU-486 has been distributed in the United States by a pharmaceutical company specializing in women's health that gets it from a producer in China.</p>
        <p>The moral condemnation, intimidation of manufacturers and consequent reliance on pariah producers in this saga all echo the hidden history of birth control that Andrea Tone exposes in her marvelously eye-opening book, ''Devices and Desires.'' A faculty member at the Georgia Institute of Technology, Tone brings an original dimension to the story by recounting the development of the American contraceptive industry, and demonstrating its resilience in the face of militant attempts to suppress it.</p>
        <p>It wasn't until the mid-1800's that contraceptive technology jumped beyond methods in use for centuries, such as making condoms out of animal intestines. After Charles Goodyear invented the vulcanization of rubber in 1839, rubber manufacturers began supplying not just condoms but douching syringes and ''womb veils'' (or diaphragms and cervical caps), and what amounted to IUD's. By the 1870's, pharmacies were selling chemical suppositories, vaginal sponges and medicated tampons. All these contraceptives were well advertised -- the ads, samples of which Tone includes, were often detailed and graphic, giving us a disconcerting idea of some of the objects that women were encouraged to insert into their bodies.</p>
        <p>The easy availability of birth control devices alarmed Anthony Comstock, a onetime salesman in New York City who believed that they assisted the vice trade by divorcing sex from marriage and childbearing. Tone argues that Comstock was an enemy only of open sexuality, not of private passion, but he was surely no friend of sex without fear of pregnancy even in the marriage bed. In 1873, joined by like-minded allies, he successfully lobbied for Congressional passage of a bill that branded contraception obscene and prohibited its distribution across state lines or through the mails. Similar legislation was soon enacted in 24 states.</p>
        <p>Historians have long believed that not least because of the Comstock law, birth control was available mostly to well-to-do Americans until around World War I. Tone convincingly upends that view with evidence from patent documents, trade catalogs, advertisements, medical articles, private letters, investigative records and trial transcripts. This material strongly indicates that, as she writes, ''Americans of all backgrounds created a zone of tolerance in which birth control was routinely made, sold, bought and used.''</p>
        <p>Tone offers fascinating vignettes of small-time birth control entrepreneurs, noting that they were predominantly women and immigrants willing to fill the market niche that respectable manufacturers left open. The business was easy to enter -- contraceptives were cheap and simple to produce in small shops or homes -- and abounded with opportunity. Disadvantaged women could earn twice the income of their middle-class sisters. Julius Schmidt, who arrived penniless from Germany in 1882, began making condoms from animal intestines, was arrested at Comstock's initiative, but returned immediately to his business, eventually earning a fortune by selling the Sheik and Ramses brands. So long as contraceptives were illegal, manufacturers like Schmidt survived by dancing on the edge of the law, advertising in euphemisms (''rubber goods'' for ''gents. 25 cents each''; ''married women's friends'') and using aliases, 26 of them in one case.</p>
        <p>Tone shows that even in the heyday of Comstockery, the courts in practice reflected ''broadly based support of bootleg birth control'' -- holding sacrosanct the privacy of the mails, for example, and denying that Congress had any power to criminalize the use of contraception. Grand jurors often declined to return indictments on people arrested for providing it, and sentences tended to be light for those convicted. Then, in 1918, amid wartime worries about the spread of venereal disease, Judge Frederick Crane ruled in a case brought to his New York appeals court that contraceptive devices were legal as instruments for the maintenance of health.</p>
        <p>Crane's ruling helped transform the birth control industry, allowing condom manufacturers to sell their products openly -- they marked the packages ''for the prevention of disease only'' -- in drugstores, barbershops, newsstands, cigar stores and gas stations. The military, puritanical in its approach to venereal disease before World War I, approved the use of condoms for prophylaxis in the early 1930's, by which time 15 companies were producing 1.44 million condoms a day.</p>
        <p>In recent years, some feminist critics have interpreted the invention of the contraceptive pill and the earlier encouragement of diaphragm use as indicators of male eagerness to place the burdens of birth control entirely on women. Tone vigorously contends the contrary -- that the development of these devices was advanced by birth control advocates to give women control over their bodies and reproductive lives. To this end, during the 1920's Margaret Sanger set out to make birth control respectable, partly by insisting that diaphragms be fitted only by doctors instead of obtained over the counter. At Sanger's urging, her second husband, a wealthy businessman, financed the</p>
        <p>Holland-Rantos Company to supply diaphragms to physicians and clinics.</p>
        <p>But Sanger's strategy posed a problem -- medicalization put diaphragms out of reach of the many women who did not have access to physicians or who were embarrassed to submit to internal examination. While used by a quarter of middle-class women in the late 1940's, they were over all the least popular method of birth control. Women continued to rely mostly on over-the-counter items sold for ''feminine hygiene,'' including vaginal jellies and suppositories, douche solutions and foaming tablets; in 1938, these products accounted for 85 percent of contraceptive sales. None required a doctor's prescription, while all were cheap and could be bought like toothpaste. Tone emphasizes that feminine hygiene was an unregulated market of misleading advertisement, unrestrained hucksterism and unreliable -- in some cases dangerous -- products.</p>
        <p>Women's resistance to consulting doctors for contraception was greatly diminished by the arrival of the birth control pill in 1960. The story of the pill, ably recounted in ''Devices and Desires,'' is told in absorbing detail and from an international perspective in ''Sexual Chemistry,'' by Lara V. Marks, a British historian of medicine. While the tale is familiar, both treatments correct common misunderstandings. Among them: Although the pill was developed by male scientists, the effort was initially fostered by two women, Sanger and Katherine McCormick, who financed it with part of her husband's International Harvester fortune. And contrary to charges that the pill was inadequately tested,</p>
        <p>the F.D.A. subjected it to more than adequate scrutiny measured by the standards prevailing before the thalidomide scare in 1962.</p>
        <p>Marks offers abundant information on the reception of the pill, including the attitudes of women and health services toward its use, debates about its role in causing and preventing cancer and its inadvertent contribution to the spread of AIDS. Marks and Tone both stress that the contraceptive pill has not proved to be a panacea, nor has it fulfilled one of the goals behind its development, the limitation of population growth in the third world. Health fears associated with it and a shortage of medical services have combined to limit its use -- to roughly 20 percent of women in the developed world, according to Marks, and 13 percent in the third world, where about a quarter of women use an IUD and another third have been sterilized.</p>
        <p>Although Tone calls for more over-the-counter devices so that women can depend less on doctors, it is difficult to imagine a chemical contraceptive that would not require medical supervision. In any case, fear of product liability suits has driven most companies out of research directed toward the development of new birth control products. And while the right to sell and use contraceptives was sanctioned by two decisions of the United States Supreme Court some 30 years ago, Comstockery persists in the United States, causing battles, like that over RU-486, fraught with implications for a woman's right to control her reproductive life.</p>
        <p>Daniel J. Kevles, a historian at Yale University, is a co-author of the forthcoming ''Inventing America,'' a history of the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daniel J. Kevles, a historian at Yale University, is a co-author of the forthcoming ''Inventing America,'' a history of the United States.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
