<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baltimore Is Setting the Bar High</title>
    <meta content="Y22NFL$21" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/22/sports/22NFLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1311482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Baltimore Ravens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland/Baltimore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football,Wages and Salaries,Athletics and Sports,Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Baltimore</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Baltimore Ravens</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Vick, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1D7133AF931A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baltimore Is Setting the Bar High</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ravens Aim for a Better Mark</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article reviews off-season for NFL teams by division, noting players signed and lost; chart shows where training camps are located and gives last year's record; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is the time of year when the defending Super Bowl champion Baltimore Ravens should feel a bit nervous. The season is approaching, and so is the realization that their title defense is about to begin. Expectations of a second consecutive championship can be as crushing as a Tony Siragusa tackle.</p>
        <p>But as the summer has gotten hotter -- a signal the annual ritual of sweaty N.F.L. training camps is about to start -- the owner, Art Modell, has remained as cool as a glass of chilled water. He has told close friends that this team is better than last season's version, which smothered the Giants, 34-7, in Super Bowl XXXV. In short, Modell says Baltimore has a strong chance to repeat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baltimore's chances of repeating their Super Bowl title are strong, but as training camps are opening, it is clear there are a number of teams right on the Ravens' tails</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is the time of year when the defending Super Bowl champion Baltimore Ravens should feel a bit nervous. The season is approaching, and so is the realization that their title defense is about to begin. Expectations of a second consecutive championship can be as crushing as a Tony Siragusa tackle.</p>
        <p>But as the summer has gotten hotter -- a signal the annual ritual of sweaty N.F.L. training camps is about to start -- the owner, Art Modell, has remained as cool as a glass of chilled water. He has told close friends that this team is better than last season's version, which smothered the Giants, 34-7, in Super Bowl XXXV. In short, Modell says Baltimore has a strong chance to repeat.</p>
        <p>''I'm not printing playoff tickets yet,'' Modell said last week. ''I also know it's tougher to stay on top than to get there. But there is no question that this team now is better than last year's. We've really improved and that's why I'm confident we can win it all again.''</p>
        <p>Baltimore has kept its top-ranked defense virtually intact and has upgraded its offense by signing the free-agent quarterback Elvis Grbac and offensive tackle Leon Searcy.</p>
        <p>Baltimore is on top, but as training camps are opening, it is clear there are a number of teams right on the Ravens' tails. Free agency has created a new N.F.L., in which every season the list of contenders seems to grow.</p>
        <p>Atlanta was the first team to open camp, with players reporting last Wednesday, and by today, eight teams will have reported, with the rest soon to follow.</p>
        <p>As of late last week, the Falcons were the only team to have their first-round pick signed, quarterback Michael Vick, who months ago agreed to an eight-year contract worth $61 million. Here's a review of each team's off-season as the league prepares for another hot summer:</p>
        <p>N.F.C. East</p>
        <p>ARIZONA: The Cardinals' off-season was a mix of good and bad. They lost three defensive players -- Andre Wadsworth, Aeneas Williams and Simeon Rice -- leaving the defense vulnerable. But the franchise did sign a solid offensive lineman in Pete Kendall, the former Seattle guard, and drafted Leonard Davis from Texas with the second overall pick. Off-season grade: C.</p>
        <p>DALLAS: The owner, Jerry Jones, said his team can win 10 games. That won't happen. The team's biggest acquisition was quarterback Tony Banks. Off-season grade: D.</p>
        <p>GIANTS: Quietly the Giants had a great off-season, keeping their two stars, running back Tiki Barber and cornerback Jason Sehorn. Then the team signed the former Tennessee defensive end Kenny Holmes. The only reason the team does not get a top grade is because no one got Ron Dayne, as he said he would, to run the monstrous hill that Barber and fullback Greg Comella train on to stay in tip-top shape. Off-season grade: B+.</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA: The team upgraded its wide receiver position by signing the speedy James Thrash and drafting U.C.L.A. wideout Freddie Mitchell. Off-season grade: B.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON: Bringing in Marty Schottenheimer to coach the team was the smartest move Daniel Snyder has made as owner. Off-season grade: A.</p>
        <p>N.F.C. Central</p>
        <p>CHICAGO: When Jerry Angelo left Tampa Bay to become the general manager of the Bears, he became the team's biggest off-season move. Angelo, of course, did not have enough time to do much with this roster, which is lacking in overall talent. Off-season grade: C.</p>
        <p>DETROIT: Another team that completely restructured its front office, bringing in Matt Millen to run the team and Marty Mornhinweg to coach it. Mornhinweg, who worked with quarterback Jeff Garcia in San Francisco, has spent a lot of time with quarterback Charlie Batch in Detroit. Off-season grade: B.</p>
        <p>GREEN BAY: The Packers barely dipped into free agency, instead choosing to re-sign their own players, including quarterback Brett Favre and running backs Dorsey Levens and Ahman Green. Off-season grade: Incomplete.</p>
        <p>MINNESOTA: The Vikings lost a number of star players including running back Robert Smith (retired), defensive lineman John Randle (signed by Seattle) and linebacker Dwayne Rudd (Cleveland). Ouch. Off-season grade: C-.</p>
        <p>TAMPA BAY: The Buccaneers made two moves that could land them in the Super Bowl, first signing the free-agent quarterback Brad Johnson, then defensive lineman Simeon Rice. If Tampa Bay does not make the championship game this season, look for those Bill Parcells to the Buccaneers rumors to begin anew. Off-season grade: A.</p>
        <p>N.F.C. West</p>
        <p>ATLANTA: Drafting Michael Vick was a brilliant move by the Falcons. Don't be surprised if he is in the starting lineup by midseason. Coach Dan Reeves has already named him the No. 2 quarterback behind Chris Chandler. Off-season grade: B+.</p>
        <p>CAROLINA: The Panthers revamped their offensive line, which was smart, but they got rid of quarterback Steve Beuerlein, meaning that Jeff Lewis is the starter, and that's not smart. Off-season grade: C-.</p>
        <p>NEW ORLEANS: The Saints needed a deep threat and the fast Albert Connell was brought in from Washington. Off-season grade: B.</p>
        <p>ST. LOUIS: The team may have eight new starters on defense, including cornerback Aeneas Williams from Arizona. Off-season grade: A+.</p>
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO: The 49ers were able to keep their offensive line intact. Off-season grade: B-.</p>
        <p>A.F.C. East</p>
        <p>BUFFALO: Re-signing wide receiver Eric Moulds was a priority for the team, and the Bills were able to keep him despite serious salary cap problems. Off-season grade: B-.</p>
        <p>INDIANAPOLIS: It may not have any impact on the field once the season begins, but when the Pro Bowl running back Edgerrin James skipped a voluntary minicamp this off-season it angered teammates. Once James gets on the field, and he again rushes for over 1,000 yards, all will be forgiven. Off-season grade: C.</p>
        <p>MIAMI: The team got more depth at quarterback with the signing of the former Jet Ray Lucas. Off-season grade: B.</p>
        <p>NEW ENGLAND: The off-season arrest of wide receiver Terry Glenn on a charge of attacking a girlfriend has clouded the coming season for the franchise. Off-season grade: D.</p>
        <p>JETS: Al Groh out, Herman Edwards in. Off-season grade: A.</p>
        <p>A.F.C. Central</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI: The Bengals put considerable resources into their offensive line and kept running back Corey Dillon in a Cincinnati uniform. Off-season grade: C+.</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND: Errict Rhett is the favorite to start at running back for the Browns, which means the team should have put more effort into finding someone better. Off-season grade: C-.</p>
        <p>JACKSONVILLE: The team was over $25 million in salary cap debt but still re-signed quarterback Mark Brunell. And Coach Tom Coughlin decided to finally allow his offensive coordinator to call some plays. Off-season grade: B-.</p>
        <p>PITTSBURGH: The Steelers gave Coach Bill Cowher a three-year contract extension, but he is slowly wearing out his welcome within the organization. Off-season grade: C+.</p>
        <p>TENNESSEE: Smart move trading with the Rams for defensive lineman Kevin Carter, who led the N.F.L. in sacks two seasons ago, and will pair with Jevon Kearse. Off-season grade: B.</p>
        <p>A.F.C. West</p>
        <p>DENVER: The Broncos made Ray Rhodes their defensive coordinator, the single smartest move any team made this off-season. Off-season grade: A.</p>
        <p>KANSAS CITY: The Chiefs hired Dick Vermeil to coach the team and run the franchise. He brought along an old friend from the Rams, quarterback Trent Green. Off-season grade: A.</p>
        <p>OAKLAND: The Raiders brought in wide receiver Jerry Rice, at minimal cost, who wants to prove he can still play. Off-season grade: B.</p>
        <p>SAN DIEGO: The Chargers got rid of 235 pounds of baggage in quarterback Ryan Leaf. Off-season grade: B.</p>
        <p>SEATTLE: General Manager Mike Holmgren was busy this off-season, trading with Green Bay for quarterback Matt Hasselbeck, then added five new bodies to his defense, including the former Steeler linebacker Levon Kirkland. Off-season grade: A.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
