<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New &amp; Noteworthy</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="567216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DE1F31F932A35752C1A964958260" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New &amp; Noteworthy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAUREL GRAEBER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAKING HISTORY, by Carolyn See. (Laurel/Dell, $10.) Jerry Bridges, a California businessman, believes in technology's ability to perfect the world -- until human error and the randomness of fate intrude. In a story framed by two devastating accidents, his family drifts apart, then reconnects. "Ms. See sets out to catch the sound of our world singing its way into the future," Susan Fromberg Schaeffer said here last year. "The miracle is how well she has succeeded."</p>
        <p>LONE STAR RISING: Lyndon Johnson and His Times, 1908-1960, by Robert Dallek. (Oxford University, $16.95.) Former President Lyndon B. Johnson was a complicated man, guilty of both egotism and ethical lapses, yet deeply dedicated to making government an agent of social progress. In this biography, the first of two volumes, Robert Dallek has taken the position of "a seeker after truth rather than someone out to attack or defend," our reviewer, Nicholas Lemann, said last year. He added: "For better and for worse, Mr. Dallek is the rare present-day practitioner of the 'three yards and a cloud of dust' school of biography. He lays out the facts and allows the grand themes to emanate from them, relatively untouched by authorial hands." A later and more personal portrait is offered by Joseph A. Califano Jr., who was Johnson's special assistant for domestic affairs, in THE TRIUMPH &amp; TRAGEDY OF LYNDON JOHNSON: The White House Years (Touchstone/Simon &amp; Schuster, $13). "What makes this memoir . . . stand out is its vividness," Laura Kalman said here last year. "Johnson leaps out of the pages in all his raw and earthy glory."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAKING HISTORY, by Carolyn See. (Laurel/Dell, $10.) Jerry Bridges, a California businessman, believes in technology's ability to perfect the world -- until human error and the randomness of fate intrude. In a story framed by two devastating accidents, his family drifts apart, then reconnects. "Ms. See sets out to catch the sound of our world singing its way into the future," Susan Fromberg Schaeffer said here last year. "The miracle is how well she has succeeded."</p>
        <p>LONE STAR RISING: Lyndon Johnson and His Times, 1908-1960, by Robert Dallek. (Oxford University, $16.95.) Former President Lyndon B. Johnson was a complicated man, guilty of both egotism and ethical lapses, yet deeply dedicated to making government an agent of social progress. In this biography, the first of two volumes, Robert Dallek has taken the position of "a seeker after truth rather than someone out to attack or defend," our reviewer, Nicholas Lemann, said last year. He added: "For better and for worse, Mr. Dallek is the rare present-day practitioner of the 'three yards and a cloud of dust' school of biography. He lays out the facts and allows the grand themes to emanate from them, relatively untouched by authorial hands." A later and more personal portrait is offered by Joseph A. Califano Jr., who was Johnson's special assistant for domestic affairs, in THE TRIUMPH &amp; TRAGEDY OF LYNDON JOHNSON: The White House Years (Touchstone/Simon &amp; Schuster, $13). "What makes this memoir . . . stand out is its vividness," Laura Kalman said here last year. "Johnson leaps out of the pages in all his raw and earthy glory."</p>
        <p>THE RUNAWAY SOUL, by Harold Brodkey. (Harper Perennial, $15.) This noted writer of short fiction turns to the past in his first novel, a middle-aged author's account of his attempts to understand the adoptive family that raised him. Last year our reviewer, D. M. Thomas, found the narrator's style often ponderous, the book "monstrous, ambitious, bold and puzzling."</p>
        <p>THE MYSTERIOUS HISTORY OF COLUMBUS: An Exploration of the Man, the Myth, the Legacy, by John Noble Wilford. (Vintage, $12.) Was Columbus a heroic adventurer or the first in a long line of European colonial oppressors? A science correspondent for The New York Times gives an overview of current scholarship. Although Columbus's character remains murky, this is a "lively, eminently readable account," Richard L. Kagan said here last year.</p>
        <p>CHINA BOY, by Gus Lee. (Signet, $5.99.) In this work of autobiographical fiction, a young Chinese-American boy learns how to use both his wits and his fists to survive on the streets of 1950's San Francisco. Last year our reviewer, Kiki Olson, called this a "hilariously poignant coming-of-age novel."</p>
        <p>BANDIT: Dossier of a Dangerous Dog, by Vicki Hearne. (Aaron Asher Books/Harper Perennial, $11.) An animal trainer and writer relates her efforts to save Bandit, "the only alleged pit bull to have gotten off death row in the pit bull wars." Her account "is not only a dog story but also a deeply eccentric lesson in justice, linguistics, racism and teleology," Sarah Boxer said in The Book Review last year.</p>
        <p>BLUE RIVER, by Ethan Canin. (Warner, $9.99.) Edward Sellers, a successful ophthalmologist, must confront his childhood when it literally arrives on his doorstep in the form of his rootless older brother, Lawrence. Last year our reviewer, Ginger Danto, found this novel "charged with such epic themes as love, death, separation and family ties." Ethan Canin, she said, "sprinkles them deftly throughout the story, like so many gems thrown into a river."</p>
        <p>FATES WORSE THAN DEATH: An Autobiographical Collage, by Kurt Vonnegut. (Berkley, $8.95.) In this collection of essays, memoirs and speeches, Kurt Vonnegut touches on such intimate issues as his experiences as a prisoner of war during World War II and his mother's and son's bouts with mental illness. " 'Fates Worse Than Death' is honest and scarily funny, and it offers a rare insight into an author who has customarily hidden his heart," Doug Anderson said here last year.</p>
        <p>THE SHADOW OF THE SHADOW, by Paco Ignacio Taibo 2d. Translated by William I. Neuman. (Penguin, $9.) Set in Mexico City in 1922, this thriller focuses on four friends -- a crime reporter, a poet, a lawyer and a union organizer -- who are drawn into a plot of international proportions. Last year our reviewer, Marilyn Stasio, described this novel as "spellbinding."</p>
        <p>NO SAFE PLACE: Toxic Waste, Leukemia, and Community Action, by Phil Brown and Edwin J. Mikkelsen. (University of California, $14.) This book chronicles the struggles of the citizens of Woburn, Mass., against the corporate giants Beatrice Foods and W. R. Grace, whom they hold responsible for the leakage of carcinogenic chemicals into the city's wells. Writing here in 1990, Andrew H. Malcolm found the authors' telling surprisingly lacking in drama, but added that many of their readers "will draw solace, learn of possible pitfalls and garner helpful organizational tips."</p>
        <p>THE ALMANAC BRANCH, by Bradford Morrow. (Norton, $8.95.) A young woman, subject to both migraines and hallucinations, tells the story of her family's dissolution after they move from the city to a farm in an effort to help heal her. Last year our reviewer, Howard Coale, found this novel tangled in its many story lines, although "from time to time it shines with a mysterious and ingenious beauty."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
