<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Honoring a Father, Through a Lens and a Love of Africa</title>
    <meta content="11kenya" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/11/world/africa/11kenya.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1760804"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Nairobi Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kenya</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Amin, Mohamed</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Amin, Idi</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDE173EF932A25756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Honoring a Father, Through a Lens and a Love of Africa</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Honoring a Father, Through a Lens and a Love of Africa</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC LACEY</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, May 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Salim Amin's desk is not just large, not just executive-size, but outright huge. He himself is a big man, but Mr. Amin could sprawl across this wooden beast and still not hang over the sides.</p>
        <p>It had been his late father's desk, and it matched him well. His father, Mohamed Amin, was larger than life, in his actions and his attitude, and for him nothing less than the grandest desk possible would do.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mo Amin was the preeminent African news photographer of his day. Now his son is celebrating Mr. Amin's life with the movie "Mo &amp; Me.&amp;#034;</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Salim Amin's desk is not just large, not just executive-size, but outright huge. He himself is a big man, but Mr. Amin could sprawl across this wooden beast and still not hang over the sides.</p>
        <p>It had been his late father's desk, and it matched him well. His father, Mohamed Amin, was larger than life, in his actions and his attitude, and for him nothing less than the grandest desk possible would do.</p>
        <p>When Salim Amin, 35, sits behind the desk these days, having followed in his father's footsteps as a Nairobi-based photojournalist and entrepreneur, he acknowledges that he sometimes feels he does not measure up. In fact, he has a recurring nightmare in which his father comes striding up to the desk -- striding is what Mohamed Amin did -- and chastises him for ruining the company he had worked so hard to build.</p>
        <p>That company, Camerapix, began in the early 1960's as Mohamed Amin's humble photography shop in Dar es Salaam in what was then Tanganyika, which merged with Zanzibar in 1964 to become Tanzania. After moving to Nairobi in 1966, Camerapix grew to become one of East Africa's most respected photojournalism outfits, a place the big news agencies in the West would call to get exclusive photographs or videotape of the news of the day from Africa.</p>
        <p>Needed some shots of Soviet military activity in Zanzibar? Or exclusive images of Idi Amin, the Ugandan dictator? Or mercenaries intent on toppling the president of Congo? Mo Amin was the one to call.</p>
        <p>Since Mohamed Amin's death in a plane crash in 1996, Camerapix has evolved, moving away from hard news and more into documentaries and corporate work. Its latest production is a documentary titled ''Mo &amp; Me'' about the company's founder and his son. (The film had its premiere in New York on May 9 and opens next week in Nairobi.)</p>
        <p>Directed by Roger Mills, the film features Salim Amin narrating his visits to some of the African trouble spots his father -- ''a man I idolized but hardly knew'' -- had photographed decades before.</p>
        <p>Mo Amin, the son of an Indian railway worker who settled in East Africa as a young man, saw the history of 20th-century Africa unfold before his lens. He was there -- inside the ambulance, actually -- in 1969 just after Tom Mboya, a major independence-era politician in Kenya, was assassinated. He was there in 1991 when rebel soldiers marched into the Ethiopian capital, having overthrown the dictatorship of Mengistu Haile Mariam.</p>
        <p>Mo Amin was there as well in 1984 when Ethiopians were starving en masse, producing poignant pictures that led to Live Aid and the outpouring of foreign assistance that kept so many Ethiopians alive.</p>
        <p>In the 95-minute film, which won an award for best international documentary at the New York International Independent Film and Video Festival held in Los Angeles earlier this year, Salim Amin went back to those scenes, and others.</p>
        <p>He visited the spot in Addis Ababa where his father had covered the explosion of an ammunition dump in 1991 and lost his arm in a follow-up blast. (An artificial arm was fashioned, and Mo Amin was soon back on the job.)</p>
        <p>Salim Amin also sat in a flight simulator with the very pilot who was flying the ill-fated Ethiopian Airways plane that Mo Amin was aboard when it plunged into the sea after being hijacked, killing 123 of the 175 people on board.</p>
        <p>Salim Amin remarks in the movie that his father was certainly not ready to go when he went but probably would have approved of his dramatic exit. In fact, Mo Amin was not sitting in his seat as hijackers were commandeering the plane. He was up, trying to negotiate with them.</p>
        <p>Mo Amin was all about capturing the unvarnished truth with his lens, and his son followed the same philosophy in the movie about Mo.</p>
        <p>''We decided to make it as true as we could,'' he said. ''I still idolize him. I still think he was a great person. But he wasn't a great father or husband. He had affairs and thought I was a waste of time. He was ruthless when it came to getting the story.''</p>
        <p>The elder Mr. Amin's outsize ego, his philandering and his neglect of his family all come across clearly in the film -- as well as his fiercely competitive nature when it came to news.</p>
        <p>When Idi Amin, to whom he was not related, seized power in Uganda, Mo Amin called the president's residence and managed to get clearance to enter the country when nobody else could. He did not exactly say he was a relative of the dictator but he did not discourage presidential aides from thinking it either.</p>
        <p>A promotional photograph for the movie shows Mo Amin as a young man, his face merged into a present-day shot of Salim, who has his father's piercing glare and goatee.</p>
        <p>Sons often become their fathers, whether they think about it or not, and that is the case here. Salim Amin, who, like his father, was born in Nairobi, began photographing in his preteen years, just as his famous father had done, earning early credits in local and national publications. He has morphed, just like Mo Amin, into a businessman, although he is regarded as a softie compared with his cutthroat father.</p>
        <p>Salim Amin is a father himself now, and he finds himself away from his children more than he would like. ''I understand now why he was not always there,'' he said. ''But even when he was here, he was working. I'm trying to do better.''</p>
        <p>In becoming the pre-eminent cameraman of his generation, Mo Amin marketed himself as an African eye who could capture Africa better than outsiders could. He had contacts in presidential mansions across the continent and could talk his way past soldiers and immigration agents alike. ''Africa has to be reported by Africans'' was one of his refrains. He surely would have approved of his son's next venture, a long-shot effort to bring an Africa-wide television station (à la Al Jazeera) to the continent.</p>
        <p>''I have no problem with people introducing me as Mohamed Amin's son,'' Salim Amin said the other day, in a darkened screening room at Camerapix, where images of his father flickered on the screen. ''That's who I am. That's who I'll always be.''</p>
        <p>Then a bit of the conniving father surfaced in the son. ''I get in doors that way,'' he said with a grin.</p>
        <p>Nairobi Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
