<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Won't Press China Over Yuan</title>
    <meta content="11china" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/11/washington/11china.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1760886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDC173EF932A25756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Won't Press China Over Yuan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Won't Press China Over Yuan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration said on Wednesday that although it was ''extremely dissatisfied'' with China's refusal to allow its currency to fluctuate more freely, it would not cite China as a currency manipulator and provoke a confrontation over the issue.</p>
        <p>The administration's announcement, made by Treasury Secretary John W. Snow in compliance with a 1988 law requiring semiannual appraisals of exchange rate issues, was attacked by an array of critics who say that China engages in unfair trade practices by keeping the value of its currency artificially low.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration said that it would not cite China as a currency manipulator and provoke a confrontation over the issue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush administration said on Wednesday that although it was ''extremely dissatisfied'' with China's refusal to allow its currency to fluctuate more freely, it would not cite China as a currency manipulator and provoke a confrontation over the issue.</p>
        <p>The administration's announcement, made by Treasury Secretary John W. Snow in compliance with a 1988 law requiring semiannual appraisals of exchange rate issues, was attacked by an array of critics who say that China engages in unfair trade practices by keeping the value of its currency artificially low.</p>
        <p>Among the critics were Republican and Democratic senators, the A.F.L.-C.I.O. and various manufacturing trade associations. All said the administration seemed reluctant to take on an issue that had become a major focus of debate in this election year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Snow said that despite dissatisfaction with the Chinese record on the issue, the administration had little latitude because China had made at least a small amount of progress on letting its currency, the yuan, float in open markets in the last year.</p>
        <p>He said the law required that China be found to have the intention of manipulating its currency to encourage exports and protect the value of its dollar assets. But he added that the record showed that China was trying to cooperate with the United States and had allowed the value of its currency to appreciate.</p>
        <p>Critics of China's currency policy say that by holding down the yuan's value, China is deliberately pursuing a policy that makes its exports more competitive on global markets and contributes to its huge trade imbalance with the United States.</p>
        <p>''The test in the '88 act ultimately comes down to intent,'' said Mr. Snow, adding that only last month the Chinese leader, Hu Jintao, pledged at his White House visit to ''increase the flexibility of the exchange rate'' and expand imports and market access for foreign investments.</p>
        <p>''China has indicated the intent to address imbalances,'' Mr. Snow said.</p>
        <p>Critics in Congress argue, on the other hand, that although China's progress in currency flexibility has been so small as to have negligible impact. The value of the yuan has risen about 3 percent against the dollar in the last year or so, Mr. Snow said.</p>
        <p>The administration's approach appeared to be a mixture of a tight reading of the law mixed with a sense of tactics, namely that a confrontation with China might backfire, especially at a time when the administration is unhappy with Beijing on a range of other issues.</p>
        <p>Other matters of contention with China include American criticism of its suppression of dissent, its military buildup, its failure to crack down on piracy of videos and high technology property, and its unwillingness to join the United States in a tough policy toward North Korea and Iran over their nuclear programs.</p>
        <p>American officials say they have had to balance toughness on these issues with flexibility and caution, because of China's leverage, including the hundreds of billions of dollars of United States debt that China holds.</p>
        <p>Many economic specialists say China has indeed been manipulating its currency to gain an advantage on trade and investment. But the debate over what to do about it is lively.</p>
        <p>Senators Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, and Lindsey Graham, Republican of South Carolina, have been demanding that China be pressed harder on currency, and they have a bill calling for tariffs Chinese exports if the country refuses. Both denounced Mr. Snow's decision on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The administration adamantly opposes their bill, but many experts say the administration also finds it useful to cite the bill as a reason China must act.</p>
        <p>''Frankly the administration likes us playing our role so it can play the other role,'' Mr. Schumer said, adding that the administration seemed more interested in working with China on other issues and not letting the currency and trade issues undermine the chances of cooperation on matters including Iran and North Korea.</p>
        <p>''I think they put economic issues at a much lower priority than geopolitical issues,'' he said of the administration. ''Most Americans would not have the same priorities.''</p>
        <p>Criticism of the administration also came from two prominent Republican senators, Olympia J. Snowe of Maine and Charles E. Grassley of Iowa, who is chairman of the Finance Committee.</p>
        <p>''China just isn't living up to its obligations as a mature economy that's benefiting greatly from open international trade,'' said Mr. Grassley, whose committee has jurisdiction over the issue. ''The country has made some reforms, but it isn't even letting those reforms work freely.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grassley called for scrapping the 1988 law under which Mr. Snow issued his report on Wednesday, saying that even if the Treasury secretary had found China to be a currency ''manipulator,'' the law called for intense talks with the Chinese and nothing else.</p>
        <p>''The next step would've been to talk more,'' Mr. Grassley said, ''and we're already talking.''</p>
        <p>A senior Treasury official, briefing reporters after Mr. Snow's announcement, said he agreed that the 1988 law might no longer be the right instrument to deal with currency imbalances, but he declined to endorse Mr. Grassley's proposal for a new law that would overhaul supervision of the currency issues.</p>
        <p>For example, the word ''manipulator'' was not defined in any economic textbook he has read, the official said, gesturing to his book shelf. He briefed under ground rules requiring that he be anonymous in order to keep the focus on Mr. Snow's words.</p>
        <p>He said that the administration instead should work more intensively with the International Monetary Fund to deal with currency problems with different countries, since the I.M.F. could serve as a more trusted and objective interlocutor.</p>
        <p>Treasury officials said that with Mr. Snow's finding, the issue would probably continue to grow in importance.</p>
        <p>They said they worried that Congress might be tempted to erect import barriers, but that since the economy has been growing the impulse for protectionism might diminish.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
