<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Envisioning a New Playground, With the Swing Sets</title>
    <meta content="16ctplaynj" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1776292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="RECREATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playgrounds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bridgeport (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">KaBoom! (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salzman, Avi</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E4DB1E30F935A25754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Envisioning a New Playground, With the Swing Sets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AVI SALZMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salzman, Avi</byline>
      <dateline>Bridgeport, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Children and parents at Kolbe Education Early Care and Learning Center in Bridgeport, Conn, offer their input for design of new playground; KaBoom!, nonprofit organization in Chicago, joins with donors to help communities build playgrounds; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF Terence Teasley could design a playground, he would build a roller coaster, with steep drops that could send him hurtling through loop-de-loops. Unfortunately for Terence, a 5-year-old at the Kolbe Education Early Care and Learning Center in Bridgeport, a roller coaster in a playground is, well, ahead of its time.</p>
        <p>Although some of their most creative ideas did not make it, the children at the school and their parents were given the chance earlier this month to design a dream playground. The charitable foundation of Diana Taurasi, the former University of Connecticut basketball star, is helping to finance the playground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF Terence Teasley could design a playground, he would build a roller coaster, with steep drops that could send him hurtling through loop-de-loops. Unfortunately for Terence, a 5-year-old at the Kolbe Education Early Care and Learning Center in Bridgeport, a roller coaster in a playground is, well, ahead of its time.</p>
        <p>Although some of their most creative ideas did not make it, the children at the school and their parents were given the chance earlier this month to design a dream playground. The charitable foundation of Diana Taurasi, the former University of Connecticut basketball star, is helping to finance the playground.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taurasi was stuck in traffic last week when she was scheduled to be at the school talking about playgrounds. A large ''Welcome Diana'' banner came down after she was unable to make it, but the children kept drawing. Ms. Taurasi would probably be happy with the results -- a basketball hoop made it into the proposed design. Also included were slides, a balance beam, a climbing tunnel, a bike track, picnic tables and a generous amount of landscaping.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taurasi, who graduated from UConn in 2004, is playing for the Phoenix Mercury of the Women's National Basketball Association and was in the area last week for a game against the Liberty and for the league's All-Star Game at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>The Bridgeport day care center, which is run by the Y.M.C.A. on the city's poor east side and receives much of its financing from the state's School Readiness Program for poor children, already has a playground, but the rubber-surfaced play space is small.</p>
        <p>School administrators applied to KaBoom!, a nonprofit organization in Chicago, to help them build a new playground. KaBoom! joins with donors to help communities build playgrounds, allowing children and parents to contribute ideas and drawings to the design. Ms. Taurasi, who did not return messages seeking comment last week, agreed to help pay for it. The school will have to find volunteers to build the playground this fall. Following KaBoom's guidelines, they plan to build it in one day as a community project.</p>
        <p>It takes a powerful imagination to imagine a new playground at the school. The two potential sites are blighted vacant lots surrounded by more vacant lots, abandoned buildings and industrial businesses.</p>
        <p>''This is quite a 'before' picture,'' said Timothy J. Bartlett, the executive director of the Bridgeport Y.M.C.A., looking out over one of the sites.</p>
        <p>But the children, who gathered at the school on July 7 to draw their designs, came up with visions for the playground. Many of them drew pools and trampolines, and one child even drew a wall to keep outsiders from stealing the toys.</p>
        <p>Those ideas didn't make it, but teachers at the school said they were heartened by designs that included plants and flowers, and benches for adults. The design will now be sent to KaBoom!, which will refine it and then send it to suppliers.</p>
        <p>The teachers had to bow to the children on at least one point: the adults wanted something more creative than swing sets, but the children demanded them.</p>
        <p>''They really, really, really wanted the swings,'' said Kristy Ruscoe, the site coordinator who runs the school.</p>
        <p>RECREATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
