<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Maximum Nice</title>
    <meta content="26DINE$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1459812"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Panico's (New Brunswick, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Karla</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5D71E30F935A15752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Maximum Nice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARLA COOK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cook, Karla</byline>
      <dateline>NEW BRUNSWICK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karla Cook reviews Panico's restaurant in New Brunswick, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you've been feeling low and surly because of the cold, take yourself to Panico's. There, you will notice in the mirrored walls that you look terrific against the peach-toned décor. The staff will coddle you and murmur approvingly as you order. As you sip the vivid red pepper and chanterelle bisque that could be summer in a spoon, luxuriate in bite after bite of tender, sea-fresh shrimp, squid, scallops and crab salad dressed in a red wine and olive oil and have the rest of your tender, flavorful osso buco wrapped to go so you'll have room for the pear-ginger cobbler with buttermilk gelato, you will agree: You are a delightful person. And warm weather will come.</p>
        <p>Those are nice messages from a restaurant. They come both from the staff and from Gregg Freda's satisfying blends of traditional and luxurious ingredients at this fine Italian restaurant, which turns 16 this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you've been feeling low and surly because of the cold, take yourself to Panico's. There, you will notice in the mirrored walls that you look terrific against the peach-toned décor. The staff will coddle you and murmur approvingly as you order. As you sip the vivid red pepper and chanterelle bisque that could be summer in a spoon, luxuriate in bite after bite of tender, sea-fresh shrimp, squid, scallops and crab salad dressed in a red wine and olive oil and have the rest of your tender, flavorful osso buco wrapped to go so you'll have room for the pear-ginger cobbler with buttermilk gelato, you will agree: You are a delightful person. And warm weather will come.</p>
        <p>Those are nice messages from a restaurant. They come both from the staff and from Gregg Freda's satisfying blends of traditional and luxurious ingredients at this fine Italian restaurant, which turns 16 this year.</p>
        <p>Like most chefs of upscale restaurants, Mr. Freda, 41, is passionate about fresh ingredients and to-order preparation. His family owned a butcher shop and he learned to cook from his mother and grandmother while growing up in Verona, N.J. He learned about produce, bakery and prepared foods while working at an affluent supermarket and then worked at a butcher/catering shop, where he learned to make mozzarella and other Italian specialties. When his uncle's restaurant, Panico's, needed a sous chef a year after opening, Mr. Freda stepped up. In 1997, he was named executive chef.</p>
        <p>Inside the restaurant, room dividers keep the cold from slipping toward the bar and along to the dining room. If cozy comfort is what you want, aim for a table pulled close to a booth and you'll feel the urge to linger rather than remove yourself from what must be some of the hardest dining room chairs in central New Jersey. Likewise, try to position yourself near a pool of light; between the fancy typography and the low light, the menu is hard to read.</p>
        <p>The menu lists antipasti, pasta and entrees sequentially. Though the menu doesn't say so, half-orders of pastas are available. That's a good thing; portions are too generous, and much of the food is bold and strongly flavored, very rich with cream and cheese, truffles, gourmet mushrooms and premium vegetables.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Freda's menu is weighted toward maximization. Belgian endive is sunk deep in a dish of fontina cheese, cream, Parmigiano-Reggiano, black truffles and pieces of prosciutto and then baked until each bite of the mildly bitter endive is nearly lost. A frying pepper stuffed with shrimp, zucchini and rice is likewise buried and baked beneath a fruity sauce, which obscures the discrete elements of this otherwise well-conceived appetizer. Even the carpaccio dressed with extra-virgin olive oil, lemon, mushrooms and Parmigiano-Reggiano should be thinner.</p>
        <p>The grilled squid, beautifully tender teepees of sweet meat laid over a smattering of greens, are brightened with an inspired lemon-coriander vinaigrette, but the dressing is marred by countless bits of coriander husk that function much like popcorn hulls between the teeth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freda lightens his touch for the pasta course. The risotto, which he says usually contains chicken, shrimp or fresh tuna, is expertly prepared and highly flavorful, though some compilations are more beguiling than others. Another real winner is the square-cut pasta strands with shrimp and clams, white wine, garlic, lemon, anchovy and rosemary -- each strand separate and slightly firm to the bite, the anchovy adding a pleasing salty complexity to what otherwise would be a light, bright sauce. The pumpkin ravioli is a masterly executed classic -- richly filled orbs of tender house-made pasta in a splash of brown butter flavored with fresh sage.</p>
        <p>Entrees also range from excellent to very good. The pan-seared turbot with artichoke hearts, fava beans and shiitakes is a pleasing combination, and the red pepper sauce, though not spicy as advertised in the menu, pulled the dish into a satisfying whole. The osso buco, braised in a sauce of the day but generally served with orzo instead of the more traditional risotto, rises and falls, like Mr. Freda's risotto, on its sauce.</p>
        <p>The fresh fish, which changes depending on availability, is reliably tender and finely cooked, though the tableside boning, with so little maneuvering space for staff, seems unnecessary. I watched one server wheel out a portable cooking station, expertly bone a branzino, heat a dinner plate over a blue flame and transfer the fish to plate. The only catch was that it wasn't my fish on a dish. It was for another table, and those diners were oblivious.</p>
        <p>Halibut wrapped in bacon, a special one night, was particularly successful. The bacon, though not crisped beneath the fish, worked its fatty flavoring magic on this otherwise low-fat, mildly flavored fish, making each bite interesting. The bacon trick was less successful with a veal chop, which already has plenty of flavor. A grilled filet served with a side of eye-rollingly delicious cipollini and shiitake mushrooms suffered from overgrilling and a thick gorgonzola-potato crust. Thin slices of veal, sautéed and then topped with slices of prosciutto di Parma, also received a layering of fontina cheese and Marsala-tomato sauce. The fresh flavor of rare sushi-grade tuna, with appealing sides of grilled fennel and roast tomatoes, would stand better with a much thinner crust of fennel seeds.</p>
        <p>The dessert list is short and refreshingly -- not cloyingly -- sweet. In addition to the homey cobbler, with its crisp crust covering slices of Bartlett pear flavored with fresh and dried ginger, there is a warm banana financier, a kind of moist single-serving cake served with caramel sauce, vanilla gelato and a dusting of crushed pecan praline. It's just right, indulgence without extravagance. Other worthwhile choices include a tiramisù with a mocha mascarpone sauce, house-made gelati and sorbets, and an exceedingly rich chocolate truffle dressed with raspberry coulis plus pistachio gelato, crème anglaise and fresh raspberries.</p>
        <p>Panico's takes it to the max; restraint would lift it higher.</p>
        <p>Panico's  103 Church Street, New Brunswick  (732) 545-6100</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Convivial buzz and bustle on weekends, glass-polishing near closing time on weeknights.</p>
        <p>SERVICE -- Coddling and sometimes anticipatory.</p>
        <p>SMOKING -- One nonsmoking section is subject to drifting smoke from the smoking section.</p>
        <p>WINE LIST -- An interesting yet pricey selection of Italian reds and whites.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Yellow or red sweet pepper soup with chanterelle mushrooms, grilled calamari, sweet sausage with escarole and cannelini, seafood salad, square-cut pasta with seafood, pumpkin ravioli, osso buco, veal chop, halibut in bacon, turbot with fava beans and artichoke hearts, tiramisù, pear-ginger cobbler, banana financier.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers, $10.50 to $16.50; pastas, $14.50 to $26.50 with risotto $22 to $24 (half orders, for half the price plus $1); entrees, $23.50 to $32.50; specials, $28 to $32; desserts, $9 to $10.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Lunch, Monday through Friday, 11:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m.; dinner, Monday through Thursday, 5:30 p.m. to 10; Friday and Saturday, 5:30 p.m. to 11.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- All major.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Restaurant and restrooms are on the same level.</p>
        <p>RATINGS -- Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
