<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Injured Gorgeous to Miss Breeders' Cup Distaff</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="395835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="BREEDERS' CUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THOROUGHBRED RACING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BELMONT PARK (NY)</location>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BREEDERS CUP</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD1F3CF934A15753C1A966958260" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Injured Gorgeous to Miss Breeders' Cup Distaff</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN CRIST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gorgeous, the 4-year-old filly who was set to challenge Go for Wand and Bayakoa in the best race today on the Breeders' Cup card at Belmont Park, was officially scratched from the $1 million Distaff after X-rays revealed a bone chip in her left foreleg yesterday.</p>
        <p>Gorgeous, who was second to Bayakoa in last year's Distaff, was rated the third choice this year behind that rival and Go for Wand. The Distaff was to be the final career start for Gorgeous, who will now be retired to Robert Clay's Three Chimneys Farm near Midway, Ky. She won 8 of 14 career starts and earned $1,171,370.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gorgeous, the 4-year-old filly who was set to challenge Go for Wand and Bayakoa in the best race today on the Breeders' Cup card at Belmont Park, was officially scratched from the $1 million Distaff after X-rays revealed a bone chip in her left foreleg yesterday.</p>
        <p>Gorgeous, who was second to Bayakoa in last year's Distaff, was rated the third choice this year behind that rival and Go for Wand. The Distaff was to be the final career start for Gorgeous, who will now be retired to Robert Clay's Three Chimneys Farm near Midway, Ky. She won 8 of 14 career starts and earned $1,171,370.</p>
        <p>Gorgeous was the only defection among the 87 runners from around the world who are set to race for $10 million in today's seven cup races, which will be televised nationally by NBC between 1:30 and 6 P.M.</p>
        <p>The Distaff remains the most compelling showdown of this seventh Breeders' Cup, which is being held at Belmont for the first time but has a nostalgic feel.  Brisk and Nippy Outings</p>
        <p>Until the Breeders' Cup became racing's definitive day of championships in 1984, the sport's titles were settled at Belmont on brisk and nippy fall afternoons like the one being forecast for today. Races such as the Champagne for 2-year-olds, the Beldame for fillies and the Jockey Club Gold Cup drew the nation's top runners and settled the questions of quality raised by the previous nine months of racing.</p>
        <p>Those races remain important fixtures on the American racing calendar and well worth winning, but they have also become mere preps for the cup races.</p>
        <p>This year's races may well not decide the sport's premier title. Criminal Type was the nation's dominant race horse this spring and summer, winning major handicap races from coast to coast and beating the champions Sunday Silence and Easy Goer. Criminal Type, however, joined those two on the sidelines last month when he was flown home wearing a cast. The Safer Route</p>
        <p>The only way he will not be awarded the Horse of the Year title is if Go for Wand posts a particularly impressive victory over Bayakoa in the Distaff, and the award voters then overlook the fact that she has not raced against males this year. Go for Wand's handlers opted for a safer spot by entering her in the Distaff instead of the $3 million Classic, a decision that will cost her many votes even if she wins today.</p>
        <p>The Classic, usually the crowning race of the day, now is one that might not determine a single championship. It is, however, an unusually competitive race to handicap and to bet, with most of the starters figuring to have a legitimate chance. The prime contenders are Flying Continental, De Roche and Izvestia, who crossed the wire in that order in the Jockey Club Gold Cup three weeks ago; Dispersal and Rhythm, who were first and third in the Woodward on Sept. 15; Unbridled, the Kentucky Derby winner, and Go and Go, the Belmont Stakes winner.  Magnified Appeal</p>
        <p>The most important races looking ahead to next year are the $1 million Juvenile for colts and the $1 million Juvenile Fillies. Fly So Free, the Champagne winner, and Best Pal, California's top 2-year-old, meet in a classic East-West showdown that will decide the early favorite for next year's Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>The best 2-year-old of either sex, though, just might be Meadow Star, the undefeated daughter of Meadowlake, who has looked better in each of her six easy triumphs. She may well be pointed to run against colts next spring in the Triple Crown, and her appeal has been magnified by her owner's decision to donate all of her future earnings to the Children's Rescue Fund, a charity that aids homeless children.</p>
        <p>Criminal Type and Go for Wand have locked up their divisions' titles, but just about every other championship will be settled in the space of four hours this afternoon. What Belmont Park once was, it is again today.</p>
        <p>BREEDERS' CUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
