<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vote Near on Deficit Plan, $10 Billion Shy of Goal</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="395889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE IN CONGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED71F3EF934A15753C1A966958260" item-length="1212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vote Near on Deficit Plan, $10 Billion Shy of Goal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As they approached final votes on a huge tax and spending plan that would affect nearly all Americans, lawmakers found today that the final negotiations had left them $10 billion short of their goal of reducing the Federal deficit by $500 billion over the next five years.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, at midnight they were pressing ahead to finish the bill, with votes scheduled in the House early Saturday and in the Senate later in the day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As they approached final votes on a huge tax and spending plan that would affect nearly all Americans, lawmakers found today that the final negotiations had left them $10 billion short of their goal of reducing the Federal deficit by $500 billion over the next five years.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, at midnight they were pressing ahead to finish the bill, with votes scheduled in the House early Saturday and in the Senate later in the day.</p>
        <p>"It's $490 billion," said Representative Leon E. Panetta, the California Democrat who heads the House Budget Committee. "I think that's not a bad package, quite frankly. It's all real deficit reduction, not phony."</p>
        <p>The push for passage was developing in a strange partisan atmosphere. President Bush, though relying on Democratic votes for approval of the plan, issued a broadside against Democrats in a campaign appearance. And many Democrats who planned to vote for the measure were taking pains to emphasize what they saw as its flaws. Criticism of 'Binge'</p>
        <p>In Orange County, Calif., where he was campaigning for Republican candidates, President Bush said, "The agreement that we get won't be the best deal possible, but in my judgment, it will be the best deal possible with this Congress."</p>
        <p>Despite saying that "we must get an agreement to start getting these deficits under control," the President attacked Democrats for having been on "an uncontrolled spending binge for years."</p>
        <p>And when John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff, arrived at the Capitol for a meeting with Republican Congressional leaders and spoke to reporters, he accused Democrats of wanting taxes to be too high.</p>
        <p>Party whips spent the day trying to round up votes, but this evening they were not sure they had enough in the House. Several recalcitrant House Democrats whose votes might have been available in a pinch backed off after the partisan attacks from the White House.</p>
        <p>Most of the 23 black Democratic Representatives said they would vote against the package, in part to protest Mr. Bush's veto of this year's main civil rights bill. The Senate failed by one vote this week to override the veto.</p>
        <p>A large majority of Democratic votes for the budget package was essential in the House because fewer than a third of the Republicans were expected to support the measure.</p>
        <p>The final tax provisions were written by Senator Lloyd Bentsen of Texas, the Democratic chairman of the Finance Committee, and Representative Dan Rostenkowski, Democrat of Illinois, who heads the Ways and Means Committee, in a one-on-one meeting that Thursday night that was not wrapped up until about 3 this morning.</p>
        <p>The provisions would result in a tax increase of more than 6 percent for people with taxable incomes of more than $200,000, a tax cut for those with incomes less than $20,000 and an higher tax bite in the neighborhood of 2 percent for those in between.</p>
        <p>Largely because Mr. Rostenkowski insisted that state and local employees not be subject to the Medicare payroll tax, and because Mr. Bentsen insisted on tax breaks for oil and gas producers and for other industries, the two Democrats came up $10 billion short of their goal of raising $147 billion in taxes over five years.</p>
        <p>That was the main reason the entire measure fell short of the $500 billion goal. Spending cuts and lower interest payments would make up the rest of the reduction.</p>
        <p>The first year's deficit cut is still expected to be about $40 billion, officials said.</p>
        <p>One provision that remained in the final package would, in 1991 only, exempt the appreciated value of donated art works and manuscripts from the alternative minimum tax. The sponsor was Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Democrat of New York, who had hoped it would become a permanent feature of the tax law.</p>
        <p>What this means, for example, is that an art collector would be able to take a charitable deduction for the full value of a $1 million painting donated to a museum, even if the collector had paid only $100,000 for the painting many years ago.  Elements of Final Package</p>
        <p>These were the central elements of the final package:</p>
        <p>*The top tax rate would be 31 percent, up from 28 percent now, on taxable income above about $80,000 for couples filing jointly.</p>
        <p>*Two provisions would push the tax rate of the wealthy above 31 percent on a portion of their income, although no taxpayers would pay more than 31 percent of their total income in taxes. Under one provision, itemized deductions would be lowered by 3 percent of all income above $100,000, meaning that taxpayers with incomes that large would pay at least 31.9 percent on the top portion of their income. Under the other provision, personal exemptions would be phased out for single taxpayers with taxable incomes from $100,000 to $225,000 and for couples with incomes between $150,000 and $275,000. That would have the effect of raising the rate by one half of one percentage point for each exemption for income within the range.</p>
        <p>*The alternative minimum tax would increase to 24 percent from 21 percent now. This is the rate paid by high-income taxpayers who have unusually large deductions.</p>
        <p>*The top capital gains tax rate would be 28 percent, even for the high-income taxpayers who would be paying more than 31 percent on a portion of their income.</p>
        <p>*The gasoline tax would rise 5 cents a gallon above the current 9 cents.</p>
        <p>*The amount of wages subject to the Medicare payroll tax would rise to $125,000 from $51,300 now. Employers and employees each pay 1.45 percent.</p>
        <p>*A 10 percent luxury tax would be imposed on cars costing more than $30,000, boats costing more than $100,000, private planes costing more than $250,000 and jewelry and furs costing more than $10,000.</p>
        <p>*The 16-cents-a-pack tax on cigarettes would increase 4 cents next year and 4 cents more in 1993.</p>
        <p>*The tax on beer would double to 32 cents a six-pack, the tax on wine would rise to 24 cents a gallon, up from 3 cents, and the tax on a gallon of 100-proof spirits would increase to $13.50 from $12.50.</p>
        <p>*Medicare payments would be cut $43 billion over the next five years from what would otherwise be spent. Most of the money would be saved by paying less to doctors and hospitals. But the elderly would be required to pay the first $100 of doctors' bills each year, up from $75 now. The monthly premium charged the elderly for coverage against doctors' bills, now $28.60, would rise over five years to $46.20 to reflect the increasing cost of medical care.</p>
        <p>*Price support payments to farmers would be cut 25 percent.</p>
        <p>*The first comprehensive Federal child-care program would be established, providing direct grants to states and $18.2 billion in tax credits to low-income working parents. Returning Bush's Fire</p>
        <p>At a lunch with reporters today, the Speaker of the House, Thomas S. Foley of Washington, took issue with the White House and many commentators who have accused Congress of dragging its feet on the budget.</p>
        <p>"I admit it is not as tidy as possible," the Speaker said. "But I think that the Congress is being denied the credit it should have for having undertaken to pass a difficult -- even a politically antagonistic -- important turnaround in our nation's fiscal policy in the face of an election."  THE STRUGGLE IN CONGRESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
