<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woodstock Meets the 90's; Two Days of Peace, Music and Interactive Video</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="691940"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOODSTOCK MUSIC AND ARTS FAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BETHEL (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINBERG, JACQUES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAVENS, RICHIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E6DD173AF935A35755C0A962958260" item-length="1373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woodstock Meets the 90's; Two Days of Peace, Music and Interactive Video</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEINBERG, JACQUES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 25 years, it has come to this: the festival commemorating Woodstock this summer in Saugerties, N.Y., will be broadcast live on pay-per-view television, just like Wrestlemania II, championship boxing and Howard Stern's New Year's Eve Party.</p>
        <p>And that is only one telling difference between the definitive countercultural event of the late 1960's and the attempt by the original organizers, now paired with a $4 billion entertainment company, to rekindle its spirit for another generation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After 25 years, it has come to this: the festival commemorating Woodstock this summer in Saugerties, N.Y., will be broadcast live on pay-per-view television, just like Wrestlemania II, championship boxing and Howard Stern's New Year's Eve Party.</p>
        <p>And that is only one telling difference between the definitive countercultural event of the late 1960's and the attempt by the original organizers, now paired with a $4 billion entertainment company, to rekindle its spirit for another generation.</p>
        <p>Like it or not, Woodstock is getting a facelift for the 90's.</p>
        <p>While the original Woodstock is remembered, at least in popular lore, as a communal mud bath that symbolized peace, love and free expression, this Woodstock is shaping up as a meticulously orchestrated, more commercial affair, with admission arranged by Ticketmaster and hamburgers dispensed by a stadium concessionaire.</p>
        <p>Consider that this time around, tickets to the two-day rock-music festival will sell for $135, which is $135 more than what most people paid to attend the original. In addition to two stages that will blare music continuously, this Woodstock -- known as Woodstock '94 -- will feature an interactive video theme park, where concertgoers will sample the latest advances in virtual reality. As for virtual unreality, the use of alcohol and drugs will be prohibited, although how strictly remains to be seen.</p>
        <p>"It sounds like they're putting on Las Vegas in upstate New York, for those who can afford it," said Todd Gitlin, author of "The Sixties: Years of Hope, Days of Rage."</p>
        <p>"It's unlikely that anyone will get pregnant as a result," he said, "or look back 20 years from now with gooey nostalgia for the glory days when they felt the full flush of their youth and tasted the infinite possibilities of being."</p>
        <p>And don't expect to see Richie Havens there either. Mr. Havens, the folk guitarist whose song "Freedom" mesmerized the first Woodstock, intends to be performing 50 miles away at the original site, Max Yasgur's farm in Bethel, where a more modest gathering is planned.</p>
        <p>"I have to be where the field is," said Mr. Havens, now 53. "What I went to back then has nothing to do with what Michael Lang" -- one of the original organizers -- "is putting together now."</p>
        <p>For the record, Mr. Lang and the concert's other promoters say they are not trying to recreate history on Aug. 13 and 14. And if their production sounds slick, they add, that is the reality of staging a festival in 1994 for a projected audience of 250,000 young people.</p>
        <p>The organizers contend that the current crop of teen-agers and 20-somethings are hungry for a shared experience that could do for them what Woodstock did for many of their parents. And the organizers should know; they have market research gleaned from focus groups.</p>
        <p>Why, the promoters reason, can't AIDS, homelessness and the environment galvanize this generation the way theirs was stirred by the Vietnam War, the civil rights movement and a desire to tweak authority? And what better place for this to happen than at a musical extravaganza set against the rural backdrop of upstate New York?</p>
        <p>"This generation has to focus on these concerns," said Mr. Lang, who is 49 but retains a youthful thatch of curly brown hair. "To use this opportunity as a vehicle to re-energize the spirit of Woodstock is, I think, what we're all trying to do."</p>
        <p>Implicit in Mr. Lang's comments, however, is that he is 25 years older this time around, planning a concert not for his peers but for people young enough to be his children. What remains to be seen, since tickets have yet to go sale, is whether they will hand over $135 each to spend the weekend with him. Yasgur's Farm Stand-In</p>
        <p>To be sure, there will be similarities between the two festivals. Crosby, Stills and Nash have agreed to be among the 30 or so acts that will play at this Woodstock, just as they did 25 years ago. And Wavy Gravy -- a founder of the Hog Farm Commune who helped soothe people at Woodstock who "freaked out" on LSD -- will be back too, this time making offbeat announcements over the public address system.</p>
        <p>The promoters were unable to reach agreement with Bethel officials to return to Yasgur's Farm. But they feel they have found a comparable substitute in Saugerties: an 840-acre dairy farm dotted with shagbark hickory trees just off the Gov. Thomas E. Dewey Thruway, about 100 miles north of New York City. (In 1994, as in 1969, the town of Woodstock itself has lent its name but little else.)</p>
        <p>Like its predecessor, the new field is in the shadow of the Catskills. And this time, as last, concertgoers will be encouraged to sleep under the stars.</p>
        <p>The presence of David Crosby notwithstanding, however, this Woodstock will have a decidedly different sound. Although the complete musical lineup is a closely guarded secret, few of the surviving original acts have been invited back, said industry executives who insisted on anonymity.</p>
        <p>Instead, the executives said, the concert will be headlined by an eclectic collection of bands that came of age after Woodstock, including Aerosmith, the powerhouse of 1970's rock that remains popular today; the Spin Doctors and Red Hot Chili Peppers, relative newcomers that combine funk and rock; Peter Gabriel, the longtime British solo artist, and Cypress Hill, a rap group. Jettisoned, apparently, are such Woodstock fixtures as Sha Na Na, Country Joe and the Fish, and Sly and the Family Stone.</p>
        <p>Lost in the lore surrounding the first Woodstock is the fact that it was intended to be a money-making venture, a $3 million production that was to cost each concertgoer $18 for three days. But the organizers were so unprepared for the crowd that showed up -- estimates ranged from 400,000 to 600,000 -- that almost all were admitted free.  Licensed T-Shirts</p>
        <p>Steeped in debt, the festival did not turn a profit for its organizers until about 15 years later, Mr. Lang said. To make sure that does not happen again, the original promoters, known collectively as Woodstock Ventures, have allied with the entertainment company Polygram, which is providing an estimated $19.5 million in backing for a concert that will cost about $30 million to stage.</p>
        <p>The promoters hope to recoup those costs through ticket sales (250,000 will be sold, all in advance, by Ticketmaster), pay-per-view (a price of about $50 per home for the weekend) and, in another sign of the times, licensed Woodstock T-shirts. Like last time, a concert movie and album are planned.</p>
        <p>Unlike its predecessor -- which was plagued by 20-mile traffic jams, insufficient parking and shortages of food and water -- this Woodstock is being planned with the precision of a military assault. Even the farm's mosquito population is being measured to determine if pre-emptive pesticide sprays are needed.</p>
        <p>Those who abandoned their cars in the road and walked miles to the last Woodstock, take note: your successors will travel to Woodstock '94 in relative luxury, on 800 shuttle buses leaving from 17 parking lots throughout the Hudson Valley. Once they get to Saugerties, concertgoers will be shepherded by a detail of 900 to 1,300 security guards.</p>
        <p>The makeshift food service at the last Woodstock was so overwhelmed by the crowd that some hungry concertgoers plucked vegetables from neighboring farms. Not this time, the promoters say. Hamburgers and hot dogs, as well as vegetarian fare, will be sold through a stadium vendor, Fine Host, at six festival marketplaces. Minds Made Up</p>
        <p>Will such elaborate planning be rewarded? The promoters will have a better idea when tickets go on sale later this month.</p>
        <p>But Daniel Eisenberg, 24, a fan of many of the bands that will be playing at this Woodstock, said he and his friends have already made up their minds. They don't plan to attend, largely because of the $135 ticket price.</p>
        <p>"To couch a two-day rock festival in some sort of ambitious political terms is either naive or just marketing," said Mr. Eisenberg, a fact checker at Vanity Fair magazine in Manhattan. "I don't feel like I'm going to miss out on some seminal moment for my generation."</p>
        <p>"I'm more apt to go down to CBGB on the Bowery to hear some music than to trek up to upstate New York," he added.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
