<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Look of a Winner Helps Dukakis Reap Support</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="148734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDORSEMENTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKE, RICHARD L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D7113AF935A15756C0A96E948260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Look of a Winner Helps Dukakis Reap Support</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKE, RICHARD L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Michael S. Dukakis today won the high level of praise here that is usually reserved for veteran Capitol Hill legislators, not outsiders from New England.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Michael S. Dukakis today won the high level of praise here that is usually reserved for veteran Capitol Hill legislators, not outsiders from New England.</p>
        <p>Michael S. Dukakis today won the high level of praise here that is usually reserved for veteran Capitol Hill legislators, not outsiders from New England.</p>
        <p>But now that the Massachusetts Governor is within grasp of the Democratic Presidential nomination, the endorsements and compliments are flowing more freely.</p>
        <p>Today the campaign announced endorsements from six Senators, bringing the total to 27, and from 17 House members, for a total of 81.</p>
        <p>At three news conferences wedged between private meetings at the Capitol, members of Congress paraded out to say nice things about a man who has never held office outside Massachusetts. 'Time to Endorse'</p>
        <p>''I decided when I saw the polls this morning it was time to endorse,'' joked Senator Dale Bumpers of Arkansas.</p>
        <p>After a private session, Senator Timothy E. Wirth of Colorado, said time constraints and the public nature of events today made it difficult for any substantive give-and-take to occur between Mr. Dukakis and the legislators.</p>
        <p>''It's a road show,'' remarked Mr. Wirth, who had endorsed the Governor before today.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Dukakis said the get-acquainted meetings and in past weeks were valuable for him to learn about issues before Congress, not to mention that they were politically helpful.</p>
        <p>''We can't go to the White House and order Congress to 'make my day,' '' Mr. Dukakis told a group of Senators. He said making contacts on Capitol Hill was a ''very, very important part of a campaign and a very, very important part of a winning Administration.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dukakis told the legislators that he had ''learned my lesson'' after losing a Massachusetts primary in 1978 amid criticism that in his first term as Governor he often spurned the State Legislature. Focus on West and South</p>
        <p>In his meetings, the Governor focused on legislators from two key battlegrounds in the November election: the West and the South. In recent Presidential elections, Republicans have carried both regions.</p>
        <p>''In the West, we feel great for the first time,'' said Representative Barbara Boxer of California, who endorsed Mr. Dukakis earlier. ''At the beginning of this whole process, people said, ''What's happened here? We have no candidate.' ''</p>
        <p>After the Governor met over breakfast with about 40 House members who have formed the ''Go West '88'' coalition to aid the nominee, Ms. Boxer described the Governor as ''very responsive.'' She said he had staked out favorable positions on protecting the coast line from offshore drilling and seeking alternative energy policies.</p>
        <p>''The fact of the matter is that Governor Dukakis has an agenda that can win in the West,'' said Representative Ron Wyden of Oregon.</p>
        <p>Amid all the praise, participants said Mr. Dukakis had received some stern advice from two House members.</p>
        <p>Representative Edward R. Roybal of California, who has endorsed Mr. Dukakis, called on the Governor to involve more Hispanic Americans in his campaign, advice to which the Governor responded favorably, according to participants. Warning From Georgian</p>
        <p>At another session with about 60 House members from the South, Representative Ed Jenkins of Georgia told the Governor that Southern Democrats would consider running independently of the Presidential ticket ''if the platform is not balanced,'' according to Peggy Connally, a spokeswoman for the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee.</p>
        <p>In response, Ms. Connally said that the Governor told Mr. Jenkins, who has not endorsed Mr. Dukakis, that ''The Democratic Party cannot be all things to all people.''</p>
        <p>In the appearances, the Governor won more praise from Westerners than Southerners. But he told the Southern House members that he expected to campaign for several days in the South immediately after the last primaries on June 7.</p>
        <p>''This is a process which is building and evolving, and I think you're going to see some very strong support in the South,'' said Mr. Dukakis, who also met at his hotel this morning with Senator Albert Gore Jr. of Tennessee, who had been a rival for the nomination. Some Southerners were optimistic about Mr. Dukakis's prospects in the region.</p>
        <p>Senator Terry Sanford of North Carolina said that Walter F. Mondale did not get more Southern support in his 1984 Presidential race because ''he overpromised.''</p>
        <p>This year, Mr. Sanford said, ''it's going to be different because we've got a different candidate. I predict he'll sweep the South.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
