<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.C.A.A. Panel Urges Looser Rules on Eligibility and Pro Drafts</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="352103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRAFT AND RECRUITMENT (SPORTS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL COLLEGIATE ATHLETIC ASSN (NCAA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESKENAZI, GERALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D6133DF933A25756C0A966958260" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.C.A.A. Panel Urges Looser Rules on Eligibility and Pro Drafts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ESKENAZI, GERALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A National Collegiate Athletic Association committee has recommended that underclassmen who make themselves eligible for professional drafts be allowed to resume their college careers if they change their minds about becoming professionals, whether or not they have been drafted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A National Collegiate Athletic Association committee has recommended that underclassmen who make themselves eligible for professional drafts be allowed to resume their college careers if they change their minds about becoming professionals, whether or not they have been drafted.</p>
        <p>A National Collegiate Athletic Association committee has recommended that underclassmen who make themselves eligible for professional drafts be allowed to resume their college careers if they change their minds about becoming professionals, whether or not they have been drafted.</p>
        <p>The immediate impact, if the proposal is adopted, would be to allow underclass collegians to declare themselves available for the National Football League or the National Basketball Association draft, but then go back and play in school if they do not make it to the pros.</p>
        <p>''It's a drastic change from the present rules of amateurism,'' Rick Evrard, the N.C.A.A.'s director of legislative services, said yesterday of the proposal. Evrard explained that colleges had defined amateurism the same way since the early 1900's: if a player declared his intent to play for money - by entering his name for a draft, for instance - he would lose any remaining playing eligibility and, in effect, his amateur standing.</p>
        <p>If adopted, the new rule would have its greatest impact on pro football and basketball, but not on baseball and hockey, sports in which players have more maneuverability. Basketball, like football, requires the athlete to declare himself available for the draft. In baseball, a player can be drafted out of high school, but can decide he does not want to play and then is not drafted again until after he plays three years of college ball. In hockey, not all college players who are drafted are asked to turn pro immediately. Many actually finish out their college careers by playing in school.</p>
        <p>Athletes and Musicians</p>
        <p>Prompted by the fact that only 18 of the 38 who declared themselves eligible for this year's N.F.L. draft were chosen, the N.C.A.A.'s professional sports liaison committee voted last month to recommend the rules change. The proposal will be submitted to the N.C.A.A. Council in August. But even if adopted, it is unlikely to affect the 20 juniors who were not selected in this year's draft.</p>
        <p>''A student athlete, like any other student, should have the right to pursue a career,'' said Charlie Theokas, head of the N.C.A.A.'s committee and athletic director of Temple University. ''A violinist doesn't lose his right to go back and play in the school orchestra if he decided to leave school to get a paying job.''</p>
        <p>Coach Joe Restic of Harvard, who is the committee's liaison with the N.F.L., said: ''I'd like to see these kids eligible to return until the end of the process. They should be able to test the waters and see what their value is.''</p>
        <p>Vote Unlikely Before January</p>
        <p>Although Restic would like to see the process speeded up, the N.C.A.A. membership is not likely to vote on the rules change until next January at its annual meeting.</p>
        <p>The juniors who entered the recent N.F.L. draft were required by the league to promise they would forfeit their remaining college eligibility. Acccording to N.C.A.A. rules, as soon as they declared themselves ready to turn pro, they immediately lost their college playing eligibility and their scholarships.</p>
        <p>As of yesterday, none of the 20 undrafted collegians had been signed by an N.F.L. team as free agents. So in some cases, players apparently threw away their collegiate playing careers - if not a possibility of a degree as well - by choosing the draft. Several of the players, however, were academically ineligible and might not have returned to college in any event.</p>
        <p>'Living in a Dream World'</p>
        <p>Brad Gaines, a running back from Vanderbilt, was a rebuffed junior, failing to be drafted or signed as a free agent. He generated good statistics in college: the leading receiver in the Southeast Conference with 67 catches. He had expected to be drafted as a middle-rounder.</p>
        <p>''I had such a great year last year and I'm a three-year starter,'' he said from his home in Old Hickory, not far from school in Nashville. ''I felt that the way the game is going nowadays, you have an athlete who can catch and run, it's another bullet in your gun. ''I'm probably going to Canada now.'' One N.F.L. draft expert was hardly surprised that Gaines, as well as more than half of the other underclassmen, have been bypassed.</p>
        <p>''Some of these kids are living in a dream world,'' the expert said. ''Some of them were prompted by agents and some just weren't eligible to return to school for whatever reason, academics or something else.''</p>
        <p>Potentially Chaotic Situation</p>
        <p>The N.F.L. is opposed to drafted players' changing their minds and returning to school. This year, for example, five of the first seven players in the draft, and eight on the first round, were juniors.</p>
        <p>The league is concerned that a potentially chaotic situation could follow if drafted players decided to return to college. Clubs would have lost their draft choices.</p>
        <p>But sources say the N.F.L. would not oppose a rule change in which juniors who were not drafted were allowed to return to play for their schools.</p>
        <p>''We continue to oppose drafted underclassmen being able to return to college ball,'' the league's vice president of communications and development, Joe Browne, said yesterday. ''We need to maintain the integrity of our draft.''</p>
        <p>Addressing the N.F.L.'s concern, Restic said: ''That's not our problem. If the N.F.L. doesn't want to take a chance losing them, then they shouldn't draft juniors.''</p>
        <p>Agents Not Necessary</p>
        <p>Restic suggested that underclassmen would not have to sign agents - which immediately makes them ineligible - in order to test the waters. He said that the players could use the colleges' career counseling services to determine whether it was worthwhile to turn pro.</p>
        <p>''I think the fact that more than half weren't drafted sends a message to kids in school,'' said the Minnesota Vikings' executive vice president, Mike Lynn. ''They shouldn't be playing Russian roulette. The majority should be staying in school.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
