<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suffolk Police Head Plays It as He Sees It</title>
    <meta content="14LIJOURN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1566167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dormer, Richard (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodriguez, Jai</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Queer Eye for the Straight Guy (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E3D6153EF937A25750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suffolk Police Head Plays It as He Sees It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with new Suffolk County, NY, police commissioner Richard Dormer, avid soccer player, referee and coach; interview with Jai Rodriguez, part of Queer Eye for the Straight Guy television show cast, who sings at Viper Bar, Hauppauge, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE new Suffolk County police commissioner, Richard Dormer, likes to think of himself as a hands-on guy. But as a right midfielder on the soccer field, he's more likely to be bopping the ball with his head or stopping it with his toe and passing it. ''I police like I play soccer,'' said Mr. Dormer, 63. ''I am all over the field. I like to be involved in the action.''</p>
        <p>So there he was on a frosty recent Sunday morning, scampering up and down the frozen turf in a pick-up game on the Harborfields High School grounds in Greenlawn. Chipper as a cheerleader, he shouted with a slight Irish lilt to his teammates, ''Make 'em kick it, guys, make 'em kick it -- that's the secret.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE new Suffolk County police commissioner, Richard Dormer, likes to think of himself as a hands-on guy. But as a right midfielder on the soccer field, he's more likely to be bopping the ball with his head or stopping it with his toe and passing it. ''I police like I play soccer,'' said Mr. Dormer, 63. ''I am all over the field. I like to be involved in the action.''</p>
        <p>So there he was on a frosty recent Sunday morning, scampering up and down the frozen turf in a pick-up game on the Harborfields High School grounds in Greenlawn. Chipper as a cheerleader, he shouted with a slight Irish lilt to his teammates, ''Make 'em kick it, guys, make 'em kick it -- that's the secret.''</p>
        <p>Moments later he trapped the ball with his foot, kicked and scored.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dormer reached his other goal, that of top police official, on Jan. 30. He replaced John Gallagher, who had been commissioner since 1997. During a 30-year career on the Suffolk police force, Mr. Dormer rose to chief of patrol before retiring. He spent the last seven years overseeing security at Sports Plus in Lake Grove. Now he heads a department with 2,760 sworn officers and 582 civilians, a $378 million budget and 565 square miles to cover.</p>
        <p>Steve Levy, the Suffolk County executive, appointed Mr. Dormer. ''He's a cop's cop who is tough but fair,'' Mr. Levy said. Mr. Dormer is also a die-hard soccer player, playing on Sunday mornings straight through the winter. Summers, he plays on the over-40 Huntington Kickers, part of the senior league. ''This is my passion and it keeps me sane,'' Mr. Dormer said. ''This is my therapy.''</p>
        <p>Three years ago, Mr. Dormer passed the written and physical tests to become a referee for the Long Island Junior Soccer League, which has 1,400 travel teams in Nassau and Suffolk. He also coaches the Elwood Rovers, an under-17 boys' travel team. His son Michael, 16, is a striker on the first-division team.</p>
        <p>Being a soccer referee, Mr. Dormer said, is like running a police department.</p>
        <p>''What a difference when you're behind the whistle,'' he said. ''When you finally attain that position and you have everybody criticizing you, and looking at you, and waiting for you to make a mistake, the pressure is on. You have to make decisions that are unpopular, but you have to call it the way you see it.''</p>
        <p>Referees are paid $50 to work a travel-team game; team coaches are volunteers. As police commissioner, Mr. Dormer's salary is $115,000. The skills are easily transferable, he said. ''You have got to remain calm when everybody else around you is losing their heads,'' Mr. Dormer said. ''You've got to have a sense of humor. You've got to be able to take control without dominating people. You've got to be in charge, but not keep your foot on them.''</p>
        <p>The lines easily blur between his passions.</p>
        <p>''You want the kids playing soccer to enjoy what they are doing, but do it within the rules,'' Mr. Dormer said. ''You want the police officers and detectives to also do their jobs and stay within the rules.'' Randy Vogt, a spokesman for the Long Island Junior Soccer League, said that Mr. Dormer was coming along nicely as a referee and, not surprisingly, was adept at the multitude of paperwork.</p>
        <p>As a coach, Mr. Dormer pressed his charges to play their finest, Mr. Vogt said. ''Some players on other teams may be better than Richie's players, but nobody outworks Richie's soccer team,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dormer said he also encouraged the police department to act like a team. ''Everybody is in this together,'' he said. ''Everybody has a role to play. Just like a soccer player, you have to make a decision yourself; you can't have the captain telling you what to do. You have to know what to do based on your training and experience.''</p>
        <p>Robert Moore, chief of the department, agreed. He said Mr. Dormer, who has a degree in criminal justice and a master's of business sdministration, was ''a strong and decisive leader who can quarterback this team.'' The commissioner set the policy, Mr. Moore said, but left it up to his commanders, and those doing the work, to follow his path. ''He is able to examine the police department and operations as someone who has an interest in the bottom line,'' Mr. Moore said.</p>
        <p>Joseph Koka, an obstetrician-gynecologist from Huntington, plays in the Sunday game with Mr. Dormer.</p>
        <p>''He's fair,'' Dr. Koka said. ''He is always very level-headed and very controlled and very objective.'' Dr. Koka said Mr. Dormer was an unselfish player. ''While the speed may be gone, the technique is still there,'' Dr. Koka said. ''He distributes the ball to his teammates, putting the team ahead of himself.''</p>
        <p>The team is a microcosm of the county Mr. Dormer serves: dishwashers and laborers, many of whom don't speak English, play alongside doctors, pilots and engineers, drawn together by a love of the game.</p>
        <p>''It's very diverse,'' said Bernard Francis, a graphic artist from Greenlawn and the organizer of the two-hour pickup game. ''Here we are all equal. We put our soccer gear on; we are all the same.''</p>
        <p>But Jeff Frayler, president of the Suffolk Police Benevolent Association, said he had yet to see evidence of Mr. Dormer's team-building prowess.</p>
        <p>''His experience as a chief of patrol was at the worst of times, back in the early 1990's when there was a true financial deficit, and his experience circles around making cuts,'' Mr. Frayler said. ''We have all sorts of directives and orders that were put out by him when he was here as the chief that relate to diminishment and/or elimination of police services.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dormer said he would like the department to be referred to as ''the police service'' and would focus on ''dealing with the issues that are bedeviling society.''</p>
        <p>Born in Ireland, Mr. Dormer was 5 when he first learned to play what Europeans call football by knocking the ball around and watching older children play. In search of adventure and a better life, he moved to Kings Park at 18.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dormer described himself as ''a hard-nosed player.'' Teammates call him competitive. In a contact game that can sometimes be static, Mr. Dormer doesn't mind getting muddy. He plays soccer to win. ''In the police business, we play to win, too,'' the commissioner said. ''It's the police and the bad guys. We want the police to win. The people that pay our salaries -- the public -- they expect us to win. We have to do it under the rules, though, just like a soccer game. You can't go tripping people and violating people. It works both ways.''</p>
        <p>A Maven Tries the Mike</p>
        <p>''I spend all my time talking to people like Oprah and Jay Leno on these talk shows about tips I give the straight guy,'' said Jai Rodriguez. ''And sometimes I just want to bust into song.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rodriguez is the impish nightlife maven on the drab-to-fab Bravo/NBC makeover show ''Queer Eye for the Straight Guy.'' He doles out advice like an Emily Post for the socially graceless male.</p>
        <p>''I'm not acting, but it's not my passion,'' Mr. Rodriguez said of his role on the reality program. Singing and dancing is. His first album is in the works. Thus the reason to belt out his single, ''Love Is Good,'' at a recent late-night appearance at the Viper Bar, a club in Hauppauge.</p>
        <p>''For me, this is the ultimate homecoming,'' Mr. Rodriguez said before gyrating on stage wearing an old Boy Scout shirt and jeans, his hair spiky, flashing a Britney Spears smile. ''I grew up five blocks from here.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rodriguez, 24, studied musical theater at the Cultural Arts Center in Syosset, a Boces program; starred as Nathan Detroit in ''Guys and Dolls'' and young Joe Hardy in ''Damn Yankees'' at Smithtown High School (he graduated in 1997); and was a featured soloist in the Smithtown Gospel Tabernacle choir. Straight out of high school, he landed a spot in the Canadian company of the Broadway show ''Rent,'' then reprised his role as Angel, the drag-queen character in the show, on Broadway. '''Rent' has been my waiter job,'' Mr. Rodriguez said. ''Most people are like, 'Oh, you are an actor -- what restaurant do you work at?'''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rodriguez said he got his big break at 13 when he landed a role in a regional production of ''Runaways,'' a musical by Creative Arts Ministries in Holbrook. The success of ''Queer Eye,'' he said, has opened up a fan base of ''screaming girls'' that want ''to go shopping with me.'' He's hoping they'll also buy his compact disc when it comes out this summer.</p>
        <p>''I have always wanted to be a performer, be a vocalist and be a singer,'' Mr. Rodriguez said. ''I didn't think it was possible. Who did I look up to? Boy George? Elton John? I didn't resemble that style. I resemble Justin Timberlake. I just wasn't straight.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
