<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Building a Future That Points to the Past</title>
    <meta content="14TV1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/14/nyregion/14tvcolumn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1566198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinraub, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elizondo, Hector</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Century City (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E6DF133EF937A25750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Building a Future That Points to the Past</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Building a Future That Points to the Past</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weinraub, Bernard</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New CBS courtroom drama Century City is set in year 2030; futuristic series stars Hector Elizondo; tricky production details discussed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAWYERS are a television staple. Even more than doctors, they have served as the dramatic fulcrum of shows ranging from ''Perry Mason'' and ''Matlock'' to ''Ally McBeal'' and ''Law &amp; Order.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOS ANGELES.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAWYERS are a television staple. Even more than doctors, they have served as the dramatic fulcrum of shows ranging from ''Perry Mason'' and ''Matlock'' to ''Ally McBeal'' and ''Law &amp; Order.''</p>
        <p>And now comes CBS's ''Century City,'' a legal drama with a twist: it's set in the year 2030.</p>
        <p>''The courtroom is inherently dramatic, a very stylized form of drama,'' said Paul Attanasio, a creator and executive producer of the show, who graduated from Harvard Law School before becoming a movie critic for The Washington Post and a successful television and film writer.</p>
        <p>''You often have two moral opposites, somebody standing in a box and somebody standing opposite them, and the audience is watching them - it's drama boiled down to its essential,'' said Mr. Atanasio, who also created the NBC series ''Homicide: Life on the Street'' and wrote screenplays like ''Donnie Brasco'' and ''Quiz Show.''</p>
        <p>''Century City,'' which has its premiere on Tuesday at 9 p.m., is clearly an attempt to break throughthe clutter of law shows. ''There are probably more legal dramas on television now than there have been at any one time,'' said Earle Marsh, an author with Tim Brooks of ''The Complete Directory to Prime Time Network and Cable TV Shows.''</p>
        <p>Instead of the quirkiness of ''The Practice'' or the ''ripped from the headlines'' histrionics of ''Law &amp; Order,'' the new series seeks to deal with issues like genetic profiling, cloning, mind-altering antibiotics and even virtual rape. It is more ''X-Files'' and ''C.S.I.'' than ''Perry Mason.''</p>
        <p>the opening episode is not from your typical lawyer series. A 7-year-old boy urgently needs a transplant because of a defective liver. The boy's father (played by David Paymer) wants to use the boy's genetic embryo clone to develop a baby who could give a portion of his liver to the ailing child. The difficult is that the boy's father has illegally brought the clone into the United States, and the government has seized it. A more lighthearted theme involves a rock band suing its lead singer for growing old while the other musicians have altered the laws of nature and stayed young.</p>
        <p>The risk of the show - finding the right balance between human drama and futuristic science - leaves the creators and producers nervous. CBS has ordered nine episodes and will gauge audience reaction over the next six weeks. (''The Guardian'' reclaims its Tuesday-night slot on April 27.)</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Attanasio, the show's creators and executive producers are Katie Jacobs, a television and film producer who is also Mr. Attanasio's wife, and Ed Zuckerman, a former executive producer of the CBS drama series 'The Agency'' and ''JAG'' and a writer-producer on NBC's ''Law &amp; Order.'' Mr. Zuckerman said the three began discussing a series in the summer of 2002, at first considering an idea involving a Sherlock Holmes-style character, which led toa discussion about a law firm specializing in high-tech issues. ''We talked for another hour about Sherlock Holmes, and Paul said, 'Wait a minute, we're actually talking about a law firm of the future,' '' Mr. Zuckerman said.</p>
        <p>The show is set in Century City, an area of high-rise buildings near Beverly Hills where many laws firms have offices. The best-known member of the cast is Hector Elizondo, who plays a veteran member of a law firm made up, it seems, of earnest, good-looking and hard-charging lawyers, one of whom is genetically engineered.</p>
        <p>''The fact is, this is only a generation removed,' Mr. Elizondo said. ''On the show we see the consequences of the seeds we're planting now. I liked the fact that this is an optimistic view. It wasn't 'Blade Runner.' It wasn't flying saucers. It wasn't terribly technical. Ironically, the writers are finding it hard to stay ahead of the curve. The future is upon us.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Attanasio said that the pace of technological change was so rapid that it was sometimes difficult for the show's writers to make hypothetical leaps into the future. ''Just today there was a story about cloning human embryos in Korea,'' he said. ''There's been this explosion of surveillance technology since 9/11. There are constant articles about artificial intelligence or cancer cures. We're trying to keep up.''</p>
        <p>''It turned out surprisingly difficult to write,'' he added. ''Literally every bit of dialogue needs not only to tell a story but expound a world.''</p>
        <p>the costumes and settings for the futuristic show involve subtle and not-so-subtle contrasts with today. What lawyers will wear in 2030 will not be much different from their wardrobe in 2004, the creators say. But the ''palate'' of the show, Mr. Attansio said, is designed to serve as a contrast to the present.</p>
        <p>''We tried to communicate the idea that L.A. in the future will be very heavily Latino, very heavily polyglot and mixed, a browning of the population,'' he said. ''We tried to take those influences in terms of the colors we use. There's more Latino art.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zuckerman said the futurist theme crated some burdens for the show's writers. ''A typical dramatic TV episode is shot in eight days,'' he said. ''Of those, three days you go to a restaurant, a park, a beach, somewhere outside. We were limited in where we could go. We could never go out to a street because of the cars, or the people wallking on the sidewalk or driving. It created a problem because we did not want to make the show feel calustrophobic.''</p>
        <p>Executives connected to ''Century City'' said the series was not an easy one to produce. ''It's one of the more demanding shows we've been involved with,'' said David Kissinger, president of Universal Television Productions, the producers of the show. ''It's hard enough to come up with strong ideas and characters. But this show also forces us to come up with an entire vision of the future, and essentially invent a world.''</p>
        <p>''The risk is too much ambition,'' he said. ''Nobody can say this is a show that plays it safe.''</p>
        <p>Nina Tassler, executive vice president of dramatic development at CBS, said she hoped that the network's audience - which has responded positively to series like the offbeat ''Joan of Arcadia'' and shows oriented toward legal issues like ''The District'' and ''Judging Amy'' - would welcome ''Century City.''</p>
        <p>''The show is appealing to us because it feels accessible,'' Ms. Tassler said. ''It's not a science-fiction show. It's not a super-technology show. It really deals with compelling legal issues in the not-too-distant future.''</p>
        <p>The show's creators, in preparing the series, spent time with futurists, some of them experts on genetic engineering and surveillance technology, as well as academics, journalists, novelists and biologists.</p>
        <p>''Actually, we got as much information from daily newspapers as we did from futurists,'' Mr. Attanasio said. ''The show is just peeking around the corner from where we are today. It's almost here.''</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
