<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Development Chief Shrugs Off Skeptics</title>
    <meta content="14LIDUGG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1566184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ain, Stewart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Duggan, Patrick G (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suozzi, Thomas R (County Exec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DF123EF937A25750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1343" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Development Chief Shrugs Off Skeptics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEWART AIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ain, Stewart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Rev Patrick Duggan, new Nassau County</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HE has not had the job a month yet, and already he knows firsthand that it is not one for the thin-skinned.</p>
        <p>''I think that if you do anything, you are going to be criticized,'' said the Rev. Patrick Duggan, who became Nassau County's deputy county executive for economic development on March 1. The post is one of the most important in county government, and lately, it has been one of the most controversial. County Executive Thomas R. Suozzi's first choice for the post, Peter Sylver, resigned in November after being accused of mismanagement, improper spending and sexual harassment of an employee, charges that he has denied and that are being investigated by the County Legislature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HE has not had the job a month yet, and already he knows firsthand that it is not one for the thin-skinned.</p>
        <p>''I think that if you do anything, you are going to be criticized,'' said the Rev. Patrick Duggan, who became Nassau County's deputy county executive for economic development on March 1. The post is one of the most important in county government, and lately, it has been one of the most controversial. County Executive Thomas R. Suozzi's first choice for the post, Peter Sylver, resigned in November after being accused of mismanagement, improper spending and sexual harassment of an employee, charges that he has denied and that are being investigated by the County Legislature.</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Sylver's departure, important development projects in the county have languished. ''Things have been moving forward, but not at the same pace,'' Mr. Suozzi said, adding that he had confidence that Mr. Duggan will be able to speed them up again.</p>
        <p>Prominent voices in the real estate industry are not so sure, and have publicly questioned whether Mr. Duggan has the knowledge and experience to do the job effectively. Among them is Wilbur Breslin, president of Breslin Realty Development in Garden City and one of Long Island's leading developers.</p>
        <p>''For that job, you have to get somebody who is conversant with real estate and knows real estate development, because that it the backbone of the job,'' Mr. Breslin said. ''If he is not familiar with real estate, it could take two years before he gets educated.'' Similarly skeptical remarks by Mr. Breslin and others in the industry greeted Mr. Duggan on his first day in office, in an article on the front page of the Long Island Business News. But Mr. Duggan shrugged them off, and said that the perspective of a knowledgeable outsider to the industry was just what the job called for.</p>
        <p>Private developers, he said, had failed the communities that needed help the most, like New Cassel, where they have built nothing substantial for three decades.</p>
        <p>''If the real estate industry was effective in advancing economic development for the area, we would not need to exist,'' Mr. Duggan said of the department he leads. ''Where real estate works well is where conditions are already created -- where the market is favorable. Real estate does not do well in emerging communities, and in areas that have been left behind and that were not well planned.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Suozzi has made economic development in Nassau one of his major priorities, in order to advance his vision for what he calls a ''new suburbia.'' He spoke of it in his budget proposal in December and again in the State of the County message last week, speaking of plans to attract more high-skill jobs; to improve mass transit and lower-cost housing; and to redevelop moribund industrial sites, struggling downtowns and communities with large nonwhite populations that have been neglected in the past.</p>
        <p>''Pat Duggan is a very intelligent man, with a degree from Harvard University and a decade of involvement in economic development,'' Mr. Suozzi said in an interview. ''His focus will be to bring in major new corporations to downtown developments, and he has the help of a team of people around him. He doesn't need any time to get up to speed.''</p>
        <p>Among the downtown areas Mr. Suozzi said he wants to see revitalized are Freeport, Roosevelt, Elmont, Westbury, Hempstead, New Cassel and his own hometown, Glen Cove.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duggan, 45, of South Hempstead, came to his new post after five years as executive director of Sustainable Long Island, a Huntington-based advocacy group promoting community revitalization. Since 1995, he has also been the pastor of the Congregational Church of South Hempstead, an affiliate of the United Church of Christ.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duggan said he will continue to be pastor, though others will handle most of the day-to-day duties at the church. ''I have assistants and 36 volunteer leaders there,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duggan said he knows New Cassel especially well, because Sustainable Long Island spent two years helping with plans to redevelop the main thoroughfare, Prospect Avenue. He said the group built up ties with community leaders and the town board, and helped organize a local development corporation for New Cassel, the least affluent corner of North Hempstead.</p>
        <p>''We brought residents, developers, business owners and the clergy together, and in July 2002 we had 800 stakeholders create a vision for the community,'' he said. ''From that, the town has received 34 proposals from 16 developers to do $50 million of development in New Cassel, including 300,000 square feet of retail and 275 units of affordable housing.''</p>
        <p>The real estate industry did not take the lead in New Cassel because ''they are not trail blazers,'' he said. ''But now that we have created the conditions, the private development community can come in.''</p>
        <p>Though he does not have a degree in urban planning, he said, his work in New Cassel and in other communities ranging from Riverhead to Oyster Bay has given him the experience he needs for the deputy executive's job.</p>
        <p>''I've worked with planners for the last five years,'' Mr. Duggan said. ''I think of myself as someone who knows how to move a project from start to finish, and to see all of the connections and ramifications.''</p>
        <p>Lee E. Koppelman, executive director of the Long Island Regional Planning Board, said he knows Mr. Duggan by reputation as a man ''who is going to be a sparkplug, and have the personality and intelligence'' to advance Mr. Suozzi's goals.</p>
        <p>''I also have a feeling he is a person of integrity, and that is important as well,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mitchell Pally, vice president for governmental affairs of the Long Island Association, a business group, said that Nassau County needs ''a very, very aggressive department'' to market the region to potential investors and retain companies in the county.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pally noted that Mr. Suozzi had subdivided the county into a series of economic development areas, but that he had not yet set priorities among the many projects that await development.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duggan said that would not be done until the county had completed a series of 35 community meetings meant to solicit views of local residents and judge the feasibility of various proposals. Twenty of these meetings have already been held.</p>
        <p>Then, choosing among the proposals ''will be a shared effort among the residents, developers, people in the real estate field and our own staff,'' he said. ''We'll sort it all out. And that's what is different from the past: It is not the developer who is saying, 'this is what we can do.' That change means everything to me, and it's what we need to do.''</p>
        <p>Near the top of the county's development agenda will probably be the Nassau Hub, the commercial heart of the county, encompassing Roosevelt Field and Mitchell Field, the former Roosevelt Raceway grounds, nearby areas of Mineola, Garden City, Carle Place and Hempstead, and facilities like Hofstra University and the Nassau County Veterans Memorial Coliseum. Mr. Suozzi said the county had secured a $1 million federal grant to help integrate the Hub, and that planning meetings would be held soon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pally noted that the Hub is home to more than half the economic activity in the county, and that plans for addressing its traffic and transportation problems and for replacing the coliseum with a more modern arena have been discussed for a decade.</p>
        <p>Of Mr. Duggan, Mr. Pally said: ''There is no question that he has tremendous vision. Now the issue is, can he go beyond that to the implementation? That is the hard part.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
