<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EDO's Founder Proved His Mother Wrong</title>
    <meta content="14LIBIZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1566170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="L.I. @ WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aerospace Industries and Sciences</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Edo Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, James M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strugatch, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D6153EF937A25750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EDO's Founder Proved His Mother Wrong</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN STRUGATCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strugatch, Warren</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Earl Dodge Osborn consulted his mother, Alice Clinton Dodge Phelps, nearly 80 years ago, just before starting a company that would manufacture aluminum floats for seaplanes, he got a dubious reaction. His mother, heiress to the Phelps-Dodge mining, railroad and forestry fortune, suspected that seaplanes were faddish and feared that if her son failed in business, it would taint the family's reputation on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>''She asked her son to name the company with his initials -- she didn't want him to use the family name,'' the company's chief operating officer, Frank Otto, told an audience of engineers, academics and business leaders assembled earlier this month at a hotel in Islandia. The occasion was the induction of four historical business leaders, including Mr. Osborn, who died in 1988, into the Long Island Technology Hall of Fame.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Earl Dodge Osborn consulted his mother, Alice Clinton Dodge Phelps, nearly 80 years ago, just before starting a company that would manufacture aluminum floats for seaplanes, he got a dubious reaction. His mother, heiress to the Phelps-Dodge mining, railroad and forestry fortune, suspected that seaplanes were faddish and feared that if her son failed in business, it would taint the family's reputation on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>''She asked her son to name the company with his initials -- she didn't want him to use the family name,'' the company's chief operating officer, Frank Otto, told an audience of engineers, academics and business leaders assembled earlier this month at a hotel in Islandia. The occasion was the induction of four historical business leaders, including Mr. Osborn, who died in 1988, into the Long Island Technology Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>Mr. Otto's explanation of how the EDO Corporation got its name produced the evening's biggest laugh (although, truth be told, the competition was light). In one sense, Mrs. Phelps's judgment proved correct, since relatively few seaplanes have been built. But EDO succeeded in making a new kind of all-metal float that made heavy wooden floats obsolete. Among the early users were Charles Lindbergh, Leroy Grumman and, perhaps problematically, Amelia Earhart.</p>
        <p>From that early success, EDO (pronounced ee-DOE) grew into a major subcontractor, providing electronic systems for major aeronautics companies like Boeing, Lockheed Martin and Grumman, as well as contracting directly with the Navy and Air Force. After downsizing in the 80's and 90's, EDO has recently gone on an acquisitions binge, in the process becoming one of the fastest-growing companies in America.</p>
        <p>From its beginnings in College Point, Queens, EDO built up a business developing electronic aviation, marine and weapons systems for the military. But the company, which moved to North Amityville in 1998, is not resting on its laurels. Last year was its most successful to date: EDO's sales surpassed $470 million, and profits reached $14.8 million, compared with sales of nearly $329 million and profits of $10.6 million the previous year.</p>
        <p>The increase in profits, nearly 40 percent, was almost entirely a result of EDO's absorbing a series of smaller companies, a growth-by-acquisition strategy that propelled it into the No. 10 spot on Forbes magazine's list of fastest-growing companies. The company has about 2,.700 employees, 500 of them in North Amityville.</p>
        <p>James M. Smith, EDO's chairman, said that its growth reflected a policy of diversification, from radar technology and aviation navigation systems to underwater ordnance and military training.</p>
        <p>''All our units are showing growth,'' Mr. Smith said. ''We are not niche-y. And we continue to win our place based on the performance of our products rather than their price.''</p>
        <p>Ken Morelly, the executive director of the Long Island Forum for Technology -- Mr. Otto is its chairman -- said that EDO was highly regarded for the quality of its engineering. ''Its reputation for product excellence'' has made it legendary, Mr. Morelly said in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>The company, which moved its corporate offices to Midtown Manhattan in 1997, merged with AIL Systems, a competitor in Deer Park, in April 2000. Both companies had been rapidly shrinking, as the defense budget shrank.</p>
        <p>''Peace broke out in the late 80's,'' said Mr. Smith, who rose through the ranks at AIL to become its chairman, president and chief executive. ''That was good, but it made it a difficult time for us.''</p>
        <p>''We were 5,300 people, and we went down to 800 people,'' Mr. Smith said, referring to AIL just before the merger.</p>
        <p>EDO was also in difficult straits. Its sales had peaked in 1989, at nearly $150 million, but had dropped to less than $80 million in 1995. An effort to diversify into nonmilitary products had proved disastrous. When it moved to North Amityville in 1998, it had managed to rebuild sales to about $90 million.</p>
        <p>Once it became clear that AIL and EDO would merge, the question was, which company would prevail. EDO endured, Mr. Smith said, in part because both sides wanted to keep its trading status on the New York Stock Exchange. His AIL roots notwithstanding, Mr. Smith took the reins of the newly merged company.</p>
        <p>''It was a two-way challenge,'' he recalled of the period of integration. ''I had to convince the EDO managers that I was really EDO, and I also had to convince the AIL managers that I was really EDO. There were two very different perspectives.''</p>
        <p>Since becoming chairman of EDO four years ago, Mr. Smith has engineered six acquisitions, three of them completed last spring. The company's aggressive shopping spree has earned the favor of a number of analysts, including Patrick J. McCarthy at Friedman Billings Ramsey, a brokerage and research firm in Arlington, Va. ''Despite concerns of a near-term decline in organic growth,'' Mr. McCarthy wrote in a report issued last summer, ''we believe that recent acquisitions in the professional military services marketplace and in surveillance and reconnaissance position EDO for continued growth over the next 18 months.''</p>
        <p>Several large military programs, including the Joint Strike Fighter and the F/A-22, two planes built by Lockheed Martin, should produce revenue for EDO for the next 20 years, Mr. McCarthy noted.</p>
        <p>William A. Walkowiak, the company's director of investor relations, said that EDO was continuing to explore mergers, although it feels no urgency to complete any. ''The fit has to be right, and the cultures have to work together,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith, whose job it would be to blend any new acquisitions into EDO's culture and operations, said that he did not shy away from what can be a draining and difficult experience. ''I was the one in charge,'' he said, referring to the downsizing efforts at AIL. ''I learned things I never wanted to learn. It was stomach-churning. But you handle it, because you have to, and you become professionally good at it.''</p>
        <p>''When you go through that,'' he said, ''other problems that come up aren't going to ruffle you.''</p>
        <p>L.I. @ WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
