<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Walking Its Last Mile</title>
    <meta content="14WESHOE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1566214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Repair Services</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chappaqua (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cartisano's Shoe Repair (Chappaqua, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, Kate Stone</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cartisano, Vitaliano</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EEDE133EF937A25750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Walking Its Last Mile</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE STONE LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, Kate Stone</byline>
      <dateline>CHAPPAQUA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cartisano's Shoe Repair, Chappaqua, NY, has closed after 58 years in business; proprietor Vitaliano Cartisano comments on how business has changed due to modern shoe construction; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS wealthy hamlet will be a bit less well heeled now that Cartisano's Shoe Repair has closed its doors after 58 years. Vitaliano Cartisano, like his father before him, has replaced countless heels and soles and is highly skilled at his work. But in what seems a sign of the times, Mr. Cartisano has sold his lease and closed his shop; the store will become home to a nail salon, which plans to open next month.</p>
        <p>That will make five nail salons in Chappaqua, and zero shoe repair shops. But the lease offer was too good to refuse, Mr. Cartisano said. He sat in his closed shop recently, cleaning up what was left of the business, while construction workers broke down walls to make way for the incoming salon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS wealthy hamlet will be a bit less well heeled now that Cartisano's Shoe Repair has closed its doors after 58 years. Vitaliano Cartisano, like his father before him, has replaced countless heels and soles and is highly skilled at his work. But in what seems a sign of the times, Mr. Cartisano has sold his lease and closed his shop; the store will become home to a nail salon, which plans to open next month.</p>
        <p>That will make five nail salons in Chappaqua, and zero shoe repair shops. But the lease offer was too good to refuse, Mr. Cartisano said. He sat in his closed shop recently, cleaning up what was left of the business, while construction workers broke down walls to make way for the incoming salon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cartisano learned to repair shoes from his father, Antonio, who himself had learned the trade in Italy. Antonio Cartisano, the oldest of 13 children, left Italy when he was 17.</p>
        <p>Over time, he opened a shoe repair shop in White Plains, but after World War II, his rent there doubled. In 1946, he bought a business and a building ''up in the country,'' in downtown Chappaqua, for $10,000.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Cartisano reminisced about the history of the store, a steady trickle of customers knocked at the locked door, coming to claim their shoes.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to last at least until I was 70 and then walk away and try something different,'' Mr. Cartisano, 68, said as he removed shoe trees from a pair of repaired shoes and gave them one last buffing with a stiff brush before handing them to their owner. ''It's been a long time and I'm really going to miss it,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The customer shook Mr. Cartisano's hand and wished him good luck.</p>
        <p>The next visitor was a woman who banged on the door asking, ''You don't have anything of mine, do you?'' After Mr. Cartisano assured her he did not, she walked out without a word.</p>
        <p>Only a few pairs of unclaimed shoes remained, along with one pair of boots which still had its $700 price tag. They had been brought to the shop for stretching more than a month ago, Mr. Cartisano said.</p>
        <p>When his father opened the store here, there was wealth in the town but it was not ostentatious, Mr. Cartisano recalled. Everyone kept up their shoes.</p>
        <p>''In this community for the longest time I had guys that fixed their shoes, even if they had a lot of money,'' Mr. Cartisano said. ''Soles and heels, general upkeep. Some guys were fastidious. They all dressed up when they went to the train. When I.B.M. came in, there was a uniform -- plain toe cordovan shoes.''</p>
        <p>Even John R. Opel, former chairman and chief executive officer of I.B.M., ''would come in Saturday morning to have his shoes repaired,'' Mr. Cartisano said. ''He was very unassuming.''</p>
        <p>Over time, it seemed to Mr. Cartisano, shoes changed and so did people. Most shoes are now constructed with glue, instead of stitching, he said. He found that glued shoes were more difficult to repair, because unless he used extreme care removing a sole or a heel for replacement, the whole shoe might pull apart.</p>
        <p>He also believes that people have become more careless about their shoes. Many customers didn't seem to know how to polish their own shoes, and then came a period -- particularly during the Stock Market's heyday in the 1980's -- when people simply viewed aging shoes as disposable.</p>
        <p>''A lot of it's the economy,'' Mr. Cartisano said. ''One of my suppliers is down on Wall Street, and that guy could tell from the store traffic if the stock market was good or bad.''</p>
        <p>After the attacks on the World Trade Center in September 2001, a curious thing happened, Mr. Cartisano said. For several Saturdays in a row, men walked in carrying shopping bags full of shoes that needed repair.</p>
        <p>''I'd get these bags of shoes, with holes in the soles, covered in dust, and the guys saying, 'I'm not going to throw these away now.'''</p>
        <p>CHANGES were visible in other parts of the business, too. Over the last decade, he said, he began to have trouble hiring local high school students who were willing to sweep the store and polish shoes two days a week. (''No work ethic anymore,'' he said. ) Mr. Cartisano graduated from Horace Greeley School in 1955, where he was captain of the football team. He maintained his love of sports as an adult and coached local Little League for 15 years.</p>
        <p>The most difficult job for Mr. Cartisano is a stiletto heel.</p>
        <p>''They get so chewed up and scarred, and women wear them right down to the nail,'' he said. ''There's a little dowel that you hammer the lift in; sometimes it's so tight you have to drill it in.''</p>
        <p>The new pointed toe shoes for women are also troublesome. ''The toe sticks out so far, the leather gets worn, and you've got to peel back part of the sole, sand it, reshape it, and make it look like the rest of the shoe.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cartisano is, by his own admission, a perfectionist. ''I'm fussy,'' he said, ''That's kind of my downfall. I spend a lot of time, more time than I should.''</p>
        <p>He said he almost always got along with his customers, except for those rare times when someone criticized his work.</p>
        <p>''Gee whiz, then I liked my shoes better than I liked the customers who brought them in,'' he said of those critics. ''There are some people who think they were shoemakers in another life.''</p>
        <p>The shoe repair business has always been conducted at the back of the store; Mr. Cartisano leased the front to children's shoe stores. Four different tenants held the space from 1950 to 2001.</p>
        <p>Chappaqua used to support two children's shoe stores, as did many neighboring towns. Mr. Cartisano remembers that after a snow storm, a line would form for boots when he opened the doors. But as big department stores like Nordstrom's and Neiman Marcus moved into the area, customers began to shop out of town.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cartisano said he has tried in vain for two years to find another children's shoe store to lease the front of the store.</p>
        <p>He said he could hang onto the business without renting the front of the space, but has little incentive.</p>
        <p>His four children are college educated and none are interested in the business. Their father sometimes gets to the shop at 5:30 a.m., and he says his children would like to see him stop working so hard. But Mr. Cartisano does not plan to retire.</p>
        <p>A widower, he says he both wants and needs to work. He is taking computer lessons at the library to update his skills and will look for a shoe repair job, and if that fails, something in shoe sales.</p>
        <p>''I could always go to Nordstrom's and sell shoes,'' he said. ''I'd have a tough time, especially when the manager is 23 years old, but I'll have a job. I can at least fit children's shoes, and with an honest fit.''</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
