<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fruit of Lessons Grabbed Along the Way</title>
    <meta content="23DUNN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/23/arts/dance/23DUNN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20020623T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1402698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THIS WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dancegalaxy (Dance Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Thaddeus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bahiri, Medhi</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2D61F3CF930A15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fruit of Lessons Grabbed Along the Way</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">DanceGalaxy's Lessons Learned</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Thaddeus Davis of DanceGalaxy, whose first work, Once before, Twice after, will be performed at season opener at Symphony Space; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THADDEUS DAVIS of DanceGalaxy was astonished when he was asked by Medhi Bahiri, the company's co-director, to create a ballet. ''I was like, 'What?' '' Mr. Davis recalled, laughing.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Davis's first piece of choreography, a quartet called ''Once before, Twice after,'' will be performed when DanceGalaxy opens its New York season at Symphony Space on Tuesday. Set to contemporary music, it is a fast, high-energy work full of big movements. He will also dance with the troupe in a program that includes works by William Forsythe, Sarah Slipper and Stanton Welch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having studied the trade of dance here and there, Thaddeus Davis of DanceGalaxy creates his first ballet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THADDEUS DAVIS of DanceGalaxy was astonished when he was asked by Medhi Bahiri, the company's co-director, to create a ballet. ''I was like, 'What?' '' Mr. Davis recalled, laughing.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Davis's first piece of choreography, a quartet called ''Once before, Twice after,'' will be performed when DanceGalaxy opens its New York season at Symphony Space on Tuesday. Set to contemporary music, it is a fast, high-energy work full of big movements. He will also dance with the troupe in a program that includes works by William Forsythe, Sarah Slipper and Stanton Welch.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis, 34, who grew up in Montgomery, Ala., began his dance training to perfect his high school football skills. He arrived in New York in 1993, after graduating from Butler University in Indianapolis.</p>
        <p>From the start, he poured himself into New York dance. ''I had no friends,'' he said. ''I had no time to socialize. I worked at McDonald's and waited tables, then I'd go to the Lincoln Center library and watch all the dance videos.'' In class and rehearsals the next day, he danced what he had seen on tape.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis went on to perform with the Dance Theater of Harlem, Donald Byrd/The Group and Complexions, a company founded by the former Alvin Ailey dancers Dwight Rhoden and Desmond Richardson. He joined DanceGalaxy in 2000.</p>
        <p>There are few opportunities today to learn the trade of dance in the old way: by long-term association with established modern-dance companies and the artists who founded them. Dancers must grab what they can, wherever they can. At Dance Theater of Harlem, Mr. Davis studied, with the guest choreographer Alonzo King, the importance of focusing hard on the work of making dances. With Mr. Rhoden, it was about ''how far can we go before we say maybe we should come back.''</p>
        <p>Although he was not accepted after auditioning for Mr. Forsythe's Frankfurt Ballet, Mr. Davis stayed around Frankfurt, picking up pointers from Mr. Forsythe and his dancers. Most of the dancers were working on projects of their own. ''They were in a creative environment, therefore they were being creative,'' Mr. Davis said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Davis's greatest influence has been Mr. Byrd, who named Mr. Davis a creative assistant last season. The Byrd company is closing because of financial difficulties, but Mr. Byrd left Mr. Davis a considerable legacy. Teaching class and restaging Mr. Byrd's dances for several years, Mr. Davis was inspired to begin working intensively on his own choreography.</p>
        <p>''It has been such an incredible thing working with Donald,'' Mr. Davis said. ''All the things I thought of, he'd say, 'Well, go ahead and try it.'</p>
        <p>''It took me a long time to admit to myself I wanted to be a choreographer. I was a little bit intimidated.''</p>
        <p>Part of the problem was his feelings for all of the choreographers he has worked with. ''I had such a respect and love for them,'' he said, ''as human beings and artists.''</p>
        <p>JENNIFER DUNNING</p>
        <p>THIS WEEK  Correction:  June 23, 2002, Sunday  A picture caption on Page 10 of Arts &amp; Leisure today with an article about Thaddeus Davis of the DanceGalaxy company misstates the surname of a dancer in the company. She is Tanya Wideman-Davis, not Davis-Wideman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 23, 2002, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Page 10 of Arts &amp; Leisure today with an article about Thaddeus Davis of the DanceGalaxy company misstates the surname of a dancer in the company. She is Tanya Wideman-Davis, not Davis-Wideman.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
