<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prescription for Allergy Sufferers</title>
    <meta content="23SOAP$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1402799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="SOAPBOX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antennas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hutchinson River Parkway</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crosby, Nicole</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Allergies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E5DB153FF930A15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prescription for Allergy Sufferers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICOLE CROSBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crosby, Nicole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nicole Crosby tongue-in-cheek essay extols virtues, for allergy-sufferers' sake, of wireless cell phone tower camouflaged as giant evergreen tree 'planted' along Hutchinson River Parkway; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I CAN'T help but notice a resemblance between the towering pine that recently sprouted in the median strip of the Hutchinson River Parkway and the fake Christmas tree in my attic -- the one I bought five years ago after developing an allergy to the needle-dropping variety. Even the assembly of this immense artificial tree is familiar to me, as I watch workers jam color-coded branches into the perfectly tapered, 152-foot trunk. They use a crane. I use a footstool.</p>
        <p>When the holidays roll around, I'm hoping they will string the tree with twinkling lights, trim it in gigantic, weatherproof glass balls and top it with a star you can see all the way from Interstate 287. Why bother schlepping to Rockefeller Center to see an ordinary tree from the forest when we can see a technologically superior one at our local Mobil station?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I CAN'T help but notice a resemblance between the towering pine that recently sprouted in the median strip of the Hutchinson River Parkway and the fake Christmas tree in my attic -- the one I bought five years ago after developing an allergy to the needle-dropping variety. Even the assembly of this immense artificial tree is familiar to me, as I watch workers jam color-coded branches into the perfectly tapered, 152-foot trunk. They use a crane. I use a footstool.</p>
        <p>When the holidays roll around, I'm hoping they will string the tree with twinkling lights, trim it in gigantic, weatherproof glass balls and top it with a star you can see all the way from Interstate 287. Why bother schlepping to Rockefeller Center to see an ordinary tree from the forest when we can see a technologically superior one at our local Mobil station?</p>
        <p>I've been told the new tree was built to camouflage a cell tower, but I prefer to believe it was erected for the benefit of allergy sufferers. The bronchially and nasally impaired can now enjoy the grandeur of these majestic specimens without dripping, sneezing and blowing. We can all be tree huggers, even those of us whose eyes turn red and throats get scratchy at the sight of the actual, chlorophyll-producing, oxygen-emitting kind. The way I see it, this remarkable botanical simulation is a breakthrough on par with Benadryl.</p>
        <p>If residents protest the new tree and demand that it be taken down, I'll be its Julia Butterfly Hill, an environmentalist who lived in a redwood tree for about two years to protest logging in California. I'll scale the trunk and set up camp amid its galvanized branches, crusading for its right to be left alone while generating a stream of e-mail messages and interviews with the news media. Julia named her tree Luna. I'll name mine Eterna. (Metallica was already taken.)</p>
        <p>But a tree this magnificent and this permanent doesn't come cheap. It cost $200,000 to build, not including Christmas ornaments. Commuters and nearby residents who view it daily owe their gratitude to the boundless generosity of America's wireless providers. This industry is poised to install even more miracles of non-nature if we're willing to do our part. Those of us who are talking only a few minutes per month on our cellphones need to log at least another 2,000 minutes. Better yet, 4,000 minutes. Why spend time on a land line phone that relies on underground fiber optics you can't even see and enjoy?</p>
        <p>There are so many ways we can help the wireless industry bring more allergy-free trees to Westchester County. For example, ride Metro-North and call someone on your cellphone to say you're riding Metro-North. Wander through the grocery store and call home to say you're wandering through the grocery store. The more unnecessary cellular calls placed and the longer and more detailed the conversations, the better.</p>
        <p>Nurtured and fed by wireless talk, these mighty evergreen replicas may someday be visible from backyards and living room windows, countywide. The future of the Bionic White Pine is in our hands -- the very hands that hold the Nokias, the Samsungs and the Startacs.</p>
        <p>So get talking. Not only God can make a tree.</p>
        <p>SOAPBOX Nicole Crosby is a member of the New Rochelle Telecommunications Advisory Committee.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nicole Crosby is a member of the New Rochelle Telecommunications Advisory Committee.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
