<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Catchy Little Rumba</title>
    <meta content="23ZALEWST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/23/books/review/23ZALEWST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1402623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zalewski, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hijuelos, Oscar</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Simple Habana Melody, A (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hijuelos, Oscar</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E7DA143CF930A15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1392" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Catchy Little Rumba</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'A Simple Habana Melody': A Rumba of Repression</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Daniel Zalewski</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zalewski, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Zalewski reviews book A Simple Habana Melody by Oscar Hijuelos; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A SIMPLE</p>
        <p>HABANA MELODY</p>
        <p>(From When the World</p>
        <p>Was Good).</p>
        <p>By Oscar Hijuelos.</p>
        <p>342 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Oscar Hijuelos's new novel, a Cuban composer writes a tune that enchants the world, but he cannot articulate, let alone act on, his deepest passions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A SIMPLE</p>
        <p>HABANA MELODY</p>
        <p>(From When the World</p>
        <p>Was Good).</p>
        <p>By Oscar Hijuelos.</p>
        <p>342 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $24.95.</p>
        <p>ISRAEL LEVIS, the decorous, effete composer at the center of Oscar Hijuelos's sixth novel, contradicts every cliché about the hot-blooded Latino lover except one: he has a whopper of a penis. However, what Hijuelos repeatedly describes as his Cuban protagonist's ''magnificent'' and ''spectacular'' member is less a symbol of tropical virility than of squandered gifts. For Levis poignantly struggles throughout his life -- one that starts and ends in Havana, save for a tragic interlude in wartime Europe -- with a curious form of emotional impotence. Indeed, this ''lumbrous, awkward and ever careful'' musician can express his fervor for the woman he loves only in the disembodied form of music.</p>
        <p>Aside from Levis's endowment, there is nothing at all outlandish about ''A Simple Habana Melody.'' Readers expecting a reprise of the rousing, blaring-trumpet prose of ''The Mambo Kings Play Songs of Love,'' Hijuelos's best-known novel, may be surprised to encounter language here that is consistently muted. Descriptions are resolutely qualified; in a single paragraph one finds ''a bit plump,'' ''a little older'' and ''a little too pious.'' The result of all this linguistic tiptoeing is a melancholy, and sometimes wan, novel about the fruits and frustrations of repression.</p>
        <p>On the one hand, Levis's affection for Rita Valladares, a sensual octoroon singer with skin the ''color of curled cinnamon bark,'' inspires his most successful composition -- Rosas Puras,'' a catchy little rumba written in 1928 that eventually becomes a global Cuban standard on the order of ''Guantanamera.'' (Levis writes the song when Rita requests a fresh number for a concert in New York.) On the other hand, Levis's ''nearly priestly reserve'' ensures that he and Rita can become one only in song. Imagine ''Love in the Time of Cholera'' without the romantic payoff, and you'll have a general sense of Hijuelos's decades-long narrative, which time and again brings Israel and Rita into potentially lusty propinquity -- such as when Rita subtly squirms on the composer's lap during a group photograph -- only to swerve away.</p>
        <p>Levis is not quite the Cuban version of Stevens, the uniquely stoppered servant in Kazuo Ishiguro's ''Remains of the Day,'' but he comes close. His tragedy, like that of Stevens, is that he cannot articulate, let alone act on, his deepest passions. More than reticence, however, Levis's fundamental problem is one of sexual confusion. Although the love he feels for Rita is genuine -- the most banal postcard from her inspires tears of joy -- his ardor lacks an erotic charge. Even as he spends hours one afternoon waiting for Rita in a Paris hotel, obsessively searching for the right words to initiate a romance, his eyes furtively follow another object of desire: ''the handsome man across the lobby.''</p>
        <p>Whereas Ishiguro's novel masterfully employs a first-person narration that, through slips and evasions, slowly exposes the private longings of the protagonist, Hijuelos adopts an omniscient view. It's a far more facile approach; the reader is given direct access into the internal churnings of Levis's ''privately lascivious'' mind, even as he maintains a ''publicly righteous'' persona. Too often, Levis's feeling of internal disconnect is rendered with blunt obviousness: '' 'If only I were different,' he always thought.''</p>
        <p>That said, Hijuelos -- whose central talent as a novelist is in his love of character -- never reduces Levis to a closet case. His sexuality is far more interesting than that. Although he can never bring himself to score with the ever-willing Rita, he secretly beds down with a gallery of female prostitutes; Levis, it turns out, is oddly turned on by red garters. (Yes, his consorts all marvel at the ''majesty of his virility.'') And when the composer moves to Paris in the 1930's, he surprises himself by at last having a sustained romantic entanglement with a woman, a Jewish dance instructor. Despite all this, the two things he most longs for -- Rita and beautiful men -- remain somehow off limits; so ''innately pent up'' is Levis that Hijuelos compares him to an hutia, the barkless Cuban dog. Without a doubt, Levis's erotic urges are contradictory and hard to categorize. But that's exactly what makes him a character worth puzzling over.</p>
        <p>Alas, his musical side, which occupies an equally central role in the novel, is comparatively devoid of tension. For unlike everything else about his conflicted mind, Levis's creativity is free-flowing. Rumbas and habaneras simply pop into being. ''He could chew his croquette with one hand,'' Hijeulos writes, ''and set down the notes onto paper with the other, whistling.'' This is charming enough, but it's the kind of effortless talent a reader can admire only from a distance; although Hijuelos traces the entire arc of Levis's musical development, there's none of the yeastiness of the best kind of Künstlerroman.</p>
        <p>More surprisingly, Hijuelos -- who captured the excitement of Cuban music so well in ''Mambo Kings'' -- fails to conjure a strong sense of Levis's signature song, ''Rosas Puras.'' Because the rumba is the central metaphor for Levis's ever-pining heart, its ''playful and nearly childish melody'' needs to resonate in the reader's mind. ButHijuelos's evocations of the song are plodding. He cornily suggests that the tune is snatched from songbirds twittering on Havana's streets. At one point, he reproduces the melodic line -- E flat, Rita's lovely eyes; F, her fulsome lips; F sharp, her delicate cheek'' -- but in so doing, reveals a most uninspired tune. Prose descriptions of music are notoriously difficult, but it can be done by a master; think of the modernist piano fragment from Vinteuil's sonata so vividly imagined in Proust's ''In Search of Lost Time.''</p>
        <p>The most effective use of ''Rosas Puras'' in the novel is the way it functions as a constant reminder of Levis's past. (The song is so popular that he can't walk through downtown Havana without hearing it.) Early in the novel, an aging Levis hears his music floating in the window from a nearby social club. In a moving passage, he's transported back to the myriad times he's heard or played his signature tune: in the basement of a Parisian whorehouse, in ''Rhumba Crazy,'' an MGM musical -- and at Buchenwald.</p>
        <p>In the novel's most misguided and contrived move, Levis, a devout Roman Catholic, turns out to be a Holocaust survivor. (In what is canonically known as a Cruel Twist of Fate, his Jewish-sounding name gets him deported during his Paris sojourn.) At the camp, he is saved by agreeing to perform his famous song -- which, it is unsurprising to learn, rather sours his feelings about it.</p>
        <p>THESE queasy musical performances are just about the only thing the reader learns of Levis's Buchenwald experience; like his protagonist in this instance, Hijuelos is too tactful to get into anything too raw or grotesque. (''For the next 14 months, the maestro did not believe the things he saw, nor the sounds he heard.'') The elided nature of the Holocaust theme saves ''Melody'' from becoming an affront on the order of ''Life Is Beautiful,'' but Hijuelos is too talented not to recognize that sentences like the following are pure kitsch: ''He still could not as much as look at the sweetest of children . . . without thinking about the infants and mother he had seen being herded off to their doom by the 'Aryan masters.' ''</p>
        <p>Worse, the Holocaust narrative has the effect of diminishing the other sadnesses in Levis's life. Perhaps out of a feeling that his story isn't big enough, Hijuelos allows a novel about the slow accumulation of regret to be swallowed by the worst event in human history. As a result, it's hard for the reader to appreciate that the most devastating moment in Levis's life occurs not in Buchenwald but in Havana, just after Rita runs off with the score to ''Rosas Puras.'' He's just secured an eternal fame -- but as Hijeulos writes with aching simplicity, his heart is bleeding. ''He remained under an arcade, making much of his own foolishness and timidity, berating himself, and giving little thought to that song.''</p>
        <p>Daniel Zalewski is an editor at The New York Times Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daniel Zalewski is an editor at The New York Times Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
