<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>15 Injured, 2 Critically, When Out-Of-Control Taxi Jumps Curb on Upper East Side</title>
    <meta content="23CAB.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/23/nyregion/23CAB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1403060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smalls, Arthur</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D6113FF930A15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>15 Injured, 2 Critically, When Out-Of-Control Taxi Jumps Curb on Upper East Side</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">15 Injured, 2 Critically, When Out-of-Control Taxi Jumps Curb on Upper East Side</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Taxicab jumps curb in heart of busy Upper East Side shopping area in Manhattan, injuring 15 people, two critically; driver Arthur Smalls tells police cab surged forward when he applied brakes at 60th Street and Lexington Ave stoplight; has had clean record over past 17 years as driver; crash scene described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A taxi careered out of control and jumped a curb in the heart of a busy Upper East Side shopping area yesterday, leaving 15 people injured, two of them critically.</p>
        <p>The cab barreled down a congested Lexington Avenue sidewalk before coming to rest near an entrance to Bloomingdale's, and witnesses said the accident sounded like a series of explosions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A taxi careered out of control and jumped a curb in the heart of a busy Upper East Side shopping area yesterday, leaving 15 people injured, two of them critically.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A taxi careered out of control and jumped a curb in the heart of a busy Upper East Side shopping area yesterday, leaving 15 people injured, two of them critically.</p>
        <p>The cab barreled down a congested Lexington Avenue sidewalk before coming to rest near an entrance to Bloomingdale's, and witnesses said the accident sounded like a series of explosions.</p>
        <p>The police declined to identify the victims, but said the most seriously injured included someone with a collapsed lung and another victim with a broken hip.</p>
        <p>The operator of the cab, Arthur Smalls, 52, of Queens, who was alone in his vehicle, was driving south on Lexington Avenue between 61st and 60th Streets just before 5 p.m. when the taxi swerved wildly, side-swiping another car and jumping the curb, according to Capt. John Paulik, executive officer of the 19th Precinct.</p>
        <p>Investigators said the taxi driver, who remained at the scene dazed but uninjured, told the police that he removed his foot from the gas pedal as he approached the stoplight at 60th Street, and tried to apply the brake. But the driver said that when he pressed the brake pedal, the taxi lunged forward faster than before and went out of control, according to Captain Paulik.</p>
        <p>After jumping the curb on the east side of Lexington Avenue, about 100 feet north of 60th Street, the cab struck a hot dog vendor and someone selling used magazines from a folding table on the sidewalk.</p>
        <p>The taxi continued moving south along the sidewalk, pushing the mangled remains of the hot dog vendor's cart and striking pedestrians in its path. It skidded across 60th Street before coming to rest just short of one of the entrances to Bloomingdale's.</p>
        <p>Witnesses said several of those who were hit were emerging from a subway exit at 60th Street and Lexington Avenue.</p>
        <p>The chain of collisions ''seemed like it lasted for only a second,'' said Reva Erlichman, 55, a witness who was standing nearby on a 60th Street sidewalk.</p>
        <p>''He hit those poor people coming out of the subway, and but for the grace of God, he would have ended up in Bloomingdale's.''</p>
        <p>Stephanie McFarland, 31, an employee of a clothing store on the west side of Lexington Avenue close to the site of accident, said, ''I thought there was an explosion.''</p>
        <p>''I ran out and there were people screaming,'' she said. ''I saw people lying on the sidewalk and not getting up.''</p>
        <p>Besides the two people who were critically injured, the victims included a 17-year-old girl and six other people who were in serious or stable condition at various hospitals last night, according to Sgt. Vincent Grivelli, a police spokesman. He said one other victim was in good condition, and five people were treated but not hospitalized.</p>
        <p>He said no charges had been brought against Mr. Smalls, but the case remained under investigation. Police experts were said to be examining the taxi to determine whether there had been a mechanical failure.</p>
        <p>Investigators said Mr. Smalls was given a Breathalyzer test on the scene and had not been drinking. They also said he had been driving a cab for 17 years and had a clean record.</p>
        <p>The accident left a grim spectacle. More than a hour after the victims were removed, the intersection of 60th Street and Lexington remained littered with colorful paper, apparently the remains of magazines that had been stacked neatly on the magazine vendor's table.</p>
        <p>The hot dog vendor's cart was smashed beyond recognition, and dozens of hot dog buns scattered in the street. Pigeons landed on the street and appeared to be feeding happily on the buns amid a jumble of emergency vehicles and police officers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
