<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No-Show Snow's Budget Impact</title>
    <meta content="SNOW.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1003940"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Phenomenon)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Musante, Fred</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFDC1E39F931A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="1409" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No-Show Snow's Budget Impact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED MUSANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Musante, Fred</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut officials expect modest budget surpluses from winter with almost no snow (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS has been one of the least snowy winters on record in Connecticut, a meteorological anomaly that comes only two seasons after the all-time snowiest. The 1995-1996 season caused huge deficits in municipal snow plowing budgets, but anyone hoping for equally large surpluses in those accounts this year will be disappointed.</p>
        <p>Mayors and public works officials from around the state said the surpluses will be modest. But they will also probably not be spent instead on pet projects as they might have been in the past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS has been one of the least snowy winters on record in Connecticut, a meteorological anomaly that comes only two seasons after the all-time snowiest. The 1995-1996 season caused huge deficits in municipal snow plowing budgets, but anyone hoping for equally large surpluses in those accounts this year will be disappointed.</p>
        <p>Mayors and public works officials from around the state said the surpluses will be modest. But they will also probably not be spent instead on pet projects as they might have been in the past.</p>
        <p>This is partly due to a series of inconveniently timed ice storms, and partly because of reverberating effects of the big winter two years ago, which raised costs for materials and contractual services that never went back down and made many municipal managers more cautious in their budget planning.</p>
        <p>Still, the relatively warm, snowless season will produce financial benefits, sometimes subtle and long-term. Fewer potholes than normal are expected this spring, which will allow city road crews to work on permanent road reconstruction instead of emergency patch-up jobs. Wear and tear on plows, vehicles and sand spreaders was light, lowering repair costs and extending their useful life spans.</p>
        <p>Most noticeably, every official reported substantial stockpiles of road salt and sand. While some cost is involved in storing the stuff, it is material that will not have to be purchased next year.</p>
        <p>El Nino, that burly warm zone in the eastern Pacific Ocean that has caused so much meteorological mayhem elsewhere in the country, has been given due credit for making this winter in Connecticut so trouble-free for public works managers.</p>
        <p>Mel Goldstein, a weather forecaster for WTNH-TV, said that in a normal winter about 20 inches of snow fall along the shoreline and about 50 inches inland. This winter, Bridgeport's total snowfall is only 8.7 inches so far, and at Windsor Locks the total for the season is 20 inches.</p>
        <p>Dr. Goldstein said El Nino sent warm air across the Southwest into the Gulf of Mexico where it picked up moisture and brought it up the Eastern Seaboard, making it a wetter than normal season. But temperatures tied the 1936 record for warmth in January and February.</p>
        <p>''What should have given us tons of snow instead gave us storms that just washed down the drain,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I am having 'I Like El Nino' buttons printed for all my staff,'' joked Glenn MacWilliams, Public Services Bureau Chief for Stamford. He noted that the oceanic anomaly caused mayhem from Florida, to California to northern New England and upstate New York, but was relatively benign to Connecticut. ''We have been very lucky,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As was typical with most other communities, Stamford planned for an average winter when setting its snow-plowing budget line items, but since the winter of 1995-1996, the definition of what is average has been revised.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Stamford had allocated $600,000 for storm overtime, sand and salt, and hiring outside contractors to augment its plowing fleet. But a relentless series of winter storms, including a three-day blizzard in early January, pushed the city's costs that year above $2 million, forcing it to scrape up the difference by reallocating funds from all over the rest of the municipal budget.</p>
        <p>The practice in Stamford had been for the public works managers to request an amount based on the average spending in previous years. ''In good budget times we'd get the full amount. In bad budget times they'd reduce it,'' Mr. MacWilliams said.</p>
        <p>''What can you budget?'' asked Micky Docimo, Stamford's Administrative Services Bureau Chief. There just isn't enough money available to budget for a worst-case winter snowfall.</p>
        <p>''There's no real way of predicting it,'' Mr. Docimo said. ''There's a big year and a low year, a big year. It's just a guess.''</p>
        <p>For 1996-1997, while the shock of the deficits from the record winter snows was still fresh in their minds, Stamford's government leaders authorized $800,000 for snow plowing, and the city used almost all of it.</p>
        <p>Sand and salt prices, as well of those of outside contractors, had frozen at the higher levels established during the record winter.</p>
        <p>For this year, Stamford raised the snow plowing allocation to $880,000. Mr. MacWilliams believes $250,000 to $300,000 may be left over; not more, however, because several evening storms coated upland road surfaces with a treacherous frozen sheen known as black ice.</p>
        <p>Mr. MacWilliams has requested a reduced amount, $863,000, for next year, reflecting the low amount of maintenance and repair expected on the city's plowing equipment and vehicles.</p>
        <p>Black ice was a budget-draining problem for other shoreline towns, and even worse inland. It demands a quick response with sand and salt, usually during hours when municipal crews get overtime or holiday pay.</p>
        <p>H. Richard Borer, Mayor of West Haven, said the two small snowstorms and a few ice storms in his area this winter, all came at night or on Martin Luther King Day.</p>
        <p>''We had bad timing,'' he said. Several Nor'easters that blew by caused shoreline flooding that also forced West Haven to dip into its overtime account.</p>
        <p>This year so far, West Haven has spent only $16,000 of its $40,000 budget line for salt, $15,000 of the $45,000 for sand purchases, and $58,000 of its $90,000 storm overtime budget. That was total spending of $89,000, contrasted with the $400,000 the city spent in the 1995-1996 record-setting season.</p>
        <p>Mr. Borer says he tries to budget defensively, but a light snowfall season can create a lot of doubters among his taxpayers -- as can under-budgeting for record years like 1995-96. In Meriden, City Manager Roger L. Kemp said he hasn't increased his $300,000 allocation for winter storms, the same amount as two years ago when the state saw ''the mother of all winters.'' That year, Meriden actually spent $1.1 million, he said.</p>
        <p>This season's ice storms, particularly one in early February that kept returning for several nights, nearly depleted his entire allocation. That doesn't surprise him, however. ''Usually we go over'' rather than under budget, he said. ''We don't budget for a doomsday winter.''</p>
        <p>Derby continued its snow insurance, something West Haven rejected this year as too expensive. Derby's Mayor, Marc Garofalo, said the premium cost $15,000, and it doesn't appear that it will pay for itself this year. The policy has a four-storm deductible, then pays $10,000 for the fifth four inches of snow in 24 hours, and $21,500 for each such snow event after that.</p>
        <p>His city collected more than $50,000 two years ago, even though it purchased its policy late and missed out on applying the first three storms of that year against its deductible. Even with the snow insurance pay-off, Derby spent overspent its $60,000 budget by about $75,000.</p>
        <p>''Our budget is depleted. It's over-spent,'' said Robert Carroll, Waterbury's Superintendent of Streets, but he noted that his city always under-budgets for snowstorms and makes it up with supplementary appropriations at winter's end. This year, he said, the shortfall is relatively small.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carroll's problem this snowless winter has also been black ice. Throughout January and February, he had to send his crews out to sand slick roads during every one of the frequent rainstorm. ''We've spent the winter watching the thermometer,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Waterbury didn't increase its budget after the 1995-1996 record snows. ''In fact, they lowered the account for hired equipment,'' Mr. Carroll said. But, a he put it, ''I just take it one storm at a time.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, caution for this season is still advised. It is, after all, still March, a month notorious for blizzards in the state. Dr. Goldstein recalled that last year it snowed across Connecticut on April Fool's Day, and Mr. MacWilliams noted that five years ago on March 20 and 21 the state was hit by Storm Beth, a monstrous Nor'easter blizzard that  stalled trains and closed highways.</p>
        <p>''I'm not counting on being out of the woods yet,'' Mr. MacWilliams said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
