<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Hurricane Katrina, a Bank Turns to Money Laundering</title>
    <meta content="29hancock" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/29/business/29hancock.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1705788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Katrina (Storm)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automated Teller Machines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mississippi</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hancock Bank (Mississippi)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belson, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Mississippi</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEFD91230F93AA1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Hurricane Katrina, a Bank Turns to Money Laundering</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Hurricane Katrina, a Bank Turns to Money Laundering</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN BELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belson, Ken</byline>
      <dateline>GULFPORT, Miss.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hancock Bank, one of Mississippi's largest financial institutions, is still repairing its network after devastation of Hurricane Katrina; branches in worst-hit areas had no phone or data lines or power for weeks, and bank tellers could not find account balances or swap crucial information with banks' backup data centers in Baton Rouge, La, and Chicago; automated teller machines were inoperable; photo of bank employees cleaning bills soiled by hurricane (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The scene would make a mob boss proud: workers in a windowless hallway scoop armfuls of grimy cash out of plastic garbage bags and sling them into a washing machine. Others fill the dryers and iron the clean bills. Nearby, a half-dozen women count the freshly pressed bills and bundle them into thousand-dollar wads.</p>
        <p>In an era of cashless and instantaneous transactions, this laundering operation, which has been up and running since shortly after Hurricane Katrina hit on Aug. 29, is no mirage. In fact, it is part of the recovery process for one of Mississippi's largest financial institutions, Hancock Bank, which like most banks in Katrina's path is still repairing its network.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hancock Bank, one of Mississippi's largest financial institutions, is putting bills through the wash cycle as part of its recovery effort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The scene would make a mob boss proud: workers in a windowless hallway scoop armfuls of grimy cash out of plastic garbage bags and sling them into a washing machine. Others fill the dryers and iron the clean bills. Nearby, a half-dozen women count the freshly pressed bills and bundle them into thousand-dollar wads.</p>
        <p>In an era of cashless and instantaneous transactions, this laundering operation, which has been up and running since shortly after Hurricane Katrina hit on Aug. 29, is no mirage. In fact, it is part of the recovery process for one of Mississippi's largest financial institutions, Hancock Bank, which like most banks in Katrina's path is still repairing its network.</p>
        <p>Hancock Bank's branches in the worst-hit areas had no phone or data lines or power for weeks. Bank tellers could not find account balances or swap crucial information with the bank's backup data centers in Baton Rouge, La., and Chicago. Automated teller machines were inoperable.</p>
        <p>About 90 of the bank's 103 branches in the New Orleans area and along the Mississippi coast were damaged in some way. Many of them lost connections to the main data center in the company's headquarters in Gulfport, which was shattered. Most branches are now functioning again, but seven were smashed and have been temporarily replaced by mobile operations in R.V.'s.</p>
        <p>''We've moved a $5 billion bank in three days to four states,'' said John Hairston, the bank's chief operating officer. ''It will take up to at least half a year to reconsolidate.''</p>
        <p>Katrina also forced the Federal Reserve operations in New Orleans to move to Atlanta, making it harder for Hancock Bank to get fresh cash to meet surging demand. To remain liquid, the bank recovered millions of dollars from its A.T.M.'s, night deposit boxes and vaults that had filled with water and silt -- and washed and dried the cash as fast as they could. ''We're doing it the old-fashioned way,'' Mr. Hairston said.</p>
        <p>Even for Hancock, which has endured hurricanes for a century, the storm exposed how dependent banks have become on telephone and power networks. Without them, Hancock was forced back to the 1960's, before centralized computers at corporate data centers turned branches into satellite offices.</p>
        <p>Still, banks on the Gulf Coast, like Hancock, typically fared better than many other businesses because they are required by federal law to keep backup copies of their data. Their disaster recovery plans are also tested and audited frequently. Hancock has a full-time manager -- whom executives jokingly call Dr. Doom -- to keep the bank's equipment and plans current.</p>
        <p>Even so, the bank was overwhelmed because the telecommunications providers, including BellSouth, that support its networks were knocked out by flooding in New Orleans and the storm surge that engulfed Mississippi.</p>
        <p>''The banking industry is extraordinarily prepared, but there's no way to keep all operations up and running when they are under the water,'' said Scott MacDonald, chief executive of the Southwest Graduate School of Banking at Southern Methodist University in Dallas.</p>
        <p>One problem, Mr. MacDonald said, is that most banks are regional, not national, so their offices and networks are heavily concentrated in one area and thus susceptible to being knocked offline during big storms. When phone and power lines go down, they can lose connections with their backup data centers, even if those are in distant states.</p>
        <p>Hancock, which has branches from Tallahassee, Fla., to Alexandria, La., has an operations center in Baton Rouge and backup computers in Chicago, which are maintained by SunGard, the financial processing company. This set-up allowed the company to get its A.T.M.'s and branches outside the affected areas running a few days after the storm.</p>
        <p>But without Internet connections to the branches in the hard-hit areas, tellers there were forced to write customers' names, account numbers and the amounts they withdrew on pieces of paper. The chits and checks were driven to Baton Rouge overnight, where workers -- more than 100 of whom are bused in from Gulfport daily -- typed the data into computers.</p>
        <p>Hancock worked with BellSouth to reconnect its local branches and the headquarters with the backup computers in Chicago. The lines were not restored until Sept. 15, or 17 days after the storm. To make sure the A.T.M.'s worked, Corrine Buchholz drove down to the machine at the Crossroads branch near the company's abandoned headquarters.</p>
        <p>''We were dancing in the driveway,'' said Ms. Buchholz, who oversees the A.T.M. network at the bank.</p>
        <p>Customers were so hungry for cash that within seconds, cars driving on Highway 49 nearby spotted her and made U-turns in traffic to get in line at the carport.</p>
        <p>''If people can get their balance and some cash, they feel better,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hairston said service would have been restored in less than a week if federal regulations had not forced BellSouth to handle other customers first. To speed restoration efforts during emergencies, the Department of Homeland Security assigns agencies and companies a Telecommunications Service Priority code. The executive branch of the federal government is at the top of the list; other agencies and utilities follow.</p>
        <p>Banks are typically in the fourth tier. As a result, when a group ahead of Hancock asked BellSouth for help, the phone company stopped work and moved elsewhere.</p>
        <p>A month after Katrina, much has been done. In addition to restarting A.T.M. service in Gulfport, the bank's command center now has landlines. It has 120 phone lines at Hancock University, the company's training center, thanks to a digital router that BellSouth installed.</p>
        <p>Before that, employees relied entirely on cellphones.</p>
        <p>After several weeks of sleepless nights, the bank's technology manager, Walter Hatten, now has time to assemble a to-do list. First on the list: Set up a new data center, most likely north of Interstate 10, which runs parallel to the coast, but was far enough north that the storm waters did not reach it. A storm might knock out power or phone service there, but the equipment and building would be unlikely to be damaged.</p>
        <p>Or so they hope.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
