<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Suspect Is in Stable Condition After the Police Fire 77 Shots</title>
    <meta content="29shot" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/29/nyregion/29shot.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1705881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Police Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EED71230F93AA1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Suspect Is in Stable Condition After the Police Fire 77 Shots</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Suspect Is in Stable Condition After the Police Fire 77 Shots</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREEM FAHIM; Matthew Sweeney and William K. Rashbaum contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officers fired 77 shots early yesterday at a gunman they were pursuing through two housing projects in East Harlem, the police said. But only three bullets struck him, and he was in stable condition at a hospital last night, they said.</p>
        <p>At least 12 officers chased the man, Cedric Rooks, 25, through the grounds of the projects -- the Robert A. Taft Houses and the Martin Luther King Jr. Towers -- on Fifth Avenue between 112th and 115th Streets, the police said. Twice during the winding pursuit, Mr. Rooks and the officers exchanged fire, and he was wounded in the neck, shoulder and hip, the police said. He was taken to Harlem Hospital Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officers fired 77 shots at a gunman they were pursuing through two housing projects in East Harlem, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Officers fired 77 shots early yesterday at a gunman they were pursuing through two housing projects in East Harlem, the police said. But only three bullets struck him, and he was in stable condition at a hospital last night, they said.</p>
        <p>At least 12 officers chased the man, Cedric Rooks, 25, through the grounds of the projects -- the Robert A. Taft Houses and the Martin Luther King Jr. Towers -- on Fifth Avenue between 112th and 115th Streets, the police said. Twice during the winding pursuit, Mr. Rooks and the officers exchanged fire, and he was wounded in the neck, shoulder and hip, the police said. He was taken to Harlem Hospital Center.</p>
        <p>None of the officers were wounded, the police said. The Police Department's Internal Affairs Bureau has began an inquiry into the shooting, said Paul J. Browne, the department's chief spokesman. The episode is the 87th involving the firing of weapons this year by the police. Mr. Browne would not characterize the conduct of the six officers -- four patrolmen and two sergeants -- who fired their weapons at a fleeing suspect in a residential area. Mr. Rooks's criminal record includes a conviction for weapons possession.</p>
        <p>Residents described concentrated gunfire around 2 a.m., and a chase that was easily visible from the high-rise apartment buildings. Traces of the gunfight were visible yesterday afternoon, including a tree with six bullet holes, shattered car windows and the pierced facade of a liquor store. Two bullets hit apartment windows at 1403 Fifth Avenue, but no one was hurt, the police said.</p>
        <p>''It sounded like they were running after many people, the way they were shooting,'' said Carmen Lopez, 63, who watched the chase from her window on Fifth Avenue. ''It just kept on and on.''</p>
        <p>It was unclear what Mr. Rooks had been doing earlier. Police Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly said that the episode started after officers riding in an unmarked car spotted Mr. Rooks at 112th Street and Fifth Avenue, and suspected that he had a gun. They called out to him, and he responded with a dismissive comment, said a police official who was briefed on the shooting but was not authorized to comment publicly.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Rooks ran, the official said. He fired the first shot in front of a firehouse on Fifth Avenue, the police said, and four to six more later. When officers found him on 115th Street, the police said, his gun was pointed toward his pursuers, but he was unable to fire -- the weapon had possibly jammed. Then he collapsed and the gun fell, the police said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
