<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tracing Gore's Roots as Supporter of Overhaul in Campaign Finance System</title>
    <meta content="16DONA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1192442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E7D61631F935A25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tracing Gore's Roots as Supporter of Overhaul in Campaign Finance System</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore's aides take pains to show he is not late and cynical convert to campaign finance reform crusade popularized by Sen John McCain; both supporters and critics agree he has been steady if largely invisible supporter of steps to change political finance system since he was first elected to Congress in 1976; Gore continues to raise soft money donations he opposes to keep up with Gov George W Bush and Republicans (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Vice President Al Gore declared late last month that he would devote himself to remaking the system of political finance, he conceded that he was an ''imperfect messenger'' for campaign finance reform.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore knows that his 1996 fund-raising exploits, including cadging cash at a Buddhist temple and dunning contributors from his White House office, make his new campaign finance reform mantra subject to skepticism and a few snickers. Also, all the while he is proclaiming the need for a campaign finance overhaul, including a ban on soft money, the vice president is busily raising these unrestricted donations to keep up with George W. Bush and the Republicans. This very weekend he is helping the Democratic National Committee sweep up more than $4 million from rich donors in Silicon Valley and Hollywood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Vice President Al Gore declared late last month that he would devote himself to remaking the system of political finance, he conceded that he was an ''imperfect messenger'' for campaign finance reform.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore knows that his 1996 fund-raising exploits, including cadging cash at a Buddhist temple and dunning contributors from his White House office, make his new campaign finance reform mantra subject to skepticism and a few snickers. Also, all the while he is proclaiming the need for a campaign finance overhaul, including a ban on soft money, the vice president is busily raising these unrestricted donations to keep up with George W. Bush and the Republicans. This very weekend he is helping the Democratic National Committee sweep up more than $4 million from rich donors in Silicon Valley and Hollywood.</p>
        <p>Since his March 27 speech proposing radical changes in the way politicians finance their campaigns, Mr. Gore's aides have taken pains to show that he is not a late and cynical convert to a crusade popularized in the presidential primaries by Senator John McCain of Arizona.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, they say, has supported campaign reform legislation since his earliest days in Congress. He has sponsored or co-sponsored bills to limit contributions from political action committees, to restrain spending in House and Senate campaigns, to provide for public financing of Congressional elections and to grant free television time to candidates.</p>
        <p>In fact, supporters and critics of Mr. Gore agree that he has been, since first elected to Congress in 1976, a steady if largely invisible supporter of measures to change the political finance system.</p>
        <p>''It would be fair to say he certainly was a supporter but an exaggeration to say he was an activist or a crusader,'' said former Senator David L. Boren, Democrat of Oklahoma, a longtime sponsor of legislation to clean up campaigns. ''I don't say that as a criticism, because every vote and every co-sponsor we got was crucial.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boren, now president of the University of Oklahoma, said that he could count on Mr. Gore's signature on campaign bills and on his vote, but that Mr. Gore was not an ally who would make sacrifices for the cause.</p>
        <p>He said that Mr. Gore, like Mr. McCain, had become a committed proponent of campaign reform because of the criticism he has endured for zealously exploiting the system's flaws. Mr. Gore said in his speech in March that he and President Clinton (with their Republican opponents) had ''pushed the system to the breaking point'' and fueled public cynicism about politics and politicians.</p>
        <p>Other Congressional advocates of campaign revisions speak similarly of Mr. Gore during his eight years in the House and eight years in the Senate: he was a reliable vote or co-signer, but his heart was elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Laura Quinn, Mr. Gore's communications director, said that it was difficult to discern his motives or the depth of his feelings after so much time. But she conceded that as a member of Congress, he had devoted far more effort to arms control, the environment and technology policy than to election law. She added, there is considerable evidence that Mr. Gore early on recognized the value of campaign finance as both a substantive and a symbolic issue.</p>
        <p>In a 1978 newspaper column, Mr. Gore wrote that changing the campaign finance system is ''one of the most important steps we can take to return government to the people.''</p>
        <p>The next year, he co-sponsored legislation introduced by Representative Abner J. Mikva, Democrat of  Illinois, to impose limits on spending in House campaigns in exchange for partial public financing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore also co-signed a bill in 1979, sponsored by Representative David R. Obey, Democrat of Wisconsin, to limit the amount of money that a political action committee could give to a candidate and the total amount of PAC money a candidate could receive.</p>
        <p>The Mikva and Obey bills went nowhere. But Mr. Gore can now justifiably claim he was an early proponent of reform.</p>
        <p>In 1986, then-Senator Gore sponsored a bill to provide public financing for Senate campaigns. In 1988, he introduced legislation to give presidential candidates free television time, to cut the cost of campaigns.</p>
        <p>''The commitment was early and consistent, and he is clearly convinced from his own experience that this is essential to his success as president and is desperately needed now to steady the course of the country,'' Ms. Quinn said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mikva, who since leaving Congress in 1979 has been a federal judge and White House counsel under Mr. Clinton, said that he had little recollection of Mr. Gore's support for his political fight to finance Congressional campaigns with public money.</p>
        <p>''It was not at the top of his agenda,'' Mr. Mikva said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mikva's 1979 legislation was a precursor of the centerpiece of Mr. Gore's proposal this year. It would have created a fund to pay for general election campaigns of candidates who agreed to limit their spending. Mr. Gore's more ambitious proposal, which he calls the Democracy Endowment, would create a $7 billion fund to pay for campaigns of candidates who agree not to take any outside money. Both measures aimed to break the link between those who write the checks and those who write the laws.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mikva agreed with Mr. Gore's acknowledgment that he was an ''imperfect messenger'' for campaign reform, having exploited every available loophole in his campaigns for Congress and the vice presidency and fashioned a few new ones.</p>
        <p>But he said that Mr. Gore was wise to adopt the cause of reform now.</p>
        <p>''I was pleased when he made a big issue of campaign finance reform,'' Mr. Mikva said. ''The consequences of 1996 are going to plague him anyway. If he's going to try to pretend it didn't happen and say nothing, he's worse off.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's proposal would provide public financing of campaigns from a $7 billion fund to be filled with tax-deductible contributions from many of the same interests and individuals who now fuel campaigns -- but without the direct contributions to candidates. It would also outlaw so-called soft money, the unlimited contributions from corporations, unions, interest groups and wealthy donors, require greater disclosure of independent expenditures and provide free television time for candidates.</p>
        <p>But until such laws are enacted, Mr. Gore intends to aggressively employ the current system to finance  his campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore told contributors at a $500,000 soft-money luncheon in Washington on Wednesday that he had no intention of taking a high-minded vow of poverty in his combat with Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>''We will fight fire with fire,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
