<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prosecutor Who Battled Corruption</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="563561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPECIAL PROSECUTORS (INDEPENDENT COUNSEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS AND SWINDLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BANCA NAZIONALE DEL LAVORO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSTON, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LACEY, FREDERICK B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARR, WILLIAM (ATTY GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Prosecutors (Independent Counsel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DB123BF934A25753C1A964958260" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prosecutor Who Battled Corruption</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSTON, DAVID</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frederick B. Lacey, the former Federal judge and corruption-busting prosecutor from New Jersey named today to investigate whether the Government bungled the Banca Nazionale del Lavoro bank fraud case, says he has a potent weapon if his independence is threatened.  He can always resign.</p>
        <p>"I want something and I don't get it," he said when asked at a news conference today whether he would truly get a free hand from the Administration that appointed him. "You know what I can do? I can submit a resignation. And I think that with the press out there, were that to happen, that would be enough of a threat to get what I needed."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frederick B. Lacey, the former Federal judge and corruption-busting prosecutor from New Jersey named today to investigate whether the Government bungled the Banca Nazionale del Lavoro bank fraud case, says he has a potent weapon if his independence is threatened.  He can always resign.</p>
        <p>"I want something and I don't get it," he said when asked at a news conference today whether he would truly get a free hand from the Administration that appointed him. "You know what I can do? I can submit a resignation. And I think that with the press out there, were that to happen, that would be enough of a threat to get what I needed."</p>
        <p>But skeptical Democrats in Congress seemed to doubt such a threat would make much difference, and no one could answer the larger question about Attorney General William P. Barr's appointment of Judge Lacey: can the Republican lawyer who describes himself as a "relative stranger to the Washington scene" stop the bleeding from an Administration caught in interdepartmental guerrilla war over whether the Government stifled an investigation into fraudulent bank loans to Iraq? Two Agencies Accused</p>
        <p>The Government prosecuted a manager of the Italian bank's Atlanta branch for defrauding the bank by setting up a scheme to make the loans. In recent days the Justice Department and the Central Intelligence Agency have been accused of misleading a Federal judge about the case.</p>
        <p>It appears that Frederick Bernard Lacey, the son of a former Newark police chief, a man who as a prosecutor changed the political landscape in New Jersey, is well equipped for the battle.</p>
        <p>Associates admire his tenacity. William J. Brennan 3d, the son of the retired Supreme Court justice and a president of the Association of the Federal Bar of the State of New Jersey, described Judge Lacey as "thorough, fearless and indefatigable." He said, "One thing you can be sure, no stone will remain unturned."</p>
        <p>Today, Judge Lacey said that when he accepted the job offer from Mr. Barr on Thursday afternoon, he insisted on one condition: complete access to every document and every person in the Government with any knowledge of the case. Letting Chips Fall</p>
        <p>"Anyone who knows me knows that when I imposed those conditions, I meant them," he aid. "And as General Barr said, where the chips fall, they fall."</p>
        <p>Facing the cameras and reporters today, Judge Lacey said he had telephoned Senator Bill Bradley, Democrat of New Jersey and a member of the Senate Intelligence Committee, and asked Mr. Bradley to introduce him to Senator David L. Boren, the chairman of the committee, which is conducting its own investigation. Mr. Bradley's aides said later that he agreed to arrange the meeting.</p>
        <p>Although a Republican, Judge Lacey was considered for the post of Deputy Attorney General in the Jimmy Carter Administration in 1979. But he withdrew after some legal groups opposed him as a prosecution-minded judge. Lawyers like Alan M. Dershowitz, the Harvard law professor, was quoted at the time as saying he was "extraordinarily competent, but he has no sense of fair-mindedness."</p>
        <p>With an undergraduate degree from Rutgers and a law degree from Cornell, Judge Lacey, who was born in 1920, began his law enforcement career as Federal prosecutor in the 1950's and in 1954 he had the case that sent Albert Anastasia, the gangster, to prison for income tax evasion. Appointed by Nixon</p>
        <p>In 1969, President Richard Nixon appointed the Mr. Lacey as the United States Attorney for New Jersey. During his 13-month tenure he initiated a series of ground-breaking corruption prosecutions against politicians and organized crime figures, including one case against the mayor of Newark.</p>
        <p>He was appointed to the Federal District Court in New Jersey in 1970 and retired in 1986. He also acquired familiarity with intelligence matters sitting from 1979 to 1985 on the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court, the special panel that considers, and virtually always, grants Government requests approve eavesdropping in national security investigations.</p>
        <p>In recent years, Judge Lacey has worked for LeBoeuf, Lamb, Leiby &amp; McRae, a large law firm in Newark and New York as a senior litigation partner while taking on occasional judicial assignments as a court-appointed special master.</p>
        <p>He was appointed a special judicial master overseeing the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, and in that job he dismissed two officers of a local in Queens, New York over corruption charges.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year managed the bitterly contested redrawing of nonpartisan boundaries for Congressional districts in New York -- asserting that he never allowed to political considerations to color his judgment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
