<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buying a Car? Location, Location, Location</title>
    <meta content="27SEU2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1072810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DA1F3CF934A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="933" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buying a Car? Location, Location, Location</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>EINOD, Germany</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Grey-market car dealers in Germany make their profits from price differences in Europe and lack of tariff barriers among member countries in European Union; these dealers buy cars at lower prices in other countries and import them to Germany, where they can undercut standard dealers' prices; grey-market dealers see little to fear from advent of euro, saying that consumers already are aware of price differences and car makers are unlikely to equalize prices; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF Europe worked in line with economic theory, Wolfgang Marschall would probably be scared to death about the euro. But he isn't, and his reasons illuminate much about the way Europe works in practice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marschall is general manager of Auto Friesen, a sprawling car dealership in this small town just a few miles from the French border. The lot looks like any other -- colorful flags to attract attention, signs promoting the latest specials and hundreds of new cars on display.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF Europe worked in line with economic theory, Wolfgang Marschall would probably be scared to death about the euro. But he isn't, and his reasons illuminate much about the way Europe works in practice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marschall is general manager of Auto Friesen, a sprawling car dealership in this small town just a few miles from the French border. The lot looks like any other -- colorful flags to attract attention, signs promoting the latest specials and hundreds of new cars on display.</p>
        <p>But unlike ordinary dealers, Mr. Marschall makes his profit by euro-arbitrage. Instead of ordering Volkswagen Passats from German factories, he buys them from other car dealers in Spain, Italy or Denmark. Then he imports them back into Germany, where he still manages to undercut standard dealers' prices.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, Auto Friesen was offering a fully loaded Passat for 36,590 Deutsche marks -- or $22,175 -- about 13 percent less than the price quoted by authorized dealers in Frankfurt. Audi's luxurious A6 Avant was on sale for 69,900 marks, or $42,363, about 5 percent less than the standard price.</p>
        <p>It isn't just German cars. Mr. Marschall also trades in Fiats, Chryslers, Hondas and most other brands sold in Europe.</p>
        <p>''My best deal right now is on Jeep Grand Cherokees,'' he said, strolling through his lot on a snowy afternoon. ''I bought them in the Canary Islands, which has been having a very special offer on them. They're about DM 20,000 below the standard price.''</p>
        <p>Impossible? Not at all. Because incomes in Spain are only about 75 percent of the European average, most car makers offer much lower base prices to Spanish dealers than those in Germany or France, forgoing profits to maintain market share.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marschall and other gray-market resellers readily exploit the price differences, because there are no tariff barriers on cars shipped within the European Union. In Germany, gray-market dealers sell 300,000 cars a year; conventional dealers sell more than 4 million.</p>
        <p>Promoters of the euro argue that the new currency will create ''transparency'' in prices, forcing companies to harmonize their prices across national borders. If so, that would take away the resellers' arbitrage play. But Mr. Marschall betrays little worry about losing his niche.</p>
        <p>''People have known about these price differences for years already,'' he said. ''If the car companies equalized prices, we would be hurt. But I don't think they will do that, because we're really too small a problem for them. If they dropped their prices in Germany, they might take our sales. But they would lose much more money on all the other cars they sell.''</p>
        <p>IN fact, car company executives say price differences on their products across Europe have narrowed considerably in recent years. Nonetheless, they have remained easy targets for gray marketeers. Few consumers travel from France to Spain for cheaper perfume, but many are willing to make the trip if it means saving several thousand dollars on a car.</p>
        <p>''The car industry is the most heavily criticized industry on this question, but it is one of the best behaved,'' said Wolfgang Schneider, vice president of public and government affairs at Ford of Europe, in Cologne. ''If you look at price differences within the euro zone, they are within a band of 10 to 15 percent, net of tax differences. That's much less than in most other consumer products.''</p>
        <p>That is not always the case; a Ford Mondeo at Auto Friesen is about 30 percent cheaper than the standard dealer's price in Frankfurt. But there is evidence to support Mr. Schneider's view, notably in the case of Volkswagen.</p>
        <p>In recent years, VW had been notorious for charging far less in other European countries than in Germany, while systematically blocking dealers in other countries from selling to German re-importers. The European Commission fined the company more than $100 million last year for the latter practice.</p>
        <p>Today, Volkswagens are easier to get and the price variations are modest. Most VW's available at Auto Friesen are priced only slightly less than at authorized dealers.</p>
        <p>Still, some disparities are likely to remain for quite some time, because they are based on tax differences among European countries. In Denmark, which has an extremely high luxury tax on car sales, many car manufacturers lower their base prices to stay in the market. Re-sellers like Mr. Marschall take advantage, because they don't have to pay the luxury tax if they are shipping the cars directly to Germany. Indeed, not counting tax differences, automobile executives say, European car prices don't vary much more than those between different regions of the United States.</p>
        <p>Moreover, car executives acknowledge, prices will remain lower in the European Union's less-affluent countries until incomes catch up to their wealthier neighbors' -- assuring Mr. Marschall and his peers a thriving business, euro or not.</p>
        <p>''Until Spanish standards of living are equal to those in the rest of Europe,'' said Mr. Schneider of Ford, ''there will be price differences.''</p>
        <p>BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
