<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Official From Union Wants To Talk With Commissioner</title>
    <meta content="27NBAA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1072912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Basketball Players Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hunter, Billy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, David (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E5DB173FF934A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Official From Union Wants To Talk With Commissioner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Players union head Billy Hunter wants to resume talks to end National Basketball Association lockout; plans to call Comr David Stern (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The union executive director Billy Hunter shows no signs of giving ground to end the National Basketball Association lockout without the league's reciprocating, but with the Jan. 7 drop-dead date looming, he expects to call Commissioner David Stern today and wants to resume talks this week.</p>
        <p>When reached yesterday at his home in Oakland, Calif., Hunter said he was flying back to New York today and planned to contact Stern, who was vacationing in Aspen, Colo. It is not clear when Stern plans to return, but he has said he can get on a flight at any time to meet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The union executive director Billy Hunter shows no signs of giving ground to end the National Basketball Association lockout without the league's reciprocating, but with the Jan. 7 drop-dead date looming, he expects to call Commissioner David Stern today and wants to resume talks this week.</p>
        <p>When reached yesterday at his home in Oakland, Calif., Hunter said he was flying back to New York today and planned to contact Stern, who was vacationing in Aspen, Colo. It is not clear when Stern plans to return, but he has said he can get on a flight at any time to meet.</p>
        <p>''It's a watch-and-wait situation,'' Hunter said. ''I'm thinking that David and I are going to be talking before the weekend is out, but I just don't know when. Right now I'm not optimistic, because nothing is happening. I don't want to go into specifics, but things continue to be the same.''</p>
        <p>Last week, when Stern set Jan. 7 as the deadline for canceling the season, it spurred some activity but no progress. Hunter said that nothing came of the secret late-night meeting he had with Stern in Los Angeles on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>A meeting this week would probably not be a full bargaining session. Only a few principals, such as the union president Patrick Ewing, and the league's deputy commissioner, Russ Granik, would be likely to join Stern and Hunter.</p>
        <p>There are still major obstacles confronting the two parties, but a swap of compromises could go a long way in resolving the labor dispute, now nearly six months old. The union is prepared to accept the league's proposal for a maximum salary on players with more than six years' experience if the owners will expand the salary cap exception and raise the minimum salary. One union official said Hunter would not compromise unless there was ''a trade, straight up.''</p>
        <p>Herb Williams, the union's vice president, said: ''If we both do some compromising in those areas and work on the numbers, I think the deal can get done. At least we can find out where we both are on those issues if we can meet this week. Hopefully, we can.''</p>
        <p>One major sticking point still exists, though. The union has been adamant about keeping 57 percent of the basketball-related revenue, while the league has not offered more than 53.5 percent. The players feel that a figure of less than 57 percent would mean returning too much of what they have earned. The owners were allowed to reopen the collective bargaining agreement when the players' share exceeded 51.8 percent.</p>
        <p>With less than two weeks to make a deal, the pressure is intense on both sides. Many believe negotiations will run into the deadline and may go beyond it. One agent said he believed a deal could still be reached in mid-January.</p>
        <p>It is a tricky situation for the union and the league as the tension builds. Stern has the task of delivering a deal that the owners will accept and prevent the N.B.A. from becoming the first major professional league to cancel an entire season. Meanwhile, Hunter has watched as Karl Malone called the league's proposal fair and Kevin Willis called for a vote on it.</p>
        <p>''I think it's more difficult for Billy than for David,'' Williams said. ''David has been doing this for a number of years. Billy came in not knowing what deals had been done in the past and what negotiating was done under the table. The only leverage Billy has is the players' standing behind him, and they are. Billy is quick on his feet. He's smart, and he knows the magnitude of getting the right deal. He knows what has to be done.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
