<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hunting Wild Turkey in Wine Country</title>
    <meta content="17napa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/17/travel/escapes/17napa.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1805290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Turkeys</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarke, John Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Wine Country</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Napa Valley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Napa (Calif)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1DD143EF934A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hunting Wild Turkey in Wine Country</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hunting Wild Turkey in Wine Country, Calif.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN CLARKE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarke, John Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on visit to California's wine country to hunt for wild turkey; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was doubtful that we'd have any luck getting wild turkeys this day, our guide said. It was raining hard, the kind of weather that had gobblers and hens lying low and dry in their roosts. But as the car crunched over a gravel road by a small mom-and-pop vineyard and dipped down toward a ravine, the guide, Jeremy Lyons, shouted, ''There!''</p>
        <p>Sure enough, there were three toms and a hen strolling away from the grapevines into the tall grass and olive trees. Though it was the spring turkey hunting season, it was raining hard and so we were out in the hills above downtown Napa simply to spot a few turkeys. And to see if they were eating wine grapes -- a behavior that, local vintners say, damages vineyards and makes them fair game for hunters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vineyard owners say that wild turkeys pose a threat to their grapes; as a result, they are fair game for hunters in Northern California.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was doubtful that we'd have any luck getting wild turkeys this day, our guide said. It was raining hard, the kind of weather that had gobblers and hens lying low and dry in their roosts. But as the car crunched over a gravel road by a small mom-and-pop vineyard and dipped down toward a ravine, the guide, Jeremy Lyons, shouted, ''There!''</p>
        <p>Sure enough, there were three toms and a hen strolling away from the grapevines into the tall grass and olive trees. Though it was the spring turkey hunting season, it was raining hard and so we were out in the hills above downtown Napa simply to spot a few turkeys. And to see if they were eating wine grapes -- a behavior that, local vintners say, damages vineyards and makes them fair game for hunters.</p>
        <p>The wild turkeys that populate 54 of California's 58 counties, including Napa and Sonoma, are the descendants of those introduced to the state more than a century ago. Since then, they have been managed as upland game birds. According to the Guide to Hunting Wild Turkey in California (published by the state Department of Fish and Game), the first recorded release of turkeys into the wild was in 1877 by ranchers on Santa Cruz Island.</p>
        <p>As the birds were introduced elsewhere in the state and their population grew, they were found to feed on grapes (as well as acorns, dandelions, grass and insects). After dining on grapes, they leave behind signs that make vineyard owners grimace: dustings of guano.</p>
        <p>The first state-sanctioned turkey hunt was a one-day event in the autumn of 1968. A spring season was added in 1971. The fall season opens the second Saturday in November and runs 16 days; the spring season opens the last day of March and runs 37 days, with an additional two weeks for bow hunters.</p>
        <p>Moreover, in January 2005, vineyard owners persuaded the state that turkeys were doing so much damage to vineyards that hunting the birds is now allowed on private land throughout the year, as long as it is done with a valid depredation permit.</p>
        <p>''THERE, they're off!'' said Mr. Lyons, pointing to the four birds he had spotted on our trip last May. ''They love the blue oak where it's bushy and dry.''</p>
        <p>The four birds were walking slowly away from the vineyard with a cocky self-assurance, as if to say: ''Be cool, man. Don't run. Be cool. If you run, they'll totally know you're guilty.'' Then Mr. Lyons sighted a fifth turkey -- the biggest of the group.</p>
        <p>''Now you see,'' he said. ''They don't have to go very far to get into trouble. The turkeys here are feeding on big reds,'' he said, meaning cabernet grapes in this small vineyard leased by Kendall-Jackson.</p>
        <p>''But I don't condone turkey hunting depredation permits,'' Mr. Lyons said. ''I think it promotes the wasting of game. I don't like it when vineyard owners allow hunters to just blow them away -- it's despicable.''</p>
        <p>We were on land that once belonged to the 19th-century military commander and rancher Gen. Mariano Vallejo. A smattering of oaks on the hillside and Spanish moss hanging from their twisted limbs lent an eerie feel to the beautiful highland landscape. Two donkeys, named Larry and Moe, grazed on a distant hilltop (Curly had died).</p>
        <p>The property, like many small vineyards dotting California's wine country, is privately owned and leased to wine-industry giants. ''This is the high-end red region for grapes,'' Mr. Lyons said, adding that turkeys seem to prefer heavy reds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lyons tried the difficult task of calling wild turkeys in the rain. His friction calls -- one a wooden box, the other a shallow, round dishlike object -- were getting wet and emitting an improper call that probably sounded like a crazy or sick turkey.</p>
        <p>Lyons demonstrated the ''come hither'' call of a hen. Other calls include the tree yelp, plain yelp, cluck, purr, putt, cackle, cut, kee kee run, hen assembly and assorted gobbles.</p>
        <p>The best way to hunt the turkeys is to get a guide and make plans in advance. Some vineyards allow hunting on their land with depredation permits; the Knoxville State Wildlife Area and Cedar Roughs Wildlife Area both offer excellent public hunting.</p>
        <p>Most hunters use 12- or 20-gauge shotguns; others use bow and arrow and even high-powered pellet guns. Mr. Lyons prefers expensive, high-powered European airguns. Not backyard tin-can shooting Crosman BB guns, but sleek $1,000 German-engineered rifles.</p>
        <p>''It's more difficult,'' he said. ''More sport.''</p>
        <p>Jan Perry, a bow hunter, said that turkeys are ''extremely hard'' to hunt. ''They move around so much,'' she said, ''and they have such fantastic eyesight and color sense. They can spot even the tiniest movement.''</p>
        <p>Tony Giorgi, a hunting guide who is a chapter president of the National Wildlife Turkey Federation, said of Napa and Sonoma Counties: ''People come from all over to go turkey hunting here. Generally, they're in the area with a convention or on a wine-tasting tour, and they'll hear about the turkeys. The spring hunting season is really the big one, but at Thanksgiving, people like the idea of bagging a wild turkey.''</p>
        <p>Sweeney's Sport Store -- 35 years old and one of Napa's two oldest hook-and-bullet shops -- was busy during last spring's season, even offering two kinds of slingshots for hunters. An announcement for a turkey-hunting contest was taped to the store window.</p>
        <p>''It's mainly just something fun for our customers,'' said Chad Hole, a Sweeney's employee and guide who has hunted in the area for 15 years. ''But turkey hunting is really popular here. They're definitely a nuisance and a pest. Vineyard owners will tell you that -- especially after they see flocks eating their grapes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hole said that spring is the better season, when hunters use calls and lure them in. Fall, he said, is more about ambush techniques.</p>
        <p>While wild turkeys are scattered throughout the state, Northern California has the largest population. According to Ryan Mathis, a National Wild Turkey Federation regional biologist, the state's population is continually growing and is estimated at over 200,000. But it is partly kept in check by the 26,000 registered turkey hunters.</p>
        <p>Not everyone is so certain that wild turkeys are such a nuisance to vineyards. A few years ago, at the urging of the wine industry, the National Wild Turkey Federation conducted a study to find out how much damage turkeys do.</p>
        <p>The study found that turkeys were to blame for only a small percentage of crop damage, and that other animals, like deer, ground squirrels, foxes and raccoons, were doing more damage. Recently, bears were added to that list. Tired of having his grapes eaten (at a loss of up to $7,000 for a ton of grapes), the owner of a Napa vineyard hired trappers to kill the bears.</p>
        <p>''Turkeys definitely eat grapes,'' Mr. Mathis said. ''But they don't eat tons of grapes. They're what we call generalists. They eat what is most abundant and what's easiest to get.</p>
        <p>''So in the hot summer months, when temperatures reach over 100 degrees and the grass is dried out and brown, the turkeys move to vineyards with drip lines and clover to eat.''</p>
        <p>ANGELO GARRO, a metalsmith who lives in San Francisco, has been hunting wild turkey in wine country for 20 years. He maintains that the turkey population needs thinning out.</p>
        <p>''They peck on the irrigation hoses and create a lot of damage,'' he said. ''There's just too many of them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Garro, who had hocks of wild boar he had bagged in Sonoma hanging from the ceiling of his workshop and kitchen, talked about the birds he hunts in Napa.</p>
        <p>''The turkeys eat a lot of grapes,'' Mr. Garro said. ''They eat whatever they can find -- like cows. They taste better in the fall. They taste different. Better. All those grapes they eat make them taste different from turkeys back east. In the fall for Thanksgiving, I cook them on a spit -- just add salt, pepper and butter.''</p>
        <p>''And they can fly,'' he added, throwing his arms up excitedly. ''Not many people know they can fly. But there's just too many of them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lyons said wild turkeys were guilty only of enjoying the sun. In the early morning, they tend to come out en masse, open up their wings and warm up.</p>
        <p>''I think people find turkeys a nuisance because they are more visible than other animals and pests that consume grape vineyards,'' he said. So, he added, turkeys appear to be the main culprits because they're out early in the day, arrogantly sunning themselves and eating grapes.</p>
        <p>Within earshot of a roaring stream cutting through the hillside, Mr. Lyons stared out from beneath the brim of his hat.</p>
        <p>''Look,'' he said, ''some of these turkeys are guilty. A friend of mine recently bagged a turkey, and when he cut open his gullet it was full of grape seeds. What can I say? That's one guilty turkey.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
