<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPITZER IS SEEN AS LIKELY TO SEEK HEVESI'S OUSTER</title>
    <meta content="17hevesi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/17/nyregion/17hevesi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1805423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comptrollers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot L (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Alan G (Comptroller)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Hevesi, Alan G</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E7D8143EF934A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1130" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPITZER IS SEEN AS LIKELY TO SEEK HEVESI'S OUSTER</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spitzer Is Likely to Seek Hevesi’s Ouster</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Nov. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov-elect Eliot Spitzer is expected to ask New York State Senate to remove Comptroller Alan G Hevisi after new term begins in Jan; Spitzer is said to be awaiting outcome of three inquiries into Hevesi's use of state worker as chauffeur for his ailing wife before he makes final decision; but he reportedly is inclined to push for Hevesi's removal based on scathing State Ethics Commission report issued last month; Hevesi issues statement reiterating apology he made for his 'mistake' and noting that he won re-election by overwhelming percentage even after matter was made public; many people in Albany expect him to resign rather than submit to trial in Republican-controlled Senate, one of two ways Legislature can remove statewide elected official; second way, considered highly unlikely, would be for Democratic-controlled Assemby to vote to impeach him; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Governor-elect Eliot Spitzer will almost certainly ask the State Senate to remove Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi, who used a state worker as a chauffeur for his ailing wife, after the new term begins in January, people involved in the discussions said on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer, the attorney general until the end of the year, is awaiting the outcome of three inquiries into Mr. Hevesi's conduct -- including one by his own office, from which he has recused himself -- before he makes a final decision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The governor-elect is reportedly inclined to ask the N.Y. State Senate to remove the comptroller.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Governor-elect Eliot Spitzer will almost certainly ask the State Senate to remove Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi, who used a state worker as a chauffeur for his ailing wife, after the new term begins in January, people involved in the discussions said on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer, the attorney general until the end of the year, is awaiting the outcome of three inquiries into Mr. Hevesi's conduct -- including one by his own office, from which he has recused himself -- before he makes a final decision.</p>
        <p>But the governor-elect is inclined to push for Mr. Hevesi's removal based on information disclosed in a scathing State Ethics Commission report issued last month, the people involved in the discussions said. Those people spoke on condition of anonymity because Mr. Spitzer's decision is not final.</p>
        <p>''While a personally painful decision, it's an easy decision because the facts are clear,'' said one person with knowledge of the governor's thinking on the issue. ''What would the drive for greater accountability and a higher ethical standard mean if you tolerated that level of abuse? He will move swiftly and aggressively to remove him.''</p>
        <p>Christine Anderson, a spokeswoman for Mr. Spitzer's transition team, had no comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi, in a statement issued by his office in response to questions for this article, said, ''Honest concern for my wife led me to make a mistake for which I have apologized.</p>
        <p>''Knowing the facts, millions of New Yorkers elected me by an overwhelming percentage to serve another four year term as comptroller,'' he said. ''That is what I intend to do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi, who, like Mr. Spitzer, is a Democrat, reimbursed the state $82,688.82 for the cost of the driver after the issue became public in late September. A few days before the election, Mr. Spitzer's office asked him to place an additional $90,000 in an escrow account pending the outcome of its investigation.</p>
        <p>The Legislature can remove a statewide elected official in two ways. The Democratic-controlled Assembly could vote to impeach Mr. Hevesi. A trial would then be held in the Republican-controlled Senate, which would be joined by judges from the state's highest court, the Court of Appeals. A two-thirds vote would be required to remove him.</p>
        <p>Under the second procedure, the governor could call the Senate into session. A trial would then be held, and a two-thirds vote would be needed to remove Mr. Hevesi.</p>
        <p>Because Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, a Democrat, has been supportive of Mr. Hevesi, Mr. Spitzer is more likely to refer the matter to the Senate, whose Republican leaders have called on Mr. Hevesi to resign. Many Democratic senators are also likely to be swayed by the new governor, who just won election by a record margin.</p>
        <p>The Senate has never removed a statewide elected official from office under the second of these procedures. If it chose to do so with Mr. Hevesi, its action might be subject to legal challenge, some political analysts have said. In 1913, the Assembly impeached Gov. William Sulzer, and he was removed after a trial in the Senate.</p>
        <p>If the Senate removed Mr. Hevesi, the governor would choose his successor. But if Mr. Hevesi resigned, the Legislature as a whole would choose his replacement, giving control to the Democrats.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi had been somewhat buoyed by his re-election last week, when he handily beat a largely unknown candidate. Whether he would submit to a trial in the Senate is unclear, and many people in Albany expect him to resign first.</p>
        <p>Aside from the inquiry by Mr. Spitzer's office, the Albany County district attorney is conducting a criminal investigation of Mr. Hevesi and Gov. George E. Pataki has hired a lawyer to review the recent Ethics Commission report, which suggested Mr. Hevesi had broken the law. Mr. Pataki is not expected to act before his term ends on Dec. 31.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Spitzer, the matter has not been an easy one, since Mr. Hevesi was until recently a close political ally who helped him design his fiscal policies. The issue has also divided Democrats. Some, like Mr. Silver, have criticized the Ethics Commission process.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Spitzer ran on a platform of raising ethical standards in Albany and revamping the way the gridlock-prone state government does business. He believes that Mr. Hevesi cannot continue doing his job with his credibility undermined, people involved in his discussions said. Shortly before the election, Mr. Spitzer withdrew his endorsement of Mr. Hevesi, and the two men have not spoken since the election.</p>
        <p>The investigation by Mr. Spitzer's office will probably end with either a financial settlement or a lawsuit, though not before the end of this month, a person familiar with the investigation said.</p>
        <p>The chauffeur issue became public in September after Mr. Hevesi's Republican opponent, J. Christopher Callaghan, was informed of it by an anonymous tipster. Mr. Hevesi said that he needed a driver for security reasons and because of the failing mental and physical health of his wife, Carol.</p>
        <p>The Ethics Commission, though, found that the State Police had identified her as a ''low-threat risk,'' that her driver had no law enforcement background and was not part of the comptroller's security team.</p>
        <p>The commission also said that the comptroller's office had failed ''to keep any record that would allow for proper reimbursement,'' suggesting that ''Mr. Hevesi did not intend to reimburse the state.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi's lawyers have called the Ethics Commission report a ''rush to judgment'' and said that it omitted important facts, including details from a July 2003 State Police memorandum that indicated there was ''a threat risk'' for Mrs. Hevesi because her husband had been ''the target of numerous threats.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi has apologized repeatedly and said he made a mistake out of concern for his wife. In his victory speech last week, he expressed determination to serve out his second term, promising to ''serve and work hard for the people of New York every day of my next four years.''</p>
        <p>He was ostracized by the rest of the party, though, and delivered his speech in a separate hotel from Mr. Spitzer and the other statewide Democratic candidates.</p>
        <p>His relationship with Mr. Spitzer has particularly soured.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi's conduct became a major issue in Mr. Spitzer's campaign debates, and when Mr. Spitzer withdrew his endorsement of Mr. Hevesi late last month, he said the Ethics Commission report ''presents information that compromises Alan Hevesi's ability to fulfill his responsibilities.''</p>
        <p>The day after the election, at a joint appearance with Governor Pataki, Mr. Spitzer said that he would not interfere with the discussions over Mr. Hevesi's fate during Mr. Pataki's final days.</p>
        <p>But he did say that the matter would be ''my responsibility'' come Jan. 1. ''And at that point,'' he said, ''I will answer all of these questions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
