<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art in Review; Norbert Schwontkowski</title>
    <meta content="17gall-4" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1805409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D9143EF934A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="277" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art in Review; Norbert Schwontkowski</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mitchell-Innes &amp; Nash  1018 Madison Avenue, near 79th Street  Through Wednesday</p>
        <p>The German artist Norbert Schwontkowski, a maker of small, beautiful, rather wispy Whistlerian paintings, is big on context. In the fourth Berlin Biennial at the KW Institute for Contemporary Art last spring, he exhibited small, dark paintings off-site, in what seemed to be a painter's apartment and was, in fact, his own. They were so at home that you almost didn't notice them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mitchell-Innes &amp; Nash  1018 Madison Avenue, near 79th Street  Through Wednesday</p>
        <p>The German artist Norbert Schwontkowski, a maker of small, beautiful, rather wispy Whistlerian paintings, is big on context. In the fourth Berlin Biennial at the KW Institute for Contemporary Art last spring, he exhibited small, dark paintings off-site, in what seemed to be a painter's apartment and was, in fact, his own. They were so at home that you almost didn't notice them.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Schwontkowski has built context into his New York gallery debut by including one painting each by Picasso, Philip Guston and Alex Katz and three by Forrest Bess. The effect is both generous and a bit self-aggrandizing, and either way gives Mr. Schwontkowski a lot to measure up to. He places his ''Winternest,'' a charcoal-on-gray silhouette of barren branches and exposed birds nests, next to Mr. Katz's ''Hamann House 2,'' a 1963 painting in a similar palette of a dark wooded shore extending its shadow over a silvery lake.</p>
        <p>His ''Fischerdorf,'' featuring a tiny moon over another lake, is a bit overpowered by Bess's city nocturne dominated by a bright street light and a similarly compact painting of a kerosene lamp by Guston. Hanging next to Picasso's ''Nude Before a Mirror'' of 1932, Mr. Schwontkowski's painting of a tall fountain and minute pedestrians, despite a shared flamboyance, mostly proves that he might consider doing New Yorker covers.</p>
        <p>As with many painters, Mr. Schwontkowski's sense of what makes a painting work is keener concerning ones he didn't make than ones he did, but it is ultimately touching to see loyalties and debts so openly and astutely acknowledged.</p>
        <p>ROBERTA SMITH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
