<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vision of the Void Behind the California Sun</title>
    <meta content="29WALL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1065633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallach, Amei</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2D71639F93AA15752C1A96E958260" item-length="1594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vision of the Void Behind the California Sun</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMEI WALLACH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wallach, Amei</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amei Wallach reviews exhibit of Los Angeles art scene from 1960 to 1997, which has moved from Louisiana Museum of Modern Art in Copenhagen, Denmark, to Armand Hammer Museum in Los Angeles; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE first time Europeans got a good look at avant-garde New York painting, it was called American painting. The year was 1958 and the Museum of Modern Art's touring exhibition, ''The New American Painting,'' with works by artists like Willem de Kooning and Jackson Pollock, announced to eight European countries that the art world's power center had shifted west across the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Four decades later, the art market may reside in New York, but the center is in transit, a temporary whistle-stop on a global art circuit constantly rushing from Cologne to Johannesburg, from London to Los Angeles. However, New York art is still called American art and Los Angeles art is, well, Los Angeles art.</p>
        <p>This bias has its uses. It makes it possible to consider the art of Los Angeles as a historical and geographical whole, something only fools would try with New York art now. In fact, Los Angeles's own institutions have seldom tried to explore more than discrete sectors of its own local art history, which is as dauntingly digressive as the expressways that define the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE first time Europeans got a good look at avant-garde New York painting, it was called American painting. The year was 1958 and the Museum of Modern Art's touring exhibition, ''The New American Painting,'' with works by artists like Willem de Kooning and Jackson Pollock, announced to eight European countries that the art world's power center had shifted west across the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Four decades later, the art market may reside in New York, but the center is in transit, a temporary whistle-stop on a global art circuit constantly rushing from Cologne to Johannesburg, from London to Los Angeles. However, New York art is still called American art and Los Angeles art is, well, Los Angeles art.</p>
        <p>This bias has its uses. It makes it possible to consider the art of Los Angeles as a historical and geographical whole, something only fools would try with New York art now. In fact, Los Angeles's own institutions have seldom tried to explore more than discrete sectors of its own local art history, which is as dauntingly digressive as the expressways that define the city.</p>
        <p>It took European curators to hold up a mirror of Los Angeles art to the city itself. They've done so in ''Sunshine and Noir: Art in L.A. 1960-1997,'' an exhibition organized by Lars Nittve and Helle Crenzien for the Louisiana Museum of Modern Art near Copenhagen, where it opened in the summer of 1997, the year Forbes Magazine counseled ''cutting-edge collectors'' to ''head directly to Los Angeles . . . one of the world's hottest centers for new art.'' After stops in Germany and Italy, ''Sunshine and Noir'' has finally made its way here, where it remains on view at the Armand Hammer Museum of Art and Cultural Center through Jan. 3.</p>
        <p>The exhibition offers a darkly romantic take on Los Angeles, imagined from the cultural products of this one-industry town in which art has had to fight for elbow room. The subtext of ''Sunshine and Noir'' comes from the movies -- the helicopters and phone sex in ''Short Cuts,'' the self-fulfilling paranoia of ''Chinatown,'' the corruption of ''L.A. Confidential.''</p>
        <p>''It has always been sunny in California, but noir came from Berlin, via the talents of emigres like Fritz Lang, Robert Sidomak and Billy Wilder,'' writes Russell Ferguson, an associate curator at the Museum of Contemporary Art, in the exhibition catalogue.</p>
        <p>This is a Los Angeles encountered more often in movie theaters than on travel posters, as often on CNN as in the international art fairs, where Paul McCarthy fulfills European visions of dislocation and the void with brutal videos in which ketchup splatters like body fluids and every expectation is frustrated. Europeans have always arrived in Los Angeles to find what they expect to see: for the artist David Hockney in the 1970's, a sexy, technicolor gloss on Matisse; for the curator Lars Nittve in the 1990's, an edgy, glamour-drenched vision of Helltown and Eden. Mr. Nittve writes in the catalogue: ''As the 747 glides slowly over 'gangland,' Compton and Watts, the city is transformed into a surface of lights . . . punctuated only by the spotlights of some police helicopters, the flames of the oil refineries at El Segundo, and the festive play of searchlights against the sky at some gala premiere way up in Hollywood.''</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles art world generally credits Mr. Nittve with making the choices for the exhibition and considers it one curator's view; it consists of 200 works (and an exhaustive video program) by 49 artists, 40 of whom are white men. Homogeneous Denmark has only recently begun to learn what it means to have any immigrant population at all, let alone the teeming cultural mix that animates and aggravates Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>In Denmark, this exhibition opened with a cordon of 12 of Chris Burden's ''L.A.P.D. Uniforms'' from 1993, each seven feet tall and made of leather, cloth and metal. They are at once an homage to the influential postwar artist Joseph Beuys, whose felt suits were a prop in his project to exorcize the German past, and an ominous reminder of the role of the police in the Los Angeles riots. Michael Duncan, writing for Art in America, took issue with what he called the show's ''lackadaisical organizational approach'' when it was in Denmark. Its ''quick flips between lighter and darker sensibilities established a somewhat schizophrenic tone,'' he wrote. The Europeans didn't particularly know what to make of the paintings of Joe Goode or the sculptures of Tony Berlant from the 60's, because it wasn't until some years later, with the conceptualism of John Baldessari and Bruce Nauman, that they met a match for their love of theoretical constructs. In the 1980's and 90's, the romance between Europe and Los Angeles heated up as artists like Jason Rhoades, Mike Kelley, Nancy Rubin, Lari Pittman and Jennifer Pastor became the darlings of the international art circuit. So in Denmark, ''Sunshine and Noir'' featured the noir of the hot and the new.</p>
        <p>But the steward of the exhibition in Los Angeles is Henry Hopkins, who is the living memory of L.A. art since the 1950's, as well as current director of the Hammer Museum. (He is to be succeeded in January by Ann Philbin, from the Drawing Center in New York, so that he can go back to teaching.) Mr. Hopkins has taken an opposite approach to the exhibition's installation. He has added stronger pieces from the early years and cut down the scale or made substitutions for more recent work.</p>
        <p>He opens the exhibition with what he calls ''sunshine'' -- Craig Kauffman's 1968 wall relief, ''Bubble,'' its lacquered acrylic surface emanating the sleekly cloudy gleam of a brand-new surfboard in the California sun. From there the show proceeds in more or less orderly fashion with works like Doug Wheeler's 1969 investigation of light as optical atmosphere in ''Rm 669''; the perceptual experiments of Robert Irwin and the Light and Space Movement and its flip side, the funky, politically outraged, stagy and storytelling assemblages of Edward Kienholz and George Herms; Ed Ruscha's text-based urban sprawl version of Pop Art, and the deconstruction of art and its stand-ins according to Mr. Baldessari and the students he spawned at Cal Arts.</p>
        <p>But the 90's portion of the Los Angeles exhibition is a mess, with lesser pieces substituted for huge ones to fit the disjointed space of the Hammer Museum. Mr. Burden's ''L.A.P.D. Uniforms'' is squashed in a room together with Mr. Pittman's 1995 ''Like You,'' a snide mural-size narrative of pop decoration and gay life and death; Jim Isermann's sculptural investigations of the intersection of interior design and sculpture, and Kim Dingle's 1994-95 ''Priss Room Installation,'' with its malevolent infant mannequins and the mayhem they have produced.</p>
        <p>FOR all its jumble, this is a curiously subdued exhibition, more intent on getting it all in than on trying to clarify the ideas behind the objects and performances, or for that matter to indicate that there is any mind at work here at all. And yet Los Angeles art is almost by definition theoretical art, bred in the universities, where leading artists teach and develop. The Europeans got that right, even if their exhibition didn't. Artists isolated on far-flung boulevards off freeway exits may complain about a lack of community, but there is no lack of conversation.</p>
        <p>''There's a sense of academy in L.A., but you can't really identify what it is,'' says Bonnie Clearwater, formerly of the Lannon Foundation and now director of the Museum of Contemporary Art in Miami. ''It's a general discussion, and somehow the work taps into the dialogue.''</p>
        <p>The conversation is to continue in the year 2000, when a consortium of Los Angeles County Museum of Art curators, led by Stephanie Barron, mounts a 100-year retrospective of California art.</p>
        <p>L.A.'s response to ''Sunshine and Noir'' is roughly equivalent to the consternation in Copenhagen that must regularly greet American surveys of Danish art. ''If the shark is the last one to criticize saltwater, maybe it does take an outsider to see things,'' says Mr. Baldessari. ''But there are glaring omissions. I was so appalled I'm pulling my work out.'' He expressed his chagrin at being crammed into a corner behind Mr. Kelley's huge, bombastic sendup of torture, ''Primaling Cabinet'' of 1992, by pulling four works and substituting a single text piece from 1966-67. ''Space Available'' it says.</p>
        <p>Views from abroad may seem flattering in the abstract, but they tend to shortchange nuance and precision. Mr. Hopkins is making up for what Mr. Nittve didn't get by seeing that 30 Los Angeles galleries have mounted complementary exhibitions and programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nittve missed the central contributions of Bettye Saar as well as Mr. Isermann's roots in the sculptural ceramics of Peter Voulkos. But somehow, amid it all, some artists managed to steal the show unexpectedly. Vija Celmins's 1966 ''Freeway'' is a clear-sighted version of the European romance with noir: It is L.A., boxy and bland, seen from the terrible solitude behind a windshield, going somewhere fast.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE Amei Wallach and the filmmaker Marion Cajori are making a feature film about Louise Bourgeois and her century.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Amei Wallach and the filmmaker Marion Cajori are making a feature film about Louise Bourgeois and her century.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
