<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Marshall Plan</title>
    <meta content="29SHIPLET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1066027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Juan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marshall, Thurgood (1908-93)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shipler, David K</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Thurgood Marshall: American Revolutionary (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E1DC1230F93AA15752C1A96E958260" item-length="1280" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Marshall Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David K. Shipler</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shipler, David K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David K Shipler reviews biography Thurgood Marshall: American Revolutionary, by Juan Williams; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THURGOOD MARSHALL</p>
        <p>American Revolutionary.</p>
        <p>By Juan Williams.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 459 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Times Books/Random House. $27.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THURGOOD MARSHALL</p>
        <p>American Revolutionary.</p>
        <p>By Juan Williams.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 459 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Times Books/Random House. $27.50.</p>
        <p>Reading a biography of the great civil rights lawyer Thurgood Marshall (1908-93) is good treatment for the disease of complacency about race relations. Progress does not look inevitable when you watch the powerful resistance that confronted Marshall's every step to gain rights for blacks. Nor do all the advances seem irreversible when you witness the backsliding that embittered his later years as the first black Justice on the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>Despite his towering victories, he retired from the Court in 1991 not in a victorious spirit but in anguish over a task that remained woefully incomplete. As an NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund attorney, he had won landmark Supreme Court decisions overturning segregation and discrimination in elections, housing, transportation and education. Yet as a justice he saw his influence wane as the Court swung to the right, leaving him isolated and angry -- and unappreciated by a generation of blacks no longer enamored of integration and too young to remember the struggles he had waged since the 1930's. Some regard him as having been a better lawyer than judge.</p>
        <p>The story of his extraordinary life contains a measure of our history, so his exhilaration and melancholy reflect more than a man's moods. They represent our national experience, which takes us to the heights of decency one moment and to the depths of bigotry the next. That larger landscape, illuminated as Marshall passes through, is deftly sketched by Juan Williams in ''Thurgood Marshall: American Revolutionary.''</p>
        <p>The term ''revolutionary'' might seem exaggerated for a man who worked wholly within the judicial system, albeit using the Constitution as a weapon of liberation. But on the first page Williams labels Marshall ''one of America's leading radicals,'' places him in a triumvirate with Malcolm X and Martin Luther King Jr. and argues that it was Thurgood Marshall who ''stood as the one with the biggest impact on American race relations.'' The ranking is debatable, but it would surely have pleased Marshall, who detested the separatism of Malcolm X; ''I think we called each other sons of bitches'' at a chance meeting on a Harlem street, Marshall told Williams. In private, Marshall also disparaged King and opposed most demonstrations -- even the Montgomery bus boycott and the lunch counter sit-ins -- as senseless invitations to violence. He initially resisted defending black students arrested at a sit-in, because he thought they had violated private property rights at a Woolworth's in Greensboro, N.C. He gives no sign, in Williams's portrait, of recognizing how King's movement mobilized the conscience of the country, creating the climate in which courtroom triumphs could be enforced.</p>
        <p>Williams is an accomplished reporter with The Washington Post who wrote ''Eyes on the Prize: America's Civil Rights Years, 1954-1965,'' the companion volume to the public television series. His skills at digging out facts have been tested here, for although he did a dozen interviews with Justice Marshall over six months in 1989, he was unable to gain access to the Legal Defense Fund's files, and Marshall's children and second wife, Cissy, declined to cooperate. Still, Williams interviewed widely, assembled accounts of debates and maneuvers within the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People and obtained documents revealing Marshall's sporadic cooperation with J. Edgar Hoover. The book is a strong piece of journalism crammed with fascinating detail, done in an unassuming style driven by the factual narrative.</p>
        <p>It portrays Marshall as a curious mixture of stubbornness and accommodation, a gruff wit who chased women and drank heavily and a dedicated lawyer who repeatedly ventured into the dangers of the South to defend blacks being railroaded on murder, rape and other charges. In 1946, he was nearly lynched with the help of the local police in Columbia, Tenn., after he got an all-white jury to acquit 23 of 25 blacks charged in riots started by whites. ''One local paper said the trial was packed with spectators who came to town to see 'those niggers up there wearing coats and ties and talking back to the judge just like they were white men,' '' Williams writes.</p>
        <p>A native of Baltimore, Marshall knew how to avoid provoking whites' resentment over an ''uppity'' black, and so he adopted a charming deference in his arguments before the Supreme Court. ''His light humor made the young black lawyer a fast favorite among the older white justices,'' Williams observes. ''Marshall always took a moment to thank the justices, whisper some confidence and make each of them feel as if he were relying on their superior knowledge to help him through the maze of laws.'' Near the end of his Court career 45 years later, though, he issued rare public criticisms of his conservative colleagues.</p>
        <p>As a reporter's book and not a legal history, this biography offers little from Marshall's briefs, opinions and dissents -- perhaps a reasonable choice, since these documents are available elsewhere. But we never quite see Marshall's legal mind at work. Williams tells of his powerful orations, but rarely shows us more than fragmentary quotations, even as Marshall argues the famous school desegregation case, Brown v. Board of Education, before the Supreme Court. A more serious flaw</p>
        <p>lies in Williams's uncritical use of McCarthy-era innuendo to describe certain civil rights activists as ''Communist-backed'' or having ''Communist ties.'' As a pre-emptive defense of the N.A.A.C.P., Marshall exchanged information on such people and groups with Hoover, who was obsessed by Communists, both actual and phantom. But Williams treats the paranoia unquestioningly. His reporting stops far short of defining the boundary between reality and fantasy, leaving his readers unsure about Marshall's role in this other crucial test of American democracy, which raised issues of free speech and free association. It is the book's largest defect.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the book offers a valuable picture of the odd Marshall-Hoover liaison. The F.B.I. Director placed Marshall under surveillance and resented his complaints that F.B.I. agents were covering up for white sheriffs' departments sympathetic to mob violence against blacks. But when the two met in 1947, Marshall ''won Hoover over with his charming, good-ol'-boy, 'I'm a little ol' Baltimore lawyer' persona,'' Williams writes. The Director offered a collaborative relationship, and Marshall suggested that the N.A.A.C.P. could defuse accusations of racism in the F.B.I. if the F.B.I. would investigate attacks on blacks. Both men got a little of what they wanted.</p>
        <p>This volume captures the sweep of Marshall's impact beyond the civil rights movement, for as lawyer and judge and justice, he expanded the rights of all Americans. Williams shows him influencing fellow justices in rulings that recognized the right to abortions, indigent defendants' right to state-paid psychiatrists, protections against double jeopardy in state courts and the right of defendants not to have jurors excluded on racial grounds. He helped shape the narrow decision to abolish the death penalty in 1972, but saw it reinstated by the Court several years later.</p>
        <p>The power of his presence was formidable. ''Marshall could be a persuasive force by just sitting there,'' the conservative Justice Antonin Scalia told Williams. ''Anyone who spoke in conference on one of these race issues had to be looking at Thurgood. . . . He wouldn't have had to open his mouth to affect the nature of the conference and how seriously the conference would take matters of race.'' The vacuum now is enormous.</p>
        <p>David K. Shipler, a former correspondent for The Times, won a Pulitzer Prize in 1987 for ''Arab and Jew: Wounded Spirits in a Promised Land.'' His most recent book is ''A Country of Strangers: Blacks and Whites in America.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David K. Shipler, a former correspondent for The Times, won a Pulitzer Prize in 1987 for ''Arab and Jew: Wounded Spirits in a Promised Land.'' His most recent book is ''A Country of Strangers: Blacks and Whites in America.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
