<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pronger Is More Than a Presence for the Oilers</title>
    <meta content="17nhl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/17/sports/hockey/17nhl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1769685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Carolina Hurricanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Edmonton Oilers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stanley Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stanley Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Edmonton Oilers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pronger, Chris</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EEDA1131F934A25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pronger Is More Than a Presence for the Oilers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pronger Is More Than a Presence for the Oilers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>EDMONTON, Alberta, June 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At 6 feet 6 inches tall, Edmonton Oilers defenseman Chris Pronger towers over opponents and sees more ice than just about anyone in the N.H.L.</p>
        <p>''He's done that since he was 16 when he played junior hockey,'' said Carolina Hurricanes left wing Cory Stillman, who played with the 220-pound Pronger in juniors and with the St. Louis Blues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At 6 feet 6 inches tall, Edmonton Oilers defenseman Chris Pronger towers over opponents and sees more ice than just about anyone in the N.H.L.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At 6 feet 6 inches tall, Edmonton Oilers defenseman Chris Pronger towers over opponents and sees more ice than just about anyone in the N.H.L.</p>
        <p>''He's done that since he was 16 when he played junior hockey,'' said Carolina Hurricanes left wing Cory Stillman, who played with the 220-pound Pronger in juniors and with the St. Louis Blues.</p>
        <p>''He played every other shift there,'' Stillman said. ''He played every other shift in St. Louis. He's always been on the ice. So wearing him out, that's not going to happen. He's been doing it for 15 years.''</p>
        <p>The Stanley Cup playoffs have been no exception. Pronger has averaged 31 minutes 11 seconds in 22 postseason games, second only to Nicklas Lidstrom, who averaged 31:54 in six games for Detroit. (The Oilers eliminated the Red Wings in the first round.)</p>
        <p>With Pronger leading the way, the Oilers became the first eighth-seeded team to reach the Stanley Cup finals. And after avoiding elimination Wednesday night with a 4-3 victory in overtime, they will play host to Game 6 on Saturday night. Carolina leads the best-of-seven series, 3-2.</p>
        <p>The Oilers are trying to become only the second team in finals history to rally from a 3-1 deficit to win the Cup. If they do, Pronger will be the favorite to win the Conn Smythe Trophy, awarded to the most valuable player of the playoffs. He leads all defensemen with 5 goals, 16 assists and 21 points in the postseason.</p>
        <p>''I am exhausted,'' the 31-year-old Pronger deadpanned when asked what it was like to play so much. ''I can't even answer your question. I am too tired.''</p>
        <p>Pronger is in his first season with Edmonton after nine with St. Louis. Oilers Coach Craig MacTavish even played part of two seasons with Pronger.</p>
        <p>''I knew he was a terrific player, but this would have been at the top of my expectations to see the way that he plays the game each and every night,'' said MacTavish, who called Pronger a truly great player because he makes his teammates better.</p>
        <p>With all his success with the Blues -- he won the Hart and Norris trophies as the league's most valuable player and top defenseman for the 1999-2000 season -- Pronger had never played in the Cup finals.</p>
        <p>''It's been nice,'' he said. ''But we're still two wins away from the Cup and it would be pretty disappointing if we don't win Saturday. I don't think anybody in the locker room is looking past that. We have to win tomorrow and get to a Game 7.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Carolina Coach Peter LAVIOLETTE confirmed that center Doug Weight (shoulder sprain) would not be available for Game 6.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
