<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Budget's Low Growth Rate for Medicare Is Questioned by Lawmakers</title>
    <meta content="Y06HEA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/06/politics/06HEAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1365507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E5D81E3DF935A35751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Budget's Low Growth Rate for Medicare Is Questioned by Lawmakers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Budget's Low Growth Rate for Medicare Is Questioned by Lawmakers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Members of Congress and health policy experts question projections in Pres Bush's new budget showing extraordinarily slow growth in Medicare over next decade; White House estimate is $300 billion less than that of Congressional Budget Office estimated; assuming slower rate of growth for Medicare saves money, but it avoids political uproar that would surround proposal for large cuts in Medicare (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's new budget shows extraordinarily slow growth in Medicare over the next decade, puzzling members of Congress and health policy experts, who say the numbers appear to be unrealistic.</p>
        <p>Reasons for the slow growth remained something of a mystery today as lawmakers pored over the budget that Mr. Bush unveiled on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's new budget shows extraordinarily slow growth in Medicare over the next decade, prompting criticism from members of Congress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's new budget shows extraordinarily slow growth in Medicare over the next decade, puzzling members of Congress and health policy experts, who say the numbers appear to be unrealistic.</p>
        <p>Reasons for the slow growth remained something of a mystery today as lawmakers pored over the budget that Mr. Bush unveiled on Monday.</p>
        <p>Assuming a slower rate of growth for Medicare has the same effect as cutting the Medicare budget; it saves money. But it avoids the political uproar that would surround a proposal for large cuts in Medicare.</p>
        <p>The White House estimate of total Medicare spending in the next decade, assuming a continuation of current policy, is $300 billion less than estimated by the nonpartisan Congressional Budget Office. That figure represents about 10 percent of what Medicare is expected to spend in the next 10 years, according to the administration.</p>
        <p>The budget office, the official scorekeeper for Congress, estimated last month that Medicare spending would double in the next decade under existing laws. By contrast, Mr. Bush said that Medicare spending would grow 73 percent in the next decade, even though the rolls would begin to swell with the addition of the first baby boomers in 2011 and 2012.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, Medicare spending doubled, to $238 billion last year.</p>
        <p>The president's budget does not explain why the administration expects slower growth of Medicare in coming years. Robert D. Reischauer, who was director of the Congressional Budget Office from 1989 to 1995, called the prediction puzzling.</p>
        <p>Trent D. Duffy, a spokesman for the White House Office of Management and Budget, said the estimates were based on projections by experts at the Department of Health and Human Services. ''The administration follows the nonpartisan Medicare actuaries' estimates,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A Bush administration official acknowledged that the growth in Medicare assumed in the budget ''does seem pretty modest, compared with prior years,'' but cited several reasons for the differing estimates. The Congressional Budget Office, he said, expects greater use of health care by Medicare beneficiaries and more inflation in the prices of goods and services used by hospitals.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, Medicare grew an average of 7.6 percent a year. But with no change in existing law, the White House says, the program will grow an average of just 4.6 percent a year in the next five years.</p>
        <p>If White House estimates are correct, Medicare would grow more slowly in the next decade than it has in any 10-year period since its creation in 1965. It would also grow more slowly than projected spending by private health insurance plans, and Medicare spending for the average beneficiary would not keep pace with medical inflation.</p>
        <p>The estimates have major fiscal and political implications. Medicare, which provides health insurance to 40 million elderly and disabled people, is one of the largest programs in the federal budget.</p>
        <p>Rapid growth in Medicare worsens the overall budget picture, raising a deficit or reducing a surplus. Conversely, if Medicare is growing slowly or moderately, it will be easier for Mr. Bush and Congress to keep commitments to add new benefits, like prescription-drug coverage.</p>
        <p>With no change in existing law, Mr. Bush said, Medicare will cost the government $3 trillion in the next decade, after taking account of premiums paid by beneficiaries. By contrast, the Congressional Budget Office puts the cost at $3.3 trillion.</p>
        <p>Senator John B. Breaux, Democrat of Louisiana, said he saw no signs of a slowing of Medicare growth. On Capitol Hill, he said, ''most people are talking about spending more, not less -- about putting back money for doctors and hospitals'' cut in 1997.</p>
        <p>Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts, asked how Medicare growth could slow when ''health care costs are going up and the number of seniors is on the rise?''</p>
        <p>The Congressional Budget Office sees Medicare growing an average of about 7 percent a year in the coming decade, while the Bush administration foresees increases averaging about 5.5 percent a year.</p>
        <p>John C. Rother, policy director of AARP, which represents millions of Medicare beneficiaries, said that ''the administration produces a more favorable overall budget picture by forecasting lower rates of growth in Medicare.''</p>
        <p>President Bush has called for sweeping changes in Medicare, to give beneficiaries a wider choice of private health plans, like those available to federal employees.</p>
        <p>A federal advisory commission recommended last month that Medicare payments to doctors, hospitals, home care agencies and health maintenance organizations be raised. Many lawmakers said they would try to do so this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
