<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Front Row</title>
    <meta content="Y05FRON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/05/living/05FRON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1299094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sex and the City (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (New York)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Dolce &amp; Gabbana</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Dkny</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Byblos</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Council of Fashion Designers of America</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Brown &amp; Wood</org>
        <org class="online_producer">IMG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Seventh on Sixth</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Field, Patricia</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cumming, Alan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bushnell, Candace</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Klein, Calvin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Herman, Stan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3D9123FF936A35755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Front Row</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ginia Bellafante</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Front Row column discusses fashions worn by actresses in televisin program Sex and the City; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sex and the Closet</p>
        <p>If the first two episodes of this season's ''Sex and the City'' are any measure, Carrie Bradshaw might have a challenge keeping the attention of Mr. Big, unless Mr. Big has come to envision the ideal woman as someone in the image of Bjork. Carrie, unlike Bjork, never wrapped herself in a giant swan, but her clothes seemed to reach for a level of eccentricity not lavishly appreciated outside the context of Japanese fashion magazines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sex and the Closet</p>
        <p>If the first two episodes of this season's ''Sex and the City'' are any measure, Carrie Bradshaw might have a challenge keeping the attention of Mr. Big, unless Mr. Big has come to envision the ideal woman as someone in the image of Bjork. Carrie, unlike Bjork, never wrapped herself in a giant swan, but her clothes seemed to reach for a level of eccentricity not lavishly appreciated outside the context of Japanese fashion magazines.</p>
        <p>In the course of one hour on Sunday night, Carrie, the dogged romantic and sample-sale fiend played by Sarah Jessica Parker, wore, at various turns, a vintage nurse's cape, bustier and fingerless white gloves that made her look like a deranged nanny; a Prada headband that looked as if it were on its way to morphing into a Davy Crockett cap; and what appeared to be a muslin bra over a slip dress, which left the impression that Carrie had dressed herself with the Sunday morning leavings from the floor of a frat house.</p>
        <p>''We kind of work bit by bit,'' Patricia Field, a costume designer on ''Sex and the City,'' explained. ''We have certain ideas we might want to try, but we don't have a grand master plan.''</p>
        <p>A few of the looks selected by Ms. Field -- a dress in an upholstery pattern and a sweater depicting a deer roaming in a forest -- came from the French designer Jean-Charles de Castelbajac, whom Ms. Field visited in Paris earlier this year when she was attending the couture shows.</p>
        <p>What inspired Ms. Field to put Carrie in knee-high argyle socks paired with high-heel sandals -- a look that never quite imparts the idea that the wearer is a functioning, job-holding person with her own A.T.M. card -- is harder to say.</p>
        <p>''We just thought, 'Oh, this looks cute,' '' Ms. Field said. ''It was supposed to be cold out or something like that.''</p>
        <p>One imagines that it wasn't supposed to be too cold at the charity fashion show that Carrie participated in during the second episode. Asked to model a Dolce &amp; Gabbana gown, Carrie, at the behest of a nutty stylist played by Alan Cumming, wound up walking down the runway in jewel-encrusted briefs and a thigh-high silk evening coat (and, winningly, in last season's Versace hair). This was the closest she got to authenticity -- or, rather, to looking like Carrie's creator, Candace Bushnell.</p>
        <p>A Wide Choice of Adrovers</p>
        <p>Editors, it appears, are not the only ones in the fashion community to have quickly outgrown their infatuation with a certain proclaimed genius. Retailers may have, too.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago, a visitor to Loehmann's, the discount clothing emporium on lower Seventh Avenue, came upon racks of clothes, estimated in the hundreds of pieces, belonging not to the Calvin Klein, DKNY or Byblos collections of three seasons ago -- typical fare at the Manhattan store -- but rather to American fashion's most recently anointed superstar, Miguel Adrover. The clothes came from Mr. Adrover's spring 2001 collection, inspired by the world of the military and lauded by critics. Jackets at stores like Barneys were originally priced at $1,500.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, it is in the nature of our business that you are never able to predict your cuttings exactly,'' Gary Nelson, head of sales for Miguel Adrover, said, referring to the risks inherent in producing clothing lines. ''I don't know a single designer in the world who hasn't had excess inventory.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nelson added that Mr. Adrover's clothes are in eight Loehmann's stores and that some of those have about 20 pieces each. He also attributed the overstock to the line's rapid expansion. ''Our distribution grew dramatically from fall to spring,'' he said. ''We literally expanded globally.''</p>
        <p>The Fashion Council Chooses</p>
        <p>Today, the 26-member board of the Council of Fashion Designers of America, a group claiming Diane Von Furstenberg, Calvin Klein and Carolina Herrera as members, will convene to select an executive director, and the man expected to be named is not a son of their own.</p>
        <p>Stan Herman, the president of the council, said that the only candidate being considered is Peter Arnold, a 43-year-old lawyer at the firm of Brown &amp; Wood.</p>
        <p>If confirmed, Mr. Wood will replace Fern Mallis, the council's current executive director, who plans to join IMG, the talent agency, which will officially take over the Seventh on Sixth fashion shows. Relieved of the responsibility of producing that event, the council will focus more on fund-raising.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arnold would not comment on the prospect of becoming the council's new director.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
