<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zone Wars: Umpire Slices It Lower and Wider</title>
    <meta content="08ZONE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1052475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: LEAGUE CHAMPIONSHIP SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Umpires</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henry, Ted</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Umpires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFD6153BF93BA35753C1A96E958260" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zone Wars: Umpire Slices It Lower and Wider</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses poor performance of plate umpire Ted Hendry in second game of American League Championship Series between New York Yankees and Cleveland Indians; Hendry not only seemingly ignored fact that Travis Fryman was out of base line during controversial bunt play in 12th inning that contributed to Indians's 4-1 victory but called many pitches strikes during game that seemed to be off plate (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ted Hendry, the plate umpire, interpreted the strike zone consistently, which is exactly what players say they prefer. But Hendry's strike zone, as always, was larger than most, perhaps a couple of inches beyond the black border on either side of the plate, perhaps an inch lower than most strike zones. These parameters changed the way yesterday's Yankees-Indians game was played, both benefiting and hurting both sides.</p>
        <p>David Cone usually relies on his slider, and yet in the early innings, he could not maintain his mechanics, his front shoulder flying open, and he could not control the pitch, leaving him vulnerable; Cone needs his slider to keep opposing batters from locking in on his fastball. He kept falling behind in the count, against 6 of the first 11 batters he faced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ted Hendry, the plate umpire, interpreted the strike zone consistently, which is exactly what players say they prefer. But Hendry's strike zone, as always, was larger than most, perhaps a couple of inches beyond the black border on either side of the plate, perhaps an inch lower than most strike zones. These parameters changed the way yesterday's Yankees-Indians game was played, both benefiting and hurting both sides.</p>
        <p>David Cone usually relies on his slider, and yet in the early innings, he could not maintain his mechanics, his front shoulder flying open, and he could not control the pitch, leaving him vulnerable; Cone needs his slider to keep opposing batters from locking in on his fastball. He kept falling behind in the count, against 6 of the first 11 batters he faced.</p>
        <p>But Cone and his catcher, Joe Girardi, recognized quickly that Hendry was particularly generous calling inside strikes on left-handed batters, and through the middle innings, Cone would keep firing fastballs at that one spot whenever he needed a big pitch. Cone threw a staggering 32 pitches in the fourth inning, but allowed just one run, on a home run by David Justice. Two of the three outs in the inning were on called third strikes, on inside fastballs to the left-handed batters Omar Vizquel and Jim Thome. Hendry's strike zone bought Cone time to find his stuff.</p>
        <p>Hendry's strike zone, too, foiled the strategy of the Yankees' hitters, to take pitches and work Cleveland's Charles Nagy deep into ball-strike counts. Twelve of the first 13 Yankee batters took the first pitch, to little effect; the wider strike zone put them on the defensive thereafter, and Nagy needed only 66 pitches to get through the first six innings. The Yankees had only three hits and -- horrors -- they trailed, 1-0, in the seventh.</p>
        <p>Bernie Williams opened the home half of the inning with a single, however, and Tino Martinez drew a four-pitch walk. The rally appeared to crumble when Tim Raines tried unsuccessfully to drop a sacrifice bunt -- something he had never attempted in the regular season -- and then struck out. When Shane Spencer smashed a long drive to deep center, Kenny Lofton catching it near the wall for the second out, Williams tagged up and moved to third. Scott Brosius, who led the American League with a .374 average with runners in scoring position this year, then pulled a high off-speed pitch into the left-field corner, driving home Williams with the tying run. Nagy was removed, disconsolate as he slumped off the mound.</p>
        <p>In a sense, the equalizer for Brosius occurred five innings later. With the Indians ahead by 4-1 and trying to close out the game in the bottom of the 12th, Brosius appeared surprised when he was called out on strikes by Hendry. The strikeout pitch, by the Cleveland closer Mike Jackson, seemed a few inches off the outside edge of the plate, but for Hendry, consistent with some of his earlier calls.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: LEAGUE CHAMPIONSHIP SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
