<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; A No-Brainer Of His Own Creation</title>
    <meta content="08ARAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1052458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Umpires</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Umpires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6D6153BF93BA35753C1A96E958260" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; A No-Brainer Of His Own Creation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column discusses controversial play at first base that led to Cleveland Indians winning second game of American League Championship Series against New York Yankees; photo M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALONG with the anxiety of a series taken for granted that has suddenly turned scary comes the time-honored tradition of the second-guess. As in: try to guess what Chuck Knoblauch could have possibly been thinking as he staked the outcome of a 4-hour-28-minute marathon on the assumption that an umpire's call would go his way.</p>
        <p>Little leaguers are admonished for what Knoblauch did, or didn't do, as he waited for Umpire Ted Hendry to lift his right arm in the 12th inning last night at Yankee Stadium. He stood on first base, the ball behind him in the infield dirt, as the winning run circled the bases. Inexcusable for a little leaguer. Unfathomable for a major league ball player, and not because he happens to earn $6 million a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALONG with the anxiety of a series taken for granted that has suddenly turned scary comes the time-honored tradition of the second-guess. As in: try to guess what Chuck Knoblauch could have possibly been thinking as he staked the outcome of a 4-hour-28-minute marathon on the assumption that an umpire's call would go his way.</p>
        <p>Little leaguers are admonished for what Knoblauch did, or didn't do, as he waited for Umpire Ted Hendry to lift his right arm in the 12th inning last night at Yankee Stadium. He stood on first base, the ball behind him in the infield dirt, as the winning run circled the bases. Inexcusable for a little leaguer. Unfathomable for a major league ball player, and not because he happens to earn $6 million a year.</p>
        <p>So hold the confetti. Put away those brooms. The Cleveland Indians, 4-1 winners in 12 exhausting innings yesterday at Yankee Stadium, will not be swept. If they can win two of three back home in Jacobs Field this weekend, the most decorated team in American League history will return home next week to face elimination in Game 6.</p>
        <p>All right, that sounds mighty dire for a team that could just as easily win the next three, but that's the typical playoff mind game, day after gut-wrenching day. That's a message to those who were going over those World Series pitching matchups with Atlanta already. Stuff happens. Kids interfere with home run balls. Major leaguers suffer brain lock.</p>
        <p>The real post-season began yesterday, after four games that looked like George Steinbrenner's blueprint for his own fantasy. A tense, fierce struggle resulted in a series of failed Yankee opportunities, one or two debatable moves by Joe Torre and, finally, Knoblauch's dishonoring of the most rudimentary rule in sports.</p>
        <p>Did he have a case that Travis Fryman was running in the baseline, as Fryman bunted pinch-runner Enrique Wilson to second, with no one out in the 12th? Yes, he did, even though the crew chief Jim Evans said Fryman was entitled to be where he was as he hit first base. The replay showed that Fryman was never between the restraining lines as he tried to beat Tino Martinez's throw from behind him. The ball arrived as Fryman did, hit Fryman in the back, bounced 15 feet behind Knoblauch, who didn't even turn around to look for the ball.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was a no-brainer,'' he would say, an unfortunate choice of words from the man who amazingly stood in his tracks, pointing at the baseline as Wilson and Fryman did what that unofficial manual for every player, 8 and over, commands you to do: Assume nothing, keep playing.</p>
        <p>''I had no idea where the ball was, to begin with,'' Knoblauch explained, lamely, failing to acknowledge that he didn't make any attempt to locate it until it was too late. Had he retrieved the ball even a couple of seconds faster, he would have thrown Wilson, who stumbled between third and home, out at the plate.</p>
        <p>No excuses for not playing on, Torre agreed, after lobbing a few verbal grenades at the umps. Martinez, given the error for his throw, admitted the call could have gone either way and decided the Yankees had no one to blame for the defeat but themselves.</p>
        <p>''We should have won the game much earlier,'' he said, citing his own inability to deliver Paul O'Neill from third with one out in the fourth. Speaking of wasted opportunities, Torre let David Cone's favorite catcher, Joe Girardi, hit against a sidearming right-hander, Steve Reed, with runners at second and third, two out in the seventh, the Yankees having just tied the game at 1-1.</p>
        <p>As it was, Cone was gone by the ninth, when the Yankees had what was their last chance to win, when Tim Raines singled and pinch-runner Homer Bush stole second. Now, I am as excited by what Shane Spencer has done as the next guy, but these are the playoffs and this isn't Joe DiMaggio. Rather than send up a left-hander, Jorge Posada or Chili Davis, against the right-handed Paul Shuey, Torre let Spencer swing away. He struck out. Posada eventually hit for Girardi with Bush on second, Scott Brosius on first. He grounded to second for an inning-ending double play.</p>
        <p>The game moved toward its ungraceful finish. The Yankees find themselves in a series after all, now returning to where they were ousted last season, after a game Torre said he hoped was ''out of character.'' Probably it was, but Martinez is in a horrible slump, the table-setter Knoblauch only positioned himself for potential infamy, and the Indians flew home citing history, their own 111-victory team from 1954 that lost, four straight, in the World Series.</p>
        <p>Stuff happens. Sound the alarms. Welcome to the real playoffs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
