<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Starrett City Sale Draws 2 New Doubters</title>
    <meta content="13starrett" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/13/nyregion/13starrett.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070216T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1825898"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Starrett City Housing Development (Brooklyn)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mitchell-Lama Projects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Housing and Urban Development Department (Hud)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Clipper Equity Llc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bagli, Charles V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schumer, Charles E (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Alphonso (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Schumer, Charles E</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jackson, Alphonso</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E1D81F3FF930A25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Starrett City Sale Draws 2 New Doubters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Starrett City Sale Draws 2 New Doubters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Sen Charles E Schumer and Housing and Urban Development Secretary Alphonso Jackson join New York City politicians and community advocates in push to ensure that new owners of Brooklyn housing complex Starrett City keep it affordable to low- and middle-income families; owner Clipper Equity LLC will buy out of Mitchell-Lama program for middle-income tenants, making rent increases virtual certainty; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer and the federal housing secretary added their voices yesterday to the growing chorus of politicians and community advocates who are demanding that Starrett City, the largest federally subsidized housing complex in the country, remain a haven for poor, working and middle-class families.</p>
        <p>Last Thursday, an investment group led by David Bistricer agreed to buy the 5,881 apartments in 46 towers on Jamaica Bay in Brooklyn for $1.3 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer and the federal housing secretary demanded that the housing complex remain an affordable enclave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer and the federal housing secretary added their voices yesterday to the growing chorus of politicians and community advocates who are demanding that Starrett City, the largest federally subsidized housing complex in the country, remain a haven for poor, working and middle-class families.</p>
        <p>Last Thursday, an investment group led by David Bistricer agreed to buy the 5,881 apartments in 46 towers on Jamaica Bay in Brooklyn for $1.3 billion.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Bistricer has said that he wants Starrett City to remain an affordable enclave, critics fear that anyone paying such a heady price would almost certainly have to raise rents and displace tenants at a complex remarkable for its economic and ethnic diversity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer said in an interview yesterday that he would ''do everything I can to block'' the transaction.</p>
        <p>''There is no way that this deal at this price can go through without massive changes at Starrett City,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Later in the day, the secretary of Housing and Urban Development, Alphonso Jackson, said in a statement: ''This transaction has the potential to threaten New York City's low-income housing market and those who need it. Starrett City is more than a piece of land: it is a community.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson added that his agency, which must approve or reject a new owner, would scrutinize the transaction closely and aggressively.</p>
        <p>In a meeting yesterday morning with city, state and federal officials at the New York offices of HUD., Mr. Bistricer pleaded with officials to tone down their rhetoric. He told them that he had no plans to oust existing tenants at the 140-acre complex, although he would like to build condominiums and subsidized rental housing on vacant parts of the property, officials said.</p>
        <p>Over the past week, executives involved with Mr. Bistricer said that his group, Clipper Equity L.L.C., would buy out of the state's Mitchell-Lama program for middle-income tenants. They said that most tenants would be unaffected, because they would qualify for federal rent vouchers. But state and city officials contend that hundreds of tenants could be displaced.</p>
        <p>One official who attended the meeting said that Mr. Bistricer had indicated that he would consider remaining in the program if certain issues could be worked out.</p>
        <p>''Our hope is to together formulate a plan that preserves long-term affordability and makes sense to all parties concerned,'' Len Grunstein, a lawyer for Mr. Bistricer, said last night. ''It was a positive meeting, but there's a lot of work to be done.''</p>
        <p>The city is in the midst of both a residential building boom and a rapid increase in prices for housing. Well-funded investment groups are now gobbling up what they had long ignored -- tenements and unremarkable apartment buildings in Brooklyn, Queens and the Bronx -- for astronomical prices. That, in turn, has generated a hue and cry about the potential loss of working-class and even middle-class housing.</p>
        <p>Starrett City Associates, the longtime owners of the complex, moved to take advantage of the market last year by putting it on the auction block. The complex, which opened in 1975, was conceived as a middle-income Mitchell-Lama co-op. But it failed to attract enough interest, and over time it acquired a web of state and federal subsidies for low-, moderate- and middle-income tenants.</p>
        <p>The sale was complicated by the fact that Starrett City Associates, led by Disque Dean, imposed an order prohibiting potential buyers from talking to state or city officials.</p>
        <p>Officials, in turn, wanted to make buyers aware that they were not free to do whatever they wanted with the property. Federal officials must review any sale. City officials insist that any major development at the complex would require a lengthy review and municipal approval.</p>
        <p>The purchase of Starrett City, Mr. Bistricer's first step into the big leagues of New York real estate, has taken a bewildering turn. Up to now, he has been a relatively small-time player who abhorred the spotlight. Eighteen months ago, he and a partner bought Vandermeer Estates, a troubled complex in East Flatbush, Brooklyn, renaming it Flatbush Gardens.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg denounced his prospective purchase of Starrett City, saying that there were nearly 9,000 building violations at Flatbush Gardens. Mr. Bistricer told officials yesterday that he inherited the violations and pleaded with the city to temper its criticism.</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 16, 2007, Friday  An article on Tuesday about growing political opposition to the pending $1.3 billion sale of the Starrett City apartment complex in Brooklyn misspelled the name of a different Brooklyn complex owned by a group headed by David Bistricer, who also wants to buy Starrett. It is Vanderveer Estates, not Vandermeer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 16, 2007, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about growing political opposition to the pending $1.3 billion sale of the Starrett City apartment complex in Brooklyn misspelled the name of a different Brooklyn complex owned by a group headed by David Bistricer, who also wants to buy Starrett. It is Vanderveer Estates, not Vandermeer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
