<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Bond Firms Are Still Giving To Politicians</title>
    <meta content="16BOND$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="923264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0DB153FF935A25757C0A961958260" item-length="1514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Bond Firms Are Still Giving To Politicians</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Major firms that underwrite Government bonds are still giving heavily to political campaigns around nation, despite recent industry rule, enforced by Securities and Exchange Commission, intended to curb such gifts; rule bars firms and their aides from giving over $250 to state and local officials empowered to grant underwriting business; rule has cut campaign giving substantially, but has several loopholes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Major bond firms are still giving heavily to political campaigns around the country, despite a recent Federal rule intended to reduce such gifts.</p>
        <p>Last year, a dozen of Wall Street's largest municipal bond firms, including Bear Stearns, Goldman Sachs and Paine Webber, gave $261,000 to the committee that produced television commercials in which Gov. George E. Pataki spoke about environmental protection. Almost all of those firms do bond work for the state, receiving millions of dollars in fees each year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Major bond firms are still giving heavily to political campaigns around the country, despite a recent Federal rule intended to reduce such gifts.</p>
        <p>Last year, a dozen of Wall Street's largest municipal bond firms, including Bear Stearns, Goldman Sachs and Paine Webber, gave $261,000 to the committee that produced television commercials in which Gov. George E. Pataki spoke about environmental protection. Almost all of those firms do bond work for the state, receiving millions of dollars in fees each year.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, bond dealers and executives at E. A. Moos &amp; Company in Summit contributed $4,000 to $11,000 to political parties in Camden, Gloucester, Ocean and Middlesex Counties last year. In each place, the firm was later awarded underwriting business.</p>
        <p>In Florida, executives of William R. Hough &amp; Company of St. Petersburg, the state's largest bond firm, contributed more than $60,000 to the two major parties and several county parties last year. By year's end, Hough was handling more than 60 govrnmental bond contracts.</p>
        <p>Four years ago, the industry adopted, with the encouragement of  the Securities and Exchange Commission, a rule known as G-37. The rule was intended to discourage the practice of ''pay to play,'' in which bond firms gave to politicians in what some saw as a search for favorable treatment in the awarding of lucrative bond contracts. G-37, which is enforced by the S.E.C., prohibits bond dealers, executives and their firms from giving more than $250 to state and local officials who have the power to grant underwriting business.</p>
        <p>Industry experts agree that G-37 has reduced campaign giving by underwriters substantially. But the rule has several loopholes. For instance, while G-37 restricts firms from contributing directly to certain officials, it does allow companies to give to the political parties that provide crucial campaign support to those same officials.</p>
        <p>The rule also allows bond underwriters to contribute to political committees that support ballot initiatives, even when those committees are closely linked to elected officials. In New York, the committee that promoted Governor Pataki's plan to sell $1.75 billion in bonds for environmental projects last year was run by the Governor's advisers, including his counsel, Michael C. Finnegan.</p>
        <p>When a government or government agency wants to borrow money for public programs, usually construction projects, it hires an underwriter. The underwriter, or a group of them, sells bonds to the public to raise money, and the government pays the principal and interest. In return for guaranteeing to sell the bonds, and buying them itself if necessary, the underwriter gets a fee,  generally from one-half a percentage point to three-quarters of a point of the value of a large bond issue, like  $1 billion or more. For a small issue, like $10 million, the firm may receive several percentage points.</p>
        <p>Officials with many large Wall Street bond firms declined to comment about their contributions, although they pointed out that the donations were allowed under the rules.</p>
        <p>But the municipal finance industry's continued practice of giving millions of dollars in campaign contributions each year stirs concern among some state legislators and government watchdog groups, who contend that such gifts raise ethical clouds over bond decisions.</p>
        <p>''It's a big game about how you are going to avoid these restrictions,'' said State Senator Franz S. Leichter, a Manhattan Democrat whose office recently completed a study showing that bond underwriters contributed as much as $1 million to state and local political committees in New York State last year. ''And it's frankly not a very difficult game to play.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leichter has sent a letter to Arthur Levitt Jr., the S.E.C. chairman and a proponent of G-37, urging him to consider expanding it to ban contributions to political parties. Chris Ullman, an S.E.C. spokesman, said Mr. Levitt thinks G-37 has ''done wonders at changing the pay-to-play culture.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''We will take Senator Leichter's concerns into consideration as we review our regulatory work.''</p>
        <p>Zenia Mucha, Mr. Pataki's director of communications, said the contributions to the Environmental Bond Act committee would have no effect on the administration's decisions about underwriting. In most years, New York sells more bonds than any other state, $2.4 billion in the 1996-97 fiscal year that ended March 31, and the Governor's office plays a major role in selecting underwriters on many of those sales.</p>
        <p>Christopher Taylor, executive director of the Municipal Securities Rulemaking Board, the industry's self-regulatory body, asserted that donations to state parties do not ''raise the same level of concern as giving to an individual candidate.''</p>
        <p>''If you are giving it to a state party,'' he said, ''provided they are not turning around and giving it to a specific candidate, I don't see how you would have a conflict of interest.''</p>
        <p>But Charles Lewis, executive director of the Center for Public Integrity, a nonprofit research organization in Washington, said contributions to state and local parties can be as effective at buying access as donations to officials. ''These politicians are creatures of their political parties,'' Mr. Lewis said. ''Could someone tell me why else bond interests would give hundreds of thousand of dollars to a party?''</p>
        <p>Wall Street firms were particularly active in New York State, accounting for nearly 20 percent of the $1.6 million raised by Mr. Pataki's Clean Water/Clean Air Environmental Bond Act Committee last year.</p>
        <p>Under G-37, those firms could not  make direct campaign contributions to Mr. Pataki. But in giving to his ballot initiative committee, bond firms helped pay for $1.2 million in campaignlike television commercials that featured the Governor advocating a cleaner environment. Pollsters contend that those spots helped raise Mr. Pataki's approval rating by several percentage points.</p>
        <p>Many firms also made large contributions to the State Republican Party's housekeeping account, used  for party-building expenses like office rents, or get-out-the-vote efforts. Among the major contributors were the firms Dillon Read, $10,000, and Paine Webber, $8,000. Both firms do bond business with the state.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leichter's study found that  eight Wall Street firms also contributed a total of $468,500 last year to the National Republican Senatorial Committee, controlled by Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato, the highest-ranking Republican in the state and Mr. Pataki's political mentor. At least $120,000 was shifted from the Federal account to the State Republican Party's housekeeping account.</p>
        <p>G-37 also has not discouraged politicians from soliciting money from bond firms. The invitation to a fund-raiser on Thursday in Manhattan for Mr. Pataki and the State Republican Party, billed as the Second Annual Governor's Reception, notes that ''individuals who are restricted because of G-37 may contribute to the housekeeping account.''</p>
        <p>Critics of G-37 say bond firms can also win politicians' favor by giving to their allies. Goldman Sach's political action committee gave $1,000 each to two Republican judicial candidates running for State Supreme Court in the Albany area last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki and the State Republican Party ardently supported the candidates, Victoria Graffeo and Mary Donohue, because they wanted more Republican judges in the Albany judicial district, which hears most cases involving state government. Both women won.</p>
        <p>Proponents of tougher restrictions say the connection between contributions to political parties and the awarding of bond contracts is perhaps more visible at the local level, where the influence of parties is sometimes stronger.</p>
        <p>E. A. Moos &amp; Company has been among the most politically active firms in New Jersey. Last year, Moos's top executives contributed $4,000 to the Camden County Democratic Committee, $4,500 to the Gloucester County Democratic Committee and $10,000 to the Middlesex County Democratic Committee, G-37 records show. Officials in all three counties, which have Democratic-controlled governments, awarded bond contracts to E. A. Moos.</p>
        <p>The firm also contributed $11,200 to the Ocean County Republican Committee last year, when it was awarded several underwriting jobs by Republican-controlled municipal agencies in that county. It has also hired political leaders in several counties to help in obtaining bond contracts, including Dale Florio, a  Trenton lobbyist who is chairman of the Somerset County Republican Committee, and Charlotte DeFilippo, chairwoman of the Union County Democratic Committee.</p>
        <p>Asked if contributions gave firms an advantage, Joseph Spicuzzo, chairman of the Middlesex County Democratic Committee, answered: ''It probably does. But it doesn't close the door to anyone else.''</p>
        <p>Bond firms elsewhere follow similar practices, a review of G-37 records shows. Wheat First Butcher Singer of Philadelphia gave $29,850 last year to county and state parties in four states where it does bond work. George K. Baum of Kansas City, Mo., gave $12,000 to parties in three states. Janney Montgomery Scott of Philadelphia contributed $9,400 last year to county parties in eastern Pennsylvania and southern New Jersey, where it seeks business.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
