<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Hot! Bring Me a Book!</title>
    <meta content="07JEFFERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/07/books/review/07JEFFERT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1406156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ON WRITERS AND WRITING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jefferson, Margo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/On Writers and Writing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Highsmith, Patricia</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Miyabe, Miyuki</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE7DC123EF934A35754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1067" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Hot! Bring Me a Book!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It's Hot! Bring Me a Book!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Margo Jefferson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jefferson, Margo</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Margo Jefferson On Writers and Writing column says summer reading should be in harmony with your vacation setting; some suggestions noted; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUMMER reading may be an escape, but escape takes work, as we've all learned from trying to plot the right vacation, pack the right clothes and get into the right mood on schedule. Your books should be in harmony with your vacation setting. Who's really going to believe you're rereading Emerson or Goethe on the beach? In the woods maybe, or alone at night by the glow of an antique lamp, but not on the beach.</p>
        <p>There is something especially appealing about fiction in the summer. Even in cities, the long unchanging stretches of heat (or of air conditioning), the slow cooling off into evening, make our own rhythms less urgent. It is so easy then to give in to someone else's voice, ride his or her imagination. I even like my thrillers to move as if psychological heat were making them slow down and sweat with anxiety. If you haven't joined the Patricia Highsmith revival yet, now is the time. ''The Selected Stories of Patricia Highsmith'' came out last summer, and they're funny, mean and very spooky. She's a ferocious social observer, whether of quarrels over Connecticut property that end in self-righteous homicide, or of a disaffected cockroach planning to relocate from a seedy hotel to an Upper East Side apartment. (Kafka's Gregor Samsa is human and tragic; Don Marquis's Archy is a gentle humanist. Highsmith's cockroach is a snob with an ancient insect lineage and no name -- he has too much disdain for bipeds to want or need one.) And it isn't just animals who beat humans at their own nasty games -- in the supernatural tales it is machines and household objects too. Thanks to the recent movie, the Ripley novels are well known again. Read ''Strangers on a Train,'' though, and then rent the Hitchcock movie. They are both masterpieces of guilt, guile and agonized complicity. But Hitchcock's changes say everything about the differences between literature and film.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Summer is the time to go on a jag and do all the works of some honorable writer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUMMER reading may be an escape, but escape takes work, as we've all learned from trying to plot the right vacation, pack the right clothes and get into the right mood on schedule. Your books should be in harmony with your vacation setting. Who's really going to believe you're rereading Emerson or Goethe on the beach? In the woods maybe, or alone at night by the glow of an antique lamp, but not on the beach.</p>
        <p>There is something especially appealing about fiction in the summer. Even in cities, the long unchanging stretches of heat (or of air conditioning), the slow cooling off into evening, make our own rhythms less urgent. It is so easy then to give in to someone else's voice, ride his or her imagination. I even like my thrillers to move as if psychological heat were making them slow down and sweat with anxiety. If you haven't joined the Patricia Highsmith revival yet, now is the time. ''The Selected Stories of Patricia Highsmith'' came out last summer, and they're funny, mean and very spooky. She's a ferocious social observer, whether of quarrels over Connecticut property that end in self-righteous homicide, or of a disaffected cockroach planning to relocate from a seedy hotel to an Upper East Side apartment. (Kafka's Gregor Samsa is human and tragic; Don Marquis's Archy is a gentle humanist. Highsmith's cockroach is a snob with an ancient insect lineage and no name -- he has too much disdain for bipeds to want or need one.) And it isn't just animals who beat humans at their own nasty games -- in the supernatural tales it is machines and household objects too. Thanks to the recent movie, the Ripley novels are well known again. Read ''Strangers on a Train,'' though, and then rent the Hitchcock movie. They are both masterpieces of guilt, guile and agonized complicity. But Hitchcock's changes say everything about the differences between literature and film.</p>
        <p>I also recommend ''All She Was Worth,'' by Miyuki Miyabe. This was named Japan's best mystery and best novel in 1992, which is remarkable in itself, and the book is a relentless dissection of 1980's finances -- stock market booms, bankruptcies, credit card scams. All of this is made particular through a young woman whose motives are so understandable and whose deeds so frightening that when she is finally caught you feel you've reached another terrible beginning. There is no resolution at all.</p>
        <p>We tend to think of summer reading as an escape from something, but it's as much an escape to what the year has crowded out. Scholars and writers are busy reading material for their next books. But since I write about books for a living, I see these months as a partial retreat to titles that aren't prime-time column fodder. This spring I saw a fascinating play based on Mark Twain's novel ''Pudd'nhead Wilson.'' And so I plan to reread ''Pudd'nhead,'' to me his most disturbing, brilliant and convoluted book. It's a novel of mixed identities and tortuous mixed motives: black and white characters change places and behaviors; so do villains, victims and heroes. Twain keeps mixing genres too. He gives us a thriller with broad comic patches and a satire with lots of everyday realism. He is always a truth-teller and a trickster, exposing, veiling, struggling with our most primal racial myths.</p>
        <p>I don't plan to read more of Twain than that. But summer is the time to go on a jag -- to do the collected works of some honorable writer, living or dead, especially one who has entered or regained entrance to the sanctuary of quality paperback reissues. My colleagues' recommendations include Stefan Zweig, Sybille Bedford, Richard Wright and Paula Fox. Or your motive can be practical: one friend is now reading the works of the psychoanalyst Karen Horney. She began with ''Self-Analysis'' the week her own analyst went on vacation. She compared it to the talisman (psychologists call it the ''transitional object'') that parents give children when they are having difficulty with leave-takings and separation.</p>
        <p>Summer sharpens our need to indulge in random pleasures. You take off somewhere on impulse. You go through a bookstore's outside sale table on a nice day and pick out something utterly unexpected. A few weeks ago, I bought a book of Brecht's poetry, ''Poems 1913-1956.'' It's the plays I'd been paying attention to for years -- I'd been told the poems were wonderful, but hadn't really thought about them. Now I'm thrilled by them.</p>
        <p>Brecht is so many poets: lyric dreamer, urban realist, storyteller, political satirist and prophet; also a formalist who drew from psalms, sonnets and medieval ballads. Call him the man of a thousand voices. The voice of a sunken ship, for example:</p>
        <p>And the waters came, and swept vast numbers</p>
        <p>Of creatures through me, so that in my timbers</p>
        <p>Creature befriended creature in the gloom.</p>
        <p>The voice of a romantic poet shocked by the city:</p>
        <p>Long before</p>
        <p>We swooped on oil, iron and ammonia</p>
        <p>There was each year</p>
        <p>A time of irresistible violent leafing of trees. . . .</p>
        <p>High above, it is true</p>
        <p>There seem to be storms:</p>
        <p>All they touch now is</p>
        <p>Our aerials.</p>
        <p>Those who flee oppressive countries (as he fled Germany) ''are almost like rumors of crimes, which escaped / Over the frontier.'' In his 1940 political elegy, ''In Times of Extreme Persecution,'' he writes</p>
        <p>Once you've been beaten</p>
        <p>What will remain?</p>
        <p>Hunger and sleet and</p>
        <p>Driving rain.</p>
        <p>But here is a four-line elegy from 1920, ''To My Mother'':</p>
        <p>And when she was finished they laid her in earth</p>
        <p>Flowers growing, butterflies juggling over her . . .</p>
        <p>She, so light, barely pressed the earth down</p>
        <p>How much pain it took to make her as light as that!</p>
        <p>Whatever your need, fulfill it; whatever your mood, indulge it.</p>
        <p>ON WRITERS AND WRITING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
