<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Allenby Takes a Two-Stroke Lead in the Western Open</title>
    <meta content="Y07GOL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/07/sports/golf/07GOLF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1406526"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Western Open Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dorfman, Daniel I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allenby, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">PGA Tour Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Allenby, Robert</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E2DD1F31F934A35754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Allenby Takes a Two-Stroke Lead in the Western Open</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Allenby Takes Lead in Western Open</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL I. DORFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dorfman, Daniel I</byline>
      <dateline>LEMONT, Ill., July 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Allenby takes third-round lead at Western Open golf tournament (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Allenby, whose performances at the Cog Hill Golf Course have swung toward the extremes of hit or miss, put himself in position for his first victory of the season with a seven-under-par 65 today.</p>
        <p>Allenby took a two-stroke lead in the Western Open over the PGA Tour veteran Neal Lancaster with a 15-under 201 after three rounds. Bob Estes and Jerry Kelly were each three shots back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Allenby put himself in position for his first victory of the season with a seven-under-par 65.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robert Allenby, whose performances at the Cog Hill Golf Course have swung toward the extremes of hit or miss, put himself in position for his first victory of the season with a seven-under-par 65 today.</p>
        <p>Allenby took a two-stroke lead in the Western Open over the PGA Tour veteran Neal Lancaster with a 15-under 201 after three rounds. Bob Estes and Jerry Kelly were each three shots back.</p>
        <p>An eagle on the par-5 15th hole was the highlight of the day for Allenby, who won this event in 2000 but missed the cut in 1999 and 2001. Allenby had birdies on five other holes, bogeying only the par-4 No. 6.</p>
        <p>''A two-shot lead is not a lot of shots when you are playing against such a great field,'' said Allenby, who won the two events -- the 2000 Shell Houston Open and the 2001 Marconi Pennsylvania Open -- in which he was either tied for the lead or in the lead after 54 holes.</p>
        <p>John Cook, who had a two-shot lead going into today's round, shot an even-par 72 and fell four shots off the lead. Joining him at 11-under was Davis Love III, who shot a 68.</p>
        <p>Early in the round, Allenby was challenged by Stuart Appleby, a fellow Australian, but Appleby fell off the pace after a double bogey on No. 13 and a bogey on No. 14.</p>
        <p>Appleby finished the day at 10 under, joining a large group that included David Frost, Chris Riley, Duffy Waldorf and Scott Verplank, who won here in 1985 as an amateur.</p>
        <p>Lancaster, who posted a five-under 67 after successive 68's in the first two rounds, was looking for his first Tour victory since his only triumph at the 1994 Byron Nelson Classic.</p>
        <p>''My goal this year was to win a golf tournament,'' Lancaster said.</p>
        <p>Allenby's round of 65 today was his career best at Cog Hill. ''It's nice to come back to a course where you have won before, because you have a lot of confidence,'' Allenby said. ''This is the kind of golf course that makes you think all the time.''</p>
        <p>Bob Tway tied Allenby for the best score of the day with a 65. The round brought him to nine under, six strokes behind the leader.</p>
        <p>Players with early tee times took advantage of ideal conditions. With 66's, Frost and Nick Price moved into contention. Frost went five under on the back nine to vault himself onto the leader board.</p>
        <p>''I played well on the back nine,'' he said. ''The greens are receptive to good shots. If we hadn't had the rain, it would be a different story.''</p>
        <p>Nick Price, a two-time Western Open champion, gave himself at least an outside chance to win; he will enter Sunday's final round six strokes back.</p>
        <p>Allenby defeated Price in a playoff two years ago to win the tournament. ''I'm very happy with the way I played today,'' Price said. ''I hit every green in regulation. If I had a better putter today, I probably could have shot 62.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
