<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Policy Makers Keep an Eye on the Election</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="185269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIP MINING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINES AND MINING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTS, STEVEN V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD71031F936A35753C1A96E948260" item-length="1488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Policy Makers Keep an Eye on the Election</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN V. ROBERTS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROBERTS, STEVEN V</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Lee M. Thomas, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, has been highly visible in recent weeks: warning of the dangers of radon gas, announcing a strategy for dealing with the nation's garbage crisis, proposing a total ban on chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone shield.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Lee M. Thomas, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, has been highly visible in recent weeks: warning of the dangers of radon gas, announcing a strategy for dealing with the nation's garbage crisis, proposing a total ban on chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Lee M. Thomas, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, has been highly visible in recent weeks: warning of the dangers of radon gas, announcing a strategy for dealing with the nation's garbage crisis, proposing a total ban on chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone shield.</p>
        <p>At about the same time, the Interior Department's Office of Surface Mining proposed new regulations that would have allowed strip mining of coal on protected public lands, including national parks. The White House quickly killed the regulations, surprising many in the agency.</p>
        <p>And recently, when Lauro F. Cavazos, the first Hispanic official to serve in the Cabinet, was sworn in as Secretary of Education, Vice President Bush took the unusual step of administering the oath, thus identifying publicly with a key voting group. In Tune With the Bush Campaign</p>
        <p>Democrats charge, almost admiringly, and Republicans concede and sometimes boast that moves like these demonstrate the vigor with which the Reagan Administration is using its resources to advance the Presidential ambitions of Mr. Bush. From key appointments to Presidential speeches, from legislative strategy to bureaucratic announcements, the Administration these days seems never to forget that there is an election coming.</p>
        <p>''People across the Government are trying to be helpful to the Vice President, '' a senior White House official said. ''They're trying to coordinate back and forth, so we're all singing from the same song sheet. ''But I don't believe policy is driven strictly by that purpose.''</p>
        <p>There is nothing all that unusual about such efforts, and no one says this Administration invented them. But it is clear that a thorough job is being done of viewing policy decisions with at least one eye on Election Day.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign has not always enjoyed such close coordination with the Administration. Earlier this year, according to one of the Vice President's closest advisers, Bush campaign aides were dissatisfied with the level of White House cooperation on a number of sensitive legislative issues, including bills that would strengthen fair housing laws and mandate advance notification of plant closings and major layoffs.</p>
        <p>Today, added the Bush adviser, ''Cooperation is 100 percent. It's the difference between dusk and day.''</p>
        <p>For example, the environmental agency has certainly built a backfire for Mr. Bush against a vulnerable area, and White House aides concede they are reviewing regulations with an eye on their political impact. 'October Surprise' Expected</p>
        <p>Moreover, State Department officials say some foreign policy matters are being managed with political concerns in mind. One example they cite is Panama, where the Reagan Administration has shelved its unsuccessful efforts to negotiate the dropping of criminal indictments against Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, the Panamanian leader, while the Presidential campaign is going on in the United States.</p>
        <p>The Administration has made assiduous efforts in recent weeks to secure the release of American hostages held captive in Lebanon. And, while White House officials insist that there are no political motives behind their efforts, Democrats fear the Administration and the hostage-holders may spring an ''October surprise'' just before the election that could bolster Mr. Bush's chances.</p>
        <p>''There's a tremendous amount of coordination with the White House and the campaign,'' said Senator Dale Bumpers, an Arkansas Democrat. ''Everything the President does is keyed directly to enhancing Bush's chances.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes the White House assistance has come directly, in the form of personal campaign appearances and money-raising efforts by President Reagan. ''When we think of a good opportunity, we call him,'' said James Lake, a public relations adviser to the Bush organization. A Presidential Platform</p>
        <p>Sometimes the aid is more subtle, by providing the Vice President with a platform to appear Presidential. Whether it is representing the President at the United Nations Security Council or greeting the space shuttle astronauts as they land in California, Mr. Bush has used his White House connections to advance his campaign in ways that Gov. Michael S. Dukakis, the Democratic nominee, cannot hope to match.</p>
        <p>''The White House,'' acknowledged a senior staff member, ''is certainly more than willing to be helpful to the Vice President in this particular way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan has openly urged his Cabinet members to devote at least six days a month to supporting the Bush campaign, and they have responded in many ways.</p>
        <p>In a flurry of activity last week, Beryl W. Sprinkel, the President's chief economic adviser, briefed reporters at the White House on the economy, made a speech in Pittsburgh on the same subject and issued a glossy, 22-page packet filled with charts and analysis. On Monday he addressed the Cabinet, providing them with ammunition to use on the campaign trail. A Twofold Economic Message</p>
        <p>The gist of his message was twofold: remind voters that the Administration has produced 69 months of economic growth, and warn the Federal Reserve Board that this performance, and Mr. Bush's standing, could be damaged if the board decides to raise interest rates again before the election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cavazos, the new Education Secretary, is a registered Democrat, but he plunged into his new political role with gusto. A few days after he was sworn in, he appeared at a Republican fund-raising event in his home state of Texas, a crucial state in this fall's election. With both the President and Vice President in attendance, he led the Pledge of Allegiance, the favorite tribute to the flag that Mr. Bush has made the watchword of his campaign.</p>
        <p>But of the high Administration officials whose efforts appear helpful to Mr. Bush, the environmental agency's Mr. Thomas has probably been the most aggressive. On Sept. 11 he issued a public health warning advising most homeowners to have their property tested for radon, a naturally occurring gas that can cause cancer. On Sept. 21 he announced a goal of reducing the nation's solid waste by 25 percent over four years. On Sept. 25 he was in the news again, promoting a ban on ozone-threatening chemicals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas's aides insist that many of these actions have been in the works for a long time, and would have been taken anyway. But Joy Wilson, the agency's assistant administator, acknowledged that she and Mr. Thomas had been in touch with the Bush campaign ''from time to time'' over various issues. Improving Environmental Image</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Bush and Mr. Dukakis have stressed environmental protection in their campaigns, and Mr. Thomas's burst of activity appears aimed at improving the image of an Administration that by its own admission has not been known for stringent environmental enforcement.</p>
        <p>''I would think there is a benefit to the President, and to the Vice President, if E.P.A. is doing a good job,'' said Ms. Wilson, the agency's assistant administrator. ''Most people want environmental protection, and there is a great deal of impatience that we're not where we want to be. I think we have some real credibility problems that need to be taken care of.''</p>
        <p>Another area where the Administration can be helpful to Mr. Bush is regulatory decisions. The new regulations proposed by the Office of Surface Mining outraged environmentalists, but the White House killed the suggested rule.</p>
        <p>Annetta Cheek, special assistant to Jed Christensen, the director of the surface mining agency, said that ''no explanation was given'' by the White House for the action. ''It surprised us,'' she added. The Flow of Information</p>
        <p>The White House is also in a position to disclose information, or withhold it, when it helps the Bush campaign. Mr. Dukakis has been assailing the Vice President for the Administration's ties to General Noriega in Panama, and a story was circulated last July reporting that Mr. Reagan had authorized covert action aimed at deposing the general.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress from both parties accused the Administration of disclosing the information to help Mr. Bush rebut the Dukakis attack, and of then trying to blame Congress for the disclosure.</p>
        <p>Senator William S. Cohen of Maine, the ranking Republican on the Senate Select Committee on Intelligence, said lawmakers were ''chagrined and surprised to find such a heavy-handed approach by the executive branch.''</p>
        <p>Senator David L. Boren, an Oklahoma Democrat who heads the panel, added, ''The political season puts great stress on the relationship between the two branches.''</p>
        <p>Elliot Abrams, Assistant Secretary of State for Latin American Affairs, has acknowledged consulting with the Bush campaign about Latin American policy. He contends that he did nothing improper, but the kind of access and information enjoyed by the Bush campaign demonstrates the advantages of incumbency in an election campaign.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
