<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil Surges to $24 a Barrel But Retreats as Rally Slows</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="480977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="FUTURES/OPTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUTURES TRADING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DB123CF934A25753C1A967958260" item-length="377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil Surges to $24 a Barrel But Retreats as Rally Slows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Crude oil futures prices jumped in heavy trading yesterday, briefly touching a nine-month high of $24 a barrel before falling back and settling lower. Analysts said it was premature to say whether the reversal signaled the end of the market's five-week rally.</p>
        <p>Most other energy futures also fell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Crude oil futures prices jumped in heavy trading yesterday, briefly touching a nine-month high of $24 a barrel before falling back and settling lower. Analysts said it was premature to say whether the reversal signaled the end of the market's five-week rally.</p>
        <p>Most other energy futures also fell.</p>
        <p>Crude oil for November delivery finished the day at $23.67 a barrel, 19 cents below Tuesday's settlement; November heating oil dropped 0.73 cent, to 68.44 cents a gallon; unleaded gasoline fell 0.07 cent, to 63.26 cents a gallon, and November natural gas rose 1.5 cents, to $2.001 for 1,000 cubic feet.</p>
        <p>Crude prices have risen steadily from their Sept. 9 low of $21.25 amid fears that cuts in Soviet exports will lead to tight world supplies of both crude oil and heating oil this winter.</p>
        <p>But $24 proved to be too strong a psychological barrier for the crude market, which has not topped that price since Jan. 22.</p>
        <p>"A lot of people were amazed to even see that level," said Stephanie Rzasa, a broker with Dean Witter Reynolds Inc.</p>
        <p>She said buying was spurred early in the session by news that the Amoco Corporation had shut down a 220,000-barrel-a-day crude-processing unit at its refinery in Texas City, Tex., for several days of repairs.</p>
        <p>But the rally "seemed to grind to a halt" at $24 and traders began taking profits, she said.</p>
        <p>The November delivery price fell as low as $23.42 before reversing itself again on buying that may or may not be a sign of renewed bullish sentiment.</p>
        <p>"It's a little early to tell," Ms. Rzasa said. "One day doesn't necessarily indicate the end of a trend, especially not at this point."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, livestock and meat futures advanced on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange, reflecting higher cash cattle and beef prices and expectations for higher cash hog prices after producers cut back on marketings yesterday because of recent price declines.</p>
        <p>Live cattle for October delivery rose 0.72 cent, to 73.92 cents a pound; October feeder cattle rose 0.20 cent, to 85.85 cents a pound; October live hogs rose 0.23 cent, to 44.60 cents a pound, and frozen pork bellies climbed 0.77 cent, to 44.57 cents a pound.</p>
        <p>Wheat and soybean futures rose modestly on the Chicago Board of Trade amid indications of fresh export demand.</p>
        <p>FUTURES/OPTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
