<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BIAS IS ADMITTED BY NEW YORK CITY IN PUBLIC HOUSING</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="539908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPANISH-SPEAKING GROUPS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">QUOTAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY HOUSING AUTHORITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LEGAL AID SOCIETY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Quotas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D8153DF932A35754C0A964958260" item-length="1517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BIAS IS ADMITTED BY NEW YORK CITY IN PUBLIC HOUSING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR,</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City acknowledges that it has steered black and Hispanic applicants away from some public housing projects and has agreed to take major steps to integrate its largely white projects, under the settlement of a discrimination lawsuit to be announced in the next few days.</p>
        <p>The city is to provide apartments for 2,000 black and Hispanic families who can show that they were victims of such discrimination in the last decade, officials said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City acknowledges that it has steered black and Hispanic applicants away from some public housing projects and has agreed to take major steps to integrate its largely white projects, under the settlement of a discrimination lawsuit to be announced in the next few days.</p>
        <p>The city is to provide apartments for 2,000 black and Hispanic families who can show that they were victims of such discrimination in the last decade, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit, filed in 1990 on behalf of more than 100,000 families, asserted that New York violated the Fair Housing Act of 1968 by setting racial quotas for certain public housing projects, by selecting tenants to meet those goals and by using codes to designate projects to which only white families should be referred. Ripple Effect in Other Cities</p>
        <p>The settlement could have a ripple effect in other cities. It sends a strong message that public housing authorities may not create white enclaves or steer minority applicants away from projects in white neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Florence W. Roisman, a lawyer at the National Housing Law Project, which represents many tenants of public housing around the country, said similar cases were pending in Connecticut, Illinois, Nebraska, Ohio, Texas and other states. "Every public and publicly assisted landlord in the country should take note," she said. "People will challenge racial segregation and will get relief."</p>
        <p>Officials from the New York City Housing Authority, the United States Department of Justice and the Legal Aid Society of New York, which represents the black and Hispanic families, said the settlement had been drafted and would be filed soon with Judge Pierre N. Leval in Federal District Court in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department has also drafted a lawsuit that accuses the Housing Authority of violating the Fair Housing Act. Its suit, which resembles the one initiated by the black and Hispanic families, is to be filed and simultaneously settled with the Legal Aid suit. Preferential Treatment</p>
        <p>John R. Dunne, the Assistant Attorney General for civil rights, also said the settlement was imminent, as did Jeanne P. Nathan, a spokeswoman for the Housing Authority, and Scott A. Rosenberg, a Legal Aid lawyer.</p>
        <p>In the suit, the black and Hispanic families argued that New York City perpetuated segregation in its public housing by giving preference to applicants who lived in neighborhoods surrounding a project with vacancies to be filled. The effect, they said, was to give preferential treatment to white families applying for apartments in public housing in predominantly white neighborhoods. Similarly, they said, the city selected disproportionately large numbers of blacks for projects in black neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>This policy paid political dividends. White neighborhoods were more willing to accept public housing when they were assured that substantial numbers of apartments would go to white families who lived in the area. An internal memorandum written by a senior official of the Housing Authority in 1986 acknowledged that its selection criteria, "although altruistic in concept, are not necessarily legally sound."</p>
        <p>The discriminatory practices described in the lawsuit were in effect throughout the 1980's, during the administration of Mayor Edward I. Koch. In some cases they continued until May 1991, more than a year after Mayor David N. Dinkins took office. It is not clear who initiated the policies, but they were carried out by top officials in the Housing Authority.</p>
        <p>The proposed settlement, still subject to approval by the three members of the Housing Authority, identifies 31 projects affected by the tenant-assignment practices from 1985 through 1990. New York City has the largest public housing agency in the United States. It operates 324 projects with 180,000 apartments housing 600,000 people. It is receiving more than $800 million from the Federal Government to operate, renovate and build housing this year.</p>
        <p>Under the settlement, the city agrees to reserve 1,991 apartments for black or Hispanic families who can show that they were excluded from those projects because of the city's selection policies. Three out of every four apartments that become vacant at those projects will go to those families until the 1,991 units are filled.</p>
        <p>In all 31 projects, the proportion of white residents is far higher than the overall proportion of white applicants, which is now running below 10 percent of the total number of applicants. In 16 of the projects, whites account for more than half of the tenants.</p>
        <p>Under a separate provision of the settlement, 200 black or Hispanic families who show they have suffered discrimination since 1983 will get receive financial assistance from the Federal Government to help them rent apartments in the private market. The Federal Department of Housing and Urban Development will provide $7.9 million in housing subsidies, or vouchers, to New York City over the next five years, with more to follow.</p>
        <p>Evidence in the case showed that the Federal Housing Department knew about some of the city's racial practices and did nothing to correct them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nathan, the spokeswoman for the Housing Authority, said the agency was "completely overhauling the system" for selecting tenants. She also said that Sally Hernandez-Pinero, the new chairwoman of the Housing Authority, and Mayor Dinkins "believe any housing practices that led to unequal access are totally unacceptable, outrageous and unconscionable."</p>
        <p>If Judge Leval approves the settlement, it will take the form of a consent decree, will dispose of both of the lawsuits -- the Legal Aid Society's and the Justice Department's -- and can be enforced by the court.</p>
        <p>In November 1990, the Bush Administration, citing evidence supplied by the Legal Aid Society, warned the Housing Authority that it had apparently violated Federal law by selecting and assigning tenants on the basis of race. Federal officials invited the city to negotiate a settlement. Chart: "Housing: Projects Affected by the Discrimination Settlement"</p>
        <p>New York City has agreed to place more black and Hispanic applicants in public housing projects in the settlement of a lawsuit. The lawsuit contended that the city, which operates 324 projects, selected tenants to meet racial goals and used secret codes to designate projects to which only white families should be referred. Here are the 31 public housing projects affected. Racial compositions are as of January 1991. BRONX Project: Boston Road Plaza (Bronxwood Ave.) Type: E White: 45.7% Project: Fort Independence (Bailey Ave.) Type: F White: 31.7 Project: Middletown Plaza (Burke Ave.) Type: E White: 76.0 Project: Parkside (White Plains Rd.) Type: F White: 19.1 Project: Pelham Parkway (Bronxwood Ave.) Type: F White: 61.6 Project: Randall Balcolm (Schley Ave.) Type: E White: 44.6 MANHATTAN Project: First Houses (Pitt St.) Type: F White: 44.8 Project: Fulton (W. 17th St.) Type: B White: 43.9 Project: Holmes Tower (E. 93d St.) Type: B White: 52.5 Project: Isaacs (E. 93d St.) Type: B White: 59.7 Project: Meltzer Towers (E. First St.) Type: E White: 49.1 Project: Robbins Plaza (E. 93d St.) Type: E White: 78.9 Project: Seward Park Ext. (Norfolk St.) Type: B White: 35.2 Project: Straus (E. 28th St.) Type: B White: 44.4 Project: Vladeck (Madison St.) Type: F White: 19.7 BROOKLYN Project: Bay View (Seaview Ave.) Type: F White: 64.9% Project: Glenwood (Ralph Ave.) Type: F White: 65.7 Project: Nostrand (Avenue W) Type: F White: 73.3 Project: Sheepshead (Avenue W) Type: F White: 63.4 QUEENS Project: Forest Hills Co-op (62d Deive) Type: B White: 65.6 Project: Latimer Gardens (Linden Pl.) Type: B White: 33.6 Project: Pomonok (Parsons Blvd.) Type: F White: 63.6 Project: Ravenswood (35th Ave.) Type: F White: 32.9 Project: Woodside (Broadway) Type: F White: 21.6 STATEN ISLAND Project: Berry (Donogan Hills) Type: F White: 79.8 Project: Cassidy-Lafayette (Lafayette Ave.) Type: E White: 74.2 Project: New Lane (New Lane) Type: E White: 85.9 Project: South Beach (Lamport Blvd.) Type: F White: 72.7 Project: Todt Hill (Manor Rd.) Type: F White: 67.3 Project: West Brighton II (Broadway) Type: E White: 29.2 (Sources: Justice Department, Department of Housing and Urban Development; New York City Housing Authority) (pg. B2)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
