<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheney, at Marine Base, Reinforces Bush's Stand On War Against Terror</title>
    <meta content="Y19CHE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/19/international/19CHEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1369080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California (USA)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheney, Dick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1D71F3FF93AA25751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheney, at Marine Base, Reinforces Bush's Stand On War Against Terror</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cheney Reinforces Bush's Stand Against Terrorism</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>MARINE CORPS AIR STATION, MIRAMAR, Calif., Feb. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Dick Cheney opens four-day campaign-style swing through California by underscoring America's resolve to stop Iraq, Iran and North Korea from continuing to develop or pursue nuclear, chemical or biological weapons; address at Marine Corps Air Station in Miramar defends Pres Bush's decision to single out three nations as an 'axis of evil,' defining new phase in Washington's war against terror; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Dick Cheney opened a four-day campaign-style swing through California today by underscoring America's resolve to stop Iraq, Iran and North Korea from continuing to develop or pursue nuclear, chemical or biological weapons.</p>
        <p>In a speech to 2,500 marines at this sprawling base north of San Diego, Mr. Cheney defended President Bush's decision to single out those three countries as an ''axis of evil,'' defining a new phase in Washington's war against terror. Some allies have criticized Mr. Bush's language.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a speech to marines, Vice President Dick Cheney underscored America's resolve to stop Iraq, Iran and North Korea from continuing to develop weapons of mass destruction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Dick Cheney opened a four-day campaign-style swing through California today by underscoring America's resolve to stop Iraq, Iran and North Korea from continuing to develop or pursue nuclear, chemical or biological weapons.</p>
        <p>In a speech to 2,500 marines at this sprawling base north of San Diego, Mr. Cheney defended President Bush's decision to single out those three countries as an ''axis of evil,'' defining a new phase in Washington's war against terror. Some allies have criticized Mr. Bush's language.</p>
        <p>''The president's remarks caused a certain amount of hand-wringing in some quarters, but most Americans find it reassuring to have a commander in chief who tells the truth and who means exactly what he says,'' Mr. Cheney said.</p>
        <p>''The United States will not permit terror states and their terrorist allies to threaten us with weapons of mass destruction,'' he said, speaking on the flight line in front of a CH-53E Super Stallion helicopter and F/A-18 Hornet fighter, two Marine Corps workhorses in the war in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>The vice president's remarks echoed those he made last week to the Council on Foreign Relations in Washington. But his words today took on added pungency as he addressed and then mingled over lunch with members of the Third Marine Aircraft Wing in their camouflage-green fatigues.</p>
        <p>Nine marines stationed here were killed in two aircraft crashes in Afghanistan last month, and family members of some of them sat in the front row today for Mr. Cheney's Presidents Day speech.</p>
        <p>Next month, Mr. Cheney is scheduled to visit 12 allied and Middle East countries in what is widely viewed as an effort to build support for toppling President Saddam Hussein of Iraq through the use of tougher economic penalties, covert operations, and, possibly, military force.</p>
        <p>To wage the war on terror, Mr. Cheney, a former secretary of defense, said today that the administration's proposed $48 billion increase in Pentagon spending for 2003, the military's largest annual budget increase in 20 years, would help ensure that America's armed forces had ''the best weapons, the best equipment and the best training.''</p>
        <p>The visit to California marks Mr. Cheney's first major trip since the terrorist attacks on Sept. 11, and his longest official foray outside of Washington as vice president.</p>
        <p>For several months, Mr. Cheney has rarely been seen in public, working at the presidential retreat at Camp David, Md., or at an undisclosed location outside Washington.</p>
        <p>But aides say he has not been to one of his secluded hideaways in more than two weeks, another sign that the administration is taking the wraps off a man who many in government and the political world believe is the most powerful vice president in the nation's history.</p>
        <p>While in California, the vice president will focus on defense and economic issues. He plans to give a speech on national security at the Richard Nixon Presidential Library in Yorba Linda, visit farmers in Fresno and tour a high-technology site in San Jose. On Tuesday night, he will appear on the NBC program ''The Tonight Show with Jay Leno.''</p>
        <p>''California is a one-stop shop for our big messages,'' said Mary Matalin, Mr. Cheney's senior political adviser.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cheney's visit also has a distinctly partisan political purpose: to pump up state Republican coffers and to rally party faithful before a three-way gubernatorial primary on March 5 to pick a candidate to challenge Gov. Gray Davis, the Democratic incumbent.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday night, Mr. Cheney will dine with some of the state's wealthiest Republican donors at a private, $25,000-a-couple fund-raiser in Los Angeles that is expected to rake in more than $1 million for the state party. Later in the week, he will raise money for two House Republicans, Richard W. Pombo and John T. Doolittle.</p>
        <p>Aides say Mr. Cheney will make at least 60 campaign appearances, mostly in House contests, between now and the Nov. 5 elections.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, Mr. Cheney raised money for three other House Republicans in tight races, John Hostettler of Indiana, and Anne M. Northup and Edward Whitfield, both of Kentucky.</p>
        <p>''Cheney is returning to one of the traditional roles of the vice president, which is to carry a large share of the political load during the mid-term elections,'' said Rich Bond, a former chairman of the Republican National Committee.</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
