<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Her Family Scattered, A Player's Focus Is Divided</title>
    <meta content="21wnba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/21/sports/basketball/21wnba.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1784444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Women's National Basketball Association</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Connecticut Sun</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Mystics</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5DE123EF932A1575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Her Family Scattered, A Player's Focus Is Divided</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Her Family Scattered, a Player’s Focus Is Divided</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ELIGON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eligon, John</byline>
      <dateline>UNCASVILLE, Conn., Aug. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The W.N.B.A. playoffs place a premium on staying focused, with best-of-three series that can end quicker than the flick of a wrist.</p>
        <p>Excuse Taj McWilliams-Franklin, however, if she has a momentary lapse in concentration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Taj McWilliams-Franklin had a lot on her mind as she helped the Sun defeat the Washington Mystics to win their Eastern Conference semifinal series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The W.N.B.A. playoffs place a premium on staying focused, with best-of-three series that can end quicker than the flick of a wrist.</p>
        <p>Excuse Taj McWilliams-Franklin, however, if she has a momentary lapse in concentration.</p>
        <p>In a span of 10 days leading up to the playoffs, McWilliams-Franklin, a power forward for the Connecticut Sun, watched her husband, Reggie Franklin, leave for Iraq and then dropped off her oldest daughter, Michele, at Arizona Western College, where she will be a freshman.</p>
        <p>Needless to say, she has had a lot on her mind.</p>
        <p>But basketball provides a distraction from the constant thoughts of her family, with one exception. When she shoots her first free throw in a game, McWilliams-Franklin said, she thinks of her husband because he is the only person who believes she will make that first foul shot, which she usually misses.</p>
        <p>McWilliams-Franklin did miss her first free throw here Sunday, but the Sun defeated Washington, 68-65, to win this Eastern Conference semifinal series, 2-0. The Sun, which had the league's best record during the regular season, will play Detroit in the conference finals.</p>
        <p>McWilliams-Franklin scored 12 points and grabbed 14 rebounds for the ninth playoff double-double of her career, and her second in two games.</p>
        <p>As she tries to win her first W.N.B.A. title, McWilliams-Franklin, 35, must also deal with her emotions.</p>
        <p>''It's not been easy,'' said McWilliams-Franklin, who has spent all eight of her W.N.B.A. seasons with the Sun organization, which was previously based in Orlando, Fla. ''It's a good thing I have basketball because you can focus in on that.''</p>
        <p>In public, McWilliams-Franklin rarely appears rattled, her teammate, Asjha Jones, said.</p>
        <p>But when she is alone, McWilliams-Franklin said, the pain is tangible. To ease it, she prays and reads. She said she recently read a 350-page book in a day.</p>
        <p>She also has her 3-year-old daughter, Maia, to keep her company. McWilliams-Franklin flew Maia to Washington with a nanny last Friday for Game 1. (McWilliams-Franklin grinned while she shot, and missed, her first free throw in that game.)</p>
        <p>Jones said seeing how McWilliams-Franklin had handled her personal situation with poise had helped her own perspective.</p>
        <p>''Anytime you can watch people like that, how they don't let things bother them, get them down, able to come in and just keep going, as a younger player it's great to have people around like that,'' Jones said.</p>
        <p>McWilliams-Franklin and her husband have been apart for most of their marriage. They were married in 2000, but since 2001, they have spent only two or three months a year with each other.</p>
        <p>Reggie Franklin, a sergeant in the United States Army, is stationed in Italy. During the off-season, McWilliams-Franklin plays overseas; she will head to Russia and South Korea this year.</p>
        <p>Once her seasons abroad are finished, McWilliams-Franklin plans to live with her husband in Italy.</p>
        <p>Franklin began his tour of duty in the Middle East in January when he went to Kuwait. About a month later, he was sent to Tal Afar, a city in northern Iraq. There, he is in charge of an air terminal, arranging transportation around Iraq for military personnel.</p>
        <p>Franklin recently had a two-week leave, and he spent it here with his wife. But he returned to Iraq on Aug. 8, only 10 days before the Sun's first postseason game.</p>
        <p>He is scheduled to return to Italy in December. McWilliams-Franklin said she would probably not see her husband until next March.</p>
        <p>Franklin calls his wife every day and sends her about three or four e-mail messages. They use Web cams to see each other. If he cannot watch Sun games on Army television, Franklin tries to watch them on the Internet or listen to Webcasts.</p>
        <p>''Taj tells me all the time that she still worries about me,'' Franklin, 27, wrote in an e-mail message. ''But I know it would be that much worse if she couldn't hear from me on a daily basis, and I think her knowing that I am O.K. helps her be able to go out on the court and concentrate more on playing basketball.''</p>
        <p>After dropping off her daughter Michele at Arizona Western on Aug. 17, McWilliams-Franklin took a red-eye flight to Washington and arrived at 9 a.m. the next day. That night, in Game 1 of the series, McWilliams-Franklin scored 10 points and had team highs in rebounds (10) and assists (6) despite her fatigue.</p>
        <p>Her solid performance was a hint, perhaps, that nothing could distract her from her title aspirations.</p>
        <p>SPARKS TIE SERIES -- Mwadi Mabika scored 9 of her 17 points in the third quarter and the host Los Angeles Sparks rallied for a 78-70 victory against the Seattle Storm, tying their best-of-three Western Conference semifinal series, 1-1. (AP)</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
