<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Voucher Program for Inner-City Children</title>
    <meta content="Y10VOUC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1023478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Private Schools</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Children's Scholarship Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forstmann, Theodore J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walton, John T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ovitz, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Jacques</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E1DB123AF933A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Voucher Program for Inner-City Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinberg, Jacques</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Group of business leaders pledges to raise $200 million for national voucher program that would permit at least 50,000 inner-city public-school children to attend parochial and other private schools over next four years; Theodore J Forstmann and John T Walton, two of founders, will each give $50 million to Children's Scholarship Fund; photo; Michael Ovitz and and Mayor Rudolph Giuliani also attend announcement at New York Public Library; Forstmann says he believes in public education but it is not working in many places (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group of business leaders pledged yesterday to raise $200 million for a national voucher program that would permit at least 50,000 inner-city public-school children to attend parochial and other private schools over the next four years. The businessmen said they were trying to prod failing public schools into improving by subjecting them to market forces.</p>
        <p>Imitating similar programs begun last year in New York City and Washington, the organizers of the venture, known as the Children's Scholarship Fund, said they had already secured commitments of $140 million, including $50 million each from two founding board members. They are Theodore J. Forstmann, a senior partner in Forstmann Little &amp; Company, an investment firm, and the chairman of Gulfstream Aerospace, and John T. Walton, a director of Wal-Mart Stores Inc. and a son of Wal-Mart's founder, Sam Walton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A group of business leaders pledged yesterday to raise $200 million for a national voucher program that would permit at least 50,000 inner-city public-school children to attend parochial and other private schools over the next four years. The businessmen said they were trying to prod failing public schools into improving by subjecting them to market forces.</p>
        <p>Imitating similar programs begun last year in New York City and Washington, the organizers of the venture, known as the Children's Scholarship Fund, said they had already secured commitments of $140 million, including $50 million each from two founding board members. They are Theodore J. Forstmann, a senior partner in Forstmann Little &amp; Company, an investment firm, and the chairman of Gulfstream Aerospace, and John T. Walton, a director of Wal-Mart Stores Inc. and a son of Wal-Mart's founder, Sam Walton.</p>
        <p>Their effort is one of the largest private investments on behalf of schoolchildren, second only to the $500 million that Walter H. Annenberg, the philanthropist, committed to public-education reform over five years, beginning in 1993.</p>
        <p>The program announced yesterday, if fully financed, would also dwarf all of the private voucher programs that have sprouted in more than three dozen cities and towns in recent years, most of them in response to long-smoldering discontent among parents and businesses with the quality of public education.</p>
        <p>The most comprehensive of those efforts is in San Antonio, Tex., where a local physician and a foundation that endorses vouchers have committed to sending every interested public-school student living below the poverty level to private or parochial school, beginning next fall, through the end of high school. The cost of that program, which is being offered to more than 13,000 schoolchildren, is estimated at $50 million over 10 years.</p>
        <p>In announcing the voucher program yesterday in the New York Public Library, Mr. Forstmann and Mr. Walton were joined by Michael Ovitz, a major investor in Livent, an entertainment company, and the former president of Walt Disney Company, and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, a graduate of the city's Catholic schools. The Mayor inspired a group of Wall Street executives to create the New York program last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forstmann said that the extraordinary demand for the New York program -- more than 40,000 applications for just 2,200 scholarships for the current school year and the next one -- was all the evidence necessary to convince him that inner-city students craved alternatives to public schools.</p>
        <p>Moreover, he said, the national voucher program would provide an outlet for businesses that are searching for new ways to invest in education and are frustrated that their financial commitments to many public schools have had little effect.</p>
        <p>''I believe in public schools,'' said Mr. Forstmann, who attended only  private schools, the Greenwich Country Day School in Greenwich, Conn., and later Phillips Academy in Andover, Mass. ''But they're not working right in a lot of places. Money's not going to fix them.''</p>
        <p>The only way to motivate public schools to improve is to threaten them with the loss of their students, Mr. Forstmann said, echoing the philosophy of the voucher movement.</p>
        <p>''Competition makes you better,'' he said. ''If you have a totally free marketplace in anything, and you don't compete, you go broke. If you do compete, you prosper.''</p>
        <p>Like the voucher program in New York City, the new foundation expects to award its scholarships to low-income students by lottery, in as many as 50 cities. But unlike the New York group, which offers scholarships to students entering first through sixth grades, the new foundation will accept applications from low-income students in all grades.</p>
        <p>While the New York organization, known as the School Choice Scholarship Foundation, has provided students with up to $1,400 annually, in some cases covering full tuition, the national foundation will ask parents to cover at least 25 percent of tuition and sometimes as much as 60 percent, depending on their means, Mr. Forstmann said. ''They should own this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The national organization specified no limit on the amounts of individual awards, but estimated that the average tuition was $1,995 a year at private schools participating in existing voucher programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forstmann said that the organization was seeking corporate and individual partners in large and small cities to match the $100 million that he and Mr. Walton had put up. He said the organization had commitments from patrons to raise $5 million or more in Los Angeles, New York, Chicago and Washington.</p>
        <p>In New York, officials at the School Choice Scholarship Foundation, which has awarded $11 million in three-year scholarships over the last two years, said yesterday that they were considering a partnership with Mr. Forstmann's group. In Jersey City, N.J., Mayor Bret Schundler said he would personally contribute $25,000 in an effort to raise $400,000.</p>
        <p>Those seeking to gain widespread acceptance for both privately and publicly financed vouchers embraced yesterday's announcement as a validation of their movement.</p>
        <p>''This is a huge boost,'' said Clint Bolick, litigation director of the Institute for Justice. a public interest law firm that defends school voucher programs nationwide.</p>
        <p>But the response was more measured from those who fear the encroachment of such efforts on public-education spending.</p>
        <p>''These are wealthy people, and if this is where they want to put their money, who am I to argue,'' said Sandra Feldman, the president of the American Federation of Teachers. Like many educators, she opposes vouchers, contending that they siphon money from public schools. ''I would much prefer to have seen a contribution like that made to the public schools, the way Walter Annenberg did,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
