<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Special Education Evaluation Teams Have Few Backers</title>
    <meta content="10EVAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1023526"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Education (Handicapped)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Lynda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Education (Handicapped)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D6123AF933A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Special Education Evaluation Teams Have Few Backers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNDA RICHARDSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richardson, Lynda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Few defenders are found for psychologist-social worker-educator teams that screen children for special education at each public school in New York City; 70 percent of special-education students have no readily defined disability, but are labeled 'learning disabled' or emotionally handicapped'; teams are overseen not by principals but by extensive bureaucracy in districts; Mayor Rudolph Giuliani is calling for privatization of assessments (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few defenders can be found for the three-member teams -- a psychologist, a social worker and educator -- who screen children for special education at each school. Some classroom teachers and principals see them as unproductive clock-watchers who play cards all day, perform a few tasks, then go home promptly when the last school bell rings. They average only an evaluation or two a week.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani joined this chorus of critics yesterday, urging the Board of Education to turn over the job to private companies in the hope that they could evaluate students and decide on placement more efficiently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few defenders can be found for the three-member teams -- a psychologist, a social worker and educator -- who screen children for special education at each school. Some classroom teachers and principals see them as unproductive clock-watchers who play cards all day, perform a few tasks, then go home promptly when the last school bell rings. They average only an evaluation or two a week.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani joined this chorus of critics yesterday, urging the Board of Education to turn over the job to private companies in the hope that they could evaluate students and decide on placement more efficiently.</p>
        <p>The school-based teams have long been criticized for simply rubber-stamping a teacher's referral, and for funneling a disproportionate number of black and Hispanic boys into dead-end, segregated classrooms. Once assigned to special education, students are rarely allowed to return to regular education and few graduate from high school.</p>
        <p>Most special-education students are not deaf, blind or classified with any other readily defined disability. Instead, 70 percent are labeled ''learning disabled'' or ''emotionally handicapped,'' terms that are loosely applied and may provide cover for a teacher who wants to get rid of a troublesome student, recent studies of the system have found.</p>
        <p>For years, schools chancellors and blue-ribbon commissions have tried to reform the city's special-education system in the hope of shifting large numbers of children back into  regular classrooms.</p>
        <p>Those efforts have singled out the evaluation system, which has developed into a parallel hierarchy within the school system.</p>
        <p>The city's 1,000 three-member teams are not required to teach any students. They mainly administer psychological and educational assessments. The teams are not under the control of school principals now, although Schools Chancellor Rudy Crew is proposing to change that system by allowing principals to assign the teams to supporting classroom teachers.</p>
        <p>The school teams are now overseen by an extensive bureaucracy consisting of 32 district outposts, known as the Committees on Special Education. The committees include a core of psychologists and other professionals supported by dozens of file clerks, typists and other workers. Extensive files are kept on each student, often reaching hundreds of pages. The committees report to special-education officials at the Board of Education's central headquarters in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>When a teacher refers a student to special education, the clock begins to tick. The school system must evaluate the child within 30 school days and decide on a placement within 60 days. A Federal court decree requires that children suspected of having a disability be processed in a timely fashion.</p>
        <p>If the school-based team determines that the child is disabled, it writes an individual education plan -- a sort of academic prescription with diagnosis and statement of the kind of services needed. The team also meets with the child's parent, who has a right to refuse the school team's recommendation and demand a hearing from an impartial hearing officer, paid for by the Board of Education.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
