<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jurors Tell of Emotional Days in a Small Room</title>
    <meta content="Y17JUR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/17/business/17JURY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1401386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ENRON'S MANY STRANDS: THE DELIBERATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Enron Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Andersen, Arthur, &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Arthur Andersen &amp; Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2D6113CF934A25755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jurors Tell of Emotional Days in a Small Room</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jurors Tell of Emotional Days in a Small Room</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN D. GLATER with JOHN SCHWARTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwartz, John; Glater, Jonathan D</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, June 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jurors describes deliberations stretching over 10 days that led to conviction of Arthur Andersen for obstruction of justice for altering documents related to its audit of bankrupt Enron Corp; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This morning, juror No. 10 called the jewelry store where she works and said she would not be back until Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''I said I couldn't come in,'' the juror, Wanda McKay explained in a telephone interview today, a day after the guilty verdict in the Arthur Andersen case was announced. She was worried, she said, that she could not get through the day without crying, after the jury found Andersen guilty of obstruction of justice for altering documents related to Enron.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The verdict came on the 10th day of deliberations, and while jurors said that discussions rarely turned bitter, every day was an ordeal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This morning, juror No. 10 called the jewelry store where she works and said she would not be back until Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''I said I couldn't come in,'' the juror, Wanda McKay explained in a telephone interview today, a day after the guilty verdict in the Arthur Andersen case was announced. She was worried, she said, that she could not get through the day without crying, after the jury found Andersen guilty of obstruction of justice for altering documents related to Enron.</p>
        <p>It was not the shredding of documents at Andersen's Houston office that proved to be decisive, Ms. McKay said, but evidence about the efforts of Nancy Temple, a lawyer with Andersen, to revise a single memorandum.</p>
        <p>The verdict came on the 10th day of deliberations, and while jurors said that discussions rarely turned bitter, every day was an ordeal. Some jurors did not seem to understand what the case was about; others simply took time to make up their minds; and the jury foreman, who planned to write a book about the experience, painstakingly copied into his notes some of the documents offered as evidence.</p>
        <p>''There were some emotional days,'' said Catina Sorrell, another juror, who is a customer service representative at Gemsa Loan Services in Houston. ''You have to sit in this little room. You can't go anywhere. You just have to focus.''</p>
        <p>The nine men and three women charged with deciding the case began deliberations every morning with a prayer. An initial poll on the first day showed that four thought the firm was innocent, four thought it guilty and four were undecided.</p>
        <p>The foreman then took over, jurors said, painstakingly leading them in the first few days through the instructions given by Judge Melinda F. Harmon, who presided over the trial. Ultimately those instructions -- which required the jury to find the firm guilty if it found that one person had persuaded others to alter or destroy a document in order to impede an official proceeding like a Securities and Exchange Commission investigation -- were fatal to Andersen, Ms. McKay and Ms. Sorrell said.</p>
        <p>''They just forced us to come back with a guilty verdict,'' Ms. McKay said. ''I'd like to know how the judge comes up with the instructions.'' Shredding was not the issue for her, she said, because she had dealt with examiners in her 24 years at Amoco. Examiners from Texaco would inspect jointly owned wells, and she recalled cleaning up paperwork in anticipation of those reviews.</p>
        <p>Initially Ms. McKay said she was convinced the firm was innocent.</p>
        <p>The jury quickly discounted the testimony of several witnesses and focused on those who struck them as credible and reliable. John Stewart, an Andersen partner who was responsible for resolving complex accounting questions, seemed the most believable, jurors said. The jury spent several hours analyzing what Mr. Stewart said about his conversations with Ms. Temple, the Andersen lawyer who the jury concluded had persuaded other employees to alter or destroy documents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart, however, wanted to preserve his documents, Ms. Sorrell said, in order to show that Andersen accounting experts had reviewed certain Enron transactions. ''He just seemed like a straightforward guy. We knew we could rely on his testimony,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Other witnesses were less important, jurors said, although the testimony of David Stulb, who heads Andersen's fraud and investigative unit and testified for the government, changed the way that some viewed David B. Duncan, the Andersen partner who managed the Enron account and who also testified for prosecutors. Mr. Stulb told the court that at one time, he admonished Mr. Duncan not to destroy a memorandum related to Enron and that Mr. Duncan did not seem to understand that it would be wrong to do so.</p>
        <p>''He felt like David Duncan was caught like a deer in the headlights,'' Ms. McKay recalled. ''He told Duncan that he needed to get some direction on what to keep and toss.''</p>
        <p>Other jurors dismissed Mr. Duncan out of hand. Ms. Sorrell noted that he had signed an plea agreement with prosecutors.</p>
        <p>Jurors painstakingly constructed timelines of events within Andersen, noting when Ms. Temple sent out her e-mail message advising the firm's staff about complying with the document-retention policy, and when Mr. Stulb said he spoke with Mr. Duncan.</p>
        <p>Not everyone understood what was going on at first. One juror, Ms. Sorrell said, thought that the case had something to do with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration; another thought they were deciding the guilt or innocence of Mr. Duncan who had pleaded guilty to obstruction of justice. (Ms. McKay said she helped set that juror straight.)</p>
        <p>Everyone did eventually come to a common understanding, Oscar Criner, the foreman, said in a telephone interview yesterday. ''Everybody understood what was being alleged and what was being looked for in the evidence and testimony, and what we found,'' Mr. Criner said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Criner, who teaches computer science at Texas Southern University, said he hopes to write a book about the trial. He said he was drawn to telling the story because ''I think the problem is much more than just the Andersen case itself. I think there are questions about American business that have to be addressed here, and the direction that business has been going.''</p>
        <p>But his constant note-taking irked other jurors, who said they might have been able to finish days earlier if he had spent less time writing everything down. Mr. Criner was also the last person to agree that the firm was guilty, late Friday.</p>
        <p>Several jurors said that proposed revisions by Ms. Temple, the Andersen lawyer, to an Andersen memorandum that described some concerns about the accounting treatment of certain Enron transactions were the decisive evidence.</p>
        <p>''When we looked at the Nancy Temple stuff, and with the instructions that the judge gave us, there was no way we could not find Arthur Andersen guilty,'' Ms. McKay said. On Thursday morning the jury had asked the judge whether they had to agree on the identity of the person at fault in order to convict the firm, but by the time an answer came on Friday afternoon, the issue was moot, she said.</p>
        <p>''Nancy Temple was found guilty of altering one document,'' she said, adding that she had known before the trial that Ms. Temple had asserted her Fifth Amendment right not to testify. ''One person did one thing and tore the whole company down.''</p>
        <p>ENRON'S MANY STRANDS: THE DELIBERATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
