<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OLYMPICS: Nagano 1998 -- A Scar That Helped Skating; Skating's Popularity Has Jumped Since Attack on Kerrigan in '94</title>
    <meta content="06OLYM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1998)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harding, Tonya</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerrigan, Nancy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DA1230F935A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1385" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OLYMPICS: Nagano 1998 -- A Scar That Helped Skating; Skating's Popularity Has Jumped Since Attack on Kerrigan in '94</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Jan. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on preparations for US Olympic figure skating trials in Philadelphia discusses how popularity of figure skating has grown since 1994 trials in which skater Nancy Kerrigan was assaulted by friend of rival skater Tonya Harding; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even now, four years later, Nancy Kerrigan's coach said he gets a sinking feeling every time he even thinks of Detroit.</p>
        <p>''I never want to go to that city again,'' Evy Scotvold said. ''Isn't that weird? It's certainly not the city's fault.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even now, four years later, Nancy Kerrigan's coach said he gets a sinking feeling every time he even thinks of Detroit.</p>
        <p>''I never want to go to that city again,'' Evy Scotvold said. ''Isn't that weird? It's certainly not the city's fault.''</p>
        <p>The Olympic figure skating trials begin here Tuesday on the fourth anniversary of the attack on Kerrigan by associates of Tonya Harding. On a snowy Jan. 6, 1994, at the Olympic trials in downtown Detroit's Cobo Arena, Shane Stant clubbed Kerrigan's right knee with a collapsible baton in what was the most horrifying, embarrassing and ultimately beneficial moment in the history of the sport.</p>
        <p>The idea that one athlete would seek to inflict harm on another, especially in a sport thought to be as genteel as figure skating, repulsed and riveted a nation, sending ratings through the roof during the Winter Olympics and helping to make figure skating the most popular television sport outside of the National Football League.</p>
        <p>Kerrigan and Harding caught a wave of interest in women's sports that had begun to rise noticeably with the 1992 Summer Olympics in Barcelona, Spain, and would crest with victories by American women in basketball, softball and soccer in the 1996 Atlanta Games.</p>
        <p>In 1994, huge numbers of women were already watching figure skating, where artistry and choreography are as important as athleticism. What Kerrigan and Harding did was to take figure skating from sport to soap opera and launch it like a triple axel into popular culture. The result was a larger male audience and television ratings that began to challenge the supremacy of professional football.</p>
        <p>''Men had a revelation,'' said Brian Boitano, the 1988 Olympic champion, referring to the increased interest in the sport generated by Kerrigan and Harding. ''Men control networks and sponsorship dollars.''</p>
        <p>Four years later, it is almost impossible to channel-surf during the weekend without happening upon some skating event. Teen-age stars such as Tara Lipinski and Michelle Kwan, along with Olympic champions such as Boitano and Kristi Yamaguchi, can now make more than $1 million a year. Recently, the United States Figure Skating Association extended its broadcast contract with ABC for $100 million over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>While a glut of televised competitions has led to a dip in the ratings the past two seasons, interest should remain fervent as Lipinski and Kwan battle for a gold medal at the upcoming Winter Olympics in Nagano, Japan.</p>
        <p>CBS is expecting large ratings for figure skating next month during the Nagano Games, although they are not likely to top the 48.5 that Harding-Kerrigan generated for the women's short program on Feb. 23, 1994, the third-highest-rated sporting event ever. Each rating point equals 1 percent of all television households in the United States. Currently, a rating point is equivalent to 980,000 households.</p>
        <p>''It's absolutely mind-boggling how figure skating became so popular because of that incident,'' said Frank Carroll, who coaches Kwan. ''As much as we put down Tonya Harding, women's sports -- figure skating in particular -- owe her a great debt of gratitude. But it was a terrible, regrettable way to go about it.''</p>
        <p>If anything, there has been too much of a good thing for the sport, which tends to have repetitive performances week after week. There is also mass confusion over which athletes are eligible for the Olympics. While other sports have insured that all their top athletes are eligible, figure skating excludes some athletes, such as Boitano and Yamaguchi, because they participate in competitions that are not sanctioned by the International Skating Union, the sport's world governing body.</p>
        <p>''I think the Olympics need to be opened to professionals,'' Boitano said. ''People stop me every day and say, 'Are you in the Olympics this year?' It's so confusing.''</p>
        <p>Harding, who finished eighth at the 1994 Winter Games in Lillehammer,  Norway, was subsequently banned for life from Olympic-type skating by the United States Figure Skating Association. She pleaded guilty to conspiring, with her former husband, Jeff Gillooly, and her bodyguard, Shawn Eckhardt, to impede the investigation of the assault. She was fined $160,000, given three years of probation and ordered to perform 500 hours of community service.</p>
        <p>Said Scotvold: ''I wouldn't do anything to thank Tonya for anything. She was a shameful blot on figure skating. That's the nicest thing you can say.''</p>
        <p>Harding is 27 now and gives interviews only when she is paid. She has continued to lead a tabloid existence in Portland, Ore., briefly managing a professional wrestler, entering into another short, failed marriage, claiming to be stalked by professional golfers, saving a woman's life in a bar by giving her mouth-to-mouth resuscitation and alleging that a man tried to kidnap her from her pickup truck.</p>
        <p>She has appeared recently as an actress in a low-budget movie, as a participant with Gillooly in a wedding-night video that became widely distributed, and as an exhibition skater at a minor league hockey game last February in Reno during which she was booed and greeted with a banner that said, ''Tonya Harding Go Home.'' Usually, skaters are showered with stuffed animals that are thrown onto the ice after a performance. In Harding's case, two collapsible batons were thrown onto the ice.</p>
        <p>Eckhardt, Gillooly, Stant and Derrick Smith all completed prison sentences in 1995 for their roles in the attack. Gillooly changed his name to Jeff Stone and remarried. At Cobo Arena, the glass door that Stant escaped through was replaced with Plexiglas, but was otherwise left untouched. ''It's kind of a shrine,'' said Patrick Imesch, Cobo's operations manager, during the Skate America competition in October.</p>
        <p>Kerrigan, who is 28, recovered to win a silver medal after the clubbing attack, narrowly missing the gold, which was won by Oksana Baiul of the Ukraine. Kerrigan married her agent, Jerry Solomon, began a professional skating career and is now the mother of a 13-month-old son. She did not emerge as a sympathetic figure after the Olympics because of petulant behavior, but Scotvold, her coach, said that she has mellowed in recent years.</p>
        <p>''She's a different person -- easy to get along with, easygoing, so happy,'' Scotvold said. ''There was a lot of stress after the Olympics. She was so exhausted. Keeping her exposed and not giving her a break turned things against her. She was making statements that were terrible, but she had suffered a tough loss. Jerry should have gotten her away and let her collect herself.''</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, it was reported that the Fox television network tried to arrange a Harding-Kerrigan rematch. Fox denied the story, but a person who said he saw the proposal to Harding said that she was to be paid $150,000 and Kerrigan was to be paid $200,000 to $250,000 for a competition and a face-to-face meeting, but the deal fell through. Solomon did not return a phone call seeking comment.</p>
        <p>''Nancy would never be for anything like that,'' Scotvold said.</p>
        <p>Dick Button, the two-time Olympic champion who produces professional competitions, floated the idea of having Harding compete professionally, saying in 1996 that ''once someone does their sentence, they should be given a second chance in life.'' However, the idea died when Yamaguchi, the 1992 Olympic champion, said she would not compete against Harding.</p>
        <p>Michael Rosenberg, Harding's former agent, drew a comparison with Latrell Sprewell of the Golden State Warriors, who was suspended by the National Basketball Association for a year after choking his coach, P. J. Carlesimo. If Sprewell is allowed to play again, Rosenberg said, then Harding deserves a chance to skate.</p>
        <p>''She has lost her livelihood, which is not the American way,'' Rosenberg said. ''There's so much hypocrisy in figure skating. Our sport is so puritanical.''</p>
        <p>If only in a joking way, even Juan Antonio Samaranch, the president of the International Olympic Committee, seemed to lament Harding's disappearance. No, the 1998 Nagano ratings would not approach 1994, he said in an interview last March at the world figure skating championships. ''But,'' he added in a laughing reference to the attack, ''maybe we could arrange something.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
