<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Do Breast Self-Exams Save Lives? Science Still Doesn't Have Answer</title>
    <meta content="06EXAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985604"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Preventive Medicine</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zuger, Abigail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Breast Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EFDD1530F935A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Do Breast Self-Exams Save Lives? Science Still Doesn't Have Answer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABIGAIL ZUGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zuger, Abigail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Question of whether women should give themselves monthly breast examination to detect lumps remains one of most disputed issues in preventive medicine; researchers try to figure out why a maneuver whose merits seem so intuitively obvious should be so remarkably resistant to scientific validation; proponents of breast self-examination acknowledge that especially in younger women, ritual results mainly in periods of dreadful anxiety and unnecessary surgical procedures; techniques for breast self-examination described (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF examining her own breasts once a month is not actually the lifesaving tool it is cracked up to be, Estelle Bolofsky does not want to hear about it.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bolofsky, 47, an office supervisor in Manhattan, is a devout acolyte of the protocol the American Cancer Society recommends for all women over the age of 20. Once a month, she doggedly inspects and massages each breast and armpit, all the while fighting off the fear that she will discover a lump like the one that sent her to the gynecologist in a panic two years ago.  That lump turned out to be benign, but Ms. Bolofsky is not taking any chances. ''You have to know your own body,'' she said. ''If you don't take care of yourself, then who's going to take care of you?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF examining her own breasts once a month is not actually the lifesaving tool it is cracked up to be, Estelle Bolofsky does not want to hear about it.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bolofsky, 47, an office supervisor in Manhattan, is a devout acolyte of the protocol the American Cancer Society recommends for all women over the age of 20. Once a month, she doggedly inspects and massages each breast and armpit, all the while fighting off the fear that she will discover a lump like the one that sent her to the gynecologist in a panic two years ago.  That lump turned out to be benign, but Ms. Bolofsky is not taking any chances. ''You have to know your own body,'' she said. ''If you don't take care of yourself, then who's going to take care of you?''</p>
        <p>But despite the determination of Ms. Bolofsky and millions of women like her to believe in breast self-examination, medical research has not yet been able to prove that the complex monthly routine does save lives.</p>
        <p>Instead, it remains one of the most disputed issues in preventive medicine, pitting experts and policy makers against one another, while doctors and patients dangle in the middle, and researchers try to figure out why a maneuver whose merits seem so intuitively obvious should be so remarkably resistant to scientific validation.</p>
        <p>Before mammography became widely used in the 1980's, breast cancer was routinely diagnosed by touch: a doctor discovered a lump in the breast, or, more often, a woman found one herself. Even now, in the mammography era, ''a significant proportion of breast cancers are found on self-exam, particularly among women less than 50,'' said Dr. Hiram S. Cody 3d, a breast surgeon at Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center in New York.</p>
        <p>Simple logic would thus dictate that the more regularly and methodically a woman examines her breasts, the more likely cancer is to be found at the earliest possible moment and the less likely the woman is to die of the disease.</p>
        <p>But this logic is evidently so confounded both by the complex biology of breast cancer and by the complicated psyches of women at risk that studies from around the world have been unable to confirm it.</p>
        <p>The evidence that the procedure is worthwhile remains lukewarm enough for the United States Preventative Services Task Force, one of the pre-eminent advisory bodies for disease screening policies in the country, to state last year, ''There is insufficient evidence to recommend for or against the teaching of breast self-examination.''</p>
        <p>Yet many cancer experts feel so strongly about the importance of self-examination, in conjunction with regular mammograms and breast examinations by doctors, that they argue that if science cannot support self-examination, then the science must be wrong.</p>
        <p>''I tell everybody to do it,'' Dr. Cody said. ''If we tell women it's not important to examine themselves, we might be making a big mistake.''</p>
        <p>And a New York oncologist, who spoke on the condition that he not be identified, said: ''I don't care what the studies show. Self-examination clearly is a way of early detection.  It's a wise thing to do.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Susan Love, a California surgeon who has written extensively on breast cancer and other women's health issues, has dismissed breast self-examination for years as overrated, pointing out that although many women find breast lumps themselves, it is usually in the course of ordinary living, without an intensely fear-provoking monthly ritual.</p>
        <p>Even proponents of breast self-examination acknowledge that especially in younger women, the ritual results mainly in periods of dreadful anxiety and unnecessary surgical procedures. Since breast cancer is more common in women over 50 than younger ones, the lumps younger women find in their breasts, like the one that sent Ms. Bolofsky into a tearful weekend panic two years ago, are far more likely to be false alarms than cancer.</p>
        <p>Still, when breast cancer occurs in younger women, it is far deadlier than in older women, making a high rate of false alarms, at least in theory, a cost worth tolerating.</p>
        <p>''But by the time a woman picks something up, it's really large,'' said Dr. Diane M. Harper, a family doctor at Dartmouth Medical School in Hanover, N.H. Tumors found on self-examination average more than a half-inch in diameter, much larger than tumors found on mammography. Some experts believe that finding tumors this large a few months earlier may make very little difference in their response to treatment. If the tumors are aggressive enough to spread out of the breast, markedly reducing chances of survival, they are likely to have done so already, these authorities say.</p>
        <p>In fact, early detection of these tumors may only increase the length of time a woman has to live with a diagnosis of cancer, without actually changing her prognosis. That may be one reason why no study has found that self-examination saves lives.</p>
        <p>Another reason may be the difficulty of coaxing women to overcome the fear of what they may find when they examine their own breasts.</p>
        <p>''Only about 25 percent of our patients do it right,'' said Dr. Kathryn Kash, director of Psychosocial Services at Strang Cancer Prevention Center in New York. Despite the intensive instruction in breast self-examination technique the center provides, Dr. Kash said: ''The high-risk women that we see are terrified to do it. They're so worried they might find something.''</p>
        <p>And yet, doing it right may make all the difference.</p>
        <p>A handful of studies, among them one reported in November in The Canadian Medical Association Journal, suggest that breast self-examination may save lives, but only in women using good techniques.</p>
        <p>Studying almost 90,000 Canadian women, researchers found no decrease in the number of fatal breast cancer cases among those taught to examine their own breasts. But the women who looked at the contour of the breasts carefully and used the pads of their three middle fingers to examine them were somewhat less likely to develop fatal disease two years later.</p>
        <p>''The overall message is that, yes, breast self-exam does seem to help,  but you have to do it well,'' said one of the researchers, Dr. Cornelia J. Baines, an associate professor in the department of public health sciences at the University of Toronto.</p>
        <p>Women who know they are at relatively lower risk of developing the disease may do the self-examination better than others, Dr. T. Gregory Hislop, an epidemiologist at the University of British Columbia in Vancouver, observed in a commentary on the study.</p>
        <p>And what will probably become the definitive study on the value of self-examination, now under way in China, has yet to confirm the finding.  In it, more than 100,000 Shanghai factory workers have been carefully instructed in self-examination techniques and are not only regularly supervised while examining themselves, but also receive periodic reminder visits from study workers.</p>
        <p>A preliminary report published in The Journal of the National Cancer Institute in March showed that after five years, the breast cancer death rates among these highly trained self-examiners were no different from those in a similar group taught techniques for preventing lower-back pain instead.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Baines said that even when the Shanghai study was finished, in 5 or 10 years, ''it's unlikely the results will apply here.'' Breast cancer rates in China are lower than those in the United States and Canada, and because screening mammography is unavailable in China, self-examination may be more important for screening.</p>
        <p>This means that the uncertainty about whether breast self-examination is worth the time and effort spent learning to do it correctly -- and the money spent promoting it -- is likely to persist here for years, forcing doctors to find a compromise they and their patients can live with.</p>
        <p>''I don't push it,'' said Dr. Eileen Hoffman, associate director for education at the Mount Sinai Women's Health Program in New York. ''I don't like to make women feel that they're responsible when they don't find their lumps 'soon enough.' I'm careful to tell them that the goal is not to find lumps but to get to know what normal is.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Soheyla D. Gharib, co-director of the Women's Health Center at Brigham and Women's Hospital in Boston, said: ''If it pushes all someone's panic buttons, then I say, don't do it. Then I may see them in the office a little more frequently. But it's such an easy and cheap thing to do. It's good to get to know your own landscape.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Harper at Dartmouth said: ''For new patients, I get a read on who the patient is, her body image, her sexuality and her self-esteem. Some really don't want to think of their breasts just as objects waiting to become diseased. But women who are doing it already, I don't discourage them. Usually they're doing it because they're good citizens.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Harper said her patients often admitted that '' 'I'm doing it because I'm supposed to, but I haven't the vaguest idea of what I'm doing.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
