<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Madden Runs Fox's Show, but NBC's Trio Works</title>
    <meta content="06SAND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fox Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Football League</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E7D71530F935A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Madden Runs Fox's Show, but NBC's Trio Works</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article compares Fox television coverage of National Football League playoffs with that of NBC (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You could not choose two more dissimilar sets of announcers than those who will call Sunday's National Football League conference championship games.</p>
        <p>Both teams describe and analyze plays completely, although Fox's John Madden still reigns supreme. Both teams rapidly and expertly describe what you cannot casually see, making points that make you think.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You could not choose two more dissimilar sets of announcers than those who will call Sunday's National Football League conference championship games.</p>
        <p>Both teams describe and analyze plays completely, although Fox's John Madden still reigns supreme. Both teams rapidly and expertly describe what you cannot casually see, making points that make you think.</p>
        <p>But NBC's threesome of Dick Enberg, Phil Simms and Paul Maguire, which will continue its act through the Super Bowl, is a rather smooth-running democracy.</p>
        <p>Fox's team is more of a benevolent dictatorship, orchestrated by the hyperkinetic Madden, with help from the very low-key Pat Summerall.</p>
        <p>When NBC assembled its partnership -- now in its third season -- the questions included: Would there be enough room for three voices? Which voice(s) would have to clam up? Would the neophyte Simms find his way in?</p>
        <p>What has happened is that Enberg has curbed his florid excesses but has not given up his ability to make very complete play calls with all the requisite details, sprinkled with player trivia and stories. Maguire has stepped back from his chattier days, and Simms has fit in without seeming to have served an apprenticeship.</p>
        <p>Maguire's generosity -- sometimes not speaking when it seems his natural turn and more often ceding to Simms the first comment after Enberg's play call -- has made Simms better. Surprisingly, they rarely step on each other's words.</p>
        <p>Let's look at second-half numbers from Sunday's Denver-Kansas City game. No one spoke more frequently than Enberg, but he must call plays, reset situations and recite network promos. In the half, Enberg spoke 101 separate times, but together Simms and Maguire spoke 129 times.</p>
        <p>Enberg's average sound bite lasted 17.7 seconds, Simms's 11.7 seconds and Maguire's 9.7 seconds. Enberg's time spoken of 29 minutes 40 seconds was more than Simms's 13:13 and Maguire's 9:52 together.</p>
        <p>In their 17th year together, Madden and Summerall present a very different product. It is Madden's show. Summerall's part is noticeable, and underrated. But unlike Enberg's role, Summerall's is subservient. Whereas Enberg is very descriptive -- and partly analytical -- Summerall epitomizes terseness.</p>
        <p>In his exuberance, Madden interrupts Summerall (a lot more last Sunday than I can recall), talking over his partner as if he were in a Robert Altman film, sometimes reducing Summerall to ''yep,'' ''no'' and ''yeah.'' Summerall adroitly plays the sidekick -- Ed McMahon to Madden's Johnny Carson.</p>
        <p>During last Sunday's Tampa Bay-Green Bay game, Madden and Summerall's output illustrated their dynamic. In the second half, Madden's sound bites averaged 13.4 seconds and Summerall's 9.0 seconds, remarkable because Summerall is the play-by-play man.</p>
        <p>In terms of airspace, Madden was more like Enberg, rolling up 28:06 in time spoken, compared with Summerall's 21:09. In a fairly typical exchange, Summerall and Madden sort of conversed:</p>
        <p>Madden: This was an interesting spot.</p>
        <p>Summerall: Yeah.</p>
        <p>Madden: It looked like the ball got beyond that.</p>
        <p>Summerall: Sure did.</p>
        <p>Madden: Then they brought it back. It's going to be short.</p>
        <p>Summerall: Do you go? You got to go?</p>
        <p>Madden: I think so. In this situation, playing at home, I'd think you would. I would think that in this situation, you'd just go quarterback sneak, but I don't think you need a deep handoff or everything. You're just talking about inches. Here, I'd think Brett Favre would just take it and sneak it. He looked a little confused.</p>
        <p>Summerall: Yes.</p>
        <p>Perhaps because Summerall does not need much airspace, the Fox team seems to have more time for mirth than NBC's does. They had time on Sunday to riff on mukluks, the origin of the ''Huck and Buck'' pose in football photography, the All-Madden Team, why Green Bay fans wear hats beneath their cheeseheads and how Fox's Matt Millen ate the food Madden wanted to eat. And did we hear Madden call Frank Winters, the Packers' center, ''Frankie Bag of Donuts''? Yep.</p>
        <p>Still, their extracurricular activities did not overwhelm such savvy stuff as isolated camera views of Travis Jervey, a Green Bay special teams player; Madden's excellent parsing of defenses like the ''cover two,'' and a rapid-fire second-half montage showing how Tampa Bay's offensive line was handling Gilbert Brown, Green Bay's tiring (and overweight) defensive tackle.</p>
        <p>Maybe the tightness of Denver's 14-10 victory over Kansas City kept too much mirth out of the NBC booth. The belief here is that while he is not the raging wit he was with Marv Albert, Maguire remains one of the game's better analysts.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, he smartly noted exactly how fullback Howard Griffith was blocking for Denver's Terrell Davis, how spinning the ball almost caused a punt by Kansas City's Louie Aguiar to be blocked, and how Kansas City was badly managing its timeouts.</p>
        <p>The adaptation to time sharing in the NBC booth is interesting in speculating about what would happen if Madden headed to ABC's ''Monday Night Football'' in the next N.F.L. TV deal. Few can imagine Madden being one of three, or even existing comfortably as one of two, with Al Michaels, who is as different from Summerall as Phil Rizzuto.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
