<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A-12 Decision Starts Scramble For Alternatives</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19910110T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="414020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">A-12 AIRPLANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY AIRCRAFT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAVIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEFENSE CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MCDONNELL DOUGLAS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL DYNAMICS CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHENEY, DICK (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D8153AF93AA35752C0A967958260" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A-12 Decision Starts Scramble For Alternatives</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defense Secretary Dick Cheney's decision on Monday to cancel the Navy's new attack plane has set off a scramble in the Pentagon to find a replacement aircraft and among military contractors to offer a solution.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon today declined to discuss alternatives to the carrier-based A-12 warplane. Mr. Cheney canceled the $57 billion program because of delays and cost overruns. The A-12 was to have replaced the A-6 Intruder, which first flew in the Vietnam War.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Defense Secretary Dick Cheney's decision on Monday to cancel the Navy's new attack plane has set off a scramble in the Pentagon to find a replacement aircraft and among military contractors to offer a solution.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon today declined to discuss alternatives to the carrier-based A-12 warplane. Mr. Cheney canceled the $57 billion program because of delays and cost overruns. The A-12 was to have replaced the A-6 Intruder, which first flew in the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>But aviation experts said the alternatives include a short-term plan to modify two existing fighter planes, the F-14 or the FA-18, for a new attack-oriented mission, or to start from scratch and build a plane like the A-12, which was planned as a deep-strike bomber that could be used in all weather and at night. The plane was to use radar-evading stealth technology.</p>
        <p>Whatever course the Pentagon takes will be dictated by forces larger than simply the need to fill the Navy's aircraft gap. Since the Navy first began developing the A-12, tensions with the Soviet Union have lessened and the military's budget has been cut.  Ex-Navy Chief's Assessment</p>
        <p>"The real issue is whether the threat out there warrants the huge costs of an plane like the A-12," said John Lehman, who was Navy Secretary in the Reagan Administration. "Is there any target in world worth that much money?"</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's decision shocked many officials in other branches of the military. The ruling, they said, broke a time-honored Pentagon tradition of bailing out troubled programs that military officials said were essential.</p>
        <p>The decision, for example, also terminated an Air Force version of the plane, the Advanced Tactical Aircraft. The Air Force plane, which would have replaced the F-111, would have been built in the late 1990's after the Navy's A-12 production line was operating.</p>
        <p>The builders of the A-12, the McDonnell Douglas Corporation and the General Dynamics Corporation, both of St. Louis, have said 9,000 workers would lose their jobs. But it is highly unlikely that political pressure caused by the layoffs will force Mr. Cheney to reverse his ruling.</p>
        <p>Unlike some programs that Congress has financed over Mr. Cheney's objections -- like the V-22, or Osprey, aircraft -- lawmakers have sharply criticized the costly A-12 program.</p>
        <p>Each alternative to the A-12 has its own set of obstacles, but in the end the Navy will almost certainly have to settle for a lesser plane than it originally wanted. Long-Term Budget Constraints</p>
        <p>The Pentagon's long-term budget constraints will make it difficult to build a plane as expensive as the A-12, even if future builders use the lessons, and some of the technology and design, from the A-12 builders.</p>
        <p>This approach, though, seemed to be the direction that Mr. Cheney was pointing to on Monday when he said, "Stealth technology will be required if attack aircraft are to elude advanced fighters and surface-to-air missiles in the future."</p>
        <p>If Mr. Cheney insists on a replacement for the A-6 that is as capable as the A-12 of evading radar, "the plane is five to nine years years away," said a Senate staff member said.</p>
        <p>By taking a less costly route and modifying existing planes, the Navy would have to accept an aircraft that would not fly as far as the A-6 or carry as many bombs, or be as capable of evading radar as the A-12.</p>
        <p>The A-6, still being built by the Grumman Corporation, can carry 10,000 pounds of bombs to a target 650 miles away and was vital in missions like the United States attack on Libya in 1986. The last of the A-6's are expected to come off the line early next year.</p>
        <p>The F-14, or Tomcat, also built by Grumman, is an carrier-based, air-to-air fighter that can be modified to carry 8,000 pounds of bombs, but does not have the A-6's range, a Navy official familiar with the planes said.  Problem With an Alternative</p>
        <p>Another alternative, the FA-18, or Hornet, a carrier-based fighter-attack plane built by McDonnell Douglas, has only about one-third the A-6's range. Even if the FA-18 were upgraded to increase its bomb-carrying range to 600 miles from 400 miles, the Navy official said it would carry far fewer bombs than the A-6.</p>
        <p>Neither plane was designed to accommodate the large amount of radar equipment stored in the A-6 nose that gives it excellent ground-tracking ability in all types of weather. Both planes could be refined to make them less observable on radar, but neither would have the A-12's ability to avoid detection, the Navy official said.</p>
        <p>Some military analysts estimated that it could cost $2 billion to make the changes needed to modify the FA-18. The analysts said that modifying the F-14 could be 20 to 30 percent less expensive than modifying the FA-18.</p>
        <p>Most military analysts today ruled out another option: building a new, upgraded A-6 model. The A-6 was first designed in 1954, and most aviation experts said its technology has been stretched to its limits.</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 10, 1991, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about the Pentagon's cancellation of the A-12 attack plane misstated the starting date of the aircraft's development. The Navy began developing it in the mid-1980's, not in the 1950's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 10, 1991, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about the Pentagon's cancellation of the A-12 attack plane misstated the starting date of the aircraft's development. The Navy began developing it in the mid-1980's, not in the 1950's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
