<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Last Few Chores of a Fading Season</title>
    <meta content="10NGAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="IN THE GARDEN" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="888765"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3D81138F933A25752C1A960958260" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Last Few Chores of a Fading Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE outdoor gardening season is winding down, But don't put the tools away just yet. A few chores remain.</p>
        <p>One of the happiest chores for anyone is that last mowing of the lawn. The final cut after the last leaf has been blown or raked off signals that the mower can be stowed away. That last cut should be a short one, about one and a half inches high, chiefly to discourage mold from developing in the early spring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE outdoor gardening season is winding down, But don't put the tools away just yet. A few chores remain.</p>
        <p>One of the happiest chores for anyone is that last mowing of the lawn. The final cut after the last leaf has been blown or raked off signals that the mower can be stowed away. That last cut should be a short one, about one and a half inches high, chiefly to discourage mold from developing in the early spring.</p>
        <p>All that said and done, it is time to stow away the mower. Be sure it is clean and the motor well drained. Some fastidious gardeners even like to cover their mowers to keep them clean over the storage months. If the garden center is willing, the lawn mower could be serviced now to beat the spring rush.</p>
        <p>The need for a general cleanup comes next. Most perennials are merely stalks now. It is helpful to cut them to the ground, lest they end up as ugly sites come spring.</p>
        <p>Bulbs truly should be in the ground by now. If planting the smaller ones like eranthis and anemone, don't forget to soak them in a bucket of water for at least 12 hours, maybe overnight, before setting them out. This plumps the bulbs, which dry out quickly in storage. These varieties need to be moist inside before planting if they are to be at full glory come spring.</p>
        <p>One remedy for where squirrels have created a big problem digging up bulbs, especially tulips, is to shake red pepper flakes on top of the ground immediately after planting. A heavy layer of leaves also helps as a mulch over the planted area, or you can use a combination of both. If the leaves are thick enough -- several inches -- the squirrels do not seem to be able to scent out the bulbs below.</p>
        <p>The furry rodents also relish crocus bulbs when they are planted in the lawn. To date, no sure remedy seems to thwart squirrels' pursuit of crocuses although many people have had good luck planting the species tommasinianus.</p>
        <p>If squirrels persist in digging up bulbs even after all defensive steps are taken, try daffodils, which can bloom and multiply for several seasons, undisturbed.</p>
        <p>Finally, the tool shed. Metal tools, especially those made of stainless steel, last longer if they are put away clean. That means free of all soil, including whatever has settled on wooden or plastic handles. Blades of pruning shears also need to be wiped free of sap and stored clean. Check to see that the cutting blades are sharp. Digging tools, spades and forks alike, need a cleaning, too. And it doesn't hurt to spray the metal parts with a rust inhibitor.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
