<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hakone, Once Stern, Now Soothes</title>
    <meta content="1HAKONE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="888666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hakone (Japan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wudunn, Sheryl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Hakone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DB1538F933A25752C1A960958260" item-length="2347" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hakone, Once Stern, Now Soothes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL WuDUNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wudunn, Sheryl</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sheryl WuDunn article on hot springs and lakes around Hakone, southwest of Tokyo; hilly, winding pass was once crossing point for feudal lords making pilgrimages to Mount Fuji; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR centuries, Japanese feudal lords struggled across the mountains around Mount Fuji, stopping to rest near the gentle hot springs and glistening lakes around Hakone, about 65 miles southwest of Tokyo.</p>
        <p>The hills in this region once formed the most treacherous stretch along the Tokaido, the famous Eastern Sea Road that crossed Japan. A hilly, winding pass, Hakone was the crossing point for wives and lovers fleeing from the capital of Edo, now Tokyo, and for feudal lords making their pilgrimages to and from the shogun -- and their wives -- in Edo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR centuries, Japanese feudal lords struggled across the mountains around Mount Fuji, stopping to rest near the gentle hot springs and glistening lakes around Hakone, about 65 miles southwest of Tokyo.</p>
        <p>The hills in this region once formed the most treacherous stretch along the Tokaido, the famous Eastern Sea Road that crossed Japan. A hilly, winding pass, Hakone was the crossing point for wives and lovers fleeing from the capital of Edo, now Tokyo, and for feudal lords making their pilgrimages to and from the shogun -- and their wives -- in Edo.</p>
        <p>Japan's shoguns, who ran the country in those days, kept the wives and daughters of their feudal lords in Edo, as hostages to insure the loyalty of the lords. Meanwhile, the lords were sent out to oversee their territories, returning to Edo periodically via the Eastern Sea Road.</p>
        <p>In 1618, the Tokugawa Shogunate set up a barrier station in Hakone to search for escaping women or for murder weapons being carried secretly into Edo. As travelers awaited their inspections, they often slipped away for dips in the enchanting hot springs nearby. Though travelers had been using the hot springs for several centuries, little bathhouses cropped up to cater to the swelling number of bathers.</p>
        <p>From such stern beginnings, Hakone over the centuries has blossomed into the largest hot springs resort area in Japan. Now, it conjures a sense of warmth and pleasure for the Japanese, many of whom dream of acquiring a villa in the hills of Hakone. Most, however, just go for a weekend, as I did with my husband and two young sons in September.</p>
        <p>Now Hakone offers long winding hikes around the hills, hot spring baths, a sky ride that lifts visitors up to the sulfurous, bubbling watering holes, and the Fujiya Hotel, a Japanese hotel in the Victorian style that is a regular respite for Japanese emperors and empresses and visiting foreign royalty.</p>
        <p>The Fujiya was Japan's first Western-style hotel, built 118 years ago by Sennosuke Yamaguchi, who had been sent abroad to learn Western ways. He created the Fujiya out of images from his European travels, seemingly intent on fashioning a different kind of elegance in this resort town. Nestled in a steep hillside, the hotel stands out from a distance, its pagodalike balcony roofs recalling European chinoiserie.</p>
        <p>The Fujiya's historical significance in Japan is still so overwhelming that it charges substantially more for Japanese than for holders of foreign passports. Thus, foreigners pay only $137 for a room on weekdays and $195 on weekends, while Japanese are charged about $217 on weekdays and $271 on weekends.</p>
        <p>Rather than sleeping on futons and walking daintily on straw tatami mats, Fujiya guests stay in expansive rooms, with water pumped from the hot springs on tap in each  bathtub.</p>
        <p>There is also a public hot springs bath in the hotel, though our children turned down the warm stony floors and steamy air of the Fujiya baths for the indoor chlorinated pool. With a bit of chagrin, I noticed a Japanese mother pouring hot spring water over her toddler, who chuckled with delight.</p>
        <p>Some Western travelers might find the Fujiya faded, a bit rundown, especially compared to the glitzy modern hotels of Tokyo. Paint is peeling on the walls in places, carpets in the rooms are somewhat worn, and some rooms have been closed in the older parts of the four-building complex. But the overall effect is still original and seductively charming, heightened by the contrast between this old-fashioned resort and its stony mountainous setting that conjures up ancient rice-scroll landscape paintings.</p>
        <p>The 149-room hotel is built almost entirely of wood, with rooms all over the sprawling complex. Though there are no tennis courts or golf courses, the hotel has both an outdoor and indoor pool and three restaurants.</p>
        <p>The Fujiya Dining Room, which serves French food, is a strikingly elegant space with carved wooden ceilings and walls that almost sparkle in the dimmed lights. Serving main dishes such as ''fried frogs' leg with tartar'' or ''fruits de mer a la bonne femme,'' it is a popular spot where meals cost about $100 a person.</p>
        <p>Below the dining room is a more modest restaurant with bright lights and white tablecloths and tasty food, both Western and Japanese, for about $50 a person.</p>
        <p>UPON entering the hotel, we ascended a green stone staircase guarded by a stone wolf and a gargoyled dragon, then found ourselves in a high-ceilinged, wood-paneled drawing room that ran seamlessly into several other sitting rooms.</p>
        <p>Both staff workers and guests were friendly to my two rambunctious young sons, even as they jumped and rolled around on the wooden floors in the main lounges or raced down the long corridors. All in all, for a hotel with four-star pretensions and five-star prices, the Fujiya is rather relaxed, though never quite casual.</p>
        <p>People come and go, or stop for British tea and cakes or finger sandwiches at the Edwardian-style tearoom that overlooks a Japanese garden. Through the large tearoom windows, one can see several dozen colored koi, or Japanese carp, swimming in the garden pond fed by a waterfall. The orange and black fish approach, mouths gaping, when anyone walks outside; they figure it is their dinner time, and since these pet fish cost $100 apiece in Japan, they should be fed well.</p>
        <p>In the upper garden, we wandered the little paths that wound throughout the nicely landscaped shrubs, grasses and trees. We passed a small pool of water and crossed over to the wooden watermill and a monstrous stone figure, seemingly at prayer. Farther along, we found a road that led to a different Hakone, a rugged one-hour climb through  brush and trees. There was a nice treat midway at a resting spot: a dreamy view of an ever-so-faint Mount Fuji, Japan's highest peak.</p>
        <p>The best way to see Mount Fuji, of course, is from the middle of the sky, or the Ropeway, as the Japanese call the sky gondola that carries one away over the mountains, which is what we set out to do on Saturday afternoon.</p>
        <p>From the Fujiya Hotel, we walked to the Miyanoshita Tozan Tetsudo, a mountain rail station, where we bought a one-way ticket for about $15 to the mountaintop. A crowded two-cabin rail car transported us a few stops to Gora Station; then we changed to the Tozan cable car, actually a tram that took us up part of the mountain. At Sounzan station, we found the Ropeway gondola, a cozy enclosed compartment that seated about 10 people.</p>
        <p>Before us, clear and majestic, was the gleaming pinnacle of Mount Fuji, piercing a ring of clouds. Down below, ribbons of white steam wafted up from the springs. Then the valley suddenly appeared, as though beckoning us to follow thousands of feet down. Some of the hills below looked like blackened volcanic rock; I felt slightly reassured that the last time Mount Fuji erupted was in 1707.</p>
        <p>At the peak, called Owakudani, we took a short stroll to the hot springs, small openings in the mountain filled with steamy bubbly water. In the gentle wind, the spreading smoke from the sulfurous pools engulfed us at times in a pungent steam bath.</p>
        <p>The water is too hot and too far inside the holes to actually reach by hand, and even if you could, there are small barriers warning you not to do so. But we ate eggs boiled in the steamy pools, which blackened the shells and gave the eggs a slight barbecue taste ($4.50 for half a dozen). This seems to be a popular snack -- the kids begged for more -- and masses of black shells were piled on the large picnic tables.</p>
        <p>At the end of the gondola ride was Ashinoko, loosely translated as Lake Ashi, a crater lake formed by volcanic activity 4,000 years ago. When the sky is blue, the lake reflects so clearly that people say you can see images of the mountain peaks in the water from a ship deck.</p>
        <p>THE 30-minute boat ride takes passengers to the Hakone town center and the Hakone Sekisho, the barrier gate set up long ago by the Tokugawa Shogunate to inspect travelers. The quaint town has become so popular that tourists often cause traffic jams.</p>
        <p>We returned by tram and rail car (a bus ride from the Hakone Sekisho takes 30 minutes) to the Fujiya Hotel. Some visitors like to stop along the rail route at the Hakone Open-Air Museum. We made it a separate side trip, for the museum is a Japanese rarity, a vast outdoor expanse of rolling hills and bridges dotted with striking sculpture.</p>
        <p>Just inside the entrance stands Rodin's bronze of Balzac, and there are numerous works by Henry Moore. Of 448 sculptures, all but six are originals. Our sons were enticed by another attraction, a life-size maze -- large, linking diamond shapes through which they crawled with glee, and huge rubber balls and big nets to bounce around on.</p>
        <p>After a picnic lunch in the Michelangelo Garden, a small group of tables clustered near copies of Michelangelo sculptures, we spun tales for the kids about the giant reproductions of his ''Rebellious Slave,'' ''Moses'' and ''Pieta.''</p>
        <p>Actually, it was a little confusing, seeing Italian sculpture in a Japanese museum park, staying in a late 19th-century hotel in the middle of Japan's largest hot springs resort. My kids, though, like the Japanese travelers around us, didn't find it strange at all.</p>
        <p>Where to stay, dine and take a dip</p>
        <p>Getting There</p>
        <p>It is a 45-minute ride on the Shinkansen bullet train from Tokyo Station to Odawara, where you switch to the Hakone Tozan Railway to Miyanoshita. Or from Shinjuku Station, you can take the Odakyu Romance Car (which requires reservations) to Hakone Yumoto and switch to Hakone Tozan to Miyanoshita.</p>
        <p>Places to Stay</p>
        <p>Hotel rates include tax and service.</p>
        <p>Fujiya Hotel, 359 Miyanoshita, Hakone town; (0460) 2-2211, fax (0460) 2-2210. For foreigners, rooms start at $137 a night on weekdays, $195 on weekends, single or double occupancy. (Japanese visitors pay higher rates.)</p>
        <p>Gora-kadan, 1300 Gora, Hakone town; (0460) 2-3331. At this elaborate hotel, traditional Japanese kaiseki cuisine is prepared by top chefs and served in the guest's own room. All rooms have Japanese-style tatami mats, where one sleeps on futons on the floor and can bathe privately in a wooden tub. Suites have an extra room with an open-air bath. The hotel charges $488 to $683 a person, single or double occupancy, including the private dinner and breakfast. (Prices have been calculated at 108.63 yen to the United States dollar.) An unusual windowed corridor, extending from the hotel to Kan'in no Miya restaurant, offers a panoramic view of the mountains.</p>
        <p>Fuyo-tei, 138 Motohakone, Hakone town; (0460) 3-1131, fax (0460) 3-7060. A reasonably priced hotel, with tatami mats and futons, run by a large Japanese chain. A room for two people starts at $331 in the main building and $212 in the annex. In the main building, one can have a Japanese-style dinner and a private bath in one's room. Guests in the annex building use public hot-springs baths and eat in a common dining room. All rooms have views of Lake Ashi, and some offer views of Mount Fuji.</p>
        <p>Dining</p>
        <p>Hatsuhana, 635 Yumoto, Hakone town; (0460) 5-8287. This quaint buckwheat-noodle shop, with low tables and floor cushions, is famous for its Tororo-soba (noodles with grated yams), served cold or hot for about $8. Open 10 A.M. to 7 P.M., closed on Tuesdays. About five minutes' walk from the Hakone Yumoto Station of the Hakone Tozan Railway.</p>
        <p>Sakurai-jaya, 138 Motohakone, Hakone town, (0460) 3-1130. A cozy Japanese restaurant, with tatami mat floors, overlooking Lake Ashi. Though it offers a variety of Japanese foods, like tempura and sashimi, its specialty is tofu. A set lunch menu, which includes a tofu seaweed soup and other traditional dishes, costs about $28. Lunch only. Open 11  A.M. to 2:30 P.M., closed on Tuesdays from January to March. From Miyanoshita you can take the bus for the one-hour trip to Hakone and get off at Fuyo-tei Mae bus stop. About a  five-minute bus ride from Lake Ashi.</p>
        <p>Kan'in no Miya, 1300 Gora, Hakone town; (0460) 2-3333. An elegant traditional Japanese restaurant, where multicourse meals are served on beautiful dishes and arranged with care. Excellent service. Complete dinners start at $41. It is also possible to order Kan'in no Miya Zen, a lunch box-style meal, for about $37. Open 11 A.M. to 3 P.M. and 5 to 9 P.M.; closed Wednesdays. Three minutes' walk from Gora Station.</p>
        <p>The Baths</p>
        <p>Rakuyo Jurin Shizenkan, 100 yards from Fujiya Hotel; (0460) 2-0265. Visitors walk down a valley into this open-air hot springs bath. In addition to an indoor bath, this charming spa has interlinking outdoor wooden baths, built in a slightly terraced fashion. Men and women bathe separately, though families or groups can rent one outdoor bath privately at a cost of $28 for 50 minutes.  General admission is $23 for adults, $14 for children. Open 10 A.M. to 8 P.M. (last entry 7 P.M.), closed Wednesdays.</p>
        <p>Yuzo, 729 Hakone Yumoto, Hakone town; (0460) 5-5791. A more reasonably priced natural hot springs spa, with both indoor and outdoor baths.  The open-air baths offer a view of the mountains. Use of the baths alone costs $12; bath and meal combinations start at $26. Hours for the baths are 10 A.M. to 9 P.M.; lunch,  11:30 A.M. to 2:30 P.M., dinner 4:30  to 7:30 P.M. A three-minute walk from Hakone Yumoto Station on the Hakone Tozan Railway.</p>
        <p>SHERYL WuDUNN is a correspondent in the Tokyo bureau of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">SHERYL WuDUNN is a correspondent in the Tokyo bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
