<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Amahl' Heralds Holidays</title>
    <meta content="MUSIC10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="MUSIC" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="888773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Concerts and Recitals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sherman, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7D71138F933A25752C1A960958260" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Amahl' Heralds Holidays</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sherman, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Sherman previews musical concert scene in Connecticut (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THANKSGIVING is still more than two weeks away, but the first concerts of the Christmas season will be given next weekend. On Friday evening at 8, the Asylum Hill Music Series celebrates its 30th anniversary with a production of Gian Carlo Menotti's opera ''Amahl and the Night Visitors'' at the Congregational Church in Hartford.</p>
        <p>Anna Maria Silvestri, a mezzo soprano, sings the role of the mother, and Ben Fink that of the young boy Amahl in a fully staged production with orchestra and chorus under the direction of Richard Einsel. Tickets will be available at the door, or one can call 860-247-3373 for reservations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THANKSGIVING is still more than two weeks away, but the first concerts of the Christmas season will be given next weekend. On Friday evening at 8, the Asylum Hill Music Series celebrates its 30th anniversary with a production of Gian Carlo Menotti's opera ''Amahl and the Night Visitors'' at the Congregational Church in Hartford.</p>
        <p>Anna Maria Silvestri, a mezzo soprano, sings the role of the mother, and Ben Fink that of the young boy Amahl in a fully staged production with orchestra and chorus under the direction of Richard Einsel. Tickets will be available at the door, or one can call 860-247-3373 for reservations.</p>
        <p>Next Sunday afternoon at 4, Ralph Vaughan Williams' ''Hodie'' opens the Fairfield County Chorale season at the Norwalk Concert Hall, the Christmas Cantata also enlisting the services of the Fairfield County Children's Choir. The occasion also marks the Connecticut premiere of ''Is This Life?'' with Sam Waterston as the narrator and the composer Johannes Somary conducting. ''Is This Life?'' was originally written in 1994 for a Kennedy Center observation of the 250th anniversary of Thomas Jefferson's death; the work uses a text drawn from Jefferson's  correspondence and from some of his favorite authors. The soprano Ellen Zimmer, the tenor John MacMaster and the bass-baritone Gary Aldrich are the other featured soloists; tickets will be available at the door, but reservations through the Chorale office (203-222-8668) save $2 a ticket.</p>
        <p>Today at 4 o'clock the Jitro Children's Choir of the Czech Republic will perform an international program in South Church, New Britain;  Irving Berlin's ''Give Me Your Tired, Your Poor'' is among the program's offerings (860-223-7555).</p>
        <p>At 8 P.M. on Friday the Yale and Princeton Glee Clubs will gather in Battell Chapel at Yale; David Connell and Richard Tang-Yuk, the groups' directors, will conduct, with the Yale Freshman Chorus under Bradley Wells singing as well (203-432-4136).</p>
        <p>Members of the Ahn Trio talk about Beethoven, Mendelssohn and Shostakovich at a 3:15 preconcert event this afternoon at St. Paul's Lutheran Church in Westport, then play a 4 o'clock recital of piano trios by the composers for Friends of Music of Fairfield County (203-938-3767). A solo recital by the pianist Horacio Gutierrez will be presented today at 3:15 in Ives Hall at Western Connecticut State University in Danbury; sonatas by Haydn and Liszt as well as Schumann's Humoreske will be offered for the Danbury Concert Association (203-748-0522).</p>
        <p>Half a dozen faculty artists and the Yale Camarata will be at Sprague Memorial Hall at 8 P.M. on Wednesday to celebrate the 50th birthday of Martin Bresnick, coordinator of the composition department at the School of Music. Among the Bresnick works to be performed at this free concert are the intriguingly titled ''High Art for Piccolo and Toy Piano'' and ''Buckjet Rider and ''BEJUST!'' (203-432-4158).</p>
        <p>The violinist Jennifer Koh, a winner in the 1994 Tchaikovsky International Competition, will perform at the weekend concerts of the Greenwich Symphony at the High School. Bruch's Scottish Fantasy, Ravel's ''Valses Nobles et Sentimentales'' and Prokofiev's Fifth Symphony are on the program, and the 8:30 P.M. Saturday program will be repeated next Sunday afternoon at 4 (203-869-2664).</p>
        <p>In a year of celebrating Johannes Brahms, Chamber Music Plus is exploring some of the controversersies that once swirled around the renowned figure of romantic music. At 8 P.M. on Thursday at the Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford the actors Colin McEnroe and John McDonough portray the composer, his colleagues and critics, while the cello-piano duo of Harry Clark and Sanda Schuldmann provide the music (203-278-7148).</p>
        <p>Brahms' String Sextet is on the program that Musicians from Marlboro are offering at the Stamford Jewish Center on Saturday evening at 8, as is a Haydn string quartet and  Shostakovich's ''Eleven Songs From Jewish Folk Poetry.'' (203-322-7900).</p>
        <p>The Parisii Quartet of Paris is presenting a program at 8 P.M. on Friday at the Jorgensen Auditorium in Storrs; the program's composers are Mozart, Webern and Schubert (860-486-4226).</p>
        <p>It's a triple-header this week for the Armstrong Chamber Concerts, as the violinist Helen Armstrong, the cellist Warren Lash and the pianist Randall Hodgkinson give back-to-back-to-back recitals, on each occasion offering sonatas by Beethoven and Faure as well as the Opus 8 Schumann Trio. Friday's 7 P.M. performance is in a Greenwich home; the first repeat has a 5 o'clock start Saturday afternoon at Southport Congregational Church, and next Sunday afternoon at 3, one can find the threesome at First Congregational Church in Washington. The number to call for directions or reservations is 860-868-0522.</p>
        <p>The pianist Alicia de Larrocha is giving two Connecticut recitals over the next two weeks. At Quick Center, Fairfield University, her 8 P.M Saturday program includes three major works of Bach and shorter pieces by the composers Federico Mompou and Enriques Granados (203-254-4010); on Nov. 19, also at 8, she takes almost the same program to Woolsey Hall, substituting Albeniz for the Granados (203-776-1444).</p>
        <p>At 8 P.M. on Tuesday and Wednesday at the Bushnell, Michael Lankester will conduct the Hartford Symphony in Mozart's Piano Concerto No. 19, with Shizue Sano as guest soloist, and Mahler's Sixth Symphony (860-246-6807).</p>
        <p>On Thursday at 8 in Woolsey Hall at Yale, Michael Palmer directs the New Haven Symphony in an all-Russian evening sparked by Stravinsky's ''Scherzo a la Russe,'' Shostakovich's Fifth Symphony and two Tchaikovsky pieces with the guest cellist Lynn Harrell, ''Pezzo Capriccioso'' and ''Variations on a Rococo Theme'' (203-865-0831).</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
