<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Company History Is No Guide for Investors</title>
    <meta content="10STEL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="INVESTING IT" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="888969"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsche Telekom</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6D8173BF933A25752C1A960958260" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Company History Is No Guide for Investors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>History of Deutsche Telekom, German telephone monopoly, discussed in light of plan to sell shares (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SELDOM has a company gone public with a longer operating history, or a more dominant position in its market, than Deutsche Telekom. Never has such a history been less relevant.</p>
        <p>Deutsche Telekom, heretofore owned by the German Government, is the largest telephone company in Europe, and it has had a monopoly on many services in Germany. But some types of services were opened to competition on Aug. 1, and the rest will open up on Jan. 1, 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SELDOM has a company gone public with a longer operating history, or a more dominant position in its market, than Deutsche Telekom. Never has such a history been less relevant.</p>
        <p>Deutsche Telekom, heretofore owned by the German Government, is the largest telephone company in Europe, and it has had a monopoly on many services in Germany. But some types of services were opened to competition on Aug. 1, and the rest will open up on Jan. 1, 1998.</p>
        <p>One might have expected the company to wait to provide evidence that it can compete. But Deutsche Telekom is deep in debt after spending billions to upgrade telephone service in eastern Germany and needs an infusion of capital. Hence a global offering that could raise $10 billion.</p>
        <p>There are two rationales for investing in Deutsche Telekom. First, it is argued, sotto voce, that this is the issue that the German Government will use to convince cautious German investors that they should get into the stock market. An issue that fails, now or even within a few years, simply will not be allowed. Or so they say.</p>
        <p>(Similar arguments were used when Nippon Telegraph and Telephone went public in Japan in 1987. The shares soon zoomed to a peak of 3.1 million yen, and anyone who bought at the offering price of 1.6 million yen had an opportunity for a quick killing. Alas, those same shares now can be had for 800,000 yen.)</p>
        <p>Second, and more loudly, it is maintained that investors are buying shares in a new, improved Deutsche Telekom, one that is showing it can downsize with the best of them by ousting workers and paring costs.</p>
        <p>To reassure investors, the company has taken the unusual position of announcing planned dividend increases stretching over the next two years. Its intention (there are no guarantees) is to pay a dividend of 0.60 Deutsche marks per share early next year, and then to double that the following year.</p>
        <p>With the shares to be priced a week from today in a range of 25 to 30 marks, or $16 to $20 (bet on the upper end), that promises a dividend of 4 percent on the purchase price within a couple of years. With two-year German Government securities yielding 3.6 percent, that is not a bad yield. Of course, shareholders do not benefit in the long run if a company pays a dividend it cannot afford.</p>
        <p>In its eagerness to make the deal fly with ordinary Germans, the company is offering them deals not available to the rest of us. Individual German investors who get in on the offering will pay half a mark (about 33 cents) a share less than others. And if those retail investors hang on for three years, the German Government will give them one more share for each 10 they own. It appears the deal is more popular with German investors than it is overseas.</p>
        <p>One interesting aspect of the offering is that Deutsche Telekom employees are being offered deeper discounts on shares than are available to the general German public, and are also being offered generous financing plans to buy those shares. So the employees who keep their jobs will have a chance to make a few marks from the savings generated from the cuts in employment.</p>
        <p>Plenty of workers are losing their jobs, which is a selling point of the offering. The company promises to reduce its work force to 170,000 by the end of 2000, from 207,000 last June and 230,000 at the end of 1994. The hope is that savings from those cuts will more than make up for thinner profit margins that will come with competition.</p>
        <p>When the offering was being discussed a few months ago, there was talk of pricing the shares so low that they would clearly be a bargain. That did not happen. So while there is likely to be an initial pop in the stock price, real money will be made only if the company's operating plan works out.</p>
        <p>In Europe, it is not uncommon for shares to begin trading in what is called a gray market, before the official offering. These shares are trading for 34 marks, an indication that the offering will be a success, at least initially. After that? It depends on how well the company manages to change its ways.</p>
        <p>INVESTING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
