<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Restaurants</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="471688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANT REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ELDORADO PETIT (NYC RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, BRYAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDE173FF935A3575AC0A967958260" item-length="1071" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Restaurants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bryan Miller</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MILLER, BRYAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Eldorado Petit opened on West 55th Street in Manhattan last year, it promised to introduce the distinctive and little-known seafood-based cuisine of Catalonia. It certainly had an impressive family lineage: Eldorado Petit in Barcelona, one of the city's most distinguished restaurants, and its namesake in nearby San Feliu de Guixols, are run by the second and third generations of the Cruanyas family.</p>
        <p>Looking to the 1992 Olympics in Barcelona and the hoopla over the anniversary of Columbus's epochal first voyage, the Cruanyas family decided the time was ripe to expand its empire to the New World. My early visits to the restaurant found the setting to be smashing; the undistinguished Continental fare, though, generated little excitement. Eldorado Petit seemed to be taking the condescending and potentially disastrous attitude that ethnic food must be tempered for American tastes.  Then two months ago, just as I was about to give up on the place, things turned around dramatically, and for the better. The highly capable chef, Antonio Buendia, formerly of the now-defunct Internacionale, steered the menu back to undiluted Catalan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Eldorado Petit opened on West 55th Street in Manhattan last year, it promised to introduce the distinctive and little-known seafood-based cuisine of Catalonia. It certainly had an impressive family lineage: Eldorado Petit in Barcelona, one of the city's most distinguished restaurants, and its namesake in nearby San Feliu de Guixols, are run by the second and third generations of the Cruanyas family.</p>
        <p>Looking to the 1992 Olympics in Barcelona and the hoopla over the anniversary of Columbus's epochal first voyage, the Cruanyas family decided the time was ripe to expand its empire to the New World. My early visits to the restaurant found the setting to be smashing; the undistinguished Continental fare, though, generated little excitement. Eldorado Petit seemed to be taking the condescending and potentially disastrous attitude that ethnic food must be tempered for American tastes.  Then two months ago, just as I was about to give up on the place, things turned around dramatically, and for the better. The highly capable chef, Antonio Buendia, formerly of the now-defunct Internacionale, steered the menu back to undiluted Catalan.</p>
        <p>Verisimilitude notwithstanding, Eldorado Petit is one of the most visually striking restaurants in town. I like to stop for a glass of wine at the angular little bar with its comfortable wicker stools before moving into one of the two main dining rooms. Glazed terra-cotta walls, alabaster funnel-shaped ceiling lights, and slide projections of various shellfish on the walls make for a hauntingly elegant setting.</p>
        <p>A good way to start a meal is with a sampling of tapas. The shrimp sauteed in garlic and a touch of hot peppers are succulent and mildly hot. Also recommended are the grilled baby squid, the extraordinarily light deep-fried balls of codfish, and the grilled whole shrimp seasoned with rosemary. Tripe, a Spanish specialty, is fresh and tender, but nearly lost in a pond of tomato sauce seasoned with chorizo, prosciutto and peppers.</p>
        <p>From the main menu, we sampled sweet peppers stuffed with a well-seasoned combination of prawns and scallops in an Americano sauce made with lobster shells, and brandada, which generally refers to a shredded puree of salt cod with various combinations of garlic, potatoes and milk. The brandada here is exceptionally creamy, explosive with garlic flavor, and served over a layer of spinach, raisins and pine nuts. The flavors are complementary, although being a non-Spaniard I could do without the thick ring of olive oil around the dish. One preparation that I flipped over on my early visits is called arrosejat de fideus, or angel hair pasta that is sauteed in olive oil and garlic until slightly crisp, then seasoned with a strong fish stock and aioli, the garlic mayonnaise. It still excels.</p>
        <p>Waiters here know the food well and are patient about describing the difference between a sofregit sauce and a picada. And the pace of the room is easygoing but not slow. The predominantly Spanish and French wine list matches the food well, and prices are moderate.</p>
        <p>The menu tilts toward seafood, and much of it is prepared with Catalan elan. A classic Catalan dish is mar i muntanya (surf and barnyard, one might say). Chicken is sauteed slowly in sofregit sauce (olive oil, garlic, tomatoes, onions, rosemary). A lobster, which is cooked separately, is added along with picada, which is a condiment of roasted almonds, garlic, parsley, fried bread and bittersweet chocolate. The multi-hued flavors punctuated with a dry kick of chocolate are sensational.  Two simpler but pleasing preparations are salmon served over thin sauteed potatoes, onions and sweet peppers, and braised monkfish in a tomato concassee with rosemary.</p>
        <p>Grilled swordfish had to be returned for further cooking, and the cynosure of the seafood menu, whole red snapper for two baked in a coating of sea salt, was more theatrics than taste. The snapper was slightly undercooked and had no distinctive seasonings.</p>
        <p>The best non-seafood dish is incredibly tender duck legs -- they are braised then roasted -- served in a pear sauce with poached pears on the side. Also good is the grilled sirloin steak basted with mustard and rosemary.</p>
        <p>When I lived in Spain a decade ago, dessert often meant dunking ribbons of deep-fried dough into hot chocolate, usually after Olympian quantities of red wine. This sweet combination is still popular, but so are a Spanish version of creme brulee (too gelatinous), chocolate mousse (rich and intense) and apple tart (soggy crust). The two best desserts are puff pastry filled with spaghetti squash and rolled in sugar and pine nuts, and poached pears with a red wine sorbet.</p>
        <p>Like Columbus on his first voyage, Eldorado Petit was propelled more by bravado than useful facts at the outset. Columbus eventually hit pay dirt. Eldorado Petit is closing in under full sail.  Eldorado Petit **</p>
        <p>47 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 586-3434.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: Striking contemporary design and moderate noise level.</p>
        <p>Service: Well informed and competent.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: Shrimp sauteed in garlic and hot peppers, deep-fried balls of codfish, grilled shrimp with rosemary, sweet peppers stuffed with prawns and scallops, brandada (puree of cod), arrosejat de fideus (angel hair pasta sauteed in olive oil and garlic), mar i muntanya (chicken and lobster), salmon with sauteed potatoes, braised monkfish in tomato concassee, duck legs with pear sauce, poached pears with red-wine sorbet.</p>
        <p>Wine: Predominantly Spanish and French selection well matched to the food.</p>
        <p>Price range: Lunch: appetizers $4 to $12; main courses $18 to $27.50; dinner: appetizers $4 to $12; main courses, $17 to $25.</p>
        <p>Credit cards: American Express, Mastercard and Visa.</p>
        <p>Hours: Lunch: noon to 3 P.M. Monday to Friday; dinner: 5:30 to 11 P.M. Monday to Saturday.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Requested.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility: Everything on ground level. What the stars mean: (None) Poor to Satisfactory * Good ** Very Good *** Excellent **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambiance and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>The Times Restaurant Line offers capsule reviews by cuisine, price and location (in New York City and suburbs), published in the last 18 months. Touch-line telephones only: 1-900-988-0101 (75 cents a minute).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
