<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Companies See Law School Ruling as a Way to Help Keep the Diversity Pipeline Open</title>
    <meta content="Y24BUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/24/national/24BUSI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1499416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THE SUPREME COURT: IMPACT ON BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Graduate Schools and Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Michigan</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, Sandra Day (Assoc Justice)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graduate Schools and Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Michigan</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7DD123BF937A15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Companies See Law School Ruling as a Way to Help Keep the Diversity Pipeline Open</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Companies See Court Ruling as Support for Diversity</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE and JONATHAN D. GLATER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Corporate executives and employment law experts say Supreme Court's rulings about diversity in higher education sends strong signal that employers can continue to use race as factor in hiring; note Justice Sandra Day O'Connor's majority opinion upholding University of Michigan Law School's admission policies cited views of General Motors and other companies about importance of workplace diversity (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court's rulings yesterday about diversity in higher education sent a strong signal to the nation's employers that they can continue to use race as a factor in hiring, corporate executives and employment law experts said.</p>
        <p>In ruling on the admissions policies of the University of Michigan Law School, the court's majority opinion, written by Justice Sandra Day O'Connor, cited the views put forward by General Motors and other companies in friend-of-the-court briefs that said achieving diversity was essential at universities and in workplaces to compete in an increasingly global marketplace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The affirmative action rulings sent a strong signal to employers that they may continue to use race as a factor in hiring, experts said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court's rulings yesterday about diversity in higher education sent a strong signal to the nation's employers that they can continue to use race as a factor in hiring, corporate executives and employment law experts said.</p>
        <p>In ruling on the admissions policies of the University of Michigan Law School, the court's majority opinion, written by Justice Sandra Day O'Connor, cited the views put forward by General Motors and other companies in friend-of-the-court briefs that said achieving diversity was essential at universities and in workplaces to compete in an increasingly global marketplace.</p>
        <p>''The particular rationale she argued for was the needs of the globalization of business,'' said Bill Lann Lee, former director of the Justice Department's civil rights division. ''She wrote about the practical benefits of diversity. She wrote that there is a business justification for diversity.''</p>
        <p>Businesses seeking to achieve diversity can breathe a sigh of relief, said Lawrence Z. Lorber, a former Labor Department official and a lawyer with the Washington office of Proskauer Rose. In upholding the law school plan, Mr. Lorber said, ''they effectively upheld employers' affirmative action plans.''</p>
        <p>James P. Hackett, chief executive officer of Steelcase, an office furniture company that helped spearhead a series of friend-of-the-court briefs signed by 65 corporations backing the university position, said the ruling would further a trend already taking place in corporate America.</p>
        <p>''This was less about affirmative action or quotas than about the university leadership having the ability to ensure diversity,'' Mr. Hackett said. ''For me that's the strong connection to business. It's something that business has been highly committed to for at least the last decade and has made tremendous strides in improving. The belief in diversity is not something that is argued anymore in business. It's a factor of being in business.''</p>
        <p>The court's decision reduced any uncertainty about what steps companies could take in hiring more women and minority employees, several legal experts said.</p>
        <p>The Microsoft Corporation was one of the companies that signed a brief supporting the use of race in admissions. It recruits at historically black colleges, finances scholarships for minority students and has donated about $15 million in cash and software to the Thurgood Marshall Scholarship Fund, said Claudette Whiting, the company's senior diversity director.</p>
        <p>The court's decision ''really is a reinforcement of the many initiatives that companies like Microsoft and others have,'' Ms. Whiting said. ''We are working diligently on the pipeline.''</p>
        <p>General Motors, an outspoken corporate supporter of the university's case, applauded the court's ruling.</p>
        <p>''General Motors' position has consistently been that diversity of background, thought and experience is essential to the education process,'' said Rod Gillum, G.M.'s vice president for corporate responsibility and diversity. ''Efforts by universities to create a diverse student body from which corporations can recruit should be supported. Although we have not yet had an opportunity to digest the court's opinions, it appears that the Supreme Court has accepted that this goal can be pursued under the Constitution.''</p>
        <p>Like many companies, officials at G.M. said they sometimes took race into account in hiring; for instance, to give the company better insights when designing cars for the Asian, the Hispanic or the African-American markets.</p>
        <p>Maria Blanco, national senior counsel of the Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund, said yesterday's ruling upholding the law school's admissions policy ''says in effect that employers can give a plus to race, as long as it's not a quota. It can be justified for diversity reasons and not just for remedying past discrimination.''</p>
        <p>And there was widespread agreement among employment experts that the separate ruling involving undergraduate admissions at the university was a warning to employers against using quotas to achieve diversity. In that 6-to-3 ruling, the court stated that the university gave too much weight to race, giving minority applicants 20 points on a scale of 150 points and thereby going far to ensure their admission.</p>
        <p>The majority in the law school ruling distinguished the facts in that case from the undergraduate case by noting that in the admissions process the law school considered race as one factor among many and did not give overriding importance to it.</p>
        <p>''Employers need to be careful in this area,'' said Samuel Estreicher, director of the Center for Labor and Employment Law at New York University. ''They don't want to override seniority systems. They don't want to use quotas. They don't want to be heavy-handed. If employers are careful and their diversity goals are related to what their available work force is, I don't think there are many legal issues for the employer.''</p>
        <p>THE SUPREME COURT: IMPACT ON BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
