<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sunday Dinner; Spots Where the Wine List Is a Good Match for the Food</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Life Style Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="484480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANT REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHIN CHIN (NYC RESTAURANT)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LES HALLES (NYC RESTAURANT)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SARABETH'S KITCHEN (NYC RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, BRYAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDD123CF930A35752C1A967958260" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sunday Dinner; Spots Where the Wine List Is a Good Match for the Food</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In today's economy it is difficult for restaurants to stock large inventories of wine. This may not be a bad turn of events, because it has forced many restaurants to rethink wine in relation to food. The result has been smaller but more thoughtful lists. Here are three restaurants in Manhattan where both the food and the wine lists are good.  Chin Chin</p>
        <p>216 East 49th Street, (212) 888-4555 -- This may be the best-looking Chinese restaurant in town. It is near the summit when it comes to food, too. The cooking cuts across various ethnic borders, and while most dishes are full-flavored, few are seriously spicy. If you like wine with Chinese food, the selection here is impressive and exceptionally well chosen. Prices are more than fair, starting at $14.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In today's economy it is difficult for restaurants to stock large inventories of wine. This may not be a bad turn of events, because it has forced many restaurants to rethink wine in relation to food. The result has been smaller but more thoughtful lists. Here are three restaurants in Manhattan where both the food and the wine lists are good.  Chin Chin</p>
        <p>216 East 49th Street, (212) 888-4555 -- This may be the best-looking Chinese restaurant in town. It is near the summit when it comes to food, too. The cooking cuts across various ethnic borders, and while most dishes are full-flavored, few are seriously spicy. If you like wine with Chinese food, the selection here is impressive and exceptionally well chosen. Prices are more than fair, starting at $14.</p>
        <p>Among appetizers on the current menu are crispy fried squid, vegetable duck pie with crepes, chicken soong in lettuce pocket and cold noodles tossed in a hot sesame sauce. Main courses include Peking duck, shredded chicken with garlic sauce, crispy sea bass and crispy orange beef.</p>
        <p>Appetizers are $4 to $12, entrees, $13.50 to $19.50. Sunday dinner is served from 5 to 11 P.M. (Review, May 3, 1991.) Les Halles</p>
        <p>411 Park Avenue South, between 28th and 29th Streets, (212) 679-4111 -- It is not easy to absorb all the interior details at Les Halles. A little tiled butcher shop is up front, and just behind is the bar. The lofty space here has a Parisian feel with elaborate wood molding, off-white walls, tulip sconces that cast soft light and tables draped in butcher paper. Charcuterie posters and black and white photos adorn the walls.</p>
        <p>Patrons come here for the gutsy French cooking. As for the wine list, it is a delight, not only for its sensible prices but also for delectable little-known country wines like Bourgueil ($16), Chateau Aiguilloux from Cahors ($15) and Vidal-Fleury from Vacqueyras ($21).</p>
        <p>For appetizers, you might start with the frisee aux lardons (chicory salad with bacon and Roquefort croutons), onion soup or warm sausage served with lentils. For entrees there are grilled flank steak with a shallot sauce, lamb shank with couscous, pigs' feet and moules mariniere (steamed mussels with white wine).</p>
        <p>Appetizers are $5 to $7.50; entrees, $12.50 to $22. Sunday hours are noon to midnight. (Review, Feb. 15, 1991.) Sarabeth's</p>
        <p>1295 Madison Avenue, near 92d Street, (212) 410-7335 -- This cheerful spot is almost too cute to be taken seriously as a restaurant, with its country cupboard at the entrance, cream-toned wallpaper, pastoral American paintings on the walls and capacious baskets of dried flowers. Yet there is nothing juvenile about the food.</p>
        <p>The American menu is sophisticated and well focused. Sarabeth's also offers a limited but quality American wine selection that is well matched to the food and reasonably priced.</p>
        <p>Starters on the current menu include cream of tomato soup; marinated goat cheese with roasted sweet peppers, black olives and toasted nut-raisin bread; Caesar salad and rigatoni with grilled tomatoes, chicken sausage, zucchini and arugula.</p>
        <p>Among main courses are grilled salmon with lentils, caramelized endive and a warm ginger vinaigrette; grilled tuna caponata with roasted potatoes; herbed linguine topped with a stew of squash, tomato, ginger and fried ricotta cheese; chicken potpie and seared duck breast served with duck tortillas, green rice and avocado.</p>
        <p>Appetizers are $4 to $6.75; entrees, $14.75 to $20. Sunday dinner is from 6 to 10 P.M. (Review, Aug. 24, 1990.)</p>
        <p>This listing is compiled by Bryan Miller from his restaurant visits, his reviews and articles in The Times, and entries in his Diner's Journal column. Review and article dates are in parentheses. Prices are current.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
