<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At New CBS, Early Signs of the Midas Touch</title>
    <meta content="25les" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/25/business/media/25les.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1734608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Warner Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Upn (Television Network)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wb Television Network</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cw (TV Network)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moonves, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ostroff, Dawn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Manly, Lorne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Viacom Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Moonves, Leslie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EEDD103FF936A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At New CBS, Early Signs of the Midas Touch</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At New CBS, Early Signs of the Midas Touch</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LORNE MANLY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Manly, Lorne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Surprise announcement that CBS and Time Warner will combine UPN and WB networks into joint venture called CW buoys CBS's stock and is getting career of chief executive Leslie Moonves off to descent start; Moonves says he will still play large role in choosing programs; ad executives credit Moonves and UPN chief Dawn Ostroff for UPN's more cohesive identity and for achieving urban and ethnic cast; Ostroff will be president of entertainment at combined network; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Viacom announced last year that it was splitting itself in two, analysts saddled the half granted to Leslie Moonves with the most invidious of labels. They deemed Mr. Moonves's publicly traded turf, the CBS Corporation -- now home to broadcast television networks and a Howard Stern-less radio division, but not the highflying cable networks of MTV -- a slow-growth company.</p>
        <p>It has not taken long for Mr. Moonves, 56, to prove that conventional wisdom wrong, at least for the present.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Analysts labeled the CBS Corporation a slow-growth company, but Leslie Moonves is proving the conventional wisdom wrong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Viacom announced last year that it was splitting itself in two, analysts saddled the half granted to Leslie Moonves with the most invidious of labels. They deemed Mr. Moonves's publicly traded turf, the CBS Corporation -- now home to broadcast television networks and a Howard Stern-less radio division, but not the highflying cable networks of MTV -- a slow-growth company.</p>
        <p>It has not taken long for Mr. Moonves, 56, to prove that conventional wisdom wrong, at least for the present.</p>
        <p>The surprise announcement yesterday that CBS and Time Warner would combine their struggling UPN and WB networks into a joint venture called the CW buoyed CBS's stock, sending it up $1.08, or more than 4 percent, to $26.90. Since CBS started trading on Jan. 3, the stock has risen 5.5 percent, according to company figures. While such gains could be short-lived, they do get Mr. Moonves's career as a chief executive of a publicly traded company, and his quest to be known as more than a master television programmer, off to a decent start.</p>
        <p>UPN, despite ratings and revenue increases since Mr. Moonves gained oversight of the channel in 2002, is still spending a lot of money. Michael A. Kupinski, an analyst with A. G. Edwards &amp; Sons, estimated that last year, UPN had negative operating cash flow of $80 million.</p>
        <p>CBS executives said that figure overstated the matter by a factor of about four.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Moonves said CW would be profitable in its first year.</p>
        <p>And despite his growing domain, Mr. Moonves said he would still play a large role in choosing programs. ''You know you can't keep me out of that room,'' he said.</p>
        <p>More than similarly placed executives at other media giants, Mr. Moonves, a former actor, keeps his hands on the material that helped him rise in corporate hierarchies at Lorimar Television, Warner Brothers Television and CBS. Last weekend, he read through eight scripts of possible pilot programs, and liked half of them.</p>
        <p>While taking pains to praise his network executives, Mr. Moonves reserves the right to sign off on major programming and casting decisions. Just a few weeks before production began on ''Everybody Hates Chris,'' UPN's critically acclaimed show, Mr. Moonves vetoed the child actor chosen for the title character.</p>
        <p>''The kid needed to be lovable,'' he said. ''I didn't think he was huggable like this kid is,'' referring to the new Chris, played by Tyler James Williams.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moonves's programming instincts, for the most part, have paid off. Despite some clunkers like ''Bette'' and ''Threshold,'' CBS is the most-watched network in the country, and after years of lagging in reaching the 18-to-49-year-old group that is most sought by advertisers, his network is just a fraction of a percentage point from catching the leader in that category, ABC.</p>
        <p>UPN, which for years trailed the WB for fifth place among the six broadcast networks, has now passed it. Advertising executives credit Mr. Moonves and UPN's chief, Dawn Ostroff, for UPN's more cohesive identity, one that went beyond just reaching the young, and achieving an urban and ethnic cast. (Ms. Ostroff will be the president of entertainment at the combined network.)</p>
        <p>''He really has had the Midas touch,'' Brad Adgate, senior vice president and research director at Horizon Media, said of Mr. Moonves.</p>
        <p>The CBS executive still faces a difficult road in transforming what are considered mature businesses into exciting and growing ones. The overall audience of broadcast television, for example, has diminished, as cable networks and other entertainment choices proliferated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moonves has made some bold moves as he tries to prove that the split-off company can be more nimble in attacking new opportunities than Viacom was. CBS recently acquired CSTV, a college sports cable channel and collection of online properties, for $325 million.</p>
        <p>Yet the stock market can be a harsh judge. CBS shares may be vibrant right now, but the stock price of the new Viacom, the half being run by Tom Freston, has increased more than 8.5 percent since it sprang free of its CBS counterpart on Jan. 3.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
