<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albany Leaning Toward Mayor on Schools</title>
    <meta content="21BOAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/21/education/21BOAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1369540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Board of Education (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanders, Steven (Assemblyman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Board of Education</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sanders, Steven</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DC153EF932A15751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albany Leaning Toward Mayor on Schools</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Albany Leaning Toward Mayor on Schools</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Steven Sanders, Democratic chairman of Assembly Education Committee, says that mayoral control of New York City school system, probably through reinvented Board of Education, is inevitable and will be in effect by school year beginning in September; says that Democratic lawmakers are seeking to tie mayoral control to strengthened formula for state fiscal oversight of city schools; it would ensure that city will not reduce its financial contribution to schools, even if state aid goes up (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A pivotal Assembly Democrat said yesterday that mayoral control of the New York City school system, probably through a reinvented board of education, was inevitable and would be in effect by the school year beginning in September.</p>
        <p>The legislator, Steven Sanders, chairman of the Assembly Education Committee, said that Democratic lawmakers were seeking to tie mayoral control to a strengthened formula for state fiscal oversight of city schools. It would ensure that the city will not reduce its financial contribution to the schools, even if state aid goes up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A pivotal Assembly Democrat said that mayoral control of the New York City school system was inevitable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A pivotal Assembly Democrat said yesterday that mayoral control of the New York City school system, probably through a reinvented board of education, was inevitable and would be in effect by the school year beginning in September.</p>
        <p>The legislator, Steven Sanders, chairman of the Assembly Education Committee, said that Democratic lawmakers were seeking to tie mayoral control to a strengthened formula for state fiscal oversight of city schools. It would ensure that the city will not reduce its financial contribution to the schools, even if state aid goes up.</p>
        <p>In his strongest endorsement of mayoral control yet, Mr. Sanders, a close ally of the Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver, said ''the pendulum is swinging'' in favor of giving the mayor more responsibility and accountability for the schools. He said the  details would be worked out within weeks. ''I think there is almost an irresistible momentum -- inexorable perhaps -- that is building that will give the mayor enhanced decision-making powers,'' Mr. Sanders said.</p>
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg has made mayoral control of city schools a central part of his agenda, mentioning it prominently in his State of the City address last month. Mr. Bloomberg's spokesman, Ed Skyler, said yesterday that the mayor still preferred direct control of the school system; he has opposed a plan for an expanded board of education with the majority of the members appointed by the mayor. The mayor now appoints two of the seven members, with the five borough presidents appointing a single member each.</p>
        <p>''The mayor wants to be accountable for the school system, no strings attached,'' Mr. Skyler said.</p>
        <p>But one alternative model would have the mayor appointing the chancellor, with the advice and consent of a board. At present the board appoints the chancellor without oversight by the mayor except as exercised through his two appointees and political influence.</p>
        <p>John McArdle, a spokesman for  Joseph Bruno, the Senate majority leader, said yesterday that the Senate was eager to conclude a deal and was ''in favor of giving the mayor greater control, not less.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sanders's prediction, so soon after Mr. Bloomberg took office, represents a major shift among Assembly Democrats. Mr. Bloomberg's predecessor, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, also crusaded for mayoral control, but was unable to reach his goal  because of opposition from the United Federation of Teachers and his antagonistic relationship with many Albany Democrats.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Giuliani's assertion that the Board of Education was dysfunctional and should be ''blown up'' did pave the way, rhetorically and in the popular psyche, for the change, making it possible for the Legislature now to act almost overnight, as if it had been just waiting to seize the opportunity.</p>
        <p>''You know the old proverb, 'Be careful what you wish for because you may get it,' '' Mr. Sanders said.  ''Mayor Bloomberg may get a lot of what he wishes for, though he may decide later that it is regrettable from his political point of view.''</p>
        <p>Randi Weingarten, president of the United Federation of Teachers, called the shift in the Assembly ''a seismic moment.'' Mayor John V. Lindsay, who served from 1966 to 1973, was the last mayor to control the Board of Education: he appointed all the members after they had been screened by a panel of civic and educational leaders.</p>
        <p>''The fact that the Assembly is talking about a form of mayoral control and is talking about it for this mayor is a huge breakthrough that no other mayor since Mayor Lindsay had,'' Ms. Weingarten said.</p>
        <p>She said that maintaining some form of a board was a guarantee of a buffer between parents, taxpayers and the politics of City Hall. ''I don't know of a city that doesn't have a board,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The proposal for stronger fiscal oversight has helped win over black and Hispanic legislators, by reassuring them that the mayor will not be able to force cuts on the schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sanders said the goal of legislative fiscal oversight was to avoid budget cuts like those made during the last year of the Giuliani administration, and now in the budget proposed by Mr. Bloomberg.</p>
        <p>The state increased aid to New York City public schools by more than $150 million last year, but the city made $400 million in cuts to education, well exceeding the state's increase. Chancellor Harold O. Levy said he was compelled to order cuts in services, including after-school reading classes, weekend math classes, art and sports.</p>
        <p>''There is a very strong feeling shared by myself, the speaker and a lot of Democratic caucus members that resources for the school system is an important part of the overall governance mix,'' Mr. Sanders said.</p>
        <p>The Board of Education budget is supposed to be protected from cuts by the Stavisky-Goodman Law, adopted in 1976, during the city's fiscal crisis. It requires the city to maintain the same proportion of its budget on education as it had, on average, for the preceding three years. But Mr. Sanders said Stavisky-Goodman had been inadequate in protecting the board from substantial year-to-year cuts, and had to be shored up by legislation.</p>
        <p>''It is sort of a safety net,'' he said. ''It provides you can't go into freefall. But it is possible that arithmetically you can reduce education spending within a given year by hundreds of millions of dollars.''</p>
        <p>The central board has come under attack for inefficiency, allegiances to local politicians and lack of direct accountability to the public. But the five borough presidents -- whose own powers have been sharply reduced in other areas -- are unlikely to surrender their power to appoint board members without a fight. One possibility may be to give the borough presidents authority to choose the sites of schools, an adviser to Democratic elected officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg also wants to abolish the 32 local school boards. The Assembly has signalled that it will also restructure the local boards, by postponing school-board elections for a year. But Mr. Sanders said a decision on the local boards would probably be deferred until a second round of legislation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
