<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>30-Day Notice for a Mass Eviction</title>
    <meta content="Y21EVIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/21/national/21EVIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1369510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Citrus Heights (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Santa Rosa (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sterngold, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kawamoto, Genshiro</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Sacramento</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Sacramento (Calif)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Social Security</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lockyer, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE3DE153EF932A15751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>30-Day Notice for a Mass Eviction</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">30-Day Notice for a Mass Eviction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES STERNGOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sterngold, James</byline>
      <dateline>CITRUS HEIGHTS, Calif., Feb. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mass eviction of 420 renters in Citrus Heights and Santa Rosa, Calif, raises questions about strategy of one of largest property owners in region, reclusive Japanese investor Genshiro Kawamoto; nearly all tenants paid bargain-basement rents, and most had month-to-month leases that permit such notices; still, news has been bombshell that threatens to disrupt families, schools and whole cities; Kawamoto's lawyer says he is selling all his houses to raise money for other investments; photo(M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jim and Judy Jacques concede that life in this middle-class suburb of Sacramento has been good, maybe too good.</p>
        <p>They live in a well-kept four-bedroom house on an attractive cul-de-sac. Even better, they pay a bargain-basement rent of $1,100 a month, perhaps $500 below market in a booming area with virtually no vacancies. An additional 419 renters in the area have enjoyed similar rents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A mass eviction has shaken Sacramento communities and raised questions about month-to-month leases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jim and Judy Jacques concede that life in this middle-class suburb of Sacramento has been good, maybe too good.</p>
        <p>They live in a well-kept four-bedroom house on an attractive cul-de-sac. Even better, they pay a bargain-basement rent of $1,100 a month, perhaps $500 below market in a booming area with virtually no vacancies. An additional 419 renters in the area have enjoyed similar rents.</p>
        <p>But their good fortune may be about to end in a mass eviction that has shaken a number of communities and raised questions about the strategy of one of the largest, if not strangest, property owners in the region, a reclusive Japanese investor, Genshiro Kawamoto.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, 420 renters received notices, some reportedly handed to children or hung from doorknobs, ordering them out of their houses in 30 days. Mr. Kawamoto's lawyer, Carol Asai-Sato of Honolulu, said he was forcing out the tenants so he could sell all the houses to raise money for other investments. An additional 150 or so tenants in Santa Rosa, 110 miles west, have received similar notices.</p>
        <p>Although nearly all the tenants have month-to-month leases that permit such notices, the news was a bombshell that threatened to disrupt families, schools and whole cities.</p>
        <p>Some renters live on fixed incomes and say there is no way that they can find similar housing in the region. They say that moving farther from Sacramento would be a burden.</p>
        <p>Even families like the Jacqueses, who say they could possibly afford the $225,000 or so that it might cost to buy their house, say the compressed time frame makes that ludicrous.</p>
        <p>''These are wonderful houses for a family,'' said Mrs. Jacques, whose husband remodels houses for a living. ''You can live great and afford it. We don't have that big a problem with the money, but in 30 days? Come on. How do you do this in 30 days?''</p>
        <p>Carol Tweet, a disabled social worker, lives around the corner with her 17-year-old daughter. Ms. Tweet said that on her fixed income, consisting largely of Social Security payments, she would have to move many miles from Sacramento, requiring her daughter to change high schools months before graduation.</p>
        <p>Edwin C. Gipson, a former state worker, said that after he had heard shuffling near his door, he opened it to find his notice stuck to the knob.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to fall back on our kids,'' Mr. Gipson said, ''but I'm not sure what else we can do. We're probably no better off or worse off than anyone else. We have no big savings to buy with.''</p>
        <p>This story is ending as strangely as it began. A little more than 10 years ago, Mr. Kawamoto swept into the region and snapped up hundreds of houses in Citrus Heights and three nearby areas, Antelope, Orangevale and Rocklin, as well as the more distant Santa Rosa. He is generally believed to have paid a total of $60 million and hired a succession of real estate companies to manage the properties. Although many Japanese companies bought large trophy properties in the United States like Rockefeller Center around that time, Mr. Kawamoto went after properties that were, relatively, out of the way and far more difficult to manage.</p>
        <p>Through Ms. Asai-Sato, a lawyer with Alston Hunt Floyd &amp; Ing in Hawaii, Mr. Kawamoto said he needed the money urgently for ''tremendous investment opportunities both in the United States and Japan which are opportunities which present themselves only once every 20 to 30 years.''</p>
        <p>Local real estate brokers said that if Mr. Kawamoto unloaded the houses en masse, he could receive $70 million for them, perhaps $15 million less than if he put them on the market a few at a time.</p>
        <p>Ten years ago, Sacramento was a relatively sleepy city far from the boom of Silicon Valley, to the west. But the hot real estate market has caught up with the region. The vacancy rate in Citrus Heights, a recently incorporated city of 88,000 people, is 4.2 percent.</p>
        <p>The eviction notices have created an unusual situation, with ad hoc groups' mobilizing the mostly middle-class tenants and seeking help from agencies that usually help the poor. The Sacramento chapter of the Association of Community Organizations for Reform Now, or Acorn, an advocacy group for poor families, has organized the tenants and approached the City Council, the state attorney general and even the Japanese Embassy in Washington.</p>
        <p>The principal legal strategy is to buy time, perhaps 60 to 90 days, and to provide government aid to help the families who can buy their houses.</p>
        <p>''We just want to give them some incentive to talk to us,'' said Brian Kettenring, an Acorn organizer.</p>
        <p>This week, the head of a tenants' group, Eric Goesch, met a Japanese Embassy official. Mr. Goesch said that the official said he had never heard of Mr. Kawamoto, questioned whether he was Japanese and said the questions would be sent to Tokyo.</p>
        <p>Attorney General Bill Lockyer said that realistically the tenants and officials could offer little more than moral suasion and delaying tactics.</p>
        <p>The Citrus Heights city attorney, Ruthann Ziegler, said the City Council was considering an emergency ordinance that would require longer notice, but added that she was not certain that would be legal.</p>
        <p>''When you have something like this happen in the hundreds, and so quickly,'' Ms. Ziegler asked, ''what do you do?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
