<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Planetarium Plan Worries a Block</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="864653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER WEST SIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALLON, JANET</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3D91E39F937A25754C0A960958260" item-length="408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Planetarium Plan Worries a Block</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET ALLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ALLON, JANET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The blocks surrounding the American Museum of Natural History are among the most desirable on the Upper West Side. But some of the residents of West 81st Street between Central Park West and Columbus Avenue fear they will have to bear the brunt of the museum's ambitious plan to build a new planetarium, outdoor restaurant and underground parking garage to accommodate more visitors. About 40 residents of the block attended a meeting on July 2 at which Community Board 7 approved the museum's preliminary environmental-impact statement with a few recommendations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The blocks surrounding the American Museum of Natural History are among the most desirable on the Upper West Side. But some of the residents of West 81st Street between Central Park West and Columbus Avenue fear they will have to bear the brunt of the museum's ambitious plan to build a new planetarium, outdoor restaurant and underground parking garage to accommodate more visitors. About 40 residents of the block attended a meeting on July 2 at which Community Board 7 approved the museum's preliminary environmental-impact statement with a few recommendations.</p>
        <p>Although many neighbors support the museum's $125 million project overall, some  are particularly concerned about increased traffic and noise. Among those who came to voice their complaints was the actor William Baldwin, who recounted how he had to install special windows in his apartment to screen out the noise from traffic and barking dogs at the museum's dog run. Another resident of the block, Steve Strauss, said an expanded garage would encourage people to drive cars into the neighborhood, calling it a "serious quality-of-life mistake." "If we let them build it," he added, "people will drive." The new planetarium is expected to attract over 600,000 more visitors to the museum each year, and the three-story parking garage is meant to accommodate them. But neighbors say traffic will pile up, aggravated by tour buses, which the garage cannot accommodate. Andrew Albert, a co-chairman of the board's transportation committee, said, "The thing is that everyone has severely underestimated how many people are going to  visit this museum." The board recommended that the museum open a second entrance, at 78th Street, on weekends when visitor traffic is expected to be the heaviest, and the museum  agreed. "We take these concerns very seriously," said James Schmidt, the museum's project manager. Mr. Baldwin and others also told the community board of their opposition to amplified music at events at the outdoor restaurant, which will sit atop the garage, and the community board concurred. It doesn't help that the neighborhood is already feeling overwhelmed by the seemingly endless reconstruction project along Columbus Avenue. In fact, 81st Street has been closed to traffic for several weeks while a giant hole at the intersection of Columbus Avenue stands unfilled and surrounded by cement barricades. The museum construction is scheduled to begin in March 1997 and to be completed in 2000.</p>
        <p>JANET ALLON</p>
        <p>NEIGBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER WEST SIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
