<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Off-Target Duke Is Latest No. 1 To Get Dismissed</title>
    <meta content="25EAST$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1186584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="N.C.A.A. BASKETBALL TOURNAMENT -- EAST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Florida</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Duke University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EED9133DF936A15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Off-Target Duke Is Latest No. 1 To Get Dismissed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>SYRACUSE, March 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Florida defeats Duke, 87-78, in NCAA basketball tournament; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a tournament full of upsets, another giant fell tonight. Duke, a top-seeded team and winner of 26 straight games in the East Regional since 1986, was suffoctaed by Florida's full-court trapping defense and lost by 87-78 in the regional semifinals of the National Collegiate Athletic Association men's basketball tournament at the Carrier Dome.</p>
        <p>The Blue Devils lost because they could not shoot straight from long range, converting just 3 of 19 3-pointers after going 2 for 17 against Kansas in the second round.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a tournament full of upsets, another giant fell tonight. Duke, a top-seeded team and winner of 26 straight games in the East Regional since 1986, was suffoctaed by Florida's full-court trapping defense and lost by 87-78 in the regional semifinals of the National Collegiate Athletic Association men's basketball tournament at the Carrier Dome.</p>
        <p>The Blue Devils lost because they could not shoot straight from long range, converting just 3 of 19 3-pointers after going 2 for 17 against Kansas in the second round.</p>
        <p>Duke's loss left the tournament with only one remaining top-seeded team, Michigan State, in the Midwest Regional. Arizona was knocked out in the second round in the West, and Stanford was eliminated in the second round in the South.</p>
        <p>The beginning of the end for Duke came with 4 minutes 59 seconds remaining in tonight's game. Carlos Boozer, a 6-foot-9-inch freshman center for the top-seeded Blue Devils, fouled out and the resulting free throw by Florida's Teddy Dupay tied the score at 74-74.</p>
        <p>''When I scored, it was like the parting of the Red Sea,'' Dupay said of his 3-point play. ''I came in and Boozer fouled me. It was his fifth foul, too. That was a big play for us.''</p>
        <p>Duke had come back from a 7-point halftime deficit to gain several second-half leads, even taking a 4-point lead with 4:01 left. But, after that, the Blue Devils did not score for the rest of the game.</p>
        <p>The Gators, seeded fifth, take a 27-7 record into the regional final against Seton Hall (22-9) or Oklahoma State (26-6), who played later tonight.</p>
        <p>The winner of Sunday's game goes to Indianapolis next weekend for the Final Four. The Gators last reached the Final Four in 1994, losing to Duke in the semifinal.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of emotion in the locker room, but we've got another game to play,'' Florida guard Kenyan Weaks said. ''We didn't come here just to beat Duke. We came here to advance to the Final Four.''</p>
        <p>Florida won tonight with balanced scoring. Brett Nelson had 15 points and Udonis Haslem had 13. Dupay added 12 and Brent Wright and Mike Miller each had 10.</p>
        <p>''I'm proud of the way our kids competed,'' Florida Coach Billy Donovan said. ''Duke, over the last 20 years, has been the model of excellence.''</p>
        <p>It was the first time Florida had beaten a team ranked No. 1 in the country.</p>
        <p>Duke (29-5) was led by Shane Battier, who had 20 points and 9 rebounds. Boozer also had nine rebounds before leaving. The senior Chris Carrawell scored 16 points for Duke and three other Blue Devils were in double figures. The freshman point guard Jason Williams added 13, but shot 6 of 20, including 1 for 9 on 3-pointers.</p>
        <p>At halftime, Florida held a 40-33 lead. Much of the Gators' success came from their press, which seemed to frustrate Duke and cause turnovers when the Blue Devils tried to organize and bring the ball up the floor.</p>
        <p>Early in the half, Duke turned the ball over on three consecutive possessions. First was a blocking foul by Battier, who had tried to clear a path with a screen. Next came a held ball after Mike Dunleavy was trapped. Finally there was a 10-second violation under pressure.</p>
        <p>In discussing the Florida press the day before the game, Duke Coach Mike Krzyzewski said that the Gators have ''a press that doesn't get tired.''</p>
        <p>''They hope that you get tired because they sub a lot of people,'' Krzyzewski said. ''I think that's what makes it unique. They keep it on. They don't just have one trap. They trap or contain throughout the exchange. It's extended because they continue to press. That's somewhat unique. It's a good press.''</p>
        <p>Duke scored the first 7 points of the second half to tie the score. But after Florida took a 3-point lead, Battier of Duke turned the ball over on a traveling call against the press.</p>
        <p>With 16:08 remaining, Weaks received a technical foul for plowing into Williams of Duke during a scramble for a loose ball. Battier made one of the two free throws.</p>
        <p>Boozer got his fourth foul with 13:57 remaining after another Duke turnover against the Florida press. He left the game, but Battier put together a layup and a free throw for a 3-point play to tie the score at 54-54.</p>
        <p>It was tied again at 56-56, 58-58, 60-60. When Florida pressured the next inbounds pass, Duke had to call a timeout.</p>
        <p>The patter resumed, with the score tied again at 62-62 and 64-64 until Duke surged ahead for a 6-point lead with Boozer back in the game. Florida called a timeout.</p>
        <p>It was Duke's largest lead of the game, but Florida cut it to 74-71 with 5:17 left.</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. BASKETBALL TOURNAMENT -- EAST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
