<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; Ruminations of a Mathematics Lover</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="529767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MATHEMATICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KING, JERRY B</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ART OF MATHEMATICS, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED81131F93BA25756C0A964958260" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; Ruminations of a Mathematics Lover</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Art of Mathematics  By Jerry P. King  313 pages. Plenum Press. $24.50.</p>
        <p>Jerry P. King writes that math anxiety nearly got him when, as a youngster, he told his teacher, "I don't understand why -2 multiplied by -3 gives +6."</p>
        <p>" 'You have,' she answered sternly, 'a very bad attitude toward mathematics. I've already told you that the product of two negative numbers is always positive.' "</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Art of Mathematics  By Jerry P. King  313 pages. Plenum Press. $24.50.</p>
        <p>Jerry P. King writes that math anxiety nearly got him when, as a youngster, he told his teacher, "I don't understand why -2 multiplied by -3 gives +6."</p>
        <p>" 'You have,' she answered sternly, 'a very bad attitude toward mathematics. I've already told you that the product of two negative numbers is always positive.' "</p>
        <p>Fortunately, as Mr. King reports in "The Art of Mathematics," he got past that moment of thoughtless dogmatism. He "learned that z x 0 = 0 x z = 0, for any real number z," and learned moreover "that w + (-w) = 0, for any number w."</p>
        <p>"Nothing more is needed to establish the law of signs," he assures us, before filling up a page with algebraic equations that conclude with ab = (-a)(-b). "Q.E.D.," he concludes. "The perplexity either goes away or else it remains because you fail to understand 'mathematics.' . . ."</p>
        <p>He learned not only to understand mathematics but also to love it. He studied its philosophy in graduate school and later taught it at Lehigh University. Eventually he concluded that in its purest form the elegance of mathematics produces an esthetic experience. So he wrote "The Art of Mathematics." The only problem with it is that he repeats the behavior of that dogmatic childhood teacher by telling us in so many words that we have a very bad attitude toward mathematics.</p>
        <p>He tells us that American intellectual life is more divided than ever into the "two cultures" that C. P. Snow first discerned over 30 years ago. Where Snow called them the "humanists" and the "scientists," Mr. King names them "type M" and "type N," or those who understand mathematics and those who do not.  The only consolation we can take is that he is harder on the M types than he is on the N's, for being isolated and elitist and neglecting their "noblesse oblige" to teach the rest of us the beauties of pure math.</p>
        <p>He tries to teach it to us himself. In a chapter called "Numbers," he shows us "that all of mathematics flows from a few fundamental principles." Starting with the counting numbers 1, 2, 3, . . ., and five assumptions called the Peano Axioms after the mathematician Giuseppe Peano (1858-1932), he systematically creates integers, rationals, real numbers and complex numbers. These passages are the most stimulating in the book, but whenever the going gets abstruse the author resorts to telling us in effect that we'll have to take his word for it. Though this is doubtless warranted, it somehow undermines the purpose of a book whose main argument is that the art of math should be accessible to all.</p>
        <p>To remedy our shortcomings, he proposes the creation of a "mathworld" comparable to the "artworld" suggested by the writings of the estheticians Arthur C. Danto and George Dickie. Their "artworld" comprises artists, works of art and a public "prepared in some degree to understand an object which is presented to them." In Mr. King's "mathworld," good teachers would prepare the public for difficult mathematical ideas in the same way that art critics prepared the public for nonrealistic art like Post-Impressionism, Abstract Expressionism and Pop.</p>
        <p>What Mr. King seems to miss in all this is the meaning of the word "prepare." He doesn't see that it is history and cultural change, not critics, that prepare us to see the world in new ways, or that good critics, far from being high priests in the temple, are merely intermediaries in the marketplace who try to explain the relation of art to the spirit of the times. His view of the art world makes it positively loathsome.</p>
        <p>Moreover, he flops as a priest of mathematics, failing as he does to convey the esthetics of his subject. He stakes his case on a proof of the irrationality of the square root of 2, but this reader did not feel any mysterious resonance in his logic, which throws one tiny monkey wrench in his thesis that the beauty of math is accessible to each of us.</p>
        <p>Nor does he bring much in the way of esthetics to the task of writing. Though he postures at some length over his love of poetry in general and Robert Frost in particular, his prose is repetitive and clunky. Nearly grotesque is his elaborate effort to diagram what he calls "the esthetic ring of mathematics and the two cultures." This is a graphic display that succeeds in a complicated way at conveying the not very difficult idea that while humanists are too far away from math to see its beauty, and engineers and scientists are too close, only mathematicians are there in the meat of the doughnut at the right esthetic distance. (Isn't that</p>
        <p>three</p>
        <p>cultures, by the way?) One wouldn't be surprised to see a parody of this in Mad magazine.</p>
        <p>Along the way Mr. King damns with faint praise Michael Guillen's eloquent "Bridges to Infinity: The Human Side of Mathematics" (1984).  He particularly chides Mr. Guillen for proposing a nonmathematical illustration involving voters</p>
        <p>not</p>
        <p>casting their</p>
        <p>nay</p>
        <p>votes (with a positive effect on the voting issue) to explain the perplexing law of signs, or why minus times minus equals plus. Mr. King accuses Mr. Guillen of patronizing the reader, and praises his own page of equations for containing "mathematics and not just air." But "Bridges to Infinity" managed without a single equation to convey the excitement of various mathematical subjects and thereby brought the reader a little closer to an arcane world.</p>
        <p>By insisting on the beauty of pure math, Mr. King has had the opposite effect. If I had the space I would illustrate this concept with a diagram of a ring of mathematicians circling a center of mathematics and a dot representing me outside of the ring and nearly off the page. Whether or not you are mathematically inclined, I think you get the idea.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
