<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's Green And Has Stripes? A Zebra Tomato</title>
    <meta content="03TOMA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1021708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tomatoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Molly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D6173BF930A35755C0A96E958260" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's Green And Has Stripes? A Zebra Tomato</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOLLY O'NEILL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Neill, Molly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Molly O'Neill comments on arrival in markets of zebra tomatoes, a striking heirloom variety that can be tawny and green or green on green; recipes for zebra tomato and polenta lasagna and cold spiced chicken and zebra-tomato salad; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TAKE heart, all ye who harbor a taste for green tomatoes. No longer do you need to wish in secret that the sun will dim and the winds will blow, so that regular tomatoes will not ripen but will fall to the ground prematurely. No longer must your hankerings for fried green tomatoes leave you dependent on the unkindness of nature.</p>
        <p>The zebra tomato has arrived, and it will remain on shelves as long as the sun shines in Southern California and Mexico, where tons of this green heirloom variety are now being grown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TAKE heart, all ye who harbor a taste for green tomatoes. No longer do you need to wish in secret that the sun will dim and the winds will blow, so that regular tomatoes will not ripen but will fall to the ground prematurely. No longer must your hankerings for fried green tomatoes leave you dependent on the unkindness of nature.</p>
        <p>The zebra tomato has arrived, and it will remain on shelves as long as the sun shines in Southern California and Mexico, where tons of this green heirloom variety are now being grown.</p>
        <p>They are available in Manhattan at Balducci's, 424 Avenue of the Americas (Ninth Street); Dean &amp; DeLuca, 560 Broadway (Prince Street), and Grace's Marketplace, 1237 Third Avenue (71st Street), and by mail through Culinary Specialty Produce, (908) 789-4700.</p>
        <p>And these zebras are lookers. Their skins can be green on green, or tawny with green stripes. The fruit is smallish and can be round or plum-shaped; the insides are firm, pulpy and chewy, finely balanced between acid and sweet.</p>
        <p>Since the zebras are fully realized adults, not striplings harvested before their time, they taste more mellow than sharp and are firm without being hard.</p>
        <p>A cornmeal dusting and some bubbling hot olive oil do wonderful things to slices of zebra. The tomatoes make delicious preserves and pickle nicely. In exotic recipes, like Vietnamese chicken salad, thinly sliced strips of zebra pulp can take the place of green papaya. A touch of sugar and a splash of vinegar or lemon let the cook exaggerate the zebras' naturally mild sweet and sour taste.</p>
        <p>Those who seek the juicy succulence of most heirloom tomatoes might find zebras lacking. They don't squirt or lend themselves to poetic recollections of Grandmother's garden.</p>
        <p>No, zebras are self-possessed. Their natural firmness allows them to hold up well in the wok, saute pan, oven or grill. They may not be juicy, but they are cool.</p>
        <p>COLD SPICED CHICKEN AND ZEBRA-TOMATO SALAD  Time: 15 minutes, plus 1 hour chilling</p>
        <p>Juice from 2 lemons, about 5 tablespoons</p>
        <p>1  tablespoon sugar</p>
        <p>1  teaspoon kosher salt</p>
        <p>1/8  teaspoon white pepper</p>
        <p>2  tablespoons Thai fish sauce</p>
        <p>1  teaspoon fresh minced chili pepper, more if desired</p>
        <p>10  green zebra tomatoes</p>
        <p>2  cups shredded, cooked chicken, cold</p>
        <p>1  cup finely shredded cabbage</p>
        <p>1  tablespoon chopped fresh mint, plus sprigs for garnish</p>
        <p>1  tablespoon chopped fresh cilantro, plus  sprigs for garnish.</p>
        <p>1. Combine lemon juice, sugar, salt, white pepper, fish sauce and chili pepper in large bowl, and stir until sugar dissolves.  2. Quarter tomatoes, and then use spoon to remove and discard pulp and seeds. Slice wedges into fine slivers, and add them to bowl.  3. Add chicken, cabbage, chopped mint and cilantro. Toss, and adjust seasoning to taste with additional salt, white pepper or chili pepper. Refrigerate for 1 hour, and serve garnished with additional sprigs of mint and cilantro.  Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>ZEBRA TOMATO AND POLENTA LASAGNA  Time: 1 1/2 hours</p>
        <p>2  teaspoons kosher salt, plus more for seasoning</p>
        <p>1  cup dry uncooked polenta</p>
        <p>25  green zebra tomatoes</p>
        <p>1  clove garlic</p>
        <p>1  teaspoon white pepper</p>
        <p>1  teaspoon olive oil</p>
        <p>1  bunch fresh oregano</p>
        <p>6  ounces feta cheese</p>
        <p>8  ounces fresh ricotta cheese</p>
        <p>1  egg.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Put 4 3/4 cups water in large pot, add salt and bring to a boil. Slowly sprinkle polenta into water in a thin stream, whisking constantly until it is absorbed. Reduce heat to simmer, and cook, covered, for 35 minutes. Every 10 minutes, give the pot 1 minute of vigorous stirring; after final stir, allow polenta to cook for 5 more minutes. Turn out into a bowl.  2. Meanwhile, cut 5 tomatoes into quarters, and place them with garlic in blender. Blend tomatoes until very smooth. Taste puree mixture, season lightly with salt and white pepper, and set aside. Slice remaining tomatoes into disks, each  1/4 inch thick.  3. Grease 8-by-8-inch baking dish with olive oil. Spoon half of polenta into dish, and press it out to sides in even layer. Arrange 1 layer of tomatoes on top of polenta, season lightly with salt and white pepper, and place 1 oregano leaf on each tomato slice. Drizzle about 3 tablespoons of puree mixture over tomatoes. Sprinkle a third of crumbled feta over puree.  4. Beat ricotta cheese and egg together, and season lightly with salt and white pepper to taste. Build second layer of tomatoes, salt, white pepper and oregano. Spread half of ricotta mixture over this layer. Make another layer from the rest of the polenta.  5. Place layer of tomatoes, salt, white pepper and oregano over polenta. Add remaining ricotta and then remaining sliced tomatoes, and season again as above. Spread remaining puree over all, and then sprinkle remaining crumbled feta over top.  6. Bake for 35 to 45 minutes, until tomatoes are bubbling and cheese is golden.  Yield: 4 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
