<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New &amp; Noteworthy Paperbacks</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="680837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAPERBACK BOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E0D91F3FF934A25757C0A962958260" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New &amp; Noteworthy Paperbacks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laurel Graeber</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE GREAT MELODY: A Thematic Biography and Commented Anthology of Edmund Burke By Conor Cruise O'Brien. University of Chicago, $22.50. This 18th-century political scholar was more than a crusty conservative. The author emphasizes Burke's stance against government tyranny, stressing his role as a champion of independence for America, Ireland and India. "Mr. O'Brien has brought back a lost treasure," John Patrick Diggins said here last year. His is "a brilliant work of narrative sweep and analytic depth."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE GREAT MELODY: A Thematic Biography and Commented Anthology of Edmund Burke By Conor Cruise O'Brien. University of Chicago, $22.50. This 18th-century political scholar was more than a crusty conservative. The author emphasizes Burke's stance against government tyranny, stressing his role as a champion of independence for America, Ireland and India. "Mr. O'Brien has brought back a lost treasure," John Patrick Diggins said here last year. His is "a brilliant work of narrative sweep and analytic depth."</p>
        <p>THE COLLECTED STORIES By John McGahern. Vintage International, $12. The characters in this fiction are, like the author, Irish, and they are usually bound to the rural regions of their nation by poverty and hard circumstance. But they are not without imagination, and these stories illustrate their various means of escape, whether it is comic-book fantasy or the wilds of romantic love. Last year our reviewer, Josephine Humphreys, said, "Mr. McGahern, a master of the clean, plain, powerful description, is able to convey the strange phenomenon of immanence, the presence in material things of nonmaterial significance." Ireland is also the subject of three memoirs by Alice Taylor reissued by St. Martin's Press. TO SCHOOL THROUGH THE FIELDS: An Irish Country Childhood ($8.95) re-creates the author's early years as a member of a large farming family. "Ms. Taylor's book seeks to memorialize a place utterly changed by time," Patricia Hampl said here in 1990. These girlhood experiences are continued in QUENCH THE LAMP ($8.95), in which Ms. Taylor fondly recalls rural rituals and eccentric neighbors. In 1991 one critic praised "the careful and generous eye of this gifted Irish writer." THE VILLAGE ($8.95) celebrates Ms. Taylor's life in Innishannon, County Cork, where she arrived as a bride in the 1960's and where she still lives. "What makes the story unique is Taylor's disarming style; she writes as though she were sitting next to you," one critic said last year. Contemporary Ireland is the setting of THE HEATHER BLAZING, by Colm Toibin (Penguin, $9.95). Eamon Redmond, a judge, finds that his conflicts with his son and daughter mirror the dissension within the nation, where secular social principles clash with a long religious history. Last year our reviewer, Lucy McDiarmid, said that the author "writes with the vision of an enlightened Republic of Ireland still being struggled toward in the world outside fiction." Another of Ireland's authors is seeing three of her early novels reappear in print in AN EDNA O'BRIEN READER: August Is a Wicked Month, Casualties of Peace, Johnny I Hardly Knew You (Warner, $11.99). In "August Is a Wicked Month," a London journalist separated from her husband goes to the south of France, where she takes refuge in an affair and pays dearly for it. "There is some pathos in this vacation from morals," Martin Levin said here in 1965. Another wife seeks escape in "Casualties of Peace," a novel that centers on a frail sculptor and her earthy housekeeper. In 1967 our reviewer, Eleanor Dienstag, said it "pulsates with . . . racy, exuberant, nervous prose." The last novel, originally titled "I Hardly Knew You," is about the violent end of a woman's love affair with a much younger man, her son's best friend. In 1978 our reviewer, Anatole Broyard, criticized the book but praised its "talented and worldly" author: "She has always ridden the passions as if they were a magnificent horse."  BOILING POINT: Democrats, Republicans, and the Decline of Middle-Class Prosperity By Kevin Phillips. Harper Perennial, $13. The majority of Americans are still reeling from the 1980's, argues the author, who demonstrates the devastating consequences of Republican tax policies and the decline in the nation's industry. Last year our reviewer, Alan Ehrenhalt, said this book is "an impressive piece of economic analysis and a troubling moral argument."  CONTENTS UNDER PRESSURE By Edna Buchanan. Avon, $4.99. The author, a Miami police reporter, has created an alter ego in the form of Britt Montero, a feisty journalist who is determined to find out the truth behind the death of a retired black football player. The police claim his car crashed while they were in pursuit, but Britt has other ideas. The outcome is "undeniably vivid and disturbing," Josh Rubins said here in 1992.  AFTER TET: The Bloodiest Year in Vietnam By Ronald H. Spector. Vintage, $13. Written by a former marine who served in Vietnam during the 12 months following the Tet offensive of 1968, this book chronicles the many misadventures of that agonizing period. Mr. Spector shows how United States foreign-policy makers exploited the young, usually working-class Americans who were thrust into the center of the war. He has also interviewed North Vietnamese, noting that their elite were also largely absent from the conflict. Last year our reviewer, Morley Safer, said, "There is a wealth of fascinating detail in 'After Tet' that will surprise both old Vietnam hands and casual readers." He added, "This is history, at its best." The often sacrificial role of American servicemen in the war is further examined in RED THUNDER, TROPIC LIGHTNING: The World of a Combat Division in Vietnam, by Eric M. Bergerud (Penguin, $11.95). The author, writing of the 25th Infantry Division, notes that the soldiers became lures to flush out the elusive enemy. Whether such a strategy would have been tolerated if the American troops had been more middle-class "is an especially unpleasant question for the reader . . . to ponder," Russell F. Weigley said here last year.  COME TO ME: Stories By Amy Bloom. Harper Perennial, $10. A finalist for the National Book Award, this collection concerns families in crisis, divided by death, extramarital love affairs, mental illness or simple accident. Last year our reviewer, Anne Whitehouse, said the author's "voice is sure and brisk, her language often beautiful; the result is humorous as well as heart-rending fiction."  LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
