<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ENVOY LISTS GOODS NEEDED BY SOVIETS</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="406732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATIONING AND ALLOCATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUBININ, YURI V (AMB)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rationing and Allocation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DC1531F934A35751C1A966958260" item-length="455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ENVOY LISTS GOODS NEEDED BY SOVIETS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">REUTERS</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Dec. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Soviet Ambassador to France, visibly embarrassed, distributed a list of goods today that he said his compatriots needed from the West in light of deteriorating conditions in the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>"The state is taking the necessary measures to soften the difficulties of the transition period," Ambassador Yuri V. Dubinin said at a news conference, adding, "The humanitarian help of our foreign partners plays an equally important role."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Soviet Ambassador to France, visibly embarrassed, distributed a list of goods today that he said his compatriots needed from the West in light of deteriorating conditions in the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>"The state is taking the necessary measures to soften the difficulties of the transition period," Ambassador Yuri V. Dubinin said at a news conference, adding, "The humanitarian help of our foreign partners plays an equally important role."</p>
        <p>In an unexpectedly direct appeal going over the heads of governments, stern-faced embassy guards then gave reporters a list of 17 needed items.</p>
        <p>The appeals were for supplies ranging from baby food to cigarettes that the Soviet Union would like to receive as donations from foreign aid groups. Bank Account for Donations</p>
        <p>"We need food supplies, medicine and medical equipment and everyday consumer goods, with the exception of clothes," the statement said. It also gave the number of a bank account to which charity donations can be made.</p>
        <p>The list included powdered milk, powdered milk-based children's foods, meat, cooked meats, vegetable oil, butter, candy, cigarettes, flour, noodles, gruel, canned fish, canned vegetables, fruit, dried fruits, washing powder and toothpaste.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dubinin said Moscow would allow monitoring on its territory of the distribution of aid by such charity groups as Doctors without Borders, a French group that usually operates in disaster areas and combat zones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dubinin's appeal followed the imposition of rationing on consumer goods in Moscow. and the arrival of the first consignments of Western government food aid to the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>"This appeal is being made here in Paris, but it is addressed to all Western public opinion," an embassy spokesman, Vladimir Fedorovsky, told reporters at the Soviet Embassy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dubinin, one of his country's senior diplomats, seemed uncomfortable as he faced a barrage of questions about what reporters called "national humiliation."</p>
        <p>Asked by one reporter if his country was "now just another third world state unable to feed its people," he replied: "Not at all. Our policy is not a failure, and we consider the aid is helping to build a new Europe."</p>
        <p>In Brussels on Monday, the Soviet representative at the European Community gave a list of needed items to Jacques Delors, president of the executive arm of the European Community, that included some of the items on Mr. Dubinin's list.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dubinin said the requests were made "because the old system of distribution had practically broken down" and needs were acute in Soviet cities.</p>
        <p>Asked how an ailing distribution system could cope with an influx of aid, he replied, "We created a special commission to handle this only this week."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
