<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Restaurants</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="406619"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MARCH (NYC RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURROS, MARIAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D71438F934A35751C1A966958260" item-length="1210" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Restaurants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marian Burros</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURROS, MARIAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ridiculous, you say, to open an expensive restaurant at the end of 1990? Diners are counting their pennies, restaurants are trading down. Why spend $45 for a fixed-price meal when you can eat at one of the new bistros for $30 or less?</p>
        <p>Why? Let me count the ways: One year into the less-is-more-restaurant style, and you are already tired of giving your money to surly waiters who act as if they are doing you a favor; you can't stand another serving of cold mashed potato; you want to see coats and ties instead of torn T-shirts. If you are nodding yes, then you might want to think about March, a tiny jewel box of a town house on 58th Street in Manhattan between Sutton Place and First Avenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ridiculous, you say, to open an expensive restaurant at the end of 1990? Diners are counting their pennies, restaurants are trading down. Why spend $45 for a fixed-price meal when you can eat at one of the new bistros for $30 or less?</p>
        <p>Why? Let me count the ways: One year into the less-is-more-restaurant style, and you are already tired of giving your money to surly waiters who act as if they are doing you a favor; you can't stand another serving of cold mashed potato; you want to see coats and ties instead of torn T-shirts. If you are nodding yes, then you might want to think about March, a tiny jewel box of a town house on 58th Street in Manhattan between Sutton Place and First Avenue.</p>
        <p>March is a grown-up restaurant with discreet, professional service, chairs you are happy to sit in for more than an hour, capacious tables that will hold all of the food the waiter serves and enough space between you and the other diners to allow for a good-neighbor policy. What if the service at March is a little too ingratiating. We need more of such coddling.</p>
        <p>The hope is that March will succeed where others with lofty ambitions have failed. This town house began its restaurant career as Dodin-Bouffant. Brive followed some time after. Neither lasted long.</p>
        <p>After an uneven start, when the food was better looking than it tasted, March is hitting its stride under the chef and co-owner, Wayne Nish, who cooked at La Colombe d'Or and the Quilted Giraffe in Manhattan. His partner, Joseph Scalice, keeps an eagle eye on the front of the house, a charming set of four small rooms eclectically done in someone's interpretation of a fine French restaurant.  Wainscoting of teak with teak floors and a stunning teak secretary, an Oriental rug on the floor, a needlepoint rug on the wall, all make you feel as if you are in a private home where the host and staff are happy to see you.</p>
        <p>It would be better if the meal started more auspiciously: the amuse gueule -- a ravioli filled with vegetables that arrives as a gift from the management -- lacks flavor. The restaurant could also come up with a better-tasting bread and a more interesting and better-priced wine list. But these flaws are easily remedied.</p>
        <p>The plates Mr. Nish sends out are carefully done, but never so fussy or prissy that they look more like still lifes than edible art. Several appetizer specials were exceptional: full-bodied plump oysters perfectly cooked in butter and served with very thin noodles are pretty classy comfort food.  New York State foie gras, nicely browned, was superb with a Concord grape sauce. And welcome back to a silken beurre blanc, here served over well-cooked scallops.</p>
        <p>On the regular menu, a tomatoey bread pudding provided a nice counterpoint to some lusty rabbit sausages. Tiny and flavorful yellow, orange and red pear and plum tomatoes were lovely with some woodsy chanterelles in a basil vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>The chef should rethink his fantasy of potato salad that goes with delicious seared, marinated beef, and lobster is too delicate for the barley risotto on which it was served. But the sauteed shrimp with butter-rich acorn squash puree and cider sauce was a felicitous marriage.</p>
        <p>After eating too much room-temperature soup, chicken and french fries elsewhere, even the copper domes on the entrees are welcome. Pretension has its place; the domes perform the function for which they were intended: they keep hot food hot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nish knows his way around a lamb, whether the rack with a savory herbed crust and tender goat cheese-touched gnocchi, or a special of buttery baby chops and loin redolent of garlic.</p>
        <p>The confit and grilled duck bathed in an aromatic sauce with sweet spices, and the meaty squab with its crackling skin, served with a happy union of orzo and wild rice, were very satisfying.</p>
        <p>Wild striped bass, though with little flavor on our first visit, was superb at another meal, the outside crisply cooked, the accompanying white beans zesty with tomato conserve. Red snapper is an equally good choice with shallots so crisp they are as addictive as peanuts.</p>
        <p>The copper domes failed the grilled chicken one night: it wasn't hot. Salmon with mushrooms, though technically correct, was bland, and the tender venison, a special, was overwhelmed by the intensity of a thick, dark truffle sauce.</p>
        <p>As much care is taken with the vegetables as with the meats and fish, and there is no lack of butter. But you needn't feel any more guilty about eating this food than you do the supposedly lighter cooking of the bistro. If it's a choice between a good beurre blanc and a soggy french fry, there's no contest.</p>
        <p>Still, if you want to be spartan about dessert, March makes it easy: choose the grapefruit and grapefruit sorbet in gin and you will at last know how grapefruit sorbet should taste.</p>
        <p>However, since you have come this far, you might as well have the fall fruit tart with vanilla ice cream. Fresh and dried fruits have been poached in white wine, port, thyme and bay leaf and wrapped in a hobo's sack of phyllo. A tart it isn't, but why quibble with anything this good.</p>
        <p>When the walnut tart is properly prepared, as it was on our third visit, the luscious filling treated like a pecan pie and cooled by a flash of hazelnut ice cream, the result is superb. And for chocolate fiends, there is an ethereal cake with pear sauce and caramel. Ginger custard and pumpkin mousse are highly recommended for those who like to mainline cream.</p>
        <p>No matter your choice, save room for the restaurant's parting gift, a sophisticated and irresistible version of almond pralines.</p>
        <p>Wayne Nish is getting better every day. I would happily trade one of his $45 dinners for two of those $30 bistro meals recently reviewed in these columns. Even if it meant washing the dishes at home one night. March</p>
        <p>**</p>
        <p>405 East 58th Street, Manhattan, (212) 838-9393.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: Sophisticated and romantic town house with four small dining rooms.</p>
        <p>Service: Professional, efficient, pleasant.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: Rabbit sausage with bread pudding, tomato and chanterelle salad, oysters with thin noodles, foie gras with Concord grape sauce, scallops with beurre blanc, shrimp with acorn squash, red snapper in red wine sauce, striped bass with white beans, confit and grilled duck, rack of lamb, baby lamb chops, fall fruit tart, pumpkin mousse, chocolate cake, walnut tart, grapefruit sorbet, ginger custard.</p>
        <p>Wine: Standard high East Side prices.</p>
        <p>Price range: Dinner: $45 prix fixe.</p>
        <p>Credit cards: American Express, Diner's Club, Mastercard and Visa.</p>
        <p>Hours: Dinner: Monday to Saturday 5:30 to 10 P.M.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Requested.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility: One step up to dining room. Restrooms one flight down. What the stars mean: (None) Poor to Satisfactory * Good ** Very Good *** Excellent **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambiance and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>The Times Restaurant Line offers capsule reviews by cuisine, price and location (in New York City and suburbs), published in the last 18 months. Touch-line telephones only: 1-900-988-0101 (75 cents a minute).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
