<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Least Yankees Get Some Rest In Ugly Loss</title>
    <meta content="03yankees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1699222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E2D91431F930A3575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Least Yankees Get Some Rest In Ugly Loss</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., Sept. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The public-address announcer was still talking, but Jorge DePaula threw a pitch anyway. Bobby Kielty doubled to the right-field corner. The Yankees did not want to be here anymore, in the sixth inning of a dreary blowout, and the Oakland Athletics still had hitting to do.</p>
        <p>In the first game of a series that could be pivotal for their playoff chances, the Yankees miserably flunked a test. The A's embarrassed Al Leiter, 12-0, a beating so bad that Manager Joe Torre made seven defensive changes at once, before the bottom of the sixth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The public-address announcer was still talking, but Jorge DePaula threw a pitch anyway. Bobby Kielty doubled to the right-field corner. The Yankees did not want to be here anymore, in the sixth inning of a dreary blowout, and the Oakland Athletics still had hitting to do.</p>
        <p>In the first game of a series that could be pivotal for their playoff chances, the Yankees miserably flunked a test. The A's embarrassed Al Leiter, 12-0, a beating so bad that Manager Joe Torre made seven defensive changes at once, before the bottom of the sixth.</p>
        <p>That was why the Coliseum P.A. man was so busy. Gone were all the fielders except second baseman Robinson Cano. In came every healthy play on the Yankees' bench.</p>
        <p>John Flaherty, the backup catcher, played first base for the first time in his career. Andy Phillips took over at third for Alex Rodriguez, who had made an error for the first time in 62 games in the fifth inning. Wil Nieves, No. 60, squatted behind the plate.</p>
        <p>So that was the Yankees' battery on the second day of September: DePaula and Nieves, both playing their first game for the team this season. They gave the Yankees a total of 50 players used this season, tying the club record from 1989, when the Yankees were also-rans.</p>
        <p>They are striving for the playoffs this season, trailing in two races. The Boston Red Sox lead the Yankees by two and a half games in the American League East. The Yankees also trail in the wild-card race; their record is 75-59, one game worse than the A's and the Los Angeles Angels, who are tied atop the West at 76-58.</p>
        <p>The Athletics came into the game with the same record as the Yankees and the best mark in baseball since May 30 (58-26). But they had lost their last two games and two crucial offensive players were gone.</p>
        <p>Shortstop Bobby Crosby is on the disabled list with a fractured ankle. Center fielder Mark Kotsay is out with back soreness. But if the A's were weaker, the Yankees could not tell the difference.</p>
        <p>The A's rank third in the league in walks. Leiter leads the majors in walks allowed. It seemed destined to be a rough night for him, and it was.</p>
        <p>Leiter hit the first batter, Jason Kendall, who stole second. Then Leiter watched Mark Ellis hit a ball off the high wall in left field. Hideki Matsui misplayed it into a triple, then Ellis scored on a ground out.</p>
        <p>After Jay Payton flied out, Leiter had a chance to start over: two out, bases empty. But a homer by Bobby Kielty sent him tumbling into a hole he could not escape.</p>
        <p>Scott Hatteberg singled. Leiter hit another batter, Nick Swisher. Dan Johnson singled to right, and Hatteberg deftly twisted his body to avoid Jorge Posada's tag at the plate. Then Leiter walked the No. 9 hitter, Marco Scutaro, to load the bases.</p>
        <p>To that point, Posada had been to the mound twice, once by himself and once with the pitching coach, Mel Stottlemyre. The Yankees had Jorge DePaula and Wayne Franklin -- two September call-ups -- warming in the bullpen. Leiter would need to summon his experience to keep the deficit at 4-0.</p>
        <p>Leiter has called this the ''MacGyver Moment,'' a reference to the TV hero who pulled himself from danger just in time. Torre trusts in Leiter's experience, but it did not help him here. Kendall pulled a hard shot down the third-base line, off the glove of a diving Alex Rodriguez and into the left-field corner.</p>
        <p>Two runs scored on the double to give the A's a 6-0 lead, and DePaula replaced Leiter. On the mound, Rodriguez screamed out a curse word. There is no telling what Leiter said to himself in the clubhouse.</p>
        <p>After two consecutive quality starts, this was Leiter's shortest outing since Game 6 of the 1999 National League Championship Series at Atlanta, when he could not get an out in the first for the Mets.</p>
        <p>The Mets came back to tie that game (before losing it), but there was no saving Leiter this time. DePaula was making his first appearance for the Yankees since April 2004, when he was shut down and needed reconstructive elbow surgery.</p>
        <p>And the results, predictably, were terrible. DePaula got the last out of the first inning, but the first four hitters of the second scored. His tale of woe: double, single, single, three-run homer by Hatteberg. The Athletics sent 15 hitters to the plate, and 10 scored.</p>
        <p>There is no mercy rule in the majors, and the Yankees had to endure the humiliation of slogging through until the end. At least their regulars would not have to witness more.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
