<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Controls on Bank-Data Spying Impress Civil Liberties Board</title>
    <meta content="29nsa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1808093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Intelligence Services</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Swift (Society for World Interbank Financial Telecommunication)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lichtblau, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveillance of Citizens by Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Intelligence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1DD113EF93AA15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Controls on Bank-Data Spying Impress Civil Liberties Board</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LICHTBLAU</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lichtblau, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Civil liberties panel appointed by White House receives classified briefing on Bush administration's program to monitor international banking transactions, and several members say are impressed with privacy controls in place to prevent abuses against Americans; program, which gives American intelligence officials access to large volumes of banking data through Brussels consortium known as Swift, has been attacked by regulators in Europe, who view it as illegal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A civil liberties panel appointed by the White House received a classified briefing Tuesday on the Bush administration's program to monitor international banking transactions, and several members said they had come away impressed with the privacy controls in place to prevent abuses against Americans.</p>
        <p>The program, which gives American intelligence officials access to large volumes of banking data through a Brussels consortium known as Swift, has been attacked by regulators in Europe, who view it as illegal and have threatened sanctions. But the administration gave no indication at Tuesday's briefing that it was rethinking the program, defending it as a vital tool in tracking terrorist financing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A civil liberties panel appointed by the White House received a classified briefing Tuesday on the Bush administration's program to monitor international banking transactions, and several members said they had come away impressed with the privacy controls in place to prevent abuses against Americans.</p>
        <p>The program, which gives American intelligence officials access to large volumes of banking data through a Brussels consortium known as Swift, has been attacked by regulators in Europe, who view it as illegal and have threatened sanctions. But the administration gave no indication at Tuesday's briefing that it was rethinking the program, defending it as a vital tool in tracking terrorist financing.</p>
        <p>The briefing, lasting nearly two hours, was held at the Treasury Department for the five members of the Privacy and Civil Liberties Oversight Board, created at Congress's direction in 2004 to examine privacy issues related to the war on terror. The board received a similar classified briefing last week on the National Security Agency's domestic wiretapping program, created by President Bush soon after the Sept. 11 attacks.</p>
        <p>The board's only Democrat, Lanny J. Davis, who was a senior aide to President Bill Clinton, said that before the latest briefing he had had doubts about the Swift banking program. But ''I was impressed with the lengths to which these people have gone to avoid infringing on people's civil rights,'' Mr. Davis said in an interview. ''It was less of a concern than I expected.''</p>
        <p>Democrats in Congress, however, have questioned the independence and resources of the board and its ability to inquire deeply into highly classified programs. Until last month the White House had resisted allowing the board to be briefed on the Swift and N.S.A. programs.</p>
        <p>The White House has now allowed security clearances for the board to look at both, and for the Justice Department's inspector general to examine the N.S.A. program. Democrats have suggested that the election victory giving them imminent control of Congress spurred the White House's change of heart, an assertion that administration officials deny.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the board gave Congressional aides a briefing on its work, and Democratic staff members raised questions about its independence, according to four officials who were present. Democratic aides said they were troubled to learn at the briefing that any final report produced by the board would be vetted by the White House and that the panel would not examine issues related to civil liberties outside American borders -- for instance, at the Guantánamo Bay detention center.</p>
        <p>Alan C. Raul, a Reagan White House adviser who is vice chairman of the panel, said that given what he heard at Tuesday's briefing, the government appeared to have tight controls to ensure that only people with clear terrorist links were made targets of the banking program.</p>
        <p>''When you hear program operators tell you how carefully they make these judgments, it's striking, and you'd have to say impressive,'' Mr. Raul said. ''The execution seems to be done with scrupulous attention to the privacy and civil liberties implications.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis, the board's Democratic member, echoed that assessment. ''Based on what I've seen so far in both programs,'' he said of the banking and N.S.A. efforts, ''I think they have struck the right balance'' between detecting terrorist threats and ensuring Americans' civil liberties.</p>
        <p>''But there's a big caveat,'' he added. ''I don't know what I don't know, and we are looking forward to getting more information.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
