<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anger Undimmed in Atlanta At Killing of Aged Woman</title>
    <meta content="29atlanta" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/29/us/29atlanta.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1808125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, Kathryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Richard J (Police Chief)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Brenda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DC113EF93AA15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anger Undimmed in Atlanta At Killing of Aged Woman</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Anger Spills Over in Atlanta at Killing of Aged Woman</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA DEWAN and BRENDA GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Brenda; Dewan, Shaila</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, Nov. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atlanta police chief Richard J Pennington meets with outraged blacks following fatal shooting of 88-year-old Kathryn Johnston by three narcotics officers; family says she lived alone, but officers had warrant saying crack was being sold there; Johnston shot all three officers with her revolver before falling in hail of gunfire; informant later says he was asked to lie about buying crack there, but police say they have drugs from house; photo of funeral (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the packed Lindsey Street Baptist Church, a man in a three-piece suit approached a microphone Tuesday night and began to preach to the man in the pulpit.</p>
        <p>''You say you're going to come in and clean up the neighborhood,'' he said. ''But there's a difference between cleaning up and cleaning out.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The shooting of an elderly woman in Atlanta by police officers has touched off outrage at the police.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the packed Lindsey Street Baptist Church, a man in a three-piece suit approached a microphone Tuesday night and began to preach to the man in the pulpit.</p>
        <p>''You say you're going to come in and clean up the neighborhood,'' he said. ''But there's a difference between cleaning up and cleaning out.''</p>
        <p>The patient object of this lecture, and others that followed, was the police chief, Richard J. Pennington, who had come to a community meeting to face an angry crowd a week after three of his narcotics officers shot an elderly woman to death at her home.</p>
        <p>The shooting, in a black neighborhood tormented by crime, has touched off outrage at the police, especially after a confidential informant came forward Monday and said that after the killing, officers instructed him to lie by saying he had bought drugs at the home of the woman, Kathryn Johnston.</p>
        <p>At a demonstration Tuesday called by the New Black Panther Party, protesters rallied angrily at police barricades in front of Ms. Johnston's house. And at the church, filled with some 400 people, critics demanded that the officers involved be arrested. Placards mocked the fact that they, along with five other members of their narcotics investigation team, had been placed on administrative leave but would continue to receive their salaries: ''Kill a black citizen and get paid.''</p>
        <p>Such a scene might be more common in cities where a police shooting can easily shred the carefully woven strands of race, authority, force and order. But it was unusual for Atlanta, with its relative racial harmony. Although the Police Department's record is not unblemished, there have not been a string of high-profile shootings, nor anything to rival the killing of Amadou Diallo in New York or the beating of Rodney King in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Further, the department is racially balanced -- of the three investigators who arrived at Ms. Johnston's door, two were white and one was black -- and is led by a black man.</p>
        <p>The family of Ms. Johnston, whose funeral was held Tuesday in neighboring East Point, Ga., has said she lived alone. But the three officers were executing a search warrant that said an informant had bought crack from a man at her address. The police had obtained a no-knock warrant, allowing them to enter without first announcing themselves, so as to prevent the disposal of evidence. They cut the burglar bars, forced open the door and then identified themselves as officers.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Johnston, 88, was already at the door with a revolver, which neighbors later said she had kept for protection. She shot all three officers before she fell in a hail of gunfire.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the informant said in an interview with Fox News that he had never been to the house and had been asked after the shooting to lie about having bought crack there. The police, on the other hand, say they have two bags of crack bought by the informant before the warrant was served, and three bags of marijuana recovered at the house after the shooting. The president of the police union said Tuesday that the informant had lied in the Fox interview to avoid entanglement.</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, the rage here appears to be less about the Atlanta police than about a general perception that the justice system is unfair to blacks and cannot be trusted to protect them. ''This is nothing new; this is not an isolated incident,'' said the Rev. Anthony Motley, the pastor of the church. ''We are experiencing a wave of police violence across this nation, and Kathryn Johnston is another victim of that violence.''</p>
        <p>Others said many people in Atlanta felt violated by the police even if the results were not frequently fatal. ''Below the surface there's some rage in people always when it comes to perceptions of the police,'' said Clarence T. Martin, a member of the City Council who is vice chairman of its Public Safety Committee.</p>
        <p>Chief Pennington has sought to take the edge off by declining to defend his department and by asking for the F.B.I. investigation that the bureau has now undertaken.</p>
        <p>And for this he has earned praise. On Tuesday night, when the crowd at the church grew unruly, Mr. Motley, the pastor, appealed for calm, saying: ''We're all family. I want you to say amen.''</p>
        <p>Those present replied, ''Amen.''</p>
        <p>''The chief has taken a pretty good beating,'' the pastor told them. ''I like what the chief has done so far.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
