<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bonn Sets Mark Rate On Savings</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="334607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL MONETARY SYSTEM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GERMANY, REUNIFICATION OF</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAST GERMANY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PROTZMAN, FERDINAND</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOHL, HELMUT (CHANCELLOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA133DF937A25750C0A966958260" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bonn Sets Mark Rate On Savings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FERDINAND PROTZMAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PROTZMAN, FERDINAND</byline>
      <dateline>WEST BERLIN, March 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany said today that East Germans would be able to exchange their personal savings at a one-to-one rate for West German marks, but that this rate would not apply to East German marks held by businesses or other institutions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany said today that East Germans would be able to exchange their personal savings at a one-to-one rate for West German marks, but that this rate would not apply to East German marks held by businesses or other institutions.</p>
        <p>Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany said today that East Germans would be able to exchange their personal savings at a one-to-one rate for West German marks, but that this rate would not apply to East German marks held by businesses or other institutions.</p>
        <p>Though the plan has been mentioned before by Bonn officials, today was the first time Mr. Kohl has specifically said the rate would be one-to-one for savers. Coming five days before East Germany's first free elections on Sunday, Mr. Kohl's comments were clearly political in nature, intended to sway the large number of undecided East German voters toward the conservative Alliance for Germany and to slow the flow of East German emigrants to West Germany.</p>
        <p>''We want savers to know that when the change in currency comes, it will be at one-to-one for them,'' Mr. Kohl said in a speech at a rally for conservative political parties held in Cottbus, a city in southern East Germany not far from the Polish border.</p>
        <p>'Crucial' Support</p>
        <p>''This will be valid for small savers but not for the whole currency,'' Mr. Kohl added. ''It is crucial that those who deserve our support and solidarity should not be disadvantaged.''</p>
        <p>The exchange-rate plan for establishing a single German currency is a crucial step in the economic unification of the two Germanys. Mr. Kohl did not say when or how currency union would be realized nor did he specify a rate for the billions of East German marks in circulation. He also did not address the dangers, such as sharp rises in inflation and interest rates, that many economists say a one-to-one rate carries.</p>
        <p>Western financial markets focused on the inflationary potential of the one-to-one rate. In New York, Treasury bond prices dropped, based on the view that higher inflation in West Germany would push German interest rates higher, forcing up rates elsewhere. The dollar rose sharply against the German mark on Mr. Kohl's announcement, but then retreated somewhat when traders recognized that the rate would apply only to personal savings.</p>
        <p>East German citizens are estimated to have about 170 billion East German marks in savings accounts. At a one-to-one exchange rate, that would be about $100 billion.</p>
        <p>A less favorable rate would wipe out much of the financial wealth East Germans have accumulated over the years. At present, East Germany's currency is officially nonconvertible to other currencies, but it trades on the black market at a rate of four East marks to one Deutsche mark.</p>
        <p>Shortly after the Berlin wall was opened in November, the rate soared to 20 to 1, but it has fallen sporadically since and the East German mark has gained strength recently from the speculation that savings would be converted at one-to-one.</p>
        <p>The generous rate on savings is likely to be coupled with a severe curtailment of the financial benefits East Germans receive when they resettle in West Germany, according to Reuters news service. It said sources in Mr. Kohl's Christian Democratic Union are saying East German emigrants would receive only the unemployment pay and pensions they would get in East Germany, rather than the extensive financial assistance they currently receive.</p>
        <p>Currency Panel Meets</p>
        <p>The comments by Mr. Kohl came on the same day that an inter-German currency commission charged with mapping the route to rapid monetary union met in East Berlin.</p>
        <p>Members of the commission would not give details of the meeting, saying only that considerable progress had been achieved. ''Currency and economic union can be rapidly accomplished given the required political will,'' a statement issued by the commission said. The talks will be resumed shortly after the East German elections, but not specific date has been released.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
