<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NORTH TELLS JURY OF PLAN FOR BUSH</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="334612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IRAN-CONTRA AFFAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSTON, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORTH, OLIVER L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">POINDEXTER, JOHN M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DB103DF937A25750C0A966958260" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NORTH TELLS JURY OF PLAN FOR BUSH</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSTON, DAVID</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Oliver L. North today confirmed a long-suspected but hazy footnote to the Iran-contra affair: that officials of the Reagan Administration had considered sending Vice President George Bush as an emissary to Iran in early 1986.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Oliver L. North today confirmed a long-suspected but hazy footnote to the Iran-contra affair: that officials of the Reagan Administration had considered sending Vice President George Bush as an emissary to Iran in early 1986.</p>
        <p>Oliver L. North today confirmed a long-suspected but hazy footnote to the Iran-contra affair: that officials of the Reagan Administration had considered sending Vice President George Bush as an emissary to Iran in early 1986.</p>
        <p>Testifying in the Iran-contra trial of John M. Poindexter, the former national security adviser, Mr. North said that two or three people discussed such a trip ''to arrange for a higher-level official, a senior-level official, perhaps even the Vice President, to meet with the senior leadership of Iran.''</p>
        <p>The mention of Mr. Bush came as Mr. North, a former aide to the National Security Council, testified about a February 1986 computer message about the trip that he sent to Robert C. McFarlane, who preceded Mr. Poindexter as security adviser under Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>Mr. North said he did not tell Mr. Poindexter, a former Navy rear admiral, about the message concerning his advance visit because ''I thought the trip was worth the risk, the admiral didn't.''</p>
        <p>There had been oblique references during the Iran-contra investigation by Congress that Mr. Bush had been considered as an emissary to Iran while he was Vice President. Mr. North's testimony today appeared to be the clearest indication that members of the National Security Council staff wanted Mr. Bush to take on the mission.</p>
        <p>North and McFarlane to Iran</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush never made such a trip. In May 1986, Mr. North. a former Marine lieutenant colonel, and Mr. McFarlane, who was acting as special consultant on arms sale to Iran, secretly flew to Iran, hoping to win the release of American hostages held in Lebanon by militants aligned with Iran. The mission failed to win the release of any hostages.</p>
        <p>The White House had no comment on Mr. North's remarks. ''We have had a longstanding policy of not commenting on anything from the Poindexter trial,'' said Stephen Hart, a White House spokesman.</p>
        <p>Richard W. Beckler, the chief defense lawyer, in his cross-examination of Mr. North, sought to use the message to show that Mr. North withheld important activities from Mr. Poindexter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Poindexter faces five felony charges, including accusations that he engaged in conspiracy, obstructed Congressional inquiries and made false statements to lawmakers about the arms sales and efforts to aid the Nicaraguan rebels at a time when Congress had banned direct aid. The maximum penalty for all the charges is 25 years in prison and fines of $1.25 million.</p>
        <p>North Again Suggested Trip</p>
        <p>Mr. Beckler also suggested that Mr. Poindexter was excluded from Mr. North's initial efforts to assist Israel in selling arms to Iran and was not told about all of Mr. North's actions to assist the Nicaragua rebels in 1984 and 1985.</p>
        <p>Mr. North has not previously said in such explicit terms that he wanted Mr. Bush to visit Teheran. Mr. North suggested such a trip again in November 1986, according to a previously undisclosed computer message obtained by The New York Times. ''We are looking at having Bush go to Eur/M.E. as special emissary to explain policy,'' said the message sent Nov. 20, 1986, to Richard V. Secord, the former Air Force major general who helped in the arms sales to Iran and the diversion of some of the proceeds to the Nicaraguan rebels.</p>
        <p>After the Iran-contra affair was disclosed, Mr. Bush said that he had supported the arms sales to ''open a channel to Iran.''</p>
        <p>In 1987, a spokesman for President Reagan said that Mr. Bush had expressed reservations about the Iran initiative, but remained loyal to Mr. Reagan's policy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Poindexter is the second national security adviser from the Reagan White House to face charges in the Iran-contra affair. Last March Mr. McFarlane pleaded guilty to misdeamenor charges of withholding information from Congress. The national security adviser is among the most senior Presidential advisers, responsible for counseling the President on a wide range of national security affairs.</p>
        <p>Note Hinted That Reagan Knew</p>
        <p>In his questioning, Mr. Beckler also referred to a handwritten note by Mr. Poindexter on a July 1986 memorandum indicating that he told Mr. Reagan about a shipment of Hawk missile spare parts in 1986 that had generated what Mr. Beckler called ''extra money.''</p>
        <p>The document, which was not made public, suggested that Mr. Reagan was informed that the Iranians were paying much more for the weapons than the Department of Defense actually charged. The surplus provided the millions of dollars ultimately diverted to the contras.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Reagan has insisted that he did not know the arms sales had produced extra funds or that he knew of the diversion of proceeds to the contras.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beckler also challenged Mr. North's credibility by pointing out inconsistencies between his testimony as a prosecution witness and his earlier statements made under oath about Mr. Poindexter's role in the affair. After completing two days of testimony on Monday, Mr. North responded today to defense questions.</p>
        <p>He will resume testifying on Wednesday before the Federal District Court jury and Judge Harold H. Greene.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
