<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Subway Fares and Tempers Rise, And Riders Brace for Bedlam</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="808728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSIT SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES (FARES, FEES AND RATES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUBWAYS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TOKENS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4DB1539F930A25752C1A963958260" item-length="1505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Subway Fares and Tempers Rise, And Riders Brace for Bedlam</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long lines at token booths, confusion over the mathematics and widespread exasperation bedeviled New York City's transit system and tens of thousands of riders yesterday as an on-again, off-again fare increase went into effect, at least temporarily. The matter goes back to Federal court tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Difficult as it was yesterday, straphanger advocates and transit officials said the real crisis was expected with the start of the work week this morning as millions of subway and bus riders seeking tiny new tokens lay siege to the city's 468 subway stations. For anyone without them, a nightmare was likely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Long lines at token booths, confusion over the mathematics and widespread exasperation bedeviled New York City's transit system and tens of thousands of riders yesterday as an on-again, off-again fare increase went into effect, at least temporarily. The matter goes back to Federal court tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Difficult as it was yesterday, straphanger advocates and transit officials said the real crisis was expected with the start of the work week this morning as millions of subway and bus riders seeking tiny new tokens lay siege to the city's 468 subway stations. For anyone without them, a nightmare was likely.</p>
        <p>It's ridiculous," Ann Mancano said as she shivered in the cold on a serpentine line of 120 people that encircled the station at 72d Street and Broadway in Manhattan. "We're standing on line to pay more money. Tomorrow is going to be real bedlam."</p>
        <p>After months of protests, blame-laying, rescue efforts and a last-ditch, still-pending lawsuit against the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, subway  and bus fares jumped 25 cents to $1.50 at 12:01 A.M. yesterday. In raw size, it  was the largest increase in the system's history, and a 20 percent jump that was the biggest since 1984.</p>
        <p>Fares on the Long Island Rail Road and theMetro-North Commuter Railroad also  went up yesterday, by an average of 9 percent, but most commuters buy monthly passes and will not feel the pinch until they buy December tickets.</p>
        <p>For subway and bus riders, however, the effect was immediate and painful. New tokens went on sale at all stations, but advance sales had been restricted for budgetary reasons to certain hours at certain stations, and the result was an enormous abrupt demand for tokens -- and an imbroglio at scores of stations.</p>
        <p>On a sleepy Sunday, when token-buying is normally a snap, lines stretched across mezzanines, snaked up stairwells and curled out onto sidewalks. Clerks, generally not known for croupier-like skills, sold new tokens and fare cards, swapped old tokens and cash for new ones, juggled conversion tables, answered questions and tried to cope with a rising tide of impatience.</p>
        <p>No one was arrested for misbehavior, the police said, but for many on both sides of the bulletproof glass it was a losing game.</p>
        <p>At the Continental Avenue-71st Street station in Forest Hills, 190 people were in a barely moving queue at 11 A.M., shifting weight from foot to foot, swapping tales of transit woe and glaring at a token seller who defiantly ate a  sandwich while her colleague snapped at complainants who had waited an hour in line, some to buy only a token or two.</p>
        <p>"This is a terrible example of public service," Fred Gelber, a manager with the Social Security Administration, said after watching 45 minutes tick away at  the Forest Hills station. "They're not providing enough agents. Only one agent is working. I can imagine what tomorrow will be like."</p>
        <p>Nearby, Sam Berman, a fashion industry sales manager, was trying to avoid the Monday crush, but had come out merely to find a Sunday crush. "It's a loss of basic common sense," he said as frustrations brimmed. "I'm being ripped off. The transit system is out of whack with the rest of the city. People have other things to do than wait in line 45 minutes."</p>
        <p>Clerks, too, were suffering. "Do I look like I have a headache?" one said at  Borough Park, Brooklyn. "I should, because I do." Since 6 A.M., a steady stream  of demanding, unappreciative, sometimes rude people had peppered her with anger, sarcasm and silly questions, she said. A moment later, she told a bewildered patron: "No, the fare didn't go down. It went up."</p>
        <p>A quick survey of stations in Manhattan between 1 and 2 P.M. found 100 people in two lines at 72d Street and Broadway, and 35 more at 79th Street. Across town on the Lexington Avenue line, 53 people waited on a single line at 68th Street,  61 people queued up at two windows at 77th Street, and 172 people waited on three lines at 86th Street.</p>
        <p>The seller's market was stunningly apparent on a northbound No. 1 train last  night when a derelict in a filthy orange quilted jacket -- persona non-grata on  any other day of the year -- began selling new tokens for $1 each. A woman went up, cautiously, found the tokens apparently legitimate and bought a few. Then others approached and began buying. No questions asked.</p>
        <p>With 100 people in line ahead of him at the Columbus Circle station, Peter Kiczek, a 27-year-old accountant, exclaimed: "Eight million people and nobody bought any tokens."</p>
        <p>It was not quite that bad. But the Transit Authority, which has 5 million subway and bus riders every weekday, said only 1 million new tokens had been sold in advance, and it appeared likely that token booths this morning would be  swamped.</p>
        <p>"We anticipate a lot of people buying tokens Monday," said Jared Lebow, a transit spokesman. He noted that Monday mornings were normally the busiest time  for token sales, that heavy sales and confusion were bound to attend a fare increase with new tokens, and he offered some advice for buyers.</p>
        <p>Try less busy stations, he said, and use a Metrocard if possible; machines will simply deduct $1.50 instead of $1.25. Extra token sellers are to be on duty at major stations, he said, including those at Times Square, Penn Station, Grand Central Terminal, 72d Street and Broadway, Archer Avenue in Jamaica and Main Street in Flushing.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, he said, vending machines have not yet been stocked with the new tokens, and most newstands and other non-transit vendors will also probably  not have them by this morning. Further restricting the flow, many turnstiles had not been altered to accept the new token; they still had tape over the token slots.</p>
        <p>Many transit riders yesterday reiterated complaints about the size of the fare increase at a time of diminishing service. "The more you put money out, the worse it gets," said Hans Elie, a Manhattan Community College student who lives  in Rosedale, Queens, and must pay two fares each way every day. "Right now, I don't know how to express myself because I'm so upset."</p>
        <p>After a year of diminishing city, state and Federal aid for the transit and commuter lines and months of warnings that fare increases -- and service cuts -- were the only way out, the M.T.A.'s trustees voted on Oct. 19 to raise all the fares. New tokens with pentagonal holes in the center were authorized to prevent hoarding of the old tokens.</p>
        <p>E. Virgil Conway, the M.T.A. chairman, said the increases were needed to balance the authority's $5 billion budget and help finance a five-year capital construction program. Opponents responded with a campaign of noisy protests and  packed public hearings, criticizing the agency, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and Gov. George E. Pataki, all to no avail.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 21, the New York Urban League and the Straphangers Campaign, a rider  advocacy group, filed a Federal civil rights suit charging that the fare plan -- a 20 percent increase for predominantly black and Hispanic subway and bus riders and a 9 percent rise for mainly white commuters on the suburban rail lines -- was racially discriminatory.</p>
        <p>The plaintiffs charged not only that the M.T.A. had divided its resources unfairly, but that the state was unfair in its allocation of transit aid. They asked for an injunction to block the increase until a trial could be held.</p>
        <p>Last Wednesday, Judge Robert P. Patterson Jr. of Federal Court in Manhattan granted an injunction to block the fare increases, ruling that the transit plan  appeared to be discriminatory under the 1964 Civil Rights Act.</p>
        <p>The M.T.A. quickly appealed, and on Thursday a three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit set the injunction aside temporarily. It ruled that the increase could take place, at least until the</p>
        <p>hearing set for tomorrow could consider whether riders would be irreparably harmed by paying a $1.50 fare while awaiting the outcome of the case.</p>
        <p>The appeals court did not address the underlying issue of whether the fare increases discriminate against black and Hispanic riders. It is expected tomorrow to hear arguments only on whether to roll back the fare to $1.25 until  the larger questions are decided. Should it ultimately lose, the M.T.A. has offered a refund plan: two free-ride days for every seven days of overcharges.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
