<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Squatters Killed in Fire In Deserted Bed-Stuy Building</title>
    <meta content="18FIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/18/nyregion/18FIRE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1536282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E3DC1E38F93BA25752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Squatters Killed in Fire In Deserted Bed-Stuy Building</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Squatters Killed in Fire in Deserted Bed-Stuy Building</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Unidentified homeless couple dies in electrical fire at Bedford-Stuyvesant (NYC) city-owned building (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A homeless couple died in an electrical fire early yesterday in the city-owned building in Bedford-Stuyvesant where they squatted, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The fire appeared to have started in faulty wiring, and was not considered suspicious, said Lt. Brian Burke, a police spokesman. Neighbors said that the building had no power, but that the couple had been poaching electricity from a streetlight out front.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A homeless couple died in an electrical fire early yesterday in the city-owned building in Bedford-Stuyvesant where they squatted, the authorities said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A homeless couple died in an electrical fire early yesterday in the city-owned building in Bedford-Stuyvesant where they squatted, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The fire appeared to have started in faulty wiring, and was not considered suspicious, said Lt. Brian Burke, a police spokesman. Neighbors said that the building had no power, but that the couple had been poaching electricity from a streetlight out front.</p>
        <p>The man and woman, who died of smoke inhalation, had not been identified as of yesterday afternoon, said Ellen Borakove, a spokeswoman for the city medical examiner.</p>
        <p>To get inside the building on Martin Luther King Jr. Place, neighbors said, the couple had climbed atop a baby stroller in the playground of Junior High School 33 next door, then on top of a concrete wall, under a chain-link fence, and into a hole in the back of the sealed building, though no one seemed to know exactly where.</p>
        <p>They collected bottles to redeem for cash, and clothes they could sell, and left few traces, the neighbors said.</p>
        <p>One neighbor who would not give his name said that the man was known as Little Mike, because he was only about 5 feet 4 inches tall. ''My friend just died in there,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''They were always collecting cans,'' he said of the dead couple. He said Mike was about 43, had grown up in the neighborhood, had children, and used to work for the city, in sanitation or construction.</p>
        <p>''He was a nice guy, a very nice person,'' the man said. ''Very humble.''</p>
        <p>''That was their stepladder,'' he said, pointing to the baby stroller.</p>
        <p>The couple moved in last summer, said Ronald Stevens, who often visits his father on the block.</p>
        <p>''They would come out in the morning, with a stroller or a shopping cart, go down the street, and fill it with clothes and bottles,'' Mr. Stevens said. He said the police had put the couple out of the house last summer, although a police spokeswoman could not confirm that information.</p>
        <p>There are only three residential buildings on the short block, as well as Public School 297 and Stockton Park. The two other apartment buildings have recently been renovated, but the brick four-story building that burned had been boarded up, with skull-and-crossbone signs on the front saying, ''Keep Out, Poison Baited, Rodents.'' It used to house four families, Mr. Stevens said, then it was marked for demolition, then was up for auction, and then was boarded up.</p>
        <p>Across the street from the building, Winston Bunbury, a worker at Stockton Park, said he never knew anybody was living there. ''And we're in this park every single day,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His co-worker, Natarcha Wright, said, ''Had they fixed that building up, that never would've happened,'' referring to the fire.</p>
        <p>Carol Abrams, the spokeswoman for the city's Department of Housing Preservation and Development, said that the building had been vacant since December 1997, and that there was no history of squatters there. She said that vacant properties acquired through tax delinquency were inspected monthly, and that the building had last been inspected on Nov. 7, when it was properly sealed.</p>
        <p>A worker for the department was shoveling burnt debris from the front of the building. The skeleton of a mattress lay on the sidewalk.</p>
        <p>There were no reports of the building being broken into, and an iron gate had covered the front door, said Chester Ricketts, a project manager for the housing department. The building is structurally sound, and plans are to seal it up again and install a new gate, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
