<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nanny Freed on Bail in Infant's Death</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="603556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NANNIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RYE (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERGER, JOSEPH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANKLIN, ANN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNNE, KIERAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D61F3AF933A15757C0A965958260" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nanny Freed on Bail in Infant's Death</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH BERGER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERGER, JOSEPH</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A nanny charged with the murder of the 10-month-old infant in her care was freed on bail today amid several new disclosures about the strengths and weaknesses of the case against her.</p>
        <p>With her parents, three sisters and her brother seated solemnly in the courtroom, Ann Franklin stood stiffly through the half-hour hearing as Judge Emmett J. Murphy reduced her bail from $500,000 to $250,000. At times, her lips quivered and her eyes blinked nervously.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A nanny charged with the murder of the 10-month-old infant in her care was freed on bail today amid several new disclosures about the strengths and weaknesses of the case against her.</p>
        <p>With her parents, three sisters and her brother seated solemnly in the courtroom, Ann Franklin stood stiffly through the half-hour hearing as Judge Emmett J. Murphy reduced her bail from $500,000 to $250,000. At times, her lips quivered and her eyes blinked nervously.</p>
        <p>The new amount was one her parents could afford to post. Shortly after 3 P.M., Ms. Franklin, in a county car, arrived at her clapboard home in Rye, N.Y., to sometimes tearful embraces from a dozen relatives and her boyfriend, Martin Curran.</p>
        <p>As a requirement of the bail, Ms. Franklin was fitted with an electronic ankle bracelet that allows officials to monitor her movements. She also turned over her passport. To keep her from fleeing, her parents pledged a home they valued at $700,000 and their savings. Defense Arguments</p>
        <p>Kieran Dunne died March 3 of several skull fractures in the rear and side of his head that he suffered a week earlier.</p>
        <p>The ruling today disappointed the dead infant's two grandmothers, who were in the courtroom, and his parents, David and Peggy Leahy Dunne, who were informed at work.</p>
        <p>"I'm very upset and so is my husband," Mrs. Dunne said. "She's free and my baby's dead."</p>
        <p>In arguing for a bail reduction at the Westchester County Courthouse, Ms. Franklin's lawyer, Michael Romano, disclosed that the police laboratory tests have so far not been able to tie any of the objects in the Dunne home to the blows that caused the infant's death. Prosecutors, in arguing that Kieran was killed by Ms. Franklin, have acknowledged they could not say whether Kieran was struck with a fist or blunt object or against a wall or floor.</p>
        <p>Asserting that the prosecution was based on "speculation and conjecture," Mr. Romano argued that the county medical examiner did not list the cause of death as a homicide until a month after the completion of the autopsy. That time lapse, he contended, gave the police time to influence the autopsy report.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the Dunne family today contradicted several statements the baby sitter had made to the police. Ms. Franklin told the police that she had not been able to reach Kieran's mother on Feb. 25 to say something was wrong with Kieran, but Mrs. Dunne said in an interview today that there were no messages from the baby sitter on her office voice mail during the late afternoon.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Dunne said that she spoke to Ms. Franklin at 4:40 P.M. on that day as she was about to go home from her job as a project manager in the business departments of The New York Times. Ms. Franklin told her the baby was doing fine, she said.</p>
        <p>She did not learn that something was amiss until she walked up the driveway of her Rye home around 6 P.M. and saw a police car parked there. Ms. Franklin told her that Kieran had suffered a seizure she could not explain and that he had been taken to United Hospital Medical Center in Port Chester.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Dunne said Ms. Franklin accompanied her to the hospital, but when she learned from doctors that Kieran had suffered serious head injuries, she asked a relative to tell Ms. Franklin to go home.</p>
        <p>Ms. Franklin told the police during an interrogation that Kieran had appeared lethargic during his last day at home and "was not himself." 'We Need Answers'</p>
        <p>But Kieran's grandmother Margaret Dunne told reporters after court today that Kieran had seemed cheerful and playful when she saw him early in the afternoon of Feb. 25. Kieran's parents had moved into David's parents' house two weeks before the baby suffered his fatal injuries because they were planning to sell their co-op and buy a house.</p>
        <p>"I always called him my Bonny Baby," Margaret Dunne said. "I'd say, jokingly, 'How come I never had one like him.' He was incredible, smiling, very smart and loved to play games."</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Romano had tried to create the impression that Kieran could have injured himself on the hardwood floors of the grandmother's house, Margaret Dunne said Kieran could neither walk nor stand up, and the house was fully carpeted.</p>
        <p>"The bottom line is that Kieran died in her care," Margaret Dunne said. "She injured him, murdered him. She murdered him and we need answers."</p>
        <p>In arguing against a bail reduction, the prosecutor, Maryellen Martirano, tried to show that Ms. Franklin was about to flee. She revealed that a plane reservation in the name of J. Franklin had been made for a 7 P.M. Aer Lingus flight on April 15 and suddenly canceled. Ms. Franklin was arraigned on April 14. But Ms. Martirano acknowledged that detectives were investigating whether the J. Franklin who made the reservation was Ms. Franklin's father, John, or an unrelated person with the same last name and first initial.</p>
        <p>To help his case, Mr. Romano, who served for eight years as a prosecutor and assistant chief of the trial bureau in Westchester County, brought in Christopher Rush, a private investigator. He helped in the defense of Olivia Riner, a Swiss au pair who was charged with burning to death the baby in her care, but was acquitted. The defense created a plausible theory for the baby's death that exculpated Ms. Riner.</p>
        <p>The main difficulty Ms. Franklin faces is that something happened to Kieran between 2:20 P.M. when he was seen by his grandfather David Leahy and 5:15 P.M. when the police were called. And Ms. Franklin was the only one with him during those hours.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors will have to prove how Ms. Franklin contributed to the baby's death. If Mr. Romano can create a number of possible hypotheses that will support the possibility of Ms. Franklin's innocence and the prosecutors cannot contradict those, the jury may not be inclined to find her guilty.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Kieran's family announced today that they have set up a foundation to aid organizations that protect children. Donations should be sent to the Kieran David Dunne Foundation, P.O. Box 747, Rye, N.Y. 10580.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
