<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alienation, Minimalism, Solidity And Ritual</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="822896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BALLET REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK, NY, USA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY BALLET</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KISSELGOFF, ANNA WILLIAM FORSYTHE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PHILIP GLASS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JEROME ROBBINS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7DE1139F936A25752C0A960958260" item-length="481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alienation, Minimalism, Solidity And Ritual</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KISSELGOFF, ANNA WILLIAM FORSYTHE;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jerome Robbins's "Glass Pieces" and William Forsythe's "Behind the China Dogs," two ballets with a contemporary tone, were given by the New York City Ballet for the first time this season on Friday night.</p>
        <p>The entire program at the New York State Theater was part of a New Generation series, predicated on the debatable premise that certain ballets to 20th-century music, if divorced from tutus, can look hip to a young audience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jerome Robbins's "Glass Pieces" and William Forsythe's "Behind the China Dogs," two ballets with a contemporary tone, were given by the New York City Ballet for the first time this season on Friday night.</p>
        <p>The entire program at the New York State Theater was part of a New Generation series, predicated on the debatable premise that certain ballets to 20th-century music, if divorced from tutus, can look hip to a young audience.</p>
        <p>In this instance, fortunately, the combination of works and outstanding performances had the house crackling with excitement. Peter Martins's latest ballet, "Reliquary," had the requisite streamlined sophistication. Conducted, as it was at its premiere on Jan. 4, by its composer, Charles Wuorinen, "Reliquary" pays tribute to the pioneering genre that New Generation celebrates: the futuristic "leotard" ballets choreographed by George Balanchine to Stravinsky's  music.</p>
        <p>The second work was Mr. Martins's first ballet, the 1977 "Calcium Light Night," danced to Charles Ives with a much-improved young cast, Cara Copeland and Edward Liang. With its alienated aura, expressed through formal structures,  "Calcium" owes something to Robbins.</p>
        <p>Even the 1983 "Glass Pieces," ostensibly an exploration of Philip Glass's Minimalist music, is colored by Mr. Robbins's eternal concern with human relationships. Only his genius could give Glass's music a classical image by anchoring an entire dance work in a classical pas de deux.</p>
        <p>The core of his ballet, then, is the duet danced with solidity and mystery by Lourdes Lopes and Ben Huys. Sculptural in their profile poses, fearful in their  fugitive glances, tender in their flowing embraces, they provided the ecstasy and emotion that contrasted with the ingenious ticker-tape line of women behind  them.</p>
        <p>Alone in a modern world, this pair is presaged by the three couples who jump  in and out of the colorful traffic jam that Mr. Robbins choreographed in the first section. Unlike the modern-dance choreographers who turned to Glass before he did, Mr. Robbins did not create modular blocks of movement. In his hands, repetitive movement becomes expressive. Even the third section, to a strong drum rhythm, suggests ritual games of seduction and abduction.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere is very much a part of Mr. Forsythe's game playing in "Behind the  China Dogs." Although too long, his stop-and-go bursts of classroom steps are brilliantly channeled into dramatic attitudinizing.</p>
        <p>Nilas Martins, in a debut, was all clarity as the angular antihero surrounded by a cast dancing deliberately off center with ferocity and enthusiasm. The others were Helene Alexopoulos, Peter Boal, Albert Evans, Tom Gold, Judith Fugate, Wendy Whelan and Monique Meunier. Leslie Stuck's electronic distortion of a Louis Armstrong recording helped, and Cara Perlman's onstage statues of five dogs fit right into the non sequiturs of a theatrical happening.</p>
        <p>BALLET REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
