<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Probation, With House Calls; Paterson Adds Health Care to Juvenile System</title>
    <meta content="16DOCT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/16/nyregion/16doctors.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1597071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">St Joseph's Regional Medical Center (Paterson, NJ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paterson (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Richard Lezin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pruden, James N (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krieger, John V (Chief)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DF153AF935A25754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Probation, With House Calls; Paterson Adds Health Care to Juvenile System</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Probation, With House Calls</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD LEZIN JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Richard Lezin</byline>
      <dateline>PATERSON, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hundreds of juvenile offenders in Paterson, NJ, receive visits from doctors and nurses along with their probation officers; Dr James N Pruden and nurses from Joseph' s Regional Medical Center volunteer their time to give checkups to youngsters and, sometimes, their families; recividism rate has been reduced from 37 percent to just over 5 percent since start of program in 1999; Chief John V Krieger of Passaic County Probation Division, who conceived program, believes it shows youths a more caring side of system; program costs $150,000 and is paid for by grant from state attorney general's office; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Benjamin said that he expected the probing, no-nonsense questions from his probation officer: Where were you when I stopped by earlier? You remember your curfew, right? You're not down with that gang anymore?</p>
        <p>What the 17-year-old didn't expect were the concerned questions that would follow, not from his tough-minded probation officer but by the avuncular physician who accompanied the officer on the visit to David's home: How' s your blood pressure? Are you feeling dizzy? How are those headaches?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several hundred juvenile offenders in Paterson, N.J., receive free home health care visits as part of their probation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Benjamin said that he expected the probing, no-nonsense questions from his probation officer: Where were you when I stopped by earlier? You remember your curfew, right? You're not down with that gang anymore?</p>
        <p>What the 17-year-old didn't expect were the concerned questions that would follow, not from his tough-minded probation officer but by the avuncular physician who accompanied the officer on the visit to David's home: How' s your blood pressure? Are you feeling dizzy? How are those headaches?</p>
        <p>''You're going to have headaches for a long time,'' said the physician, Dr. James N. Pruden, who explained that David was suffering from post-concussion syndrome, but tried to lighten the mood when he noticed the youngster turn downcast at the news. ''But I still think you're going to live.'' He paused. ''Just not forever.'' Both doctor and patient smiled.</p>
        <p>David is one of several hundred juvenile offenders in Paterson who, as part of their probation, receive free home health care visits from Dr. Pruden and a team of nurses from St. Joseph's Regional Medical Centerhere. Dr. Pruden and the nurses, who all volunteer their time for the monthly consultations, accompany probation officers on home visits, answering questions, dispensing medical advice and offering cursory checkups to youngsters and, sometimes, their family members.</p>
        <p>But it is not just altruism at work here. Paterson juvenile justice officials hope that something as simple as reaching out to those on probation in a gentler way might help reduce the number of repeat offenders.</p>
        <p>According to the county's statistics, the visits -- which are part of a program called the Village Initiative (as in, ''It takes a village'') -- might be showing some promise in cutting recidivism. In the five years since the program began, recidivism rates that once hovered around 37 percent have fallen to just over 5 percent for those who receive visits.</p>
        <p>Although those involved with juvenile probation concede that a more in-depth analysis must be done before a direct cause-and-effect relationship can be drawn between the visits and the decrease, they are encouraged by what they have seen.</p>
        <p>''This stuff is hard to quantify,'' said Chief John V. Krieger of the Passaic County Probation Division. ''But I ask myself, 'Why is the rate as low as we've ever seen it?'''</p>
        <p>Whatever the debate over the effectiveness of the visits, there can be no question that the doctor's presence shows a different face of a system that often seems to care about these children only when they misbehave.</p>
        <p>''These children are in a position where the system is coming down pretty hard on them,'' Dr. Pruden said. ''Now, they see the other side. It becomes less of a cold, uncaring, police-state situation and more of a 'Look, we care.'''</p>
        <p>This marriage of handcuffs and stethoscopes was the brainchild of Chief Krieger as an effort to reach some of the county's most troubled youngsters and alter their path of self-destruction, whether it is involvement in gangs, as in David's case, or drug use.</p>
        <p>The idea, Chief Krieger said, was to identify what was going wrong in the lives of youngsters on probation before they decide to commit another offense. For many of the teenagers, who often live in communities where the push and pull of poverty and drugs is ever present, the visits give officials another entryway into the lives of youngsters whom they serve.</p>
        <p>Last year, the medical team made about 250 home visits. The $150,000 cost of running the program is financed through grants from the office of the New Jersey attorney general, Peter C. Harvey.</p>
        <p>''It's a holistic approach,'' Chief Krieger said.</p>
        <p>And one of the reasons why officials say that approach seems to be working is the work of Dr. Pruden and the nurses. On a recent Friday, the medical team and the probation officers set out in a caravan from the Probation Division offices and began wending their way through the night.</p>
        <p>The first stop was the narrow second-floor apartment on 18th Street where David Benjamin lives. In April, during a stay at a juvenile detention center, he was attacked by a few members of a gang that is the rival of one in his neighborhood. With a single punch from David's blind side, a boy drove his head into the floor.</p>
        <p>He does not remember much between then and waking up in the hospital, vomiting. Now, just over two months later, he still has intense headaches.</p>
        <p>After exchanging introductions, David sits in a rocking chair and Dr. Pruden starts with a series of tests -- follow my finger with your eye; lift your left leg -- and questions about the weeks since David's injury.</p>
        <p>''How long were you out?'' the doctor asks, referring to the time David was unconscious after he was struck.</p>
        <p>''They told me a couple of minutes,'' David replied.</p>
        <p>''How many times did you vomit?'' Dr. Pruden asks.</p>
        <p>''The whole day I was in the hospital,'' the youngster replied. ''I was spitting up blood.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Pruden stretches a stethoscope to David's chest. Both of them are in jeans and T-shirts -- the uniform of a generation for David, camouflage for the doctor. David confides that although he had a CAT scan several weeks ago at a local hospital, he's still worried about his recovery.</p>
        <p>He received the results of the scan -- several typed pages -- but found them confusing and never saw a doctor to discuss them. He asks Dr. Pruden to take a look.</p>
        <p>For a few minutes the conversation turns to zygomatic fractures and the rates at which bones heal, but after a few minutes of reviewing the scan results the doctor offers a prognosis that is easy enough to understand: David will be fine. The lanky teenager, who had seemed worried and nervous for much of the visit, visibly relaxes.</p>
        <p>And although the medical team is there to assuage many of the probationers' health concerns, that does not mean they are necessarily treated with kid gloves. At one point during the visit -- shortly after Dr. Pruden and a nurse, Barbara Koegel, packed up an electronic blood pressure gauge -- a member of the probation team, Sonia Valentin, pressed David on his gang membership.</p>
        <p>''No more,'' Ms. Valentin said, ''right?''</p>
        <p>David, silent, nodded.</p>
        <p>''You can be real with me,'' she said, insistent.</p>
        <p>''I am being real with you,'' he replied, defensively, a hint of an edge in his voice.</p>
        <p>''Good,'' she said, ''because that brought you nothing but problems.''</p>
        <p>He nodded again, sheepishly.</p>
        <p>Later, framed by a half-dozen posters of Tupac Shakur in his room, David said that he appreciated the visits, but Dr. Pruden did not hear him. He was already headed down the stairs to his next appointment.</p>
        <p>There will be many probationers to see this night. At one visit, the team encountered a 16-year-old who is eight months pregnant with her second child. At another, they checked on a probationer's grandmother who complained of a serious shoulder strain. At each stop, Dr. Pruden was sent off with handshakes, embraces, and words of thanks.</p>
        <p>In the end, though, perhaps it was Ashley Orr who paid Dr. Pruden the highest compliment in the lexicon of 17-year-olds when he nodded in the direction of the departing physician and said simply, ''He's cool.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
