<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INTO THE HEART OF OLD ALBANY</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="147358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOYLE, T CORAGHESSAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, WILLIAM</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">QUINN'S BOOK (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED61338F931A15756C0A96E948260" item-length="2377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INTO THE HEART OF OLD ALBANY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By T. CORAGHESSAN BOYLE; T. Coraghessan Boyle's most recent novel, ''World's End,'' won this year's PEN/Faulkner award. His new collection of stories, ''Sorry Fugu,'' will be published next year.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOYLE, T CORAGHESSAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  QUINN'S BOOK  By William Kennedy.  289 pp. New York:  Viking. $18.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  QUINN'S BOOK  By William Kennedy.  289 pp. New York:  Viking. $18.95.</p>
        <p>QUINN'S BOOK  By William Kennedy.  289 pp. New York:  Viking. $18.95.</p>
        <p>In the opening chapter of ''O Albany!,'' William Kennedy's rich and vastly entertaining chronicle of his hometown, the author gives us a tongue-in-cheek account of Albany's literary associations, ranging farther and farther afield until he ends with the observation that ''Hemingway married Martha Gellhorn, who used to work on the  [ Albany ]  Times Union, and William Faulkner died unaware that Albany existed.'' Maybe so. But after the now legendary success of Kennedy's Albany cycle - ''Legs'' (1975), ''Billy Phelan's Greatest Game'' (1978) and ''Ironweed'' (1983) - and the 1984 reissue of ''The Ink Truck,'' the historic little city on the Hudson is as firmly established in the literary geography as Joyce's Dublin or Faulkner's own Yoknapatawpha County.</p>
        <p>''Quinn's Book,'' like its predecessors, is set in Albany. The action spans a period of 15 years, from 1849 to 1864, a particularly tumultuous time not only for Albany but for the country at large; the Civil War, the New York draft riots and the workings of the Underground Railroad are all given play here. Against this historical backdrop, the narrator and protagonist, Daniel Quinn, struggles to liberate himself from ''life's caprice,'' establish his career as a journalist and win the hand of Maud Fallon, a heroine as magical and elusive as Dickens's Estella. Indeed, ''Quinn's Book'' does have a decidedly Dickensian flavor to it, particularly in the opening chapters. As the book begins, Quinn is a 14-year-old orphan, his parents and sister having succumbed to the cholera epidemic of the preceding year. Like Dickens's child heroes, Daniel is at the mercy of the adult world, apprenticed first to a canal man who beats him and refuses to pay his wages and then to a boatman, John the Brawn McGee, who, while less brutal, is hardly more scrupulous.</p>
        <p>Together, McGee and Daniel come to the aid of La Ultima, a renowned danseuse-courtesan, who piques the fates by trying to cross the ice-swollen Hudson in December. A floe crushes the skiff, and down go La Ultima, her maid and her 12-year-old niece, Maud Fallon.</p>
        <p>While the mercenary McGee recovers the courtesan's precious baggage and apparently lifeless self (''One dead slut,'' he says, hauling her aboard with his boat hook), Daniel rescues Maud. ''It's you who have first right to my life,'' she tells him, and thus begins the love affair that becomes central to Daniel's life and the book's development.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Kennedy manages brilliantly to evoke Dickens, he does so through a sensibility informed by the age of Gabriel Garcia Marquez and the school of magic realism. La Ultima (a k a Magdalena Colon) is a character of such fine, lusty and absurd proportions that she might have wandered into town with the gypsy troupe from ''One Hundred Years of Solitude'': '' 'It eees a pleasure to meet a rrreal mon,' she said in her fraudulent, Hispanicized English (she was of Hibernian stock and spoke the language perfectly).'' Her twitting of the powers that be brings instant retribution and cataclysmic woe down upon the heads of Albany's hapless citizens. No sooner have Quinn and McGee returned to the pier with Maud and the inanimate Ultima than the span itself collapses, plunging ''a hundred or more'' into the torrent.</p>
        <p>And no sooner do the renewed rescue efforts begin than an even greater disaster strikes - a towering wall of ice plugs the river, builds rapidly to a glassy pyramid and then blasts loose in ''a Vesuvius of crystal, showering the shores of both Albany and Greenbush  [ across the river ]  with fragments, wounding an unsuspecting half-dozen people, killing two horses and a pregnant cat on the quay, and loosing a tidal wave that swept away'' the whole business - goods, boats, pier and people. But worse! The rising waters then creep into the warehouses along the shore, slaking the lime stored there and starting a fire that ravages the waterfront. All this is sustained in a comic tour de force of piggy-backing disasters, ''the gods gone mad'' indeed.</p>
        <p>Quinn, John the Brawn McGee and Maud manage to escape this scene of devastation, John hauling La Ultima's corpse and baggage with him. Maud, remarkably self-possessed considering what she's been through, directs them to the mansion of Hillegond Staats, widow of Petrus, a man who traced his lineage to the time of the patroon. Hillegond is a capacious woman, in physique and spirit both, and she takes them all in, though Maud's only connection to her is tenuous: she and La Ultima had stayed with Hillegond during their last tour of Albany. It is here, in the dood-kamer, or ''dead chamber,'' of this ancient and august mansion, that La Ultima is laid out. No need to mourn her, though. For John the Brawn, besides being broad of back and opportunistic, seems to be something of a necrophiliac as well.</p>
        <p>In a bawdy and very funny scene, he manages to resuscitate La Ultima through the act of coitus, and she comes alive in his arms. Aroused, Hillegond joins in, while, unbeknownst to the participants, Quinn and the prepubescent Maud look on. A short time later, after witnessing a second and even more astonishing resurrection, Maud and Quinn fling themselves at each other in a fury of oscular passion, until they are rudely separated by a scandalized Ultima. The separation is emblematic of their relationship, which is not resolved till the last page of the novel.</p>
        <p>It is this house, the Staats mansion, around which the remainder of the book revolves. Quinn and his friends become Hillegond's guests during the period of La Ultima's recovery, and, as a result, the young Daniel gets his first taste of newspaper work, which will become his education and profession both. Through Hillegond, he meets Will Canaday, the heroic and high-principled editor of The Albany Chronicle, and discovers a surrogate father and a home as well. Unfortunately, he soon finds himself separated from Maud - through the machinations of John the Brawn - and embroiled in other adventures. When next he meets Maud - two years later, in Saratoga, where she has become essential to her aunt's stage performances - he is just shy of 17, a working journalist, and his part in delivering Hillegond's son from his kidnappers has earned him a lifelong annuity. The two come together again, only to be parted once more, and cruelly.</p>
        <p>''Quinn's Book'' now leaps 15 years into the future. Hillegond is dead, a victim of murder; La Ultima, still a beauty in her 50's, is succumbing to the ebb of time; John the Brawn is famous, having become a champion pugilist, a strong-arm man for New York City's politicos and the owner of several Albany gambling houses; Quinn is famous too, as an unsparing Civil War correspondent; and Maud, delectable and mysterious, has earned herself a certain notoriety in the theater for a risque act involving an on-stage horseback ride. The war itself is conducted offstage, but in a riveting speech delivered to the beautiful people gathered for the races at Saratoga, Quinn brings its reality home. He has grown confident, no longer the orphan buffeted by the winds of fate, but a man able ''to alter existence, to negate life's caprice and become causality itself.'' In the finale, he must fight to win Maud from her fiance, Gordon Fitzgibbon, the new lord of the Staats mansion.</p>
        <p>As a writer of historical fiction, William Kennedy is unparalleled among his contemporaries. Rooted firmly in Albany, he sees ''an archetypal as well as an historical context in which to view the city's mutations,'' and asserts that the ''task'' of his fiction is ''to peer into the heart of this always-shifting past, to be there when it ceases to be what it was, when it becomes what it must become under scrutiny, when it turns so magically, so inevitably, from then into now.'' The books of the Albany cycle are a testament to this ars poetica, books that live comfortably in their history, convincing and true. ''Legs,'' Kennedy's fictional life of Jack (Legs) Diamond, Albany's most notorious bootlegger, illuminates with equal grace the dark country lanes of Catskill and the mean streets of Albany, presenting, in the process, the most sympathetic gangster since Gatsby. And ''Ironweed,'' justly celebrated for its haunting, elegiac prose and its vision of a man crippled by the past, reinvents historical fiction. ''Quinn's Book,'' especially in its harrowing riot scenes (there are two: a glimpse of the aforementioned New York draft riots and a full-blown depiction of a clash between two Irish immigrant clans in Albany, circa 1850) and its look at boxing and the races at Saratoga, is a lively addition to the canon.</p>
        <p>On the negative side, ''Quinn's Book'' does seem occasionally to warp under the weight of its history, sacrificing narrative drive and cohesion to the historical sidelights. Then, too, the author's use of an ersatz 19th-century idiom often rings false, as in the 12-line opening sentence, or in this description of Quinn's feelings on rescuing Maud from the icy Hudson: ''We made our way back to the pier, I full of such fears as might have paralyzed me had I not been in thrall to the vivid young girl who held my hand with the same tenacity a starving wolf might grip with peerless jaws the flank of a vagrant deer.'' After John Barth's ''Sot-Weed Factor'' and its sendup of the false idiom of the historical novel, it is difficult to take such locutions seriously.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, however, the language of ''Quinn's Book'' rises above the occasional lapses, and Quinn, as the book progresses, becomes increasingly eloquent, dropping the convoluted syntax in favor of a cleaner, more contemporary line. And if the history sometimes overwhelms the story, it is always fascinating. There are marvelous divagations on the lineage of the Staats family and the Underground Railroad, and a colorful sample of the age's sportswriting. Mr. Kennedy does indeed have the power to peer into the past, to breathe life into it and make it indispensable, and Quinn's battle to control his destiny and win Maud is by turns grim, amusing and deeply moving. In an era when so much of our fiction is content to accomplish so little, ''Quinn's Book'' is a revelation. Large-minded, ardent, alive on every page with its author's passion for his place and the events that made it, it is a novel to savor. One puts down ''Quinn's Book'' with a sigh, ever envying Mr. Kennedy his roots.  MAGDALENA'S WHIM</p>
        <p>When Magdalena Colon decided she was about to die for the second time, she announced from her bed that the only way she could die properly was lying by the water under a tree. . . . Instead of a birthday party to celebrate her being alive for fifty-five years, what she now wanted was a wake to acknowledge her passing over into lovely death, but held while she was still alive and able to enjoy both sides of existence at the same time. . . . She then sent for me to ask my advice in publicizing her wake, since she wanted all her friends and enemies to come. I suggested a handbill.</p>
        <p>''Fine,'' said Magdalena, ''and I also want you to write something about me and how I changed the world.'' ''How did you change the world?'' I asked. ''I have no idea, That's why I want you to write it.'' ''I'll do what I can,'' I said. ''Splendid. And you can read it tonight at the wake instead of some poopy old prayer.''  From ''Quinn's Book.''  THE RESPONSIBILITY OF CARRYING THE DEAD</p>
        <p>William Kennedy describes ''Quinn's Book'' as ''a project of long standing in my imagination'' - so long, in fact, that it was there before ''Legs,'' ''Billy Phelan's Greatest Game'' and ''Ironweed,'' and lent shape to those novels.</p>
        <p>''The genesis was a conversation I had with my father in 1965,'' Mr. Kennedy said in a telephone interview from Paris, where he was meeting with the publishers of the French edition of ''Legs.'' ''My father was endlessly full of small detail about his life, his neighborhood, working in a foundry. I thought about how important it all was to him - of the long-dead past being so vivid and wanting to communicate it to me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy said he had held on to the notes he scribbled during that and other conversations, intending to write an epic novel that would trace the history of Albany from its beginnings. ''I eventually abandoned the idea as excessively ambitious and decided instead on the cycle of novels'' centered on an Albany family. ''Quinn's Book,'' which fills in an ancestral branch of the family tree, is the story of Daniel Quinn, eponymous grandfather to young Danny Quinn of ''Ironweed.'' (Francis Phelan, the central character in ''Ironweed,'' is the boy's other grandfather.) ''They're all interconnected,'' Mr. Kennedy said. ''I've worked out the genealogies. New lines are established that I hope will be part of future books. It's inexhaustible - I've got about five books in my head.'' Like the other novels, ''Quinn's Book'' is faithful to the historical record, but the author was less concerned with reproducing actual events. ''In 'Legs,' I was fanatical about getting every murder correct and every murderer pinned down, which proved impossible. The research on this one was casual reading in many, many books, and discovering language. The main thing is to create characters who signify something very important to you. The suicidal tendencies of the immigrants, the incredible street fights, the lynchings, all these things have absolutely direct application to our own time. From the secret societies to Iran-contra to the resurgence of the Ku Klux Klan, it's an almost eerie equation.''</p>
        <p>But ''Quinn's Book'' is also a very personal reminiscence, ''the voice of a man remembering his childhood and the childhood of his great love.'' In his own life, Mr. Kennedy said, childhood was wound up in family, family in the generations that went before: ''You grow up on the dead; I did. Going to funerals, one after the other. Then you become a bearer -you're given the responsibility of carrying the dead - and there's that feeling of maturity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy said his next novel is set in 1958. And is everyone still in Albany? He hooted with laughter: ''Where else? There is no place else.''  KIM HERON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
