<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marching In the Parade Of Animals</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="756741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ASIA SOCIETY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MUSEUM OF AFRICAN ART (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PIERPONT MORGAN LIBRARY (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW SCHOOL FOR SOCIAL RESEARCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COTTER, HOLLAND</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D71039F932A15757C0A963958260" item-length="2292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marching In the Parade Of Animals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOLLAND COTTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COTTER, HOLLAND</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAN is the crown of creation, or so the common wisdom runs. Not everyone in history has agreed. The ancient Egyptians didn't always think so. Nor did the people of Africa or India. For those cultures, animals -- from lions to falcons to tsetse flies -- not only had the power to shape human lives but also provided a mirror in which, for better or worse, humans could see themselves reflected.</p>
        <p>Even in New York City in the 1990's, animal images are everywhere: macho camels on cigarette packs, heroic Disney beasts on subway posters, aggressive crocodiles stitched on T-shirts. And for the next few months, entire menageries can be found ensconsed in exhibitions at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Pierpont Morgan Library, the Museum for African Art and -- beginning on April 30 -- the Asia Society.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAN is the crown of creation, or so the common wisdom runs. Not everyone in history has agreed. The ancient Egyptians didn't always think so. Nor did the people of Africa or India. For those cultures, animals -- from lions to falcons to tsetse flies -- not only had the power to shape human lives but also provided a mirror in which, for better or worse, humans could see themselves reflected.</p>
        <p>Even in New York City in the 1990's, animal images are everywhere: macho camels on cigarette packs, heroic Disney beasts on subway posters, aggressive crocodiles stitched on T-shirts. And for the next few months, entire menageries can be found ensconsed in exhibitions at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Pierpont Morgan Library, the Museum for African Art and -- beginning on April 30 -- the Asia Society.</p>
        <p>Three of the shows are officially part of a multi-disciplinary program, "In the Company of Animals," initiated by the New School for Social Research with the purpose of exploring human and animal interaction. A grab bag of events that includes lectures and poetry readings, the concept is overall a trifle vague, but it brings together an interesting mix of people -- African dancers, Talmudic scholars -- and its visual components are pure delight.</p>
        <p>Of the three exhibitions now on view, "Animals in African Art: From the Familiar to the Marvelous" at the Museum for African Art is the most ambitious and has the least familiar material. The show was organized by Allen F. Roberts, professor of anthropology at the University of Iowa, and Carol Thompson, an associate curator. It brings together a wide range of public and private objects on loan, and boasts a handsome catalogue by Mr. Roberts that manages to be both scholarly and entertaining.</p>
        <p>Entertainment is one of the show's goals -- children will find a plentiful supply of drawing materials available in the galleries -- and it is effortlessly achieved, beginning with the first object encountered. A Nigerian shrine sculpture depicting a life-size man framed by upright serpents and the figure of a plump antelope under attack by a leopard, it vividly suggests the complex balance of human and animal interaction, with its mix of tranquillity and violence, that underlies the show.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts's tracing of this connection moves from the familiar to the fabulous. It begins with domestic animals: a charming terra-cotta figure of a goat made as a grave offering, an ox-head mask used in initiation ceremonies and a Yoruban image of a submissive sacrificial ram held in the arms of a magnificently carved young woman. The role of beasts as nourishers, spiritual intermediaries and ethical models -- strong but self-sacrificing, hard-working but wise -- are captivatingly established.</p>
        <p>With the appearance of a seven-foot-long carved snake from Cameroon, the exhibition enters more exotic and ambiguous territory, out of the farmyard and into the wild. The creature looks threatening, poised as if to strike. But in African thought, snakes are beneficent beings, bridges between the human and the celestial, a role reinforced in a child's bronze serpentine bracelet displayed nearby.</p>
        <p>The beasts that follow belong to realms of dreamlike strangeness. For some, their oddity is natural, as in the case of the chameleon, which changes its colors, or the pangolin, which lives both in trees and on land and plays dead when captured. (A lovely, circular image of this creature, serving as a container for kola nuts, is included.) Others, by contrast, are composite beings with no zoological equivalents, like the fabulous Senufo helmet mask from the Ivory Coast, bristling with animal tusks and positively radiant in its ugliness.</p>
        <p>None of the 170-plus smallish images in "An Egyptian Bestiary: Animals in Egyptian Art" at the Metropolitan are as expressively hot as this one. Rather, the show, organized by Dorothea Arnold (who also wrote the spring Museum Bulletin, which serves as its catalogue), is notable for its cool combination of smooth, unruffled naturalism and suave stylization.</p>
        <p>Ms. Arnold, too, has organized her animals by habitat. Among the domestic creatures are avid-looking bronze cats, one of which was made to hold a mummified animal, and wooden cows meant to accompany a burial. Creatures in the wild range from a carved jasper mosquito, much feared as a carrier of disease, to a delicate, feather-by-feather relief of a swallow in limestone, to a turquoise hippopotamus marked with lotus blossoms to suggest its immersion in river water. Here as everywhere in the show, the exactitude of observation is astonishing.</p>
        <p>So astonishing, in fact, that even the most unlikely images make perfect, if slightly surrealistic, sense. One is not inclined to doubt for an instant that a faience baboon with its quizzical glance and excellent posture is also Thoth, the god of wisdom. Nor is one given more than momentary pause by the sight of a seated goddess with a lion's face peering from beneath her wig or the svelte, dignified standing deity with an ibis's head. Within the seamless psychological fabric that is Egyptian art, god, man and animal are cut from the same cloth.</p>
        <p>The melding of animal and human also occurs in Western art, from classical centaurs to the Romanesque grotesques, though often in profane rather than sacred contexts. In the smart little show titled "Animals as Symbol in Medieval Illuminated Manuscripts," organized by William M. Voelkle at the Pierpont Morgan Library, animals take starring roles in depictions of the Seven Deadly Sins. Lust, in a 15th-century French Book of Hours, is represented as an effete young dandy riding a king-size billy goat, while a virulent demon with horns, talons and a human face reigns in the margin below.</p>
        <p>Naturalism is only sometimes a priority in these illuminations. Where animals appear as religious symbols, they are often highly stylized. This is true in an Evangelists page from a 12th-century German Gospel, where St. John's symbolic eagle is as decorative and inorganic as a piece of furniture. But in a how-to book on the care of dogs, the faces of the hounds are carefully characterized, as are the creatures in the margins of a 14th-century German missal. A close look reveals that here a traditional hunting scene has been reversed. A rabbit carries a dead wolf across its back; a fox carries a dog. The hunted are the hunters at last.</p>
        <p>In a sense, hunting is a subtext of all three shows. Ms. Arnold's list of animals extinct, or all but extinct, in Egypt today -- the ibis, the baboon, the hippopotamus -- partly because of human predation, makes for sad reading. And in contemporary Africa as in the West, the position of man and beast as ecological adversaries is all too familiar.</p>
        <p>But none of these shows presses this point. With images ranging from the sweet to the hallucinatory, visual delight is uppermost, and the interdependence of human and animal life rather than their antagonism is the heartening theme. On every level, animal lovers will be enthralled, and even people-people (peculiar creatures that they are) will find much to ponder on the beauty and the beast in us all.  What, Where and When</p>
        <p>Here is information on the exhibitions mentioned in the accompanying art review and on the events that are part of "In the Company of Animals," a series of lectures and shows that explore the multi-faceted relationship between animals and humans, which runs through June at several Manhattan locations. Unless otherwise noted, events are included in museum admission. Here is a listing: THE MUSEUMS</p>
        <p>ASIA SOCIETY, 725 Park Avenue, at 70th Street. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Thursdays, 11 A.M. to 8 P.M.; Sundays, noon to 5 P.M.; closed Mondays. Admission: $3; $1 for students and the elderly; free for children under 12, members and all on Thursdays, from 6 to 8 P.M. Information: (212) 517-2742.</p>
        <p>JEWISH MUSEUM, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92d Street. Hours: Sundays, 10 A.M. to 5:45 P.M.; Mondays, Wednesdays and Thursdays, 11 A.M. to 4:45 P.M.; Tuesdays, 11 A.M. to 8 P.M. Admission: $7; $5 for students and the elderly; free for children under 12 and museum members and for everyone on Tuesdays from 5 to 8 P.M. Information: (212) 423-3224.</p>
        <p>METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART, Fifth Avenue at 82d Street. Hours: Fridays and Saturdays, 9:30 A.M. to 8:45 P.M.; Sundays and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 A.M. to 5:15 P.M.; closed Mondays. Suggested admission: $7; $3.50 for students and the elderly. Information: (212) 535-7710.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM FOR AFRICAN ART, 593 Broadway, at Houston Street, SoHo. An exhibition of 150 artworks from the 11th to 20th century that features sculptures and figures made of wood, bronze, ivory, terra cotta and iron. Through Dec. 31. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10:30 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 6 P.M. Admission: $4; $2 for children, students, the elderly and museum members. Information: (212) 966-1313.</p>
        <p>PIERPONT MORGAN LIBRARY, 29 East 36th Street, Murray Hill. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturdays, 10:30 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Sundays, noon to 6 P.M. Suggested contribution: $5; $3 for students and the elderly. Information: (212) 685-0008, extension 347. SHOWS AND LECTURES</p>
        <p>Today</p>
        <p>"AN ANCIENT EGYPTIAN BESTIARY: ANIMALS IN EGYPTIAN ART," Metropolitan Museum of Art. A display of about 150 sculptures, reliefs, paintings and other artworks (not part of "In the Company of Animals"). Through Oct. 15.</p>
        <p>"ANIMALS AS SYMBOL IN MEDIEVAL ILLUMINATED MANUSCRIPTS," Pierpont Morgan Library. Through Sept. 3.</p>
        <p>"ANIMALS IN AFRICAN ART: FROM THE FAMILIAR TO THE MARVELOUS," Museum for African Art. An exhibition of 150 works from the 11th to 20th century that features figures made of wood, bronze, ivory, terra cotta and iron. Through Dec. 31. Tomorrow</p>
        <p>"THE ROOSTER (ARISTIDE) AND THE GUINEA HEN (POLITICAL CORRUPTION): ANIMAL MOTIFS IN THE HAITIAN POLITICAL STRUGGLE," Museum for African Art. Lecture by Dr. Karen McCarthy Brown, a sociology and anthropology professor at Drew University in Madison, N.J. 4 P.M. Lecture fee, which includes museum admission, is $7; $5 for children, students, the elderly and museum members.  Tuesday</p>
        <p>"THE ELUSIVE HARE: A STUDY IN JEWISH NATIONAL SELF-IDENTITY," Jewish Museum. Lecture by Marc Michael Epstein, of the department of Jewish Studies at Vassar College. 6:30 P.M. Admission: $10; $8 for students and the elderly; $6 for museum members. Information: (212) 423-3224. April 29</p>
        <p>"ANIMAL AVATARS IN CLASSICAL AFRICAN ART: YORUBA, SHONA, AND ABAKUA EXAMPLES," Museum for African Art. Lecture by Robert Farris Thompson, a professor of art history at Yale University. 4 P.M.  April 30</p>
        <p>"MONKEY," Asia Society. An exhibition of sculpture, prints and other artifacts from Asia that feature images of the monkey. Through Sept. 10. May 3</p>
        <p>"HUMANS AND ANIMALS: TO GUARD OR TO CONQUER," Jewish Museum. First of three lectures in the series "Judaism and the Beast: Animals in Jewish Tradition," by David Kraemer, a professor of Talmud at the Jewish Theological Seminary of America in New York. 2:30 P.M. Admission: $8; $6 for students and museum members.  May 6</p>
        <p>"HAVOC IN HEAVEN AND ON EARTH: MONKEYS IN ASIAN LITERATURE AND PERFORMANCE," Asia Society. Daylong symposium with Jamie Guan of the Beijing Opera; I Nyoman Catra, a Balinese dancer; Jamie H. J. Guan, an operatic actor; Suarti Laksmi of the Indonesia Art Institute; Anthony D. Yu of the University of Chicago Divinity School; Philip A. Lutgendorf of the University of Iowa; Ronald S. Jenkins of Emerson College and Alice Tuan, a playwright. 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Symposium admission: $25; $20 for society members. Also "Music, Dance and Theater of Bali: Monkeys, Warriors and Clowns," a performance, at 8 P.M.; tickets, $20; $16 for society members.</p>
        <p>"ANIMAL SYMBOLISM IN ANCIENT EGYPT," Museum for African Art. Lecture by Theophile Obenga, visiting professor of Nile Valley civilization and ancient Egyptian language at Temple University in Philadelphia. 4 P.M.  May 10</p>
        <p>"ANIMAL SYSTEMS IN JUDAISM," Jewish Museum. Second lecture in the series "Judaism and the Beast: Animals in Jewish Tradition," given by David Kraemer. 2:30 P.M. Admission: $8; $6 for students and museum members. May 13</p>
        <p>"FANTASTIC OTHERNESS: BLACKS FIGURED AS ANIMALS AND MONSTERS IN POPULAR CINEMA," Museum for African Art. Lecture by Ed Guerrero, assistant professor of English at the University of Delaware in Newark. 4 P.M.  May 17</p>
        <p>"FANTASTIC ANIMALS IN JEWISH LITERATURE AND CULTURE," Jewish Museum. Last lecture in the series "Judaism and the Beast: Animals in Jewish Tradition," given by David Kraemer. 2:30 P.M. Admission: $8; $6 for students and museum members. May 20</p>
        <p>"DYNAMIC INTERACTION: AFRICAN-ISLAMIC CONCEPTS OF ANIMALS POWERS," Museum for African Art. Lecture by Sulayman Nyang, a professor of African Studies at Howard University in Washington. 4 P.M.  June 3</p>
        <p>"YORUBA VOICES IN PRAISE OF ANIMALS," Museum for African Art. Lecture by Babalorisha John Mason, founder and director of the Yoruba Theological Archministry in Brooklyn. 4 P.M.  June 7</p>
        <p>"THE SEVEN DEADLY SINS," Pierpont Morgan Library. Lecture by William M. Voelke, curator of medieval and Renaissance manuscripts. 6 P.M. Admission: $10; $5 for library members.  June 10</p>
        <p>"ANIMAL DANCES FROM ZAIRE AND ANGOLA," Museum for African Art. Lecture by Elie Kihonia, founder and director of the Umoja African Art Company in Pittsburgh. 4 P.M.  June 17</p>
        <p>"SOUND OF SILENCE: VOICELESS CREATURES IN AFRICAN ART," Museum for African Art. Lecture by Philip M. Peek, an anthropology professor at Drew University. 4 P.M.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
