<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Italy, Political Fallout Over Plans for Telecom</title>
    <meta content="27tele" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/27/technology/27tele.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1793035"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Telecom Italia Spa</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Prodi, Romano</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Provera, Marco Tronchetti</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E2D81F31F934A1575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Italy, Political Fallout Over Plans for Telecom</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Italy, Political Fallout Over Plans for Telecom</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SYLVERS</byline>
      <dateline>MILAN, Sept. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It started with the announcement of a clear-cut plan to split up Italy's largest phone company, Telecom Italia, into separate mobile and fixed-line units.</p>
        <p>But that seemingly simple plan has led to a verbal slugfest between the prime minister, Romano Prodi, and the company's chairman, Marco Tronchetti Provera, who is also the country's best-known executive. Now, Mr. Prodi's government, which has a razor-thin majority in Parliament, seems to be wavering for the first time since he took office in May.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A plan to split Italy’s largest phone company into separate mobile and fixed-line units has led to a political slugfest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It started with the announcement of a clear-cut plan to split up Italy's largest phone company, Telecom Italia, into separate mobile and fixed-line units.</p>
        <p>But that seemingly simple plan has led to a verbal slugfest between the prime minister, Romano Prodi, and the company's chairman, Marco Tronchetti Provera, who is also the country's best-known executive. Now, Mr. Prodi's government, which has a razor-thin majority in Parliament, seems to be wavering for the first time since he took office in May.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, he faces public scrutiny by opposition members of Parliament when he appears before the lower house to answer to criticism that he might be interfering in Mr. Tronchetti Provera's corporate sphere. Then, on Oct. 5, Mr. Prodi will again face opposition Parliament members at a hearing in the Senate.</p>
        <p>Some members of Parliament are concerned that Mr. Prodi appears to be meddling in the affairs of a private company, despite European Union guidelines against such interference.</p>
        <p>It would not be the first example of European government involvement in domestic businesses. In Spain, government officials are seeking to shield the country's largest power company, Endesa, from an unwanted foreign takeover bid from a German company. French officials organized a merger between Gaz de France and Suez, two French companies, to thwart a bid for Suez from an Italian company, Enel. And last year, the governor of the Bank of Italy, Antonio Fazio, was forced to step down after a scandal in which he was accused of trying to avert a foreign takeover of Banco Antonveneta of Italy.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Prodi, an economist who served as president of the European Commission, often stresses the importance of following directives of the European Union, which tends to be less protectionist than some officials of its member governments. Mr. Prodi also has a record of being reform-minded.</p>
        <p>During his first term as prime minister a decade ago, he reduced Italy's spending and raised taxes to lower the nation's deficit so it could adopt the euro. In the first months so far of this term, he has pushed through measures to liberalize the Italian economy.</p>
        <p>But his latest moves are raising eyebrows. When the opposition first demanded that Mr. Prodi, 67, appear before Parliament, he called the idea ''crazy.'' But he later bowed to pressure rather than alienate allies in his fractious nine-party coalition who insisted on hearing about the events surrounding Telecom Italia.</p>
        <p>The situation became more confusing last week when Italian police arrested 20 people, including the former head of security at Telecom Italia, who was said to have spearheaded a group that illegally tracked the calls of more than 1,000 people. The arrests are part of a series of events that have weakened both Mr. Tronchetti Provera and Mr. Prodi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tronchetti Provera is chairman of Pirelli, which controls Telecom Italia. But he resigned as Telecom Italia's chairman after the breakup plan was made public and Mr. Prodi expressed surprise at it. Mr. Prodi said he had not been informed of the plan in advance, even though he had met with Mr. Tronchetti Provera in July and again earlier this month.</p>
        <p>Soon afterward, one of the prime minister's closest advisers resigned, after two newspapers considered close to Mr. Tronchetti Provera printed a document the adviser sent him suggesting the government could buy some of Telecom Italia assets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prodi, who was chairman for a decade of a government holding company that oversaw all state-owned companies, has been trying to deflect suggestions that he is reverting to old habits of the Italian government, which once controlled most of the country's largest companies.</p>
        <p>''I have been a privatizer of the Italian economy,'' Mr. Prodi said in a private interview last week. ''We need it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Prodi last week warned his coalition partners, who waited in the wings for five years while Silvio Berlusconi ran the country, that if he fell from power he would bring down everybody else with him. Mr. Berlusconi on Saturday said Mr. Prodi's government would not last much longer and that when the government fell, he would be ready to retake the reins.</p>
        <p>Paolo Natale, a political science professor at the University of Milan, said the events were a serious blow for the Prodi government. ''The evidence is that Prodi was not able to manage the Telecom Italia situation in a transparent way,'' he said. ''That has cost the government some of the consensus it had, but Italians have a short memory and Prodi has always been considered capable in the past, so this may blow over.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tronchetti Provera's own problems could intensify. Prosecutors investigating the case that led to the 20 arrests have linked secret bank accounts in Monte Carlo to him and to Telecom Italia's chief executive, Carlo Buora, according to La Repubblica, a Rome daily. The prosecutors suspect that a Pirelli employee bought and sold stocks through the Monte Carlo branch of Banca del Gottardo, deposited profits into the secret bank accounts of Mr. Tronchetti Provera and Mr. Buora, and covered the losses with a Pirelli account in Luxembourg, La Repubblica reported.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tronchetti Provera vigorously defended himself in an appeal to journalists at a news conference in Milan on Monday.</p>
        <p>''This evening I am here to ask for help not for me, but for the Telecom Italia group because these are healthy companies,'' Mr. Tronchetti Provera said. ''Help us get the truth to come out. These are good people who haven't taken any money from the company.''</p>
        <p>In a sign that tensions have not abated, one of Mr. Prodi's ministers over the weekend said that things were better at Telecom Italia when it was owned by the government, which privatized the phone company in 1997. Telecom Italia was bought the next year in the country's largest hostile takeover ever. Pirelli, with Mr. Tronchetti Provera at the helm, bought control of Telecom Italia in 2001, in an investment that has lost half its value in five years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tronchetti Provera's most recent problems began three weeks ago when he presented to the board of Telecom Italia a plan to split the mobile and fixed-line operations into separate companies. The move would be a complete about-face for Telecom Italia, coming less than two years after the company acquired the part of the mobile unit it did not already own. At the time of that purchase, Mr. Tronchetti Provera trumpeted the importance of integrating the mobile and fixed-line businesses.</p>
        <p>The proposed breakup drew angry reactions from politicians who saw it as the first step to the sale of the mobile unit, the only one of the four Italian mobile phone companies that is domestically owned. Mr. Tronchetti Provera says he has no plans to sell the mobile unit, which analysts estimate is worth about 35 billion euros, though he also said that if offers arrived they would be considered. Mr. Tronchetti Provera has made no secret that he is trying to shed some of Telecom Italia's crippling debt, which at 40 billion euros may be more than the company's market value.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
