<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Africans Head to Olympics With Few Stars and Few Chances</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="542360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1992)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (NON-US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCCER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AFRICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLER, BILL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DC103AF930A25754C0A964958260" item-length="1635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Africans Head to Olympics With Few Stars and Few Chances</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KELLER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KELLER, BILL</byline>
      <dateline>JOHANNESBURG, July 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bobang Phiri burst from the blocks at the African Games in Mauritius last month to become the 400-meter champion of the continent. Gary Lemke, the sports editor of The Pretoria News, hailed Phiri as "the finest prospect in South African athletics."</p>
        <p>Marcel Winkler, a sprinter with the shy grace and liquid speed of an impala, could, in the estimation of the respected track master who coaches her, "quite possibly become the fastest woman in the world."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bobang Phiri burst from the blocks at the African Games in Mauritius last month to become the 400-meter champion of the continent. Gary Lemke, the sports editor of The Pretoria News, hailed Phiri as "the finest prospect in South African athletics."</p>
        <p>Marcel Winkler, a sprinter with the shy grace and liquid speed of an impala, could, in the estimation of the respected track master who coaches her, "quite possibly become the fastest woman in the world."</p>
        <p>Never heard of them? Neither had most of their own sports-infatuated countrymen. Two months ago, even the National Olympic Committee of South Africa, in the glossy magazine it published to celebrate this country's multi-racial return from sporting exile, neglected to mention their names. 'Four-Year Apprenticeships'</p>
        <p>Phiri and Winkler, two of the 11 non-whites on the 97-member South African Olympic team, are remote long shots in this year's Olympics, but in many ways they are representative of South African sport in its season of rehabilitation.</p>
        <p>This is a team unknown, untested and unsure of itself after three decades of banishment from world competition. It is a team that has been hobbled both by its history of racial exclusion and its recent, fitful politics of transition. It is a team running to catch up with its potential.</p>
        <p>"I don't think there's any gold for this team at Barcelona," said John Short, the veteran University of Pretoria track coach who trains Winkler. "I don't expect anything from our team, and I don't think our public does, either. We have vast amounts of talent, but we are just entering into a four-year apprenticeship."</p>
        <p>No one among the 97 South African Olympians is old enough to remember the country's last Olympic medal, Malcolm Spence's bronze in the 400 meters in the 1960 Rome Olympics.</p>
        <p>The country was discouraged from competing in the 1964 and 1968 Games, and formally banished from Olympic competition in 1970 for its policy of racial separation, a ban gradually extended to almost the entire kingdom of world sport.</p>
        <p>The International Olympic Committee restored South Africa's full recognition a year ago, after President F. W. de Klerk renounced apartheid and entered negotiations aimed at giving blacks the vote. That absolution was contingent on each sport winning readmission to its international sporting federation, a process that kept many athletes in doubt about Barcelona until this spring.</p>
        <p>The squad that leaves next Monday for Barcelona will be just over half the size of the 176-member, all-white team that competed in Rome 32 years ago, and much weaker than could be expected of a country with ideal weather, great wealth, abundant talent and a fanatic devotion to sports.</p>
        <p>South Africa will be unrepresented in some sports that won international recognition too late for qualifying tournaments. Those who missed the plane to Barcelona include the predominantly black soccer team, which re-entered world competition only this week by playing host to Cameroon, and the volleyball, basketball and men's and women's field hockey teams.</p>
        <p>The team's weakness is partly the price of apartheid, which systematically denied black athletes the facilities, coaching, sponsors and competition necessary to reach Olympic heights.</p>
        <p>"We have good black marathoners because you can take any road in South Africa and just run," said Daniel Moyo, assistant to the president of the National Olympic Committee. "But for short distances you need a track. The only place you'll find a tartan track -- or a discus, or a shot-put -- is in white schools in white suburbs."</p>
        <p>Winkler, whose mix of English, Swiss and African heritage made her "colored" in the crude taxonomy of apartheid, started running at age 7, but never got to race against a white athlete until high school, when a coach spotted her talent and got her into top meets.</p>
        <p>"At school we only competed with other colored schools, so it was difficult to get competition," said the softspoken, 21-year-old sprinter, who will race in the 100 meters and 200 meters at Barcelona.</p>
        <p>"It's nice to say, 'Oh, we've eliminated all the discrimination now,' " added her coach, John Short. "But it is not so easy to overcome the psychological damage to a girl who was told all through her childhood, 'No, you aren't good enough to run at white meetings.' " Two Talented Exceptions</p>
        <p>Though apartheid laws have been repealed, the townships where most non-whites live still fester with poverty and violence that tend to overwhelm all but the most irrespressible talent.</p>
        <p>Phiri, who at 24 is still coming into his prime, traces his late bloom in part to the student unrest that periodically rocked his school in a black township of Randfontein, making studies -- let alone track meets -- impossible.</p>
        <p>Phiri and Winkler were saved by prodding, educated parents and universities that began in the late 1980's to open their doors to a few promising non-whites. Phiri now majors in "human movement studies," -- i.e., physical education -- at the University of the Western Cape in Cape Town. Winkler studies personnel management at University of Pretoria.</p>
        <p>Others among the black Olympians -- like Xolile Yawa, who holds the South African record over 10,000 meters, and sprinter Tsakile Nzimande -- flourished on the sporting fields of South African mining conglomerates, which invested heavily in athletics as a way to minimize frustrations in their all-male worker hostels.</p>
        <p>The current South African Olympic committee, whose leaders come from the anti-apartheid movement, has been accused by some of lowering standards to increase the number of "disadvantaged" athletes going to Barcelona.</p>
        <p>In the only blatant case, the country's top female table-tennis player, who is white, was bumped in favor of a mixed-race woman rated No. 2.</p>
        <p>Olympic officials concede that they opened extra slots in some events, like the marathon, where blacks excel, but insist that all competitors were chosen on the basis of merit.</p>
        <p>In addition to the Olympic team, the committee is flying 25 non-white athletes to Barcelona for the experience, and has begun lining up business sponsors for an intensive athletic development program in the townships. Student Athletes, Not Miners</p>
        <p>"It shouldn't be black athletes working in the mines," said Phiri. "It should be black student athletes, doing masters programs somewhere."</p>
        <p>The country's long absence from international competition means that its athletes, white or black, have not honed their skills against the best in the world.</p>
        <p>"South Africa still has to learn that the world is bigger than Pretoria," said Short, the coach. "Tactically, they don't know the opposition to plan their races. Spiritually, we've got this sense that we are way behind the world."</p>
        <p>Their preparations for Barcelona have suffered, too, from recurring threats that the team's trip would yet be aborted by politics. The African National Congress contemplated an attempt to reimpose the Olympic boycott to protest alleged Government complicity in last month's massacre of more than 40 blacks in the Boipatong township.</p>
        <p>Instead, the congress extracted a promise that wherever international rules allowed, South African athletes would be encouraged to wear armbands or stickers advocating "peace and democracy."</p>
        <p>This provoked fresh howls from traditionalists, who were already upset that the Olympic team had forsaken the South African flag, the national anthem and the springbok emblem long associated with white South African athletics.</p>
        <p>Most Olympians, however, tended to agree with the white rugby player who told reporters that he would wear a pink tutu if that was what it took to get him back in international competition.</p>
        <p>"If it's for peace and democracy, I wouldn't mind wearing a cap, too," said Phiri. "I don't mind wearing a T-shirt, too. Sure, peace and democracy." Five Known Quantities</p>
        <p>At least the South African team will travel relatively unburdened by expectations.</p>
        <p>The Olympic Committee's magazine, wishfully entitled "Olympic Gold," singled out five athletes, all of them white, with realistic prospects of making the finals in their events: Elana Meyer, the elfin middle-distance star who is given a chance of winning the 10,000 meters; her rival Zola Budd Pieterse, South Africa's best-known runner by virtue of her collision with American Mary Decker while competing as a British citizen in the 1984 Olympics; 400-meter hurdlers Myrtle Bothma and Dries Vorster, and Tom Petranoff, a American-born, former record-holder in the javelin who recently obtained South African citizenship.</p>
        <p>"After our top five contenders, the well runs dry," the magazine lamented.</p>
        <p>In other sports, yachtsmen Alec Lanham-Love and Martin Lambrecht are favored to do well, and the national tennis heartthrob Wayne Ferreira will be closely watched.</p>
        <p>Among black competitors, distance runners Zithulele Sinque and Xolile Yawa are given outside chances of making their finals.</p>
        <p>Some surprises may lurk in the pack. Phiri's winning 400-meter time in Mauritius, 45:42, was nearly a second off the pace of top American runners, but his times have been improving rapidly and he has never faced the world's best.</p>
        <p>Winkler, she and her coach agree, is more likely to claim her medal at the 1996 Games in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>For most South Africans, it will be enough to tune in their televisions and see their country back on the world's track.</p>
        <p>As it happens, even that modest joy may be denied them. The predominantly black Media Workers Association of South Africa has been on strike for higher wages since May 18 against the South African Broadcasting Corporation. The association succeeded last week in blacking out the South African soccer team's three matches against Cameroon, and it has threatened to pull the plug on the Olympics.  OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
