<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knick Fan's Guide to Getting Over It</title>
    <meta content="07WISE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/07/sports/07WISE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1291434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Miami</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Clyde</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Patrick</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Sacramento</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Madison Square Garden</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rice, Glen</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Houston, Allan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Riley, Pat</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Smith, Charles</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mason, Anthony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Webber, Chris</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Van Gundy, Jeff</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD61F38F934A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knick Fan's Guide to Getting Over It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Wise</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses future of New York Knickerbockers following elimination from playoffs by Toronto Raptors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because Glen Rice and Allan Houston could not make an important shot, because the front line could not corral a crucial rebound -- and because Miami was not around to beat up on -- we interrupt this regularly scheduled Knicks postseason run to bring you back your life.</p>
        <p>Seeing as how it has been 10 years since the Knicks have been eliminated in the first round -- and since you won't be spending those long hours at Madison Square Garden for the next month or so -- some coping mechanisms are in order for the true zealots.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Because Glen Rice and Allan Houston could not make an important shot, because the front line could not corral a crucial rebound -- and because Miami was not around to beat up on -- we interrupt this regularly scheduled Knicks postseason run to bring you back your life.</p>
        <p>Seeing as how it has been 10 years since the Knicks have been eliminated in the first round -- and since you won't be spending those long hours at Madison Square Garden for the next month or so -- some coping mechanisms are in order for the true zealots.</p>
        <p>Here, then, for all those in severe withdrawal after Toronto's stunning Game 5 victory over the Knicks at the Garden on Friday night, The Official Knick Fan's Guide to the Rest of May.</p>
        <p>Now that the Knicks are done, you can:</p>
        <p>*Take stuff out to the Hamptons a month early. Once you get there, be sure to stock up on essentials from the Barefoot Contessa.</p>
        <p>*End your decade-long pattern of parental neglect. For a change, take Mom out for a real Mother's Day celebration, rather than trying to pass off a Garden foot-long hot dog, curly fries and a Bud Lite as her special-day brunch.</p>
        <p>*Coax a promoter into offering a pay-per-view Heat vs. Knicks series. Two out of three, no referees, no suspensions. No ambulance, no foul. This time, it's personal.</p>
        <p>*Attend a self-help seminar with fans from other National Basketball Association teams knocked out in the first round. Guest lecturer and welcome presentation: Pat Riley, Should I Fire Myself?</p>
        <p>*Make Memorial Day plans for Knick Reunion Cookout, featuring all your old playoff-heartbreak favorites, who are currently on their couches eating Cheetos: Patrick Ewing, John Starks, Charles Smith, Anthony Mason and, of course, your 2000-2001 Knicks.</p>
        <p>*Kindle long-lost love affair with baseball. Take in a Yankee doubleheader and enjoy the nuances and subtleties of the grand old game. Like salary arbitration and the infield fly rule.</p>
        <p>*Rearrange your wardrobe. Replace the orange-and-blue drawer and substitute the No. 8 jerseys with polo shirts and yachting wear.</p>
        <p>*Clean out your closet and go on a shopping spree with Clyde. Walt Frazier will teach you to shop for black leather pants, fedoras, cream-colored coats and alligator-skin, square-toed boots. In addition, you'll enhance your vocabulary with words like ''ubiquitous,'' ''loquacious,'' ''indubitably'' and phrases like ''Oakley is a hackin' and a wackin' and a houndin' and a poundin'.''</p>
        <p>*This weekend, attend mass or temple and promptly ask for forgiveness for all those awful things you said about Patrick.</p>
        <p>*Engage in a passionate conversation with an overnight talk-radio host about what's wrong with the Jets' backup long snapper.</p>
        <p>*Make a real appointment with your therapist, not the kind in which you discuss Knick abandonment issues. Stop trying to get in touch with your inner fan. After all, it's not important why Allan Houston missed a big shot; it's important to know how you felt about Allan missing the shot.</p>
        <p>*Go outside. It's nice this time of year. Honest.</p>
        <p>*Write daily letters to Chris Webber, pleading with him to come to New York. Tell him you're his No. 1 fan. If the Sacramento free-agent-to-be slaps you with a restraining order, say Latrell Sprewell made you do it.</p>
        <p>*Keep emotional distance from your surrogate Garden family. You know, the people who know where your daughter is going to college, why you had an ulcer and why Jeff Van Gundy needs to go deeper into his bench -- the people you have absolutely nothing in common with except for the fact you have celebrated and commiserated with them since 1991.</p>
        <p>All right, maybe they do care about you. But if they could move 20 rows closer to the floor tomorrow, you think they're coming back to visit?</p>
        <p>*Write a letter to your congressman. Volunteer. Instead of wasting fruitless hours discussing trade rumors at work and at home, become involved in matters that might change the world, not the Knicks frontcourt.</p>
        <p>*Wait. Check that. After 28 years, it may be easier to start following a team that actually has a chance to win the championship, no?</p>
        <p>*If you can't get the ''Go, New York, Go'' song out of your head, start thinking today about how the Knicks will go all the way next season. If you're a terminal case, you know all they need is one blockbuster trade, a new offense. Next year will be your year. You can feel it, as you wait in line for a currant scone at the Barefoot Contessa.</p>
        <p>ON PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
