<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Can Learn From Cuba's AIDS Program</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="590726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACQUIRED IMMUNE DEFICIENCY SYNDROME (AIDS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CUBA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LLANOS, RAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CONCEPCION, JUAN CARLOS DE LA (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DF1E3BF935A25751C0A965958260" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Can Learn From Cuba's AIDS Program</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your "AIDS in Latin America" special report (front page, Jan. 25) grossly misrepresents the situation in the only country that has successfully held the virus in check. You dismiss the successes of Cuba's AIDS control and prevention program with the irrelevant comment that Cuba "is the region's only nation with a totalitarian government."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your "AIDS in Latin America" special report (front page, Jan. 25) grossly misrepresents the situation in the only country that has successfully held the virus in check. You dismiss the successes of Cuba's AIDS control and prevention program with the irrelevant comment that Cuba "is the region's only nation with a totalitarian government."</p>
        <p>You state that Cuba's accomplishment in limiting the virus to 862 known cases (in a population of more than 10 million) is a result of "mandatory testing and the quarantining of infected people." And you editorialize that the "apparent epidemiological success" of the Cuban program has been carried out "at the expense of individual liberties, a cost resisted by other societies in the Americas."</p>
        <p>As Cuban citizens infected with the human immunodeficiency virus, which causes AIDS, and activists in the Grupo Prevencion SIDA, or AIDS Prevention Group, we think it is unfortunate more people can't learn from and duplicate Cuba's successes.</p>
        <p>Cuba has the same population as New York City. Visiting and exchanging experiences with AIDS care providers in your city and around your country, we have learned that New York has had 42,737 reported cases of full-blown AIDS. Cuba has 159.</p>
        <p>Your Centers for Disease Control, which has no official figures of AIDS deaths, says that two-thirds of reported cases of AIDS can be assumed to have died. That means that since the beginning of the epidemic, at least 28,000 New Yorkers have died. In Cuba, where records are kept, the number who have died of AIDS is 84.  No one knows how many New Yorkers are carrying the virus; the estimates vary from 5 to 10 times the number of full-blown AIDS cases. In Cuba, after massive routine (not mandatory) testing, fewer than 900 have tested positive (official estimates suggest 240 more may be infected, but not yet tested).</p>
        <p>Even more heartbreaking are the figures relating to children. New York City has 987 reported cases of pediatric AIDS; more babies are born with H.I.V. every day, and children are dying or left orphans at a frightening rate. In Cuba only one child has died of AIDS: three are carrying the virus. (All pregnant women get H.I.V. antibody tests as part of prenatal care, and if they test positive, they may, after counseling, choose a therapeutic abortion.)</p>
        <p>Lest you think this contrast applies only to New York City, we should note that Puerto Rico, a Spanish-speaking Caribbean island like Cuba, with one-third Cuba's population, has had 8,117 reported cases of AIDS, 208 of them pediatric cases.</p>
        <p>Had you used the word "socialism" to describe Cuba's political system, readers might have been able to understand that it is Cuba's national preventive health-care system, fully funded and free to all citizens, that makes Cuba unique in Latin America, and is most responsible for its success in curtailing the AIDS epidemic.</p>
        <p>Cuba in addition had early, widespread screening of the entire blood supply (only nine Cubans became infected with H.I.V. through transfusion), has almost no drug culture and a complete lack of injectible drugs. It also has a sanitorium system.</p>
        <p>What you refer to as quarantining is the requirement that almost all who test positive enter the sanitorium system, in which they are given free medical evaluation and treatment, psychological services, food, housing, recreation and work (if they so desire) in a beautiful, stress-free environment, and an intensive course in AIDS education.</p>
        <p>To those who say that we Cubans who are H.I.V.-positive are deprived of our rights, or that our health benefits come at too high a price, we ask:</p>
        <p>Aren't the people who are dying of AIDS without proper medical care, often without jobs, food or housing, and aren't those infected because of lack of adequate education, too little money for research, too much indifference and too much rampant individualism, paying too high a price? JUAN CARLOS DE LA CONCEPCION, M.D. RAUL LLANOS  Havana, Jan. 28, 1993</p>
        <p>This letter was translated for the writers by Karen Lee Wald.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
