<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AIDS Expert Helps Doctors Learn From the Dead to Help the Living</title>
    <meta content="18DOC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/18/health/18DOC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1465856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THE DOCTOR'S WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Autopsies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cryptococcus (Fungus)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lucas, Sebastian (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DeCock, Kevin (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/The Doctor's World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D81E3AF93BA25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AIDS Expert Helps Doctors Learn From the Dead to Help the Living</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">AIDS Expert Helps Doctors Learn From Autopsies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Feb. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Doctors and scientists report to conference in Boston that autopsies on AIDS victims have given them new knowledge and perspectives on AIDS, shedding light on damage that HIV can inflict on various organs and tissues; Dr Sebastian Lucas, British pathologist, describes how autopsy on AIDS patient revealed that mysterious red rash on patient was caused by cryptococcus fungus, one of myriad opportunistic infections that can blossom when HIV severely damages immune system; Dr Kevin M DeCock says autopsy studies have greatly influenced approaches to treatment and management, particularly in Africa; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of red spots covered the African H.I.V. patient's skin -- so many, and so baffling, that his doctors at a leading hospital in London thought he might have smallpox, even though no case has been seen for 20 years. As the doctors remained stumped, the man died.</p>
        <p>It was left to an autopsy to determine the cause of the mysterious rash, Dr. Sebastian Lucas, a British pathologist, said at an AIDS meeting here last week. It was the cryptococcus fungus, one of myriad opportunistic infections that can blossom when H.I.V. severely damages the immune system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Sebastian Lucas, who has performed 1,000 autopsies on H.I.V. patients, teaches doctors how to learn from the dead to heal the living.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hundreds of red spots covered the African H.I.V. patient's skin -- so many, and so baffling, that his doctors at a leading hospital in London thought he might have smallpox, even though no case has been seen for 20 years. As the doctors remained stumped, the man died.</p>
        <p>It was left to an autopsy to determine the cause of the mysterious rash, Dr. Sebastian Lucas, a British pathologist, said at an AIDS meeting here last week. It was the cryptococcus fungus, one of myriad opportunistic infections that can blossom when H.I.V. severely damages the immune system.</p>
        <p>The British doctors knew cryptococcus, but they had never seen it cause that kind of rash, Dr. Lucas said.</p>
        <p>The same could be said of many of the AIDS scientists at the 10th Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections, where Dr. Lucas presented a series of stunning, if grim, autopsy photographs. Even though these molecular biologists, statisticians and other scientists are a vital part of the AIDS research team, they do not take care of patients, so they seldom witness the damage that H.I.V. can inflict on various organs and tissues.</p>
        <p>By the same token, doctors practicing today see autopsy results much less often than did their counterparts a few decades ago because far fewer autopsies are now being done. By contrast, Dr. Lucas has gained an extraordinary perspective on AIDS from having performed 1,000 autopsies on H.I.V. patients in England and Africa. He has found many ways to apply the classic credo of pathology: to learn from the dead to heal the living.</p>
        <p>Doctors often ''get the first one wrong,'' Dr. Lucas said in an interview. ''When you have seen something once, you can say, 'I will remember that the next time it turns up, and get it right.' '' The African H.I.V. patient, for example, might have survived with more timely diagnosis and treatment.</p>
        <p>Photographs are effective educational tools in medicine as they are in other fields. So Dr. Lucas went on to show slides of other H.I.V.-related conditions like toxoplasmosis, tuberculosis, pneumocystis pneumonia and H.I.V. nephropathy, a kidney disease that is common in blacks.</p>
        <p>Doctors who take care of AIDS patients have come to know such conditions well, though their incidence has declined with wide use of powerful drug combinations. But nonclinical scientists often focus on what no one can see -- the way a virus disrupts the function of cells at a molecular level. Much of what they look at every day are schematics and diagrams deduced from what appears to occur in laboratory tests when H.I.V. snags certain blood cells to entwine itself into the cellular machinery.</p>
        <p>Lectures like Dr. Lucas's about clinical and autopsy findings are seldom part of the meetings these scientists attend. Dr. Lucas said his aim was to encourage scientists from all disciplines of AIDS research to communicate more with one another to improve the understanding of the complexity of the epidemic and its human dimensions.</p>
        <p>In addition to the autopsies Dr. Lucas has performed in England, health workers in Africa mail him specimens to diagnose, and he replies through e-mail. ''Sometimes the reply is too late to help a particular patient,'' he said, ''but we do it to help mission hospital doctors and educate our trainees.''</p>
        <p>Using this information, Dr. Lucas is working with the Armed Forces Institute of Pathology in Washington to publish an atlas of ''every conceivable variant'' of the way that H.I.V. can damage the body.</p>
        <p>Autopsies are not particularly risky, he said, if ''you take the sensible standard precautions.'' He added that he had never cut himself while examining an H.I.V.-infected body.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kevin M. DeCock, an AIDS epidemiologist who has worked in Africa for many years for the United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, said in an interview here that autopsy studies had greatly influenced approaches to treatment and management, particularly in Africa.</p>
        <p>About a decade ago, he said, when he was working in Abidjan, Ivory Coast, he wanted to know whether pneumocystis carinii pneumonia, or P.C.P., was as common among AIDS patients in West Africa as it was in developed countries, and whether these patients could be helped by the drug Bactrim. The African hospitals could not afford the diagnostic techniques and laboratory facilities that are routine in developed countries. So Dr. DeCock persuaded Dr. Lucas to look for P.C.P. in his autopsies in Ivory Coast.</p>
        <p>''Everyone was saying P.C.P. occurred there, but you did not find it,'' Dr. Lucas said. ''I said, rubbish, I have taken five pieces of the lungs at every autopsy, and I have looked at them the same way as I do in Britain.''</p>
        <p>P.C.P. turned out to be uncommon among adults in West Africa but common in infants, largely because their immune systems were immature when they became infected with H.I.V.</p>
        <p>In another autopsy study in the early 1990's, Dr. Lucas found that one-third of H.I.V.-infected people in Abidjan were dying from tuberculosis. The finding ''knocked the socks off'' officials of the World Health Organization ''because it was absolutely new to them,'' Dr. DeCock said.</p>
        <p>Ivoirian colleagues were ecstatic when Dr. Lucas organized what is standard elsewhere, a weekly conference to discuss autopsy findings. He said: ''The doctors were absolutely thrilled. You could just see light bulbs popping up in their heads. 'Oh, that was nocardia,' '' a fungal disease, '' 'not lymphoma,' '' a cancer. '' 'Next time I see this I will try and recognize it better.' ''</p>
        <p>Autopsies can play a crucial role in monitoring the complications of therapy. For example, they have helped detect problems of liver toxicity directly related to anti-H.I.V. drugs. Now a major concern is the possibility that the newer anti-H.I.V. drugs may lead to heart complications, and pathologists have increased their vigil for such damage.</p>
        <p>A sobering fact of modern medicine is that despite the widespread use of imaging tests like M.R.I. and C.T. scans, autopsies show that doctors often miss important information in all kinds of cases.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lucas said that after his lecture here, many participants told him they did not know why a number of their H.I.V. patients had developed failure of many organs and died. One reason for their ignorance might be that they never asked for an autopsy.</p>
        <p>THE DOCTOR'S WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
