<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tormenting Hevesi</title>
    <meta content="30HERB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/30/opinion/30HERB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1321106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="In America"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Post</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbert, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Alan G (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bob Herbert</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Post</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hevesi, Alan G</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4DD1530F933A0575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tormenting Hevesi</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tormenting Hevesi</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB HERBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herbert, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Herbert Op-Ed column on Alan Hevesi's curious reaction to charges by Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani and New York Post that he accepted bribe; says no candidate can let allegations of corruption go unanswered, but Hevesi has come to believe that this high-profile fight with mayor enhances his stature and will boost his chances of reaching mayoral runoff on Sept 11; says while Hevesi's aides may be right, that this fight may be good thing for Hevesi, none of other Democratic candidates would be willing to trade places with him (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One night in June 1939 Joe Louis fought a championship bout with Tony Galento, a tavern owner from Orange, N.J., who was shaped like a beer barrel and nicknamed Two-Ton.</p>
        <p>The highlight of Galento's career came in the third round when he knocked Louis down. Louis got off the canvas quickly and in the next round he pummeled Galento with a fury that frightened ringsiders and left the challenger helpless. The referee stopped the fight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alan Hevesi is getting trashed by Mayor Rudolph Giuliani, but Mr. Hevesi's aides say the high-profile fight is a good thing</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One night in June 1939 Joe Louis fought a championship bout with Tony Galento, a tavern owner from Orange, N.J., who was shaped like a beer barrel and nicknamed Two-Ton.</p>
        <p>The highlight of Galento's career came in the third round when he knocked Louis down. Louis got off the canvas quickly and in the next round he pummeled Galento with a fury that frightened ringsiders and left the challenger helpless. The referee stopped the fight.</p>
        <p>After the fight came the spin. With blood streaming down his face from cuts that would require 23 stitches to close, Galento argued ferociously that the fight should not have been stopped, that things were going his way, that Louis surely would have been defeated if only the referee hadn't intervened.</p>
        <p>From Two-Ton Tony's perspective, the beating that he was absorbing was a good thing.</p>
        <p>Something similar is happening in New York's Democratic mayoral primary. Alan Hevesi is not nearly in as woeful a condition as Galento was in that fourth round against Joe Louis. Mr. Hevesi still has a good chance of making it into a runoff, and in a runoff anything can happen. But Mr. Hevesi has been taking a pretty severe pounding from a couple of heavyweight antagonists -- Rudolph Giuliani and The New York Post.</p>
        <p>And the latest spin from the Hevesi camp is that somehow this is a good thing.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 17 The Post ran a flimsy article with a big Page 1 headline that said ''Hevesi Bribe Claim.'' (A similar article ran in Newsday, although it was not prominently displayed.) The story was so weak that The Post, in an editorial on Tuesday, noted: ''. . . the bribe claim is unsubstantiated. And, from what we know of Hevesi, unlikely to be true.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, that big headline with the word ''bribe'' in it was out there. Meanwhile, like the other half of a tag team, Mayor Giuliani climbed into the ring. He said that Mr. Hevesi, the city comptroller, should be investigated. He charged repeatedly that the comptroller was ''ethically challenged.'' He said Mr. Hevesi had used his office inappropriately to help set up a business meeting for a campaign contributor. And he told reporters that Mr. Hevesi had trouble telling the truth.</p>
        <p>(In the midst of that onslaught, which went on for days, the mayor also said he had ''a hard time believing'' that Alan Hevesi had taken a bribe.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi's campaign was already struggling. And no candidate can let allegations of corruption go unanswered. So the comptroller, who called the bribe charge a ''despicable lie,'' fought back against the mayor by accusing him of ethical lapses and bully-boy tactics. I don't know what else he could have done, but you could almost feel the voters tuning out.</p>
        <p>And here is where the comparison with Tony Galento comes in. Aides to Mr. Hevesi, while not happy over the ugly charges being leveled against their candidate, have come to believe -- or are trying to get others to believe -- that this high-profile fight with the mayor enhances the comptroller's stature and will boost his chances of reaching a runoff on Sept. 11. Never mind that the guy is being trashed daily, accused of lying and engaging in corruption. The spin is that, on balance, this whole episode is a good thing.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday Mr. Hevesi further escalated the fight, releasing a television ad attacking Mr. Giuliani and The Post. ''Rudy's at it again,'' the ad says. ''He's joined Rupert Murdoch's right-wing New York Post in attacking Democrat Alan Hevesi.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani and the people at The Post seemed delighted with the opportunity to keep the brouhaha going. ''Get Rupert on the phone,'' Mr. Giuliani joked at City Hall.</p>
        <p>The Post, meanwhile, ran a huge front-page photo of Mr. Hevesi's head superimposed on the body of an infant clad in a diaper. The one-word headline was ''Crybaby.''</p>
        <p>(The Post's front page was a ripoff of a Daily News front page from Nov. 16, 1995, that featured an illustration of Newt Gingrich as an infant having a temper tantrum under the headline ''Cry Baby.'')</p>
        <p>The folks in Mr. Hevesi's corner may be right. This fight may be a good thing for the comptroller. It's interesting to note, however, that none of the other Democratic candidates would be willing to trade places with him.</p>
        <p>In America</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
