<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revision of Growth Data Pushes Shares Sharply Lower</title>
    <meta content="Y30STO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/30/business/30STOX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1321117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Industrial Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Sherri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Commerce Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E3DC1530F933A0575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revision of Growth Data Pushes Shares Sharply Lower</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Revision of Growth Data Pushes Shares Sharply Lower</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERRI DAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Day, Sherri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dow Jones industrial average falls 131.13 points, to 10,090.90; Nasdaq composite index drops 21.81 points, to 1,843.17, while Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index declines 12.91 points, to 1,148.60; graph; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks fell sharply yesterday, after the government said that United States economic growth for the second quarter remained weak.</p>
        <p>For the second quarter, the gross domestic product grew at a revised annual rate of 0.2 percent, the Commerce Department said. That number was less than the 0.7 percent the department had reported in its advance estimate in July and below the first-quarter growth rate of 1.3 percent. Analysts had been expecting the revision to be flat or slightly negative and had begun to forecast that a recession could be imminent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks fell sharply Thursday, after the government said that United States economic growth for the second quarter remained weak</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks fell sharply yesterday, after the government said that United States economic growth for the second quarter remained weak.</p>
        <p>For the second quarter, the gross domestic product grew at a revised annual rate of 0.2 percent, the Commerce Department said. That number was less than the 0.7 percent the department had reported in its advance estimate in July and below the first-quarter growth rate of 1.3 percent. Analysts had been expecting the revision to be flat or slightly negative and had begun to forecast that a recession could be imminent.</p>
        <p>When the government released a revision this morning that was slightly better than expected, stocks edged higher on the news. But by late morning the market had turned decidedly negative as investors digested the report.</p>
        <p>''When it first hits, it's like a relief rally,'' said James W. Paulsen, chief investment officer at Wells Capital Management. ''But then as people look through the report and see what's really the difference between a 0.2 and a negative 0.01?''</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average fell 131.13 points, or 1.3 percent, to 10,090.90. The technology-weighted Nasdaq composite index dropped 21.81 points, or 1.2 percent, to 1,843.17, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index declined 12.91 points, or 1.1 percent, to 1,148.60.</p>
        <p>Last week, Cisco Systems, which said it saw signs that its business might be stabilizing, touched off a rally that produced a 4 percent one-day gain in the Nasdaq.</p>
        <p>While yesterday's report from the government seemed to confirm the widespread notion that the economy was bumping along the bottom of its growth cycle, ''the worst, as far as individual companies' earnings are concerned, may not be over,'' said William V. Fries, manager of the Thornburg Value Fund.</p>
        <p>He described the market's drop yesterday not as a direct reaction to the government's report but as an unwinding of last week's rally.</p>
        <p>Comverse Technology, a software maker, fell $2.50, to $26.05, after it  reported a 20 percent decline in second-quarter earnings.</p>
        <p>Semiconductor stocks, which had been showing strength in recent weeks, pulled back sharply. Texas Instruments dropped $1.66, to $34.05; Altera slipped $1.91, to $28.05; Xilinx fell $1.83, to $37.95; and Intel slipped 41 cents, to $28.10.</p>
        <p>Financial services companies also showed weakness. Bank of America  fell $1.81, to $60.05; J. P. Morgan Chase slipped 92 cents, to $39.57; and Citigroup dropped 60 cents, to $46.45.</p>
        <p>One of the few bright spots in the market was the merger of the paper makers Mead and Westvaco. They said the all-stock transaction was worth $3 billion. Mead gained $1.99, to $32.17; Westvaco rose $2.09, to $29.75.</p>
        <p>The revision of the gross domestic product followed a report from the Conference Board on Tuesday that consumer confidence in August fell to its lowest level in four months. Analysts said the negative effect of the economic reports could only be counteracted by positive news from corporations.</p>
        <p>''Once we set out a program where investors start getting a little more confidence, I think this market can rebound sharply in a short amount of time,'' said John Forelli, a senior vice president and portfolio manager at Independence Investment.</p>
        <p>''That catalyst has not yet appeared,'' he added. ''We don't see one appearing for the next weeks or months. We expect near-term news out of both the economy and companies to be negative.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Treasuries Are Higher</p>
        <p>(By Reuters) -- Treasury bond princes rose yesterday after a government report indicated the economy barely grew in the second quarter, bolstering hopes of another Federal Reserve interest rate cut.</p>
        <p>The 10-year note rose 19/32, to a price of 101 28/32. The note's yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, fell to 4.76 percent from 4.84 percent on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The price of the 30-year Treasury bond rose 24/32, to 100 9/32. The bond's yield fell to 5.36 percent from 5.41 percent on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Following are the results of yesterday's Treasury auction of two-year notes:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>High Price: 99.885  High Yield: 3.685%  Low Yield: 3.620%  Median Yield: 3.650%  Accepted at low price: 31%  Total applied for: $34,980,539  Accepted: $18,666,698  Noncompetitive: $1,095,176  Interest set at: 3 5/8</p>
        <p>The notes mature on Aug. 31, 2003.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
