<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH LEAVES OPEN TIMING OF ASSAULT ON IRAQ'S FORCES</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="413222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY ACTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, ANDREW</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, JAMES A 3D (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEREZ DE CUELLAR, JAVIER (SEC GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AZIZ, TARIQ (MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DB1239F935A35752C0A967958260" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH LEAVES OPEN TIMING OF ASSAULT ON IRAQ'S FORCES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSENTHAL, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush said today that American military action against Iraq would not necessarily begin immediately after Jan. 15. But he warned President Saddam Hussein in a letter that he would "face destruction" if he did not withdraw his forces from Kuwait by that date, an Administration official said.</p>
        <p>In a radio address delivered 10 days before the United Nations deadline, Mr. Bush said "time is running out" and that each additional day the United States waits to act could mean more casualties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush said today that American military action against Iraq would not necessarily begin immediately after Jan. 15. But he warned President Saddam Hussein in a letter that he would "face destruction" if he did not withdraw his forces from Kuwait by that date, an Administration official said.</p>
        <p>In a radio address delivered 10 days before the United Nations deadline, Mr. Bush said "time is running out" and that each additional day the United States waits to act could mean more casualties.</p>
        <p>"We risk paying a higher price in the most precious currency of all -- human life -- if we give Saddam more time to prepare for war," Mr. Bush said. No 'Secret Diplomacy'</p>
        <p>The President, who met today with the United Nations Secretary General to review the crisis, promised in his speech to explore a peaceful solution. But he said there would be no "secret diplomacy" when Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d meets with Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz of Iraq in Geneva on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>"Secretary Baker will restate, in person, a message for Saddam Hussein: Withdraw from Kuwait unconditionally and immediately, or face the terrible consequences," Mr. Bush said.  [ Text of his address, page 4. ]</p>
        <p>In an apparent effort to step up the pressure, Mr. Bush used blunter language in a letter that Mr. Baker is to hand Mr. Aziz in Geneva. A senior Administration official said the letter warns Mr. Hussein that he must withdraw his troops from Kuwait or "face destruction." 'Two Choices' for Hussein</p>
        <p>"The letter says to Saddam, you have two choices: Get out or we will use force, there will be a war," the official said. The purpose of the letter, the official said, is to "hand over something tangible that Saddam Hussein will have to read in case Tariq Aziz doesn't have the nerve to repeat our message word for word."</p>
        <p>In Baghdad today, a senior Iraqi official said the Iraqi leadership still believed that a meeting in Baghdad between Mr. Baker and President Hussein should "not be excluded" from the final rounds of diplomacy. But Iraq rejected a meeting with the European Community, which on Friday offered to work to resolve all problems of the Middle East if the gulf crisis could be settled peacefully.  [ Page 4. ]</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush seems to be leaving himself some room to maneuver at a time when the United States expects a flurry of diplomatic activity -- perhaps even some new effort by Mr. Hussein.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said the United States was approaching the meeting with Mr. Aziz with the expectation that the Iraqi official would come with some kind of surprise. The challenge for Washington, they said, was to find a way to continue to show a desire for a peaceful solution without raising public expectations or pressure to make a deal with Iraq.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker will be in London on Monday to meet with European Community officials. Mr. Bush has said he would reject any direct linkage between the gulf crisis and the plight of the Palestinians, but has not explicitly ruled out an approach like the one suggested by the European Community. The White House has otherwise been silent on the European offer to address Middle East issues generally, and Mr. Bush did not mention it in his speech, which was taped on Friday.</p>
        <p>Asked about the proposal today, an Administration official said the White House considered it a "nonstarter" but did not want to get into a public dispute with its European allies about it. The official said the United States viewed the proposal as linking the gulf crisis with other Middle Eastern issues, but that the Europeans did not define it that way.</p>
        <p>"It's a matter of semantics that's certainly not worth creating a hornet's nest about," the official said. Meeting With U.N. Chief</p>
        <p>France, which had extracted the commitment from the community to help resolve other Middle East conflicts, also suggested that it would be "desirable" for the United Nations Security Council to meet again near Jan. 15 "before unleashing a war."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush met today at his Camp David retreat in Maryland with the United Nations Secretary General, Javier Perez de Cuellar. Mr. Bush said on Friday that while he did not see any need for further United Nations action, "I'd be interested to hear if the Secretary General feels to the contrary."</p>
        <p>A White House statement issued after the meeting said the two men "discussed the general situation in the gulf, including diplomatic activities aimed at resolving the crisis in a peaceful manner." Mr. Bush had invited the United Nations leader to Camp David to compare notes. White House officials gave no indication that anything more than that had occurred.</p>
        <p>In his radio address, Mr. Bush said, "We should go the extra mile before asking our servicemen and women to stand in harm's way," adding, "We should and we have." He called next week's meeting between Mr. Baker and Mr. Aziz "one more step." 'Time Is Running Out'</p>
        <p>"Eleven days from today, Saddam Hussein will either have met the United Nations deadline for a full and unconditional withdrawal, or he will have once again defied the civilized world," Mr. Bush said. "This is a deadline for Saddam Hussein to comply with the United Nations resolution, not a deadline for our own armed forces."</p>
        <p>The remark seemed to give the President some leeway in case the meeting between Mr. Baker and Mr. Aziz produces some movement toward ending the stalemate in the Middle East. But Mr. Bush said: "Time is running out. It's running out because each day that passes brings real costs."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, who has drawn criticism for not fully explaining his reasons for contemplating war, said that Iraq "already poses a strategic threat to the capital cities of Egypt, Saudi Arabia, Turkey, Israel and Syria" with its missiles and warplanes. Burden of Rising Oil Prices</p>
        <p>He noted that Iraq has chemical weapons, and he repeated his assertion that "each day that passes brings Saddam Hussein further on the path to developing biological and nuclear weapons and the missiles to deliver them."</p>
        <p>"If Saddam corners the world energy market, he can then finance further aggression," Mr. Bush said. "Each day that passes increases Saddam's worldwide threat to democracy."</p>
        <p>The President also raised an economic argument: higher oil prices are "a crushing burden" that the new democracies in Eastern Europe and Latin America cannot afford. "Our own economy is suffering," he said, "suffering the effects of higher oil prices and lower growth stemming from Saddam's aggression."</p>
        <p>He said the economic sanctions imposed on Iraq by the United Nations "are taking a toll, but they are still not forcing Saddam out of Kuwait."</p>
        <p>"Nor do we know when or even if they will be successful," he said.</p>
        <p>CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
