<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Was Serenely Independent and Yet ...</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="413504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SINCLAIR, ANDREW</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARRISON, REX</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">A DAMNED SERIOUS BUSINESS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDF123FF935A35752C0A967958260" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Was Serenely Independent and Yet ...</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew Sinclair; Andrew Sinclair's most recent books are "War Like a Wasp," on the arts in Britain in the 1940's, and "The Need to Give: The Patrons and the Arts."</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SINCLAIR, ANDREW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A DAMNED SERIOUS BUSINESS  By Rex Harrison. Illustrated. 288 pp. New York: Bantam Books. $21.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A DAMNED SERIOUS BUSINESS  By Rex Harrison. Illustrated. 288 pp. New York: Bantam Books. $21.95.</p>
        <p>WE had grown accustomed to his face. It was wrought so artfully. The slit eyes of superior amusement, the lines that mockery etched at the corner of eye and nostril and mouth, the generous and skeptical lips -- these were the features and the weapons that Rex Harrison created to win his audience and his knighthood. His was the mobile mask of high comedy.</p>
        <p>He saw himself as the heir of Sir Gerald du Maurier, not of Sir Henry Irving. Restraint was his profession. His polish was his performance. He was the noble egotist, the sympathetic cad, the supreme Professor Henry Higgins.</p>
        <p>In "A Damned Serious Business," his last observations on his life in comedy, he declares that Shaw was his Shakespeare. In fact he had discovered that his attempts to speak the words of the Bard were like missing an appointment. His impeccable timing could not state, "What is't o'clock?" If anything, he preferred, "Got the time on yer?" It amused him more.</p>
        <p>Vulgar and vain, appealing and arrogant, Rex Harrison always worked at what he did best: presenting a superior facade over calculated insecurity. This book is another demonstration of his art. Often he repeats others' praise of his performances, all the way from Kenneth Tynan to Louis Armstrong, who told him that he was hitting every note right down the middle in "My Fair Lady." Yet he confesses his hysteria before accepting any role, particularly that of Higgins, and he reveals the fearful labor required to invent for that part a new form of</p>
        <p>Sprechgesang,</p>
        <p>which he claimed to have derived from music-hall patter.</p>
        <p>That is where he hits every note right down the middle in "A Damned Serious Business," a quotation taken from a description of comedy by the 18th-century actor David Garrick. He is absorbing on how essential props are to an actor; the adroit use of things points the scene. The cigarette lighter put in front of the face stops the other actor in full flow. He has to light up and shut up. In fact the banning of smoking onstage has made comic acting far more difficult. What can the poor players do with their hands, how may they whet their performance? Du Maurier is praised for having had a brand of cigarettes named after him, while Olivier's brand rapidly became a dead butt.</p>
        <p>Actually, Lord Olivier was something of a hero to Sir Rex, because his hybrid style of dangerous acting comprehended both high comedy and Shakespearean rant. Olivier and Vivien Leigh were friends of Harrison and his third wife, the comedienne Kay Kendall, whose slow dying of leukemia found a link in Leigh's self-destruction. Although the book is discreet to the point of no-show on the subject of Harrison's many marriages (surpassed in number by Alan Jay Lerner's), it does tell some intimate stories, which are the stock in trade of a theatrical life.</p>
        <p>One story has a wife of Lerner's, after he had taken a stroll with Harrison down Fifth Avenue, accusing him of ignoring her and screaming, "What you really mean, Alan, is why can't a woman be more like a man?" -- only to have this tiff transposed to a lyric for "My Fair Lady." Another is about his repertory days with the English actor A. E. Matthews, when the two were drinking in a railroad inn while waiting for a train and Matthews asked impatiently, "What time does this bloody hotel get to London?" Another tale is a complaint about acting in a film with Charles Laughton and not being able to get into the picture -- the screen was simply too full of the fat man. And Harrison's comments on the "Scratch and Grunt School" of method acting taste like a mouthwash of mustard.</p>
        <p>Bitching and telling stories of something funny happening on the way to the theater are the spice of the performing arts. But there are already too many published versions of such carping and fond memoirs. Every star has attempted one or two -- on tape if illiterate, by proxy if inconsequential. Yet teaching manuals are rare, especially on how to play high comedy. Fort Knox does not guard its gold more carefully than an actor hoards his or her secret art, only flashing it on paid display. If "A Damned Serious Business" had revealed more of Sir Rex's mastery of timing and bits of business, it would have been damned serious reading. But between the mockery and the anecdotes, there are precious few lessons, and many mistakes.</p>
        <p>An envoi declares that this book remains exactly as Sir Rex left it when he died last year at the age of 82. Alas, exactly so. The farceur Ralph Lynn was not "Lynne," while the showman "Cochrane" was Cochran. Willy Lomas did not appear in "Death of a Salesman," nor did Gladys Cooper win an Oscar for "My Fair Lady." A magnificent sloppiness pervades this missed opportunity. But it is characteristic of an actor who was no author. As he says of himself and of his self-centered life, "Nobody is as interesting to spend an evening with as a really good part."</p>
        <p>That is an honest statement, and the statement of a true craftsman. He put his life on the stage and the screen, from which he made his living, and on which his presence endures. But such commitment to performance cannot reach the page. Sir Rex was star-struck and character-deep. The perfection of his timing and the studied instinct of his gestures are to be viewed, not to be read. He was and is what the eye can see and the ear hear, and that is all.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
