<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Expos Wins Seventh Straight; Reds' Rijo Breaks His Ankle</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="454272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DC1731F932A15755C0A967958260" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Expos Wins Seventh Straight; Reds' Rijo Breaks His Ankle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>CINCINNATI, June 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dennis Martinez anchored a combined three-hitter and Marquis Grissom singled home a run in the 11th inning tonight as the Montreal Expos beat the Cincinnati Reds for their seventh consecutive victory.</p>
        <p>In the sixth inning, Reds pitcher Jose Rijo broke his right ankle attempting to steal a base.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dennis Martinez anchored a combined three-hitter and Marquis Grissom singled home a run in the 11th inning tonight as the Montreal Expos beat the Cincinnati Reds for their seventh consecutive victory.</p>
        <p>In the sixth inning, Reds pitcher Jose Rijo broke his right ankle attempting to steal a base.</p>
        <p>Martinez gave up two hits over the first eight innings, Barry Jones (3-4) gave up one in the next two, and Scott Ruskin pitched the 11th for his fifth save, giving Montreal a 7-2 record in extra-inning games this season.</p>
        <p>Spike Owen led off the 11th with the Expos' sixth hit of the game off Don Carman (0-1), the fourth Cincinnati pitcher. Bret Barberie sacrificed him to second, and Grissom lined an r.b.i. single to right.</p>
        <p>Martinez, whose earned run average dropped to 1.87, retired the first 17 batters he faced before Rijo lined a single up the middle with two outs in the sixth. The right-hander allowed just one more hit, a soft single in the eighth by Todd Benzinger, as he extended his streak of consecutive scoreless innings to 24.</p>
        <p>In the sixth inning, Rijo caught his cleats while sliding into second base on a steal attempt. X-rays at Christ Hospital found a chip fracture on the inside of the right ankle. Rijo, the 1990 World Series most valuable player, will be out four to six weeks. Phillies 7, Astros 3</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA (AP) -- Rookie Wes Chamberlain had four hits and John Kruk drove three runs to lead Philadelphia over Houston.</p>
        <p>Chamberlain, who played in 18 games for the Phillies in 1990 and saw brief action in April, was recalled from Scranton-Wilkes-Barre of the International League on June 15. He is 10 for 24 in six games since returning.</p>
        <p>Danny Cox (2-1), who came off the disabled list on June 17, gave up two runs and three hits in five and two-thirds innings. Dodgers 3, Pirates 2</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES (AP) -- Stan Javier's bad-hop single in the eighth inning gave Los Angeles its fifth straight victory.</p>
        <p>Brett Butler led off the eighth with a single off John Smiley (8-4) and was sacrificed by Juan Samuel. Javier followed with what appeared to be a routine grounder to shortstop, but the ball bounced over the outstretched glove of Jay Bell.</p>
        <p>The Pirates have lost five of their last eight games. Giants 4, Cubs 3</p>
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) -- Robby Thompson and Will Clark had r.b.i. singles and another run scored on a wild pitch in the seventh inning as San Francisco dealt Chicago its sixth consecutive defeat.</p>
        <p>Francisco Oliveras (3-2) worked two innings in relief of rookie Mike Remlinger to earn the victory. Dave Righetti got the last three outs for his eighth save. Royals 3, Orioles 2</p>
        <p>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) -- Brian McRae singled home Kurt Stillwell from second base with one out in the 10th inning as Kansas City beat Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Stillwell drew a leadoff walk from Todd Frohwirth (1-1) and Terry Shumpert sacrificed. McRae followed with a drive over the head of center fielder Brady Anderson.</p>
        <p>Steve Crawford (2-0) got the victory as Kansas City evened its record at .500 for the first time since April 27. Baltimore has lost three straight games and five consecutive times to the Royals dating back to last season. Angels 7, Tigers 5</p>
        <p>DETROIT (AP) -- Dave Parker's tie-breaking, two-run homer in the seventh inning sent California past Detroit in a game interrupted by a bench-clearing, beanball dispute.</p>
        <p>California rookie Luis Sojo was hit in the head by a pitch from Dan Gakeler in the fourth inning, and was admitted to a hospital with a mild concussion. In the bottom of the fourth, Chuck Finley was ejected after hitting Detroit's Mickey Tettleton in the leg with his first pitch.</p>
        <p>The dugouts emptied after Tettleton was hit, but no punches were thrown. Angels Manager Doug Rader argued the ejection. Brewers 4, Mariners 0</p>
        <p>MILWAUKEE (AP) -- Jaime Navarro pitched a four-hitter for the second shutout victory of his career Milwaukee defeated Seattle.</p>
        <p>Navarro (7-4) struck out four and walked two. He gave up four singles in his team-high fourth complete game and second shutout of the season.</p>
        <p>The Mariners put runners on first and second with one out in the seventh inning, but shortstop Dale Sveum caught Omar Vizquel's line drive and threw to first base, doubling off Dave Cochrane. Rangers 7, White Sox 3</p>
        <p>CHICAGO (AP) -- Ruben Sierra sparked a five-run rally in the ninth inning with a two-run homer against Bobby Thigpen as Texas defeated Chicago.</p>
        <p>Chicago starter Jack McDowell pitched three-hit ball for eight innings and left with a 3-2 lead. Thigpen (3-2), who converted 57 of 65 save opportunities last year, blew his fifth save in 18 chances.</p>
        <p>Julio Franco followed Sierra's go-ahead homer with another home run off Thigpen.</p>
        <p>Nineteen-year-old Ivan Rodriguez, married earlier in the day after being called up Tulsa, added a two-run single off Melido Perez to complete the scoring.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez, a catcher who also threw out two runners trying steal, postponed the wedding Wednesday night to get to Chicago in time to play his first major league game.  Red Sox 8, Athletics 7</p>
        <p>BOSTON (AP) -- Tom Brunansky doubled home the tying run and then scored on Tony Pena's single in the eighth inning Boston ended its three-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Oakland went ahead 7-6 in the seventh with the help of Willie Wilson's 2,000th career hit before Boston bounced back.</p>
        <p>Mike Greenwell began the comeback with a single off first baseman Mark McGwire's glove. Steve Chitren (1-2) relieved Curt Young and threw a wild pitch.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
