<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Campaign Trail, Edwards Is Working on Sounding Vice Presidential</title>
    <meta content="26EDWARDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="P" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/26/politics/campaign/26edwards.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1599508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="DEVELOPING THE STRATEGIES: THE NORTH CAROLINA SENATOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John Edwards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Edwards, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kerry, John F</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2D8143DF935A15754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Campaign Trail, Edwards Is Working on Sounding Vice Presidential</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On the Campaign Trail, Edwards Is Working on Sounding Vice-Presidential</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>SAN ANTONIO, July 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Edwards tailors message to reflect his position on ticket, reserving spotlight for Sen John Kerry; in comparison with stump speech he gave during primary season, Edwards appears more measured in tone; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Those who saw John Edwards in the final weeks of his own presidential campaign last spring, when he had buffed his stump speech to a shine, know that the rougher version he is giving these days is still very much a work in progress.</p>
        <p>That's largely because Mr. Edwards has had to go from a speech pushing his own skills to one praising his running mate -- from, in essence, ''me, me, me'' to ''him, him, him.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Edwards' stump speech is still a work in progress, as Mr. Edwards has had to go from a speech pushing his own skills to one praising his running mate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Those who saw John Edwards in the final weeks of his own presidential campaign last spring, when he had buffed his stump speech to a shine, know that the rougher version he is giving these days is still very much a work in progress.</p>
        <p>That's largely because Mr. Edwards has had to go from a speech pushing his own skills to one praising his running mate -- from, in essence, ''me, me, me'' to ''him, him, him.''</p>
        <p>''It's a difficult transition to make,'' said one top campaign strategist.</p>
        <p>In the week and a half that he has been campaigning on his own, Mr. Edwards has run a purposely low-key campaign, focusing on fund-raisers and reserving the spotlight for the party's presumptive presidential nominee, John Kerry. On stage Sunday afternoon at an old rail depot near downtown San Antonio that has been transformed into a gleaming events hall, Mr. Edwards was as smooth and energized as he has been on his solo tour.</p>
        <p>''We are excited about opening our convention in Boston tomorrow,'' Mr. Edwards said, working all sides of the stage, arms raised, palms out. ''We want the country to hear our positive view, our optimistic view to restore American values.''</p>
        <p>Part of the difference in Mr. Edwards's speech, of course, is that he is no longer his own boss.</p>
        <p>When Larry King asked him on CNN last week whether he had to clear his speeches with Mr. Kerry's campaign, Mr. Edwards demurred. ''That's evolving, is the honest answer to that question,'' he said. ''But for the most part, Senator Kerry and I have just gone out and done our thing.''</p>
        <p>True as far as it goes, aides to both men say. The running mate may have a long leash, but it is still a leash. ''Let's put it this way,'' one Edwards strategist said. ''We are running one campaign here, not two.''</p>
        <p>Although those who did not see him on stage during the primaries may not notice it, still missing from Mr. Edwards's speeches is the deep sense of confidence in the material, tested and honed on crowd after crowd, that allowed him to give exactly the same speech, time after time, down to the smallest throwaway line, with the sense that it was tumbling out of his head newborn.</p>
        <p>In his primary speech, for instance, he would always include a line about President Bush's Medicare legislation with the supreme confidence, based on hundreds of speeches, that it would elicit a hall-rumbling groan from his audience. Then, Mr. Edwards would pause, grin, point his finger and say, ''Right answer!'' as though they were the first audience he had encountered who had gotten it right.</p>
        <p>Such moments are either absent or rare now, but one can see him working toward them. Now he is as likely to elicit an audience response in a less subtle way, by asking them a direct question. (''Aren't you sick of it?'' he asks about negative television advertising. Invariably, they are.)</p>
        <p>But it is still early in the campaign, aides point out, and Mr. Edwards has been largely limited to fund-raising events and further distracted by the need to assemble an acceptance speech for the convention, which will introduce him to a national audience.</p>
        <p>A senior campaign official said Sunday that Mr. Edwards's convention speech was essentially finished, except for some last-minute fine-tuning, and will run about 20 minutes. He will touch on the theme of ''two Americas'' -- one rich and one struggling -- that was the touchstone of his own primary campaign, as well as the war in Iraq, but will dedicate most of the address to describing Mr. Kerry's strengths, laying out his own background and explaining their vision for America, the official said.</p>
        <p>As for tone, it will be upbeat and optimistic. ''It's hard to imagine someone listening to the speech and not thinking it's positive,'' the senior official said.</p>
        <p>He said that Mr. Edwards and Mr. Kerry had spoken several times about their convention speeches, including a phone chat on Sunday morning, but that neither candidate had requested that the other make any changes. Neither did Mr. Kerry's top aides dictate the shape of Mr. Edwards's speech, the official said. ''They didn't say A, B, C. They didn't say these are the parameters,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards wrote ''most of the speech'' himself, the official said, beginning with an outline scrawled in longhand followed by more than two dozen typewritten versions updated with marginalia during down periods on the campaign trail.</p>
        <p>''I think, in some ways, Edwards's convention speech is more important than any vice president's speech I can recall,'' said Bill Carrick, a veteran Democratic strategist. ''And his stump speech is important for the same reason. Edwards gives Kerry something that he really needs. Edwards's middle-class background and folksy appeal help dilute this idea that Kerry is a blueblood who went to all the best schools.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Edwards's demonstrated stump appeal was one of the top reasons he was asked to be Mr. Kerry's running mate.</p>
        <p>At his best, Mr. Edwards has a stand-up comic's effortless rapport with a crowd, creating the illusion that it is not a speech or a performance, but a conversation. The difference is that Mr. Edwards reaches for inspiration rather than amusement and keeps the sentiment from easing into treacle with a combination of boyish charm and self-deprecating humor.</p>
        <p>In a speech in Florida last week, he told the audience about how ''we decided on this ticket,'' then caught himself, paused, and said with a sheepish smile, ''I mean, he decided on this ticket.'' The audience laughed. He grinned.</p>
        <p>But so skilled can Mr. Edwards be with faux ad-libs that those following the campaign discussed afterward whether it had been an actual slip of the tongue or the first appearance of some new material in the stump speech, a way of winningly genuflecting to Mr. Kerry's alpha status at the top of the ticket.</p>
        <p>Something similar happened Sunday in San Antonio, when Mr. Edwards referred to his running mate as ''President Kerry,'' and then blushed, apologized and added: ''Well, why don't I go ahead and say it right.''</p>
        <p>Rosalind DeLaGarza, who runs a San Antonio antique business and is on the steering committee of a group called ''Texans for Kerry,'' studied speech communications in college, and said she marvels at Mr. Edwards's stump skills.</p>
        <p>''You really get the sense that he's authentic, because you can tell he truly believes what he's talking about,'' Ms. DeLaGarza said. ''He's very confident in his body stance and he conveys such honesty, which is what the country really needs now.''</p>
        <p>DEVELOPING THE STRATEGIES: THE NORTH CAROLINA SENATOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
