<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recalling the Musical Matriarchs Who Gave Birth to the Blues</title>
    <meta content="28JEFF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="968537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jefferson, Margo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallace, Sippie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Bessie (1894?-1937)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waters, Ethel (1896-1977)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EFDE1431F93BA15753C1A961958260" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recalling the Musical Matriarchs Who Gave Birth to the Blues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGO JEFFERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jefferson, Margo</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Margo Jefferson Critic's Notebook column deplores underappreciation of female blues singers of 1920's, both the greats like Ethel Waters and Bessie Smith and some lesser artists who are included in a new two-CD anthology, I Can't Be Satisfied; photo of Sippie Wallace; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All-women anthologies of any sort tend to make some people think: ''Oh, yes, women's studies. I don't really have to pay any attention unless I happen to have a special interest in the subject.''</p>
        <p>But I've been listening to a two-CD set of female blues singers from the 1920's, and they're wrong. It's called ''I Can't Be Satisfied'' (Yazoo), and it is one of quite a few such collections you can find nowadays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All-women anthologies of any sort tend to make some people think: ''Oh, yes, women's studies. I don't really have to pay any attention unless I happen to have a special interest in the subject.''</p>
        <p>But I've been listening to a two-CD set of female blues singers from the 1920's, and they're wrong. It's called ''I Can't Be Satisfied'' (Yazoo), and it is one of quite a few such collections you can find nowadays.</p>
        <p>Thanks to the recording industry, these were the black singers who first brought the blues to a white culture that proceeded to embrace, imbibe, copy and amend the form for use in every branch of popular music. It is exactly the process that would take place 30 years later, when male blues singers set rock-and-roll in motion. But there was never a danger of that story becoming marginal. It is a tale told again and again, each time as though it were a new-found heroic saga.</p>
        <p>Honor the bold and primal black men, the saga goes, who made music filled with cool humor, tough-minded grief and sexual heat. Celebrate the daring young white men who dismantled the shackles of genteel pop music and, struck by the blues as if by a thunderbolt from the gods, determined to master and extend its power. Black bluesmen are celebrated for their musical and racial purity. (The two become identical in this tale.) White rockers are praised for their explorer's cunning and inventiveness.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the blueswomen who set this cultural process in motion generally get ignored (or offered a brief, dutiful nod) in histories and anthologies of blues and rock.</p>
        <p>Of course, there were individuals, collectors and historians like Chris Albertson and Rosetta Reitz, who made sure that some of these singers stayed in our minds and record collections. But even greats like Bessie Smith and Ethel Waters are still treated as though they were sideshows to the main events in the great pop music narrative.</p>
        <p>Why? The most tired standard answer is that these women sullied the blues when they took them into commercial arenas. But what is rock-and-roll if not commercial music? And what were black bluesmen, who had worked in small-change semi-obscurity for years, finally able to do, but enter just those arenas, thanks to rock's mass popularity?</p>
        <p>The second most tired standard answer is that these women mingled the strictly black blues form with other more miscegenated or white-based forms like ragtime and pop songs. But rock singers do nothing but mix and match. And when rock critics admire a performer, they salute this mix as a sign of imaginative potency.</p>
        <p>I'm not claiming that every woman on ''I Can't Be Satisfied'' (or any other anthology) is a Bessie Smith or an Ethel Waters. Some sound as if they got rustled into a recording studio by an agent who didn't know any better, and made do with a creditable imitation of some blue notes and phrasings. (A quality they share with the lesser male singers to be found in so many anthologies.)</p>
        <p>The greats tend to have their own CD's; so, now, do first-rate second-tier performers like Memphis Minnie and Ma Rainey, who each get one cut in this collection. So does Clara Smith, known as the Queen of the Moaners and thought by many to be Bessie's equal. Otherwise, the best-known singers are Bertha (Chippie) Hill, Sippie Wallace and Victoria Spivey, whose records have slipped in and out of print since the 1970's.</p>
        <p>A lot of the women in this collection are third-tier, but they have plenty to offer, because when a form is in its heyday, even the minor players know just what to do with it. There is nothing but blues authenticity here; and so much temperamental variety, too.</p>
        <p>Volume I features rural and small-town-based singers, backed by guitar, piano or jug band. Memphis Minnie is tough, hard and totally in control. Irene Scruggs is high-voiced and high-strung. Geeshie Wiley saunters through dance songs about men, money and moving on, while Bertha Henderson's are slow-moan soliloquies.</p>
        <p>Volume II showcases the urban singers who toured and recorded regularly, often with a jazz-inflected trio or quartet. With that long beautiful line of hers, Clara Smith gives intensity a kind of ease. Victoria Spivey's quavering voice and songs about death and violence make her a creature of obsessions and mood plunges.</p>
        <p>Ma Rainey has a voice like a ball and chain, but a steady, generous temperament: her blues are chapters in a story, and she is always the omniscient narrator.</p>
        <p>Blues singers are making their way through contrary feelings and states of mind, and the voice has to show it. Good and great singers resist and submit to the beat, and they do the same with pitch, sliding around or into notes as if they were testing them. (The test of a dreary to bad blues singer is that the phrasing rarely if ever varies from verse to verse, so the sense of emotions in process gives way to claustrophobia.)</p>
        <p>I imagine that some readers shrieked with horror when I cited Ethel Waters as a great blues singer several paragraphs back. Ethel Waters? She and her ilk used white -- i.e., theater and cabaret -- diction, and they sang at least as many pop songs as they did blues. The shadow accusation? They were race social climbers and turncoats.</p>
        <p>Ethel Waters (like Alberta Hunter and others) used varieties of white speech and diction as theatrical and musical tools. She did the same with varieties of black speech and diction. That's what speech and diction are for when you're a singer.</p>
        <p>Bessie Smith is generally considered to come as close as a woman can to singing wholly authentic blues. (She would be home free if she had played the guitar.) But if you listen closely, you will hear in that big, beautiful, ostensibly all-black Southern voice some crisp Northern consonants and word pronunciations applied whenever they suit a musical line or lyric.</p>
        <p>Everyone says it's a new age for girl rockers and rappers: they are free to play fast and loose with any musical style or stance now; free to be smart, wanton, moody, passionate or killer cynical. Every age has its past, though, and if these 90's women are looking, they can find a good part of theirs in the unpredictable, unexpurgated voices of these 1920's blueswomen.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
