<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Horse of a Different Color, Literally</title>
    <meta content="RACE28" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="968746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3D91531F93BA15753C1A961958260" item-length="377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Horse of a Different Color, Literally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Patchen Beauty, all-white race horse, preparing for her maiden race (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>She is untested as a race horse and comes from a line of also-rans, but Patchen Beauty's place in history is secure.</p>
        <p>The 2-year-old filly's fame was guaranteed at birth, when she literally appeared as a horse of a different color. Patchen Beauty is pure white, making her only the ninth white thoroughbred registered with the Jockey Club.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>She is untested as a race horse and comes from a line of also-rans, but Patchen Beauty's place in history is secure.</p>
        <p>The 2-year-old filly's fame was guaranteed at birth, when she literally appeared as a horse of a different color. Patchen Beauty is pure white, making her only the ninth white thoroughbred registered with the Jockey Club.</p>
        <p>''I think she's a celebrity, but she's kept her head,'' her owner, Warren Rosenthal, said. ''She knows she gets a lot of attention. She even gets attention from the other horses. They look at her a little bit funny, too.''</p>
        <p>Rosenthal said his young prize is a ''sweet-tempered horse.''</p>
        <p>''Of course, she's been spoiled since she was born,'' he said. ''So she's very calm and easy to handle and enjoys being patted.''</p>
        <p>The filly is stabled at Churchill Downs' off-track barns in Louisville, Ky., and is being prepared for her maiden race at the fall meet.</p>
        <p>It was not purely accidental that Patchen Beauty was born pure white at Rosenthal's Patchen Wilkes Farm in Lexington, Ky. Her mother and great-grandmother were white. Her sire, Hatchet Man, was gray.</p>
        <p>Her great-grandmother, White Beauty, became the first white thoroughbred registered with the Jockey Club. Rosenthal did not own the white matriarch but owns the filly's mother, Precious Beauty.</p>
        <p>Rosenthal hopes that Patchen Beauty does not emulate her mother and great-grandmother as a runner. White Beauty won just once, and Rosenthal said that was ''by accident.''</p>
        <p>White Beauty's only victory came on a cold, wet fall day when attendance was sparse at Keeneland in Lexington, so there was little crowd noise to distract her.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>Yonkers Raceway  Races Are Canceled</p>
        <p>Yonkers Raceway, citing a lack of money, has canceled the Clare Pace and the William Haughton Memorial Pace, the track's general manager, Bob Galteria, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The $35,000 Clare was scheduled for Saturday, and the $100,000 Haughton Memorial was to be raced on Nov. 7.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Yonkers canceled the George Morton Levy Pace and the Cane Pace.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
