<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Tyranny of Time In Every Detail? Creepy</title>
    <meta content="20COTT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="ART REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="938265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Museum of Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotter, Holland</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Ivan (1897-1983)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDC153EF933A15755C0A961958260" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Tyranny of Time In Every Detail? Creepy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOLLAND COTTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotter, Holland</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Holland Cotter reviews exhibition of the paintings of Ivan Albright at Metropolitan Museum of Art; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Summertime often produces a rash of grade-B horror films catering to a vacation state of mind. But the creepiest show to hit town so far this season is an exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum of Art titled ''Ivan Albright: Magic Realist.''</p>
        <p>Albright, who lived from 1897 to 1983, was born near Chicago and spent much of his life in that city. He came from a family of artists (his father was a painter, as was his identical twin, Malvin) and studied  at prestigious schools. But early on he concocted a style that was peculiarly his own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Summertime often produces a rash of grade-B horror films catering to a vacation state of mind. But the creepiest show to hit town so far this season is an exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum of Art titled ''Ivan Albright: Magic Realist.''</p>
        <p>Albright, who lived from 1897 to 1983, was born near Chicago and spent much of his life in that city. He came from a family of artists (his father was a painter, as was his identical twin, Malvin) and studied  at prestigious schools. But early on he concocted a style that was peculiarly his own.</p>
        <p>How to describe it? Old Masterism with a ghoulish twist. Albright made no bones about citing El Greco, Rembrandt and Velazquez as his models and his peers, but the human figure as he envisioned it was a zany, bad-dream version of the classical ideal.</p>
        <p>Set under harsh, raking overhead light against black backgrounds, his men and women are human shambles in terminal decay. Every sagging fold, branching wrinkle and blemish of their lividly colored flesh is rendered in fascinated close-up, suggesting some far-gone organic matter freshly turned up by a spade.</p>
        <p>Albright's painting isn't, however, realism in any ordinary sense (and magical is maybe too pretty a word for it). Although he worked from live models and elaborate studio setups, he wasn't recording what was in front of him as much as applying to it a cosmetic repertory of grisly ornamental effects. Whether he was painting a young woman in ''Into the World There Came a Soul Called Ida'' (1929-30) or a self-portrait, the spectacle of unsightly bumps, rheumy eyes and puckered cellulite is the same. Even when he toned things down for a commissioned work, like his portrait of the Chicago art collector Mary Lasker Block, it made little difference. With her demonic eyes and cast-iron perm, the sitter looks like Mamie Eisenhower as played by Linda Blair.</p>
        <p>Fittingly, the artist's big moment in the public limelight came through a brush with Hollywood. In 1943, Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer was making a film of ''The Picture of Dorian Gray,'' the Oscar Wilde story of a young man's Faustian wish to remain eternally young while his painted portrait grew old.</p>
        <p>Who better to create that horrific image of mortality-in-process than Albright? For a year he slaved away at what was essentially a glorified film prop in his fidgety, one-inch-a-day style. And the finished product --  a 7-foot-tall figure seemingly composed of mildew and mold -- is a centerpiece of the Met show.</p>
        <p>The film, it turned out, was a bust (the Met will be screening it later in the summer), but the painting caused a stir, and Albright could probably have sold it for a bundle at the time. Instead, he held onto the piece, as he did to most of his work, eventually giving it to the Art Institute of Chicago, where the present exhibition originated. (Courtney Graham Donnell is the curator; William S. Lieberman has made a few nips and tucks for the New York appearance.)</p>
        <p>Albright could afford to be an avid self-collector. Family money along with an advantageous late-in-life marriage had left him financially independent. Yet that circumstantial ease did nothing to broaden his art. His painting remained deeply conservative, an example of end-in-itself virtuosity touched up with philosophical glosses.</p>
        <p>He got a lot of mileage, for example, out of insisting that his still lifes were 20th-century versions of Northern Baroque ''vanitas'' paintings: those elaborate table-top pileups of fly-blown fruit and withering flowers that symbolized life's transience.</p>
        <p>This, anyway, is the ostensible import of his most often reproduced painting, ''That Which I Should Have Done I Did Not Do (The Door)'' (1931-41), an image of a coffinlike door hung with a disintegrating funeral wreath. Albright worked on the piece for a decade, but to little avail. With its kitschy theatrics -- the pretentious title, the disembodied Fright Night hand reaching in from the side -- it ended up being, like much of his output, a Grand Guignol version of Norman Rockwell, nothing more.</p>
        <p>Still, it's all good clean fun, mildly engaging once you get into the swing of it, and the Met has helped out by painting its gallery walls the same bruisey purples and blues that Albright liked so well. But even such visual mood-music touches can't do much to insure Albright's lasting claim on our attention, or his place in the history books.</p>
        <p>It is true that his art connects up with a definable strain of mid-century, interwar painting, an Expressionist realism exemplified by Otto Dix and George Grosz in Europe, and Philip Evergood and Peter Blum in America. The difference, of course, is that these artists used the grotesque to make specific political statements, where in Albright's hands it was primarily a stylistic tic.</p>
        <p>But his work may be less interesting as a relic of yesteryear than as a comment on the esthetic tastes of today, when traditional painterly realism still evokes genuflections, and a downbeat vision of ''reality'' is, in some quarters at least, automatically regarded as a stamp of intellectual seriousness. In some ways, for example, Albright's decaying bodies are just a hop, skip and jump from those of Lucian Freud. Albright's paint is a lot thinner and his ideas far less urbane, but the essential resemblance is there, and perhaps a little too close for comfort, leading one to speculate how well Mr. Freud's art is going to age.</p>
        <p>And what is the significant difference between Albright's grubby figures and the rotting biological forms in paintings by a currently hot neo-magical-realist painter like Alexis Rockman? Mr. Rockman gives his work a savvy eco-sensitive spin, but his self-portrait as a decomposing corpse (in his show at Jay Gorney Modern Art in SoHo through June 28) is throughly Albrightesque in spirit, if not in fact.</p>
        <p>In sum, if there was ever a moment when Albright deserved a peek, this is probably it. The art world is already pushing predictable, Halloweenish, fin-de-siecle concepts in anticipation of the millennium. (The recent flurry of ''Gothic'' whatever seems part of this market-oriented move.) And Albright's masterly brand of freakishness -- opportunistic and entertaining, perfect for summer chills and thrills -- fits right in.</p>
        <p>''Ivan Albright: Magic Realist'' remains at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82d Street, through Sept. 7.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
