<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil Price Falls $1.39 On Rumors</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="382368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUTURES TRADING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SADDAM (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED8143FF93BA3575AC0A966958260" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil Price Falls $1.39 On Rumors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Wild rumors helped push the price of oil down yesterday for the first time in six trading days, but the price of a barrel of crude stayed above $30.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Wild rumors helped push the price of oil down yesterday for the first time in six trading days, but the price of a barrel of crude stayed above $30.</p>
        <p>Continued Volatility Expected</p>
        <p>But the shooting did not touch off the war that oil traders have been bracing for, and prices declined yesterday.</p>
        <p>But traders said that given the current volatile atmosphere and this weekend's summit meeting between the leaders of the United States and the Soviet Union, yesterday's movement gave no clue to what will happen next week.</p>
        <p>When trading ended for the week on the New York Mercantile Exchange, light, sweet crude oil for October delivery closed at $30.04, down $1.39 for the day. The close was $2.72 above last week's finish, a rise of 10 percent. Since the Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait by Iraq, the price of a barrel has risen 72.5 percent.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi coup rumor, which pushed the price down in Tokyo, circulated later in London and at the opening in New York and again early in the afternoon.</p>
        <p>A Reason to Sell</p>
        <p>Victor S. Yu, vice president of futures at Prudential-Bache Securities Inc., said the market tends to be more affected by rumors on quiet days. ''A lot of people used it as a reason to sell off,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yu said the rumors, which were unfounded, were reminiscent of frequent rumors in the 1980's that President Ronald Reagan had had a heart attack or that Iran's leader, the Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, had died. The Khomeini rumor sometimes crossed the trading floor more than once a day.</p>
        <p>Product prices also fell yesterday. Gasoline closed at 93.06 cents a gallon for October delivery, down 2.01 cents, and heating oil fell to 83.98 cents a gallon, off 4.26 cents. That brought prices back to almost exactly where they were on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department reported yesterday that for the last week in August, despite the loss of exports from Iraq and Kuwait, imports of oil rose 4 percent, to an average of 6.9 million barrels a day.</p>
        <p>Experts say that the figures for crude oil do not yet reflect the events in the Persian Gulf, which is about 45 days away by tanker. Before the Iraqi invasion 37 days ago, the longer-term trend for crude imports had been showing a decline, in part because of high inventory levels here.</p>
        <p>Data From Tanker Charters</p>
        <p>Robert P. Boslego, an oil consultant in Lexington, Mass., said the effect of the embargo was likely to be reflected soon in the amount of oil reaching American ports. But he added that an examination of tanker charter agreements over the last few weeks shows that Persian Gulf production is heading up again.</p>
        <p>The charter agreements, which cover tanker loadings that could occur any time in the following 30 days, had fallen sharply after early July, but appear in the last week to have regained about two-thirds of the decline. The data show an increase in the volume of charters bound for the United States, but that increase is relatively small, he said, indicating that most of the extra Middle East production is going to other countries.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department also released statistics yesterday indicating that even though gasoline prices at the pump are up by about 20.4 percent since the end of July, excluding taxes, this rise is modest compared with the increases in other countries. In France over the same period, prices are up 45.4 percent; in Germany, 38.5 percent; in Italy, 28.3 percent; in Britain, 25.5 percent; and Belgium, 24 percent, the department said. In Japan, prices are up 7.8 percent.</p>
        <p>In most of those countries, pretax prices are $1.50 a gallon or more, and taxes add a dollar or two. In the United States, the average pretax price is 99 cents and the average tax is 25 cents. Reverse of Normal Direction Experts say that the differential between prices here and in Europe is luring some cargoes east across the Atlantic, the reverse of the normal direction.</p>
        <p>The prices are for the gasoline commonly used in each country; for the United States, unleaded regular, and for Europe, leaded premium. The numbers are also affected somewhat by currency fluctuations, the department said.</p>
        <p>The department said gasoline inventories in the United States are at 210.9 million barrels, down slightly from the previous week and 10 million barrels below the figure a year ago. This level of stock is relatively close to what the industry calls its minimum operating inventory.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
