<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aid to Airbus Called Unfair In U.S. Study</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="382363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE, WEST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AIRBUS INDUSTRIE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMMERCE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DE143FF93BA3575AC0A966958260" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aid to Airbus Called Unfair In U.S. Study</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration intensified a long-simmering conflict over European aerospace subsidies today by reviving charges that the Airbus consortium gets unfair support from its government backers and poses a significant long-term risk to American competitiveness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration intensified a long-simmering conflict over European aerospace subsidies today by reviving charges that the Airbus consortium gets unfair support from its government backers and poses a significant long-term risk to American competitiveness.</p>
        <p>The report, which was prepared by a private consulting firm, Gellman Research Associates of suburban Philadelphia, found that the government backers of the consortium -France, West Germany, Britain and Spain - had already committed or disbursed $13.5 billion into Airbus Industrie programs since the late 1960's. With the addition of commercial interest rates, the total value of the aid was put at $25.9 billion.</p>
        <p>Yet none of the programs are commercially viable, or are likely to be, the study said. Instead, the report added, Airbus sold aircraft below cost to increase market share, a process that deprived American makers of revenues to invest in new aircraft.</p>
        <p>The subsidies ''provide an unfair advantage over United States manufacturers and could injure the industry's future competitiveness,'' said J. Michael Farren, Under Secretary of Commerce for international trade. Against an overall trade deficit last year topping $100 billion, he noted, this industry generated a $12 billion surplus.</p>
        <p>Europeans respond that the United States Government distorts free and fair trade in aerospace at least as much as the Europeans through Pentagon and National Aeronautics and Space Administration contracts and ''Buy American'' policies. According to Henri Martre, chairman of Aerospatiale, a French aerospace organization, the American industry receives at least three times as much overall support as the European.</p>
        <p>Europeans also say that the American industry is now being helped by the low dollar exchange rate, which makes American planes more competitive. Bonn has just agreed to provide Daimler-Benz guarantees of more than $2 billion to cover the currency exchange risk from Airbus programs until 1999.</p>
        <p>Daimler-Benz, Germany's largest industrial corporation, recently acquired Messerschmitt-Bolkow-Blohm, the German partner in the Airbus consortium. The other partners are Aerospatiale of France, British Aerospace and Construcciones Aeronauticas of Spain.</p>
        <p>Program Strongly Criticized</p>
        <p>Washington has strongly criticized the currency guaranty program and threatened to file charges against Bonn under the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, the world's free-trade charter. Exchange loss reimbursement undermines free trade by forestalling a normal redressment of deficits, American officials argue.</p>
        <p>The Administration has warned that it will be forced to take legal action against the consortium if the issue is not resolved by Oct. 1.</p>
        <p>A European Community spokesman, Peter Doyle, said that the publication of the report came in the middle of the negotiations and was therefore ''untimely and unhelpful.'' He added that the release was ''even more surprising'' in that it came a day after ministers from the Airbus countries had met with a member of the community's Executive Commission, Frans Andriessen, in London and concluded that there was common ground for the continuation of talks with the United States.</p>
        <p>Report 'Was Ready'</p>
        <p>Asked why the report was issued at this time, Commerce Under Secretary Farren said only that ''it was ready.'' He added that he did not expect it to affect the negotiations.</p>
        <p>The United States for at least the last five years has been highly critical of Airbus subsidies for the reasons cited in the report. But officials said this was the first time a detailed objective analysis of the subsidies had been placed within a single complete package. Entitled ''An Economic and Financial Review of Airbus Industrie,'' the report is expected to figure prominently in internal Administration discussions about what action to take on Oct. 1.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department paid Gellman Associates $50,000 for the study. The same firm did a similar paper for the department in 1986, but it was never published. The earler work cost the department $150,000.</p>
        <p>Asked whether the Europeans provided any data for the report, Aaron J. Gellman, the president of the consulting firm, said: ''We sought assistance from them. We were promised much and virtually nothing was delivered.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
