<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From a Scientist's Life, Art's Cautionary Tales</title>
    <meta content="12habe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Movies; Arts; Theater; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/12/arts/12habe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20051014T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1709033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chlorine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Zyklon B (Poison Gas)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haber, Fritz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thiessen, Vern</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charles, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ragussis, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">King, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Einstein's Gift (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Master Mind (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Haber (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Zyklon (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Haber, Fritz</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D8163FF931A25753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1048" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From a Scientist's Life, Art's Cautionary Tales</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From a Scientist's Life, Art's Cautionary Tales</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Fritz Haber, 1918 winner of Nobel prize in chemistry, Jew who developed chlorine gas, oversaw its use in World War I and fled Nazi Germany before his relatives were gassed with another of his inventions, Zyklon B, in concentration camps; Haber is subject of new play, Einstein's Gift, by Vern Thiessen, new book, Master Mind: The Rise and Fall of Fritz Haber, the Nobel Laureate Who Launched the Age of Chemical Warfare by Daniel Charles, new short film, Haber, directed by Daniel Ragussis and new opera, Zyklon, by jazz musician Peter King; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite the flurry of attention over the continuing announcements of this year's Nobel Prizewinners, many previous recipients in the prizes' 104-year history remain unfamiliar. So it is not surprising that many Americans are unaware that Fritz Haber won the 1918 Nobel in chemistry for the invention of a process used to manufacture cheap fertilizer, which helped feed billions. Or that he made modern chemical warfare possible with his development of chlorine gas and personally oversaw its use in World War I.</p>
        <p>Or that his first wife, also a chemist, seemingly distraught over his work on poison gases, shot herself through the heart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The life of 1918 Nobel Prizewinner Fritz Haber will soon become much more familiar with a new play, a new biography, a new short film and even a new opera that are either out or in the works.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite the flurry of attention over the continuing announcements of this year's Nobel Prizewinners, many previous recipients in the prizes' 104-year history remain unfamiliar. So it is not surprising that many Americans are unaware that Fritz Haber won the 1918 Nobel in chemistry for the invention of a process used to manufacture cheap fertilizer, which helped feed billions. Or that he made modern chemical warfare possible with his development of chlorine gas and personally oversaw its use in World War I.</p>
        <p>Or that his first wife, also a chemist, seemingly distraught over his work on poison gases, shot herself through the heart.</p>
        <p>Or that Haber, a Jew, fled his beloved Germany because Nazi race laws made it impossible to live and work there, or that his relatives were later gassed with another of his inventions -- Zyklon B -- in concentration camps.</p>
        <p>But the details of Haber's tumultuous life will soon become much more familiar with a new play, a new biography, a new short film and even a new opera that are either out or in the works.</p>
        <p>One reason for Haber's sudden rediscovery is the relatively recent availability of research documents. ''For decades, much of the raw material of the Haber story was locked up by a single researcher, a protégé of Haber's, until the beginning of the 1990's,'' said Daniel Charles, whose biography ''Master Mind: The Rise and Fall of Fritz Haber, the Nobel Laureate Who Launched the Age of Chemical Warfare'' came out in August. After those archives were opened, Mr. Charles wrote in an e-mail message, ''books started coming out, first scholarly works in German.''</p>
        <p>''Now,'' he continued, ''the English-language wave has begun.''</p>
        <p>Vern Thiessen, the Canadian author of ''Einstein's Gift,'' which opened Thursday at the Acorn Theater Off Broadway, said he first learned about Haber from a friend, a biochemist, while they were at a bar in Edmonton. It was like finding ''a lost storybook,'' he said in a recent interview, ''like a Dead Sea Scroll or something.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thiessen was interested in the ethics of applied science and the effort to remain true to one's principles, particularly in time of war. His play touches on Haber's conversion to Christianity as a young man and his Nobel-winning idea, as well as his orchestration of the first gas attack on the battlefield in Ypres, Belgium, in 1915, and the evening soon after, when his first wife, Clara, killed herself.</p>
        <p>The play, Mr. Thiessen said, is about a man ''who wants to do good but fails miserably.''</p>
        <p>In a speech to German officers, Haber said that battles were won ''not through the physical destruction of the enemy, but rather because of the imponderables of the soul that, at the decisive moment, undermine his ability to resist and cause him to imagine defeat.''</p>
        <p>Such a view has particular resonance now, a number of those involved with Haber projects said. Daniel Halpern, publisher of Ecco Press, which issued ''Master Mind,'' said the idea of chemical warfare was at the ''core of our terror at the moment.''</p>
        <p>The chemical-warfare episode (and Clara Haber's suicide) are at the center of ''Haber,'' a short German film by Daniel Ragussis that is now in postproduction. Mr. Ragussis said over the telephone that the Haber story was about ''a major turning point in the history of the world -- the way that modern warfare erupted onto the scene.''</p>
        <p>Peter King, the English jazz musician who wrote the opera ''Zyklon'' with the librettist Julian Barry, said he was also interested in Haber's relevance to contemporary events. ''Haber was the first scientist in modern times to confront the terrible moral dilemma that has faced so many others since,'' he wrote in an e-mail message. ''Science is a double-edged sword and can be used for good or evil. Can we blame I.T. specialists because Al Qaeda used the power of the Internet to such devastating effect, or computer scientists for the use of 'smart' bombs against innocent Iraqis and Afghans?''</p>
        <p>The opera, Mr. King said, was ''a kind of fantasy, in which Haber appears as a ghost -- seeking absolution for his perceived crimes -- in a war crimes tribunal in 1946.''</p>
        <p>A short workshop version of ''Zyklon'' was performed last year in New York, and excerpts from it in June in London, but Mr. King said he was hoping for a full staging.</p>
        <p>Writing and researching ''Einstein's Gift'' took Mr. Thiessen seven years, which included a stint at the Max Planck Society Historical Archives in Berlin.</p>
        <p>He portrays Haber as the anti-Einstein. Haber is applied science; Einstein is theoretical. Haber knows how to work with scientists, military people and industrialists; Einstein is a self-selected outsider. And yet they were great friends, and their witty, philosophical exchanges in the Epic Theater Center's production of Mr. Thiessen's play (with Aasif Mandvi as Haber and Shawn Elliott as Einstein) lighten the sometimes brutally heavy show. About Einstein and Haber, Mr. Thiessen said, ''They are a bit of the Odd Couple, right?''</p>
        <p>In early drafts of ''Einstein's Gift,'' Haber narrated the story, but ultimately Einstein won the role of narrator because it better framed the tale for modern theatergoers, Mr. Thiessen explained. ''Einstein is a trustworthy character,'' he said. ''Everybody likes him and tries to overlook his faults.''</p>
        <p>''I learned nothing about science working on this project,'' he added, ''but I learned a tremendous amount about scientists.'' And his goal, he said, is to put ''the audience in a position where they can understand the passion behind the work.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 14, 2005, Friday  Because of an editing error, an article in The Arts on Wednesday about interest in the life of the German chemist Fritz Haber, the subject of a new biography, play, opera and short film (''Haber''), referred incorrectly to the film. It was shot in the United States, not Germany, and is in English.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 14, 2005, Friday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in The Arts on Wednesday about interest in the life of the German chemist Fritz Haber, the subject of a new biography, play, opera and short film (''Haber''), referred incorrectly to the film. It was shot in the United States, not Germany, and is in English.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
