<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Songs Like Historical Novels, A Kind of Celtic Mood Music</title>
    <meta content="09MCKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1015556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckennitt, Loreena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E2DC1031F93AA35756C0A96E958260" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Songs Like Historical Novels, A Kind of Celtic Mood Music</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers reviews singer Loreena McKennitt concert at Radio City Music Hall; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Watching Loreena McKennitt plucking her harp at Radio City Music Hall on Thursday night, one could almost imagine what it must have felt like to watch Jenny Lind, America's first musical superstar. P. T. Barnum imported the so-called Swedish nightingale in 1850 as a messenger from an ancient northern Eden. She made him a fortune. Ladies swooned at her bell-clear voice; gentlemen rioted over tickets for her concerts. And so the marketing of the mystical feminine began.</p>
        <p>Ms. McKennitt, also a northern lass -- Canadian, actually -- with a crystalline soprano, has perfected a contemporary version of this enduring persona. Recently achieving success with the hit ''The Mummers Dance,'' she has been presenting her Celtic-based, electronically augmented mood music to enthusiastic fans for over a decade. Her charisma, like Miss Lind's, relies on an aura of uplift that comes from connecting folk traditions to notions of spiritual integrity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Watching Loreena McKennitt plucking her harp at Radio City Music Hall on Thursday night, one could almost imagine what it must have felt like to watch Jenny Lind, America's first musical superstar. P. T. Barnum imported the so-called Swedish nightingale in 1850 as a messenger from an ancient northern Eden. She made him a fortune. Ladies swooned at her bell-clear voice; gentlemen rioted over tickets for her concerts. And so the marketing of the mystical feminine began.</p>
        <p>Ms. McKennitt, also a northern lass -- Canadian, actually -- with a crystalline soprano, has perfected a contemporary version of this enduring persona. Recently achieving success with the hit ''The Mummers Dance,'' she has been presenting her Celtic-based, electronically augmented mood music to enthusiastic fans for over a decade. Her charisma, like Miss Lind's, relies on an aura of uplift that comes from connecting folk traditions to notions of spiritual integrity.</p>
        <p>Setting the poems of William Shakespeare and Alfred, Lord Tennyson to music that echoes common English and Irish airs, and invoking great figures like Marco Polo in her own lyrics, Ms. McKennitt makes music closer to historical novels than to most pop. She relies on the same simple ballads and dances that inspired many classical composers, played with a clean, careful warmth that invokes a concert hall more than a bonfire.</p>
        <p>Embellishing this base with Middle Eastern rhythms rendered by the percussionists Rick Lazar and Donald Quan and with occasional rock licks provided by the guitarist Brian Hughes and the flashy violinist Hugh Marsh, Ms. McKennitt offered a modern vision of the folk not unlike the historical re-enactments she once participated in as part of Canada's Stratford Shakespeare Festival. Her vocal duet with the cellist Caroline Lavelle also showed her ties to 1960's folk rockers like Fairport Convention.</p>
        <p>But Ms. McKennitt, who also plays piano and accordion, prefers the world-wandering style of New Age music. Aligning herself with the Celtic diaspora allows her to lightly mine Latin and North African music without appearing imperialistic. ''They were a motley group of individuals,'' she said of the Celts. ''I don't think much has changed over the centuries.'' Such comments encouraged her predominantly white audience to view itself as an indigenous group with a colorful heritage.</p>
        <p>This heritage is real, and Ms. McKennitt interprets it artfully. But her updating of the legacy of the feminine makes her a pop star and not a folklorist. Leading her own band (and running her own music business, described in promotional material distributed at the show), Ms. McKennitt presents herself as a strong woman true to her ancient obligation to bear secrets and preserve home truths. Such a lovely picture still seduces, after centuries of refinement.  POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
