<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witnesses Tell Of Cover-Up In Police Graft</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="637418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MOLLEN COMMISSION (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">POLICE DEPARTMENT (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAAB, SELWYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRIMBOLI, JOSEPH F (SGT)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FERRUGIA, ALEXANDER (DETECTIVE)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D71439F93AA1575AC0A965958260" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witnesses Tell Of Cover-Up In Police Graft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELWYN RAAB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAAB, SELWYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Witnesses drawn from the ranks of police corruption investigators yesterday recalled how they painfully discovered what they depicted as an unwritten policy in New York City's Police Department that discouraged major corruption inquiries from 1986 to 1991.</p>
        <p>The witnesses were called by a mayoral commission on the second day of its hearings into police corruption. While the witnesses did not name any specific police supervisor who stymied corruption inquiries, the sum of their testimony seemed to be intended to paint a portrait of a culture that sidestepped inquiries that had the potential for large-scale roundups that would embarrass the department and ruin careers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Witnesses drawn from the ranks of police corruption investigators yesterday recalled how they painfully discovered what they depicted as an unwritten policy in New York City's Police Department that discouraged major corruption inquiries from 1986 to 1991.</p>
        <p>The witnesses were called by a mayoral commission on the second day of its hearings into police corruption. While the witnesses did not name any specific police supervisor who stymied corruption inquiries, the sum of their testimony seemed to be intended to paint a portrait of a culture that sidestepped inquiries that had the potential for large-scale roundups that would embarrass the department and ruin careers.</p>
        <p>Testifying both openly and in disguise, the witnesses told the panel investigating police corruption that "top" commanders blocked two major inquiries into allegations of widespread corruption in two precincts in Manhattan and Brooklyn, where some officers were accused of robbing drug dealers, selling drugs and other abuses.  Isolated Arrests Preferred</p>
        <p>The witnesses, who included detectives, police supervisors and an undercover informer, said that after the two investigations were thwarted or closed, police officials suggested to them that they preferred isolated or fragmented arrests.</p>
        <p>But neither the witnesses nor members of the investigating panel, known as the Mollen Commission, said they would identify the officials who were said to have discouraged potentially major investigations.</p>
        <p>One witness who was identified, Police Sgt. Joseph F. Trimboli, said that while singlehandedly trying to investigate allegations against more than 20 suspected officers in the 75th Precinct in East New York, Brooklyn, he was summoned to a meeting of high officials and warned that he was under suspicion as a drug trafficker.</p>
        <p>He said that at the meeting in 1989 he was also berated for continuing the investigation for three years without producing more substantial evidence. Sergeant Trimboli was not asked to identify specifically the officials, but he said they included assistant chiefs, inspectors and captains. He said that although he had "a wealth of evidence" about corruption in the 75th Precinct, he was hindered by officials in charge of corrupution inquiries. He said they refused to give him sophisticated equipment, including eavesdropping devices, or an unmarked police car. He added that he often worked on his own time, using his own car, and that the only equipment his superiors provided was a pair of binoculars.</p>
        <p>Upon completing his testimony before the commission -- an investigative panel appointed by Mayor David N. Dinkins -- the 41-year-old Sereant Trimboli announced that he was retiring. He gave no reason for leaving the police force after 20 years.</p>
        <p>But in his testimony he said he had "belatedly learned" that his attempts to expose corruption in the 75th Precinct were stymied by fears among high officials of "initiating a scandal similar to the 77th." He was referring to the arrests in 1986 in the 77th Precinct in Bedford-Stuyvesant and Crown Heights in Brooklyn of 13 officers on narcotics-related charges. An Unusual Demand</p>
        <p>Sergeant Trimboli, who was a field investigator in Brooklyn, said that in an unusual demand the Internal Affairs Division, which oversaw all corruption inquiries until last year, required him to submit weekly reports on evidence obtained in the 75th Precinct investigation. In 1988, when he was late in forwarding a report, he said two division agents cautioned him to submit the reports promptly because they were being reviewed by Benjamin Ward, then the Police Commissioner, and Daniel F. Sullivan, the Chief of Inspectional Services.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward and Mr. Sullivan retired from the department and could not be reached for comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>A police official identified as a former commanding officer of the Field Internal Affairs Unit in the Manhattan South Patrol zone told commission lawyers of pressure applied after the 77th Precinct arrests against undertaking massive corruption cases.</p>
        <p>Portions of an audiotape interview with the official were played at the hearing. On the tape, the commander said Mr. Ward took the 77th Precinct arrests as "a personal affront."</p>
        <p>On the tape, the commander said high-level officials wanted corruption cases "fragmented."</p>
        <p>The commission also focused yesterday on an attempt by corruption investigators in 1991 to snare 15 officers and two former officers in the Ninth Precinct in the East Village who were suspected of protecting narcotics dealers, robbing dealers and snorting cocaine and drinking while on the job. An informer who cooperated in 1991 with investigators from the Field Internal Affairs Unit in lower Manhattan testified yesterday that he had worn a concealed tape recorder to obtain information on more than a dozen officers from the Ninth Precinct.</p>
        <p>The informer, who wore a ski mask and was referred to as Mr. X, said officers met almost daily in his store on Third Street to discuss their robberies, narcotics sales and dealers they protected from arrests and from harassment by rival drug traffickers.</p>
        <p>Alexander Ferrugia, a detective in the Field Internal Affairs Unit, testified that his unit and the Manhattan District Attorney's office had authorized the informer to attend a barbecue party on July 4, 1991, on Staten Island, which at least 17 current and former officers from the Ninth Precinct had been invited to attend by Officer Alan Brown, who was suspected of being a ringleader of the precinct's corruption gang.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferrugia said that the informer had secretly tape-recorded drug sales from Officer Brown and that the officer was heard saying that narcotics would be plentiful at the party. Despite a plan to use the barbecue as a stage for gathering evidence against many officers, Mr. Ferrugia said that officials in the Internal Affairs Division and the Manhattan Borough South Patrol zone ordered Mr. Brown's arrest on June 14, 1991, for selling drugs to the informer.</p>
        <p>The detective said the decision to arrest Mr. Brown was made without consulting detectives or the assistant district attorney working on the case. "We were dismayed," he said.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Ferrugia works in confidential inquiries, he testified from behind a screen.</p>
        <p>On Monday, police officials said Mr. Brown was arrested because of fears that he was using drugs and might be a danger to the public.</p>
        <p>Leslie U. Cornfeld, the commission's deputy counsel, said at the hearing that "not a single commanding officer in the Internal Affairs Division or Manhattan South could remember who directed the order" to arrest Mr. Brown.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
