<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Testimony About Delusions With 'Cosmic Proportions'</title>
    <meta content="15fake" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/15/nyregion/15fake.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Psychology and Psychologists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Braunstein, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E6DE1331F936A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Testimony About Delusions With 'Cosmic Proportions'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Testimony About Delusions With ‘Cosmic Proportions’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the prosecution, it was a sinister crime that a troubled but calculating man committed against one terrified woman. But to a defense psychologist, Peter Braunstein's attack on a former colleague in the fashion press was a symbolic attack on the hypocrisy of the fashion industry and of American society.</p>
        <p>He saw himself as a ''hit man for God,'' the psychologist, Barbara R. Kirwin, told a Manhattan jury yesterday in State Supreme Court. ''He's an avenging angel, a special person who has been chosen to right hypocrisies.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A defense psychologist testified that Peter Braunstein’s attack on a colleague in the fashion press was a symbolic attack on the hypocrisy of the fashion industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the prosecution, it was a sinister crime that a troubled but calculating man committed against one terrified woman. But to a defense psychologist, Peter Braunstein's attack on a former colleague in the fashion press was a symbolic attack on the hypocrisy of the fashion industry and of American society.</p>
        <p>He saw himself as a ''hit man for God,'' the psychologist, Barbara R. Kirwin, told a Manhattan jury yesterday in State Supreme Court. ''He's an avenging angel, a special person who has been chosen to right hypocrisies.''</p>
        <p>His paranoid fantasy began as an urge for revenge against a woman who dumped him, Dr. Kirwin said, but it grew into a need to punish a morally corrupt society.</p>
        <p>''Now it had assumed cosmic proportions,'' Dr. Kirwin said yesterday at Mr. Braunstein's trial. He wanted revenge, she testified, ''against the fashion industry that was superficial, against post-9/11 hypocrisy, against firefighters as phony heroes, against a world that treats talented, sensitive people this way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Braunstein, 43, charged with kidnapping and sexual abuse, is accused of dressing as a firefighter and setting off smoke bombs to gain entrance to the Chelsea apartment of a woman he hardly knew on Oct. 31, 2005. Once inside, he threatened her with a pellet gun and a knife, drugged her with a chloroform-soaked rag, stripped her, tied her to her bed and groped her for what the prosecutors said was 13 hours.</p>
        <p>The witness testified that Mr. Braunstein's case was ''clearly the most textbook case of paranoid schizophrenia that I had ever seen.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Kirwin went on to say that Mr. Braunstein had told her his attack on the woman was a ''fantasy,'' a ''comic book crime'' and a ''game.'' He told her it was not sexual, and said that ''at a certain point, I just lost it and became bored.''</p>
        <p>His victim, who had been a co-worker in the fashion press, became a symbol of the vacuousness of that life to him, Dr. Kirwin said.</p>
        <p>''I was a synthetic person, she was a synthetic person,'' Dr. Kirwin quoted Mr. Braunstein as saying.</p>
        <p>He incorporated elements of his fantasy life with a former girlfriend -- like sexual bondage -- into the crime, but did not realize his victim would object, the psychologist said.</p>
        <p>He said he was surprised the victim reported the crime to the police, Dr. Kirwin said.</p>
        <p>''I thought we were playing a game, like 'Rashomon,' '' she quoted Mr. Braunstein saying, adding that this was one of many inappropriate cultural references. ''I guess I knew it was a crime, but I didn't consider it wrong.''</p>
        <p>As a further testimony to Mr. Braunstein's being unaware of the seriousness of his crime, Dr. Kirwin described a note he left on the woman's bathroom mirror after the attack, which read, ''Bye -- Hope things turn around for U soon.''</p>
        <p>''The note on the mirror reflects that he's so out of touch that he does not know that he's terrorized this woman for 12 hours,'' Dr. Kirwin said.</p>
        <p>One of the few points the defense is disputing is how long Mr. Braunstein held the woman captive, because the legal definition of kidnapping is more than 12 hours.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kirwin testified that Mr. Braunstein had showed signs of paranoid schizophrenia and ''downward drift'' since college. These alternated with periods of stability when he had easy jobs or when he was in relationships with strong women, like his former wife, Donna Keane (they divorced in 1994), and Debra Michals, a feminist historian, she said.</p>
        <p>But she said his job at Women's Wear Daily and his relationship with Jane Larkworthy, the beauty editor of W magazine, had been too much of a ''pressure cooker,'' and had sent him over the edge.</p>
        <p>He perceived being fired from Women's Wear Daily in October 2002, and then being dumped by Ms. Larkworthy in November 2003, as apocalyptic events, Dr. Kirwin said.</p>
        <p>''It was very simply the end of his world as he knew it.''</p>
        <p>In other action yesterday, Justice Thomas Farber ruled that prosecutors could not bring up portions of Mr. Braunstein's writings in which he talked about serial killers like David Berkowitz (the Son of Sam) and the fictional Hannibal Lecter, and the Columbine school shootings.</p>
        <p>The defense argued that the jury could infer that Mr. Braunstein was a potential killer, even though he is not accused of murder.</p>
        <p>The judge ruled that the defense could use a statement from Mr. Braunstein's manifesto where he talked about killing Anna Wintour, the editor of Vogue, because it fit into the context of his rage against the fashion industry.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
