<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Innocents in a Brutal Land, Together Against the Tides</title>
    <meta content="15eder" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/15/books/15eder.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070516T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Crace, Jim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3D71231F936A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Innocents in a Brutal Land, Together Against the Tides</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Pesthouse</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD EDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eder, Richard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pesthouse  By Jim Crace  255 pages. Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $24.95.</p>
        <p>An unspecified war or series of wars has dragged the world back into a harsh, preindustrial existence. In what was the United States, its cities gone and its population vastly reduced, the survivors live meagerly off the land, using the most rudimentary of tools. A crude social structure has sprung up in isolated local communities; bandits maraud through stretches of countryside; and life has been reduced to the Hobbesian state: nasty, brutish and short.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jim Crace’s futurist nightmare, in which a cruel myth leads emigrants to slave ships, is witty, graceful and haunting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Pesthouse  By Jim Crace  255 pages. Nan A. Talese/Doubleday. $24.95.</p>
        <p>An unspecified war or series of wars has dragged the world back into a harsh, preindustrial existence. In what was the United States, its cities gone and its population vastly reduced, the survivors live meagerly off the land, using the most rudimentary of tools. A crude social structure has sprung up in isolated local communities; bandits maraud through stretches of countryside; and life has been reduced to the Hobbesian state: nasty, brutish and short.</p>
        <p>It is the setting for ''The Pesthouse,'' which, unlikely as it may seem, is a romance. At least, that is as close as definition can get to the undefinable art of Jim Crace. The least known among the crowning trio of living British writers, along with Barry Unsworth and Ian McEwen, he lodges his finest work in extremity.</p>
        <p>Here it is a futurist nightmare; in ''The Gift of Stones'' it was the twilight of a Stone Age community; in ''Quarantine,'' possibly his masterpiece, it was Jesus spending 40 irritatingly hysterical days among a collection of desert dwellers. In ''Being Dead,'' it was the beachside decay of the bodies of two murder victims.</p>
        <p>This last description impales itself on its own thumbnail, of course. Who could read it without suspecting parody or pretention? Who could guess that Mr. Crace is so witty, graceful and haunting?</p>
        <p>He brings his large, distant abstractions -- prehistory, a dystopic future, religion, death -- up close, segmenting them into tangible and particular fictional parcels. His universal themes are paced out in wry individual footsteps.</p>
        <p>Everyone and everything have their voices. In ''The Pesthouse'' it is not just a man and a woman, waifs who grow into mastery as they make a pilgrimage through blighted landscape. It is also the rain deciding to let up, their horse considering the lake he is to ford, an insomniac's ill-digested dinner ''foraging with its nocturnal snout.''</p>
        <p>(In ''Being Dead,'' even the bodies have points of view; so do the gulls tearing at them, and the crabs laboring corpseward ''through their exaggerated countryside.'' This phrase transforms their crooked gait from our take on crabs to the crabs' take on the world.)</p>
        <p>The journey in ''The Pesthouse'' is quite different from that in Cormac McCarthy's recent book, ''The Road,'' though both run through postapocalyptic landscapes. Mr. McCarthy's father and son themselves are at a postapocalyptic end, though they keep walking. Mr. Crace's Franklin and Margaret, outcast innocents traveling counter to the tides of their brutal world, will find the beginnings of redemption.</p>
        <p>A cruel myth has set throngs of emigrants fleeing from their weary inland lives toward the Atlantic coast. (Mr. Crace has little use for America's westward dream; his irony unspools it eastward.) There, it is said, sailing ships will transport them to lavish prosperity across the ocean, where land is plentiful and fertile, and disease so unknown that ''people would travel for a day just to watch a man sniff.''</p>
        <p>Franklin, lame and hesitant, was left behind on a high bluff overlooking Ferrytown, the last big river crossing on the way east. There he meets Margaret, stricken by a plaguelike disease and deposited by her family in a hut -- the pesthouse of the title -- to heal or die.</p>
        <p>Instead of shunning her, Francis cares for her, and care slowly evolves into a mutual ardor that will be played out only after their journey, and the book, ends. Tumescence, finely suggested in the author's stately, faintly archaic prose, pulses this strange story and stops the heart as no consummation would.</p>
        <p>By the time Francis and a slowly recovering Margaret are able to climb down to Ferrytown, it is a place of the dead. A landslide has churned up the bottom of the lake, releasing its lethal gases. Something similar happened in Africa a few years ago, but for Mr. Crace there are no safely remote horrors.</p>
        <p>The couple get across the river; their trek east is a series of ordeals through a blasted America, the worst of which is Francis's temporary abduction by a savagely jocular bandit gang. Mr. Crace writes of these things with an oddly lyrical lightness, the kind of lightness that made Seamus Heaney's rendering of ''Beowulf'' move in a way that eases as it grips.</p>
        <p>Some of the episodes that follow -- Margaret takes refuge in the stronghold of a creepy penitential sect; the bandits raid it; Francis breaks free; he and Margaret ride off on the bandits' horses -- froth up the novel's limpid current. Only for a while. The sailing ships that so many have tried to reach turn out to be slave vessels. The ocean itself, when they glimpse it, signals not promise but rejection. ''Margaret could not have guessed how leaden it would be, and lacking in expression.''</p>
        <p>And they turn back, heading to what they know. The west, that is (in Mr. Crace's sardonic reversal), with hardships that nevertheless stand for life, as against the easy poison of eastward delusion. The return is as poetically detailed as the way out, but a doom has been lifted from it.</p>
        <p>''They no longer felt defeated by America, as most emigrants had on the journey out, driven eastward by their failings,'' the author writes. ''It was as if the country that had once been hostile to them was regretful for it and was now providing recompense -- fewer dangers, warmer nights, softer going.''</p>
        <p>The book ends in a pastoral lighting that could be sentimental, except that the travelers have been put through so many aching horrors that they -- and we -- have earned the right to hope. Mr. Crace is the coldest of writers, and the tenderest.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 16, 2007, Wednesday  The Books of The Times review yesterday, about ''The Pesthouse,'' by Jim Crace, misstated the name of one character at several points. As noted elsewhere in the review, he is Franklin, not Francis. The review also misspelled the surname of a writer who was described in the review as part of ''the crowning trio of living British writers,'' along with Mr. Crace and Barry Unsworth. He is Ian McEwan, not McEwen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 16, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>The Books of The Times review yesterday, about ''The Pesthouse,'' by Jim Crace, misstated the name of one character at several points. As noted elsewhere in the review, he is Franklin, not Francis. The review also misspelled the surname of a writer who was described in the review as part of ''the crowning trio of living British writers,'' along with Mr. Crace and Barry Unsworth. He is Ian McEwan, not McEwen.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
