<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cavaliers Hold On After Carter Doesn't</title>
    <meta content="15nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/15/sports/basketball/15nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DE1331F936A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cavaliers Hold On After Carter Doesn't</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Poor Shooting Night Puts Nets’ Backs to the Wall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., May 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vince Carter had the ball in his hands, a roaring crowd on its feet and, it seemed, an entire franchise on edge.</p>
        <p>The Nets' playoff fate, and their future, was surely on the line late Monday night as Carter, dribbling 15 feet from the basket, backed down Cleveland's Eric Snow. It all unraveled in a flurry: Snow swiped, Carter stumbled, the ball flittered away and the series quite possibly went with it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cavaliers edged the Nets on Monday night, giving them a 3-1 lead in the Eastern Conference semifinal series as it heads back to Cleveland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vince Carter had the ball in his hands, a roaring crowd on its feet and, it seemed, an entire franchise on edge.</p>
        <p>The Nets' playoff fate, and their future, was surely on the line late Monday night as Carter, dribbling 15 feet from the basket, backed down Cleveland's Eric Snow. It all unraveled in a flurry: Snow swiped, Carter stumbled, the ball flittered away and the series quite possibly went with it.</p>
        <p>When the ball skipped over the sideline with 1.9 seconds left, the Cavaliers took possession and closed out an 87-85 victory to seize a 3-1 lead in their best-of-seven Eastern Conference semifinal series.</p>
        <p>Despair swept over the packed stands at Continental Arena and over Carter, the star who failed to deliver when the Nets needed him most. All three of the Nets' All-Stars faltered -- Carter, Jason Kidd and Richard Jefferson shot a combined 11 of 48 from the field -- but it was Carter who wore the darkest expression afterward.</p>
        <p>He missed two free throws, a driving layup and a tip-in attempt in the final four minutes. His loose-ball foul led to two huge free throws by Anderson Varejao. He lost a key possession with an errant pass.</p>
        <p>With 11.4 seconds left, Carter nearly redeemed himself, making two free throws to make it a 1-point game.</p>
        <p>This loss may haunt him for some time, however.</p>
        <p>''They put the ball in my hands to make plays, and that's what I want to do,'' Carter said. ''That one, I take hard. It's on me.''</p>
        <p>LeBron James was the only star to match up to his billing Monday, leading the Cavaliers with 30 points, 9 rebounds and 7 assists. He had his own stumbles down the stretch, including a missed free throw with 10.3 seconds left, but did enough to secure the victory.</p>
        <p>The 22-year-old James is a victory from his first trip to the Eastern Conference finals, and can get it Wednesday night in Cleveland. The Nets are a loss from an off-season of potentially drastic change. To save their season, they will need to win twice in Cleveland, where they lost Games 1 and 2. Only 8 of 170 N.B.A. teams have won a series after trailing by 3-1.</p>
        <p>''We still are a confident team,'' Kidd said. ''We're a veteran ball club. We've been in this position before.''</p>
        <p>Rarely, however, have the Nets' best players been this bad in such a big game. Kidd had 17 rebounds and 7 assists but only 5 points after making 2 of 13 shots. Jefferson had 15 points but went 3 of 12 from the field. Carter had a near triple-double -- 25 points, 9 rebounds and 9 assists -- but it was offset by poor shooting (6 of 23) and four turnovers.</p>
        <p>The Nets did not make a field goal in the final 6 minutes 58 seconds.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to figure,'' Coach Lawrence Frank said. ''I mean, we had shots at the rim, open shots.''</p>
        <p>And still, they had chances to win. James missed a deep jumper and a fadeaway 14-footer down the stretch, either of which could have sealed the victory. He was 2 for 4 from the free-throw line in the last 3:13.</p>
        <p>The Nets had the chance to force overtime when Carter got the ball in the final 10 seconds, with the smaller Snow on his hip. It was a moment scripted for a star player to shine. But the savvy Snow poked the ball, and Carter, trying to slap it toward Kidd, smacked it out of bounds.</p>
        <p>''A great play by Eric,'' Cavaliers Coach Mike Brown said.</p>
        <p>Carter said: ''I felt it was a foul, but it's just the way it goes at the end. If they're going to put the ball in my hands, I have to make a play.''</p>
        <p>It was perhaps a bad omen that the journeyman Mikki Moore was the Nets' most consistent threat. He finished with career-high 25 points, going 11 of 14 on a combination of dunks and long jumpers.</p>
        <p>But Moore was also involved in a third-quarter scuffle that seemed to inspire Cleveland's final push.</p>
        <p>Moore knocked down a driving Sasha Pavlovic with a two-handed shove in the lane. Pavlovic leapt up to confront Moore before Jefferson moved between them.</p>
        <p>Pavlovic was called for a technical foul, but the Cavaliers promptly went on a 14-3 run, which included two 3-pointers by James. A 4-point Nets lead became a 60-53 Cavaliers lead.</p>
        <p>The Nets tied the score at 69-69 on a 3-pointer by Kidd, but Cleveland never lost the momentum. James snapped at Moore, then let his game do the rest.</p>
        <p>''I can't let anyone on the opposing team try to intimidate one of my teammates or try to hard foul one of my teammates without me saying something, either with my play or with my mouth at times,'' James said.</p>
        <p>''It definitely fired me up as an individual.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, James scored 14 of his points after the confrontation. Now he has the chance to remove one of the largest asterisks from his résumé, by leading his team to the conference finals.</p>
        <p>''It's not over,'' Brown said. ''We already know it's going to be a tough ballgame.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
