<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Island's Organic Landscapers Get Organized</title>
    <meta content="09LAWN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1190383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lawns</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Defoliants and Herbicides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fungicides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Organic Horticultural Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defoliants and Herbicides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0D6143FF93AA35757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Island's Organic Landscapers Get Organized</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Increasing number of Long Island-based lawn care and landscaping companies are not using pesticides, herbicides and fungicides, because of risk they pose to health and environment; group of 26 professional landscapers have formed Long Island Organic Horticultural Assn, what members say is country's first landscapers association pledging to use 100 percent organic methods; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RONALD CASSIDENTO said he traveled to an organic fair at Suffolk County Community College in Southampton last weekend because there was no more promising place for the still-fledgling organic landscaping industry than Nassau and Suffolk counties.</p>
        <p>''For organic, Long Island is where it's happening,'' said Mr. Cassidento, president of North American Organics Company, which sells environment-friendly lawn care products. ''It's a very hot market.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RONALD CASSIDENTO said he traveled to an organic fair at Suffolk County Community College in Southampton last weekend because there was no more promising place for the still-fledgling organic landscaping industry than Nassau and Suffolk counties.</p>
        <p>''For organic, Long Island is where it's happening,'' said Mr. Cassidento, president of North American Organics Company, which sells environment-friendly lawn care products. ''It's a very hot market.''</p>
        <p>An increasing number of Long Island-based lawn care and landscaping companies seem to agree. As the seasonal ritual of lawn spraying, weed killing and home gardening begins, a group of 26 professional landscapers have formed what members say is the country's first landscapers association pledged to using 100 percent organic methods.</p>
        <p>''We felt that since there are full programs available for organic landscaping and lawn maintenance it was probably about time for an association that would spread the word and the techniques,'' said Steven J. Restmeyer of Eco-Logical Organic Landscaping in Yaphank and the president of the new group, the Long Island Organic Horticultural Association.</p>
        <p>Many other lawn care companies and professional landscapers are moving to add organic products and methods to their services. ''Any landscaper that is worth his salt right now can offer this to his customers,'' said H. Pat Voges, a spokesman for the Nassau and Suffolk Landscape Gardeners Association, which counts public works and parks departments, landscapers, golf course superintendents, nurserymen, cemetery directors and maintenance people among its 1,562 members. Mr. Voges said he saw no reason why a new trade group was necessary.</p>
        <p>The newly formed organic landscapers' group is backed by a number of breast cancer and environmental organizations whose members believe traditional lawn care pesticides, herbicides and fungicides carry health risks. Those organizations are supplying their members and the public with the names of the association members.</p>
        <p>''What we are going to do is change the market,'' said Neal Lewis, executive director of the Long Island Neighborhood Network and an officer of the organic association. ''We are giving people the choice to put their money where their environmental values are.''</p>
        <p>The network has supported the use of organic products and methods on golf courses and won a lawsuit last year directing that no new public golf course be built in Suffolk County until alternative greenskeeping methods were considered. It is also lobbying for state law requiring neighbor notification at least 48 hours before lawns are sprayed with conventional chemicals.</p>
        <p>Lawn care companies that employ conventional chemical treatments say the products they apply are extensively tested for safety, labeled by the Environmental Protection Agency and registered by New York State after meeting strict standards.</p>
        <p>''There is a great deal of confidence in these products,'' said Roger A. Yeary, a toxicologist and a vice president for TruGreen Chemlawn, the country's largest lawn care company and a major lawn care service provider on Long Island.</p>
        <p>But even from his office in Ohio, Dr. Yeary said he had heard of the influential Long Island breast cancer groups and their potential impact on shaping attitudes toward chemicals used in the lawn care business.</p>
        <p>''The buzz word now is the precautionary principle,'' Dr. Yeary said. ''It says, 'Well, if we don't know everything about these chemicals, why take a chance?' And of course we will never know everything.''</p>
        <p>Karen Miller, president of the Huntington Breast Cancer Action Coalition, said there was ample reason for choosing organic over chemical lawn and garden care now that alternatives are available.</p>
        <p>''There are so many unknown causes of cancer and some other diseases,'' she said. ''Shouldn't we be looking at environmental causes more closely?''</p>
        <p>The coalition is urging property owners who treat lawns and gardens with organic methods to post pink lawn flags that say, ''I Am Fed Naturally,'' a contrast, the group said, to notices on chemically treated properties warning people to stay off for 24 hours.</p>
        <p>''The breast cancer groups are making a change in the public's script,'' Ms. Miller said. ''When people call their tried-and-true professionals, we are encouraging them to say, 'I want you back, but without those toxic chemicals.' ''</p>
        <p>Organic landscapers use substances like corn gluten as a pre-emergent weed killer and an alternative to chemical herbicides such as the commonly used pendimethaline.</p>
        <p>In lieu of chemical applications, they may use rock dust for minerals, compost to build soil, garlic spray for insect repellent and a growing number of other organic products.</p>
        <p>Odor from the garlic spray quickly subsides below the level of human detection, sellers of the product say, but remains a potent repellent of mosquitoes, ticks and other pests.</p>
        <p>Some organic landscapers use biological means to combat grubs, insects, aphids and other unwanted pests as an alternative to pesticides.</p>
        <p>Mr. Restmeyer said that in some circumstances he introduced praying mantises for insect control and microscopic mushrooms to rebuild soil. He said songbirds had been major casualties of lawn and garden chemicals, leaving properties bereft of large consumers of insects. A chickadee, a small bird native to Long Island, consumes 200 to 400 insects a day ''if it doesn't get poisoned first,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Many of the methods he used, Mr. Restmeyer said, were ''nothing new'' but part of knowledge that was lost as dependency on chemicals increased. ''This is old stuff,'' he said, ''ancient stuff.''</p>
        <p>In Westhampton, Jeff Frank of the Lyceum, a private school, teaches organic methods to landscapers who emerge from his course as what Mr. Frank calls green guerrillas.</p>
        <p>''We are the only school in the country teaching organic landscaping methods, which is the saddest thing I could possibly tell you,'' said Mr. Frank.</p>
        <p>He said his courses also ''dispel the myth created by the chemical companies that organic methods are too expensive.''</p>
        <p>''Organics are the best-kept secret since the atomic bomb, and Long Island is the hotbed for organics in this country,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Members of the association and their supporters said that while organic methods might initially cost more than conventional chemical treatments, they would eventually restore lawns to greater natural health and cut expenses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Voges of the Nassau and Suffolk Landscape Gardeners Association said his group had asked the Cornell Cooperative Extension to design a lawn care program using organic products.</p>
        <p>Turning conventional wisdom upside down, he said his association had reservations about organics because ''these things really haven't been tested for the effect on humans, animals and the environment.'' But, he said, if the products were deemed safe and shown to work, they are ''a new tool we can put in our tool box.''</p>
        <p>''As long as the golf course is green and customers get what they want, we have absolutely no problem in using these things,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Yeary of TruGreen Chemlawn said his company was interested in  organic products but had found none to compete with chemicals.</p>
        <p>He said a pilot organic program the company tried in Buffalo ''didn't get much acceptance'' because it was ineffective in controlling weeds.</p>
        <p>He said that while corn gluten was ''highly touted'' and would ''satisfy some people,'' it took more time to do less than chemicals.</p>
        <p>''Customer satisfaction on a large scale would not be good,'' he said. ''People expect results in a reasonably short period of time.''</p>
        <p>''We are an impatient group of people,'' he said. ''We can't wait for our computers to boot up.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
