<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toxic Heroin Has Killed 12, Officials Say</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="420236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEROIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH BRONX (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIEVES, EVELYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heroin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DA153CF937A35751C0A967958260" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toxic Heroin Has Killed 12, Officials Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NIEVES, EVELYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The death toll from a batch of poisonous heroin rose to 12 yesterday, the authorities in four Northeastern cities said.</p>
        <p>But hospitals in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut said the number of addicts seeking treatment dropped sharply yesterday, in contrast to more than 100 overdose cases treated in the 24 hours after the drug was first sold on the streets of the South Bronx on Friday night. Officials speculated that the tide of poisonings from the drug, known by the label "Tango and Cash," may have subsided for now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The death toll from a batch of poisonous heroin rose to 12 yesterday, the authorities in four Northeastern cities said.</p>
        <p>But hospitals in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut said the number of addicts seeking treatment dropped sharply yesterday, in contrast to more than 100 overdose cases treated in the 24 hours after the drug was first sold on the streets of the South Bronx on Friday night. Officials speculated that the tide of poisonings from the drug, known by the label "Tango and Cash," may have subsided for now.</p>
        <p>Police cars with loudspeakers continued to cruise known drug-selling areas blaring warnings. Dozens of undercover and uniformed officers worked the squalid blocks around Brook Avenue and 138th and 139th Street in the South Bronx to trace the toxic heroin to its source.</p>
        <p>They were not the only ones looking for "Tango and Cash." The sidewalks of Mott Haven on Saturday night were thick with groups of men huddled on the same corners where the heroin is thought to have been sold -- in pursuit, many said, of a potent if dangerous high.</p>
        <p>A 39-year-old heroin user named Richie said: "When an addict hears that someone O.D.'d, the first question they ask is: 'Where'd they get it?' Because they want to find some of it for themselves."</p>
        <p>The addicts are confident, he said, that they would be able to dilute the drug enough to survive, but preserve the powerful high.  Potent Tranquilizer</p>
        <p>Authorities said the drug sold as heroin appeared to have been laced either with a synthetic drug, methyl fentanyl, a potent tranquilizer that New York City health authorities described as 27 times stronger than the same amount of heroin, or with a pure form of fentanyl. An overdose of the drug, which is used to tranquilize patients undergoing surgery, causes nausea and tightening of the chest muscles, and eventually can lead to cardiac arrest.</p>
        <p>Since the drug began to be sold on Friday night, five people have died in New York City, three in Newark, two in Paterson, N.J., and two in Hartford, the authorities in those cities said.</p>
        <p>Most of the 100 or so drug users treated on Saturday have been released, hospital officials said. But at Mount Sinai Hospital in Hartford, four drug users remained hospitalized, two in critical condition in the intensive care unit, said a hospital spokesman, Pete Mobilia. Mr. Mobilia said that through the weekend, 24 overdose patients were seen at Mount Sinai and its affiliate, St. Francis Hospital and Medical Center. He added that paramedics had treated other patients in the field, administering a much larger dosage of the heroin antidote, known as Narcon, than they anticipated.</p>
        <p>Peter Lynn, a spokesman for the New York City Health Department, said officials suspected other heroin users might have been affected as well. "Because of the nature of the people who use heroin, it's not always easy to find out where they are," he said.</p>
        <p>Hospital officials said that most of the addicts coming in for treatment yesterday had not overdosed, but were nervous. "There was more hysteria than anything else," said Michael Aragon, the administrator of Lincoln Hospital in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>In Paterson and Newark, the police were warning users not to use several brands of heroin besides "Tango and Cash" -- "Goodfella," "Chinatown" and "ackpot" -- as a precaution against drug dealers who have been changing the label of "Tango and Cash." That name is taken from a film with Kurt Russell and Sylvester Stallone about police officers going after drug dealers.</p>
        <p>It is common for heroin to be sold under informal brand names, as dealers seek to build a steady following for a particular mix or type, police officials say.  Tracing the Source</p>
        <p>The Newark police reported arresting two men who sold packets of "Goodfella" heroin to undercover officers. The police in Paterson arrested two men and confiscated 20 bags of "Tango and Cash," and are now testing them to determine the exact composition of the substance, said Detective Michael McNamara, a department spokesman.</p>
        <p>The police in New York and Hartford said they had made no arrests involving the toxic drug because they were focusing on an intensive investigation that would pinpoint the drug's distributors.</p>
        <p>In the two most recent deaths in New York City, acquaintances told the police that the victims had used "Tango and Cash," said Sgt. Edward Burns, a police spokesman.</p>
        <p>In the Broadway section of Paterson, an area known as a drug market, a volunteer at the Good Shepherd Mission for Men described an atmosphere of fear. "Some addicts are scared and death is in the air," said the volunteer, James Eason.</p>
        <p>But some heroin users in Hartford, as well as in the South Bronx, were said to be looking for the deadly drug. In Hartford's North End, near Stowe Village, a public housing project of squat, red-brick buildings where most of the city's 25 overdose cases occurred, residents said the word on the streets was that the drug "must be good."</p>
        <p>On Saturday night near Brook Avenue, Richie and another heroin user, a 38-year-old named Frankie, said that they had been buying heroin on the same corners of 138th Street and Brook Avenue for 20 years. Roy Friberg, a 41-year-old former heroin user who now counsels addicts throughout the city, said the block was well known among drug users. "It's legendary," he said. "And it goes on 24 hours a day."</p>
        <p>Luz Roman, the stepmother of the first drug user reported to die, Angel Luis Morciglio Jr., said mothers walking their children to school have to push their way through rows of drug dealers who peddle drugs on corners with the vigor of old-time paper boys hawking newspapers.</p>
        <p>"You have to fight your way through," she said. "They're in the schoolyards, on the sidewalks, everywhere."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
