<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Arrest in a 30-Year-Old Killing Reignites the Pain of a Victim's Family</title>
    <meta content="23cold" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/23/nyregion/23cold.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1784832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Englewood (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feuer, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fernandez, Manny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garland, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyles, Toby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Atkinson, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paneck-Saglimbene, Joyce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7DF133EF930A1575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Arrest in a 30-Year-Old Killing Reignites the Pain of a Victim's Family</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Arrest in a 30-Year-Old Murder Case Reignites the Pain of a Victim’s Family</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FEUER; Manny Fernandez, Sarah Garland and Toby Lyles contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Garland, Sarah; Fernandez, Manny; Lyles, Toby; Feuer, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas Atkinson is charged with 1976 murder of Joyce Paneck-Saglimbene in Englewood, NJ; Atkinson was 13 years old at time of fatal stabbing; served 20 years in prison for other crimes and was free for four years and living in New York City at time of arrest; question arises over whether Atkinson can be tried as adult or minor; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The ordinary life of Thomas Atkinson began five years ago when he got out of prison -- for the fifth time.</p>
        <p>He was working, married, living in the Bronx and going with his teenage son to barbecues and ballgames. It seemed like quite the turnaround for a career criminal who, in the 20 years from 1981 to 2001, had been free for only 4.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A career criminal from the Bronx has been arrested and charged with murder in a 30-year-old cold case in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The ordinary life of Thomas Atkinson began five years ago when he got out of prison -- for the fifth time.</p>
        <p>He was working, married, living in the Bronx and going with his teenage son to barbecues and ballgames. It seemed like quite the turnaround for a career criminal who, in the 20 years from 1981 to 2001, had been free for only 4.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Atkinson had paid his dues for a list of crimes -- assault, burglary and possession of stolen property -- officials said that until this week, he had gotten away with his worst. On Monday, he was arrested yet again and charged with murder in a 30-year-old case: the fatal stabbing of Joyce Paneck-Saglimbene in New Jersey, committed, officials say, when he was just 13.</p>
        <p>That Mr. Atkinson had been returned to jail for the events of May 14, 1976, when Ms. Paneck-Saglimbene, of Long Island, was found dead in a parking lot in Englewood, N.J., shocked his friends and neighbors -- though only slightly less than the arrest shocked the victim's family.</p>
        <p>In the Morris Heights section of the Bronx, where Mr. Atkinson has lived on and off for about seven years, his neighbors described a pleasant, happy-go-lucky man who, at local fish fries, liked nothing better than to win a smile as he manned the fire. In the southern New Jersey community of Browns Mills, Richard Paneck, the victim's brother, described a shocking pair of phone calls, 30 years apart: the first in 1976 to inform the family of his sister's death; the second this week to inform him that Mr. Atkinson had been caught.</p>
        <p>Mr. Atkinson, now 43, was 13 at the time of Ms. Paneck-Saglimbene's death. While he was arraigned yesterday in Bergen County Family Court, where he pleaded not guilty, John L. Molinelli, the county prosecutor, said that he planned to try him in Superior Court as an adult.</p>
        <p>That could be difficult, said Alan Zegas, a criminal defense lawyer in New Jersey. He said that at the time of the killing, the legal standard for prosecuting minors as adults was stricter than today and centered on the question of whether a suspect could be rehabilitated. These days, Mr. Zegas said, the severity of a crime is often the determining factor in trying a minor as an adult. The question remaining to be answered, he added, is which standard the court will apply.</p>
        <p>The police in Englewood have long believed that Ms. Paneck-Saglimbene, 27, was the victim of a robbery gone wrong. They say that on the day of her death, she left her desk at Diebold Computer Leasing to meet some friends for lunch. At the last minute, she changed her mind and went instead to cross an errand off her list: buying plants.</p>
        <p>That led her to the underground parking lot at Dean and Chestnut Streets, where the authorities say Mr. Atkinson was waiting. He had a knife, they say, and when his victim resisted, he stabbed her up to 19 times.</p>
        <p>Mike Mordaga, chief of detectives for the prosecutor's office, declined to say what evidence led investigators to Mr. Atkinson after all this time. He spoke only in general terms about cold cases. Often, he said, a cold case turns on a former friend who once protected a suspect and then suddenly comes forward.</p>
        <p>''Relationships change and diminish,'' Chief Mordaga said. ''What people may have said years ago can change.''</p>
        <p>Some things do not change -- a brother's grief, for one. Mr. Paneck was in his early 20's and drifting, a few years from enlisting in the Air Force, when his older sister was murdered. She was tall, blond, pretty -- like a model, he said. A Catholic high school girl who loved ''The Sound of Music'' and her pets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paneck worked nights at a service station near the family's house in Valley Stream on Long Island. He was asleep that day 30 years ago when the telephone rang.</p>
        <p>''I heard my mother scream, 'No! Not my daughter!' Then my father was talking to some detective. I ran into the kitchen. It was lunch. I remember it like it was yesterday,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Atkinson was born in Englewood, said his cousin, Henry Atkinson. There were three younger sisters and an older brother, Mr. Atkinson said, but all of them have died.</p>
        <p>''I don't think he killed nobody,'' said Mr. Atkinson, who is 56 and lives in Englewood. ''He was just 13. He would have told somebody about it.''</p>
        <p>Marjorie Merrick, who lives in Mr. Atkinson's building in a hilly area of the Bronx, not far from the Cross-Bronx Expressway, called Mr. Atkinson ''very friendly. He was Thomas. Everybody knows Thomas as Thomas. All these years I knew him, I never seen him angry.''</p>
        <p>She went on: ''You could be in a bad mood and you see Thomas, and he's going to come over to make you laugh. I just don't believe that he actually did this, even at 13. People can seem to be one way, but be another way, but still, the Thomas that I know, I can't picture it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
