<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cricket's Swan Song</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="571056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENCE WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRICKETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARS AND HEARING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">YOON, CAROL KAESUK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Ears and Hearing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ears and Hearing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DB1F3CF934A25752C1A964958260" item-length="337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cricket's Swan Song</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YOON, CAROL KAESUK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is built like a cricket's ear. It even hears like a cricket's ear. But this ear belongs to a fly.</p>
        <p>Researchers have reported that a fly whose young live off the flesh of male crickets has evolved a unique ear that can hear the trilling summer love songs of its prey. The findings of the study appear in the current issue of the journal Science.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is built like a cricket's ear. It even hears like a cricket's ear. But this ear belongs to a fly.</p>
        <p>Researchers have reported that a fly whose young live off the flesh of male crickets has evolved a unique ear that can hear the trilling summer love songs of its prey. The findings of the study appear in the current issue of the journal Science.</p>
        <p>Dr. Daniel Robert, a post-doctoral fellow at Cornell University who was the lead author of the study, said that under ideal conditions the Ormia fly's ear, one of the most sensitive ever discovered among insects, can hear the singing of a male cricket from a distance of more than 80 yards.</p>
        <p>"It's fairly mind-boggling," said Dr. Ron Hoy, a professor of neurobiology and behavior at Cornell who took part in the study. "It's more sensitive to the songs than a female cricket.  It's been able to do the cricket one better." While the antennae of flies can detect the low buzzing sounds made by other nearby flies, they are not built to detect the higher frequency songs that male crickets broadcast from afar to the eardrum-like hearing organs of female crickets. To hear the songs of the males they seek, Ormia flies have evolved a kind of eardrum in their chests , the first such ear ever discovered in the fly world.</p>
        <p>"I think it's amazing that there's an ear so different on a fly," said Dr. Thomas Walker, professor of entomology at the University of Florida who is a leader in the field of insect acoustics. Dr. Walker said that until this study, it was unknown how these flies, which are used in cricket pest control, managed to hear their prey.</p>
        <p>When a female Ormia's ear hears a singing cricket, she drops down onto him from out of the sky, leaving behind a squirming maggot that bores into him and eats the cricket, eventually killing him.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert said the females' zeal in seeking out singers was quite understandable. If not deposited on a cricket, it appears that these voracious maggots soon begin devouring their mother from the inside out.</p>
        <p>SCIENCE WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
