<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vivendi Is Said to Get 2 Bids for U.S. Units</title>
    <meta content="Y19VIV$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/19/business/media/19VIVE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1513172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vivendi Universal Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cablevision Systems Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Liberty Media Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bronfman, Edgar Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabrikant, Geraldine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Vivendi Universal</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cablevision Systems Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Broadcasting Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E2D91030F93AA2575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vivendi Is Said to Get 2 Bids for U.S. Units</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2 Bids Submitted for Vivendi Unit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabrikant, Geraldine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investor group led by Edgar Bronfman Jr that includes Cablevision Systems and by Liberty Media bid for Vivendi Universal's American entertainment assets; NBC, division of General Electric, is also still interested in Vivendi's entertainment assets although it does not make formal offer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even though Vivendi Universal itself was not taking the deadline seriously, two bidders submitted offers yesterday for the company's American entertainment assets, according to a person close to the process.</p>
        <p>The bids were turned in by an investor group led by Edgar Bronfman Jr. that includes Cablevision Systems and by Liberty Media, said this person, who could not provide details of the offers. The companies declined to comment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Liberty Media and a group led by Edgar Bronfman Jr. that includes Cablevision Systems were said to have submitted bids for the entertainment assets of Vivendi.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even though Vivendi Universal itself was not taking the deadline seriously, two bidders submitted offers yesterday for the company's American entertainment assets, according to a person close to the process.</p>
        <p>The bids were turned in by an investor group led by Edgar Bronfman Jr. that includes Cablevision Systems and by Liberty Media, said this person, who could not provide details of the offers. The companies declined to comment.</p>
        <p>NBC, a division of General Electric, is also evidently still interested in Vivendi's entertainment assets although NBC did not submit a formal offer yesterday.</p>
        <p>Several weeks ago Vivendi set yesterday as the date for receiving the next round of offers. But as it has become increasingly clear that there is not enough interest by the bidders in a formal auction process, mainly because no one appears ready to agree to the $14 billion Vivendi is said to be asking, the company seems to be holding no potentially interested party to firm deadlines.</p>
        <p>Bidders have generally placed a value of only about $12 billion on the assets, which are known as Vivendi Universal Entertainment and include the USA Network, the Sci-Fi Network, Universal Pictures and Universal Television.</p>
        <p>And in NBC's case, rather than a purchase of the assets, the discussions have involved a joint venture with Vivendi, with NBC perhaps putting in little or no cash.</p>
        <p>Also still in the mix is the cable giant Comcast. Last week several people close to Comcast's planning indicated that it might make a bid. Last Thursday, Comcast issued a statement saying it was not interested in acquiring Vivendi Universal Entertainment. But later that same day, Comcast released another statement saying that it and Vivendi were exploring joint ventures that would include the two companies' cable services as well as Vivendi Universal Entertainment's production businesses.</p>
        <p>Vivendi Universal so far has been standing firm on its $14 billion valuation, in part because the company is no longer as eager to sell assets as it was last year, when Vivendi was hard pressed to raise cash. Lately, Vivendi has indicated that it might decide not to accept a bid and might instead sell a stake to the public.</p>
        <p>The company plans a board meeting early next week in Paris to discuss the current offers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
