<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trojans' Youngster Is Adapting to the Pace</title>
    <meta content="19BOOTY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/19/sports/ncaafootball/19booty.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1513291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Southern California</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seeholzer, Don</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Booty, John David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Southern California</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E4DF1130F93AA2575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trojans' Youngster Is Adapting to the Pace</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Young Star Adapting to Pace at U.S.C.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON SEEHOLZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seeholzer, Don</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Southern California University backup quarterback John David Booty is adapting to college football after leaving high school after junior year; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It might not have ranked with Bob Beamon's world-record long jump at the 1968 Olympic Games or Neil Armstrong's moon walk in 1969, but it would have indeed been a giant leap. It will not, however, happen this year.</p>
        <p>The jump from high school junior to big-time college quarterback is going to take some time for John David Booty, who will not begin the season as Southern California's starter and will probably not see much playing time this season. At the moment, Booty, a talented 18-year-old, has his hands full simply trying to adapt to college football and the culture shock of moving from Shreveport, La., to Los Angeles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The jump from high school junior to big-time college quarterback at Southern California is going to take some time for John David Booty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It might not have ranked with Bob Beamon's world-record long jump at the 1968 Olympic Games or Neil Armstrong's moon walk in 1969, but it would have indeed been a giant leap. It will not, however, happen this year.</p>
        <p>The jump from high school junior to big-time college quarterback is going to take some time for John David Booty, who will not begin the season as Southern California's starter and will probably not see much playing time this season. At the moment, Booty, a talented 18-year-old, has his hands full simply trying to adapt to college football and the culture shock of moving from Shreveport, La., to Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>What has been his biggest adjustment so far?</p>
        <p>''Speed and the mental game of college and the speed of life compared to Louisiana,'' Booty said. ''Everybody's trying to go to the top out here. If you stop, you're going to get run over, but that's good. That's what I need in my life. I really love it out here in L.A., the people have been wonderful to me and I hope to be here for years to come.''</p>
        <p>U.S.C. is counting on it. The back soreness that cost Booty three practice days also ended any chance he had at the starting quarterback job, but he is still a player to watch in the months and years to come.</p>
        <p>''He's got great accuracy,'' Trojans Coach Pete Carroll said. ''He's a natural thrower. He has natural instincts for throwing the ball, all different kinds of throws, and putting the ball right on the money. He's not ready yet. But there's tremendous promise there for us and for him somewhere down the road.''</p>
        <p>Booty had struggled through a practice that included a tipped ball and bobbled snap, among other miscues. Such growing pains are to be expected from a player who skipped his final season at Evangel Christian Academy to enroll at U.S.C., but Booty, who could be redshirted at any time this season, figures to be fine in time. Take it from Matt Leinart, the winner of the Trojans' five-man quarterback race to succeed Carson Palmer, the Heisman Trophy winner.</p>
        <p>''He's a really talented kid and a good quarterback, but it's tough to learn this system when you have three weeks before a game,'' Leinart said. ''He'll get it. It's just going to take time.''</p>
        <p>Booty, who passed for 8,474 yards and 88 touchdowns during his final two seasons at Evangel Christian, is believed to be the first football player to graduate from high school a year early and enroll at a major Division I-A university. It is a decision he reached in April after his father, Johnny, was fired as quarterback coach and head of school at Evangel Christian, and one that Booty says he has had no cause to second-guess.</p>
        <p>''I'm right on the edge,'' he said. ''A lot of the plays I know, but there are a few where I'll know half the play and not know what the other side's doing. You know, I wasn't able to come in during spring, so I'm a little behind as far as the learning curve goes, but for the most part everything's going well. My job now is I'm not trying to start. You know, all that would be nice, but these other quarterbacks have been around for three or four years. I'd like to be around them and learn.''</p>
        <p>Based on what they have seen so far, Carroll and U.S.C. are confident Booty will be worth the wait.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
