<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.B.I. Seizes Tyrannosaur In Fight on Fossil Custody</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="529863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALEONTOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEARCH AND SEIZURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SIOUX INDIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDIANS, AMERICAN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH DAKOTA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL BUREAU OF INVESTIGATION (FBI)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BLACK HILLS INSTITUTE OF GEOLOGICAL RESEARCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DD1E38F93AA25756C0A964958260" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.B.I. Seizes Tyrannosaur In Fight on Fossil Custody</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acting on a complaint by leaders of an Indian tribe who say a private company had illegally taken fossils from tribal land, Federal agents in South Dakota have seized the largest and best-preserved Tyrannosaurus rex fossil ever found.</p>
        <p>The seizure ignited a struggle involving the Justice Department, Indian leaders, scientists, a large fossil dealer and many dinosaur enthusiasts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Acting on a complaint by leaders of an Indian tribe who say a private company had illegally taken fossils from tribal land, Federal agents in South Dakota have seized the largest and best-preserved Tyrannosaurus rex fossil ever found.</p>
        <p>The seizure ignited a struggle involving the Justice Department, Indian leaders, scientists, a large fossil dealer and many dinosaur enthusiasts.</p>
        <p>The dispute centers on ownership of the remains of the dinosaur, which in life would have been more than 50 feet long. Though such fossils are worth nothing in the ground, an important fossil like the South Dakota dinosaur could bring several million dollars, particularly from a museum abroad, paleontologists said. Fear of Damage</p>
        <p>More important, from the paleontologists' point of view, the specimen offers rare opportunities to learn more about the Tyrannosaurus rex. Though care was taken in packing the bones, they said they feared the bones might be damaged in the move.</p>
        <p>The seizure began 7:30 A.M. Thursday, when 30 officials of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, under orders from United States Attorney Kevin Schieffer, sealed off the premises of the Black Hills Institute of Geological Research in Hill City, S.D. They packed up the gigantic bones along with the company's files, photographs and specimens relating to the dinosaur.</p>
        <p>Although paleontologists frequently criticize commercialized fossil collecting, many prominent paleontologist say the Black Hills Institute takes great care to preserve scientific assets and makes them available to scholars.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, the F.B.I. trucked off the load for storage in a vault at the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology in Pierre. The skeleton is "criminal evidence," the United States Attorney's office said, but by yesterday no charges had been made against the company.</p>
        <p>"I'm reminded of the last scene in the Indiana Jones movie 'Raiders of the Lost Ark,' in which the U.S. Government, having seized the ark of the covenant, locks it away in a forgotten warehouse," said Dr. Robert Bakker, a University of Colorado paleontologist who has protested the seizure.</p>
        <p>Peter L. Larson, a geologist and president of the Black Hills Institute, said in a telephone interview yesterday that he was "stunned" by the Government's action.</p>
        <p>The dinosaur, nicknamed Sue, was excavated in 1990 after a rancher near Faith, S.D., discovered what looked like dinosaur bones sticking through the soil, Mr. Larson said.</p>
        <p>He said the institute paid the rancher, Maurice Williams, $5,000 "for the right to excavate whatever was there. We got a clear title to the find."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Williams is a member of the Cheyenne River Sioux Tribe, and his reservation land is held in trust by the Federal Bureau of Indian Affairs. Although he owns mineral rights to the land, a law requires Federal permission for the sale of antiquities found there.</p>
        <p>Mark Van Norman, a leader of the tribe, and two tribal lawyers, Steve Emery and Jim Joranko, said in a telephone interview that the seizure followed a request they had presented to the Assistant United States Attorney in Pierre for an investigation of what they asserted was illegal fossil hunting on Indian land.</p>
        <p>The excavation "was a clear violation of the Federal Antiquities Act as well as Title 25 of the U.S. Code prohibiting outsiders from making contracts with people of the Indian community without Federal permission," Mr. Van Norman said. He added that tribal leaders fully approved on the confiscation of the fossil. Possible Court Action</p>
        <p>Indian leaders said they were considering legal action aimed at taking possession of the tyrannosaur. The leaders say the tribe should have control over fossils found on tribal land.</p>
        <p>Mr. Larson said the F.B.I. officials who seized the dinosaur were "polite and sympathetic" but acted under orders. "They permitted us to supervise the packing of the bones in plaster casts and cases to prevent any more damage than necessary, but whenever bones go through something like this the risk of damage is great," he said. As the seizure proceeded, schoolchildren gathered outside with signs protesting the operation.</p>
        <p>The Black Hills Institute at Hill City, which is seven miles from Mount Rushmore, had announced in March that it planned to build a museum in Hill City, in which the tyrannosaur fossil would be the centerpiece. The institute has applied for tax-exempt status as a nonprofit institution.</p>
        <p>Among several prominent paleontologists who have voiced anger over the seizure was Dr. Bakker.</p>
        <p>"This tyrannosaur is by far the best preserved of any in the world," he said. "The Black Hills Institute people from whom it was seized are commercial fossil dealers, but they are also scientists who have made this dinosaur and other fossils available to scholars, schoolchildren and the public. They keep meticulous scientific records of their finds."</p>
        <p>The fossil is 6 percent larger than its two closest competitors: tyrannosaurs owned by the Museum of the Rockies at Bozeman, Mont., and the American Museum of Natural History in New York City.</p>
        <p>The Federal seizure took place four days before the dinosaur's five-foot skull was to have been shipped to NASA's Marshall Space Flight Center at Huntsville, Ala., for X-rays.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bakker, who obtained the agreement of NASA to make their three-dimensional X-ray machine available for the tyrannosaur skull, said the X-rays would have been of extraordinary scientific importance. Unlike other tyrannosaur skulls, this one is that of a mature adult, in which details of the brain case and other features are unusually well preserved.</p>
        <p>Another leading paleontologist and dinosaur hunter, Jack Horner of the Museum of the Rockies at Bozeman, Mont., called the seizure "absolutely ridiculous." Federal officials could easily have left the gigantic fossil where it was until the legal dispute was settled, he said. "Who's going to walk off with a tyrannosaur?" he said.</p>
        <p>Also joining the protest was Dr. Phillip Currie of the Tyrrell Museum of Paleontology at Drumheller, Alberta, Canada, which has one of the greatest dinosaur collections in the world.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schieffer, the United States Attorney, did not respond to numerous telephone calls to his office. Mr. Larson said the United States Attorney had stated that "the fossil is the property of the United States. Period."</p>
        <p>Tomorrow a meeting is scheduled between Cheyenne tribal leaders and the Black Hills Institute, at which Mr. Larson said "negotiations may yield a united front to gain Sue's release from the Feds."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
