<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surrounding the Bride With the Aura of Generations Past</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="789197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">YOUNG, SUSAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WITTEMANN, BETSY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED6133FF934A2575AC0A963958260" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surrounding the Bride With the Aura of Generations Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETSY WITTEMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WITTEMANN, BETSY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUSAN ALYSON YOUNG has degrees in art and education and a professional background in ballet dancing, costume design and college teaching. But it was in the 1960's, while working as a bridal consultant in the salon at G. Fox &amp; Company, the now-defunct Hartford department store, that she found her calling.</p>
        <p>"It was an exquisite salon, and service was the key word," recalled Ms. Young. "We worked on appointment. We wrote the articles for the newspaper. We went and dressed the brides the morning of the wedding."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUSAN ALYSON YOUNG has degrees in art and education and a professional background in ballet dancing, costume design and college teaching. But it was in the 1960's, while working as a bridal consultant in the salon at G. Fox &amp; Company, the now-defunct Hartford department store, that she found her calling.</p>
        <p>"It was an exquisite salon, and service was the key word," recalled Ms. Young. "We worked on appointment. We wrote the articles for the newspaper. We went and dressed the brides the morning of the wedding."</p>
        <p>Fox's, she said, "made me love the drama and the excitement and the wonderment of being a bride."</p>
        <p>For the past nine years she has conveyed that special quality to more than 400 young women for whom she has restored vintage wedding dresses, one for a bride who was the 11th in her family to wear a treasured early 19th-century gown.</p>
        <p>Never mind today's use-it-up, throw-it-out mentality. Her brides, Ms. Young said, "are going to walk down the aisle being themselves but wearing the tradition, the family value, the sentimentality of something that has been worn by one or two or more generations. Surrounding the girl is all of the love and the good feeling" of her predecessors.</p>
        <p>Susan Young runs her business, Alyson Originals, from her antiques-filled, Cape Cod-style home in Glastonbury. The first meeting with a prospective bride and, usually, her mother, takes place in the dining room. The gateleg table is pushed to one side and a three-way mirror stands in one corner. It is apt to be an emotional moment. The bridal gown -- no matter how terrible its condition -- is presented for inspection.</p>
        <p>"Picture this," said Ms. Young.  "Here is a Mom whose joys and hopes for her future were expressed when she wore this dress. This child, standing here now, 25 years later, she never knew about at that time. . . . It's like childbirth, or what I imagine it would be, a combination of joy and pain, of watching someone of the next generation look at something you love."</p>
        <p>Very rarely does the mother try to pressure her daughter into wearing her gown, and that's a good thing, Ms. Young said. "If I sense this is happening, and it has happened a couple of times, I will talk the bride out of the dress," she added. "You can't do that; it is going to cause problems." More commonly, the bride-to-be has loved, and wanted to wear, the mother's or grandmother's gown for years. What can be worrisome is dress size.</p>
        <p>"The average young woman today is larger than her mother," Ms. Young explained. "The diaphragm, rib cage and across the shoulders -- 9 out of 10 dresses I see don't fit in those areas." But they can be made to fit. The process takes several months and involves four to five consultations and fittings. The cost can be the same as that for a new dress.</p>
        <p>In addition to restoring the dress -- itself a specialty, often with mind-boggling challenges -- Ms. Young, 45, designs a veil and headpiece, makes suggestions on bridesmaids' outfits (simple off-the-rack dresses with clean lines or Laura Ashley dresses are her preference), explains the etiquette of the wedding day, and soothes nerves along the way.</p>
        <p>As a member of the Costume and Textile Society at the Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford, and a former associate professor in costume history and design at the University of Hartford, Ms. Young is serious indeed about restoration.</p>
        <p>She has worked with netting and lace so frayed it could barely be touched, with early 19th-century white velvet from the Cheney Mills of nearby Manchester, with gowns sometimes black from mold and mishandling.</p>
        <p>"If it is all made by hand, we do all of the work by hand," said Ms. Young. "If it was sewn on a treadle machine with a chain stitch, we sew it on a treadle machine with a chain stitch. If it was sewn on a modern machine, then we will sew it on a modern machine. We do all of the finish work by hand. All lace is sewn on by hand, all beads are sewn on by hand. God forbid a glue would enter the room."</p>
        <p>About two weeks before the wedding, the bride tries on the restored dress with the veil, often a tearful time. "If anything's going to crack a bride, it's when they put on that veil, because it's no longer just a dress, it's a reality, and it's not just a reality as in 'I'm a bride,' but the real reality is, 'I'm about to be a wife.' The mothers cry," said Ms. Young. She keeps a box of tissues in the room.</p>
        <p>The final consultation is an hourlong meeting with the bride, the bride's mother, and the honor attendant a day or two before the wedding, when they pick up the dress. These appointments appear in bright red in Ms. Young's complex calendar, kept in her second-floor studio, and are her favorites.</p>
        <p>"It's like I'm living with them their day. In the olden days we used to have tribes where the elder women would pass on information to each girl and help her move through her life," Ms Young said. "Many girls don't even have that relationship with their Moms now. And so I try and bring everyone back together again. And for a few brief moments we become like a little tribe in the room, and we sit here with this new bride and we laugh and we giggle and we talk about what's going to happen to her and how to deal with certain situations, and we share it and we're re-living our own day."</p>
        <p>Ms. Young's eyes are bright -- possibly with memories of her 1983 wedding to Charles Young, a paper conservator, at the Fine Bouche restaurant in Centerbrook when she became the fifth bride to wear a wedding gown from the Edwardian period. She sewed her name into the waistband the night before.</p>
        <p>Among the pieces of advice given to new brides -- most of them her well-kept secrets -- is to have a banana early on the wedding day to help keep up energy, and advice to the maid of honor not to rearrange the bridal train just before the newly married couple walks back down the aisle (it interrupts the emotion of the moment).</p>
        <p>Susan Young handles up to 90 weddings each year, and says she laments the passage of each one of her "girls." If she is lucky, however, they may return for the next big event in their personal lives. She also restores christening gowns.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
