<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Streetscapes: Temple B'nai Israel; A Church Tackles Renovation</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="789189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SYNAGOGUES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HARLEM (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BAPTIST CHURCHES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GOSPEL MISSIONARY BAPTIST CHURCH (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TEMPLE B'NAI ISRAEL (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROTH, EMERY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Synagogues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DF153FF934A2575AC0A963958260" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Streetscapes: Temple B'nai Israel; A Church Tackles Renovation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH hidden away on a side street, the 1923 Temple B'nai Israel, at 604 West 149th Street, was one of the grandest synagogues in upper Manhattan until its congregation finally left in 1979. Now, after years of neglect and decay, a Baptist church is trying to revive this behemoth.</p>
        <p>In the 1900's and 1910's, Broadway above 125th Street along the new subway route sprouted apartment houses on land that had been largely vacant before the turn of the century. The new line brought the area within commuting range of downtown factories and offices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH hidden away on a side street, the 1923 Temple B'nai Israel, at 604 West 149th Street, was one of the grandest synagogues in upper Manhattan until its congregation finally left in 1979. Now, after years of neglect and decay, a Baptist church is trying to revive this behemoth.</p>
        <p>In the 1900's and 1910's, Broadway above 125th Street along the new subway route sprouted apartment houses on land that had been largely vacant before the turn of the century. The new line brought the area within commuting range of downtown factories and offices.</p>
        <p>In 1917 a group of newly arrived residents met to incorporate Congregation B'nai Israel of Washington Heights and bought a plot on 149th off Broadway. They announced a $100,000 synagogue designed by Emery Roth with schoolrooms and an auditorium seating 1,400 people. Roth's first proposal was for a twin-towered neo-Classical building, richly carved and decorated. But World War I intervened, and afterward Roth produced a revised design, which was completed in 1923.</p>
        <p>This building was less extensively decorated but more expensive -- $200,000. Set in a plain, limestone wall, a semicircular window suggests the circular space within, confirmed by a giant, eight-sided copper dome that surmounted the top. On the inside, a large balcony runs across the front wall, facing south, but the rest of the sanctuary is high and open, rising perhaps 75 feet to the dome.</p>
        <p>B'nai Israel apparently prospered during the 1920's. Hyman Reit, its president, was also president of the United Synagogues of America, and at a Chanukah celebration at B'nai Israel in 1930 he urged the teaching of Hebrew in the public schools. "Hebrew is just as classical and cultural a language as Latin and Greek," he told The New York Times.</p>
        <p>By the 1960's the neighborhood was almost completely Latino and black, but B'nai Israel held on until 1979. In that year Ernest Milchman, an investor, bought the property. "There were only two or three people left in the congregation," he remembered, adding that the building operated principally as a yeshiva.</p>
        <p>He has resold the building three times since his purchase. In 1980 he sold the building to a revivalist Christian church, but, he said, he was forced to foreclose. "We found it full of stray dogs," Mr. Milchman said. It was at that time, with the building in severe but not fatal disrepair, that Mr. Milchman replaced the windows -- including the giant, semicircular stained-glass window facing 149th Street -- with cinder block.</p>
        <p>IN 1985, Mr. Milchman sold the building to a real estate operator but in 1993 was again forced to foreclose. At one point the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints was interested, he said, but the church decided that the building was too far away from where most of its parishioners lived.</p>
        <p>In 1985 the Landmarks Preservation Commission rated the building of "outstanding significance" in a citywide survey of potential landmarks, but the survey was not released and the building has not received landmark status.</p>
        <p>During the late 1980's and early 1990's the building deteriorated. Vandals gained entrance and damaged the interior. Worse, thieves began to steal parts of the giant copper dome, letting water destroy what was left.</p>
        <p>In 1991 two Manhattan preservationists, Michael Adams and Ronald Melichar, found, on the roof of a car, a huge copper lion's head from the dome.</p>
        <p>They found the owner of the car and detained him, they said, but their repeated attempts to enlist the aid of the police were unavailing, and now the only copper left on the dome is beyond reach. Since that time, when it rains outside, it has rained inside.</p>
        <p>In 1994 Mr. Milchman sold Temple B'nai Israel a third time, to the Gospel Missionary Baptist Church, which currently worships in a rented basement. The recorded deed states a price of $454,900, payable in monthly installments of $4,504.87 until the year 2023.</p>
        <p>What the new owner has gotten is a building in serious trouble. The church has cleaned out the debris and put a new interior roof underneath the dome, but the entire exterior is otherwise still derelict. Inside, the plaster, the ornamental marble gilding and other decorations have fallen away to the underlying brick walls, in some places to the bare steel.</p>
        <p>And 18 months after the purchase there is no plumbing and no electricity -- only a flashlight.</p>
        <p>The pastor, the Rev. Henry L. Smalls, said he somehow plans to open the church to his congregation of about 300 in October, but he still has no architect, no engineer and no estimate for a renovation. "We have faith," he said. "We know that God will make a way. I really want to restore that dome, maybe with a steeple on it, so you can see the Gospel Missionary from all over."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
