<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former KPMG Partner Settles in Xerox Case</title>
    <meta content="07audit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/07/business/07audit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1707813"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Floyd Norris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">KPMG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Xerox Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6D81E30F934A35753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former KPMG Partner Settles in Xerox Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Former KPMG Partner Settles in Xerox Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former KPMG partner who was involved in audits of the Xerox Corporation settled with the Securities and Exchange Commission yesterday, leaving four other partners still facing litigation over the audits from 1997 to 2000, which the S.E.C. claims allowed the company to overstate profits by $1.3 billion.</p>
        <p>The former partner, Joseph T. Boyle, 62, agreed to pay a civil penalty of $100,000 and accepted an injunction barring him from violating a section of the securities laws in the future. The S.E.C. also barred him from auditing public companies for a year. He neither admitted nor denied the accusations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former KPMG partner who was involved in audits of the Xerox Corporation settled with the Securities and Exchange Commission yesterday, leaving four other partners still facing litigation over the audits from 1997 to 2000, which the S.E.C. claims allowed the company to overstate profits by $1.3 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former KPMG partner who was involved in audits of the Xerox Corporation settled with the Securities and Exchange Commission yesterday, leaving four other partners still facing litigation over the audits from 1997 to 2000, which the S.E.C. claims allowed the company to overstate profits by $1.3 billion.</p>
        <p>The former partner, Joseph T. Boyle, 62, agreed to pay a civil penalty of $100,000 and accepted an injunction barring him from violating a section of the securities laws in the future. The S.E.C. also barred him from auditing public companies for a year. He neither admitted nor denied the accusations.</p>
        <p>The $100,000 fine was the largest ever imposed on an individual auditor by the S.E.C., said James A. Kidney, the assistant chief litigation counsel of the S.E.C. KPMG paid $22.5 million in August to settle its part of the case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boyle was KPMG's relationship partner with Xerox in 1999 and 2000, at a time when KPMG auditors were concerned over what some saw as violations of accounting rules by the company. The S.E.C. later charged Xerox with abusing accounting rules to continue reporting strong profits even as competition in the copier market intensified.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C., in a suit filed in federal court in New York in 2003, claimed that Ronald A. Safran, a KPMG partner who was the lead engagement partner on the Xerox account in 1998 and 1999, told Mr. Boyle that Xerox was engaging in improper conduct and that KPMG had an obligation to tell the company's audit committee. The board was not told, and KPMG did not force Xerox to change the accounting procedures the S.E.C. concluded were improper.</p>
        <p>''Auditors, including relationship partners, are gatekeepers who bear special responsibilities in the financial reporting process,'' said Linda Chatman Thomsen, the S.E.C.'s director of enforcement. ''Auditors who fail to perform those legal duties risk meaningful sanctions.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boyle retired from KPMG in 2003, after the S.E.C. suit was filed. His lawyer, Samuel J. Winer of Foley &amp; Lardner in Washington, said, ''Mr. Boyle, who has been retired for nearly two years, is pleased that the S.E.C. dropped all but one of the charges against him and looks forward to continuing his retirement without the distraction of litigation.''</p>
        <p>After Xerox complained about Mr. Safran, KPMG removed him as the lead partner on the account, transferring him to Houston from New York after he turned down a move to Finland.</p>
        <p>Mr. Safran is one of the KPMG partners still facing S.E.C. civil action. The commission contends that he acted wrongly in signing off on the Xerox audits even after he voiced concerns. A trial is scheduled for March 6.</p>
        <p>Deloitte Audits Examined  By Bloomberg News</p>
        <p>The auditing firm Deloitte &amp; Touche had deficiencies on about 6 percent of audits reviewed last year by the agency created to oversee the accounting industry, according to a report issued yesterday.</p>
        <p>The agency, the Public Company Accounting Oversight Board, said it had found deficiencies on audits of eight Deloitte client firms, four of which revised financial statements as a result.</p>
        <p>It is the second report the agency has issued on one of the big four accounting firms. A report issued last week on KPMG found deficiencies in 19 audits, or 25 percent of the 76 reviewed.</p>
        <p>Reports on Ernst &amp; Young and PricewaterhouseCoopers have not been released.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
