<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraq Threatens To Shoot Down U.S. Spy Planes</title>
    <meta content="04IRAQ$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="970540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Amb)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EED91330F937A35752C1A961958260" item-length="1363" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraq Threatens To Shoot Down U.S. Spy Planes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Nov. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iraq threatens to shoot down American U-2 spy planes used by international disarmament monitors; threat follows demand that surveillance flights end and that all American arms inspectors in Baghdad with UN team be withdrawn; Bill Richardson, US Ambassador to UN, calls demand irresponsible and direct threat to world body; Iraq says it will welcome three-member diplomatic mission from UN to discuss impasse; Sec Gen Kofi Annan says he has asked Pres Saddam Hussein to abide by UN rules for arms inspections; is optimistic Hussein will meet with envoys; State Dept spokesman says Clinton Administration is prepared to await results of diplomatic mission before exploring further options; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Saddam Hussein of Iraq, in a move sure to isolate his country further, threatened today to shoot down the American U-2 spy planes used by international disarmament monitors.</p>
        <p>The United States has not said it has any plans to ground the U-2's. Tonight, after meeting with the United Nations Security Council, Richard Butler, the head of the organization's inspection commission charged with eliminating Iraq's weapons of mass destruction, said, ''The U-2's have been authorized to go ahead.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Saddam Hussein of Iraq, in a move sure to isolate his country further, threatened today to shoot down the American U-2 spy planes used by international disarmament monitors.</p>
        <p>The United States has not said it has any plans to ground the U-2's. Tonight, after meeting with the United Nations Security Council, Richard Butler, the head of the organization's inspection commission charged with eliminating Iraq's weapons of mass destruction, said, ''The U-2's have been authorized to go ahead.''</p>
        <p>The final decision to fly, however, would have to rest with the Pentagon. Iraq has defensive missiles capable of hitting the plane, officials said here, and the Pentagon would have to assess the risks, but the likelihood of hitting the high-altitude planes is low. [Page A6.]</p>
        <p>Bill Richardson, the United States representative to the United Nations, called the threat against the U-2 flights ''irresponsible.''</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration, under pressure from Congress to react forcefully to Iraq, has tried to contain the dispute within the United Nations system, where Washington can count on the backing of the Security Council. Any independent use of force by the United States without Council approval would shatter that unity at this point.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson said pointedly today that the warning about U-2 flights was ''a direct threat to the United Nations'' and did not portray it as a strictly national issue, but rather as an outgrowth of the coalition built within the United Nations that was critical to the United States during the 1991 war with Iraq.</p>
        <p>Some diplomats believe that President Hussein may in fact be trying to goad Washington into military action to drive a wedge between Washington and other Council members, particularly Russia and France, which have argued in the past for an easing of sanctions. But that plan could backfire. A Western diplomat said today that Iraq's action was ''not the best way to consolidate support.''</p>
        <p>The threat to shoot down -- or shoot at -- the surveillance aircraft was in a letter sent to Mr. Butler on Sunday night by Iraq's United Nations representative, Nizar Hamdoon. It follows a demand made last Wednesday that the surveillance flights end and that all American arms inspectors based in Baghdad for the United Nations be withdrawn.</p>
        <p>But while Iraq is threatening attacks on American aircraft, Iraq's Deputy Prime Minister, Tariq Aziz, told Secretary General Kofi Annan in a telephone conversation today that a three-member diplomatic mission from the United Nations would be welcomed in the country to discuss the impasse. The delegation -- composed of Algerian, Argentine and Swedish diplomats appointed on Sunday by Mr. Annan -- will arrive in Baghdad on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The diplomatic mission to Iraq -- to be led by Lakhdar Brahimi, a former Algerian foreign minister who has represented the Secretary General in Haiti and Afghanistan -- was first proposed on Friday, with the enthusiastic support of France but was rejected initially by the United States and Britain.</p>
        <p>Intense diplomatic efforts over the weekend led to the formation of a slightly different team with a clearly limited mandate, and a change of heart in Washington. The other two members of the team are Emilio Cardenas, a former envoy of Argentina to the United Nations, and Jan Eliasson, a Swedish diplomat and former United Nations Under Secretary General.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing to negotiate,'' Fred Eckhard, the United Nations spokesman said today. ''This is a diplomatic effort to defuse a very dangerous situation. The next step is up to Iraq.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Annan told reporters today after briefing the Security Council on his mission that he had written to President Hussein urging him to abide by the United Nations rules for inspections. He said he hoped that the Iraqi President would meet with the three envoys.</p>
        <p>In Washington, James P. Rubin, the State Department spokesman, said that the Administration was prepared to wait until the diplomatic mission returns from Iraq this weekend before considering any other options.</p>
        <p>''Whatever it takes for Saddam to get the message we believe would be helpful,'' Mr. Rubin said.</p>
        <p>Since Baghdad announced the ban on Americans last week, inspections of Iraq's biological, chemical, nuclear and missile programs have been suspended. They could not be resumed today as planned after the Iraqis stopped a team of biological arms experts from visiting a site because one experts was an American. Twice in the last week, Iraq has also barred other Americans from entering the country to join the Baghdad-based teams.</p>
        <p>After today's incident the United Nations immediately called off two other inspections, for chemical weapons and missiles. All inspections were halted for the first time last Wednesday after the Iraqis gave American arms experts working for the United Nations in Baghdad a week to leave the country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Butler said tonight that he was hoping to resume normal work on Tuesday. Iraq, which first threatened to halt all inspections, apparently decided to put pressure on the United States because the Clinton Administration has been trying to increase sanctions on Iraq over its lack of cooperation in accounting for prohibited arms.</p>
        <p>Today, Council members were busy in closed-door meetings to discuss, among other topics, the question of whether Iraq is breaching its 1991 cease-fire obligations and therefore vulnerable to military action should the confrontation continue or worsen. French and Russian delegations, backed by Arab and African nations, have said that the use of force would not be acceptable without further Council action. At the State Department, Mr. Rubin took another view.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there's any question in our minds that we have all the authority we need,'' he said. ''But that's not what the policy of the United States is now to emphasize. The policy of the United States to emphasize right now is that we want Saddam Hussein to get the message, to change his mind, to get on with the show of compliance with the U.N. Security Council resolutions, and if that doesn't happen, for the Security Council to take firm action to convince him to do so.''</p>
        <p>The discussions over how to force Iraqi compliance come at an interesting time for the Security Council. China, which generally opposes sanctions and military intervention, holds the rotating Council presidency for November. The Iraq issue could be an early test of relations with Washington after the recent visit of President Jiang Zemin.</p>
        <p>In Baghdad, the official Iraqi News Agency announced that President Hussein stressed at a Cabinet meeting on Sunday that while the country was prepared for American attacks, he believed in ''the importance of conducting a dialogue that will put things in their proper perspective, where rights and obligations will be clarified without any confusion, ambiguity or procrastination.''</p>
        <p>The news agency reported that the Iraqi leader hopes to discuss a date for lifting of a blanket United Nations embargo. Apparently, the Iraqis think that the ban on Americans is negotiable. But that is exactly what the United States and the United Nations will not accept. Mr. Richardson, the United States representative, has said every day since the Iraqi decision was announced last week that there was nothing to negotiate.</p>
        <p>Baghdad cannot hope to have the sanctions lifted until the Security Council is convinced that all prohibited Iraqi weapons systems have been destroyed and that the country does not have the industrial base for creating new ones. The United States has also insisted that Iraq meet additional requirements, including returning stolen property, releasing  Kuwaiti prisoners and accounting for others missing since the 1990 invasion of Kuwait.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
