<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AUTOS ON MONDAY/Collecting; What the Faithful Drive While Awaiting Alfa's Return</title>
    <meta content="10CARS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/10/automobiles/10CARS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1708789"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4D61F30F933A25753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AUTOS ON MONDAY/Collecting; What the Faithful Drive While Awaiting Alfa's Return</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What the Faithful Drive While Awaiting Alfa's Return</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH MARTIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MANY automakers have tried to carve out a permanent place in the American market, only to fail and leave behind bankrupt dealerships and multitudes of frustrated customers.</p>
        <p>Despite the hardships caused by the companies' departures, few tears were shed when European marques like Citroën, Fiat, Peugeot and Renault went back home. Offering cars that were not well-suited to American driving conditions or that earned poor reputations for reliability, these brands attracted only small -- and not especially loyal -- followings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The loyal Alfisti continue to drive their old Alfa Romeos as they hope for the return of the Italian marque."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MANY automakers have tried to carve out a permanent place in the American market, only to fail and leave behind bankrupt dealerships and multitudes of frustrated customers.</p>
        <p>Despite the hardships caused by the companies' departures, few tears were shed when European marques like Citroën, Fiat, Peugeot and Renault went back home. Offering cars that were not well-suited to American driving conditions or that earned poor reputations for reliability, these brands attracted only small -- and not especially loyal -- followings.</p>
        <p>The parting of Alfa Romeo was different.</p>
        <p>A decade after the last new Alfa was sold in the United States, the automaker's mystique is still potent. Those who know and love the cars -- the Alfisti -- remain devoted. At the annual convention of the Alfa Romeo Owners Club, held in July in Bellevue, Wash., hundreds of owners arrived in prized models from the Milanese carmaker's past. Many of those collectors would welcome the company's return to this country, a possibility the company admits it is considering.</p>
        <p>Alfas have always been raced, from the first model -- the 24 HP of 1910 -- to the current 156, a consistent winner in the hotly contested World Touring Car Championship, a series as popular in Europe as Nascar is here. Some of Alfa's racing heritage always seemed to find its way into production cars, even the most mundane sedans.</p>
        <p>Many Americans' first exposure to Alfa was the Duetto Spider that Dustin Hoffman drove in the 1967 film ''The Graduate.'' That roadster was an excellent example of Alfa's practice of transferring racing technology to its road cars. Many features of the Duetto's engine -- an aluminum block and cylinder head, twin overhead camshafts and dual-throat Weber carburetors -- were ahead of the competition's.</p>
        <p>The racing-bred engine gave the Duetto a kick that enthusiasts loved. The same basic chassis and engine design also served as the basis for a homely four-door sedan of the same era, the Giulia Super.</p>
        <p>The practice of sharing components was employed by Alfa as far back as 1924, when a similar chassis was used for coupes, convertibles and sedans, all powered by 1.5-liter engines. And it was true of Alfa's last model sold in the United States, the quirky 164 sedan, which shared its architecture with the Saab 9000, Lancia Thema and Fiat Croma.</p>
        <p>Since the company's departure from the United States in 1995, Alfisti have held on to a spark of hope that the marque might someday return.</p>
        <p>Getting a definitive answer to questions about Alfa's return is about as difficult as finding authentic pizza in Pyongyang -- which is to say, nearly impossible. The official position, outlined in an e-mail message from Richard Gadeselli, vice president of international corporate communications for Fiat, describes the conditions that must be met before Alfa returns to America.</p>
        <p>''We have stated that the return of Alfa Romeo to the U.S. market is in the cards,'' Mr. Gadeselli said, ''but not before Alfa's increasing and consolidating its sales in Europe. Our plan calls for 300,000 Alfa sales per year in some three to four years. In 2004, Alfa sold 175,000 cars worldwide. I would also mention that none of the current lineup has been engineered for federal use.''</p>
        <p>According to Ron Tonkin, whose Portland, Ore., dealership is an authorized Alfa Romeo parts and service center, preparations are actually further along than the company's statement indicates.</p>
        <p>''I have had conversations with some decision-makers at Alfa Romeo,'' Mr. Tonkin said. ''They have said that Alfas will be sold through Ferrari-Maserati dealers when they return to the U.S. We will probably see the first of those cars in late 2007.''</p>
        <p>The lack of new cars is not keeping enthusiasts from enjoying Alfas they already own. For a car whose sales peak in America was about 8,200 -- in 1986, the same year Fiat took control of the company -- parts and service are surprisingly plentiful. While Alfas are regarded by owners as mechanically robust (though it takes a well-versed technician to tune them properly) finding various trim and upholstery parts was once a problem.</p>
        <p>Restorations have become simpler than they were 10 years ago with the emergence of companies like Re-Originals, in Houston, that deal in everything from original seat-cover materials for 1960's Spiders to rubber floor mats for other Alfas of the era.</p>
        <p>Alfas are often considered a logical first step for collectors attracted to Italian sports cars, starting them on the path to brands of increasingly greater performance and sophistication: Lancia, Maserati and Ferrari.</p>
        <p>''Alfas have always been the poor man's Ferrari,'' said Mark Leonard, a classic car dealer in La Jolla, Calif. ''But there was a lot of racecar in every production Alfa.''</p>
        <p>Each Alfa, from the earliest cars in 1910 to the models sold in Europe today, offers a graceful amalgam of style and performance that sets it apart.</p>
        <p>Even Henry Ford recognized this. Legend has it that he once said, ''Every time an Alfa goes by, I tip my hat.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
