<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing a Cat-and-Mouse Game</title>
    <meta content="08NORT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/08/international/worldspecial/08NORT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1479167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION AT WAR: IN THE FIELD | THE NORTHERN FRONT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dibaga (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohde, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EFD81038F93BA35757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing a Cat-and-Mouse Game</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Playing a Cat-and-Mouse Game</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID ROHDE with C. J. CHIVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohde, David; Chivers, C J</byline>
      <dateline>NEAR DIBAGA, Iraq, April 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Northern front in war in Iraq has become cat-and-mouse game between small American Special Operations units and group of Iraqi commanders who are proving to be surprisingly tenacious; American goal is to pin down estimated 100,000 Iraqi soldiers near Dibaga, to prevent them from going to Baghdad; Iraqis are retaliating against Americans with increasingly accurate artillery fire; they have thwarted attempts by Special Operations teams to advance, despite aid of hundreds of Kurdish soldiers and heavy American airstrikes; small, lightly armed American Special Oeprations teams have had several close calls, but they have succeeded in stabilizing area and helping to deter Turkey from dispatching troops into northern Iraq; US is resisting Kurds' plea to launch major offensive there, hoping not to inflame Turkish-Kurdish relations; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two American Special Operations soldiers sat in their Humvee on a small ridge here this afternoon and watched a white-and-orange taxi speed down a nearby road. As they viewed the car through binoculars, a second group of Americans shot at it with a .50-caliber machine gun.</p>
        <p>The soldiers said the driver of the taxi was an Iraqi soldier trying to lure them into an ambush. ''They're begging you to follow him,'' one of the soldiers said, as the taxi disappeared around a bend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The northern front has pitted small American units against a group of tenacious Iraqi commanders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two American Special Operations soldiers sat in their Humvee on a small ridge here this afternoon and watched a white-and-orange taxi speed down a nearby road. As they viewed the car through binoculars, a second group of Americans shot at it with a .50-caliber machine gun.</p>
        <p>The soldiers said the driver of the taxi was an Iraqi soldier trying to lure them into an ambush. ''They're begging you to follow him,'' one of the soldiers said, as the taxi disappeared around a bend.</p>
        <p>The scene was typical of what the northern front in the war in Iraq has become: a cat-and-mouse game between small American Special Operations units and a group of Iraqi commanders who are proving to be surprisingly tenacious.</p>
        <p>American forces are trying to destroy Iraqi units and pin down the estimated 100,000 Iraqi soldiers here so that they cannot go to Baghdad. The Iraqis are retaliating against the Americans with increasingly accurate artillery fire.</p>
        <p>On one level the Iraqis are succeeding. After withdrawing from a series of frontline positions around Mosul early last week, they have put up unexpectedly tough resistance along a second defensive line. Over the last several days they have thwarted attempts by Special Operations teams to advance, despite the aid of hundreds of Kurdish soldiers and heavy American airstrikes.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is that we can't seize terrain,'' said a Special Operations soldier.</p>
        <p>But on another level, the Americans are succeeding. They have kept the Iraqi forces occupied with a relatively small number of soldiers -- as many as 1,000 Special Operations troops and roughly 2,000 paratroopers -- not enough for a major offensive. The American forces have also stabilized the area and helped deter Turkey from dispatching troops into northern Iraq.</p>
        <p>Some Americans and many Kurdish officials have expressed frustration with the American tactics.</p>
        <p>Although Kurdish officials say their military units are eager to mount a larger offensive, the United States has resisted. Senior officials have described two principal reasons for their restraint, one political and the other military.</p>
        <p>First, they say, Turkey remains concerned about Kurdish military action against Kirkuk and Mosul, and the United States hopes not to inflame Turkish-Kurdish relations. The United States also does not have the large ground units here with tanks and artillery required to ensure that an attack would succeed.</p>
        <p>Given these constraints, the northern front now involves Special Forces units guiding airstrikes that ''encourage'' Iraqi units to withdraw, American soldiers said. Following the orders of American troops, Kurds, who have no tanks of their own, either attack Iraqi positions or move in to fill the vacuum left by retreating Iraqis.</p>
        <p>''We wait for each collapse at the lines,'' a senior Kurdish official said, ''and then go through them and secure the ground.''</p>
        <p>The operations here can be deadly. A few hundred yards from where the soldiers sat this afternoon, an accidental bombing of a convoy of American and Kurdish soldiers killed 19 Kurds on Sunday. The strike -- the worst single incident of mistaken fire in the war -- was a hint of what American bombs may have been doing to Iraqi conscripts on the other side of the front line for more than two weeks.</p>
        <p>The small, lightly armed American Special Operations teams have had several close calls. An American team that was discovered by Iraqis behind their lines last week reportedly had to be airlifted out by helicopter. And Iraqi artillery shells that killed two senior Kurdish commanders last week came within 50 yards of hitting Americans.</p>
        <p>''They're good,'' one Special Operations commander said after several days of combat with the Iraqis.</p>
        <p>To the surprise of some Special Operations soldiers, American air power alone has not been enough to force the Iraqis to retreat. An infantry truism -- that tanks and soldiers are needed to seize and hold ground -- is apparently being reinforced here.</p>
        <p>In a three-day period on the front line due east of Mosul, Special Operations soldiers had American planes drop more than 200 bombs on Iraqi positions in Khazir. The Iraqis did not budge from the route, the shortest into Mosul from the Kurdish-controlled enclave in northern Iraq. In fact they reinforced their positions and retook some lost ground.</p>
        <p>''Two companies of light infantry attacked us,'' a Special Operations soldier said, referring to roughly 200 troops. ''We fought them off with light machine guns and rifles.''</p>
        <p>An effort by a Special Operations team and several hundred Kurdish fighters to attack Mosul from the south through the town of Gwer on Sunday morning also stalled. Despite heavy American airstrikes, Iraqi artillery units were able to fire dozens of shells accurately onto advancing Kurds and Americans.</p>
        <p>To the north of Mosul, Kurdish troops and American Special Operations forces moved into the town of Sher Khan on Sunday morning. Kurdish commanders said they defeated the Iraqis, but residents said the Iraqis withdrew after heavy American bombing. The Iraqis have set up a new defensive line south of the city and so far have held their ground, Kurdish officials said.</p>
        <p>The only clear success in seizing terrain has occurred here, to the far south of Mosul, where American and Kurdish forces destroyed 10 tanks and cut the main road linking Mosul and Kirkuk on Sunday.</p>
        <p>A NATION AT WAR: IN THE FIELD | THE NORTHERN FRONT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
