<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing It Safe Works For Now</title>
    <meta content="21BROO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1178283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/David Brooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEED61730F932A15751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing It Safe Works For Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Brooks</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was as if we were watching a cross between ''The Newlywed Game'' and ''The Jerry Springer Show.'' John and Cindy McCain were up there on the podium conceding the South Carolina primary on Saturday night, and they were smiling and nuzzling as if they had just won a dining room set from Bob Eubanks. But if you listened to Senator McCain's words, what you heard was rage and indignation. He basically called George W. Bush a fraud, a sleaze artist and an empty suit.</p>
        <p>It was one of the most remarkable concession speeches of recent memory, and it was a mistake. But it wasn't a mistake because it showed Mr. McCain's inner temper. It was a mistake because it showed that he misunderstands this campaign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was as if we were watching a cross between ''The Newlywed Game'' and ''The Jerry Springer Show.'' John and Cindy McCain were up there on the podium conceding the South Carolina primary on Saturday night, and they were smiling and nuzzling as if they had just won a dining room set from Bob Eubanks. But if you listened to Senator McCain's words, what you heard was rage and indignation. He basically called George W. Bush a fraud, a sleaze artist and an empty suit.</p>
        <p>It was one of the most remarkable concession speeches of recent memory, and it was a mistake. But it wasn't a mistake because it showed Mr. McCain's inner temper. It was a mistake because it showed that he misunderstands this campaign.</p>
        <p>John McCain is trying to make this an election about honor. Ever since Mr. Bush stood with a fringe M.I.A. activist who accused the Arizona senator of abandoning the veterans, Mr. McCain has seemed intent on restoring his honor and undermining Mr. Bush's. But that's never going to work. Republicans are never going to vote against Mr. Bush because he's part Lee Atwater. No party minds low-road campaign tactics that are perpetrated by its own candidates. Besides, Mr. Bush is so gracious he will just brush off any attempts by Mr. McCain to portray him as the Black Knight.</p>
        <p>The problem with Mr. Bush is that he is part Bob Dole. Over the past month, he has run an utterly orthodox Republican campaign, wrapping himself in the party's conservative establishment. In South Carolina, he bombarded the state with taped phone calls from Strom Thurmond, Barbara Bush and Elizabeth Dole, not exactly fresh faces in the Republican firmament. On the issues, he is running the G.O.P. paint-by-numbers campaign: tax cuts, abortion, limited government. He's already got so many living Republicans endorsing him he might have to start rolling out Herbert Hoover and William McKinley.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and his allies Rush Limbaugh and Pat Robertson controlled the debate in South Carolina precisely by building a wall around conservatives and reminding voters that John McCain -- that media darling who met with the gays -- is not One of Us. It was classic identity group politics.</p>
        <p>Senator McCain's slim hope of winning in Michigan and beyond depends on whether he can turn Mr. Bush's tactics against him. He has to remind Republican voters that this G.O.P. establishment that Mr. Bush has stapled himself to lost in 1992, lost in 1996 and almost lost the House in 1998. On Capitol Hill, this Republican establishment has been bloodied and battered, ceding policy ground to the Democrats for the past four years.</p>
        <p>In other words, Mr. McCain has to take advantage of the line that runs down the Republican Party -- the divide between the regulars and the rebels. The regulars think the standard conservative issues, like tax cuts, can still win elections if articulated by an attractive candidate. The rebels believe the conservative movement has cracked up, the Republican establishment has ossified, and the Goldwater-Reagan ideological message needs to be overhauled. In New Hampshire, Mr. McCain showed signs of running as head of the rebel alliance, before he got sidetracked on the matter of his personal honor.</p>
        <p>What Mr. McCain needs to do is run the sort of campaign Mr. Bush set out to run a year ago. Back then, the Bushies correctly diagnosed that a Republican regular could not win in November. Mr. Bush posed as an innovator who would transform the G.O.P. He blasted the Republican Congress for trying to balance the budget on the backs of the poor. He issued activist initiatives like federally funded after-school programs. He came to New York and called for ''focused and effective and energetic government.''</p>
        <p>But that George W. Bush vanished at the first whiff of political combat. Today's regular George W. Bush appeals to conservatives, but he has not demonstrated any ability to win over independents, not even in his huge win in South Carolina. Modernizing the party has been ceded to Mr. McCain.</p>
        <p>Of course it could be that the Republican Party is in no mood to be transformed. It could be that conservative voters are not where liberal voters were in 1992, willing to accept ideological innovation in hopes of of winning the White House. There's something honorable about that, sticking to your policies even if it means electoral defeat. Of course if this is true, it means the year 2000 is going to be a good year to be a Democrat.</p>
        <p>David Brooks, a senior editor at The Weekly Standard, is the author of the forthcoming ''Bobos in Paradise,'' about the new upper class.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Brooks, a senior editor at The Weekly Standard, is the author of the forthcoming ''Bobos in Paradise,'' about the new upper class.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
