<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canada's Farmers Profit From Being Told What to Do</title>
    <meta content="01CANA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/01/business/worldbusiness/01canada.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1615501"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Milk</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austen, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3DA1238F932A35753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1412" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canada's Farmers Profit From Being Told What to Do</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Canada's Farmers Profit From Being Told What to Do</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN AUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Austen, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>NORWOOD, Ontario</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Canada's dairy and poultry farmers benefit from Canada's unusual system known as supply management; system allows only trickle of duty-free imports and otherwise imposes tariffs reaching 300 percent; country's 22,680 dairy, chicken, turkey and egg farmers produce fixed amount under quotas in system that maintains stable prices and assures markets; World Trade Organization's current attempt at overhauling global agricultural trade will most likely turn some of its attention to Canadian arrangement; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hans Vink says his dairy farm has turned a profit in each of the last 30 years. And he is confident that Vink Farms will wind up in the black again this year.</p>
        <p>Like all 22,680 dairy, chicken, turkey and egg farmers in this country, Mr. Vink produces a fixed amount under quotas in a system that maintains stable prices and assures markets for his farm's milk. While that has pretty much guaranteed the profitability of Vink Farms, situated outside Norwood, in rolling dairy country about 100 miles east of Toronto, Canada's unusual system, known as supply management, has its costs and its critics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Canada's unusual farming system, known as supply management, which gives farmers fixed quotas that maintain stable prices, has its costs and its critics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hans Vink says his dairy farm has turned a profit in each of the last 30 years. And he is confident that Vink Farms will wind up in the black again this year.</p>
        <p>Like all 22,680 dairy, chicken, turkey and egg farmers in this country, Mr. Vink produces a fixed amount under quotas in a system that maintains stable prices and assures markets for his farm's milk. While that has pretty much guaranteed the profitability of Vink Farms, situated outside Norwood, in rolling dairy country about 100 miles east of Toronto, Canada's unusual system, known as supply management, has its costs and its critics.</p>
        <p>The system allows only a trickle of duty-free imports and otherwise imposes tariffs reaching 300 percent. Mr. Vink, who is also director of the Dairy Farmers of Ontario, the group that runs the fluid milk supply management system in that province, is all too aware that the World Trade Organization's current attempt at overhauling global agricultural trade will most likely turn some of its attention to the arrangement.</p>
        <p>''It works very, very well,'' said Mr. Vink who ships most of his milk to dairies in Toronto. ''Because of it, I always know where I'm at. But I have to keep in the back of my mind that there are some idiots out there in trade that might create some problems for me.''</p>
        <p>The trade talks are not the only source of worry for supply management farmers, who account for about 20 percent of Canada's otherwise export-oriented agricultural products. Some critics say supply management inflates the prices Canadians pay for dairy and poultry products.</p>
        <p>Many commercial customers, including some restaurant owners, complain that the system limits their ability to expand their businesses because domestic production does not always meet their needs and the tariffs make most imports prohibitively expensive. Others view the protections as being inconsistent with the country's otherwise strong push for open agricultural trade, an important cause for Canadian grain, oilseed, pork and beef farmers.</p>
        <p>''Supply management is a pretty good thing for producers,'' said George Brinkman, a former chicken farmer who is now an agricultural economist at the University of Guelph in Ontario. ''But I do think its days are numbered.''</p>
        <p>Canada has long argued at trade talks that dairy and poultry are ''sensitive'' products that deserve extraordinary protection. The sensitivity may be mostly political, particularly with regard to dairy products. Dairy farms are a prominent enterprise in many parts of politically volatile rural Quebec, which dominates the dairy business with neighboring Ontario.</p>
        <p>Under the supply management system, which gradually made its way across Canada in the 1960's and 1970's, marketing boards forecast demand and adjust the amount of milk or the number of chicken, turkeys or eggs that farmers participating in the system can produce. Based on that, the boards also set the prices that farmers receive.</p>
        <p>Quotas are initially given to farmers at no cost but can be bought and sold. The marketing boards limit the amount any single operator can hold as well as the total amount available to the industry. As a result, supply-managed farmers are relatively small operators, like Mr. Vink, who milks about 105 cows, rather than the food giants like Tyson and Perdue, which dominate the United States chicken industry.</p>
        <p>When the W.T.O. was formed nearly a decade ago, Canada agreed to end complete bans on imports of farm products covered by supply management and opened a small amount of its market -- about 5 percent for dairy, for example -- to imports more or less duty free. Anything above that amount, however, faces high tariffs.</p>
        <p>Despite all the criticism, said Larry Martin, an economist and chief executive of the George Morris Center, a nonprofit agricultural research group based in Guelph, Ontario, there is little effective political pressure within Canada to end the system.</p>
        <p>Besides, the fact that it is not a subsidy and that it does not involve any tax dollars make it palatable to the federal and provincial governments and taxpayers alike.</p>
        <p>While Canadian dairy groups argue that retail prices are lower in Canada than the United States, Dr. Martin and some other economists argue the opposite. But Dr. Martin acknowledged that the price differences are not all that apparent to most shoppers. ''It's a small thing in the overall food basket,'' he said. ''In the grand scheme of things, it's not something to get worked up about.''</p>
        <p>The Canadian Restaurant and Foodservices Association, however, has long protested supply management.</p>
        <p>''Canada is trying to preserve free trade for 80 percent of the producers and protect supply management from globalization forces,'' Stephanie Jones, vice president for food supply at the group. ''You can't do both at the same time.''</p>
        <p>Restaurant owners have their complaints. Price premiums that consumers might overlook can limit profits in a restaurant.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jones said that mozzarella cheese imported duty free from the United States costs about 30 percent less than Canadian cheese. And chickens pose other problems, she said. Because the quota system measures the market in terms of whole chickens, it has been poor at adjusting supply to reflect changes in tastes for particular parts. (''There are only two wings on every chicken,'' Ms. Jones said.)</p>
        <p>So restaurants, especially chains, often have to base expansion decisions on the supply of specific chicken parts or the availability of appropriately sized birds.</p>
        <p>The system even limits the farms it protects. After the W.T.O. ruled against Canada in December 2002 in a dairy export case brought by New Zealand and the United States, Canadian farmers largely abandoned their export efforts.</p>
        <p>And when Mr. Vink recently wanted to expand his business, building a 20,000-square-foot barn, complete with milking parlor and milk storage area, he first had to buy more quota through a specialized exchange.</p>
        <p>Still, that just means he has more to safeguard.</p>
        <p>''If we were to lose the system, I can tell you right now there's probably somewhere around 2.5 million to 3 million dollars in quota value that would just go out the window here,'' he said, referring to the approximate long-term value of his holdings in Canadian dollars (about $1.9 million to $2.3 million).</p>
        <p>Beyond the loss of quota rights as an asset, the impact that ending the system would have on Canadian farmers is less clear. Dr. Martin says that efficient Canadian milk producers would probably become successful exporters to the United States, assuming an end to United States subsidies and an open border.</p>
        <p>Both he and Dr. Brinkman, however, are much less sanguine about Canada's chicken and turkey farms. ''The poultry industry would have to change very, very quickly because you can't compete with Perdue and Tyson through small farms,'' especially in northern climes, where heating costs are higher, Dr. Brinkman said.</p>
        <p>At the end of July, the W.T.O. released a framework for its agricultural talks. Canada's negotiators had effectively forestalled the day of reckoning by fending off mandatory cuts in the steep import tariffs.</p>
        <p>But, mandatory or not, changes are probably coming. Denis Landreville, the deputy director of market access at Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, a government agency, says Canada is willing to increase the dairy and poultry imports allowed to enter Canada duty free and reduce the large quotas somewhat in exchange for agricultural reforms from other countries. The question is how large those changes will be.</p>
        <p>''If you take 60 percent off 250 percent you still have a 150 percent tariff,'' Dr. Martin said. ''There will still be a fair amount of protection even if this happens.''</p>
        <p>Thomas Cox, a professor of agricultural and applied economics at the University of Wisconsin-Madison, said ending the Canadian dairy system was not likely to be a priority for United States trade negotiators.</p>
        <p>''The dairy distortions are big, but Canadian dairy is a very small part of world trade,'' he said. In any case, Dr. Cox said that demanding changes from Canada would require the United States to alter its dairy price subsidy programs.</p>
        <p>Several nations, particularly New Zealand, are likely to press Canada at future trade talks, however.</p>
        <p>Total elimination of the tariffs and import quotas might involve decades of gradual reductions, Dr. Brinkman speculated. ''If you give them 20 years to adjust,'' he said, ''it's not exactly leaving the farmers dangling.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
