<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tea Bags in Hand, Senator Says Coffee Never Flew</title>
    <meta content="12ada" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/12/nyregion/12ada.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1754034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Ada L (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Smith, Ada L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4DB1F30F931A25757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tea Bags in Hand, Senator Says Coffee Never Flew</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tea Bags in Hand, Senator Says Coffee Never Flew</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Senator Ada L Smith pleads not guilty to assault charge levied by former aide Jennifer C Jackson; holds that Jackson was reprimanded for inappropriate behavior and quit; says that she did not throw cup of coffee at alleged victim; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State Senator Ada L. Smith says that she does not even drink much coffee, let alone throw it at members of her staff.</p>
        <p>''I usually have tea, with milk and sugar,'' she said, reaching into her purse and producing two bags of Earl Grey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ada L. Smith, a Queens Democrat, discussed her case in detail for the first time since being accused of throwing coffee at an aide last month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State Senator Ada L. Smith says that she does not even drink much coffee, let alone throw it at members of her staff.</p>
        <p>''I usually have tea, with milk and sugar,'' she said, reaching into her purse and producing two bags of Earl Grey.</p>
        <p>Senator Smith described her preference for tea over lunch here on Tuesday, discussing her case in detail for the first time since she was accused of throwing hot coffee at one of her aides last month and charged with third-degree assault. This was the latest in a string of brushes with the law that have led newspapers to describe her as the ''Wild Woman of Albany.''</p>
        <p>The aide who made the accusations, Jennifer C. Jackson, told the police that Senator Smith threw coffee in her eyes and pulled her hairpiece on March 21 after a discussion of the senator's weight. Ms. Jackson said in a deposition that after Senator Smith announced that she had lost 4.3 pounds, she responded, ''Oh, that's good, Senator, but at the rate you go around I would have thought you'd lose 20 pounds.'' Then, she said, Senator Smith threw coffee at her.</p>
        <p>Senator Smith, a Queens Democrat, gave a different account of what happened that day in the State Capitol complex, and her plea of not guilty to the charge last week in Albany City Court.</p>
        <p>She said that Ms. Jackson, a new employee who had been reprimanded that morning for making errors on her daily schedule, greeted her announced weight loss in her Senate office with the remark, ''You need to lose 100 pounds.'' Senator Smith said she never threw coffee or tea at her and did not pull her hairpiece. She said that she was not carrying a hot drink, only a small seafood salad -- she thinks it was whitefish -- which she picked up at a school group's breakfast reception that morning on her way from a Weight Watchers session.</p>
        <p>Senator Smith said that she ''told off'' Ms. Jackson. Then, she said, Ms. Jackson quit, filled out her time sheets, and left.</p>
        <p>Claude Nelson, who has been the nine-term senator's chief of staff for the past five years, said he witnessed the interaction and that there was no throwing of coffee. ''The employee got chastised for her performance after making a rude and crude remark,'' he said. ''That's basically the way it was.''</p>
        <p>As news of the accusation spread, Senator Smith, who was convicted in 2004 of speeding past a State Capitol garage's security check point here -- and who has been accused of outlandish behavior before, including a report that she bit a New York City police officer after a traffic stop in 1998 -- found herself being ridiculed on the Internet and in newspapers around the state. She said that people had left messages on her office phone in the middle of the night, telling her she should be in jail.</p>
        <p>''She's become a punch line,'' her lawyer, Ravi Batra, said.</p>
        <p>And Senator David A. Paterson, the Democratic minority leader and candidate for lieutenant governor, stripped Senator Smith of the balance of a $9,500 stipend on top of her $79,500 salary and took away her state-issued car, citing ''a pattern of inappropriate, unprofessional and often-abusive behavior.''</p>
        <p>Senator Smith, who faces re-election in November, said it has all been an ordeal. ''You just want to go home, get in the bed, and hide, even though you know you've done nothing wrong,'' she said. ''But you get up, you get dressed, and you face the public.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Batra -- whose firm once employed Clarence Norman Jr., the former assemblyman and Brooklyn Democratic Party leader who was convicted last year of corruption charges -- called the accusations against Senator Smith ''a felonious hoax.''</p>
        <p>In a communiqué issued to reporters by Mr. Batra on Tuesday, he said that he was soliciting letters from anyone who has heard the ''hot coffee'' story, inviting them to state that they ''will not tolerate their elected leaders to throw burning coffee on their employees.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Batra added, ''But, I also want each such letter to also state what they would do to Jennifer Jackson, including jail time, if her story unravels and it becomes obvious that she committed perjury and perpetrated a fraud upon the police and the district attorney's office.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Jackson, who was taken to St. Peter's Hospital in Albany on March 21, said in her deposition that she was given a ''preliminary diagnosis as suffering from 'corneal superficial burns and cervical/shoulder sprain and contusion.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Jackson did not return a phone call seeking comment on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Senator Smith said that she hoped the matter could be resolved quickly. ''It is an election year,'' she said, ''and you don't want this hanging over your head.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
