<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fine Print: A periodic look behind the law.; Spy Plane That Came in From Cold Just Will Not Go Away in the Senate</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="697495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY AIRCRAFT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SR-71 BLACKBIRD (AIRPLANE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BYRD, ROBERT C (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINER, TIM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7D8113CF937A35754C0A962958260" item-length="1178" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fine Print: A periodic look behind the law.; Spy Plane That Came in From Cold Just Will Not Go Away in the Senate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM WEINER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEINER, TIM</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sleek black supersonic spy plane called the SR-71 Blackbird is a museum piece, a mighty relic of the cold war gathering dust. So what is $100 million to resurrect the plane doing in the Senate's bill authorizing $263.3 billion in military spending for the coming year?</p>
        <p>The bill contains hundreds of millions of dollars for other weapons and programs the Pentagon says it does not want, like money to keep building the $2.2 billion-a-copy B-2 bomber. The money keeps flowing for many reasons: keeping a military contractor solvent or defense workers on the job in a powerful politician's home district, for example.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sleek black supersonic spy plane called the SR-71 Blackbird is a museum piece, a mighty relic of the cold war gathering dust. So what is $100 million to resurrect the plane doing in the Senate's bill authorizing $263.3 billion in military spending for the coming year?</p>
        <p>The bill contains hundreds of millions of dollars for other weapons and programs the Pentagon says it does not want, like money to keep building the $2.2 billion-a-copy B-2 bomber. The money keeps flowing for many reasons: keeping a military contractor solvent or defense workers on the job in a powerful politician's home district, for example.</p>
        <p>But the renaissance of the Blackbird is a special case, less about pork than about power and prerogative. The will of one man made it happen: Robert C. Byrd, the West Virginia Democrat who heads the Senate Appropriations Committee.</p>
        <p>In reviving the Blackbird, Mr. Byrd appears to have adopted some of the Pentagon's stealthier and more secretive techniques. Surprise for Pentagon</p>
        <p>Prominent members of the Senate's Armed Services and Intelligence Committees, along with top Pentagon officials, were taken unawares by Mr. Byrd's move, the Senator's aides acknowledge. Vice President Al Gore; the national security adviser, Anthony Lake, and the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Gen. John M. Shalikashvili, knew nothing about the plan when they were visited last month by the senior members of the Congressional Intelligence Committees, according to several Congressional staff members.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Gore nor Mr. Lake nor General Shalikashvili voiced any enthusiasm for Senator Byrd's plan to take the plane out of mothballs and send it flying over North Korea's suspected nuclear sites. The Pentagon believes that its existing satellites and spy planes can do the job.</p>
        <p>Senior intelligence officers working for the Joint Chiefs of Staff said that it would take at least a year to refurbish the aircraft and retrain their crews, that the cost would be far greater than $100 million and that no one in the Pentagon wanted the Blackbirds, other intelligence officials said. The senior officers questioned whether the United States had the political will to use the aircraft against North Korea, its likeliest target, they said.</p>
        <p>But the combination of Senator Byrd's prestige, the current worries raised by targeting North Korea and the failure of the Pentagon to produce a secret aircraft to replace the Blackbird have won the battle thus far. Fight Began 4 Years Ago</p>
        <p>The Blackbird is not built in West Virginia nor do Senator Byrd's constituents depend on Lockheed, the plane's manufacturer, for jobs. But the plane was killed by the Defense Department over Senator Byrd's objections and its resurrection, if approved by Congress, would be a small personal triumph for the Senator.</p>
        <p>The story begins four years ago, when Mr. Byrd fought the Pentagon's forced retirement of the Blackbird, a unique aircraft that flew faster than 2,500 miles an hour and used sophisticated cameras to snap pictures of foreign targets. That fight was one of several battles begun in the late 1980's over secret spending for classified programs like the Blackbird's flights over North Korea, China and other lands targeted by United States intelligence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Byrd, a Senator since 1959, president pro tempore of the Senate since 1989 and a zealous defender of Congressional prerogatives, joined the battle as a matter of principle.</p>
        <p>He contended that the Defense Department, aided by the secrecy that shields classified projects, was refusing to spend huge sums appropriated by Congress for certain programs and flouting Congressional instructions to stop spending money on others. The Bush and Reagan Administrations routinely ignored classified Congressional directives on secret spending, he said in 1990.</p>
        <p>When the Pentagon canceled the Blackbird in 1990, citing the huge cost of operating and maintaining the fleet, it assured Senator Byrd and a handful of his senior colleagues on the Armed Services and Intelligence Committees that it was working on a very fast, very expensive, very secret reconnaissance plane to be a successor to the Blackbird. Missed in Gulf War</p>
        <p>But that program collapsed after consuming several hundred million dollars, according to members of Congress and their aides. And despite rumors that another successor is secretly in the works, they said, nothing of the sort is on the horizon at the secret Air Force base in Nevada where classified prototypes of state-of-the-art aircraft are flown.</p>
        <p>Though no supersonic secret reconnaissance aircraft remain in the nation's arsenal, and by many accounts the Blackbird's ability to target specific sites quickly was sorely missed during the 1991 Persian Gulf War, the Central Intelligence Agency and the Pentagon have several other ways of taking pictures of foreign soil from the sky, including a variety of classified intelligence satellites and the well-known U-2 spy plane. A multibillion-dollar investment in a new series of hugely expensive spy satellites is under way.</p>
        <p>So Pentagon officials were chagrined last week when they read the following language in the Senate's defense authorization bill: "The committee sees no reason, in principle, why the Department of Defense could not also operate the SR-71 in an austere manner." The committee recommended $100 million to revive three Blackbirds, the bill said. The money was inserted by the subcommittees of the Appropriations Committee Mr. Byrd heads. Senator Sam Nunn, the Georgia Democrat who heads the Armed Services Committee, was also instrumental in moving the idea forward.</p>
        <p>The provision now goes to a conference with the House, whose bill does not include the item. Its prospects are uncertain. Is $100 Million Enough?</p>
        <p>Even those who support reviving the Blackbird predict it may be a far more expensive proposition than a mere $100 million.</p>
        <p>"It's going to be pretty difficult to do that kind of mission with that kind of money," said Tom Alison, a retired SR-71 Blackbird pilot who works as a curator at the National Air and Space Museum, which owns one of the planes. "If they didn't feel they could afford it five years ago, then I don't understand why they think they can afford it now."</p>
        <p>But Richard D'Amato, the counsel for national security policy at the Senate Appropriations Committee, said the idea was "generated by Senator Byrd because there is a gap in our abilities, the unique capability that the Blackbird provides."</p>
        <p>"The idea wasn't generated only by Korea but in like situations, in the Middle East," he said.</p>
        <p>While acknowledging that senior Pentagon officials and many of Senator Byrd's colleagues were "blind-sided" by the move -- and that many of them maintain that the plane is "an antique, a museum piece" -- he said three of the planes could be ready to serve the nation by next summer for $100 million or less.</p>
        <p>And $100 million is, as everybody in Congress knows, a mere drop in the world's biggest single pool of public capital, the Pentagon's budget.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
