<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Few Tears Shed for Closing Of Brooklyn's Big House; Rikers Would Take Inmates in Consolidation Enabled by a Decline in People Behind Bars</title>
    <meta content="10JAIL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/10/nyregion/10JAIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1487644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brooklyn House of Detention</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rikers Island Prison Complex (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cardwell, Diane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E7DA153FF933A25756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Few Tears Shed for Closing Of Brooklyn's Big House; Rikers Would Take Inmates in Consolidation Enabled by a Decline in People Behind Bars</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Few Tears Shed for Closing of Brooklyn's Big House</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE CARDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cardwell, Diane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Mayor Michael R Bloomberg administration plans to close Brooklyn House of Detention, if only temporarily, to transfer inmates to Rikers Island in effort to both save money and managerially consolidate prison system; says closing is result of falling crime rates; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Say goodbye to all that. To the long lines of girlfriends carrying babies and grandmothers carrying bail. To the sad comings and goings, and occasional escape, of men already convicted or just accused. To the catcalls and shouts mysteriously emanating from behind the multitude of tiny, reinforced panes of glass looming over Atlantic Avenue.</p>
        <p>As falling crime rates and shifting law enforcement policies increasingly make overcrowded jails in New York a thing of the past, the Bloomberg administration is planning to close the Brooklyn House of Detention this summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As falling crime rates make overcrowded jails in New York a thing of the past, the Bloomberg administration is planning to close the Brooklyn House of Detention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Say goodbye to all that. To the long lines of girlfriends carrying babies and grandmothers carrying bail. To the sad comings and goings, and occasional escape, of men already convicted or just accused. To the catcalls and shouts mysteriously emanating from behind the multitude of tiny, reinforced panes of glass looming over Atlantic Avenue.</p>
        <p>As falling crime rates and shifting law enforcement policies increasingly make overcrowded jails in New York a thing of the past, the Bloomberg administration is planning to close the Brooklyn House of Detention this summer.</p>
        <p>It may not be forever, city officials say. But given that the city's main jail complex, Rikers Island, can absorb the 600 or so inmates currently housed in Brooklyn without even reopening two jails that are closed, it makes both fiscal and management sense to transfer the inmates to the Rock.</p>
        <p>Correction Commissioner Martin F. Horn told a City Council committee yesterday that the department would save about $5.3 million in labor costs by closing the Brooklyn jail. Department officials said that the 153 correction officers who now work in Brooklyn would be transferred elsewhere, but that the department plans to lay off 315 officers overall.</p>
        <p>The city has already closed the Bronx and Queens Houses of Detention. (The Bronx jail was reopened briefly last summer to ease overcrowding for homeless families applying for shelter with the city.) The Correction Department has also shed a jail known as the Brig at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Once the Atlantic Avenue jail closes, all that will be left is Rikers, a barge tethered near it and the Tombs, the old Manhattan detention complex, now named for Bernard B. Kerik, the former correction and police commissioner.</p>
        <p>Correction experts said that the Brooklyn closing made sense because it is more efficient to manage fewer, fuller jails. ''Nothing saves as much money as closing a jail,'' said Michael P. Jacobson, a professor at the John Jay College of Criminal Justice who has been commissioner of both the Correction and Probation Departments. ''Instead of having 10 jails that are 90 percent full, you would rather have 9 jails that are 98 percent full,'' because the administrative savings are so large, he said.</p>
        <p>The reason the city can pursue this path is that the jail population has been steadily dwindling of late.</p>
        <p>For decades, New York mirrored the nation, with its city jail and state prison populations skyrocketing, experts said. According to Robert Gangi, executive director of the Correctional Association of New York, a prison watchdog group, there were about 200,000 people incarcerated in this country in 1970; that number is now more than 2 million. In 1980, New York City's jail population was about 7,000, he said. In 1986 that number was about 13,000, and it grew to a peak of 22,600 in 1991. It is now about 14,300.</p>
        <p>These days, though, jails are a ripe target for budget officials looking to trim expenses. Many states have looked to thin their prison populations by releasing inmates early or changing sentencing laws. In the city, however, experts say a different dynamic has been at play in reducing the jail population. And, they say, the city's much-heralded drop in crime tells only a small part of the story.</p>
        <p>''A little-known or understood dynamic is that crime rates have relatively little to do with incarceration rates,'' Mr. Gangi said. ''In 1972, you could commit a drug offense and get treatment; 1973, the drug laws are passed and you go to jail. But the crime rate didn't change.''</p>
        <p>One factor contributing to empty jail beds, experts say, is the city's continuing attention to low-level quality-of-life offenses. Mr. Jacobson said that although arrests and indictments for the most serious crimes had gone down, misdemeanor arrests were exceptionally high, which means that those people who are arrested spend much less time in the system.</p>
        <p>And so, goodbye to the Brooklyn jail. Built in 1957, it has helped create a whole world there at the crossroads of Downtown Brooklyn, Cobble Hill and Boerum Hill, although it has not been a welcoming one. Across Atlantic Avenue sits a row of bail bond businesses. At night sometimes, when the shadows of the men locked up inside are visible from the street, women park their cars there, communicating love and trouble through hand signals, holding up children for their fathers to glimpse.</p>
        <p>It is an institution whose passing few will mourn, although its closing will inconvenience many. ''Four hours for a one-hour visit?'' Victoria Levy said, incredulous, the other day outside the Visitors House, a corrugated metal shack on State Street that leads into the jail. ''Oh, no, that's too long,'' Ms. Levy said, explaining to another woman, Victoria Vasquez, who was visiting her son-in-law and seemed uninitiated in the ways of the system, that the check-in process at Rikers was more arduous than at other facilities.</p>
        <p>''Even in Sing Sing,'' Ms. Levy continued, where her husband currently resides, ''it only takes 15 minutes to get in.'' At the Brooklyn jail, Ms. Levy was trying to post bail for her son, who, she said, had never been in trouble before. ''I wouldn't bring my mother to Rikers,'' she said. ''I wouldn't put her through that. She couldn't take it.''</p>
        <p>''But the thing is,'' she added, ''it doesn't matter where they are. You're still going to go visit them, no matter how long it takes to get there.''</p>
        <p>For Jack Robbins, a bail bondsman who has worked in the area for 45 years (''Maybe I've been in the business too long,'' he said, sounding resigned), the old detention house is already gone.</p>
        <p>''Years ago,'' he said, dapper in a dark suit-vest on a recent afternoon at his office across the street from the jail, ''you used to have the toughest people coming in here, but they minded their p's and q's. Now they come in with a chip on their shoulders.'' This, he said, may be a reflection of the treatment they receive on the other side of the avenue.</p>
        <p>''At the facility, it's terrible what they do,'' he said, adding that sometimes officers manning the bail window will slam it shut and tell those waiting to come back in an hour, even though it is supposed to be open around the clock. ''Years ago you had people with a sense of values working there. Now you get people whose only joy is in giving other people a hard time.''</p>
        <p>For some, of course, goodbye will simply be good riddance. ''A slug on the cabbage of life, that's what it's been,'' said Heloise Gruneberg, who has lived practically in the jail's shadow for more than 30 years. Ms. Gruneberg, president of the Boerum Hill Association, said she and others who had been engaged in buffing the area's rough edges would begin formulating ideas for what the building could become.</p>
        <p>Correction officials say they will hold onto the jail in case it is again needed. Yesterday, Correction Commissioner Horn told the Council committee that the renovation work that had already been started on the Brooklyn House of Detention would continue. The work includes a new visitors entrance, installing sprinklers and fixing the facade.</p>
        <p>''The population is down now,'' said Thomas Antenen, chief spokesman for the Correction Department, ''but there's an ebb and flow to the inmate population.''</p>
        <p>But that has not stopped residents, elected officials and real estate developers from projecting their own desires, whether retail or residence or office complex, onto the institution, which takes up the entire block between Atlantic Avenue and State Street from Boerum Place to Smith Street.</p>
        <p>''This is a great opportunity to do something for Downtown Brooklyn's revitalization, and I think it would be silly for the city to just let it sit empty for years and years,'' said David Yassky, the city councilman who represents the area. There are, he said, plans under way for Brooklyn Law School dormitories and an apartment building in the surrounding blocks.</p>
        <p>Borough President Marty Markowitz, who has been urging the city to sell the building, agreed. ''It is finally time to close the doors on the House of Detention and throw away the key,'' he said through a spokesman. ''During this fiscal crisis, it makes absolutely no sense to keep pouring at least another $10 million, by the city's own estimate, of desperately needed funds into the never-ending renovation of a prison that will remain empty.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
