<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inching Toward a Budget Deal</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="813520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DA1E39F936A35751C1A963958260" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inching Toward a Budget Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The White House and Republicans continue to bicker over the budget. The two sides remain far apart. The White House, though claiming to embrace the Republican goal of balancing the budget within seven years, attacks the Republican deficit-reduction bill for crippling Medicaid, food stamps and other  programs for the needy. The Republican leaders accuse the White House of hypocrisy in cynically attacking the Republicans for their cuts while refusing to identify who would lose under White House plans.</p>
        <p>The blame game eased a bit last weekend when Democrats and Republicans slipped back from rigid positions. Leaders of both parties began to gravitate ever so slowly toward a compromise plan put forth by a coalition of moderate and conservative Democrats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The White House and Republicans continue to bicker over the budget. The two sides remain far apart. The White House, though claiming to embrace the Republican goal of balancing the budget within seven years, attacks the Republican deficit-reduction bill for crippling Medicaid, food stamps and other  programs for the needy. The Republican leaders accuse the White House of hypocrisy in cynically attacking the Republicans for their cuts while refusing to identify who would lose under White House plans.</p>
        <p>The blame game eased a bit last weekend when Democrats and Republicans slipped back from rigid positions. Leaders of both parties began to gravitate ever so slowly toward a compromise plan put forth by a coalition of moderate and conservative Democrats.</p>
        <p>The coalition would, like the G.O.P., balance the budget in 2002 and cut discretionary spending by almost 30 percent by 2002. But its plan forgoes all tax cuts, choosing instead to soften blows to Medicare and preserve Federal entitlements to welfare, Medicaid and food stamps. The coalition proposes to lower inflation adjustments -- in effect raising taxes and lowering Social Security benefits -- which will only happen if the President joins hands with Republican leaders in announcing collective support.</p>
        <p>For all its good sense, the coalition plan cannot pass the House, whose 73 freshman Republicans swear to pass a $245 billion tax cut. That is the gap that  the two parties must close. It will not be easy.</p>
        <p>Over the weekend, leaders from both parties began groping for compromise. The Senate budget chairman, Pete Domenici, and his House counterpart, John Kasich, signaled that a smaller tax cut and inflation adjustment would be acceptable, as long as the Democrats simultaneously agreed. But even if the tax cut were reduced by half, the compromise plan would be over $100 billion short of balancing the budget.</p>
        <p>The Congressional Budget Office will provide some relief when it issues new,  probably lower, deficit projections, which could reduce the need to cut spending by between $30 billion and $100 billion. After that, the options are limited. The Republicans appear unwilling to cut needless weapons systems out of the defense budget. The White House, playing to the elderly, appears unwilling to make doable cuts in Medicare. That leaves only two places to find additional savings: non-defense discretionary spending and entitlement programs for the poor. Yet the coalition budget already makes huge cuts in both these areas.</p>
        <p>The sobering truth is that Congress will be trapped into a vicious trade-off. Every dollar that Congress gives away in needless tax cuts will be taken from heavily hit discretionary programs or need-based entitlement programs. Here is where President Clinton could display leadership by stepping forward to forswear his own $100-billion-plus tax cut. In return he needs to insist that Congress preserve, at the very least, Federal entitlements to Medicaid and food stamps.</p>
        <p>The best plan that will emerge from Congress will not be good. It will make unwarranted cuts in public investments in job training, education and research as well as poverty programs for the arbitrary purpose of eliminating the deficit in seven years. But the damage can be limited if good news from the C.B.O. can be combined with new flexibility by Mr. Clinton and the Republicans controlling  Capitol Hill.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
