<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="722904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EFDB143EF937A35752C1A962958260" item-length="411" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TENNIS  Navratilova Fights Back  Martina Navratilova, overcoming careless errors and the power of Amy Frazier, rallied for a 2-6, 6-4, 6-1 victory last night to reach the semifinals of the Bank of the West Classic in Oakland, Calif. Navratilova, the No. 2 seed playing in her next-to-last tournament, made repeated mistakes in the first set and was within two games of losing the match at 4-4 in the second. At one point, she turned to Coach Craig Kardon and spread her arms, palms upward, as if to say, "What can I do?" But she suddenly turned those errors into winning shots and Frazier fell apart, losing eight of the last nine games, including her last four service games. (AP) Becker's Serve Dominant: Boris Becker, thundering aces from the start, beat Guy Forget, 7-5, 7-6 (7-3), yesterday to advance to the quarterfinals of the $2.25 million Paris Open. Becker, a three-time champion, produced 22 aces, including his first 7 service points. Also winning third-round matches were the top-seeded Pete Sampras, the defending champion; Goran Ivanisevic, and Andre Agassi. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TENNIS  Navratilova Fights Back  Martina Navratilova, overcoming careless errors and the power of Amy Frazier, rallied for a 2-6, 6-4, 6-1 victory last night to reach the semifinals of the Bank of the West Classic in Oakland, Calif. Navratilova, the No. 2 seed playing in her next-to-last tournament, made repeated mistakes in the first set and was within two games of losing the match at 4-4 in the second. At one point, she turned to Coach Craig Kardon and spread her arms, palms upward, as if to say, "What can I do?" But she suddenly turned those errors into winning shots and Frazier fell apart, losing eight of the last nine games, including her last four service games. (AP) Becker's Serve Dominant: Boris Becker, thundering aces from the start, beat Guy Forget, 7-5, 7-6 (7-3), yesterday to advance to the quarterfinals of the $2.25 million Paris Open. Becker, a three-time champion, produced 22 aces, including his first 7 service points. Also winning third-round matches were the top-seeded Pete Sampras, the defending champion; Goran Ivanisevic, and Andre Agassi. (AP)</p>
        <p>BASEBALL  'Play Ball' in Puerto Rico  The Puerto Rican Winter League season opened in three cities Wednesday night, featuring several major leaguers and a 54-game season certain to go uninterrupted by labor problems. Oakland Athletics pitcher Carlos Reyes allowed one run in five innings and Toronto Blue Jays first baseman Carlos Delgado doubled and scored in the fourth for San Juan in its 2-1 home victory over Santurce before a crowd of 14,230. Second baseman Roberto Alomar of Toronto went 0 for 3 for Santurce and right fielder Gerald Williams of the Yankees made a throwing error. In other games, Mayaguez beat Arecibo, 7-3, and Ponce beat Caguas, 8-4. (AP) YACHTING  Too Much Wind Now  The second race of the International America's Cup Class world championship in San Diego was canceled yesterday because of too much wind. The winds off Point Loma clocked 20 knots with gusts of 30 knots and 8-foot swells. The race was supposed to be a makeup of last Saturday's race, which was abandoned due to a lack of wind. (AP) GOLF  Long Course, Low Score  Jim McGovern shot a course-record, seven-under-par 66 on the longer Plantation Course and the defending champion Fred Couples, Tom Lehman and Gary McCord each had 66's over a shorter course to share the first-round lead yesterday in the Kapalua International in Hawaii. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
