<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dotel Has Sights Set On a May Return</title>
    <meta content="28yanks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/28/sports/baseball/28yanks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1750287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dotel, Octavio</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dotel, Octavio</person>
        <person class="online_producer">John, Tommy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E0D71430F93BA15750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dotel Has Sights Set On a May Return</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Added Relief: Dotel Is Ahead of Schedule</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>KISSIMMEE, Fla., March 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees pitcher Octavio Dotel will face hitters for first time since elbow surgery in batting practice (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is a chance that Kyle Farnsworth will hand every lead safely to Mariano Rivera early this season. But if he falters, one name will be heard constantly in the background around the Yankees: Octavio Dotel.</p>
        <p>When they break camp Thursday, the Yankees will leave Dotel behind with a good feeling about what they have seen. He will throw 35 pitches of batting practice Tuesday, facing hitters for the first time since reconstructive elbow surgery June 7. His rehabilitation will continue in Tampa, with an eye on the eighth-inning role in the Bronx by June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Octavio Dotel will throw 35 pitches of batting practice, facing hitters for the first time since reconstructive elbow surgery June 7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is a chance that Kyle Farnsworth will hand every lead safely to Mariano Rivera early this season. But if he falters, one name will be heard constantly in the background around the Yankees: Octavio Dotel.</p>
        <p>When they break camp Thursday, the Yankees will leave Dotel behind with a good feeling about what they have seen. He will throw 35 pitches of batting practice Tuesday, facing hitters for the first time since reconstructive elbow surgery June 7. His rehabilitation will continue in Tampa, with an eye on the eighth-inning role in the Bronx by June.</p>
        <p>That is the Yankees' timetable, at least. They signed him as bullpen insurance last December and pledged not to rush his return. But Dotel said he did not think he should have to wait until June to return.</p>
        <p>''No, May,'' he said. ''In May, I'm pretty close to a year. I see guys come back in nine months. There's a couple more guys who come back in 8 or 10 months. It depends on how your body is built. Me, I feel really good -- for real, man.''</p>
        <p>Dotel had the kind of operation known as Tommy John surgery. John, a Yankees' spring instructor, won 288 games in a career that nearly ended with a major elbow injury in 1974. John waited more than a year before returning after the operation, and he has cautioned Dotel to do the same.</p>
        <p>''You're going to feel good,'' John said. ''But no matter how much rehab you do, you can't speed up the healing process. I'd rather a guy come back in 14 months and pitch seven, eight, nine more years than come back in 10 months and get hurt again. You can't mess with mom and dad -- Mother Nature and Father Time. Nature will heal it if you give it time.''</p>
        <p>As Dotel remembered it, his last pitch for the Oakland Athletics last season was 94 miles an hour. But with every throw came a sensation that felt like an electric charge to his elbow. Now, Dotel said, he is throwing more than 90 m.p.h. again.</p>
        <p>''I'm excited,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''I can't appear too excited in front of him, because I don't want him to think he has to hurry up and do it. But he seems very comfortable in what he's doing.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know him at all, but he's got a great personality as far as friendly and open and relaxed. I think all that stuff will probably help him get to where he needs to go.''</p>
        <p>Once he gets there, the setting will be familiar. Dotel broke into the majors with the Mets in 1999, winning the epic fifth game of the National League Championship Series with three innings of relief against the Atlanta Braves. After four and a half seasons in Houston and one and a half in Oakland, Dotel is eager for the spotlight again.</p>
        <p>''I don't care about what people say about New York, the media or whatever,'' he said. ''Media is good. If you do what you've got to do, you're going to be fine. So, hey, why not take a chance here?''</p>
        <p>Dotel was phenomenal for Houston after leaving the Mets in a trade for Mike Hampton. In three seasons as a setup man for Billy Wagner (2001-3), he had a 2.08 earned run average in 216 relief outings, with 343 strikeouts in 2681/3 innings.</p>
        <p>''If you didn't beat us by the seventh, you weren't going to beat us,'' the Astros' Jeff Bagwell said this spring. ''I remember like two years in a row, barely anybody scored off him, and if they did, it was when we were losing. Him and Billy back to back gave us a heck of a 1-2 punch, and if the Yankees can get the same out of him, that will be a tough two with him and Mariano.''</p>
        <p>Working on a one-year contract, Dotel is eager to show he can be a dominant force again. He has been among the most joyful Yankees this spring because, he said, he believes his live arm is back.</p>
        <p>''That's why you see my smile on my face,'' he said. ''That's why you see me happy. Because that's not what I saw in spring training last year. It's a different feeling.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Chien-Ming Wang, who was struck on the right kneecap by a hard one-hopper Sunday, continued to make progress Monday. The trainer Steve Donohue said through a spokesman that swelling around the knee had gone down and that Wang was showing good range of motion. Joe Torre said he expected to know the Yankees' season-opening rotation by Thursday, when the team leaves for Arizona for two exhibition games.  Torre said he expected catcher Jorge Posada to be ready to catch on opening day next Monday. Posada, who broke his nose when he was hit by a ball last Wednesday, could be the designated hitter in Tuesday's game.  Shawn Chacon threw 92 pitches in the Yankees' 5-4 loss Monday to the Braves at the Ballpark at Disney. Alex Rodriguez was 2 for 3 with a double and a home run.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
