<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debate on Kenya's Future: Serious Talk and Fruit Tossing</title>
    <meta content="16kenya" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/16/international/africa/16kenya.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1710101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kenya</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0D9143FF935A25753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1125" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debate on Kenya's Future: Serious Talk and Fruit Tossing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Debate on Kenya's Future: Serious Talk and Fruit Tossing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC LACEY</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The debate over how to revamp Kenya's colonial-era Constitution has its lofty moments. On the sidewalks of downtown, regular folks can be overheard discussing the merits of having a prime minister in what has long been a presidential system, the importance of increasing the clout of the Parliament, and the necessity of shifting power from here, the capital, to the outlying provinces.</p>
        <p>But there are plenty of base moments, as well -- rock throwing, chair hurling and fruit tossing, to cite some of the more colorful examples in recent weeks. Insults are also being traded, so much so that an exercise intended to unify the country has already succeeded in doing the opposite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The debate over how to revamp a colonial-era Constitution has ranged from lofty discussions to chair throwing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The debate over how to revamp Kenya's colonial-era Constitution has its lofty moments. On the sidewalks of downtown, regular folks can be overheard discussing the merits of having a prime minister in what has long been a presidential system, the importance of increasing the clout of the Parliament, and the necessity of shifting power from here, the capital, to the outlying provinces.</p>
        <p>But there are plenty of base moments, as well -- rock throwing, chair hurling and fruit tossing, to cite some of the more colorful examples in recent weeks. Insults are also being traded, so much so that an exercise intended to unify the country has already succeeded in doing the opposite.</p>
        <p>The other day, a group of demonstrators disrupted a rally in Garissa, an eastern town, by hoisting bananas and yelling support for the government's draft constitution. They were set upon by opponents holding oranges. Riot policemen put down the resulting melee with nightsticks.</p>
        <p>The two fruits -- adopted for use as ballot symbols easily recognized by illiterate voters -- represent the two positions on a referendum set for Nov. 21. While a banana means yes and an orange means no, there is also a third option, a group that is pushing for a middle ground that calls itself fruit salad.</p>
        <p>Despite an existing Constitution that has many of the niceties of a democracy, Kenya knows autocratic rule too well, having been presided over by just two men in the first 40 years since it became independent.</p>
        <p>When the third president, Mwai Kibaki, took office in December 2002, backed by a broad coalition, he promised to revamp the Constitution to diffuse the powers now centralized in his office. But Mr. Kibaki has since backed off the idea of adding a powerful prime minister post. His vice president, Moody Awori, explained the change of heart this way at a recent rally: presidents are father figures in Africa, and the voters would not put up with having someone outside the family rivaling the father.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kibaki's proposal does give Parliament the power to pass judgment on presidential appointments, although the prime minister in his draft is virtually powerless.</p>
        <p>The person most upset with Mr. Kibaki's plan is Raila Odinga, who supported him in the last election after receiving a signed pledge that he would become prime minister. Mr. Kibaki contends that political realities have changed since then. Mr. Odinga is a minister in Mr. Kibaki's government, but that has not stopped him and other allies from campaigning vigorously against the government's draft. In fact, Mr. Kibaki now finds himself disparaged by some of his own ministers, something that is unheard of in Kenya. Mr. Kibaki fired back at his detractors, recently, using a Swahili word that translates roughly as stupid.</p>
        <p>One troubling aspect of the debate is that the tribal divisions that showed signs of fading in Kenya in recent years have resurfaced. The Kikuyus, Kenya's largest tribe, are overwhelmingly backing the constitution proposed by Mr. Kibaki, a fellow Kikuyu. The Luos, the second-largest tribe, support Mr. Odinga, who comes from their community, in his opposition to the draft. The dozens of other tribes are, by and large, lining up behind their elected representatives.</p>
        <p>Many political analysts see the debate as a referendum on Mr. Kibaki, the once-popular president who finds himself increasingly on the ropes. His election, coming after years of misrule by Daniel arap Moi, was regarded by Kenyans as the beginning of an era. He pledged to fix a broken country by wiping out corruption and reviving the stagnant economy. But three years later, many Kenyans have grown disillusioned.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kibaki is pulling out all the stops to win the referendum. His justice minister announced recently that state money would be used to pay for the banana campaign, prompting ambassadors from 25 donor governments, including the United States, to hold a news conference denouncing that plan and calling for an end to the violence.</p>
        <p>At a recent rally in Nakuru, north of Nairobi, banana supporters told thousands of people at a sports arena that the new constitution would transform their lives by providing them with clean water, revamping the economy and giving them more of a say in civic affairs.</p>
        <p>To win even more support, Mr. Kibaki's government has promised land to some squatters and farmers, pledges that have been denounced by government opponents as blatantly political.</p>
        <p>But the concerns with the proposed constitution are many. Some Muslims worry that the draft weakens Islamic courts. Teachers say it will weaken their union. Shepherds fear they will lose grazing land. Some supporters of abortion rights oppose a line that says life begins at conception.</p>
        <p>In addition, there has been disagreement on whether the language opposing discrimination would protect gay men and lesbians, who are scorned here. (One government minister called a rival minister a homosexual at a rally the other day, and the crowd roared with laughter. The same politician made a point of saying that he and other supporters of the charter were all married to members of the opposite sex.)</p>
        <p>The back-and-forth has laid bare to Kenyans not only the importance of having a constitution but also the need to follow one. As Kenyans have debated the kind of country they want Kenya to become, the police have arrested journalists accused of offending the government and politicians have resorted to the common tactic here of paying young people to disrupt political rallies with force. Recently, a man was arrested as he tried to sneak some beehives into a rally, presumably to set the bees on the crowd.</p>
        <p>''The side that will win in the referendum should not do so because it threw more stones at its opponents and shouted the loudest,'' The Daily Nation said recently in a front-page editorial calling for calm. ''That would be a hollow victory.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
