<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Troubled Streets Where Officer Died, A Gun Battle in the Night Is No Surprise</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="836961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="SHOOTOUT IN THE BRONX: THE NEIGHBORHOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBBERIES AND THEFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATTACKS ONPOLICE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRONX (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GILLESPIE, KEVIN (POLICE OFFICER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURDY, MATTHEW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E4DA1639F935A25750C0A960958260" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Troubled Streets Where Officer Died, A Gun Battle in the Night Is No Surprise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PURDY, MATTHEW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the bleak patch of the Bronx where Officer Kevin Gillespie was killed Thursday night, life is controlled in a harsh way by the drug trade.</p>
        <p>Savvy residents know which side of which street to walk on to avoid the dealers. They know that the stream of cars from outside the neighborhood and the chorus of drug hawkers yelling out brand names is as sure a sign of evening as the sunset.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the bleak patch of the Bronx where Officer Kevin Gillespie was killed Thursday night, life is controlled in a harsh way by the drug trade.</p>
        <p>Savvy residents know which side of which street to walk on to avoid the dealers. They know that the stream of cars from outside the neighborhood and the chorus of drug hawkers yelling out brand names is as sure a sign of evening as the sunset.</p>
        <p>And they knew not to be surprised by the explosion of gunfire that killed Officer Gillespie and injured another officer and three bystanders when the officers tried to break up a carjacking.</p>
        <p>"Not around here it wasn't a surprise," said Robert Wade, sitting on a porch  just off 183d Street, nodding toward the knots of young men on the corners yesterday. "There's shooting here every night."</p>
        <p>That a gun battle could play out on the Grand Concourse just south of Fordham Road seemed to surprise no one -- not residents, community leaders or even the police. Officers, who make pin maps to plot the shootings and killings, say that area of the Bronx has a cluster of violence like few places in the city. The local community board had tagged the South Fordham neighborhood as one of the most troublesome areas in the borough.</p>
        <p>Since the beginning of the month, members of the Police Department's special  Street Crimes Unit, including Officer Gillespie, had been detailed to the neighborhood to combat violent street crime. The 46th Precinct had been expecting an infusion of 57 more officers on Monday to help clamp down on the neighborhood and other so-called hot spots.</p>
        <p>"It's been likened to the wild, wild West," said Sgt. Stuart Gang, of the borough police command office. Because of the heavy drug trade and violent crime, he said, "There was an increased attention being paid to that area."</p>
        <p>The 46th Precinct, which runs between the Cross Bronx Expressway to Fordham Road and from Webster Avenue to the Major Deegan Expressway, has recorded well over 90,000 radio calls annually in recent years, more than double other precincts, Sergeant Gang said. There were 42 homicides in the precinct last year.</p>
        <p>The particular neighborhood that has been targeted is a teeming area of graffiti-scarred brick apartment buildings and small stores bounded by Burnside  Avenue and 183d Street between Jerome and Webster Avenues. In recent years, residents said, the neighborhood has become home to many immigrants from the Dominican Republic, some of whom have moved to the Bronx from Washington Heights in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Jose Rivera, the City Councilman who represents the neighborhood, said that although the men arrested in the shooting did not live in the neighborhood, the incident drew attention to problems there. He said residents have organized  anti-drug marches along the Grand Concourse in each of the last few summers to show their resolve against the ingrained drug trade.</p>
        <p>Adolfo Carrion, the district manager of Community Board 5, said the crime problem can be traced to "a lot of the young males who hang out on the street" and skirmish over drug turf.</p>
        <p>In the neighborhood yesterday, residents expressed an odd sense of inevitability about the killing.</p>
        <p>"Another one bites the dust, " said Alice Galarza, a licensed practical nurse at a medical clinic on 183d Street, not being callous, but reflecting the regularity of the shootings. "It's routine." Recently, she added, "there was a shooting right around the corner. A kid was shot. He was going into a building and they told him to stop. They took his jewelry. I guess he thought he was Superman. He went after them and they shot him. Bing! Bing! Bing! Bing!"</p>
        <p>Sergio Sanchez, 35, who operates a billiard hall on 181st Street said he heard gunfire a month ago while walking near 183d Street and Creston Avenue. "It's a district of drugs, every day, every corner," he said, adding that he has come to feel safe in the neighborhood, even knowing that the drug business can suddenly become violent.</p>
        <p>"It's not scary," Mr. Sanchez said. "They know me. They are not bad people. At least to me. It's their business. It's not like you're going to pass by and they're going to shoot you." But he said he does worry about stray bullets.</p>
        <p>Stray bullets are what Jose Gutierrez thought of Thursday night when he, his  wife and their two children, Jeremy, 4, and Mariah, 3, were walking down Ryer Avenue on their way home from a bodega and the gunfire broke out. "I heard a few, then a whole bunch of rapid fire," he said. "My kids were on their bikes and I picked them up." When they reached their building, he and his wife shoved  their children inside the door. "I looked outside and I saw one guy running by,  then two plainclothes cops after him," he said.</p>
        <p>Three people were hit by stray bullets -- two 14-year-old boys who were playing basketball nearby and a 40-year-old woman.</p>
        <p>In the area of the shooting yesterday, there was sorrow for the latest victims of violence. But among the residents, there was also mourning for their  neighborhood.</p>
        <p>"This used to be a really nice area," Earl LaForce, a 21-year-old, said. "I could go to the window and listen to the birds. Now I listen to the gunshots. I  think even the birds have left."</p>
        <p>SHOOTOUT IN THE BRONX: THE NEIGHBORHOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
