<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Learning to Work With Nature's Clock</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="446439"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="GARDENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEASONS AND MONTHS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D6123BF93AA25756C0A967958260" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Learning to Work With Nature's Clock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"WHEN the oak leaves are the size of a mouse's ear, plant corn." This was a treasured bit of planting advice given by many Eastern Indian tribes and followed seriously. The local Indians knew that the soil had to be warm enough to receive the corn seed. And if the oak leaves were beginning to unfurl, the Indians knew that their vital crop of corn would not be chilled in the ground needlessly.</p>
        <p>Another adage that they used to follow was planting by the phases of the moon. They were particularly careful to observe the rise or wane of the new moon to know when to plant or delay planting of particular crops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"WHEN the oak leaves are the size of a mouse's ear, plant corn." This was a treasured bit of planting advice given by many Eastern Indian tribes and followed seriously. The local Indians knew that the soil had to be warm enough to receive the corn seed. And if the oak leaves were beginning to unfurl, the Indians knew that their vital crop of corn would not be chilled in the ground needlessly.</p>
        <p>Another adage that they used to follow was planting by the phases of the moon. They were particularly careful to observe the rise or wane of the new moon to know when to plant or delay planting of particular crops.</p>
        <p>The Indian tribes understood the phenomenon that temperature is one of the major factors governing the survival of plants and seed.</p>
        <p>How many times have modern-day gardeners heard that they should prune the rosebushes when the neighborhood forsythia was in flower? Or that they should put down pre-emergent crabgrass controls before the lilacs were in full bloom?</p>
        <p>Here is another one: controls for the black-vine weevil (on rhododendrons and yew) should be delayed until the large-flowered rhododendrons are in flower, usually early to mid-June. These concepts are often shelved by many as just plain old wives' tales.</p>
        <p>But are they?</p>
        <p>The local Indian tribes did not have access to radio, televsion or local newspapers to tell them what the day's weather would be. All they had to depend on was what they observed outdoors, on nature's clocks. These masterful gardeners were rarely wrong and produced their crops abundantly. Their lives depended on it.</p>
        <p>As for those who may pass off these claims merely as old tales, wise have been any of those who have followed what comes naturally.</p>
        <p>Although these early practitioners of following nature's schedules did not realize it, they were leading the way to one of the horticultural world's newest sciences called plant phenology, the study of biological clocks. Many proponents of gardening do not believe this is serious science, but there are many others who are giving it deep consideration. And why not, for the old adage has always been that nature knows best.</p>
        <p>The world of plants (and insects) sets its own timetables and does not rigidly follow a calendar, as so many suburban gardeners are prone to do. Granted, certain outdoor chores can be done by the calendar: getting the ground ready usually by April 1, for example, so it can settle down a bit before planting. And certain months are said to belong to certain plants: May for dogwood, June for roses and August for the tomato and corn harvest.</p>
        <p>But the emphasis on environmental awareness has given this study credence, particularly in the field of insect control. Instead of making spray applications by the calendar, professionals and home gardeners alike are learning to observe what is going on outdoors before they get the spray equipment out.</p>
        <p>Fewer services are (or should be) contracting for take-care visits to homes by the book, just because "they are going to be in the neighborhood that week." Rather, the maturity of particular insects is being observed and the progess of the plants watched. Sometimes spraying is either deemed unncessary or delayed until a later time. One of the researchers who is following this tack is Daniel Herms, an entomologist for the Dow Chemical Company. Dr. Herms found, for example, that while studying the pine needle scale closely, he observed that its hatch coincided with bloom on the common lilac. Hence the application of any materials to control the scale was delayed to a time when the insect was most vulnerable.</p>
        <p>Although borers are rarely seen, the damage done results in either weakening or death of many plants, particularly dogwoods, lilacs and peach trees.</p>
        <p>If the plant subject to the borer damage is monitored closely, the controls can be applied at the time when the insect is most vulnerable, rather than waiting until the damage is done. In this way, the trouble can be nipped in the bud before the valuable plant is ruined.</p>
        <p>To make this concept successful, gardeners will have to learn to work with nature and know what is going on in the world around them. The emphasis should be on close observation of plants, not just a casual stroll around the grounds.</p>
        <p>Learning to turn over leaves, to get down on the hands and knees once in a while and peer under plants or pull away mulches to see what is going on should be just as important as keeping the sidewalks tidy and the steps clear.</p>
        <p>The welfare and the success of any garden is up to those who contract for its care, the homewoners.  GARDENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
