<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Experts, Fire Tapes Provide Rare Evidence</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="605198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUICIDES AND SUICIDE ATTEMPTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARSON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELIGIOUS CULTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOOTINGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WACO (TEX)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRANCH DAVIDIANS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL BUREAU OF INVESTIGATION (FBI)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHULZ, MICHAEL J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, PATRICK M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religious Cults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DE1E3AF93BA15757C0A965958260" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Experts, Fire Tapes Provide Rare Evidence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL deCOURCY HINDS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</byline>
      <dateline>WACO, Tex., April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because the fire that consumed the Branch Davidian compound last week unfolded on live television, fire experts around the nation had the rare opportunity to record it on videotape and analyze its path of destruction.</p>
        <p>As a result, some outside experts were able to say that they agreed with the preliminary results of the fire investigators, who concluded on Monday that cult members started the lethal fire. Others, however, said the videotape was inconclusive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Because the fire that consumed the Branch Davidian compound last week unfolded on live television, fire experts around the nation had the rare opportunity to record it on videotape and analyze its path of destruction.</p>
        <p>As a result, some outside experts were able to say that they agreed with the preliminary results of the fire investigators, who concluded on Monday that cult members started the lethal fire. Others, however, said the videotape was inconclusive.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the experts said in interviews today, the fire was a text-book example of a deadly blaze involving a unsafe building and a 30-mile-an-hour wind. They described a quick, ferocious fire that would have left cult members less than five minutes to escape and that would have produced toxic, disorienting gases.</p>
        <p>An estimated 86 Branch Davidians, including the cult's leader, David Koresh, were killed in the April 19 fire. The blaze followed a 51-day siege and a Feb. 28 raid by the Federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms that left four agents and several cult members dead. F.B.I. officials said the fire began after they tried battering down walls and shooting tear gas into the compound in the hope of flushing Mr. Koresh out.</p>
        <p>Three of the seven experts interviewed said that the videotapes indicated that the fire was set by the cult members. The other four experts said the videotapes were inconclusive. The final report, which awaits laboratory results, might not be completed for weeks, although a preliminary report will be submitted on Wednesday to the Justice Department. A Shift in Policy</p>
        <p>At a news conference here today, the state officials overseeing the investigations announced an an apparent shift of policy. Once the voluminous amount of evidence from the compound is all collected, they said, it would be shipped to Federal laboratories in Washington. "Our crime laboratory in Austin has to be available to handle criminal matters that come up in Texas," said Mike Cox, a spokesman with the state Department of Public Safety.</p>
        <p>Earlier, officials conducting the investigation into how the fire started said they would use private laboratories in an effort to avoid any appearance of conflict of interest that might arise from a Federal laboratory making conclusions about evidence in a case in which Federal agents' actions are being questioned.</p>
        <p>Also at the news conference, officials gave an update on the progress of identifying the bodies. David W. Pereya, a justice of the peace who has jurisdiction over the coroner's inquest, said that 20 more autopsies had been completed but that no cause of death had been determined in those cases.</p>
        <p>A third victim has been identified, but Mr. Pereya said he would not disclose the name until relatives were notified. On Monday, he said two bodies had been identified as David M. Jones and Shari Doyle and said they had died from bullet wounds in the head.  The Experts Weigh In</p>
        <p>As the investigation continues, the the videotape of the compound fire will be an important piece of evidence, the seven arson experts said today. But they were split on how conclusive it was.</p>
        <p>Patrick M. Kennedy and Michael J. Schulz, e co-authors of the national fire code standards that sets out the procedures for investigating fires and explosions, dismissed the possibility that the F.B.I. tanks battering holes in the compound could have started the fire by knocking over kerosene lanterns. "If a tank knocked over a lantern, it would have caused a fire right away and the fire would have spread to maximum perimeter of the kerosene right away," Mr. Kennedy said.</p>
        <p>But the first fire did not appear near the openings left by the tanks, but in a second-story window, above the tank and about 30 feet to the side. The second fire, he said, started in the tower to other side of the tank.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy said officials had apparently done what they could to prevent a fire, including shutting off the compound's electricity and using what the authorities have called non-flammable tear gas.</p>
        <p>Should they have had fire trucks standing by? "To contain that fire, they would have needed to spray thousands of gallons of water per minute on the fire and even then they may not have been able to put it out," Mr. Kennedy said. He said the gunfire that Federal officials maintained came out of the compound when the tanks assaulted the building also was a factor. "They couldn't have used firefighters because they are not paid or trained for a situation like that," he said.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Klem, director of the National Fire Protection Association in Boston, a research organization that publishes national fire codes for buildings, said the speed and ferocity of the Branch Davidian fire was not unusual, given the compound's flimsy construction and the 30 m.p.h. winds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klem said the videotapes he saw provided too little information for him to conclude what had caused the fire. He also said the black smoke that appeared over the compound was not unusual and did not necessarily suggest that some kind of accelerant fuel had been used.</p>
        <p>He said the building was built without regard for fire safety, and the fire, which probably reached temperatures of 2,400 degrees, sped through the compound unimpeded, since there were no masonry walls between buildings or horizontal fire stops between floors. Open stairwells, flimsy interior partitions and wooden exterior walls fed the fire, as did tanks of propane and mounds of ammunition and grenades.</p>
        <p>Bales of hay stacked against windows in the compound were cited as a fuel by both cult members and Mr. Gray. But Mr. Klem said tightly packed bales of hay were difficult to ignite and burned slowly at first. He also said kerosene, which the cult members used for lamps, was very difficult to ignite. For a kerosene lamp to have had a role in starting the fire, it would have had to have been lit at the time it was knocked over. Cult members have said they were lit and used for lighting since the electricity had been cut.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klem estimated that once one room had become engulfed by fire, a point referred to as flashover, the cult members throughout the compound had only about five minutes to escape. After a flashover, the fire produces an enormous amount of toxic gases that cause confusion.</p>
        <p>"It's not unusual for people to try to return to burning buildings, and it's not because they are going back to collect valuables or to die," Mr. Klem said. "They are intoxicated and disoriented."  Conflict of Interest</p>
        <p>The announcement today that Federal laboratories would be used in the investigation contradicted earlier statements that lab work would be done in state and private labs in the hopes of avoiding a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>Pressed by reporters today about the apparent shift in policy, Mr. Cox of the Texas Department of Public Safety said today, "The Texas Rangers are investigating the crime scene and if you are concerned about a conflict of interest, you should talk to the U.S. Attorney's Office."</p>
        <p>The United States Attorney referred inquiries to the Department of Justice, and Carl Stern, a department spokesman answering reporters' inquiries, said, "All the shifts in police I know of, are the ones you invented."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
