<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stocks Climb Broadly as Dow Gains 17.56</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="605247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCK PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STOCK EXCHANGE (NYSE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDA153FF93BA15757C0A965958260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stocks Climb Broadly as Dow Gains 17.56</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Skittish investors, apparently relieved that the Clinton Administration was being frustrated in its spending plans or simply exasperated with the last six losing sessions, bid up the stock market on a broad front yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average closed up 17.56 points, to 3415.93. After ignoring positive news on consumer confidence from the Conference Board and falling 14 points, the Dow surged nearly 19 points in the last hour of trading. Computerized buy programs helped, traders said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Skittish investors, apparently relieved that the Clinton Administration was being frustrated in its spending plans or simply exasperated with the last six losing sessions, bid up the stock market on a broad front yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average closed up 17.56 points, to 3415.93. After ignoring positive news on consumer confidence from the Conference Board and falling 14 points, the Dow surged nearly 19 points in the last hour of trading. Computerized buy programs helped, traders said.</p>
        <p>Volume yesterday was almost exactly the same as Monday's relatively heavy trading: about 284.1 million shares, compared with 283.3 million a day earlier. Gaining stocks on the Big Board narrowly outnumbered losers, 962 to 954.</p>
        <p>The New York Stock Exchange Composite index rose 2.02 points, to 241.93. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500 rose 4.47 points, to 438.01, and the Nasdaq composite index rose 6.65 points, to 652.52.</p>
        <p>The gold stocks, winners on Friday and Monday, generally closed down yesterday. Gold prices fell from seven-month highs Monday as investors concluded that high inflation was not in danger of returning.</p>
        <p>Some traders reacted positively to the budget director Leon Panetta's remarks Monday that he was discouraged about the outlook for President Clinton's budget passing Congress. Pharmaceutical stocks, like Merck, rose on heavy trading, perhaps on the theory that Mr. Clinton could not pass his health-care reform package and thus hurt industry profits.</p>
        <p>"The Bush guys were out of touch from the right wing and the Clinton guys are out of touch from the left wing," said David G. Shulman, chief equity strategist for Salomon Brothers. "I voted for Clinton, but there are too many Rhodes Scholars in the Administration whose instinct is to regulate and to tax. The market is reacting to that."</p>
        <p>Other traders simply said that a rising market is what investors do this time of month. "The market is always strong in the last few trading days of the month," said Harry W. Laubscher, a senior vice president and market analyst for Tucker Anthony. "The market has been down, so we put out the word today to start buying."</p>
        <p>Mr. Laubscher added, "We'll start selling next Wednesday or Friday because the market is weak at the beginning of the month."</p>
        <p>The Dow industrials were lifted by four stocks -- McDonald's, J. P. Morgan, Procter &amp; Gamble and Merck -- whose price increases accounted for 11 of the Dow's nearly 18-point rise.</p>
        <p>Most surprising of these stocks was McDonald's, up 1 1/2, to 47 5/8, on no discernible news. Procter &amp; Gamble was up 1 3/8, to 67 3/4, on higher third-quarter earnings.</p>
        <p>The rise in broader indexes seemed to indicate that investors were revisiting stocks they had sold earlier, repurchasing them at cheaper prices. The S. &amp; P. 500, for example, was led by diversified health-care companies, like Johnson &amp; Johnson and Bristol- Myers, as well as drug companies like Pfizer and Merck and food companies like General Mills and Sara Lee. Merck was the second-most-active stock on the Big Board.</p>
        <p>Pepsico was the most active stock on the Big Board, with 5.64 million shares changing hands on news that its quarterly earnings rose but not as high as analysts' expectations. It closed down 5/8, to 36 5/8.</p>
        <p>Telefonos de Mexico, a popular telecommunications stock, was the third most active on the Big Board, with volume of 4.2 million shares. It closed down 1/2, to 51 1/4, on remarks by Secretary of the Treasury Lloyd Bentsen that the North American Free Trade Agreement was in for a "rough ride" in Congress.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
