<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking a Gift Painting in the Dollar Sign; Paterson Examines Its Legacy of Art: How Much It's Worth and How to Restore It</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="605252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIBRARIES AND LIBRARIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PATERSON (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">DANFORTH LIBRARY (PATERSON, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, JOSEPH F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD6123FF93BA15757C0A965958260" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking a Gift Painting in the Dollar Sign; Paterson Examines Its Legacy of Art: How Much It's Worth and How to Restore It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH F. SULLIVAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, JOSEPH F</byline>
      <dateline>PATERSON, N.J., April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During the first half of the century, industrialists and business leaders filled the Danforth Library here with gifts of books and works of art. But as important industries left the city and its economy declined, so did appreciation for its cultural treasures.</p>
        <p>Much of the art, including statues, bronzes, rare furniture and more than 60 paintings, is now in storage and, like the building itself, in need of maintenance and repair. But while a makeover is planned for the 88-year-old library, an acrimonious debate is growing over the art -- what it is worth, who should care for it and even where it is.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During the first half of the century, industrialists and business leaders filled the Danforth Library here with gifts of books and works of art. But as important industries left the city and its economy declined, so did appreciation for its cultural treasures.</p>
        <p>Much of the art, including statues, bronzes, rare furniture and more than 60 paintings, is now in storage and, like the building itself, in need of maintenance and repair. But while a makeover is planned for the 88-year-old library, an acrimonious debate is growing over the art -- what it is worth, who should care for it and even where it is.</p>
        <p>At least twice the city has tried to raise money by selling paintings from the library collection. Public outrage stopped one sale in the 1970's. In 1982 it took a lawsuit filed by a dozen citizens to save a painting titled "In the Park" by William Merritt Chase that has been appraised at $500,000 to $1 million. The painting was one of 26 donated in 1926 by Jennie Tuttle Hobart, the widow of Garret A. Hobart, who served as William McKinley's Vice President from 1897 until Mr. Hobart's death in 1899.</p>
        <p>"Part of the reason we sued was that we felt if that painting was sold the whole collection might go," said Howard Sterling, now a member of the library's art committee. Publicity led to display of the painting in a retrospective on Chase's work at the Metropolitan Museum of Art.  And the attention caused the city to take a new look at the art.</p>
        <p>"What's happening in Paterson is not unique," Mr. Sterling said. "What is going on is that a lot of people who collected art around the turn of the century began giving it to public institutions in the 1920's, and people are just now beginning to take notice of things they just considered decorations gathering dust. In many cases folks don't know what their collections are worth or how to maintain them."</p>
        <p>A couple of years ago a library official went looking for 28 19th-century American and European paintings donated to the library by Ralph P. Ross, a textile manufacturer.</p>
        <p>Several paintings were found in a vault, some of them torn and deteriorating from dampness, said Dominic A. DiNardo, a member of the library's board. "Nobody will say who put them there," he said.</p>
        <p>A former Paterson resident who wants to establish a museum to house the city's art claims more than two dozen pieces donated by Mr. Ross are missing. Nick Sunday, a magazine writer and graphic artist who lives in nearby Prospect Park, has sent a list of the items that he claims are missing to the State Attorney General, Robert J. Del Tufo, who forwarded Mr. Sunday's complaint to the Passaic County Prosecutor. In the last few days Mayor William J. Pascrell has asked the library for an accounting of each piece of art. He also estimated the cost of restoring the paintings at $50,000 and pledged to find the money.</p>
        <p>Norma Harrison, president of the board since January, has said the library can account for all of the objects listed in Mr. Sunday's complaint.</p>
        <p>In addition, Ms. Harrison says, the library has asked the city and council, which must approve its budget request, for $12,000 for a part-time curator to examine the paintings, appraise their value and determine which ones are worth restoring and which are too damaged to repair. "We also hope a curator will help us attract grants, interpret the art and develop a curriculum for the schools in Paterson and elsewhere," she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sunday has also taken on another Paterson institution, the Hamilton Club, a businessmen's group founded in the late 1800's, in defense of another group of paintings.</p>
        <p>He has persuaded Sotheby's auction house in New York to delay the sale of 19 paintings that he contends were once owned by Mr. Ross. "He was very firm about what he wanted done with his paintings," Mr. Sunday said of the city's best-known philanthropist. "He wanted them to be available for the young people of the city."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sunday says the paintings were part of a collection of 50 works that Mr. Ross gave to the local chamber of commerce in the 1930's, specifying that if the chamber ever wanted to dispose of them they should go to the city's two high schools and the library.</p>
        <p>In the early 1950's, he said, the chamber moved out of its quarters in the Fabian Building, and Mr. Ross took 25 of the paintings to the library and 25 to the Hamilton Club, the businessmen's club. Some of these paintings were taken to Sotheby's late last year by Hamilton Club Associates, a limited partnership that had obtained them from the club, Mr. Sunday said.</p>
        <p>Walter Hunziker Jr., the president of the Hamilton Club, said discussions are under way to clear up questions about ownership of the paintings, whose history, he said, is "very confused, nothing is clear." But he said the story about their being given to the chamber of commerce and earmarked for the schools "is made up out of whole cloth and supposition."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sunday has set up a nonprofit museum named for Jennie Tuttle Hobart to protect the city's art collection from future attempts to sell it off. But the museum exists only on paper so far.</p>
        <p>Last year Mr. Sunday and his fledging museum won a $10,000 grant from the New Jersey Committee for the Humanities to make a catalogue of the library's art collection, but the award was rescinded when the library board said it would not cooperate with the project.</p>
        <p>"It was a total surprise," said Mr. Sterling, who was on the library committee in 1991 when Mr. Sunday served as a member for a few months.</p>
        <p>"He quickly decided we weren't capable and wanted us to turn over the library's collection to him," he said.</p>
        <p>He said it was regrettable that Mr. Sunday's relations with the library soured. "He was absolutely right when he said many pieces of art are at a critical stage, need attention and will deteriorate faster if we don't do something," he said. "But we are not at the stage where we will absolutely lose some of the art."</p>
        <p>"I have this idea that some think crazy, that somewhere down the road the city will be restored to economic vitality, and that benefactors and resources will be found to restore the collection and appropriately display it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
