<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fordham Heads Into Season With Attitude Adjustment</title>
    <meta content="18FORD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/18/sports/18FORD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1248210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fordham University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Lena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hill, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1D6103BF93BA25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fordham Heads Into Season With Attitude Adjustment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LENA WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Lena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Hill, new Fordham men's basketball coach, discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bob Hill did not know what to expect when he signed as coach of the Fordham men's basketball team last season, but he did not like what he found: a team lacking in principles, values and discipline.</p>
        <p>Hill, who had coached everyone from a young Patrick Ewing and a sneakerless Dennis Rodman to players on the European circuit, immediately established his rules and expectations for the team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bob Hill did not know what to expect when he signed as coach of the Fordham men's basketball team last season, but he did not like what he found: a team lacking in principles, values and discipline.</p>
        <p>Hill, who had coached everyone from a young Patrick Ewing and a sneakerless Dennis Rodman to players on the European circuit, immediately established his rules and expectations for the team.</p>
        <p>Hill made himself perfectly clear by twice suspending Bevon Robin, the team's leading scorer and co-captain, for failing to attend study hall. The second suspension took place on the eve of the Atlantic 10 tournament.</p>
        <p>The Rams are still a work in progress, according to their coach, but it was a more focused Fordham team that opened the season last night against North Carolina-Charlotte in the CoSida Classic in Raleigh, N.C. The Rams lost, 88-75, for their third straight season-opening loss. They play Pennsylvania, a 77-64 loser last night to North Carolina State, tonight in the tournament's consolation game.</p>
        <p>Fordham played without power forward Jeff McMillan, the 6-foot-8 freshman whom some say can rebound the Rams into the postseason. McMillan, a preseason pick to the Atlantic 10 rookie team, was ruled ineligible because he received financial aid during his two years at St. Thomas More prep school, a violation of National Collegiate Athletic Association guidelines. McMillan will have to sit out the first three games of this season.</p>
        <p>''It's an unfortunate situation,'' said Hill, who managed to win over the heavily recruited McMillan, from Staten Island, even beating out St. John's. ''Jeff was unaware of the regulation at the time he received the financial aid, and really had no other recourse because of his family situation.''</p>
        <p>A year ago, the Rams were expected to be no more than a .500 team and finished 14-15, with a 7-9 conference record. This season, Fordham, which was picked to finish in a sixth-place tie with St. Joseph's, still lacks the depth, size and postseason experience to challenge the conference's top teams, Xavier and Temple.</p>
        <p>But Fordham is perhaps deeper than it has ever been. McMillan will play alongside Teremun Johnson, a 6-6 junior. Antoine Knighton, a 6-2 transfer from Atlanta Metropolitan College, can bring added punch to the backcourt. Guard Jason Harris is emerging as one of the top defensive players and 3-point shooters in the conference, and the 6-9 center Duke Freeman-McKamey is coming off a season in which he was named the conference's most improved player.</p>
        <p>''I'm not afraid to go to the 10th guy now, whereas last year I was a little concerned to go beyond seventh,'' Hill said.</p>
        <p>More than anything, Fordham has a rejuvenated floor leader and captain in Robin, who recently acknowledged playing much of last season while angry and unhappy.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, I'm smiling a lot more now,'' Robin said. ''Last year I didn't understand what it took to be a point guard. Coach tried to tell me, but when you have a new coach you try to fight the system a little bit.''</p>
        <p>Fordham's Lady Rams also opened last night, losing at home to 12th-ranked Florida, 76-36.</p>
        <p>The women have a new head coach, Jim Lewis. He comes to Fordham with 30 years of experience, including 14 seasons as head coach at George Mason and two with the Washington Mystics of the Women's National Basketball Association.</p>
        <p>Just as Hill did last season, Lewis immediately put in a new system, designed to build on last year's 4-24 record.</p>
        <p>''Defense is our hallmark and we will play a lot of pressure man, and go downcourt and play a variety of presses,'' Lewis said. ''We're not a very big team, so we can't afford to sit back and let teams come down and pound the floor on us.''</p>
        <p>Fordham added some size to its lineup, with the freshman Lauren Fleischer, a 6-2 forward-center, and Caitlin Chiaramonte, a 6-1 transfer student from the University of Richmond, where she played power forward. The Rams have three additions to the backcourt: the freshman Patty Williams, who brings depth as a shooting guard, Annie DeRoy and Erika Slayton.</p>
        <p>The senior guard Maureen Garvey, who tore the anterior cruciate ligament in her right knee last season after averaging 9.9 points and 4.4 assists in her first eight games, is healthy, and the senior forward Nailah Wallace, last season's leading scorer at 14 points a game, is expected to make a major contribution.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
