<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Fall Short Against Canucks</title>
    <meta content="18RANG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/18/sports/18RANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1248239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vancouver Canucks</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Vancouver Canucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7DE113BF93BA25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Fall Short Against Canucks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>VANCOUVER, British Columbia, Nov. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vancouver Canucks defeat New York Rangers, 4-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The boos grew louder every time Mark Messier touched the puck tonight. Messier was booed even when he stood still in the face-off circle.</p>
        <p>This was not a homecoming, nor was it a triumphant return to the place where Messier spent three seasons in exile, even if he refuses to call it that. After turning in one of their best periods of the season in the first, the Rangers were blown out of the building in the second by the Vancouver Canucks, who won their first meeting against their old captain, 4-3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The boos grew louder every time Mark Messier touched the puck tonight. Messier was booed even when he stood still in the face-off circle.</p>
        <p>This was not a homecoming, nor was it a triumphant return to the place where Messier spent three seasons in exile, even if he refuses to call it that. After turning in one of their best periods of the season in the first, the Rangers were blown out of the building in the second by the Vancouver Canucks, who won their first meeting against their old captain, 4-3</p>
        <p>Messier expected a mixed reaction from the fans here tonight in his first visit to Vancouver since signing with the Rangers this summer after a three-year stint with the Canucks.</p>
        <p>''No big deal,'' said Messier, who has heard his share of boos at opposing arenas over the years. ''No problem.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps it wasn't. But the visit was in contrast to the ones Messier had made to New York the first time he came in with the Canucks, and in Edmonton every time he has visited since leaving the Oilers.</p>
        <p>''I was largely viewed as a guy breaking up a good thing in Vancouver, which would have happened whether I was there or not,'' Messier said earlier this week. ''But you could see it starting to turn the corner last year. And I can take a lot of satisfaction from that, especially because they're not in our conference. There was a lot of work to do there. The organization went through a complete overhaul two or three times in the time I was there.''</p>
        <p>One person who wished Messier was still here as his team's captain was Vancouver's general manager, Brian Burke, who said he hoped the fans would show Messier the proper respect tonight.</p>
        <p>''I just hope we don't show him too much respect on the ice during the game,'' Burke said.</p>
        <p>The Canucks must have heard Burke. Trailing by 1-0 after one period -- Jan Hlavac scored a power-play goal 5 minutes 34 seconds into the game for the Rangers -- the Canucks owned the second. Matt Cooke, who took the game-opening face-off against Messier, scored at even strength 1:35 into the second to tie it. Markus Naslund, who replaced Messier as the Canucks' captain, scored on the power play at 5:37 to give Vancouver the lead for good.</p>
        <p>Then Daniel Sedin, one of the heralded rookie twins the Canucks were hoping Messier would provide a little guidance, rifled a wrist shot from the left circle past Mike Richter (28 saves) on the power play, with Messier chasing, at 9:28. Vancouver took a 3-1 lead into the final period.</p>
        <p>The Rangers opened the game on a strong note. They outshot the Canucks, 13-2, early on and kept Vancouver goalie Felix Potvin (29 saves) busy. Hlavac scored his seventh goal of the season on a passing play with his Czech linemates, Petr Nedved and Radek Dvorak. Brian Leetch seemed to be everywhere, and the Rangers got the better of the action in a crisp, well-played period.</p>
        <p>Then the Rangers' wheels fell off. Once the rookie defenseman Tomas Kloucek was whistled for hooking at 14:56 of the first period, the momentum shifted. By the time the second period was over, the Rangers had been whistled for eight minor penalties, two by Rich Pilon on the same play, and twice for having too many men on the ice.</p>
        <p>Todd Bertuzzi, the former Islander, scored an unassisted goal at 10:36 of the final period by getting by Kloucek behind the net before putting a no-look, reverse backhander past Richter from off the right post. That gave the Canucks a 4-1 lead, and it seemed just about over.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers staged an improbable rally. Kim Johnsson, back after missing five games with a hand injury, pounced on a Nedved rebound and punched it in from the right post at 11:14. At 12:21, Potvin allowed a goal to Valery Kamensky from a spot near the right-wing boards. Messier assisted, hearing his loudest boos yet. Leetch also got an assist, tying Rod Gilbert for the franchise mark with the 615th assist of his career.</p>
        <p>The Rangers failed to win in Vancouver for the first time since Oct. 11, 1997 -- Messier's first season with the Canucks.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>VLADIMIR MALAKHOV, who reinjured his left knee in Wednesday night's 3-2 victory over Minnesota, will probably be examined by team doctors in New York on Monday.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
