<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Diplomats May Talk Peace, But Bosnia Presses the War</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="791581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">US-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-YUGOSLAVIA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BANJA LUKA (BOSNIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEDGES, CHRIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SILAJDZIC, HARIS (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D6173BF93AA1575AC0A963958260" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Diplomats May Talk Peace, But Bosnia Presses the War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS HEDGES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HEDGES, CHRIS</byline>
      <dateline>ORAHOVLJANI, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Sept. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The headlines may be filled with talk of peace. But the impression here on the front lines, where Bosnian forces today battled their way toward the high ground overlooking Banja Luka, is quite different.</p>
        <p>This morning heavy artillery, including tanks, hammered at Serbian positions surrounding the town of Mrkonjic Grad, about 40 miles from Banja Luka, Government troops said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The headlines may be filled with talk of peace. But the impression here on the front lines, where Bosnian forces today battled their way toward the high ground overlooking Banja Luka, is quite different.</p>
        <p>This morning heavy artillery, including tanks, hammered at Serbian positions surrounding the town of Mrkonjic Grad, about 40 miles from Banja Luka, Government troops said.</p>
        <p>The troops said Bosnian Serb MIG-21 planes pounded the advancing Bosnian Army soldiers and the Bosnian Croat militiamen that fought beside them. They said retreating Serbs also unleashed VBR multiple rockets that exploded on the forested slope of a nearby hill.</p>
        <p>The bombastic talk among Bosnian Government soldiers who fought today was not of resting on their recent gains but of continuing to fight until they drove the Serbs out of the region altogether.</p>
        <p>"We have no intention of stopping now," said Haris Pecinkovic, a senior front-line commander in the Bosnia V Corps, as he stood with his bodyguards near a deserted farmhouse outside this village. "For three and a half years we signed every piece of paper the international community placed in front of us, and then watched the Serbs violate the agreements and take advantage of our weakness. Now the tables are turned. We will not put down our weapons until we have our country, all of it, back under our control."</p>
        <p>Bosnian Government soldiers said they had captured troops from neighboring Yugoslavia, as well as Serbs from Bosnia, but were unable to present their prisoners to the outside world because, they said, the captives had been executed.</p>
        <p>"We don't have the time or the facilities to take care of prisoners now," said an officer in the elite Ljutoc battalion, a unit made up of soldiers who lost their homes in the Serbs' "ethnic cleansing" campaign more than three years ago. "But we have picked up Serbian troops from Belgrade in this advance. They just aren't around anymore to show you."</p>
        <p>There was no confirmation of their assertions of executions or that troops from Yugoslavia had entered the fighting in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>Although the Bosnian Government has promised not to seize Banja Luka, the largest remaining Serbian stronghold in Bosnia, the commanders in the field say otherwise.</p>
        <p>Commanders here said they had been ordered to move around Banja Luka, taking the high ground, and effectively cutting the city off from the rest of Bosnian Serb territory. They scoffed at a proposal today from Belgrade to negotiate a cease-fire and dismissed American efforts to end the fighting.</p>
        <p>Distrustful of the Serbs, and lacking faith in peace efforts, they said their advance was aimed at seizing huge chunks, and perhaps all, of the Bosnian land still in Serbian hands.</p>
        <p>The United Nations and military analysts have said that taking Banja Luka would be difficult for the Bosnian Government, and almost impossible without the support of Croatian Government artillery, but that the Bosnian Army on its own might be able to lay siege to the city, where 100,000 Serbian refugees have swollen the population.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Haris Silajdzic said today in Sarajevo that he saw no reason for his country to stop fighting. "As long as there is no peace, there is war," he said. "So long as the Serb terrorists do not accept peace, we have the right to liberate every inch of Bosnia-Herzegovina."</p>
        <p>Omar Sacirbey, an aide and brother to the Bosnian Foreign Minister, Muhamed Sacirbey, said today that the Bosnian Government might be willing to give up its recent territorial gains "if the Bosnian Serbs give up claim to Gorazde and Sarajevo."</p>
        <p>The drive by the Bosnian Army could upset the delicate American-led negotiations to end the war. The Bosnian Serbs and the Bosnian Government each control about half the country, after Bosnian Army and Croatian forces wrested about 30 percent of Bosnian territory from Serbian hands this month.</p>
        <p>The split conveniently fits the plan to give the Bosnian Government 51 percent of Bosnia and the Serbs 49 percent of the country.</p>
        <p>"Once we have the town of Mrkonjic Grad, which rests on heights overlooking Banja Luka, we have Banja Luka," said Commander Peckinkovic. Taking the high ground would represent an advance, but it is still far from Banja Luka.</p>
        <p>Bosnian Government commanders asserted today that the Serbs were desperate, and pointed to strikes by the Bosnian Serb jets and the launching of powerful Luna and Orka rockets on Bosnian Government positions, including an attack on the town of Travnik on Wednesday that killed 2 people and wounded 25.</p>
        <p>Government and Croatian troops on the southern front were bombed twice Wednesday by three Bosnian Serb war planes and three times today, they said.</p>
        <p>"The Serbs have brought in a lot of troops to try and shore up their positions," said a senior Bosnian commander, who asked to remain unidentified.</p>
        <p>"There is a lot of new artillery and we are meeting stiffer resistance than we met two weeks ago, when most of the Serbs simply fled. But the Serbs are still retreating, and we expect that as we close in on Banja Luka these rocket and air strikes will increase. They are getting desperate."</p>
        <p>It was unclear today whether Croatian Government troops were fighting today. The Croatian Government said that its soldiers were no longer involved in the offensive against the Bosnian Serbs, although the Bosnian Croat militias are.</p>
        <p>The Bosnian Serbs, however, contend that regular Croatian Army troops are taking part. The Bosnian Serbs have shelled Croatian towns along the border with Bosnia over the last few days in "retaliation" for the alleged Croatian involvement.</p>
        <p>Bosnian Government commanders said that regular army troops from Yugoslavia, along with a mercenary militia group led by the Serbian legend, Arkan, have tried to shore up the beleaguered Bosnian Serbs, who are still reeling from two weeks of NATO air strikes.</p>
        <p>The Ljutoc unit, which said it had engaged Arkan's forces this morning in a heavy firefight, later sat wearily drinking cans of beer in a pasture. Many wore bandanas tightly around the tops of their heads or had bandoliers of machine gun bullets draped across their chests. The boom of tank rounds echoed off the surrounding hills as they told their war stories.</p>
        <p>"Four years ago the Serbs stripped us of everything," said Sgt. Emir Seferovic, 26. "Now we are here to take it all back. Don't expect us to stop until then."</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Serb Disciplines Troops</p>
        <p>BANJA LUKA, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Sept. 28 (Reuters) -- Gen. Ratko Mladic, the Bosnian Serb military commander, has arrested officers he blames for huge battlefield losses against allied Muslim and Croat forces in northwest Bosnia, military officials said today. Those under investigation are suspected of working for the Serbian-led Yugoslav Government in Belgrade.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
