<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="138154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLADSTONE, BERNARD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Q&amp;A (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DF1E3FF932A15757C0A96E948260" item-length="397" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bernard Gladstone</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GLADSTONE, BERNARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Q. Last summer we had the bricks on the front of our house cleaned and tuck pointed. They are light tan face bricks with a semismooth finish. Since the job was done the brick is dull, with numerous white stains, apparently from the chemicals used in cleaning. Can I restore the brick to its original condition?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Q. Last summer we had the bricks on the front of our house cleaned and tuck pointed. They are light tan face bricks with a semismooth finish. Since the job was done the brick is dull, with numerous white stains, apparently from the chemicals used in cleaning. Can I restore the brick to its original condition?</p>
        <p>Q. Last summer we had the bricks on the front of our house cleaned and tuck pointed. They are light tan face bricks with a semismooth finish. Since the job was done the brick is dull, with numerous white stains, apparently from the chemicals used in cleaning. Can I restore the brick to its original condition?  A.It sounds as if the white stains are from mortar that was smeared around and not thoroughly washed off after the pointing was finished. If so, they can be washed off with a diluted solution of muriatic acid: one part acid to five parts water.</p>
        <p>Mix in a glass or plastic bowl (pour the acid into the water, not vice versa) and wear rubber gloves and safety goggles while working. Scrub on with a bristle brush, let soak for about five minutes and flush off with lots of water.</p>
        <p>It might be a good idea to test this on a small section before doing the entire wall.  Q.I have recently had new hardwood floors installed in two rooms. These were finished with three coats of polyurethane. What is the proper daily care for this, and is an annual touch-up required?  A.Keeping the floors clean by daily dry mopping or vacuuming is probably the most important maintenance, especially where people walk in from the outside. Keeping the floors lightly waxed (even though some manufacturers say it is not necessary) is also a good idea because it helps prevent scratching and simplifies cleaning.</p>
        <p>Use a cleaner-polish once a year to clean the finish more thoroughly. Annual touching up of worn spots with polyurethane is seldom required; it seldom works anyway, because the touch-ups (if needed) always tend to be noticeable. When the finish shows signs of wear it usually must be completely redone.  Q.Our house, which has a dry-wall interior, was built six months ago. Our contractor advised waiting two years before we put up any paper. The walls are painted with flat latex paint. Must we wait that long before papering, and is it necessary to apply oil paint or other coating before the paper?  A.No to both questions. Waiting a couple of months is a good idea. You can put wall covering over latex paint, as long as the paint is at least six months old.</p>
        <p>If any other preparation of the surface is required (as with some of the more specialized wall coverings) the directions furnished with the wall covering material will say what to do.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
