<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Full House</title>
    <meta content="21GOODMAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1025930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E0DF1F3AF932A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Full House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Walter Goodman</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHUT UP AND DEAL</p>
        <p>By Jesse May.</p>
        <p>217 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Anchor Books/Doubleday.</p>
        <p>Paper, $12.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHUT UP AND DEAL</p>
        <p>By Jesse May.</p>
        <p>217 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Anchor Books/Doubleday.</p>
        <p>Paper, $12.95.</p>
        <p>Reading ''Shut Up and Deal'' while hanging around at the World Series of Poker, held every May at Binion's Horseshoe in downtown Las Vegas, was a chastening experience. Jesse May, the author of these ostensible confessions of a professional poker player, does not let the reader who thinks he knows how to play the game forget that in the company of the pros, he is a tourist, a mark, the live one. And being there at Binion's, watching the big boys with their stacks of $100 bills and their piles of chips in expensive hues, only enlarges the gulf between you and them.</p>
        <p>''Shut Up and Deal'' is presented as a novel, but that may be a bluff. The characters seem to have been inspired by players May has observed or heard about on the casino circuit. Mickey, the narrator, tracks the Las Vegas, Atlantic City and Connecticut regulars, with excursions abroad and afield. He brings on Russian Alex, Vinnie the Greek, Uptown Raoul Abdul, Johnny World and Hot Mama Earl and chronicles the rivalry between bad Bart Stone and stoned John Smiley.</p>
        <p>There's plenty of the smoky, jittery atmosphere of the establishments where, given the odds and casino economics, even the great stud and hold-'em specialists must wind up losers -- at the tables as well as in what passes for life away from them. They are susceptible to bad hands and the bad dreams they inspire.</p>
        <p>Missing in May's dash from anecdote to unresounding anecdote is a sustaining narrative, which may be a comment on the poker player's attention span: ''Shut up and deal!'' Insofar as there is a plot, it concerns a young man's disillusionment with his dream existence of playing poker all the time.</p>
        <p>Mickey himself is a dim figure, and the castoff outfits he wears for luck or to provide the semblance of a personality don't help much: ''I'm standing there trying to stay calm wearing a 1930's maroon pinstripe three-piece gangster suit that looked real wild and crazy and made a big hit in the poker room when I came gallivanting in about 14 or 15 hours before. Now it's wrinkled and smelly and hot and not real comfortable.'' Like the nicknames and the scenery, the costumes are efforts to invest the pallid characters with some color.</p>
        <p>May is at his best in delivering the occasional flash of frenetic energy. Here's a player named Josh Vasaki busting in on a $100-200 game: He ''throws a pile of money down and sits down in the open seat and stands up and then sits down and then gets up on his knees and lights a cigarette and says, 'Deal me in. Hello, boys, what are you playing? Let's raise the limit. Yo, World, Johnny World, I want to play you head up, World. Fresca Kid! Kid, Kid, Kid, how's it going? You think you're the king. They say you're the best, Kid -- I'm gonna beat you, I'm gonna break you, I'm gonna take all your money, Kid. Who's it to? Is it to me? Raise. I raise! What is this game, it's eight or better, right?' ''</p>
        <p>Such an introduction brings the prospect of action, but there's no follow-through, just another unmemorable episode. Players come and go; yesterday's winner is today's loser; connections are lacking. Just like in a casino.</p>
        <p>A common problem with poker tales is a want of climactic variety: either a shrewd bluff drives out the better hand or the cards defy credibility and somebody makes a straight flush against the other guy's four aces. When, like May, an author sticks closer to the reality of poker, which is more like ritual than opera, there's not much punch. In his search for a theme, the best May comes up with is: ''People always want to know what's going on and what's going on is people are going broke. That's mostly it. And the trick is not to be one of them.'' The reader who is not already hooked on poker lore is likely to begin drifting.</p>
        <p>Reading this short book, especially between sessions at the (in my case, low-stakes) tables during the World Series, where all the talk is poker talk, is like tuning in at the bar to somebody else's triumphs and beats. You've heard them before, and they go down better with a drink.  Walter Goodman is a television critic for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Walter Goodman is a television critic for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
