<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kent Enlists a Star In Land Preservation</title>
    <meta content="21PATT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026100"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kent (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kent Land Trust (Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lupone, Patti</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Litchfield County</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DF113DF932A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kent Enlists a Star In Land Preservation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Actress/singer Patti LuPone comments on decision to perform preview segment of new concert to benefit Kent Land Trust in Kent, Conn, and her new farm home in town; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PATTI LUPONE said she was ''just a kid in acting school'' when she found her dream retreat in the woods and hills of Kent, in an early 19th-century farmhouse on 90 acres ''where all the kids stayed in the hearth.'' That's country talk for kitchen.</p>
        <p>It was 1968 and ''all the kids'' were first-year students in a historic acting program, itself in its first year. The program was set up and headed by John Houseman as the drama division of Juilliard, the music conservatory that moved that year to the then-new Lincoln Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PATTI LUPONE said she was ''just a kid in acting school'' when she found her dream retreat in the woods and hills of Kent, in an early 19th-century farmhouse on 90 acres ''where all the kids stayed in the hearth.'' That's country talk for kitchen.</p>
        <p>It was 1968 and ''all the kids'' were first-year students in a historic acting program, itself in its first year. The program was set up and headed by John Houseman as the drama division of Juilliard, the music conservatory that moved that year to the then-new Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>It was 13 years later, just after Ms. LuPone seized diva-dom in ''Evita,'' that she bought a piece of that land, the last parcel that was being sold off by the father of Jared Sakren, the student who lured Ms. LuPone to a rural hangout in Litchfield County.</p>
        <p>''I bought it, never thinking I would ever do anything with it,'' Ms. LuPone said during a rehearsal break for the Tony Awards show on television recently. She was appearing in the opening number, ''The Broadway Divas,'' in an excerpt from ''Don't Cry for Me, Argentina,'' her signature song from ''Evita.'' Although she was a new landowner in Kent, Ms. LuPone said, ''I never even went up to it at that time. You couldn't actually get to it. We would hike through the woods but when we got to this ravine, there was a cow path that sort of ended. Then you had to climb up the steep mountain. The woods up there are incredibly thick. When I took Matthew, my future husband, up to see it, we macheted our way up to the pasture. It was around Thanksgiving and huge snowflakes started to fall through the trees. It was magical.''</p>
        <p>It is for the preservation of that magic and for the benefit of the Kent Land Trust, a not-for-profit organization formed in 1989 to preserve the countryside, that Ms. LuPone, now a full-time resident of Kent Hollow, with her husband, Matthew Johnston, and their 7-year-old son Joshua, is performing a preview segment of her new concert, ''The Heart of the Matter,'' on Saturday in the Mattison Auditorium at the Kent School.</p>
        <p>The spread of commercial development from Norwalk along Route 7 in the 1980's aroused activists in Kent to form an organization with a save-the-landscape mission. ''Route 7, which parallels the Housatonic River here, is central to Kent, which is important scenically and historically,'' said Claire Murphy, a vice president of the trust. ''And we thought, 'If the suburban sprawl happened here, there goes the town'.'' Kent (population 3,000, with 300 belonging to the trust) attracts tourists with promotion by the Litchfield Hills Travel Council. ''A world as nature intended'' is what the brochure says. ''Unspoiled, unhurried, untroubled, uncrowded, undiscovered, unequalled, unforgettable.''</p>
        <p>Bicycling, canoeing, rafting, hay, sleigh and horse-drawn carriage rides as well as trips to amusement parks, vineyards, farms and forests are advertised, along with clothing and ice cream shops, a video store and an inn in Kent.</p>
        <p>But it is the trust's credo that protected land is essential. The organization attempts ''to achieve a balance between the conservation and development needs of a viable community'' in the words of the trust's recent bulletin. ''So that houses are not lined up like little soldiers, with gas stations and McDonalds along the road. We want those in our commercial zone,'' Ms. Murphy added. ''It is important to enter and exit our village in the midst of open country. That is our identity.''</p>
        <p>In six years, the trust's 12-member board raised $800,000 to buy 135 acres of farmland and cornfields along 3.5 miles, ''and fix it up and hold it in trust,'' Ms. Murphy said.</p>
        <p>Ms. LuPone's concert is the organization's first real benefit. General admission tickets (860-927-3936) cost $40; $1,000 ticket holders, called benefactors, are invited to a pre-performance reception at the home of Faye and Jim Preston; Mr. Preston is the chief executive officer of the Avon Products company.</p>
        <p>When Juilliard's first graduating drama class evolved into the still-existing Acting Company in 1972, giving full seasons of classics, contemporary plays and musicals, countrywide as well as on Broadway, Ms. LuPone was fortified with the irreplaceable, rigorous experience that informs her work as a performing artist of uncommon range and depth.</p>
        <p>Chekhov, Saroyan, Sheridan, Gorky, Shakespeare and John Gay alternated in the young actress's repertory. Side trips to the explosive terrain of David Mamet as well as appearances in the early days of the Yale Cabaret and Hartford Stage nurtured the temperament of a star in ascent and the adaptability of an ensemble player.</p>
        <p>As the chosen Evita, she was not known as a singer, but the musical's director, Harold Prince, was known for long-shot casting that usually worked. That one critic called her performance ''colorless'' marked the beginning of a series of obstacles Ms. LuPone has transcended, emerging renewed, award winning (a Tony for ''Evita'') and literally enriched. (A $1 million settlement from Andrew Lloyd Webber for reneging on the ''Sunset Boulevard'' Broadway contract paid for some luxuries of living in Kent.)</p>
        <p>The centering of her life, the having of a life, distanced from the hysteria of the business there's no business like has been a curative for such blows as Madonna's movie ''Evita,'' Bernadette Peters' landing Annie in the upcoming Broadway revival of ''Annie Get Your Gun'' and the failure to get a Tony nomination for her rending performance in last season's ''Old Neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>Ms. LuPone -- the great-grandniece of opera's legendary Adelina Patti -- was born to play Maria Callas; she can negotiate coloratura leaps and, with interpretive flair, moves close to ballads as lieder. But she was passed over in various aborted television versions of the incendiary Callas's life. Finally Ms. LuPone was asked to play Callas, the soprano who was dubbed La Divina, in ''Master Class,'' after Zoe Caldwell, by the producer Robert Whitehead in 1996. .</p>
        <p>Why did she appear on the Tonys after the nominating committee ignored her performance in ''Old Neighborhood''?</p>
        <p>''I am here to thank and to honor Rosie,'' she said of Rosie O'Donnell, the host of the awards. When Ms. LuPone was invited to appear on Ms. O'Donnell's television show, Ms. LuPone said, ''They told me 'You can't come on if you don't sing.' That was an ultimatum. I hate that and I called Rosie personally and said, 'You have to understand why I don't want to sing. It's not all I do with my career. Right now I'm in a play.' She understood that and she allowed me to come on and not sing.''</p>
        <p>The world of theater as opposed to the glitz of Broadway influences Ms. LuPone's choices. After ''Evita,'' she turned down Lady Macbeth at Lincoln Center, flew to Minneapolis to play Rosalind in ''As You Like It.'' Then she went to a small Off Broadway theater for a small role in ''Edmond,'' by Mr. Mamet. Two movies are coming up: ''Cherry Pink,'' to be directed by Jason Alexander, and Spike Lee's ''Summer of Sam.''</p>
        <p>Ms. LuPone and Mr. Johnston -- an assistant camera operator on television when they were married in 1988, now ''a gentleman chicken farmer'' -- live on 26 acres with springs, a pond and a pool, two barns and a woodshed as well as 21 chickens ''who are freaked out by two dogs,'' she said. ''One breeding hen just hatched five beautiful chicks.'' Add a rabbit, wild turkeys, ''a killer parrot.'' All that and ''a little boy growing up,'' she said.</p>
        <p>It is no accident that ''Ain't Nobody Here But Us Chickens,'' a swing song by Alex Kramer and Joan Whitney, is to be included in the Kent Land Trust benefit show, along with original material. Composers include Rupert Holmes, Jimmy Webb, Ricki Lee Jones -- and a touch of Sondheim.</p>
        <p>''I like to tell a story when I sing, be it a rock song or a show tune,'' Ms. LuPone said. ''So the songs were chosen from a series about women who are talking about, singing about, their success, their failures, their confusion. That's where we're going.''</p>
        <p>''I walked onstage as an actress in 'Evita' and I came out as a singer,'' she mused. ''But I didn't know how to sing. Now I've learned that I'm not a belter.''</p>
        <p>Since her triumph in 1987 as Reno Sweeney in a new version of Cole Porter's ''Anything Goes,'' her name has been linked with Ethel Merman's, an association since reinforced by Ms. LuPone's one-night-only benefit performance this year in ''Annie, Get Your Gun'' at the Vivian Beaumont Theater at Lincoln Center. ''But Merman was not a belter. That's a misconception,'' Ms. LuPone added. ''A belter yells. A belter howls. She has complete control of that instrument and now I'm starting to learn about voice placement, about how to sing correctly. I've come full circle.''</p>
        <p>Lonny Price, who directed Ms. LuPone as the ''oversexed'' socialite Vera in an Encores staging of ''Pal Joey'' and as the illiterate and ingenuous Annie Oakley, observed: ''There are two Patti LuPones and they influence each other, and there's nothing either or both cannot do, and do it better than anyone in musical theater.</p>
        <p>''As Annie Oakley she strode onto the stage as if she owned it, radiating the unbridled joy of musicals, full of confidence, power, fun and the innocence people don't know is inside of her. Then she returned to the brassy persona, tough and bawdy. She was heartbreakingly wonderful.</p>
        <p>''Patti is a stage animal and she is of the land.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
