<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mining for Nuggets Of Financial Data</title>
    <meta content="21EDGA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980623T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Korman, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DA163CF932A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mining for Nuggets Of Financial Data</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD KORMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Korman, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Guide to interpreting Securities and Exchange Commission's Edgar, online database of corporate filings; cartoon (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you are after the important dope on a public company, set aside the glossy annual report and the spin-doctored announcements. The really telling stuff is often in the filings to the Securities and Exchange Commission, where the company has to come clean or risk a securities fraud suit, or worse.</p>
        <p>Since 1995, getting at those filings has become much easier for investors, thanks to the commission's Electronic Data Gathering, Analysis and Retrieval system, known as Edgar, which is available on the Internet at www.sec.gov.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you are after the important dope on a public company, set aside the glossy annual report and the spin-doctored announcements. The really telling stuff is often in the filings to the Securities and Exchange Commission, where the company has to come clean or risk a securities fraud suit, or worse.</p>
        <p>Since 1995, getting at those filings has become much easier for investors, thanks to the commission's Electronic Data Gathering, Analysis and Retrieval system, known as Edgar, which is available on the Internet at www.sec.gov.</p>
        <p>But just as public education has not wiped out illiteracy, easy access to dense, dry S.E.C. documents does not make them easy to decipher. To the uninitiated, Edgar can seem an immense haystack of boilerplate, arcana and gobbledygook, in which the valuable needles of telling information can be especially hard to find.</p>
        <p>Mary Ellen Bates, who teaches corporate employees to find competitor information in S.E.C. filings, calls annual 10K's ''quintessential overload documents.'' ''It's all there, but it's buried,'' she said. ''It's almost too rich.'' Less well-known forms can be even more forbidding.</p>
        <p>Once an investor learns how to hack through the semantic camouflage, though, the payoff can be great. A savvy Edgar reader might spot questionable policies, hidden vulnerabilities and ticking time bombs before they make news and bite unsuspecting stockholders.</p>
        <p>It takes practice to become proficient at mining Edgar. But even the casual investor can save a great deal of time by recognizing details, phrases and sections where the most interesting tidbits are likely to lurk.</p>
        <p>Of course, companies don't always report the most telling information in the places you would expect. For example, the part of a 10K marked ''Liquidity and Capital Resources'' is usually a bland section demonstrating that the company has enough money to continue operating. But in the SMC Corporation's 1996 report, something very unusual turned up there: Capital expenditures of $11.1 million, including a $3.8 million corporate jet -- a lot of money for a luxury motor coach maker whose entire operating cash flow that year was only $4.6 million.</p>
        <p>Naturally, it is impractical to read every word of every filing from hundreds of companies when first scanning for interesting businesses. Experts suggest developing a short list of target companies and then reading the Edgar filings on them.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. filings are becoming less off-putting as the commission gradually forces companies to write their reports in plain English.</p>
        <p>Beginning in October, companies must submit easy-reading cover pages, business summaries and risk factors. The greater challenge lies in ''getting people to the document,'' says Nancy M. Smith of the S.E.C.</p>
        <p>Here are some examples of places to look in S.E.C. filings for signals of potential trouble or strength.</p>
        <p>MISMATCHED NUMBERS  Even a cursory glance at income statements and balance sheets in a company's 10K report can turn up curious figures. On March 31, a report for the 1997 fiscal year by FPA Medical Management, a medical-practice manager in San Diego, showed accounts receivable doubling from the year before and positive operating income in a year when cash flow was negative, signs that something -- the accounting or the business -- may be amiss.</p>
        <p>The numbers in the 10K were published in time for investors to bolt before the stock tumbled to 93.75 cents from $14. ''If you are looking for warning signs, look for confusing, contradictory numbers and ignore the spin from management,'' said John Ransom, an analyst for Raymond James.</p>
        <p>A BULL IN THE CORNER OFFICE The Tultex Corporation, a maker of cotton sportswear, is losing money, and its stock is way off its 52-week high. But S.E.C. filings show that one investor apparently hasn't given up hope -- the company's chief executive, Charles W. Davies Jr. During Tultex's decline, he has been buying blocks of the company's stock on the open market, paying $4.50 to $5.50 a share. Each time he did, the assistant corporate secretary filed a Form 4 that shows up in Edgar.</p>
        <p>PAST EMPLOYMENT Proxy statements filed in Edgar include biographies of people who are up for election as directors. Judging by Amcor Capital's proxy, Dale P. Paisley probably can't get a letter of recommendation from Travelmax International, where he was chief financial officer for 18 months. Amcor, a real estate and agricultural company in Coachella, Calif., discloses in its proxy that Travelmax is suing Mr. Paisley and others for ''fraud, misappropriation of funds, breach of fiduciary duty and unjustified enrichment.'' It goes on to say that Mr. Paisley, a former partner at Coopers &amp; Lybrand, denies Amcor's accusations, which involve an alleged attempt to illegally acquire large blocks of Amcor stock very cheaply,  and believes he has been released from liability for his conduct.</p>
        <p>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST Go straight to the phrase ''related party transactions'' for a quick read on a company's determination to stay free of suspicious entanglements with shareholders and directors.</p>
        <p>In the 10K for 1997 filed by Sulcus Hospitality Technologies, a software maker in Greensburg, Pa., the company notes that it leases its main office from a trust established by Jeffrey S. Ratner, a principal shareholder and former director. When the company says ''these leases were not the result of arms-length negotiations,'' it means no disinterested party has checked to see if the terms are fair to both sides.</p>
        <p>FAMILY TIES In publicly traded companies where a single family controls much of the stock, the line between shareholder and family interest can be hard to draw.</p>
        <p>The Zapata Corporation in Houston has been controlled by its chairman, Malcolm I. Glazer, in recent years. While analysts have wondered whether the company's strategy hangs together -- it diversified from marine products and food service into Internet magazines and plans to change its name to Zap -- the company's 10K filings leave no doubt that the Glazer family does. Malcolm's sons Avram, Bryan and Edward are directors, and Avram is chief executive; Malcolm's daughter Darcie is employed by Zapata as an investment analyst.</p>
        <p>OVERDUE NOTICES PILING UP Late filings appear with the letters NT beforethe form name and can sometimes presage accounting trouble. Think New Ideas, an Internet advertising company, filed notice of a late quarterly report on May 15. When the NT-10Q appeared on May 21, it came with upward restatements of expenses for the quarter ended March 31, 1997. Then, on May 27, the company reported that it had dismissed its auditor in February.</p>
        <p>COURT TANGLES The ''Legal Proceedings'' section in S.E.C. documents will note problems that could drain money and distract managers' attention, says John Bajkowski, a financial analyst with the American Association of Individual Investors.</p>
        <p>Neuromedical Systems, which uses computerized scans to improve cervical cancer tests, faces the formidable task of convincing doctors, technicians and insurers to accept its methods.</p>
        <p>But lately, the Suffern, N.Y., company has been waging an increasingly costly multifront war in the courts against two rivals, Neopath and Cytyc. The patent infringement, business interference and unfair competition suits probably won't have a material financial effect, the company says in its 10K, but, as they drag on, the company says costs during 1998 ''could be significant.''</p>
        <p>CHUTZPAH  Personality can seep through the boilerplate format of S.E.C. filings, and smaller companies sometimes reveal themselves in unusual ways. Paradise Inc. in Plant City, Fla., strikes a note of self-congratulation in its annual 10K.</p>
        <p>The company writes that it ''knows of no other manufacturer in the Western Hemisphere'' that claims as big a share of the candied fruit business.</p>
        <p>But self-confidence only goes so far. The report also says that as of March, Paradise has failed to comply with new minimum requirements for listing on Nasdaq's market for small-cap stocks.</p>
        <p>An Edgar Scorecard</p>
        <p>Successful navigation of the Securities and Exchange Commission's Edgar database of corporate filings depends on recognizing which forms contain which information. Here is a menagerie of the most common filings from publicly traded companies.</p>
        <p>10-K The official version of a company's annual report, with a comprehensive overview of the business; due within 45 days after the company's fiscal year ends.</p>
        <p>10-Q An abridged version of the 10-K, filed quarterly for the first three quarters of a company's fiscal year.</p>
        <p>8-K If anything significant happens that should be reported before the next 10-Q or 10-K rolls around, the company files one of these.</p>
        <p>12b-25 Request for a deadline extension to file a required report, like a 10-K or 10-Q. When the late report is ultimately filed, NT is appended to the report's name.</p>
        <p>13-D Notice that someone has acquired 5 percent or more of the stock of a company. Must be filed within 10 days; changes in holdings after that call for an amended 13-D.</p>
        <p>13-F Quarterly report of stock holdings by institutions managing $100 million.</p>
        <p>14D-1 Notice of a tender offer for at least 5 percent of a company's stock by anyone other than the company itself.</p>
        <p>S-1 Registration form for new securities, most often initial or secondary public offerings. Variants are used for companies already reporting to the S.E.C. (S-2, S-3), or in connections with mergers and stock swaps (S-4), employee stock plans (S-8), or for real estate investment trusts (S-11). Foreign companies use similar forms beginning with F; for example, F-6 is used to register American depository receipts.</p>
        <p>Proxy statement Information and ballot materials for shareholder votes, including election of directors and approval of mergers and acquisitions when required.</p>
        <p>Forms 3, 4 and 5 Directors, officers and owners of more than 10 percent of a company's stock report their initial purchases on Form 3 and subsequent purchases or sales on Form 4; they file an annual statement of their holdings on Form 5.</p>
        <p>INVESTING IT  Correction:  June 23, 1998, Tuesday  An article in the Money and Business section on Sunday about companies' filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission referred incorrectly at some points to the company that is suing Dale P. Paisley, a director of the Amcor Capital Corporation, which disclosed the suit. The lawsuit is by Mr. Paisley's former employer, Travelmax International (which has changed its name to Network Holdings International Inc.), not by Amcor.</p>
        <p>The suit accuses Mr. Paisley of having illegally tried to acquire Travelmax stock, not Amcor stock; Mr. Paisley denies the accusations and believes Travelmax has released him from liability. Amcor has not sued Mr. Paisley or accused him of anything in its S.E.C. filings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 23, 1998, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in the Money and Business section on Sunday about companies' filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission referred incorrectly at some points to the company that is suing Dale P. Paisley, a director of the Amcor Capital Corporation, which disclosed the suit. The lawsuit is by Mr. Paisley's former employer, Travelmax International (which has changed its name to Network Holdings International Inc.), not by Amcor.</p>
        <p>The suit accuses Mr. Paisley of having illegally tried to acquire Travelmax stock, not Amcor stock; Mr. Paisley denies the accusations and believes Travelmax has released him from liability. Amcor has not sued Mr. Paisley or accused him of anything in its S.E.C. filings.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
