<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Good Pitching Has Yanks Halfway to 100</title>
    <meta content="21YANK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D9143CF932A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Good Pitching Has Yanks Halfway to 100</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, June 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ronald Reagan was voted into the White House the last year the Yankees won 100 or more games, in 1980. Don Mattingly never played on a pinstriped team that won 100 games, nor did Dave Righetti. No easy feat, 100 victories.</p>
        <p>But the 1998 Yankees already are halfway there after beating Cleveland by 5-3 this afternoon. David Wells allowed two runs in eight innings, improving his record to 9-2 and the Yankees' record to 50-17.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ronald Reagan was voted into the White House the last year the Yankees won 100 or more games, in 1980. Don Mattingly never played on a pinstriped team that won 100 games, nor did Dave Righetti. No easy feat, 100 victories.</p>
        <p>But the 1998 Yankees already are halfway there after beating Cleveland by 5-3 this afternoon. David Wells allowed two runs in eight innings, improving his record to 9-2 and the Yankees' record to 50-17.</p>
        <p>The Yankees became the first team in the major leagues with 50 victories this season, despite playing the fewest games of any team as well as the fewest home games (31). They have had six postponements, because of rain and the closing of Yankee Stadium after a 500-pound expansion joint fell. The Atlanta Braves are 50-24 after defeating Montreal by 5-1 tonight.</p>
        <p>''We've been pretty impressive,'' said Chuck Knoblauch, the Yankees' second baseman. ''The whole team. The whole deal.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees have won four of their last eight, their pace slowing somewhat in the midst of what figures to be the most challenging two weeks of their season, with games in Baltimore and Cleveland and against the Braves and the Mets. The Yankees are playing without Bernie Williams, sidelined with a sprained knee perhaps the next two weeks.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the Yankees' winning percentage is .746; they would win 121 games if they continue this pace and would shatter the modern-day single-season record of 116 victories. Should the Yankees win 47 of their remaining 95 games -- just less than half -- they would finish the season 97-65.</p>
        <p>A hundred victories seems inevitable, particularly because the Yankees' starting pitching is so sound, so deep.</p>
        <p>With Wells's outing today, the Yankees' pitching rotation has turned in 17 consecutive starts of five and one-third innings or more; only twice in 39 games since May 6 has a Yankees starter failed to last five innings.</p>
        <p>Wells's performance today may have been his best since his perfect game on May 17, he agreed. His curveball dived across the strike zone, and his fastball was explosive.</p>
        <p>It may be, Wells said, that the shoulder tendinitis that bothered him for two weeks is gone for good. Pitchers with arm ailments usually cannot control what they throw, and today, catcher Jorge Posada set his target, inside or outside, and Wells hit it constantly, expertly. Wells struck out eight, walking none.</p>
        <p>''He had good stuff,'' said Chad Curtis, the Yankees' center fielder. ''But it seems like every time I've seen him, he's had good stuff.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees scored two runs in the fourth inning, two more in the fifth, and with a 4-1 lead and his ninth victory in sight, Wells seemed to bear down in the middle innings, retiring Cleveland in order in the fourth, six and seventh. Three times he struck out David Justice, the Indian All-Star. Later, Wells spoke of the challenge of facing the Cleveland lineup.</p>
        <p>''I wish I could pitch against those guys all the time,'' he said. ''They bring out the best in me, I bring out the best in them.''</p>
        <p>Wells walked to the mound for the eighth inning, the top of his jersey flapping open two buttons down. He knew this would be his last inning. It turned out to be his finest.</p>
        <p>David Bell led off and lined a hit to right-center, but he numbly tried for a double and, after falling, was caught in a rundown. The Indians scored their second run with two outs, and with a runner at first, the slugger Jim Thome came to the plate as the potential tying run. Thome had homered twice on Friday night in Cleveland's 7-4 victory.</p>
        <p>''Thome is a scary hitter right now,'' Curtis said. ''You throw him a fastball and he can hit it out. You throw him a curve and he can hit it out.''</p>
        <p>Wells threw him a curve with the count two balls and one strike, and Thome took it. Strike two. Wells spun another curve, and Thome fouled it off. ''I don't know how,'' Wells said.</p>
        <p>Wells then fired a fastball over the outside corner, Thome hacked at it, and missed. It was, Torre mused later, a big pitch, a big out, in the crucial part of the game.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees have made the crucial plays, got the big outs, got the big hits, in winning 50 games.</p>
        <p>''It's been a great start,'' said David Cone, the Yankee pitcher. ''Early on, we banged the ball around and scored lots of runs. Lately, we've been pitching much better.''</p>
        <p>Throughout, their defense has been outstanding. The Yankees have allowed five unearned runs since April 30.</p>
        <p>''We've been winning all sorts of ways,'' Cone said.</p>
        <p>Halfway to 100, and it is mid-June.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DEREK JETER, in his second game since coming off the disabled list, made a throwing error in the third inning, only his third error of the season and his first throwing error of the year. Jeter said he still felt out of sync. . . . The Yankees made two errors; it was their first multi-error game since May 20. . . . TINO MARTINEZ, whose batting average has plummeted nearly 50 points since he was hit on the shoulder blade by ARMANDO BENITEZ on May 19, had a double in four at-bats Saturday, driving in a run. ''He's not healthy,'' Manager JOE TORRE said. ''But it's going to get better gradually. His shoulder's bothering him -- something that three hits would do a lot to help.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
