<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Swedish Suntan Prescription</title>
    <meta content="21CONV$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1DE163CF932A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Swedish Suntan Prescription</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES G. COBB</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HAVING developed some eye-catching curves, Volvo is going topless.</p>
        <p>A C70 convertible will go on sale early next month at a base price of $43,570, a neighborhood that the Mercedes CLK320 Cabriolet, which arrives in the fall, will also inhabit. Options will push fully equipped C70's to $48,000, making it the most costly Volvo ever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HAVING developed some eye-catching curves, Volvo is going topless.</p>
        <p>A C70 convertible will go on sale early next month at a base price of $43,570, a neighborhood that the Mercedes CLK320 Cabriolet, which arrives in the fall, will also inhabit. Options will push fully equipped C70's to $48,000, making it the most costly Volvo ever.</p>
        <p>The C70 is Volvo's first convertible since the plastic-body Volvo Sport of 1956, and it is a stylish showcase for a company trying to break out of its safe, staid box. The top goes up or down at the push of a button, with no latches to release or covers to snap in place. Touching another button lowers all four windows simultaneously.</p>
        <p>The well-made top has a glass rear window with a built-in defroster, but its thick rear ''pillars'' make the C70 -- so svelte with the top down -- look a bit stubby. The bulk of that top, along with the car's high rear deck and smallish back window, also impede visibility, usually so good in Volvos.</p>
        <p>Like the coupe, the convertible is elegantly appointed -- the test car had unusual, but pleasing, suede trim. The back seat was quite roomy for two adults whether the top was up or down. They'd better travel light, though: The mechanisms for the elaborate power top steal much of the trunk space.</p>
        <p>Twin roll bars pop up behind the rear head restraints if a sensor detects that the car may roll over.</p>
        <p>While the C70 convertible looks like the coupe, it uses the 2.4-liter five-cylinder from the S70 GLT. With a light-pressure turbo-charger, it pumps out 190 horsepower, 46 less than the coupe. The soft-top car comes only with a four-speed automatic transmission, and its standard tires and wheels are smaller, 16-inch versions. With less power and an extra 200 pounds of bracing, the convertible is speedy, but does not have the coupe's neck-snapping takeoff.</p>
        <p>While Volvo boasts that the convertible is reinforced with tough Boron steel, in addition to a ''safety cage'' that helps to protect occupants in a crash, the C70 does not feel as stiff and strong as, say, the less expensive BMW 328. The test car had no rattles or squeaks, but slight vibrations could be felt through the floor pan, doors and steering wheel, and the suspension was bouncy. Quick stops caused awkward shudders.</p>
        <p>While the coupe can't figure out whether it's a lady or a scamp, the convertible doesn't pretend to be a sports machine. It's an upscale, head-turning cruiser -- an impress-the-neighbors alternative to the Chrysler Sebring. Alas, you could impress them with two Sebrings for the tab of one C70.</p>
        <p>INSIDE TRACK:  High style, high price.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
