<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Figures Are Released On Jail Injury Claims</title>
    <meta content="21JAIL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Overtime</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Absenteeism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pozzi, Rocco a (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Callahan, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7DD1E3DF932A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1317" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Figures Are Released On Jail Injury Claims</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM CALLAHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Callahan, Tom</byline>
      <dateline>VALHALA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Westchester County Acting Corrections Comr Rocco A Pozzi releases figures claiming that average of 120 of 779 correction officers were unable to work in 1997 because of injury at cost of more than $6 million in overtime pay; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the latest salvo of an increasingly heated labor dispute between the county and correction officers at the County Jail here, the Spano administration claimed last week that every day last year an average of 120 of the 779 correction officers were unable to work because of injury.</p>
        <p>Officials estimate that this cost the county more than $6 million of the $9.8 million in overtime salaries paid at the jail last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the latest salvo of an increasingly heated labor dispute between the county and correction officers at the County Jail here, the Spano administration claimed last week that every day last year an average of 120 of the 779 correction officers were unable to work because of injury.</p>
        <p>Officials estimate that this cost the county more than $6 million of the $9.8 million in overtime salaries paid at the jail last year.</p>
        <p>They proposed changing the way disability claims have been handled since 1989 by eliminating a controversial appendix to the municipal law. In addition, the county plans to sue workers for back pay if their injuries are determined not to be job related.</p>
        <p>''I am very concerned,'' County Executive Andrew J. Spano said. ''There are officers who come in day to day and do an exceptional job. And there are people with job-related injuries who should be out. Our problem is with a situation that has gotten out of hand. It is draining millions of dollars from the county, and that money cannot be applied to direct services.''</p>
        <p>Acting Corrections Commissioner Rocco A. Pozzi added: ''No sane person can look at this system and say that it is not being abused. We have suspicions that more than a few of these injuries are questionable.'' Without giving names, he cited the case of one worker out for 182 days after reportedly injuring his thumb opening a security gate. In another example, an officer missed 199 days of work after claiming he hurt his back while moving a fan.</p>
        <p>Members of the Westchester County Correction Officers Benevolent Association have been working at the jail without a contract since late 1995. Union officials angrily rejected these latest charges and accused the Spano administration of trying to cut costs at the expense of workers.</p>
        <p>''The jail is a difficult and dangerous work environment,'' said Joseph Spano, president of the union and not related to the County Executive. ''By bringing up the job-injury issue, they are trying to apply pressure to make us come to the negotiating table and surrender our benefits. Under this administration, there has been an effort to break the back of this organization. They have blatantly violated contractual agreements, court orders and policy agreements.''</p>
        <p>The union leader said his union is currently suing the county in State Supreme Court in White Plains over several issues, including the right of senior workers to select their posts and paying workers who have been suspended.</p>
        <p>At the crux of the job-injury dispute is Appendix B of a 1989 contract with the union that relates to Section 207c of the State Municipal Law. This appendix allows workers who claim they are injured on the job to receive their salaries, tax free, until a hearing can be held to determine if the injury was job related. Officials claim that Westchester is the only county in the United States with such a clause.</p>
        <p>Correction workers are not the only law enforcement officers affected by Section 207c. The statute covers ''any sheriff, undersheriff, deputy sheriff or correction officer of the sheriff's department of any county or any members of a police force of any county, city of less than one million population, town or village.''</p>
        <p>Ordinarily, when filing a 207c claim, the injured worker would use his or her sick time until a hearing is held. But appendix B makes that unnecessary. The clause says, ''It is presumed that an accident which occurs in the course of employment also has arisen out of the employment.'' All an officer has to do is say that the injury was job related and he can continue to receive his salary.</p>
        <p>''In other places, the burden of proof is on the individual claiming 207c,'' R. L. Davis, chief of operations at the jail, said. ''By using up their sick time, they are gambling that the injury will be ruled valid and they will be granted disability benefits. But here the burden of proof is on the county, and it can drag on for months because of the problem of scheduling timely hearings.''</p>
        <p>The union and county must each agree to the arbitrators who hear the disability cases. The county accuses the union of dragging its feet in scheduling hearings, agreeing only to two a week on average. The union says there were 27 hearings during a one-month period last year. Any delay, Joseph Spano said, is caused by the county's ''favor shopping,'' or seeking to use only arbitrators who will give them favorable decisions.</p>
        <p>Injured workers must be replaced by other workers, who are paid overtime. The Valhalla center includes three components: the jail, a penitentiary where inmates serve sentences of up to a year and a unit for women. To cover all three components during a 3-shift, 24-hour day, 441 officers are needed. The inmate population is now 1,450. The jail holds a maximum of 1,600.</p>
        <p>''I suspect that when they put in Appendix B it looked benign until somebody began to abuse it,'' Luke Smith, Deputy Corrections Commissioner, said. ''We had labor problems here in the mid-90's. There was no contract then, and what followed was an explosion of job-related injuries.''</p>
        <p>Joseph Spano denied this. ''Our members work in an environment where they are subject to physical injury every day,'' he said. ''They have to deal with inmates spitting on them and throwing urine and feces at them. I'm familiar with the numbers the county is using. But they have ways to make those numbers look good for them. What I have is officers who have to wait two to three months for surgery and therapy.''</p>
        <p>He attributed the high overtime costs to the county's decision to house 195 Federal inmates, for which the county is reimbursed. He described new contract negotiations as going nowhere since the county's latest offer will ''gut'' the protection of 207c along with other benefits obtained in past contracts. ''We negotiated the linking of 207c with workers compensation because we need the best protection,'' the union leader said.</p>
        <p>The one thing both sides agree on is that the morale of officers at the jail is poor. They disagree on the impact this is having on safety. ''The jail is not as safe as it was prior to the administration eliminating 27 posts earlier this year,'' Joseph Spano said. ''When you combine that with the number of problems there, it takes the focus away from what we should be doing and that impacts on safety.''</p>
        <p>County Executive Spano said: ''I don't understand what he is talking about. We cut those posts with the consent of an objective evaluation by the State Department of Corrections. They agreed that it would not compromise safety. And for the first time, we are making sure that all officers will be equipped with silent body alarms.''</p>
        <p>The next round of the dispute will most likely be played out in the courts. The administration received permission from the Board of Legislators on May 18 to bring legal action for the first time against a correction officer who was found not to have a work-related injury. They are seeking the return of the $32,000 he was paid during the seven months he was off.</p>
        <p>The union has a court hearing scheduled for Aug. 13 in which it is seeking to jail county officials for violating prior agreements with the workers. ''We are being forced to litigate everything,'' Joseph Spano said. ''I don't see this being resolved anytime soon.''</p>
        <p>The County Executive was more optimistic. ''We're dealing with it as best we can,'' he said. ''I talk to Joe Spano all the time. There is no animosity here. We are both doing our jobs.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
