<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sarah Lawrence Festival</title>
    <meta content="21MUSI$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sherman, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5DF113DF932A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sarah Lawrence Festival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sherman, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Sherman column on upcoming musical events in Westchester County, NY, including Summer Music Festival at Sarah Lawrence College; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Summer Music Festival at Sarah Lawrence College in Yonkers, reinstated last year, returns next Sunday at 4 P.M. with the first of six faculty recitals at Marshall Field House. Under the direction of Sung-Rai Sohn, first violinist of the resident Laurentian String Quartet, the festival is more than a performance cycle. As the director put it, ''This is a lively chamber music training program for serious musicians between the ages of 8 and 20, with a faculty of distinguished international artists.''</p>
        <p>At the opening concert, Mr. Sohn  will play an all-Brahms program with the pianist Tammy Lum, a Hong Kong native who teaches at Nyack College. Later recitals will be presented by the violinists Larry Watson and Ronald Gorevic, the cellist Chungsun Kim and the pianists David Korevaar and Natalia Krassii. There will also be four free student concerts in Reisinger Hall on the first four Fridays in July at 3 P.M. The number to call for tickets is 395-2447.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Summer Music Festival at Sarah Lawrence College in Yonkers, reinstated last year, returns next Sunday at 4 P.M. with the first of six faculty recitals at Marshall Field House. Under the direction of Sung-Rai Sohn, first violinist of the resident Laurentian String Quartet, the festival is more than a performance cycle. As the director put it, ''This is a lively chamber music training program for serious musicians between the ages of 8 and 20, with a faculty of distinguished international artists.''</p>
        <p>At the opening concert, Mr. Sohn  will play an all-Brahms program with the pianist Tammy Lum, a Hong Kong native who teaches at Nyack College. Later recitals will be presented by the violinists Larry Watson and Ronald Gorevic, the cellist Chungsun Kim and the pianists David Korevaar and Natalia Krassii. There will also be four free student concerts in Reisinger Hall on the first four Fridays in July at 3 P.M. The number to call for tickets is 395-2447.</p>
        <p>The Sundays on the Island series continues today at noon at Le Refuge Inn on City Island. The program features Yuval Waldman playing Mozart's Fifth Violin Concerto and Wolfram Kossell playing the Boccherini Cello Concerto in B flat, both with the 21-member City Island Baroque Ensemble. Next Sunday and through July, the weekly recitals offer chamber music, with visits by the violin-piano duo of Yosuke Kawasaki and Ilan Rechtman, the Essex String Quartet and other ensemble artists. For concert information, call (212) 721-7711. For directions to the inn at 620 City Island Avenue in the Bronx, call (718) 885-2478.</p>
        <p>Also in the Bronx, there is free jazz today at 3 P.M. at a summer solstice concert celebrating American music in the New York Botanical Garden at 200th Street and Southern Boulevard. The flutist Dave Valentin heads a backup quartet on bass, drums, piano and percussion. For more details, call (718) 601-7399.</p>
        <p>At Caramoor in Katonah, the resident St. Luke's Chamber Ensemble performs all six of the Bach Brandenburg Concertos in the Venetian Theater today at 4:30 P.M. in the Venetian Theater. A preconcert talk starts at 4.</p>
        <p>The first of the summer's Introductions series follows on Thursday at 4:15 P.M. in the form of a string quartet master class taught by Peter Oundjian, Caramoor's artistic director and former first violinist of the Tokyo String Quartet. On Friday at 8 P.M. a Rossini evening in the Spanish Courtyard features the soprano Vivica Genaux, acclaimed for her Met debut in ''The Barber of Seville.'' She will sing selections from that opera and other Rossini favorites, accompanied on the piano by Will Crutchfield, director of the Bel Canto at Caramoor cycle.</p>
        <p>New to the Caramoor festival this summer is the term artist in residence, which refers to distinguished guests who will appear at both Saturday and Sunday concerts. The first celebrity is the clarinetist Richard Stoltzman, who will play the Mozart Clarinet Concerto with the Orchestra of St. Luke's next Saturday at 8:30 P.M. in the Venetian Theater, and who will return next Sunday at 4:30 P.M. to join the violinist and violist Arnold Steinhardt, the cellist Peter Wiley and the pianist Gilbert Kalish in Trios by Mozart, Brahms and Bartok. Also on the program next Saturday are Schubert's Fourth Symphony and the Suite from Stravinsky's ''Pulcinella'' Ballet, with Mr. Oundjian conducting the Orchestra of St. Luke's. For tickets, call 232-1252.</p>
        <p>For a combined total of 48 summers, the Westchester Concert Singers and the Westchester Choral Society have invited those who want to sing or listen to choral music to take part in informal readings.</p>
        <p>For the Society, the 20th anniversary Summer Sings begin Tuesday at 8 P.M. at the Hoff-Barthelson School in Scarsdale with the music director, Lyndon Woodside, guiding the audience through ''A German Requiem'' by Brahms. Daniel Paget, Jack Goodwin, Robert Bass and Johannes Somary take over on the next four Tuesdays, conducting the Faure Requiem, Mendelssohn's ''Elijah,'' the Mozart Requiem and Handel's ''Judas Maccabaeus,'' respectively. Scores and refreshments will be provided for an admission fee of $7 at the door. For details, call 793-4714.</p>
        <p>John Daly Goodwin, music director of the Concert Singers, presides over the opening of his ensemble's 28th season of Summer Sings on July 1 at 8 P.M. at the Mount Pleasant Public Library in Pleasantville. He will lead two French requiems, those by Durufle and Faure. Ludwig Sheffield, founding director of the chorus when it was the Pleasantville Cantata Singers, takes the podium on July 8 to lead the Vivaldi ''Gloria,'' and Bernard La Due and Timothy Lewis round out the readings on July 15 and 22 with the Mozart Requiem and Mendelssohn's ''Elijah,'' respectively. The information number is 769-2314.</p>
        <p>The Clearwater Great Hudson River Revival concludes today, running from 10 A.M. to dusk at Marist College in Poughkeepsie. There will be performances by Pete Seeger, Odetta, the David Amram Quartet, the Paul Winter Consort and a host of ethnic artists representing West African, Latin American, Bulgarian Gypsy and American Indian traditions. For directions, call (800) 677-5667.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
