<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Neediest Cases; Trying to Spot a Happy Place Through Worn Branches</title>
    <meta content="03neediest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1736752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haskell, Kari</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feaster, Janine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feaster, Saed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E0DE163EF930A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1093" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Neediest Cases; Trying to Spot a Happy Place Through Worn Branches</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KARI HASKELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haskell, Kari</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janine Feaster describes financial difficulties she has experienced doing her best to take care of her six-year-old son Saed, who has potentially fatal lung disease; New York Times Neediest Cases Fund and other organizations have helped Feaster; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A packed-up Christmas tree sat in a box opposite a stack of diapers and an oxygen tank in Janine Feaster's long hallway. She bought the tree seven years ago for $127; she joked recently that she would keep putting it up till it had one branch left, like the one in ''A Charlie Brown Christmas.''</p>
        <p>As for the oxygen, she was thankful that she has not had to use it for a while. The diapers, however, are another story -- even with 18 per pack, she cannot get enough of them from the local food pantry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A packed-up Christmas tree sat in a box opposite a stack of diapers and an oxygen tank in Janine Feaster's long hallway. She bought the tree seven years ago for $127; she joked recently that she would keep putting it up till it had one branch left, like the one in ''A Charlie Brown Christmas.''</p>
        <p>As for the oxygen, she was thankful that she has not had to use it for a while. The diapers, however, are another story -- even with 18 per pack, she cannot get enough of them from the local food pantry.</p>
        <p>Her 6-year-old son, Saed Lewis, who was born prematurely, is developmentally delayed and has a potentially fatal lung disease, bronchopulmonary dysplasia.</p>
        <p>''He's only fed milk,'' Ms. Feaster, 35, explained, sitting in the living room in her apartment in Harlem. As quickly as the milk passes through the feeding tube to his belly button, it seems Saed has already digested it and needs to be changed.</p>
        <p>''I triple the diapers sometimes, just to keep him dry,'' she said.</p>
        <p>When her son learns to eat solid food, she hopes that the diaper changes will be less frequent.</p>
        <p>But hope alone will not get him to that point. Just 1 pound 8 ounces at birth, he was on a ventilator until he was 3. Eating solid food will be just as big of a milestone as the day his tracheotomy tube was removed at age 4, or the moment he sat up for the first time at 2.</p>
        <p>Saed is undergoing occupational, physical and speech therapy at Public School 138, and Ms. Feaster is now advocating for food therapy to help him learn how to manage solids.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Feaster was earning $31,500 a year as a transportation security agent at La Guardia Airport, the salary did pay the bills. But when she was done with covering monthly expenses, there was a little left over to buy her ailing son a small toy, like a Barney purple dinosaur.</p>
        <p>And unlike the happy family Barney sings about in his theme song, the Feasters find themselves in a different place these days.</p>
        <p>She lost her job after she missed 130 days from work in two years because the home attendants -- provided through Medicaid, which also pays for her son's medications and medical visits -- did not show up.</p>
        <p>Her two daughters from a previous marriage, Nyasia, 18, and Tahkima McCleary, 16, baby-sat for Saed when it did not conflict with their school schedules. But every day she missed work was a lost wage, a smaller paycheck. At times, a weekly paycheck might be only $200 because of the days she took off after she used all her vacation and medical leaves.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the bills kept coming. The escalating costs for air-conditioning, an air purifier and a humidifier made her electric bill $300 some months. In the winter, she had to keep Saed from getting a cold. With lungs as fragile as his, even the slightest cough can be serious enough for him to need oxygen. The heating bill each month was $100.</p>
        <p>By last March, Ms. Feaster had failed to pay $715, her Section 8 share of the $1,180 rent to her landlord at the first of the month. ''I never intended not to pay,'' she said. ''I just wasn't working enough hours.''</p>
        <p>One month passed, then a second, then a third. The missed rents kept adding up. At the end of May, an eviction notice arrived.</p>
        <p>''The landlord, in all honesty, really didn't care that I have a son with special needs,'' Ms. Feaster said. ''The only thing they want is their money. Their job is to say 'pay.' ''</p>
        <p>Trying to juggle housing court, her son's care and the demands of her job put her further behind.</p>
        <p>''I was trying to get control, then another month was due,'' she said. ''The numbers every month just kept adding and adding.'' By October, she was behind $6,000 in rent. Then, to make matters worse, she lost her job.</p>
        <p>Help came from an unexpected place. During one of her son's medical visits, a nurse referred her to New Alternatives for Children, a member of the Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies. The federation is a beneficiary of The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>''Our biggest goal was to stabilize the home situation,'' said Angie Foster, a social worker from New Alternatives. The agency helped secure $1,500 from the Neediest Cases, as well as additional aid from the Legal Aid Society, the Metropolitan Council on Jewish Poverty, and the city's Department of Social Services to eliminate her debt.</p>
        <p>Unemployed, Ms. Feaster recently took a Civil Service exam in hopes of becoming a police officer outside Manhattan, perhaps in one of the boroughs or in Baltimore.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't born rich,'' she said. ''You learn how to adjust to bad times. You just learn how to get through them.''</p>
        <p>Previously recorded: $6,639,740.70  Recorded Tuesday: $63,527.00  Total: $6,703,267.70  Last year to date: $7,162,308.82</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to 4 Chase Metrotech Center, 7th Floor East, Lockbox 5193, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11245, or any of these organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE  285 Schermerhorn Street  Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS  191 Joralemon Street  Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK  1011 First Avenue  New York, N.Y. 10022</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY  105 East 22nd Street  New York, N.Y. 10010</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK  105 East 22nd Street  New York, N.Y. 10010</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES  281 Park Avenue South  New York, N.Y. 10010</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK  Church Street Station  P.O. Box 4100  New York, N.Y. 10261-4100</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>Donations may be made with a credit card by phone at (800) 381-0075 or online, courtesy of NYCharities.org, an Internet donations service, at www.nytimes.com/neediest or www.nycharities.org/neediest. For instructions on how to donate stock to the fund, call (212) 556-1137 or fax (212) 556-4450.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
