<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the 89th District, a Party Divided</title>
    <meta content="08NAOM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1421878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matusow, Naomi (Assemblywoman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DD153EF93BA3575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the 89th District, a Party Divided</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on incumbent Assemblywoman Naomi Matusow and White Plains political leader Adam Bradley, who is challenging her in Democratic primary in Westchester County's 89th Assembly District; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH less than a week to go until the Democratic primary, Naomi C. Matusow, the assemblywoman representing the 89th District, relaxed in the backyard of her North Castle home and clucked playfully to Sasha, a greyhound she adopted after the dog could no longer race. Sasha went out a winner, she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Matusow, 63, hopes to win her sixth straight election to the Assembly. She is facing a stiff challenge from Adam Bradley, a White Plains lawyer. Ms. Matusow, a 10-year incumbent, has not been challenged in a primary since 1992, when she was first elected to the seat. Mr. Bradley, a political leader in White Plains, has never run for office. Whoever wins the primary will win the seat, since no Republican has registered to run in November.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH less than a week to go until the Democratic primary, Naomi C. Matusow, the assemblywoman representing the 89th District, relaxed in the backyard of her North Castle home and clucked playfully to Sasha, a greyhound she adopted after the dog could no longer race. Sasha went out a winner, she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Matusow, 63, hopes to win her sixth straight election to the Assembly. She is facing a stiff challenge from Adam Bradley, a White Plains lawyer. Ms. Matusow, a 10-year incumbent, has not been challenged in a primary since 1992, when she was first elected to the seat. Mr. Bradley, a political leader in White Plains, has never run for office. Whoever wins the primary will win the seat, since no Republican has registered to run in November.</p>
        <p>The lack of a challenger is somewhat unusual, since the district is split between Democratic and Republican registered voters. Ms. Matusow's predecessor was a Republican, Peter M. Sullivan, who held the seat for 18 years. Ms. Matusow upset him in 1992, and she has defeated all challengers since then, by increasing margins.</p>
        <p>The district cuts a broad swath through northern and central Westchester, from Harrison and most of White Plains up through Bedford, Mount Kisco, New Castle, North Castle, Pound Ridge and Lewisboro.</p>
        <p>The race has involved hardball campaigning. It has strained political loyalties and highlighted divisions in the county Democratic Party, which is rife with infighting.</p>
        <p>Ms. Matusow is backed by state and county politicians and has endorsements from the state attorney general, Eliot Spitzer and Westchester's county executive, Andrew J. Spano. She is also endorsed by the major local unions. She has broad support in many of the Democratic committees in the affluent towns in the northern part of the district. She has a better-financed campaign and better name recognition, but Mr. Bradley has been campaigning hard the past month to introduce himself to voters.</p>
        <p>Though a newcomer to elective politics, Mr. Bradley is a savvy political player from the bare-knuckle world of White Plains politics. He sees a rare opportunity in the district, which, based on the 2000 census, has been redrawn to include a much larger portion of White Plains, his political base. It no longer includes Somers and North Salem, which were Matusow strongholds.</p>
        <p>The two opponents have similar platforms that include abortion rights, pro-environment and pro-union stances.</p>
        <p>Ms. Matusow is a lawyer and former math teacher with two grown sons. She cited a long, successful record of legislative accomplishments. She has waged successful fights for property tax relief, open-space preservation and assistance for the elderly, and money for education, school construction and libraries.</p>
        <p>Her legislative victories in the State Assembly include a bill passed banning assault weapons, a bill to require mandatory fingerprinting and background checks of school personnel, and a bill requiring mandatory reporting to the police of any allegation of child molestation. There is also her bill regulating pollution from jet-skis.</p>
        <p>She serves on many Assembly committees, and is the chairwoman of the Library and Educational Technology Committee. Her husband, Gene R. Matusow, is an ophthalmologist who is the state committeeman from the same district. He is her campaign director and faces his own stiff challenge on Tuesday from B. J. Markus, a district leader from the New Castle Democratic committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley, 41, is divorced with no children. He has been the chairman of the White Plains Democratic Committee since 1995. He characterizes himself as a grassroots candidate who will bring reform to a dysfunctional political system both here and upstate. Ms. Matusow is caught in the political flypaper of Albany politics, he said, and has become a political pawn of state and county Democratic leadership.</p>
        <p>Ms. Matusow is a longtime friend Mr. Spano and an ally of David A. Alpert, who recently stepped down as the county's Democratic chairman. Mr. Bradley, on the other hand, is an ally of Richard Brodsky, the powerful assemblyman from Greenburgh.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley has said that Ms. Matusow has shown a shameful lack of leadership and now serves the will of party leaders in Albany and not her constituents. He criticized her for blocking legislation to reform the Rockefeller drug laws, and for refusing to support legislation that regularly renews the half-percent sales tax for White Plains.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley is also running on two alternative party lines, the county's Independence Party and the Working Families Party. Both parties previously supported Ms. Matusow.</p>
        <p>Ms. Matusow was long considered a ''marginal,'' a term in state politics for a candidate facing stiff opposition running for a crucial seat. Party leaders help marginals, and this help, Mr. Bradley said, indebts Ms. Matusow to the powerful Democratic Action Committee in Albany.</p>
        <p>''She has become a creature of Albany, controlled by a system that doesn't work,'' he said in an interview last week. ''She has put political expedience above public policy. She works for her own political self-preservation and that's wrong.''</p>
        <p>He called Ms. Matusow ''missing in action'' on Indian Point safety issues and complicit with ''nonaggression pacts'' made by Democratic and Republican leaders in the county to assure that incumbents are not significantly challenged in elections. To this end, he questions why the Republican party ''mysteriously'' did not field a candidate against Ms. Matusow.</p>
        <p>Ms. Matusow called this allegation preposterous, and countered that Republican leaders ''did a poll and found they wouldn't be able to beat me.''</p>
        <p>James Cavanaugh, the Westchester Republican party chairman, said last week that, based upon a poll of voters in the district, Republican leaders determined that they had no potential candidates strong enough to beat Ms. Matusow in November.</p>
        <p>Ms. Matusow dismissed Mr. Bradley's attacks as the bluster of a desperate candidate. She pointed out that she has bucked party leadership when she had to. She called the White Plains sales tax burdensome to people on fixed incomes, and a force that could drive shoppers to Connecticut. She said she did not vote to dismantle the drug laws because it would offer leniency for some violent offenders.</p>
        <p>''My record speaks for itself,'' she said. ''I don't see this as an overly tough race, but I don't discount the challenge.''</p>
        <p>POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
