<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Rx for Independent Drugstores</title>
    <meta content="08DRUG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1421822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugstores</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">White Plains (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cvs Drug Stores</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saxon Chemists Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicolais, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marszalek, Diana</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugstores</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E3DC173EF93BA3575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Rx for Independent Drugstores</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA MARSZALEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marszalek, Diana</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on changes independent drugstore owners in Westchester County, NY, are being forced to make to stay competitive as chain stores open more outlets; Jack Nicolais, owner of Saxon Chemists in White Plains, says nearby CVS drugstore has made him smarter businessman; other pharmacists comment; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR Jack Nicolais, becoming an owner of Saxon Chemists was a boyhood dream come true. Mr. Nicolais had wanted to be a pharmacist since he was an 8-year-old awed by the neighborhood pharmacists in 1950's Queens.</p>
        <p>''I was so impressed with the docs in the white coats who took care of our needs,'' Mr. Nicolais said. ''They were very personal, very trustworthy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR Jack Nicolais, becoming an owner of Saxon Chemists was a boyhood dream come true. Mr. Nicolais had wanted to be a pharmacist since he was an 8-year-old awed by the neighborhood pharmacists in 1950's Queens.</p>
        <p>''I was so impressed with the docs in the white coats who took care of our needs,'' Mr. Nicolais said. ''They were very personal, very trustworthy.''</p>
        <p>He bought Saxon Chemists in 1984. Within a year, however, his fantasy looked as if it could become a nightmare. A CVS drugstore opened just four storefronts away from Saxon's Mamaroneck Avenue location. Saxon Chemists had survived as a downtown fixture since the mid-1940's, but its end seemed perilously near.</p>
        <p>''I was here six months after my wife and I hocked everything to buy a third of this business and all of a sudden we heard a national chain was coming in,'' Mr. Nicolais said. ''I had to rethink if I was going to bail out or take on the national chain coming in.''</p>
        <p>He chose the latter. He computerized the pharmacy and offered customers home delivery and charge accounts. After losing before-work business to CVS, Mr. Nicolais stopped selling morning staples like cosmetics and hosiery. Instead, he added medical aids like walkers, braces and support hose and nutritional products.</p>
        <p>''CVS forced me to make some decisions and stay in business,'' said Mr. Nicolais, who became Saxon's sole owner soon after CVS's arrival. ''The alternative was doing nothing, trying to stay traditional and being swallowed up.''</p>
        <p>More than a decade later, Saxon is not only afloat, he said, but its business has also grown steadily.</p>
        <p>Now he faces a new set of challenges. New competitors, like mail-order pharmacies, managed care plans that dictate drug dispensing and changes in drug distribution have taken a toll on small pharmacists, primarily by reducing their profit margins, Mr. Nicolais said.</p>
        <p>Old-fashioned pharmacies are dwindling in number, so much so that just 28 percent of American pharmacies today are independent, said Lou Flacks, president of the Westchester Rockland Society of Pharmacists.</p>
        <p>Westchester and Rockland Counties are still strongholds of the small stores -- about 150 independent pharmacies are here, at least three times the number of chain stores -- and more independent pharmacists than in the states of Maine, Rhode Island, New Hampshire and Vermont put together, Mr. Flacks said. Still, those counties had about twice as many stores 15 years ago, he said.</p>
        <p>Pharmacies have long been neighborhood hubs where patrons could also buy gifts, toys and beauty products, and pharmacists were on call to do everything from working with doctors and answering late-night calls to removing splinters. Pharmacists say the declining number of independent stores not only threatens a piece of Americana but also means their patrons' health is at stake.</p>
        <p>Many local pharmacists spent years on their higher education and even more honing their relationships with clients. They say that their knowledge on both professional and personal levels is a key part of their jobs, which includes heading off potential dangers like drug interactions.</p>
        <p>''We're the final check,'' said Dan Molino, an owner of Trotta's West Street Pharmacy in Harrison and Grassy Sprain and Le-Mac pharmacies in Yonkers. ''We're the last line of defense to most people who live in the community.''</p>
        <p>Trotta's has been a mainstay since 1925 and the stores in Yonkers since the 1950's. Not all have survived. Charles Sorkin owned the Larchmont Pharmacy for 27 years before closing it nearly four years ago. At that time, the store operated in the same fashion as elegant pharmacies on the Upper East Side of Manhattan, offering customers cosmetics, fragrances and gifts.</p>
        <p>Closing the store was a hard call for Mr. Sorkin, 67. ''I really loved what I was doing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Sorkin said changes in the business, like answering to insurance companies' mandates, took the joy out of the job.</p>
        <p>''There are other people who can change their mindset, who can stay with it and battle it out,'' said Mr. Sorkin, who now works at R&amp;R Pharmacy in Mamaroneck, one of the stores that has survived despite a neighboring CVS. ''I couldn't do it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sorkin wasn't the only pharmacist in Larchmont who closed up shop. Five of the town's seven pharmacies have closed in the last 10 years. One of the remaining two, Buck's Plaza Pharmacy, has nearly doubled its business as the result of those closures, despite having two CVS stores in town and possibly another one coming, said Howard Friedman, the owner of Buck's.</p>
        <p>That is part of the natural progression of absorbing the other stores' customers, Mr. Friedman said. It also is a result of new customers coming to the store in search of personal service that large chain stores can't provide, he said.</p>
        <p>Fans of independent drugstores say they like the personal touch at a small store with a family feel.</p>
        <p>''The prices are the same but the service is three times as good,'' said Dr. Edward Holtzman, a White Plains psychiatrist who has been shopping at Saxon Chemists for 20 years.</p>
        <p>As a doctor, Dr. Holtzman said the relationship he has with Saxon's pharmacist is important.</p>
        <p>''I call him all the time for questions about dosages on medicines,'' Dr. Holtzman said. ''This is something I just can't get from CVS.''</p>
        <p>Shoppers at larger drugstores, however, feel just as strongly that they are making the right choice.</p>
        <p>''The bigger store is a little cheaper and you can kill a lot of birds with one stone,'' said Carl Catauro, who shops at the White Plains CVS on his lunch break. ''Time is always at a premium.''</p>
        <p>For their part, chain store representatives say they have no desire to run local stores out of business.</p>
        <p>''In the pharmacy industry, chains and independents in the community wind up complementing each other,'' said Mike DeAngelis, a CVS spokesman. ''We often refer patients who need a compounded medication, for example, to an independent pharmacist because that is something that many chains do not offer. On the other hand, if you prefer to order your prescriptions online that's something we can do.''</p>
        <p>And some small pharmacy owners have gone so far as to say the emergence of chain drugstores has given them the incentive they needed to bring business into the 21st century.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad I'm here to compete against someone next door,'' Mr. Nicolais, the White Plains owner, said. ''They made me a smarter businessman.''</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
