<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Graffiti as Art. As a Gang Tag. As a Mess.</title>
    <meta content="08GRAF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1421876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ferris, Marc</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E0DE153EF93BA3575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="2505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Graffiti as Art. As a Gang Tag. As a Mess.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC FERRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ferris, Marc</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on graffiti, once most prevalent in cities, that is spreading across suburbs of Westchester County, NY; local and state officials and police officers describe efforts to combat graffiti, noting that gang taggers and graffiti 'artists' move on if cleanup squads move quickly; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO most people, graffiti is scrawl on the wall, defacement of property. To others, it can be a form of artistic expression. For some local police officers versed in deciphering the modern hieroglyphics, graffiti can track gangs and help determine the identities of their members.</p>
        <p>However it is regarded, graffiti is spreading in Westchester, on playground equipment in Dobbs Ferry, a white wall of a historic villa along the Old Croton Aqueduct trail in Irvington, the back of a building in downtown Ardsley that faces the New York State Thruway, and the side of a house under construction on the Yonkers-Greenburgh border.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO most people, graffiti is scrawl on the wall, defacement of property. To others, it can be a form of artistic expression. For some local police officers versed in deciphering the modern hieroglyphics, graffiti can track gangs and help determine the identities of their members.</p>
        <p>However it is regarded, graffiti is spreading in Westchester, on playground equipment in Dobbs Ferry, a white wall of a historic villa along the Old Croton Aqueduct trail in Irvington, the back of a building in downtown Ardsley that faces the New York State Thruway, and the side of a house under construction on the Yonkers-Greenburgh border.</p>
        <p>It has also appeared with a vengeance on street signs and local highways, where bridge pillars and retaining walls beckon like big blank canvases. New markings cover several layers of faded scrawls along the concrete barriers at the hairpin turn leading from the Cross County Parkway into the southbound Hutchinson River Parkway, for instance. And in Greenburgh, the yellow and black signs along both sides of Jackson Avenue indicating a curve in the road at the intersection of Old Jackson Avenue are persistent targets for a vandal wielding red spray paint.</p>
        <p>''It's a never-ending battle and it's very frustrating,'' said Colleen McKenna, a spokeswoman for the New York State Department of Transportation, which spends $400,000 a year in Westchester to combat graffiti through a contract with ELQ Industries of Mamaroneck. ''We clean it off one day and it seems like a day or two later, it's back.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, the cleanup itself is unsightly. Each batch of concrete comes out a different color, so no one shade of paint can match every surface. Cleanup crews often cover patches of graffiti with blotches of paint rather than an entire new coat.</p>
        <p>Graffiti is becoming a more common part of the suburban wallpaper, perpetrated not just by gang members but teenagers of all social echelons. ''It was more prevalent in the cities, but it appears to be migrating,'' said Lieut. Don McArthur of the Westchester County Police, which patrols the parkways. ''There are no numbers to back that up, but it's a constant battle. We've arrested kids from Scarsdale painting graffiti on bridge abutments. It doesn't know any economic strata.''</p>
        <p>In Putnam County, officials have been vexed by vandals who persistently cover an abandoned railroad bridge visible on Route 6 with large white letters. After a crew painted over the word ''Brewster,'' preceded by an expletive, someone circumvented a secure fence and put up the name ''Andrew'' to memorialize Andrew McArdle, a high school student who died in a car crash in January. Graffiti covering a nearby fence read ''Miss you, Andrew's Bridge,'' and ''#68,'' his football jersey number.</p>
        <p>Retaining walls and buildings along Metro-North tracks also attract taggers, graffiti perpetrators who put up their tags, or signatures. ''You can see the various places where they've put graffiti that they were taking their lives in their hands,'' said Tom Kelly, a spokesman for the Metropolitan Transportation Authority police, which patrols Metro-North property. ''Where there's a will, there's a way. They cut holes in fences and put their stuff up in the middle of trestles. The only way someone could do that is by dangling over the side.''</p>
        <p>Catching graffiti vandals in the act is difficult. ''If we get graffiti, they'll stake it out,'' Mr. Kelly said. ''If we have a problem, then you sense from the patterns when a particular wall is getting hit. If it's not there at 9 o'clock and it shows up at 10, then we'll take an unmarked car and we'll watch, but usually, it's a hit-and-miss kind of thing.''</p>
        <p>One evening last month, at 10 o'clock, a 14-year-old Yonkers resident whose alias is Chubbs and did not want his name used, went with a few friends down to the Ludlow train station with spray paint and wide-tip markers. By Chubbs's account, they had the run of the place for an hour before the police arrived.</p>
        <p>Though he said he is only a dabbler, Chubbs's friends are teenagers for whom graffiti is integral to their lives.</p>
        <p>''All the kids do it at school,'' he said. ''They write on the walls in the bathroom, scratch their initials in the glass. You walk by and you're like, 'Yeah, that's me right there.' ''</p>
        <p>Chubbs was arrested for putting up graffiti that night. If he is caught at it again, he will go to jail, where he has already spent two days for stealing a car for a joy ride.</p>
        <p>MOST graffiti is done by hit-and-run guerrillas who enjoy playing cat-and-mouse with the police and revel in their rebel image. In certain areas, however, the messages carry more sinister meanings.</p>
        <p>For Kenneth Davis, a Yonkers community police officer, who has been tracking graffiti for the last decade, the wall markings offer a useful barometer of gang activity. He teaches his techniques to new recruits at the Westchester Police Academy in Valhalla and has given PowerPoint presentations on graffiti to many groups; last month, for instance, he spoke at a conference in Chicago sponsored by the National Gang Crime Research Center.</p>
        <p>On a recent tour of Yonkers neighborhoods, in a doorway just west of Ashburton Avenue and North Broadway, Officer Davis pointed to scribble that read BHW, which stands for Body Hurtin' Warburton, a local gang that haunts Warburton Avenue. The tag also included a list of members -- Burgah, Blaque and Kid -- who pledge allegiance to the crew. Along Lawrence Street and its tributaries in the city's southwest corner, the Lawrence Posse marked their territory with their distinctive TLP tags. At Bruce Avenue and Lawrence Street, the group also put up a roll call. Officer Davis will be seeking information from his sources about Boy Boy, Demo and Murdock, three names new to him.</p>
        <p>Community police officers in Greenburgh also track gang activity through graffiti. Black felt tip pen markings covering a sign at the entrance to the Greenburgh Housing Authority property at 9 Maple Street included the initials CK with an arrow pointing down, which stood for Crip Killers, along with a roll call of nine names.</p>
        <p>Some groups that claim an affiliation with national syndicates like the Bloods and the Crips are like Little League teams that name themselves after the Yankees, Mets or Cubs but have no official connection, though bonafide members of the Bloods and Crips have infiltrated parts of Westchester, according to Greenburgh police officers. Whether local or national in scope, gangs often turn to violence to protect their turf. The Greenburgh police have compiled a list of 25 suspected gang members who are responsible for at least 250 felonies.</p>
        <p>Knowing how to translate gang markings makes it easier to track suspects.</p>
        <p>''Once I get the groups, the individuals start coming out,'' Officer Davis said. ''The hardest thing is finding their true identity, because they hide behind so many street names, but with the graffiti, I can identify core members, monitor recruiting and departures, and predict the strength of a gang. They don't think we realize what their markings mean, but no one said they were rocket scientists.''</p>
        <p>WHETHER graffiti is gang messages or random scribbling, the best way to stop graffiti in a particular area, say those on the front lines, is to clean it up as soon as possible and the taggers will move on. The White Plains Business Improvement District removes it immediately and the city's downtown is relatively graffiti free.</p>
        <p>''Graffiti is a quality-of-life issue that needs to be addressed immediately,'' said Kathleen Gunn, the organization's executive director. ''Fortunately, we don't have that big a problem, partly because we have a lot of police presence here, but it's like the broken-window theory: when it does appear, it needs to be controlled.''</p>
        <p>Yonkers has also made headway by going after the writers and by serving notice to property owners, who have 24 hours to remove the mess. After that time, Richard Fedor, graffiti coordinator for the city's Department of Public Works, will have his three-man crew clean it up and send a bill. ''I try to cut them some slack,'' he said. ''If they call me right away, and it's not a real big job, I'll do it for nothing. But if they leave it up and it becomes worse, then I have to charge.''</p>
        <p>The biggest job he ever tackled was at the New York City water-treatment plant on Palmer Road. It took his crew 10 hours and the bill came to $1,600, which the agency was happy to pay, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fedor's crew uses a chemical called Scram-It, which is brushed on and then removed with a power-washer that sprays a concentrated blast of hot water.</p>
        <p>Last month, Insane and Fens, two vandals whose marks can be found all over the city, left their calling cards in two-foot-high silver letters on the side of a brick building at 209 Riverdale Avenue in Yonkers along with the initials FSV, which stood for Famous Subway Villains. Erol Liguori, the building's owner, called Mr. Fedor, who removed it that afternoon.</p>
        <p>''My attitude is that every day it's here, they're gaining more air time, so I say hit it right away,'' said Mr. Liguori, owner of Prolific Art Galleries, which has its offices in the building. ''A lot of landlords don't have my attitude and the city ends up looking terrible.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Liguori had no control over the graffiti that surrounded his building on the corner of Downing Street. ''Sexy thug wuz here'' and ''Murderuz,'' written with a black felt tip pen, marred a lightpost that stands a foot away from his building's wall. On the same post, Oz and Fane engaged in a subtle game of one-upmanship. Oz put his tag up first, but Fane crossed it out with a green slash, then put his signature next to his handiwork as if challenging his rival. The mailbox on the corner showed evidence of being painted over several times and someone wrote the almost illegible mark ECKS on the doorway of the building across the street.</p>
        <p>Officer Davis, an art major in college who has studied graffiti like a scholar, marvels at the resilience of wall painting. ''It's been around since the first signs of civilization,'' he said. ''Today, it channels the basic instincts of communication and self-worth. It will be on the first lunar station. I don't think it can ever be stopped, but it can be managed.''</p>
        <p>Spray-Paint Artists Who Create Open-Air Galleries, Legally</p>
        <p>OUTLAW graffiti scribblers tarnish the reputation of legitimate graffiti artists, who put up their pieces with property owners' permission. Carlos Lopez, director of Off the Wall, an AIDS education and awareness program founded 10 years ago by Ken Davis, a Yonkers community police officer, and run by the Yonkers Community Action Program, tries to channel the creative impulse into constructive outlets and frames his message in a form that youths can relate to.</p>
        <p>Though they have created more than 30 large-scale murals around town, the group suffers from the stigma attached to graffiti art.</p>
        <p>''I have approached established artists to work with us and when they found out they would be working with graffiti, they turned us down,'' Mr. Lopez said. ''We're not like kids off the street, tagging up on anybody's stuff. We're doing something positive and working on a higher level, but the knuckleheads ruin it for everybody.''</p>
        <p>Graffiti art emerged as a key component of hip-hop culture in the mid-1970's. Though break dancing faded, rap and the distinctive styling of spray-paint artists endure as an expression of inner city youth, despite being co-opted by mass marketers, Mr. Lopez said.</p>
        <p>Off the Wall has helped turn parts of Yonkers into an open-air art gallery. The group makes ''masterpieces,'' large works known as ''pieces,'' which take several hours of planning and execution, along with dozens of cans of paint. Financing for the program, which has a budget of $69,000 a year, comes from the New York State Department of Health, the AIDS Institute and a New York State Community Service block grant.</p>
        <p>Across from the group's headquarters on Ashburton Avenue and Jones Place, in a rundown part of town, stands a 10-foot-high, 30-foot-wide antidrug mural that is almost as pristine as the day Alexis Hiraldo (whose tag is Nekst), 18 years old, and Daniel Gomez (Blame), 17, created it two months ago. The main section depicts a boxing ring. The message: ''Don't Get in the Ring with Hard Hitting Heavyweights.'' Off the Wall's logo, emblazoned in bold letters in the lower left corner, along with amoeba-like splotches of color, add abstract flourishes.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1990's, Off the Wall helped transform hundreds of square feet along a concrete walkway in the Vark Street Playground into a showcase. Eighteen artists put up their tags along 4-by-6-foot sections of the wall, which have faded and chipped over the years. Only a few neighborhood youths have added unauthorized tags and irreverent remarks over the years, though one artist's work has been completely crossed out.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez plans to hold an event later this fall that will wipe the slate clean and put up new work. He is inviting some of the region's best-known artists to contribute and give local teenagers something to strive for. ''Some people use graffiti in a destructive manner,'' Mr. Lopez said. ''It can be constructive, too.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez offers the ultimate incentive: $400 to $650 for a mural, and he pays artists to give school presentations.</p>
        <p>''Once kids sit down and meet my artists, they know we came from the same streets,'' he said. ''Once I grab them and get them in here for 15 minutes, I've got them for the whole year and we can do AIDS education, job-training and college preparation.''</p>
        <p>MARC FERRIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
