<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For President, Final Say on a Bill Sometimes Comes After the Signing</title>
    <meta content="16letter" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/16/politics/16letter.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1732509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="White House Letter"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/White House Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Columns/White House Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3DC143FF935A25752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For President, Final Say on a Bill Sometimes Comes After the Signing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For President, Final Say on a Bill Sometimes Comes After the Signing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <dateline>Washington</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shortly after 8 p.m. on Friday, Dec. 30, the White House sent out an e-mail message with an innocuous ''Statement by the President'' in the subject line. As might be expected of a seemingly routine announcement released in the dead time before New Year's weekend, almost no one paid attention.</p>
        <p>But last week, Washington opened its eyes. Mr. Bush's quiet little statement not only set off fireworks at the Supreme Court nomination hearings of Judge Samuel A. Alito Jr., but also ignited a new debate about the Bush administration's drive to expand the powers of the president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A quiet statement from President Bush has ignited a new debate about the administration's drive to expand the powers of the president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shortly after 8 p.m. on Friday, Dec. 30, the White House sent out an e-mail message with an innocuous ''Statement by the President'' in the subject line. As might be expected of a seemingly routine announcement released in the dead time before New Year's weekend, almost no one paid attention.</p>
        <p>But last week, Washington opened its eyes. Mr. Bush's quiet little statement not only set off fireworks at the Supreme Court nomination hearings of Judge Samuel A. Alito Jr., but also ignited a new debate about the Bush administration's drive to expand the powers of the president.</p>
        <p>To start at the beginning, Congress late last year passed what became known as the torture amendment, sponsored by Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, to ban cruel, inhumane or degrading treatment of prisoners in American custody. Mr. Bush at first opposed the amendment, but gave in when it became clear that it had overwhelming support from the two parties on Capitol Hill. The president then invited Mr. McCain, his old political nemesis, to the Oval Office to announce that he agreed with him and ''to make clear to the world that this government does not torture.''</p>
        <p>But on Dec. 30, after signing the legislation into law with no ceremony at his Texas ranch, Mr. Bush issued an accompanying ''signing statement'' -- the 8 p.m. e-mail message -- that Democrats and some Republicans say asserted that he could ignore the law if he wished.</p>
        <p>Specifically, the statement said that the administration would interpret the amendment ''in a manner consistent with the constitutional authority of the president to supervise the unitary executive branch and as commander in chief and consistent with the constitutional limitations on judicial power.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain issued a strong statement rejecting Mr. Bush's assertion, even as the White House has repeatedly declined to say what the president meant. But Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts, had no doubts, and told Judge Alito at the hearings that Mr. Bush had in essence stated that ''whatever the law of the land might be, whatever Congress might have written, the executive branch has the right to authorize torture without fear of judicial review.''</p>
        <p>Judge Alito, Mr. Kennedy pointed out, had in 1986, as a lawyer in the Reagan administration Justice Department, helped Edwin Meese III, then attorney general, develop a theory that signing statements could be used to advance the president's interpretation of legislation. Before then, the statements had largely been triumphal proclamations. Mr. Alito wrote at the time that the new signing statements would ''increase the power of the executive to shape the law'' even as they created resentment in Congress.</p>
        <p>At his hearings, Judge Alito distanced himself from the memorandum, calling it the work of a government employee, and sidestepped questions about his current view on the statements. At this point, their legality is largely untested.</p>
        <p>But one thing is clear: Mr. Bush has issued more than 100 of them, which scholars believe might be more than any other president. (Signing statements have been around since at least the administration of Andrew Jackson.) More significant, scholars say, Mr. Bush has greatly expanded the scope and character of the signing statement, even from the time of the Reagan administration.</p>
        <p>''The whole history of American government is one of trying to figure out what executive power actually is, so here is the president saying, 'Well, it's my job to tell you what that power is,' '' said Andrew Rudalevige, an associate professor of political science at Dickinson College in Pennsylvania and the author of ''The New Imperial Presidency: Renewing Presidential Power After Watergate.''</p>
        <p>Scholars say that many of Mr. Bush's most significant signing statements have been attached to national security and intelligence legislation and that he frequently uses them to assert that the administration regards requirements to turn over information as purely advisory.</p>
        <p>For example, in signing the legislation that created the independent commission that investigated the Sept. 11 attacks, Mr. Bush said that while the law established ''new requirements for the executive branch to disclose sensitive information,'' he would interpret the law ''in a manner consistent with the president's constitutional authority to withhold information'' for national security.</p>
        <p>Members of the Sept. 11 commission soon learned they would have a difficult time obtaining information from the White House.</p>
        <p>''Now, we can't prove that the reason the administration held back the information was because of the signing statement, but it announced its intentions quite clearly,'' said Phillip J. Cooper, a professor of public administration in the Mark O. Hatfield School of Government at Portland State University in Oregon and the author of ''By Order of the President: The Use and Abuse of Executive Direct Action.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also used a signing statement in November 2003 to assert that an inspector general created for oversight of the Coalition Provisional Authority, the American administration that governed Iraq, should ''refrain'' from audits or investigations into matters of intelligence or counterintelligence.</p>
        <p>In December 2004, Mr. Bush used a signing statement to say that in the act that created the post of national intelligence director, he considered provisions setting forth how -- and from whom -- he received intelligence information to be ''advisory.''</p>
        <p>Or as Mr. Rudalevige put it, ''The president is basically saying that those structural changes are nice, but I don't have to listen to anybody in particular.''</p>
        <p>White House Letter</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
