<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islanders Running Low on Defensemen</title>
    <meta content="19ISLE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="974241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Red Wings</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Bashir, Tarik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berard, Bryan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vaske, Denis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pilon, Rich</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Detroit Red Wings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D9163BF93AA25752C1A961958260" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islanders Running Low on Defensemen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TARIK EL-BASHIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">El-Bashir, Tarik</byline>
      <dateline>SYOSSET, N.Y., Nov. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Islanders defensemen Bryan Berard, Dennis Vaske and Rich Pilon are not expected to play against Detroit Red Wings on Nov 19 because of injuries (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Islanders play the Stanley Cup champion Detroit Red Wings on Wednesday, they will be without half their regular defensemen as they face the best offensive team in the National Hockey League.</p>
        <p>Bryan Berard (groin), Dennis Vaske (concussion) and Rich Pilon (ankle) are not expected to face the Red Wings, who have collected a league-best 73 goals in 22 games this season. Left wing Ken Belanger (thumb) is also expected to miss the the game for the Islanders, the first of three matchups in four days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Islanders play the Stanley Cup champion Detroit Red Wings on Wednesday, they will be without half their regular defensemen as they face the best offensive team in the National Hockey League.</p>
        <p>Bryan Berard (groin), Dennis Vaske (concussion) and Rich Pilon (ankle) are not expected to face the Red Wings, who have collected a league-best 73 goals in 22 games this season. Left wing Ken Belanger (thumb) is also expected to miss the the game for the Islanders, the first of three matchups in four days.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the Islanders play at New Jersey and on Saturday they are at Buffalo.</p>
        <p>Today, the Islanders (8-8-4) recalled the defensemen Zdeno Chara and Jason Holland and right wing Steve Webb from Kentucky, the American Hockey League affiliate. Doug Houda, a seldom used defenseman, will round out the backlines.</p>
        <p>For Berard, who is third on the team in scoring with seven goals and nine assists, it will be the fourth game this season he has missed with a lingering groin strain. He has been in and out of the lineup since his skate caught a rut in the ice at San Jose last month.</p>
        <p>Berard, who did not practice today, sat out last Friday's game at Tampa Bay. He returned to the lineup for Saturday's 1-0 loss to the Florida Panthers and aggravated the injury.</p>
        <p>''It's not sore,'' Berard said after today's practice. ''It's just weak. It doesn't feel 100 percent. We're taking precaution. I don't want to play all year with a strained groin. I want to be back as soon as I can.''</p>
        <p>Vaske, who sustained a mild concussion last Friday in Florida, will not make the trip to Detroit. He did not play last against Florida on Saturday and did not practice today. His availability for the games against the Devils and Sabres is doubtful.</p>
        <p>In each of the last two years, Vaske, a reliable, stay-at-home defender, has sustained season-ending concussions in mid-November, missing 111 games.</p>
        <p>Though this most recent concussion is not considered to be as serious as the previous two, the Islanders and their team doctor, Elliot Pellman, are taking no chances given Vaske's history.</p>
        <p>Pilon, a gritty, hard-nosed defenseman, has been hobbled the last two weeks by a bruised foot caused by a shot to the ankle in practice a couple of weeks ago. He has already missed a game this season because of the injury.</p>
        <p>Pilon's availability for Wednesday's game will be determined after a morning skate, although it seems unlikely he will be able to play.</p>
        <p>Belanger, the Islander tough guy, injured his left thumb in a brawl with the Panthers' Paul Laus last Wednesday. It was the second fight between the two heavyweights this season, the first resulted in a concussion for Belanger. He missed four games with the injury.</p>
        <p>''There's never any good timing for this,'' Coach Rick Bowness said of the recent injuries. ''It's a tough week for us; it's just become more of a challenge. But we're going there to win.''</p>
        <p>Bowness has cautiously answered questions about the Islanders' moderate success this season, saying he would evaluate his team's progress after 20 games. Saturday, he said, ''We've played 20 games, and we haven't been out of a game yet.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders have their best mark through 20 games since the 1987-88 season. But that was achieved with a healthy team.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
