<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Approves New York Hospital Proposal for New Building Over F.D.R. Drive</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="585765"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOSPITALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANKLIN D ROOSEVELT DRIVE (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK HOSPITAL (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CITY PLANNING COMMISSION (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNLAP, DAVID W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DB133BF935A15752C0A965958260" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Approves New York Hospital Proposal for New Building Over F.D.R. Drive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNLAP, DAVID W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Hospital will construct a 776-bed building on a platform above the Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive, between 68th and 70th Streets, under a proposal approved unanimously yesterday by the City Planning Commission.</p>
        <p>The hospital plans to start construction in April and complete the 12-story, $908 million building in 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York Hospital will construct a 776-bed building on a platform above the Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive, between 68th and 70th Streets, under a proposal approved unanimously yesterday by the City Planning Commission.</p>
        <p>The hospital plans to start construction in April and complete the 12-story, $908 million building in 1998.</p>
        <p>The proposal is not subject to a vote by the City Council unless it is called up for review by a majority of the 51 members. The Councilman from the Upper East Side, Charles Millard, said yesterday that he had no intention to seek such a review, unless there were "glitches" with the public amenities that had been negotiated as part of the proposal.</p>
        <p>With one million square feet, the new hospital structure would have as much floor space as the Chrysler Building. It would rise about 185 feet above the platform level, roughly equal to a 20-story apartment house.</p>
        <p>The new building would contain emergency rooms, intensive-care units, a burn center, operating rooms, labor and delivery suites and rooms for general pediatric, medical, surgical and psychiatric patients.</p>
        <p>Although the existing Upper East Side campus of the New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center is physically imposing, the buildings date as far back as the early 1930's.</p>
        <p>"A 60-year-old hospital facility, given all that has happened in advances in medicine, is pretty much out of date," Dr. David B. Skinner, the president of the hospital, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Under a deal struck with New York City in 1973, the New York Hospital, the Rockefeller University and the Hospital for Special Surgery are permitted to build over the F.D.R. Drive.</p>
        <p>"I'm not crazy about diminishing access to the waterfront," Mr. Millard said, "but this was an arrangement that was settled upon by the city and the hospital a couple of decades ago. I don't think now would be a responsible time to upset that apple cart."</p>
        <p>Rather than negotiating the broad outlines of development, talks in the past couple of days have centered on the details of the public amenities that the hospital is to provide.</p>
        <p>Louis F. Reuter 4th, a vice president of the hospital, said the amenities would cost $6.1 million: $2.5 million for a new pedestrian bridge over the drive, to the East River esplanade, at 71st Street; $2.1 million for a new park at the foot of East 60th Street, and $1.5 million as part of an endowment to maintain that park.</p>
        <p>After the vote by the planning commission, Borough President Ruth W. Messinger of Manhattan said, "We're pleased that there is approval for a new facility for New York Hospital which allows it to give quality care into the next century." She said negotiations had resulted in the assurance that "a park will be developed and maintained into the future."</p>
        <p>The new building has been designed by Hellmuth, Obata &amp; Kassabaum and Taylor Clark Architects. It is meant to complement the existing structures -- with their distinctive, neo-Gothic pointed arches -- and will be connected to them. Health-Care Network</p>
        <p>Dr. Skinner said its development was part of the overall goal of creating a health-care network in which the primary level would be local doctors' offices, the secondary level would be affiliated hospitals offering basic medical and surgical services and the tertiary level would be the Upper East Side campus, with its teachers, specialists and high technology.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, he said, there would be fewer beds on the East Side campus than the 970 that are there now. In addition to the 776 beds in the new building, only 144 will remain in existing buildings. Space will be converted to other uses and the Payne Whitney Psychiatric Clinic will be razed.</p>
        <p>Construction of the platform will take about 18 months, Dr. Skinner said, but work will be done only from midnight to 5 A.M. The drive will be closed for minimal periods between those hours, he said, when the beams are being erected over it.</p>
        <p>Two other buildings have been constructed over the drive as part of the 1973 arrangement: the 38-story Scholars Residence, between 62d and 63d Streets, which is used by the Rockefeller University and the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, and the 14-story John D. Rockefeller Jr. and David Rockefeller Research Building, which the Rockefeller University completed last year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
