<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sears Eliminating Its Catalogues and 50,000 Jobs</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="585941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CATALOGUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAYOFFS (LABOR)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SEARS, ROEBUCK &amp; CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PINSTRIPE PETITE STORES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WAL-MART</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOME DEPOT INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STROM, STEPHANIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARTINEZ, ARTHUR C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mail Order Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD91F31F935A15752C0A965958260" item-length="1148" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sears Eliminating Its Catalogues and 50,000 Jobs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STROM, STEPHANIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company announced yesterday that it was pulling the plug on its "big book" catalogues, the tomes that have staked a place beside the family Bible in rural American homes for 97 years, as part of an extensive revamping that will close 113 of its stores and carve 50,000 jobs from its payroll.</p>
        <p>The huge overhaul effort, the most extensive of Sears's many attempts to halt the decade-long decline of its retail business, is a big step toward making Sears nimble enough to compete in today's lean retail environment, where stores like Wal-Mart, Toys "R" Us and Home Depot brag about their low cost structures rather than their sales.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company announced yesterday that it was pulling the plug on its "big book" catalogues, the tomes that have staked a place beside the family Bible in rural American homes for 97 years, as part of an extensive revamping that will close 113 of its stores and carve 50,000 jobs from its payroll.</p>
        <p>The huge overhaul effort, the most extensive of Sears's many attempts to halt the decade-long decline of its retail business, is a big step toward making Sears nimble enough to compete in today's lean retail environment, where stores like Wal-Mart, Toys "R" Us and Home Depot brag about their low cost structures rather than their sales.</p>
        <p>It also sounds a death knell for the entrenched bureaucracy that resisted change at Sears for years, and rings in the reign of Arthur C. Martinez, the outsider hired to revamp Sears's retail businesses. For those who doubted his ability to engineer a turnaround at the nation's third-largest retailer, yesterday's announcement showed that Mr. Martinez has the authority to slaughter Sears's sacred cows.</p>
        <p>"I feel this is a definitive restructuring of the merchandise group," Mr. Martinez, chairman and chief executive of Sears's merchandising group, said in a telephone interview. "It gets us out of a number of unprofitable businesses and frees up the playing field for us to move forward."</p>
        <p>He said he did not want to go down in history as the catalogue's executioner, but would instead "like to be known as the guy who got Sears back on its feet."</p>
        <p>The catalogue had $3.3 billion in sales last year but losses of as much as $175 million. Analysts and consultants said Sears had little chance of revitalizing the operation without making significant investments of time and money. Richard Grunsten, president of GSP Marketing Services Inc., one of the largest specialty catalogue publishers and a one-time Sears consultant, said Sears's catalogues made a profit in December after about 20 straight years of losses.</p>
        <p>In spite of their abysmal record, the demise of the "big books," with their 1,000-plus pages devoted to everything from farm implements to dresses, evoked waves of nostalgia. The catalogues were the cornerstone of the Sears retail empire, which in its heyday was to the industry what Wal-Mart is now. Sears now ranks behind Wal-Mart, which is No. 1, and Kmart. 'The World Has Changed'</p>
        <p>"To see it die gives you a little, well, your heart skips a beat because it was something that was so American," said Robert F. DeLay, editor of the DeLay Newsletter, a direct-marketing newsletter. "Nonetheless, the world has changed, and the catalogue has not changed with it."</p>
        <p>The "big books" were among the last catalogues to adopt the use of an "800" telephone number for taking orders. The operation, which also published 50 small specialty catalogues, only recently began accepting Visa and Mastercard for purchases, and for many years, customers had to pick up their purchases at a Sears store even though other catalogues would mail items directly to homes. The merchandise pickup counters were closed last year, and the 2,000 catalogue stores are now set to close. Customers may still order from the catalogues until the end of this year.</p>
        <p>In the revamping, Sears will eliminate 16,000 full-time and 34,000 part-time jobs out of a total of about 350,000. Most of the jobs involved are clerical and management positions; few salespeople will be affected. Sears said it would try to place those losing their jobs into openings that might develop elsewhere in the company.</p>
        <p>Sears will also sell or close its 35 Pinstripe Petites specialty stores and offer about 4,000 salaried employees in the merchandise group a voluntary early-retirement program.</p>
        <p>The Sears cutbacks follow similar recent moves by some of the largest and best-known American companies. The International Business Machines Corporation said in December it would cut 25,000 jobs in 1993 and the General Motors Corporation said it would accelerate its plans to close auto plants and trim thousands of jobs.</p>
        <p>Analysts applauded Sears's changes, which had been expected. And Wall Street bid the company's stock up $1.875, to $50.75, a 52-week high.</p>
        <p>Still, most analysts hesitated to say that the revamping alone would put Sears back on its feet. "Put it this way: They're off their knees," said George A. Ashur, director of corporate bond research at Chase Securities Inc. "This is without a doubt good medicine for the company, but I have to see a few quarters of good returns before I'm ready to ditch the conservative show-me attitude."</p>
        <p>Analysts also expect Sears to announce soon that it will streamline its merchandising organization, paring the current six divisions to three: apparel and other soft goods; hard lines like washing machines, tools and computers, and automotive.</p>
        <p>That would eliminate even more expensive management jobs. "There are going to be a lot fewer people saluting each other in the halls," said Walter F. Loeb, a retail consultant.</p>
        <p>Sears expects about $300 million in savings to drop to its bottom line after it completes the revamping early next year. But the cuts leave Sears awash in billions of dollars in red ink for 1992.</p>
        <p>For the fourth quarter that ended on Dec. 31, the company will show a $1.7 billion after-tax charge to cover the costs of revamping its merchandise group, a $1.9 billion after-tax charge for changes in accounting standards and a $1.65 billion after-tax loss at its Allstate Insurance unit, which handled an avalanche of claims last year from Hurricane Andrew and other natural disasters. Emphasis on Shopping Malls</p>
        <p>Most of the full-line stores that will be closed are free-standing units in rural areas and downtowns, leaving Sears primarily a mall-based retailer. Traffic in malls has slowed somewhat in recent years, but analysts said the company had little choice but to focus on its mall stores, which are its most profitable.</p>
        <p>"The mall is still an incredibly powerful draw," Mr. Martinez said. "Some of our better-performing stores are there."</p>
        <p>Sears said five stores in New York State would close: Rentar Plaza in Flushing, Queens; Hillside Avenue in Jamaica, Queens; Central Park Avenue in Yonkers and stores in Hornell and Rome. In Connecticut, the Riverview Center store in Middletown and a store in Hamden will close. No stores in New Jersey were on yesterday's list, but Sears said a personnel office in Wayne would be closed.  Shrinking the Payroll</p>
        <p>To reflect current valuations, Sears will establish a $200 million after-tax reserve to write down land and certain office properties in its Homart Development Company, its previously closed catalogue pickup operations and its retail stores.</p>
        <p>A Sears spokesman said Prodigy, an on-line computer service that markets items in the Sears catalogues, would obviously lose some of its catalogue sales business.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
