<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inquiry Challenges Doctors On Ordering Diagnostic Tests</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="680136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCTORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOYNIHAN, DANIEL PATRICK (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E1DA103EF930A25757C0A962958260" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inquiry Challenges Doctors On Ordering Diagnostic Tests</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doctors order many more diagnostic tests when they have a financial interest in the equipment and clinics that perform the tests, Congressional investigators said today.</p>
        <p>The General Accounting Office, an investigative arm of Congress, said that doctors were three to five times as likely to order CAT scans, magnetic resonance imaging, ultrasound procedures and other diagnostic imaging services when the equipment was owned by the doctors themselves or by groups with which they were affiliated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Doctors order many more diagnostic tests when they have a financial interest in the equipment and clinics that perform the tests, Congressional investigators said today.</p>
        <p>The General Accounting Office, an investigative arm of Congress, said that doctors were three to five times as likely to order CAT scans, magnetic resonance imaging, ultrasound procedures and other diagnostic imaging services when the equipment was owned by the doctors themselves or by groups with which they were affiliated.</p>
        <p>The accounting office produced the report at the request of Representative Pete Stark of California, a California Democrat who is chairman of the Ways and Means Subcommittee on Health, the first Congressional panel to take up proposals for restructuring the health care system.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the Capitol, Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, the New York Democrat who is chairman of the Finance Committee, suggested today that work on health care legislation might not go as quickly as the Administration had hoped. Mr. Moynihan said his committee would continue holding hearings on health issues through mid-May and would probably not start writing a bill until some time in June, about a month later than planned. Timetable Troubles Mitchell</p>
        <p>Senator George J. Mitchell, Democrat of Maine, the majority leader, expressed disappointment at the delay. "It had been my hope we could begin a little sooner than that," he said.</p>
        <p>As part of any comprehensive legislation, Congress is considering proposals to tighten the limits on doctors' ability to profit from the referral of patients, an issue that has been debated for some time.</p>
        <p>Congress has already prohibited doctors from sending Medicare patients to laboratories with which the doctors have financial relationships. On Jan. 1, 1995, the ban will be extended to cover these services under Medicare and Medicaid: physical therapy, radiology, home health services and hospital services.</p>
        <p>But the law permits one doctor to refer patients to another one in the same group practice. In the last few years, some doctors have formed loose affiliations among themselves so they can call it a group practice. These "clinics without walls" have proliferated in Florida, California and other states as doctors try to avoid the ban on certain referrals. Stark Cites Abuse</p>
        <p>The accounting office reviewed 2.4 million claims for imaging services. It did not try to determine whether the tests were medically necessary. But Mr. Stark said the data suggested that some doctors were "ripping off taxpayers" by ordering too many tests.</p>
        <p>"The magnitude of over-ordering of tests by doctors who own an interest in an X-ray or M.R.I. practice is staggering," he said. "We are talking about billions of dollars of waste and abuse."</p>
        <p>The American Medical Association declared in 1991 that it was unethical for a doctor to refer patients to clinics and other health-care businesses in which the doctor had a financial interest. But the application of this policy to specific cases is hotly debated. Doing What Comes Naturally</p>
        <p>Kirk B. Johnson, senior vice president and general counsel of the association, said today that the data collected by the General Accounting Office were not surprising.</p>
        <p>"If you have the equipment at your fingertips and you operate it yourself, you have complete confidence in the results, and you're more likely to use it," he said. "I'd rather go to a doctor who has his own machine and will feel free in a close case to use it. The economics of medicine are such that blatant overutilization is going to make a physician's practice uncompetitive."</p>
        <p>With the spread of managed care and other techniques to control costs, Mr. Johnson said, "the real issue for patients is whether they will get the tests they need, not whether they are getting too many." Hospitals Official Sees Harm</p>
        <p>At the Finance Committee hearing today, lobbyists for hospitals, doctors and the elderly said it would be disastrous to cut the growth of Medicare as much as President Clinton and authors of competing health plans have proposed.</p>
        <p>Richard J. Davidson, president of the American Hospital Association, said: "Hospitals are firm supporters of fundamental health care reform. But hospitals strongly disagree with the idea that Medicare reductions are a reasonable way to finance reform."</p>
        <p>The cutbacks proposed by the Administration would harm the quality of care, forcing hospitals to lay off workers and postpone the purchase of new equipment, he said.</p>
        <p>White House officials, by contrast, assert that hospitals could be much more productive and could save money by sharing costly new technology.</p>
        <p>The Congressional Budget Office says the Clinton plan would cut the growth of Medicare by $103 billion, or 9 percent, from 1996 to the year 2000. Under these proposals, Mr. Davidson said, the Government would pay hospitals 71 cents on the dollar for Medicare patients, as against 88 cents today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
