<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Towns; Where Justice Is Served With Mercy</title>
    <meta content="01TOWN0AA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1058720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hastings-on-Hudson (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McElroy, Michael (Justice)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E2D8153FF932A35752C1A96E958260" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Towns; Where Justice Is Served With Mercy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>HASTINGS-ON-HUDSON, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane Gross Metro Matters column describesscene in village court of Justice Michael McElroy in Hastings-on-Hudson, NY (M)9</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE night a week, Justice Michael McElroy, in long black robes, takes the bench in Village Justice Court here and renders judgment on a parade of suburban offenders, many of them neighbors and friends.</p>
        <p>He metes out punishments for acts like shoving a fellow commuter on the Metro-North railroad, walking off with a gym bag with a child's bite plate inside and urinating on the stoop of the local dry cleaners (a violation known in the village code as ''deposit of offensive matter'').</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE night a week, Justice Michael McElroy, in long black robes, takes the bench in Village Justice Court here and renders judgment on a parade of suburban offenders, many of them neighbors and friends.</p>
        <p>He metes out punishments for acts like shoving a fellow commuter on the Metro-North railroad, walking off with a gym bag with a child's bite plate inside and urinating on the stoop of the local dry cleaners (a violation known in the village code as ''deposit of offensive matter'').</p>
        <p>His docket commonly includes landlord-tenant disagreements, disputed traffic tickets and violations of village ordinances. But last spring, in the first slaying here in two decades, Justice McElroy presided over the initial court appearance of Michael B. Laudor, a schizophrenic charged with killing his girlfriend.</p>
        <p>As the lowest-level trial court in the state, village courts pass felony cases on to the State Supreme Court for trial. But Justice McElroy's jurisdiction is broad. ''This is the people's court, if there is such a thing as a people's court,'' he said. ''We have immediate involvement in the lives of a heck of a lot of people, many of whom we know.''</p>
        <p>When intimacy interferes with justice, Justice McElroy, a corporate lawyer who has served in his elected post for 15 years, recuses himself and another jurist fills in. That happened last week in the case of a man accused of harassment for kicking his 17-year-old son.</p>
        <p>The boy is a friend of Justice McElroy's youngest daughter and the justice has heard many accounts of violence in the defendant's home. He hopes that the case will end with the man agreeing to counseling instead of spending 15 days in jail.</p>
        <p>''This is social work, almost,'' he said as the alternate judge and the police officer who made the arrest met in chambers with the father, a pale, slightly built man in a sagging cardigan sweater.</p>
        <p>The vast majority of Justice McElroy's cases are traffic violations, which he handles with the mercy of a man who commutes 112 miles each day to Suffolk County. A woman has been caught driving 51 miles per hour in a 30-m.p.h. zone. But she was late for her duties as a Girl Scout leader, she explains. Justice McElroy lets her plead to 39 m.p.h., thus lowering her fine and the points on her license.</p>
        <p>His understanding of village matters informs his judgment, particularly when it comes to parking tickets issued at the railroad station, a frequent indignity in the suburbs, where two-career families compete for an inadequate number of spaces.</p>
        <p>So last week, Justice McElroy dismissed the case of a woman who parked illegally in a permit-only spot because the metered lot was full, leaving four quarters on her windshield in a gesture of good faith. Justice McElroy told her that the next summons would yield a fine, then begged her to join a community letter-writing effort to protest the lack of parking.</p>
        <p>The last case of the evening was a dispute between neighbors of nearly 20 years. Their houses face each other on Overlook Road, with vistas of the Hudson River and the last blaze of autumn foliage.</p>
        <p>In June, one man parked his car at the curb beneath an oak tree on the other's property. A tree limb, 17 feet long, fell on the car with crushing results. Insurance paid for the damage, except for the $500 deductible.</p>
        <p>That $500 was the subject of a lawsuit that reached trial before Justice McElroy. Each man testified, sniping insults at the other. Photographs were offered in evidence, along with bills from a tree service. Was the tree limb dead at the time it fell? Had its owner been negligent? Was the weather stormy, or merely overcast?</p>
        <p>Justice McElroy determined that the plaintiff had not proved his case, offering him sympathy but no cash judgment. He urged the men to mend their broken friendship, since amity is essential to small-town life. He persuaded them to shake hands, which they did grudgingly, eyes averted and hands limp.</p>
        <p>The plaintiff said he had never expected to win. ''What I really wanted was just an 'I'm sorry,' '' he grumbled.</p>
        <p>''I think you're entitled to that,'' Justice McElroy said. ''But it's not in the jurisdiction of this court.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
