<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.Y.I.</title>
    <meta content="01FYI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1058542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Traffic Signals and Signs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deafness</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sign Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Daniel B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Deafness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Signs and Symbols</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Traffic Signals and Signs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sign Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sign Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deafness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E3DF163FF932A35752C1A96E958260" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.Y.I.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Daniel B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FYI column answers questions on reason for pictograms mounted above NYC intersection that spell out School for the Deaf in sign language, route of New York to Paris auto race and location of old US Assay Office; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sign Language Signs</p>
        <p>Q.  A mysterious set of traffic signs, covered with pictograms instead of words, is mounted high above the intersection at East 23d Street and Second Avenue. The signs depict stylized hands, which spell out the words ''School for the Deaf'' in sign language. Since the deaf can read words as well as hands, what is the point of these signs?  A.  Though they do announce the presence of a nearby school for the deaf -- Junior High School 47, at 225 East 23d Street -- the signs are more properly understood as part of a multisite artwork called ''Traffic Signs for the Hearing Impaired.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sign Language Signs</p>
        <p>Q.  A mysterious set of traffic signs, covered with pictograms instead of words, is mounted high above the intersection at East 23d Street and Second Avenue. The signs depict stylized hands, which spell out the words ''School for the Deaf'' in sign language. Since the deaf can read words as well as hands, what is the point of these signs?  A.  Though they do announce the presence of a nearby school for the deaf -- Junior High School 47, at 225 East 23d Street -- the signs are more properly understood as part of a multisite artwork called ''Traffic Signs for the Hearing Impaired.''</p>
        <p>Made of aluminum and posted in the summer of 1990, the signs were painted by Martin V. Wong, an artist then living on the Lower East Side, who created them during a six-month residency at the Department of Transportation's sign shop. Others were hung near schools for the hearing-impaired in Brooklyn, Queens and the Bronx. The signs, which cost about $3,500 altogether to produce, are similar to ordinary traffic signs but were painted using stencils Mr. Wong cut by hand. They come in pairs. Each hand-covered sign is placed directly below a school crossing sign redesigned by Mr. Wong to make the figures more pudgy and childlike.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wong established his artistic reputation in the early 1980's with paintings of decaying tenements beneath fiery, apocalyptic skies. He began using the manual alphabet for the deaf in his paintings early in his career, after he was given an alphabet donation card on Lexington Avenue. As for his unusual traffic signs, ''I wanted to give deafness a visibility,'' said Mr. Wong, who now lives in San Francisco. ''I know that the deaf read like everyone else.''</p>
        <p>Paris, the Long Way</p>
        <p>Q.  I came across a photograph, taken in Times Square in 1908, showing six cars roaring off at the start of the ''New York to Paris Automobile Race.'' Could you drive across the Atlantic Ocean back in those days?  A.  It takes a moment to sink in, but since the New York to Paris auto race was by definition over land, the six competing teams rolled up Broadway, then turned their backs to the Atlantic and set off for France on a westerly course. The chosen route  crossed the continental United States, Alaska and the frozen Bering Strait, continuing through Siberia, Russia, Poland, Germany, and finally, to France. The length of the trip, which took about six months, was 19,877 miles. As the canvas-topped cars set out from the New York Times building that uncommonly cold February morning, a crowd of more than 150,000 lined the streets to watch.</p>
        <p>Because the drivers were clearly insane.</p>
        <p>At that time, most roadways were impassable or nonexistent during winter. One of the French cars bored into a snowdrift and quit the race, only 44 miles outside the city. The remaining entrants -- fitted out with goggles, fur coats, picks and canvas sails -- spent much time in front of their racers, shoveling. Crews fumed, drivers quit and routes were redrawn. The eventual winner was George Schuster, an American mechanic. He piloted his Thomas Speedway Flyer into Paris on July 30 -- and was promptly stopped by a policeman for driving without a headlight.</p>
        <p>The Old Assay Site</p>
        <p>Q.  Where was the old United States Assay Office located before its sober facade was re-erected in the courtyard of the American Wing of the Metropolitan Museum?</p>
        <p>A.  Originally built to house the Branch Bank of the United States, the Greek Revival building occupied a site on the north side of Wall Street, between Nassau and William Streets. It was designed by Martin E. Thompson, architect of the Arsenal in Central Park and many other city buildings, and completed in 1824.</p>
        <p>DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
