<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting Electricity From a Volcano</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="78" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="205705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="FOLLOW-UP ON THE NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAWAII</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KILAUEA VOLCANO (HAWAII)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DB1031F932A25751C1A96E948260" item-length="301" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting Electricity From a Volcano</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: HAWAII depends almost entirely on imported oil for fuel and badly needs another energy source, but the question before the state's Supreme Court was: Would geothermal power development of Kilauea Volcano hamper worship of the legendary volcano goddess Pele?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: HAWAII depends almost entirely on imported oil for fuel and badly needs another energy source, but the question before the state's Supreme Court was: Would geothermal power development of Kilauea Volcano hamper worship of the legendary volcano goddess Pele?</p>
        <p>HAWAII depends almost entirely on imported oil for fuel and badly needs another energy source, but the question before the state's Supreme Court was: Would geothermal power development of Kilauea Volcano hamper worship of the legendary volcano goddess Pele?</p>
        <p>Worshipers argued that digging would desecrate Pele's body. The court ruled in July 1987 that it would not interfere with the volcanic eruptions. And so the state received a green light to tap and harness the raging volcano, whose scorching lava has demolished more than 60 homes and severed a highway on the island of Hawaii in the last five years.</p>
        <p>Imposing plans are being developed to get 500 to 600 megawatts of electricity from Kilauea (prononounced Kila-WAY-ah) and to transmit it by deep-sea cable to Honolulu on the main island of Oahu, reports Maurice Kaya, energy administrator for the state's Department of Business and Economic Development.</p>
        <p>Several geothermal power plants are envisioned on private and state land in the East Rift zone of the volcano, he says, and early indications are that this is ''technically feasible.'' But the transmission of the power is an engineering challenge that is ''pushing the state of the art of laying an undersea cable.''</p>
        <p>The power cable will have to traverse ocean canyons that are 6,000 to 7,000 feet deep, a feat never before done, Mr. Kaya says. A cable made by the Pirelli Cable Company of Milan, Italy, is being tested, he says, ''to see if it can withstand the forces and stresses and carry the currents and voltages.''</p>
        <p>If all goes well, Mr. Kaya says, starting in 1995, the Hawaii Electric Light Company could start integrating the new geothermal power into its system. The utility already operates a model three-megawatt geothermal plant at Kilauea and says the concept is sound.</p>
        <p>FOLLOW-UP ON THE NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
