<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Emma Bloomberg, Christopher Frissora</title>
    <meta content="12BLOO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20050619T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1679611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLOOMBERG, EMMA BETH (EMMA BETH FRISSORA)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRISSORA, CHRISTOPHER PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E5DA1138F931A25755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="220" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Emma Bloomberg, Christopher Frissora</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Emma Beth Bloomberg was married to Christopher Paul Frissora last evening by her father, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg. The wedding was held at the home of the bride's mother, Susan E.B. Bloomberg, in North Salem, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom is a son of Jennifer Frissora and Mark P. Frissora of Lake Forest, Ill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Emma Beth Bloomberg was married to Christopher Paul Frissora last evening by her father, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg. The wedding was held at the home of the bride's mother, Susan E.B. Bloomberg, in North Salem, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom is a son of Jennifer Frissora and Mark P. Frissora of Lake Forest, Ill.</p>
        <p>Both the bride, 26, and the bridegroom, 25, are candidates for M.B.A.'s and master's degrees in public administration at Harvard. They met at Princeton, from which they both graduated, the bride magna cum laude.</p>
        <p>The bride's father was elected the 108th mayor of New York in 2001. He is also the founder and the majority owner of Bloomberg, the financial information and media company. The bride's mother is on the board of Puppies Behind Bars, a program in New York through which inmates at maximum security prisons raise dogs that eventually are trained to guide the blind or to detect explosives.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom's father is the chairman and the chief executive of Tenneco Automotive, the supplier of automotive components, in Lake Forest. He is also a member of the Business Roundtable, an association of chief executive officers.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 19, 2005, Sunday  A report last Sunday about the wedding of Emma Beth Bloomberg and Christopher Paul Frissora included an outdated reference to the time and place of the ceremony. After the section had gone to press, The Times learned that Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, the bride's father, officiated on Friday at a small private marriage ceremony at Gracie Mansion. The mayor's spokesman later said the change became necessary when the mayor's office learned that Mr. Bloomberg's legal authority did not extend to North Salem, N.Y., where the mayor performed another ceremony, symbolically, on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 19, 2005, Sunday</p>
        <p>A report last Sunday about the wedding of Emma Beth Bloomberg and Christopher Paul Frissora included an outdated reference to the time and place of the ceremony. After the section had gone to press, The Times learned that Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, the bride's father, officiated on Friday at a small private marriage ceremony at Gracie Mansion. The mayor's spokesman later said the change became necessary when the mayor's office learned that Mr. Bloomberg's legal authority did not extend to North Salem, N.Y., where the mayor performed another ceremony, symbolically, on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
