<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Town, Another Civil Action</title>
    <meta content="12DUPO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1391787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pompton Lakes (Nj)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Du Pont De Nemours, E I, &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pearce, Jeremy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDA1030F931A25756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1344" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Town, Another Civil Action</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEREMY PEARCE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pearce, Jeremy</byline>
      <dateline>POMPTON LAKES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on trial in Pompton Lakes, NJ, in suit brought by group of residents against E I du Pont de Nemours &amp; Co, claiming that industrial water pollution from blasting cap production has caused deaths, miscarriages and cancer rate four times national average; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is something about the water in Pompton Lakes, a town built around rivers, lakes and rushing brooks.</p>
        <p>Visited by Washington during the Revolution and a cradle of early industry in Passaic County -- home to some of New Jersey's main reservoirs -- the town has recorded its history in cannons, statues and, yes, water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is something about the water in Pompton Lakes, a town built around rivers, lakes and rushing brooks.</p>
        <p>Visited by Washington during the Revolution and a cradle of early industry in Passaic County -- home to some of New Jersey's main reservoirs -- the town has recorded its history in cannons, statues and, yes, water.</p>
        <p>Last week, in a cumbersome civil trial trying to unravel Pompton's past, a group of residents rested their case after claiming that water polluted here by industry caused deaths, miscarriages and a cancer rate four times the national average. The residents are suing E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, the chemical giant that made blasting caps within a 600-acre compound in Pompton Lakes for more than nine decades.</p>
        <p>The trial has divided the town into two groups, those who view DuPont -- once Pompton's largest employer -- as a major benefactor, and the 1,600 residents behind the lawsuit who see the company as the borough's major polluter. The factory has been shut since 1994, and DuPont settled an earlier pollution suit five years ago, paying a group of local litigants $38.5 million. This week, the company plans to mount its legal defense in court.</p>
        <p>''I drink the water, I bathe in the water,'' said Leon G. Feinbloom, a real estate agent and longtime resident who is not involved in the case. ''We're a very wet community. But if I didn't know Pompton Lakes before this, I'd be scared to death.''</p>
        <p>State regulators have found mercury, lead and other metals and solvents in groundwater and in Acid Brook, which crosses DuPont's property and empties into Pompton Lake itself -- a popular fishing and boating spot -- although tests show that contaminants are not tainting the municipal water system. DuPont was not fined for the releases, but has spent $130 million to restore the brook and some residential basements since the 1980's.</p>
        <p>''People ask, if you started this in the 1980's, why aren't you done cleaning it up?'' said G. Irvin Lipp, a DuPont spokesman. ''There is no doubt we have cleanup to work on. We are working to stabilize the contaminants and to keep them on the site.''</p>
        <p>The trial may be gaining wider interest because it follows a familiar New Jersey story line -- another town forced toward reconciling a clouded industrial past with questions about present-day public health.</p>
        <p>In December, for example, residents in Toms River reached an out-of-court settlement with Union Carbide Corporation, Ciba Specialty Chemicals Corporation and United Water Resources, a water supplier, after chemicals were found to be leaking from hazardous waste landfills into the town's public water system. Residents believe that exposure through drinking water to pollutants has caused high cancer rates among local children.</p>
        <p>On federal Superfund lists, New Jersey remains the most heavily polluted state in the nation, with 111 sites according to the federal Environmental Protection Agency. DuPont's property in Pompton Lakes is not considered a Superfund site, but a state-ordered plan for cleaning the land was drafted in 1988.</p>
        <p>DuPont is involved in a similar lawsuit in Mississippi, where workers at the its Delisle chemical manufacturing plant have alleged soaring cancer rates, miscarriages and neurological problems tied to plant emissions of dioxins. Further, some 1,500 plaintiffs are also suing the state itself, which has said the region's cancer rates were normal.</p>
        <p>The Pompton Lakes trial, under way for the past month in Passaic County Superior Court in Paterson, has been watched by hundreds of residents, many of them among the roughly 1,600 plaintiffs. (Making the legal picture more complex, a separate federal lawsuit filed by 400 residents awaits trial in Newark.) In the state case, residents are requesting $80 million to study their medical conditions and an unspecified amount in damages. Part of the lawsuit involves more than 20 charges of wrongful death from pollution-related illnesses, but Judge Frank M. Donato has elected initially to hear 10 cases picked at random.</p>
        <p>''These cases were chosen, literally, out of a box,'' said Paul R. Garelick, an Edison lawyer representing the residents.</p>
        <p>Jurors have heard testimony from James Dahlgren, an environmental toxicologist hired by the plaintiffs to examine local cancer rates. Dr. Dahlgren said that he found the rates to be four times the national average and that some residents in his study had depleted immune systems. Cancer rates for children were also abnormally high, he testified. DuPont's lawyers questioned the study's methods in cross-examination, and cited a state health department study from 1994 that they said showed no elevated instances of cancer in the town.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, lawyers for the residents played videotaped testimony by Joseph Tachine, a retired DuPont maintenance worker. Mr. Tachine, who is also a plaintiff, said that he was ordered to bury at least 60 barrels of motor oil and solvents and that hundreds of other barrels had been similarly disposed of. DuPont officials later responded that the company had excavated the area and uncovered only a few empty barrels.</p>
        <p>Last week, accompanied by reporters and Judge Donato, jurors made a visit to the DuPont property in order to view for themselves Acid Brook, empty lagoons, ponds and other water bodies that plaintiffs say have spread contamination further. Across from the property's entrance, jurors may have also glimpsed backhoes scratching out a residential development called the Highlands. Real estate agents and borough officials said the trial was having little effect on sale of local real estate.</p>
        <p>''People still want to buy into Pompton Lakes,'' said Carol Kehoe, the borough clerk. ''They see a sense of security here -- the white picket fence and the tree-lined streets. We have that.''</p>
        <p>In most cases of alleged cancer clusters, scientists are wary of identifying an absolute cause of illness. In the Toms River case, state and federal epidemiologists took five years to complete a $10 million study that even then noted ambiguities in pinning down causes of cancer. In Pompton Lakes, the plaintiffs are less hesitant: ''We feel we already have proven cancer, bladder cancer in our case, that was caused by metals and chemicals in Pompton Lakes drinking water and soils,'' Mr. Garelick said.</p>
        <p>Surprising to some plaintiffs, the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection has been largely silent since drafting the consent order to monitor groundwater and clean the soil and water in Acid Brook. State environmental officials said that the state had issued no fines or citations to DuPont and that officials have made no effort to speed up the cleanup.</p>
        <p>''DuPont has been cooperative in addressing the problems at the site,'' said Mary Helen Cervantes, a spokesman for the environmental department. ''That doesn't mean there isn't room for new and improved approaches to cleaning there.'' She declined to specify alternatives.</p>
        <p>Other residents continue to assert loyalty to a company that they say once stood at the core of the town's identity. Before DuPont moved the factory to Mexico, it was connected to a larger tradition of making fuses and blasting caps that began in Pompton Lakes in the 1880's. DuPont arrived in 1902 to supply caps for quarries and oil exploration concerns. Later operations included metal cladding -- bonding layers of metal -- said company officials, before DuPont began selling off its blasting businesses in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>Bill Branthwaite, a retiree who spends much of his time fishing Pompton's waters, said that whatever the result of the trial, he won't change the way he spends his afternoons.</p>
        <p>''I've been drinking out of these lakes for 50 years,'' Mr. Branthwaite said as he checked his lures. ''My kids have been fishing here all their lives, and it hasn't been a problem. The only problem we have is that DuPont treated this town too good.''</p>
        <p>THE ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
