<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BRING ON THE HIPPOS</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="49" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="124686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HIPPOPOTAMUSES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GULFSTREAM PARK</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRIST, STEVEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FLORIDA DERBY</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D91631F936A35750C0A96E948260" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BRING ON THE HIPPOS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN CRIST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CRIST, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>HALLANDALE, Fla.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Gulfstream Park will briefly change from a hippodrome to a hippo hippodrome this morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Gulfstream Park will briefly change from a hippodrome to a hippo hippodrome this morning.</p>
        <p>Gulfstream Park will briefly change from a hippodrome to a hippo hippodrome this morning.</p>
        <p>Three African hippopotamuses will waddle down the stretch, straining for the same finish line that will decide the winner of the Florida Derby for thoroughbred horses six hours later.</p>
        <p>The smart money says that the 650-pound pygmy hippo will outsprint the pair of 2,000-pound African hippos in this all-female, 120-yard waddle to the wire. My hippo sources also make it about 6-5 that bedlam will ensue if one of the hippos spies the infield lake, for she will surely bolt for the water and go for a wallow.</p>
        <p>The hippo race, the 21st annual wild-animal contest to be staged at Gulfstream, is an appropriately bizarre bit of pageantry because it refelects the weirdness of Florida racing.</p>
        <p>Racing at Gulfstream seems conducted through the looking glass, a nearly hallucinogenic version of the game.</p>
        <p>Imagine an afternoon at Aqueduct gone psychedelic. The walls turn pink and green. Tropical shrubbery and purple flowers spring up everywhere. Twelve horses contest each race. Trifectas are offered every half hour. Mystery horses from South America dot the entries. First-time starters by sires you've never heard of fill the maiden races. Aging jockeys and horses who disappeared years ago return from oblivion for one last moment in the sun.</p>
        <p>This goes on for 49 seemingly surreal days, and then suddenly turns sober. Come Florida Derby Day, once the zoo animals leave the track, it's time to get serious about the Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>Gulfstream closes today, and the local racing moves to Calder, not to Hialeah, as it did last year and will next year. The Florida Derby runners will be leaving town, because conventional wisdom says that Calder is not the place to race a star 3-year-old in the weeks leading to the Derby. Hialeah, which is angry with Calder for winning its spring dates this year, is trying to make sure that these 3-year-olds do not race at Calder.</p>
        <p>The three tracks in the Miami area devote most of their energies to fighting one another in a perpetual battle over prime racing dates and patrons. Their petulance does more damage to the sport than to their rivals. This year, the horses are the victims.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Calder closed its stable area, citing a need for much-needed repairs, during Hialeah's winter meeting. Horses were turned out at local farms instead of raced at Hialeah.</p>
        <p>So this year, Hialeah officials tried to serve up some revenge. They announced last month that they would close their stables March 15, a week into the Calder meeting. Hialeah did this after promising Northern trainers that it would stay open until early April, when these stables can move back into their New York stables, currently occupied by winter outfits.</p>
        <p>The New York trainers, who did Hialeah a favor by shipping south earlier than usual to contest Hialeah's first-ever fall meeting, feel betrayed, caught in the middle of the childish war among the tracks. Hialeah's claim that it badly needs the time to make stable repairs is bogus. The track will not reopen until next March, and the minor repairs could certainly wait until next month.</p>
        <p>Woody Stephens, John Veitch, Tom Skiffington, Howie Tesher and Phil Gleaves are among the trainers whose horses will be thrown out onto Palm Avenue in 10 days unless Hialeah officials relent.</p>
        <p>Florida's track operators would be wise to realize that these New York stables are not going to put up with this nonsense indefinitely just to enjoy a couple of months in the sun.</p>
        <p>Texas has legalized parimutuel racing, and California's purses grow more attractive each year. If the New Yorkers stop coming to Florida, the racing here might as well be run at Calder all year long. It will be a dreary local numbers game devoid of national importance. The Florida Derby will crown either Forty Niner, Ruhlmann or Cherokee Colony as the solid early favorite for the Kentucky Derby May 7. The race is the best and richest so far this year, but will hold that distinction for only a day. The Santa Anita Handicap in California tomorrow offers a $1 million rematch between the last two Kentucky Derby winners.</p>
        <p>Remember Ferdinand and Alysheba? When they finished a nose apart in that order in the $3 million Breeders' Cup Classic 14 weeks ago, the sport's major titles were decided and the race was called the best in a decade. They will meet tomorrow for the first time since then, and the nation yawns.</p>
        <p>Santa Anita will attract its usual season-high crowd of more than 65,000 for the race, but you have to be there to see it. ESPN offered to show it between periods of a hockey game if the track would move the race back half an hour on the program, but Santa Anita balked.</p>
        <p>The race comes up a peculiar one, with only five horses entered, three of them trained by Charlie Whittingham. He will send out Ferdinand, Judge Angelucci and Temperate Sil, who among them will probably earn most of the $1 million purse for facing Alysheba and Super Diamond. Under California's questionable racing rules, the three Whittingham trainees will race as separate betting interests.</p>
        <p>Horses with the same trainer should always race as a single betting interest. It's a little bit like the hippopotamus race, where all three beasts have the same trainer. If there were parimutuel wagering on that event, bettors would be a little wary of which hippo the stable was trying to score with.</p>
        <p>That's what happened last month at Santa Anita in the San Antonio Handicap, where Whittngham sent out half the field. He won with Judge Angelucci as a long shot, while Ferdinand had some useful exercise in his seasonal debut, and was not unduly pressured to reward those who bet on him as the heavy favorite.</p>
        <p>Presumably, every horse will be fully extended for $1 million tomorrow, and Ferdinand is supposed to be the best of his stable, if not the nation, but the whole thing is unseemly - epecially because Whittingham is a co-owner of Temperate Sil but not of the other two.</p>
        <p>So here is what we have for the year's best weekend of racing: the favorite for the Kentucky Derby faces eviction, and California bettors try to outguess the stable monopolizing a $1 million race. Bring on the hippos.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
