<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Long History and Longer Menu</title>
    <meta content="05DINE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1453908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bengal Tiger (White Plains, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7DD123FF936A35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Long History and Longer Menu</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Bengal Tiger restaurant in White Plains, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INDIAN spices could be the inspiration for the decor at Bengal Tiger. The hues of chilies, cinnamon, turmeric, fennel, mustard, cumin and coriander, to name a few, are echoed in the dazzling patchwork canopies tenting the space of the narrow dining rooms. Indian sculpture and tapestries and sconces shedding mellow light line the walls.</p>
        <p>In one dining area, a glass wall reveals the tandoori kitchen, where a cook usually works two vertical cylindrical clay ovens called tandoors. He slaps dough for nan bread to the sides of the oven and drops long skewers threaded with chicken and shrimp into its roasting depths.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INDIAN spices could be the inspiration for the decor at Bengal Tiger. The hues of chilies, cinnamon, turmeric, fennel, mustard, cumin and coriander, to name a few, are echoed in the dazzling patchwork canopies tenting the space of the narrow dining rooms. Indian sculpture and tapestries and sconces shedding mellow light line the walls.</p>
        <p>In one dining area, a glass wall reveals the tandoori kitchen, where a cook usually works two vertical cylindrical clay ovens called tandoors. He slaps dough for nan bread to the sides of the oven and drops long skewers threaded with chicken and shrimp into its roasting depths.</p>
        <p>Simpson Kalathara, the owner of Bengal Tiger since its inception almost 30 years ago, manages to keep his dining rooms buzzing with diners intrigued by the haunting, myriad flavors of Indian cuisine.</p>
        <p>Never static, the well-annotated menu has grown over the years and now lists more than 100 dishes. An ever-changing special menu offers regional dishes. While shrimp has always been on the menu, fish, a great omission in this restaurant's past offerings, now makes an appearance in the form of halibut. Can pomfret, mackerel and sardines -- no strangers in Indian cuisine -- be far behind?</p>
        <p>Recent specials come from the Malabar Coast of India's southwest, a tropical region lush in vegetation; the dishes are redolent of ginger, coconut, cardamom, black peppers and a variety of hot chilies.</p>
        <p>Rolled into a long glossy cylinder stuffed with a potato mixture, masala dosa starts a meal nicely. Begin by shattering the thin crust at the roll's middle, nearest the filling. Plump pastries called samosa are lovely as well, whether filled with ground lamb or potato. Two or three diners might share kebab ''cocktail,'' an assortment of tandoori-cooked shrimp, minced lamb and chicken kebabs.</p>
        <p>Portions of shrimp and gingery halibut steamed in a banana leaf are small, making seafood the most expensive item on the menu. But shrimp is worth having, either for appetizer or entree. It is prepared in a number of appealing ways: sauteed with onions, ginger and garlic; marinated and baked or roasted on a skewer in the tandoor, where the charcoal adds its own subtle flavor.</p>
        <p>Straightforward kebabs cooked in the tandoor have improved recently and arrived succulent.</p>
        <p>Lamb is the classic vehicle here, as it is for a delectable stew in the Balti style, served in an iron casserole filled with vegetables, mint and fenugreek; and for patties ground with onions and seasonings, like a savory meat loaf. Only a lamb dish called aterechi olathiyathu proved disappointing; the lamb arrived blackened.</p>
        <p>For diners allergic to nuts, the menu now warns when nuts have been used. Often ground and imperceptible, nuts are employed to enrich the flavor and texture of some dishes.</p>
        <p>Spinach-based items are a personal favorite. The spinach, or saag, is pureed into a mild sauce brightened by a touch of fresh ginger, tomato, coriander and cumin. Chicken, goat or vegetarian dishes are especially delicious with saag.</p>
        <p>Vegetarian dishes, like cauliflower and potato, or cottage cheese and saag, remain a delight. An order of angoori paneer, an irresistible new entry, brought a bowl of grape-size dumplings of seasoned cheese bobbing in light brown gravy.</p>
        <p>Rice or soft, warm bread called nan sops the sauces nicely. Add some raita (cool yogurt with chopped cucumber) to temper dishes that are too hot.</p>
        <p>End with mango ice cream. Or try the rice pudding; flavored by cardamom and rose water, it is delicious, if a tad heavy after an Indian meal.</p>
        <p>Beverages will suit all palates: spice tea, mango lassi (a sweet yogurt drink), and especially Indian beer or wines on the sweet side -- like Riesling or Vouvray -- balance the feisty flavors of this cuisine.</p>
        <p>Bengal Tiger  144 East Post Road,  White Plains.  (914) 948-5191.</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE Long, narrow dining areas lined with Indian art, pretty sconces and brilliant wall and ceiling hangings. Helpful, snappy service. Small but well-stocked retail shop for Indian groceries and gift items is next door.  RECOMMENDED DISHES Masala dosa, samosa, tandoori items, all shrimp dishes, chicken and minced lamb kebabs, halibut, Balti lamb, chicken curry, chicken do-piaz, saag dishes (spinach sauce), cauliflower and potatoes (aloo gobi), angoori paneer (cottage cheese dumplings), paneer palak, nan, dal, raita, rice pudding.  PRICES Buffet lunch, Mondays through Saturdays, $11; Sundays, $16. Dinner, main dishes, $11 to $27.  CREDIT CARDS Major cards accepted.  HOURS Buffet lunch, Mondays through Saturdays, 11:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 2:30 p.m. Dinner, Sundays through Thursdays, 5 to 10:30 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 5 to 11 p.m.  RESERVATIONS None accepted.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY Street level.  THE RATINGS Excellent, Very good, Good, Satisfactory, Poor.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambience and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
