<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mutual Funds Report; A Bond Manager Says It's Time for a Dose of Risk</title>
    <meta content="05BOND$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/05/business/yourmoney/05BOND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1454068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pimco Total Return Fund</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pimco Advisors Holdings</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDE1F3FF936A35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mutual Funds Report; A Bond Manager Says It's Time for a Dose of Risk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Bond Manager Says It's Time for a Dose of Risk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pimco Total Return fund portfolio manager Bill Gross comments on bond market outlook, interview; says he will be buying more emerging-market debt to keep yields competitive; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN mid-December, Bill Gross, the portfolio manager of the $66 billion Pimco Total Return fund, shifted about 15 percent of the money in his personal 401(k) account into riskier territory: emerging-markets bonds and American junk bonds.</p>
        <p>Other bond investors may also want to consider such moves because, as Mr. Gross put it, ''the salad days of the bond market are over.'' He is already adding risk to the Total Return portfolio, the world's largest mutual fund.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For three years, bonds have outperformed stocks by a wide margin. Now Bill Gross, the portfolio manager of the Pimco Total Return fund, thinks bond prices and yields will stagnate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN mid-December, Bill Gross, the portfolio manager of the $66 billion Pimco Total Return fund, shifted about 15 percent of the money in his personal 401(k) account into riskier territory: emerging-markets bonds and American junk bonds.</p>
        <p>Other bond investors may also want to consider such moves because, as Mr. Gross put it, ''the salad days of the bond market are over.'' He is already adding risk to the Total Return portfolio, the world's largest mutual fund.</p>
        <p>For three years, bonds have outperformed stocks by a wide margin. Now Mr. Gross thinks bond prices and yields will neither fall nor rise very much, which means that a small stock market rally could leave bonds in second place this year.</p>
        <p>As recently as last fall, Mr. Gross took a different view. Bonds were more attractive then because he worried about deflation and thought stocks would not be fairly valued until the Dow Jones industrial average fell to 5,000.</p>
        <p>He is more sanguine about the economic outlook now but still does not think the economy is ready to take off. ''I don't think it will necessarily thrive,'' he said, ''but I think it will survive.''</p>
        <p>In this lukewarm environment, he does not think that his Total Return fund will be able to do better than a return of 4 percent to 5 percent this year, about half the fund's return in 2002 and in 2001 and well below the 11.6 percent return in 2000.</p>
        <p>The reason for the lower expected return is simple: interest rates fell last year to levels not seen in decades and, absent another recession or some new terrorist attack, they cannot go much lower, he said. The yield on the Treasury's 10-year note fell to 3.57 percent in October, the lowest since 1958. By Dec. 31, that yield had risen to only 3.82 percent.</p>
        <p>If bond yields don't fall, there will be no capital gain for investors as bond prices, which move in the opposite direction, rise. Last year, half the 11.6 percent total return from the Treasury market came from the rise in prices as yields fell.</p>
        <p>The return for investors this year is likely to be just the interest rate on the bonds they own, minus some capital losses as interest rates rise modestly and push prices lower, Mr. Gross said.</p>
        <p>To get a return of 4 to 5 percent, Mr. Gross said, he will have to add some risk to the Pimco portfolio by moving money from safe Treasuries to emerging-markets bonds from countries like Brazil and Mexico, which offer much higher interest rates.</p>
        <p>In an interview last month, Mr. Gross said he expected to increase the holdings of emerging-markets bonds in the Total Return fund to 5 percent from 4 percent during the first quarter this year.</p>
        <p>He might also pick up a ''pinch'' of high-yield, or junk, bonds for the Total Return fund, he said. But while he likes junk bonds for his own portfolio, he is more comfortable in the Total Return fund with bonds like those of AT&amp;T and Sprint, which are at the bottom of the investment grade category but still offer yields like those of junk bonds. He said that emerging-markets bonds gave him as high a risk position as high-yield bonds. But, he added, ''I would not dissuade investors who cannot buy a 30-year Mexican bond or a Brazilian C bond'' on their own. ''I wouldn't dissuade them from buying a pinch of high yield,'' he said.</p>
        <p>High-yield, emerging-markets and low-rated investment grade bonds bolster return in two ways. First, the bonds pay higher interest rates, easily more than twice those of comparable Treasuries. The other boost is through capital gains.</p>
        <p>IN improving economy in the United States and abroad is likely to be more of a plus for riskier bonds than for Treasuries.</p>
        <p>Economic growth may make investors worry about inflation and shift their assets into stocks, diminishing demand for all bonds. But a stronger economy can markedly improve the outlook for emerging-markets economies and the companies that sell junk bonds or lower-rated investment grade bonds. As a result, their prices are not as likely to fall as much as those of Treasuries, giving them a better total return.</p>
        <p>But an investor has to pick the right time to take on added risk. As it turned out, 2002 might not have been the best year to do that because the Treasury market did quite well. Many bond fund managers, including Mr. Gross, did not think that Treasuries could rally as much as they did last year, so they lifted their exposure to higher-yield bonds, like those from emerging markets, downtrodden telecommunications companies and European governments to bolster return.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Gross's case, this meant that he had less invested in Treasuries than his benchmark, the Lehman Brothers U.S. Aggregate Index, so outperforming the benchmark was difficult. In 2002, after fees, the fund had a total return of 9.69 percent, less than the 10.26 percent return for the index.</p>
        <p>The return for the year and the gap between the fund's performance and the index's would have been worse if not for a November-December rally in some of his telecommunications, emerging-market and German bonds. Through September, his fund had a return of 7.57 percent, compared with 8.55 percent for the index.</p>
        <p>''It was a November-December miracle,'' he said, adding that the interest rate cut by the European Central Bank in December finally enabled the German bonds he owned to outperform American Treasuries.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Gross is taking on more risk, he said he would be restrained, a reminder of an important reason for buying bonds: they are safer investments than stocks. The goal of the Total Return fund is to make just one percentage point more than its benchmark, which Mr. Gross failed to do last year.</p>
        <p>Based on current interest rates, he estimated that the return on the Lehman Brothers U.S. Aggregate for 2003 should be about 4.3 percent, so his fund's target for the year is 5.3 percent.</p>
        <p>But for Mr. Gross, falling short of his goal does not mean he will pile on more risk to bolster returns.</p>
        <p>''A bond investor has to know the market is not always going to turn in near double-digit returns,'' he said. ''And I don't feel that I have to go and get it for them. The way you survive is to scout out relative opportunities and shrink back into the woodwork when they are not there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
