<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese-American Gloom on Canvas, Circa '42</title>
    <meta content="28ARTS$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/28/arts/28ARTS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1281253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS IN AMERICA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Japanese-Americans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Japanese-American National Museum (Los Angeles)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinraub, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sugimoto, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arkansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arkansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Japanese-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pearl Harbor</location>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Fresno</location>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Los Angeles</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Tokyo</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Wakayama</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Arkansas</location>
        <location class="online_producer">San Francisco</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Central Park</location>
        <org class="online_producer">assembly center</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Smithsonian Institution</org>
        <org class="online_producer">West Side</org>
        <org class="online_producer">church</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Relocation Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5DF1F3CF93BA15750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese-American Gloom on Canvas, Circa '42</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weinraub, Bernard</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, March 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First retrospective survey by Japanese-American artist Henry Sugimoto opens at Japanese-American National Museum in downtown Los Angeles (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several months after the attack on Pearl Harbor, Henry Sugimoto, his wife and their 6-year-old daughter were interned with other Japanese-Americans in California and sent to an assembly center in Fresno. Mr. Sugimoto had been a rising artist, trained in France and known as a painter of the placid fields and lush landscapes of rural California. Almost as soon as he was interned he began sketching somber portraits of the Japanese-American families devastated by government policy.</p>
        <p>''The internment experience completely transformed him, and it continued for the rest of Sugimoto's life,'' said Kristine Kim, associate curator at the Japanese American National Museum in downtown Los Angeles, the only museum in the nation focusing on the Japanese-American experience. ''He no longer looked to nature for inspiration for his art but instead depicted on canvas his personal experiences, his beliefs.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Several months after the attack on Pearl Harbor, Henry Sugimoto, his wife and their 6-year-old daughter were interned with other Japanese-Americans in California and sent to an assembly center in Fresno. Mr. Sugimoto had been a rising artist, trained in France and known as a painter of the placid fields and lush landscapes of rural California. Almost as soon as he was interned he began sketching somber portraits of the Japanese-American families devastated by government policy.</p>
        <p>''The internment experience completely transformed him, and it continued for the rest of Sugimoto's life,'' said Kristine Kim, associate curator at the Japanese American National Museum in downtown Los Angeles, the only museum in the nation focusing on the Japanese-American experience. ''He no longer looked to nature for inspiration for his art but instead depicted on canvas his personal experiences, his beliefs.''</p>
        <p>The first retrospective survey of more than 100 paintings by Mr. Sugimoto, who spent his postwar years in Manhattan, opened on Saturday at the museum in the Little Tokyo section of Los Angeles. The  show offers not only a glimpse into the internment -- which has rarely been explored in art and, for that matter, in movies and television -- but also seeks to explore the life of a relatively unknown artist whose career was cut short by his incarceration and who never regained his footing.</p>
        <p>Lawrence M. Small, secretary of the Smithsonian Institution, which has three paintings by Mr. Sugimoto in its permanent collection, said that the artist once wrote that he was most concerned about ''leaving my mark on this world.'' Mr. Small said that he need not have worried, adding, ''Initially in secret and then openly, Sugimoto created an extensive series of paintings that powerfully capture that painful time'' and ''he conveys the struggles, suffering and complexity of life in a detention camp.'' The show runs through Sept. 16.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sugimoto, who was born in Wakayama, Japan, and was the grandson of a samurai, moved to Hanford, Calif., when he was 19. He died at the age of 90 in 1990, living after the war in apartments on the Upper West Side and in Hamilton Heights. His daughter, Madeleine Sumile Sugimoto, who lives in New York, said her father moved there after the family was released from an internment camp in Arkansas largely because he had always yearned to experience the artistic life in the city.</p>
        <p>''When the government said we could go home, my father talked to my mother and said we were halfway to New York already -- why not go?'' recalled Ms. Sugimoto, a retired nursing educator. ''It was 1945. The government gave us $25 each. It was a precarious existence.'' Ms. Sugimoto said her mother, Susie, was the principal breadwinner, working as a church secretary. (She died in 1987). Mr. Sugimoto painted all day at home, using only available sunlight. He also created fabric patterns for a textile company. Ms. Sugimoto said her father had several one-man shows at New York galleries and sold some paintings over the years.</p>
        <p>But bad luck dogged him. A one-man show at the Galerie Internationale that Mr. Sugimoto had hoped would bring a commercial breakthrough was ignored in part because of the 114-day New York newspaper strike, which started in late 1962. ''It was a tremendous disappointment, and after that he really felt sad,'' Ms. Sugimoto said.</p>
        <p>His internment at two camps in Arkansas left him melancholy and broken in spirit, but it also gave his work a depth and poignancy that were absent from his earlier optimistic canvasses, which were clearly derived from French and Mexican muralists.</p>
        <p>He painted the lavishly beautiful California landscapes of Yosemite and the Carmel Coast as well as the French countryside. In the decade before World War II, he had a one-man show at the California Palace of the Legion of Honor in San Francisco and participated in Los Angeles in a group exhibition of artists with Asian backgrounds. A brochure at the Legion of Honor called Mr. Sugimoto ''a rising artist, whose achievements are the results of unceasing endeavor, strong will power and perseverance.''</p>
        <p>The Museum of Modern Art in New York offered to exhibit his paintings in the mid-1930's, but he declined because he had committed the paintings to other California museums. He later regretted the decision and attributed it to his inexperience with the art world.</p>
        <p>The government suspected all Japanese of being unpatriotic, and as soon as Mr. Sugimoto and his family were interned he began painting realistic pictures of the life he saw: Japanese mothers with infants and fathers carrying suitcases as they left their homes; inmates gathering wood to warm their barracks; a family huddled around a heater; a communal washroom; families eating in a mess hall. The work was almost uniformly bleak, the faces sad.</p>
        <p>Several portraits show Japanese-Americans leaving the internment camp after enlisting in the American armed forces. Years after his release, Mr. Sugimoto still painted and created woodblock prints of life at the Jerome Relocation Center in southeastern Arkansas.</p>
        <p>There were also sketches of Central Park and New York and portraits based on his research, including images of Japanese immigrants working on farms or the railroad or confronting signs with epithets proclaiming that they were unwelcome.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kim, the curator, said that Mr. Sugimoto was unusual in choosing to depict the internment because many Japanese-Americans simply wanted to forget the experience.</p>
        <p>''He obviously was working through, over the years, what he saw and felt in those years that he was interned,'' Ms. Kim said. ''Very few did that. They didn't want to talk about it. There was shame. They wanted to restart their lives. But Sugimoto was constantly re-envisioning it.''</p>
        <p>Irene Y. Hirano, executive director of the museum, which is at the site of a former Buddhist temple, said that in some ways Mr. Sugimoto's career and life reflect those of many Japanese-Americans in ways that are not tangible. ''Clearly there was the dollar impact of the war in terms of homes and property and personal possessions and family treasures that were lost and never recovered,'' she said. ''But what's difficult to measure is the loss of potential careers, the loss of someone's livelihood.''</p>
        <p>''In this case a gifted artist's life was severely altered by the war. Had the war not come along, his career and life would have been so different. How can you measure that loss?''</p>
        <p>ARTS IN AMERICA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
