<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>March Survey Of Consumers Is Brighter</title>
    <meta content="Y28ECO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/28/business/28ECON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1281310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Confidence (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Conference Board</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlantic</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Reserve Board</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Merrill Lynch &amp; Company Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Nomura Securities</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenspan, Alan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinberg, Bruce</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2D81F3CF93BA15750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>March Survey Of Consumers Is Brighter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stock rise sharply after Conference Board reports that its consumer confidence index rose to 117.0 in March from 109.2 in February, first increase since September; economists are reluctant to read much into one monthly figure, but say recent decline in consumer confidence may be bottoming out; graphs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A crucial measure of consumer confidence rebounded sharply in March after falling for five consecutive months.</p>
        <p>Financial markets interpreted the data, which were much better than anticipated, optimistically. Stock prices jumped after the figures were released at 10 a.m. By the close, all three major market indexes had risen by more than 2.5 percent. [Page C13.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A crucial measure of consumer confidence rebounded sharply in March after falling for five consecutive months.</p>
        <p>Financial markets interpreted the data, which were much better than anticipated, optimistically. Stock prices jumped after the figures were released at 10 a.m. By the close, all three major market indexes had risen by more than 2.5 percent. [Page C13.]</p>
        <p>But economists were reluctant to read much into one monthly figure from the Conference Board. They said the recent decline in consumer attitudes might be bottoming out, which should help put a floor under measures like retail sales.</p>
        <p>Alan Greenspan, chairman of the Federal Reserve Board, has said many times in recent months that he considers consumer sentiment an important economic barometer.</p>
        <p>Economists pointed out that the performance of one indicator over one three-week period said little about the overall health of the economy and practically nothing about whether the Fed would cut short-term interest rates before its next scheduled meeting in May.</p>
        <p>Additional economic data, including employment figures for March, are expected to be a factor in determining when, or if, the Fed will make a move.</p>
        <p>''No matter how much importance Mr. Greenspan puts on the confidence data, both the equity and the bond market are probably overreacting'' to the new figures, said Bruce Steinberg, chief economist at Merrill Lynch &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>In its monthly report, which covered the first three weeks of March, the Conference Board said its consumer confidence index rose to 117.0 from 109.2 in February. It was the first increase since September.</p>
        <p>The Conference Board's monthly survey is based on a representative sample of 5,000 households across the country and is considered an important indicator because consumer spending accounts for two-thirds of the nation's economic activity.</p>
        <p>The confidence index reached an all-time high of 144.7 in January 2000. It reached that level again in May last year.</p>
        <p>Given the generally gloomy news that has been released so far this month, most economists had expected the index to post a decline. Consumer attitudes about the present situation were little changed from a month ago, but expectations about what the economy would look like in six months were much brighter.</p>
        <p>''If confidence is stabilizing, all that says is that consumer spending won't take off,'' said Donald J. Fine, chief market analyst and managing director at J. P. Morgan Chase. ''These numbers are strong historically, but well off the recent peaks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fine and other economists said that despite the improvement, consumer confidence remained fragile.</p>
        <p>Indeed, since the list of companies announcing layoffs and lower earnings rose in the first three weeks of March and since stock prices have moved sharply lower, the surprise is that confidence rose at all.</p>
        <p>Lynn Franco, director of the consumer research center at the Conference Board, said that as bad as things seemed earlier in March, those surveyed considered things even worse in January and February.</p>
        <p>''Fuel bills have been a bit smaller,'' Ms. Franco said, ''and the shock of the dramatic slowdown from the first half of last year to the second half has lessened a bit.''</p>
        <p>''And there could also be a sense that the Fed is on the case,'' she added. ''One would expect the effects of easier monetary policy to filter through the system relatively soon. That may alleviate concerns about conditions getting much worse.''</p>
        <p>Should the March employment report show a spike in the unemployment rate, the sense of unease could quickly return, economists said. Those figures are expected to be released on April 6.</p>
        <p>''We have had a pretty ugly trend in initial unemployment insurance claims for the last five or six weeks,'' said David Resler, chief economist at Nomura Securities International.</p>
        <p>''If that trend continues or the numbers rise,'' Mr. Resler said, ''it will be something people will sit up and take note of. If there are many more layoffs, confidence will deteriorate.''</p>
        <p>Confidence rose in every section of the country except in the Middle Atlantic states, a region that includes New York. The consumer confidence index for the Middle Atlantic region slipped to 98.9 in March, from 101.8 in February. Respondents in the Middle Atlantic states were markedly less optimistic about the future than they had been in February.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
