<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pioneer Among Rabbis Helps Extend Blessing of Unions</title>
    <meta content="Y01LIVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1188343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Religion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Rabbi Shira Stern</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Conference of American Rabbis</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Shira (Rabbi)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E7DA103CF932A35757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pioneer Among Rabbis Helps Extend Blessing of Unions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <dateline>GREENSBORO, N.C.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Rabbi Shira Stern, co-president of Women's Rabbinic Network, caucus within Central Conference of American Rabbis, which drafted resolution that conference adopted, stating that conference will support any of its members who decide to officiate at union of two gay Jews; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RABBI Shira Stern counts herself among the ''first 50,'' which is shorthand for saying that she belongs to a pioneering generation within Judaism's Reform movement, that early group of women who first claimed a place in pulpits once reserved for men.</p>
        <p>''At the very beginning, we were truly groundbreakers,'' said Rabbi Stern, who was ordained in 1983, barely a decade after the movement's first female rabbi. In those days, she said, few people could conceive of ''a woman in a position of power within a religious, Jewish context.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RABBI Shira Stern counts herself among the ''first 50,'' which is shorthand for saying that she belongs to a pioneering generation within Judaism's Reform movement, that early group of women who first claimed a place in pulpits once reserved for men.</p>
        <p>''At the very beginning, we were truly groundbreakers,'' said Rabbi Stern, who was ordained in 1983, barely a decade after the movement's first female rabbi. In those days, she said, few people could conceive of ''a woman in a position of power within a religious, Jewish context.''</p>
        <p>But if women were groundbreakers in Reform Judaism then, so they were once again this week, during the annual convention here of the movement's rabbinic organization, the Central Conference of American Rabbis.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the conference adopted a resolution, drafted by the Women's Rabbinic Network, a caucus within the organization, stating that the conference will support any of its members who decide to officiate at the union of two gay Jews. The conference, whose rabbis serve congregations with nearly 1.5 million members, became the largest religious body ever to take such a stand.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Stern, director of Jewish chaplaincy in Middlesex County, N.J., is one of the caucus's two presidents, along with Rabbi Susan B. Stone of Hudson, Ohio. Both are 1983 graduates of Hebrew Union College, which trains students for the Reform rabbinate.</p>
        <p>The two women were elected to head the caucus in March 1999 and, Rabbi Stern said, were immediately entrusted with the task of preparing the ground for a vote on the resolution. Given that she had already been an advocate for civil rights for gays, she said, ''I didn't have to be convinced this was the right thing to do.''</p>
        <p>They met with other rabbis in the movement to discuss the resolution and listen to their concerns. ''I have to say we incorporated a great many suggestions in the final document,'' Rabbi Stern said. ''It was truly a collaborative effort of rabbis across the country.''</p>
        <p>Rabbi Stern, 43, said she was taught a ''love of activism from birth.'' She grew up in New York City, the oldest of three children of Isaac Stern, the violinist, and Vera Stern. Her parents, she said, ''have fought the good fight'' on behalf of causes like support for Israel, liberty for Soviet Jews and efforts to discover what happened to Raoul Wallenberg, the Swedish businessman who rescued thousands of Hungarian Jews during World War II and disappeared after his arrest on espionage charges by Soviet authorities in 1945.</p>
        <p>In her childhood home, visitors dropped in to argue passionately about causes they believed needed help, Rabbi Stern said. ''There was always someone there who had a cause to plead and the good sense to do it in my parents' study, because they knew my parents would be responsive,'' she said. ''I truly believe individuals can make a difference, and that's something Don and I try to teach our children.''</p>
        <p>Don is Rabbi Donald A. Weber, her husband. They have three sons.</p>
        <p>NEITHER of the two rabbis has been asked to officiate at a gay union. ''As long as it's between two Jews, I'd be happy to do it,'' Rabbi Stern said.</p>
        <p>But as two married rabbis who have served separate congregations, the couple has become a role model to seminary students who are considering marrying each other. ''They call us,'' Rabbi Weber said, ''and they say, 'Tell us how it works.' '' Implicit in such a question are concerns like, Whose religious school do you send your children to?</p>
        <p>Rabbi Stern was 16 when she first laid eyes on a female rabbi. She can readily recall how exciting that was for her. She had gone with her mother to Sabbath services at the Stephen Wise Synagogue in New York, where the assistant rabbi there happened to be Sally Priesand, the first woman ever ordained in the Reform movement. The sight of Rabbi Priesand standing before the congregation was deeply moving for Rabbi Stern, who had been raised in a traditional synagogue where women sat in the balcony.</p>
        <p>When Rabbi Stern got to Brown University as a freshman in 1974, the first course she signed up for was an introduction to Judaism class. Two years later, she departed for a year's study at Hebrew University in Jerusalem, an experience she found thrilling. ''I loved doing biblical exegesis,'' she said. ''I loved doing Jewish history, surrounded by it.''</p>
        <p>After her ordination, she served a small congregation in New Jersey for 13 years. Recently, she took up her present position as head of the chaplaincy program, in which she supervises volunteers and makes visits to patients in no fewer than 13 institutions -- 4 hospitals, 8 nursing homes and a hospice.</p>
        <p>She may be, she said, the only professional who goes to visit these patients who is not there specifically to talk about medicine or to ask them medical questions. Instead, she listens to them, prays with them and sings to them, too. (The song should not be surprising, given that music runs in her family. Her two brothers, David and Michael, are both conductors.)</p>
        <p>These days, there are more than 300 women in the Reform rabbinate and although many may continue to see differences and difficulties in how they are treated compared with men, the passage of time and the growth of their numbers has worked some change.</p>
        <p>''We are much more of a known entity,'' Rabbi Stern said, ''and with that knowledge comes a certain amount of acceptance.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
