<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Switzerland With Lots of Buzz</title>
    <meta content="23ROCH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Travel; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/23/movies/23ROCH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1353612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rochlin, Margy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forster, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thornton, Billy Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berry, Halle</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Monster's Ball (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pacific Ocean</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Monster</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Thornton, Billy Bob</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDA153EF930A15751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="2104" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Switzerland With Lots of Buzz</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Switzerland With Lots of Buzz</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGY ROCHLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rochlin, Margy</byline>
      <dateline>TOPANGA, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Margy Rochlin profiles Swiss-born film director Marc Forster, whose latest project, Monster's Ball, starring Billy Bob Thornton and Halle Berry, may gain him recognition as one of Hollywood's hottest new talents; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH its hilltop Topanga Canyon location, outdoor hot tub and floor-to-ceiling glass windows framing an un obstructed view of a glittering Pacific Ocean, Marc Forster's home has all the trappings of a hot feature film director's. That is, for a few more days, until the wealthy owners of this remote hideaway return from the Caribbean, and Mr. Forster moves back to the tiny apartment he rents in nearby Santa Monica. ''If I could afford it, I would live like this,'' said Mr. Forster, who was only house-sitting for some friends this fall. ''But the choices I have made have led me down another path.''</p>
        <p>True, that path may not have gotten the Swiss-born Mr. Forster the fancy digs, but it's brought him a more valuable Hollywood commodity: buzz. Unknown less than a year ago, Mr. Forster has, at 31, gone from being the director of a first feature shot entirely on digital video for less than $10,000 to winning awards as a low-budget filmmaker to being entrusted with a highly praised and much passed-around script he then turned into a film that people are predicting will make him one of the hottest new talents in the business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 31-year-old Swiss-born director Marc Forster has moved quickly from unknown to about-to-be-A-list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH its hilltop Topanga Canyon location, outdoor hot tub and floor-to-ceiling glass windows framing an un obstructed view of a glittering Pacific Ocean, Marc Forster's home has all the trappings of a hot feature film director's. That is, for a few more days, until the wealthy owners of this remote hideaway return from the Caribbean, and Mr. Forster moves back to the tiny apartment he rents in nearby Santa Monica. ''If I could afford it, I would live like this,'' said Mr. Forster, who was only house-sitting for some friends this fall. ''But the choices I have made have led me down another path.''</p>
        <p>True, that path may not have gotten the Swiss-born Mr. Forster the fancy digs, but it's brought him a more valuable Hollywood commodity: buzz. Unknown less than a year ago, Mr. Forster has, at 31, gone from being the director of a first feature shot entirely on digital video for less than $10,000 to winning awards as a low-budget filmmaker to being entrusted with a highly praised and much passed-around script he then turned into a film that people are predicting will make him one of the hottest new talents in the business.</p>
        <p>That movie, ''Monster's Ball,'' scheduled to open Wednesday in New York and Los Angeles, is set in rural Georgia. It revolves around the emotional evolution of Hank Grotowski (Billy Bob Thornton), a bigoted death-row executioner who lives with his equally racist father (Peter Boyle), a retired prison guard, and his own son (Heath Ledger), a sensitive young man uncomfortable about entering the family line of work. The bleak routine that Hank calls his life consists of tending to his ailing, vitriolic father, eating vanilla ice cream late at night in his favorite empty restaurant, and ushering convicts to their electric-chair deaths with by-the-book rigidity. When a series of tragic circumstances brings Hank into contact with a luckless African-American woman, Leticia (Halle Berry), an unexpected romance develops.</p>
        <p>Since the film's first-time screenwriters, Milo Addica and Will Rokos, completed the script in 1995, it seems as if almost every member of Hollywood's antihero A-list has been attracted to this tale of a hard-shelled man who allows himself to be cracked open. Oliver Stone had been linked to the project, as had Tommy Lee Jones and Marlon Brando.</p>
        <p>''Sean Penn called me directly and said De Niro wanted to do it,'' said Mr. Addica, adding that he felt the stop-and-start process was worth it because, in the end, it meant landing the gentle, perceptive Mr. Forster. ''But it just didn't happen. The thing about all those guys is that they'd been there, done that; they had their own ideas about America. I knew that Marc, being from Switzerland, would be able to bring a fresh perspective to something very American Gothic. I don't want to sound corny here, but Marc was definitely the right guy for the gig. He seemed to understand the piece in his soul.''</p>
        <p>From an American point of view, perspectives don't get any more exotic than Mr. Forster's. He was raised in Klosters, the tiny Swiss ski resort known for its storybook vistas of shimmering blue lakes and snowcapped mountains. Because his father, Wolf, a doctor and scientist, and his mother, Ulli, a homemaker, disapproved of television and movies, Mr. Forster didn't see his first film until he was 12.</p>
        <p>''I just thought it was so beautiful, dreamlike,'' said Mr. Forster, who was taken by a friend of his mother's not to a Disney film or a family comedy but, of all things, to Francis Ford Coppola's Vietnam War epic, ''Apocalypse Now.''  ''I went home and told my parents, 'I want to make movies.' They said: 'Oh, you dreamer! Stay in Switzerland and study law or medicine.' ''</p>
        <p>IT was after graduating from high school that Mr. Forster read a newspaper article about the world's top film schools and was inspired to apply to New York University's Tisch School of the Arts. Though he was accepted, his status as a foreigner rendered him ineligible for an N.Y.U. scholarship, and his father, who had lost everything in the stock market crash in 1987, was unable to help him with tuition. So Mr. Forster sent a pleading letter to everyone, anyone, who might have surplus funds. Touched by the passion in Mr. Forster's solicitation, one recipient, the French businessman Robert Louis-Dreyfus (the actress Julia Louis-Dreyfus's uncle), whose family had successfully squelched his own early interest in filmmaking, offered to underwrite Mr. Forster's entire education.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forster spent most of 1990 at N.Y.U. playing catch-up, watching movies his classmates had seen long ago and thinking, ''Oh God, everyone is way more talented than me.'' Struggling to improve his halting English, Mr. Forster, who still has a soft accent, made only silent films; he was too insecure to write dialogue or voice-overs. There was an unintended benefit, though. ''What I learned was how to tell a story without words,'' he said, and his films are indeed filled with extended, quiet master shots in which actions are as meaningful as anything anyone says.</p>
        <p>In 1995 his friend Greg Lauren lured him out to Los Angeles to direct a sort of feature-length actor's reel. Called ''Loungers,'' it starred Mr. Lauren as a two-bit lounge singer and ladies' man. Although ''Loungers'' was never released, it turned out so well that Mr. Lauren and Mr. Forster entered it in the Slamdance Film Festival, an offshoot of Sundance. It won the audience award and got Mr. Forster an agent, as well as a lot of directing offers from the producers of teenage movies, the current proving ground for fledgling directors.</p>
        <p>''To this day, I have people come up to me and say: 'Oh, man! I loved that movie!' '' said Mr. Lauren, adding that he knew that their quirky, song-laden collaboration was more of a lark for Mr. Forster than a chance to express himself artistically. ''As a filmmaker, he wanted to be able to lift the veil on humanity, to show the darkness that exists underneath.''</p>
        <p>''Everything Put Together'' marked Mr. Forster's official directing debut. Shot in two weeks on a small Sony VX-1000 digital camera, ''Everything Put Together,'' written by Adam Forgash, Catherine Lloyd Burns and Mr. Forster, tracks the psychic disintegration of an affluent suburban housewife (Radha Mitchell) after she loses her day-old son to sudden infant death syndrome. Last year, when critics at the Sundance Film Festival reviewed it, they made quick comparisons to the Danish Dogma hit ''The Celebration'' because of Mr. Forster's reliance on natural lighting and home-video-style camerawork. The pointed rejection of Ms. Mitchell's character by her female friends and her tragically heightened isolation, though, also led pundits to liken the film's slowly compounding sense of doom to that of classic Roman Polanski squirmfests like ''Repulsion'' and ''Rosemary's Baby.''</p>
        <p>Last spring, when the Los Angeles-based nonprofit arts group American Cinematheque selected ''Everything Put Together'' as the first original film to be released under its newly formed distribution arm, American Cinematheque Presents, the group didn't even know about ''Monster's Ball.'' Instead, American Cinematheque's marketing and publicity manager, Margot Gerber, was hoping to save the film from oblivion when it was not picked up by anybody on the festival circuit.</p>
        <p>''It was such an emotional experience, but worth the ride, in my opinion,'' said Ms. Gerber, whose organization, lacking a publicity budget, decided that its smartest strategy would be to roll out ''Everything Put Together'' in art-house theaters around the country so slowly that somewhere, someone would be showing it within hype distance of ''Monster's Ball.'' (''Everything Put Together'' was released in New York on Nov. 9, but won't hit San Francisco and Chicago until next month.) With that kind of staggered release, success rises and falls on word of mouth.</p>
        <p>On that front, the actress Megan Mullally is doing her part. ''His idea of what's beautiful and true isn't what we're always used to seeing,'' said Ms. Mullally, whose turn as a wearily cynical mother in ''Everything Put Together'' bears no resemblance to Karen, the gleefully snide character she plays on television's ''Will and Grace.''  ''There's no artifice about him. He's not trying to be something that he's not.''</p>
        <p>He could best be described as not quite American, but not exactly Swiss. ''I've changed so much,'' said Mr. Forster, who, with his shaved head, pale blue shirt, loose cotton pants and bare feet has the kind of beatific look you might find on the guy on the mat next to you at yoga class. ''Here, people are more emotional; they talk about things. When I look back to my friends in Switzerland, they're much more restrained, judgmental.''</p>
        <p>In the midst of making this remark, Mr. Forster abruptly leaned back against the white overstuffed living room couch he was sitting on and, for maybe the sixth time in an hour, craned his head and peered anxiously outdoors. Mr. Forster's girlfriend, Renee Chabria, a filmmaker, had left her gray cat, Kelly, in his care, and even without the presence of coyotes in the surrounding hills, Kelly needed extra watching. ''She licked up some antifreeze, and her back legs were paralyzed,'' Mr. Forster explained. Distracted by the vigil, Mr. Forster finally padded outside, plucked the green-eyed tabby from the bushes and set her down on the couch.</p>
        <p>Of course, were Kelly a character in one of Mr. Forster's movies, she'd probably be a goner. Suffering and loss are, after all, among Mr. Forster's recurring themes. Like ''Everything Put Together,''  ''Monster's Ball'' has a spare, disturbing intensity -- death as a catalyst, grief as a major emotion. Even the pivotal sex scene in ''Monster's Ball'' occurs less as the outcome of physical attraction than as the act of two people desperate to dull their terrible sadness. (As postgraduation money gigs, Mr. Forster added a pair of grim entries to his résumé: a segment for a European television documentary about teenage suicide and another segment on child burn victims that was never completed.)</p>
        <p>When asked to explain his affinity for such somber material, Mr. Forster replied that he had seen a lot of tragedy in his life, then added that his older brother committed suicide in 1998 and that his father and grandmother died shortly thereafter. ''I think it changed my life and how I look at it,'' he said. ''You really don't know what's going to happen tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>THE unpredictability of filmmaking, then, is probably nothing to Mr. Forster. He was at first so wary of Halle Berry's movie-star status -- he wanted to cast a new face -- that the actress had to lobby aggressively for the role of Leticia. Wes Bentley (''American Beauty''), originally hired to play the young man, abruptly bowed out two weeks before production began and was replaced by Heath Ledger (''A Knight's Tale''), who couldn't arrive on the set until the night before shooting.</p>
        <p>At that point, Mr. Thornton, who hails from Hot Springs, Ark., looked around and wondered what he had gotten himself into: a young Swiss was directing him in a slice-of-the-Deep-South drama featuring a New Yorker, Mr. Boyle, as his father and the Cleveland-born Ms. Berry as his girlfriend. Mr. Ledger is from Perth, Australia.</p>
        <p>''Listen, Marc,'' Mr. Thornton recalled fretting to Mr. Forster. ''I'm the only hillbilly in the entire movie!'' Mr. Forster alleviated his leading man's fears by putting him in charge of accent patrol. ''He's such a calm guy,'' Mr. Thornton said. ''A lot of people are going to want to work with him. I think he's going to be a real force in this business.''</p>
        <p>But what does Mr. Forster want to do? Recently, while talking to his mother, who still lives in Switzerland and has never seen his films, he mentioned that he had been offered a large-scale studio film with an accompanying large-scale payment, but had turned it down. He imitated her bleated response: ''What? Are you nuts?''</p>
        <p>''You don't understand,'' Mr. Forster said he told his horrified mother. ''I just want to do what I'm passionate about. I just want to tell stories that are really out of my heart.''</p>
        <p>FILM Margy Rochlin's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the actress Brittany Murphy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Margy Rochlin's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the actress Brittany Murphy.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
