<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nancy Weil, Dennis Gottfried</title>
    <meta content="23VOWS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/23/fashion/weddings/23VOWS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1353728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEIL, NANCY LOUISE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOTTFRIED, DR. DENNIS J.</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weil, Nancy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gottfried, Dennis (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellin, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Msnbc</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE0DB1E3EF930A15751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nancy Weil, Dennis Gottfried</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nancy Weil and Dennis Gottfried</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY ELLIN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vows column on wedding of Nancy Weil and Dennis Gottfried; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN less than an hour, Nancy Louise Weil became a wife, stepmother and step-grandmother. And in a few months, she hopes to add ''new mother'' to that list.</p>
        <p>Ms. Weil, 44, and her new husband, Dr. Dennis J. Gottfried, 55, are hoping to adopt a baby from Russia, which they say should happen sometime within the next few months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Friends knew that this relationship was well-cemented when they heard of great dates at Home Depot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN less than an hour, Nancy Louise Weil became a wife, stepmother and step-grandmother. And in a few months, she hopes to add ''new mother'' to that list.</p>
        <p>Ms. Weil, 44, and her new husband, Dr. Dennis J. Gottfried, 55, are hoping to adopt a baby from Russia, which they say should happen sometime within the next few months.</p>
        <p>''As soon as we submit a certified marriage certificate,'' said Ms. Weil, a former producer for MSNBC and more recently for ''Video House Call,'' a medical show she developed with Dr. Gottfried, an internist. ''We're told we can expect to fly to Russia within the next two to six months,'' she said. ''But the facilitator said it doesn't hurt to have a bag packed.''</p>
        <p>It's a far cry from Ms. Weil's previous existence, which had been like that of many New York-area women: filled with long days at the office and less-than-thrilling dates with men. ''Work was too important,'' she said. Babies, of course, were another matter. Ms. Weil has wanted one ''forever,'' but realities delayed that dream. ''I respect women who raise children by themselves, but I didn't want to do it alone. I think babies need daddies.''</p>
        <p>Two and a half years ago a friend introduced her to Dr. Gottfried through an exchange of phone numbers. Ms. Weil was so blasé about meeting him that on their first face-to-face outing at a restaurant in Westport, Conn., she wore a black sweater covered with hair shed by her two dogs. Despite having spent weeks chatting comfortably together on the phone, she didn't have high hopes for Dr. Gottfried. Ms. Weil's hairy sweater didn't bother him in the least. ''I don't pay attention to things like that,'' said Dr. Gottfried, the medical director of cardiac rehabilitation at Charlotte Hungerford Hospital in Torrington, Conn., and the owner of three dogs. He also has three grown children from an earlier marriage that ended in divorce, and a grandchild too.</p>
        <p>She recalled finding him to be bright and honest and liked his quirky sense of humor and shared interest in cross-country skiing and travel. The attraction solidified when at the end of the meal he said, ''I feel like I want to hold your hand.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Weil smiled and put out her hand. He held it.</p>
        <p>In a grocery store the next day, she ran into the waiter from the evening before. He asked if she had been on a first date. Ms. Weil remembers that when she nodded, the waiter said: ''Go out with him again. He seems like an awfully nice guy.''</p>
        <p>He was and she did.</p>
        <p>''I knew it was serious when she told me they had a great time together at Home Depot,'' said Barbara Weil, the bride's mother.</p>
        <p>Domestic tools and appliances notwithstanding, they were in no rush to tie the knot, especially since Ms. Weil, who initially planned to adopt from Ukraine, had been told by her adoption contacts that under that country's rules it was best to do so as a single mother and have her future husband adopt the child afterward.</p>
        <p>But in November, Ms. Weil received a phone call from her liaison at Jewish Family Services in Philadelphia, who said a Russian child had become available and that it might be better to be married. Dr. Gottfried told her to pick a date -- provided he wasn't on call -- and Ms. Weil and her mother and sister, Marjorie Weil, burst into action, rushing around to caterers, florists, photographers and boutiques. She found her wedding dress only two weeks ago. (''Not too Barbie,'' Ms. Weil said.) She got her engagement ring two days before the wedding.</p>
        <p>The couple were married on Dec. 15 before a small group of family members at the home of the bride's parents in Stamford, Conn. The next day, the couple held a catered reception there for 50 friends.</p>
        <p>How does Dr. Gottfried feel about being a father for the second time?</p>
        <p>''I love children,'' he said. But since he's already been through 4 a.m. feedings and diaper changes, Ms. Weil has agreed she'll be in charge of that.</p>
        <p>She doesn't mind, she said. ''I'm proof that it's not too late to make your dreams come true.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
