<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Sense of Christmas</title>
    <meta content="23COLU$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1353684"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="COUNTY LINES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EED9103EF930A15751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Sense of Christmas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAREK FUCHS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH garlands and tinsel, twinkling lights dangling from houses, illuminated reindeer on lawns, electric menorahs glowing in windows and candles burning to mark the winter solstice, the season of light is a most visual feast. But Becky Barnes cannot see it. She must experience Christmas, her favorite holiday, in other ways.  Mrs. Barnes, 50, is blind and has been since birth.</p>
        <p>Even as a girl, Mrs. Barnes loved the sense that Christmas was approaching. ''I would hear grown-ups start to whisper,'' Mrs. Barnes said. ''And I'd hear the carols and the Salvation Army bells and start to smell the pine. I always knew Christmas was getting closer. You can always feel it starting around you.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH garlands and tinsel, twinkling lights dangling from houses, illuminated reindeer on lawns, electric menorahs glowing in windows and candles burning to mark the winter solstice, the season of light is a most visual feast. But Becky Barnes cannot see it. She must experience Christmas, her favorite holiday, in other ways.  Mrs. Barnes, 50, is blind and has been since birth.</p>
        <p>Even as a girl, Mrs. Barnes loved the sense that Christmas was approaching. ''I would hear grown-ups start to whisper,'' Mrs. Barnes said. ''And I'd hear the carols and the Salvation Army bells and start to smell the pine. I always knew Christmas was getting closer. You can always feel it starting around you.''</p>
        <p>In school, there was the anticipation of Christmas break. ''Like everyone else,'' Mrs. Barnes remembered, ''I couldn't wait for school to let out. And I'd come right home and open the door and smell my mother baking cookies and cutting fudge and candy. It was wonderful.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Barnes grew up outside Chicago and eventually moved to Buffalo. She met a sighted man, Jim, in church, and they married five years ago, later settling in Mount Kisco because, as Mrs. Barnes said, ''it has good sidewalks.''</p>
        <p>As an adult, Christmas has the same magic: ''You can just feel it in everyone around you. Everyone has a little more bounce, a little more excitement in their voices. Of course, there's a little less excitement and bounce this year.'' But even this year, with all that has happened, there is still the smell of baking and of the evergreens, twin joys.  ''For me, Christmas is an almost undefinable feeling. It's a combination of so many things,'' she said.</p>
        <p>If she's not cooking Christmas dinner herself, Mrs. Barnes's favorite thing to do is to walk into the house where she's eating Christmas dinner an hour early. ''Always an hour early,'' she stressed. ''That's before anything is ready, but while they are cooking and preparing. All those smells! There can be nothing visual as strong as the overwhelming smell of Christmas dinner cooking. It smells like home.</p>
        <p>''And I am fortunate enough,'' she said, ''to have a little bit of peripheral vision out of the corner of my right eye.'' Out of that corner, she can sometimes, if the situation is right, make out contrasts. If, for example, Mrs. Barnes is in a room where there is a Christmas tree and its lights are off, she knows when they are turned on. She lives on a dark street where one neighbor puts up big wreaths with big white spotlights shining on them. Mrs. Barnes loves them. When she and her husband went to see the tree at Rockefeller Center, she could tell that it was big.</p>
        <p>Most years, Mrs. Barnes also makes it to a display in Armonk that is perfect for her.  It has a large number of bright white lights set against a backdrop of the night sky. ''It's a wonderland,'' Mrs. Barnes said. ''In this situation everything you have is a blessing.''</p>
        <p>She also recognizes the ubiquitous icicle lights. ''They're amazing,'' she said, but added, ''of course, they can be overdone.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Barnes works as a community outreach coordinator and tour guide at the Guiding Eyes for the Blind in Yorktown Heights, a town, she said ''which is famous for not having good sidewalks.'' Guiding Eyes for the Blind is a nonprofit organization dedicated to helping the blind and the visually impaired get around safely. It is a major trainer of seeing-eye dogs.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Barnes, whose own 8-year-old seeing-eye dog, Rowan, is ''a big mush,'' also talks to school groups. ''I always tell them that people who are blind experience things with the same intensity,'' she said. ''It is different, but no less real and no less intense.  Being blind is darn inconvenient, but if you can't see, you just have to find other ways of doing things.</p>
        <p>''We are created,'' Mrs. Barnes always tells the children, ''with an uncanny ability to adapt.''</p>
        <p>This last thought is a lesson she always tries to get through to the people she speaks to who have recently lost their sight, people, Mrs. Barnes said, who have it much worse than she does. ''They usually have a difficult time believing me,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Barnes is already having a wonderful Christmas this year. There have been the whispers and the carols and the bells and the baking and those glorious flashes of light in the corner of her right eye. ''You can always find ways to enjoy the things we were meant to enjoy,'' she said.</p>
        <p>COUNTY LINES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
