<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>1995 N.H.L. Playoffs; The Rangers Turn to Healy in Their Hour of Need</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="764964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA FLYERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICHTER, MIKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEALY, GLENN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDA153FF935A15756C0A963958260" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>1995 N.H.L. Playoffs; The Rangers Turn to Healy in Their Hour of Need</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>RYE, N.Y., May 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers, facing the doom of a four-game sweep by a playoff-sharpened legion of Philadelphia Flyers, will try to change the momentum of their Eastern Conference semifinal with a change of goalies. Instead of Mike Richter, who started the first three games of the playoff series, the Rangers will go with Glenn Healy in Game 4 Friday night at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Richter said he was told today of the decision during an optional practice at Rye Playland Ice Casino. The mood of the room was subdued as the players, trailing by 3-0 in games, realized they might be in their final hours as defending Stanley Cup champions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rangers, facing the doom of a four-game sweep by a playoff-sharpened legion of Philadelphia Flyers, will try to change the momentum of their Eastern Conference semifinal with a change of goalies. Instead of Mike Richter, who started the first three games of the playoff series, the Rangers will go with Glenn Healy in Game 4 Friday night at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Richter said he was told today of the decision during an optional practice at Rye Playland Ice Casino. The mood of the room was subdued as the players, trailing by 3-0 in games, realized they might be in their final hours as defending Stanley Cup champions.</p>
        <p>The captain, Mark Messier, who didn't have much to say after Wednesday night's 5-2 defeat at the Garden, said today: "I'm going to be very honest. It's been a very difficult kind of season." He said the struggle throughout April to qualify for the playoffs "takes a lot out of you."</p>
        <p>Wednesday's defeat, after two losses in overtime in Philadelphia, was most disheartening. The Rangers seemed overmatched by the bigger, younger Flyers, who smashed them with body checks and then sprinted past them on rushes with the puck as goaltender Ron Hextall kept them at bay.</p>
        <p>"With the pressure and scrutiny we've been under, it's human nature to get fatigued, physically and mentally," Messier said. "You have to get some gas in your tank."</p>
        <p>Messier explained the "one-game-at-a-time" mentality for a team that needs four consecutive victories to avoid elimination.</p>
        <p>"It's not wise to look that far ahead," he said. "Over all, the picture is too overwhelming. Any time there is a pulse, we're still alive."</p>
        <p>Only the 1942 Toronto Maple Leafs (against Detroit) and the 1975 Islanders (against Pittsburgh) have won a round after losing the first three games.</p>
        <p>Colin Campbell, the Ranger coach, played on that Penguins team. Now, he is trying to rally a veteran team in his rookie year as a head coach. Campbell spoke to the team and to reporters today in a voice that alternated between a croak and a whisper.</p>
        <p>"Everyone hates to lose the fourth game," he said. "Nobody wants to get swept."</p>
        <p>He blamed the Philadelphia goals that beat the Rangers in Game 3 on "outlandish mistakes," two of them by defenseman Jeff Beukeboom, who accidentally passed the puck to the Flyers' Kevin Dineen on the first goal and got caught up ice checking Eric Lindros on the second.</p>
        <p>"If you have to be positive about something, it's that we're beating ourselves," Campbell said. "We've got to quit beating ourselves. We shot ourselves in the foot."</p>
        <p>Campbell said that in addition to the change in goaltenders, defenseman Aleksandr Karpovtsev will miss his second consecutive game because of a shoulder injury; his likely replacement, again, will be Mattias Norstrom.</p>
        <p>Healy, who replaced Richter on Wednesday night and gave up only the fifth Flyers goal, has made two starts in the team's nine playoff games this season. His record is 2-0 with a goals-against average of 3.18. Richter is 2-5 and 3.59.</p>
        <p>Richter said: "There's disappointment, embarrassment, anger -- all the negative emotions that come with a loss."</p>
        <p>But Healy added: "We're not about to feel sorry for ourselves."</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Down by 3-0 in games, the Rangers are on the brink of becoming only the second defending Stanley Cup champions to be swept in a four-of-seven-game playoff series. In 1951, the Toronto Maple Leafs were the champions, but the following year the Detroit Red Wings eliminated them in four straight in the semifinals and went on to win the cup. . . . Television gave the Rangers a big vote of no-confidence on Thursday.  Although the Rangers are a bigger ratings attraction in this market, the Fox network elected to carry the Devils-Pittsburgh game on Sunday afternoon instead of taking a chance on the possibility that the Rangers will be around to play the Flyers. If the Rangers survive, they will play Sunday night in Philadelphia, beginning at 7:30 P.M., and the game will be televised on the MSG Network.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
