<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On My Mind; A Lonelier President</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="572981"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, A M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D71238F934A15752C1A964958260" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On My Mind; A Lonelier President</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. M. ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, A M</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Americans like to think of their President as the leader of the free world -- a thought that hugely annoys a sizable number of other presidents, prime ministers and the people who happened to vote them into office.</p>
        <p>"A" leader, certainly. "Important" leader, without doubt. But around the globe there are millions crude and ungrateful enough to believe that their own leaders also are exercising some kind of role and have some use in the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Americans like to think of their President as the leader of the free world -- a thought that hugely annoys a sizable number of other presidents, prime ministers and the people who happened to vote them into office.</p>
        <p>"A" leader, certainly. "Important" leader, without doubt. But around the globe there are millions crude and ungrateful enough to believe that their own leaders also are exercising some kind of role and have some use in the world.</p>
        <p>And of course, despite American money and power, it was never true that the American President was the single leader. It could not be true, not while Churchill lived, or de Gaulle peered down like a great giraffe on lesser creatures, while a Thatcher or Adenauer dispensed courage, while Havel was speaking the dreams of the captive peoples, while the mind of a Nehru leapt across continents to make itself felt, or Sadat and Begin leapt across hatred to make a decent peace.</p>
        <p>But suddenly, it really is true -- Bill Clinton is the leader of the free world. The new American President will have a tougher job than his predecessors, because he will be all alone out there.</p>
        <p>And it is not only just because the leaders who shared influence with American Presidents are dead, out of power, or, like Havel, unable to fulfill their dreams.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton will be alone because their equals have not come to office.</p>
        <p>In Europe the British Prime Minister seems wan and puzzled. The President of France is obsessed by his future biographers. The Chancellor of Germany is unable or unwilling to carry out his overriding duty: to face down, control and conquer the Nazi movement.</p>
        <p>In Central Europe top Communist hacks have taken over or are working themselves back. Inevitable -- since their nations decided not to bar top Communist hacks from office for a period of denazification.</p>
        <p>Boris Yeltsin, who still can be a leader of a democratic Russia, is being left to hang out and freeze. The West gives him more mouth than help. And some Western Sovietologists still dream of a Gorbachev Soviet reborn. In Russia, Communists and Fascists, brothers from the womb, try to destroy him.</p>
        <p>So President Clinton will be alone at a time when America does not have all the money in the world, when American military might has become less mighty than the blood lusts of Balkan and African tribes.</p>
        <p>There he is, promising to keep the faith, so perverse to many bureaucrats in and out of office, that there really is a difference between democracy and tyranny -- yes, as he put it, from Baghdad to Beijing.</p>
        <p>The realpoliticians, who led the world from one war to another, simply cannot stomach his democratic realism. They will be pecking at the man forever, trying to get him to recant.</p>
        <p>They have started already. They decide that his restatement of belief in pressuring Communist China into human rights decencies, plus some overly polite words about Bushbaker, somehow mean that he has changed his core beliefs.</p>
        <p>But he is hardly to be pitied. Worthy leaders will rise, as one has in Mexico. What's more Mr. Clinton has self-protective common sense. If he uses it he will pick a Secretary of State as he picked a Vice President: somebody who will bring him expertise and political strength.</p>
        <p>An excellent somebody would be Jeane Kirkpatrick -- experienced, wise and intellectually expansive. Her life and beliefs would send a message around the world: America will protect its interests, and one of them is freedom.</p>
        <p>Well, Mr. Clinton has seen free to disregard my advice before, so he may do so again. But surely he will consult Vice President-elect Al Gore about the secretaryship, and, over the years, about foreign matters generally. He should: Mr. Gore would make a great Secretary of State if he could be excused from baby-sitting the Senate.</p>
        <p>And any time I think of Mr. Clinton's job and how hard it will be, I also think of Socrates Butsikares. He was an editor at The New York Times, a newsman born. Once I complained to him that all day long his news clerk had to get up and walk 20 steps whenever he wanted to talk to him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Butsikares looked up at me.</p>
        <p>"So what?" he said. "The kid came here looking for work, didn't he?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
