<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fassero Costs Himself No-Hitter With 2 Out in 9th</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="693524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Colorado Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7DF1F3AF937A25755C0A962958260" item-length="491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fassero Costs Himself No-Hitter With 2 Out in 9th</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Expos 10, Pirates 2</p>
        <p>Jeff Fassero lost his no-hitter with two outs in the ninth inning when he failed to catch Carlos Garcia's line drive last night in the Montreal Expos' 10-2 victory over the Pittsburgh Pirates at Montreal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Expos 10, Pirates 2</p>
        <p>Jeff Fassero lost his no-hitter with two outs in the ninth inning when he failed to catch Carlos Garcia's line drive last night in the Montreal Expos' 10-2 victory over the Pittsburgh Pirates at Montreal.</p>
        <p>Fassero (5-4) had a 1-2 count when Garcia hit a waist-high drive back to the mound. Fassero, a left-hander, stuck out his glove to the right side, but the ball bounced out and rolled toward third base. Fassero quickly recovered and made a strong throw to first baseman Randy Milligan, but Garcia slid head-first and barely beat the play. Umpire Bob Davidson made the call, and there was no dispute about his decision -- or the ruling that it was an infield single, not an error.</p>
        <p>"I think the (ball) hit my thumb," Fassero said. "I lost it for a second when I looked into my glove, because I thought I had caught it." Rockies 7, Braves 2</p>
        <p>A former Atlanta pitcher, Marvin Freeman, helped Colorado end its 16-game losing streak against the Braves, leading the Rockies to a road victory. The Braves had been the only club the Rockies, in their second season, had never defeated.</p>
        <p>Freeman (6-1), signed as a free agent after three and a half years with the Braves, allowed eight hits and one run, didn't walk a batter and struck out three in seven innings. Giants 5, Astros 2</p>
        <p>Matt Williams hit his National League-leading 23d home run and William VanLandingham and three relievers combined on a eight-hitter as San Francisco beat visiting Houston. The Giants also got a home run from Todd Benzinger in ending their four-game losing streak. Rangers 17, Mariners 9</p>
        <p>Jose Canseco hit three homers and drove in eight runs, offsetting Ken Griffey Jr.'s grand slam and six r.b.i., leading Texas over Seattle.</p>
        <p>Canseco went 5 for 6 with a team-record 14 total bases. He set a career-high for r.b.i., as did Griffey. Indians 7, Blue Jays 3</p>
        <p>The Cleveland Indians won their 12th straight home game and Mark Clark (8-1) kept his Jacobs Field record perfect. Albert Belle hit his 16th home run and Manny Ramirez his 11th for Cleveland. Joe Carter hit his 16th for Toronto. White Sox 1, Athletics 0</p>
        <p>Jason Bere (8-1) allowed two hits to Terry Steinbach over eight innings and struck out a career-high 14 to lead the Chicago to its tight victory over Oakland in Chicago. Lance Johnson led off the Chicago fifth with a triple and, after two outs, Tim Raines singled in the run. Twins 5, Red Sox 2</p>
        <p>Boston lost to Minnesota at Fenway Park for its fifth straight setback as Roger Clemens (6-3), the only Red Sox starter to win since May 26, allowed four runs on eight hits in six innings but was outpitched by Jim Deshaies. The Twins won their fifth in a row and seventh in eight games. Royals 12, Angels 7</p>
        <p>Pinch-hitter Hubie Brooks's grand slam capped a seven-run comeback in the eighth that won for Kansas City. Tim Salmon homered and drove in five runs for the visiting Angels.  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
