<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Price Decline In Treasuries Continues</title>
    <meta content="23BOND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="931850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hurtado, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDF133BF930A15756C0A961958260" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Price Decline In Treasuries Continues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HURTADO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hurtado, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Treasury prices fall for second consecutive session; price of 30-year Treasury bond falls 11/32, to price of 95 17/32; yield rises to 6.98 percent from 6.95 percent on May 21; graph (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Treasury prices fell yesterday for the second consecutive session, as  investors grew concerned that the economy was still growing fast enough to move the Federal Reserve toward another increase in interest rates.</p>
        <p>Bond prices were weaker after the Labor Department reported that weekly initial unemployment claims rose by 5,000, to a seasonally adjusted 322,000. Analysts had forecast  324,000 claims, which was more or else in line with expectations. Still the numbers are an indication that the labor market continues to be tight, leaving the door ajar for future inflation and higher rates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Treasury prices fell yesterday for the second consecutive session, as  investors grew concerned that the economy was still growing fast enough to move the Federal Reserve toward another increase in interest rates.</p>
        <p>Bond prices were weaker after the Labor Department reported that weekly initial unemployment claims rose by 5,000, to a seasonally adjusted 322,000. Analysts had forecast  324,000 claims, which was more or else in line with expectations. Still the numbers are an indication that the labor market continues to be tight, leaving the door ajar for future inflation and higher rates.</p>
        <p>''The unemployment claims this week were watched more closely than normal by financial market investors primarily because these figures were compiled during the week that the monthly employment surveys are conducted,'' said Anthony Chan, vice president and chief economist at the Banc One Investment Advisers Corporation in Columbus, Ohio.</p>
        <p>''It's important to note that the data on initial unemployment claims was contaminated during April to early May by the impact of auto strikes and the Midwest floods. However, data over the past two weeks has been mostly devoid of these effects and has provided strong hints that the economy may not be slowing down as quickly as many credit market investors had anticipated.''</p>
        <p>The price of the 30-year Treasury bond fell 11/32 , to a price of 9517/32 . The bond's yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, rose to 6.98 percent, from 6.95 percent on Wednesday. For the long bond, the yield has not been over 7 percent since the end of April.</p>
        <p>Prices received a little support from the late afternoon release of the minutes of the Fed's policy-making meeting on March. Policy makers were unanimous in voting for a quarter-point increase in the target for the Federal funds rate. Some traders and analysts had been concerned that policy makers were divided.</p>
        <p>Still, for bonds to rally substantially, market participants will have to see convincing evidence the economy will slow to a point that is sustainable, but without inflation. So far there is little evidence that inflation is quickening.</p>
        <p>One indication that inflation remains constrained came yesterday when the Labor Department also reported that the 12-month changes in its experimental Consumer Price Index were running three-hundredths of a percentage point less than the official index.</p>
        <p>Today, trading of Treasury securities, mortgage securities, corporate bonds, municipal bonds and secondary money market is expected to close early, at 2 P.M. Bond markets will also be closed on Monday in observance of Memorial Day.</p>
        <p>Treasury auctions will commence on Tuesday, with the regular weekly bill auction, followed on Wednesday by the sale of two-year notes and five-year notes on Thursday. In when-issued trading late yesterday the two-year note was offered at a price to yield 6.27 percent and the five-year note at a price to yield 6.58 percent. Both were up slightly from the previous day.</p>
        <p>Yesterday the Treasury auctioned $13.75 billion of new one-year bills at an average rate of 5.55 percent, down from 5.72 percent the month before. Analysts said retail demand was good, but that the total number of bids was down slightly. Following are the results of that auction:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>Average Price</p>
        <p>94.388</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>5.55%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>5.88%</p>
        <p>High Price</p>
        <p>94.409</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>5.56%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>5.89%</p>
        <p>Low Price</p>
        <p>94.378</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>5.53%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>5.85%</p>
        <p>Accepted at low price</p>
        <p>11%</p>
        <p>Total applied for</p>
        <p>$48,015,258</p>
        <p>Accepted</p>
        <p>$13,777,108</p>
        <p>Noncompetitive</p>
        <p>$1,099,258</p>
        <p>The one-year bills mature on May 28, 1998.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
