<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH AND YELTSIN PROPOSE DEEP CUTS IN ATOMIC WEAPONS</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="504243"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS CONTROL AND LIMITATION AND DISARMAMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE WEAPONS (STAR WARS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, ANDREW</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">YELTSIN, BORIS N (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D91639F933A05752C0A964958260" item-length="1221" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH AND YELTSIN PROPOSE DEEP CUTS IN ATOMIC WEAPONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSENTHAL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush and President Boris N. Yeltsin made new arms control proposals this week that envision slashing American and Russian long-range nuclear arms by well over half and could eliminate the class of missiles considered the biggest threat to peace.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's proposal, outlined in the State of the Union Address on Tuesday, asks Mr. Yeltsin to take a step that no Soviet leader ever entertained: give up his advantage in one area of nuclear arms competition, land-based missiles, in return for an important concession but not parallel cuts in the area of American advantage, submarine-based missiles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush and President Boris N. Yeltsin made new arms control proposals this week that envision slashing American and Russian long-range nuclear arms by well over half and could eliminate the class of missiles considered the biggest threat to peace.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's proposal, outlined in the State of the Union Address on Tuesday, asks Mr. Yeltsin to take a step that no Soviet leader ever entertained: give up his advantage in one area of nuclear arms competition, land-based missiles, in return for an important concession but not parallel cuts in the area of American advantage, submarine-based missiles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's plan would reduce the American strategic nuclear arsenal to between 4,500 and 5,000 warheads, about 60 percent of the current level and far less than envisioned in last year's strategic arms reduction treaty. Multiple-Warhead Missiles</p>
        <p>It would eliminate missiles with more than one warhead that are fired from land, the most dangerous kind of nuclear weapon and the mainstay of the Soviet nuclear force. In exchange, the United States would sharply reduce its stock of weapons launched from submarines, which are the ones the Russians worry about the most, but Washington would retain an edge.</p>
        <p>In response, Mr. Yeltsin said today that he would propose cutting long-range nuclear warheads to between 2,000 and 2,500. That did not appear to include cruise missiles and bombs dropped from airplanes, but would still mean a total significantly lower than what Mr. Bush suggested.  [ Page A8. ]</p>
        <p>Administration officials said prospects were good for some sort of an agreement, which Mr. Bush and Mr. Yeltsin will begin discussing at Camp David on Saturday. Mr. Bush on Tuesday described Mr. Yeltsin's early response as "very positive." Offer Called 'Lopsided'</p>
        <p>But Soviet officials visiting the United States in advance of Mr. Yeltsin's arrival for a United Nations Security Council meeting on Friday are reported to have said in conversations here that Mr. Yeltsin found the offer "lopsided" and told Mr. Bush so in a letter received by the White House on Monday. Mr. Yeltsin had been advised in advance of Mr. Bush's proposal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin also made clear in a speech today that his Government will continue to oppose Washington's "Star Wars" anti-missile program unless the United States agrees to share the technology, something the Bush Administration has refused to consider.</p>
        <p>Both sides have indicated in recent days that they recognize that the dynamics of arms control have been transformed. Just last week, Mr. Yeltsin announced that Russian nuclear missiles would no longer be aimed at American targets, and the Pentagon has long conceded there is no apparent military threat from what used to be the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Administration officials said these sorts of developments led Mr. Bush to propose the concessions that Soviet leaders always refused, with some confidence that his ideas would be at least considered. 'Out to Sea'</p>
        <p>"This is what we've been trying to do since the beginning of strategic arms negotiations in 1969 -- 'push the Soviets out to sea,' where we have our missiles," said Dunbar Lockwood, a senior analyst with the Arms Control Association, a private research group.</p>
        <p>He added, "It has always been our premise that it's more stabilizing to have the bulk of missiles in subs, because they are invisible under the sea and therefore more useful for retaliation and not an attractive target for someone considering a first strike."</p>
        <p>As dramatic as the newly proposed cuts may seem, arms control is not the only item on the agenda for Saturday's meeting, nor perhaps even the most pressing.</p>
        <p>The White House views the meeting as a chance for Mr. Bush to impress on Mr. Yeltsin the need to continue political and economic liberalization without Russia imposing its will on other former republics. 'Big Brother Fashion'</p>
        <p>"We believe there is a need for all the former Soviet republics to move forward along these lines, mutually and not in Big Brother fashion," an Administration official said. "The Russians have shown a tendency to confuse their national interests with those of the peoples surrounding them."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also planned to give what one official called his "imprimatur" to Mr. Yeltsin's economic policies, which Washington hopes will give the Russian leader a political boost at home, in much the same way that Mr. Bush once sought to shore up President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>Equally important, officials said, Mr. Bush hopes to establish with Mr. Yeltsin the kind of personal rapport and working relationship that he had with Mr. Gorbachev. "It's the first time he's met with Yeltsin that Bush hasn't had to worry about the problem of dual power and conflicting loyalties," a senior official said.</p>
        <p>Another official said, "The only alternative to Yeltsin that we can see is dictatorship and so we want to, A, make sure that he's politically entrenched and, B, make sure as we did with Gorbachev that he follows the path of democracy and reform." 1991 Arms Treaty</p>
        <p>Last July, the United States and the Soviet Union signed the Strategic Arms Reduction Treaty, which calls for reducing the American arsenal of about 11,600 nuclear warheads aboard ballistic missiles, jet-like cruise missiles and bombs dropped by airplanes to about 8,600 before the end of the century. The Soviet arsenal would be cut from about 10,900 warheads to about 6,900.</p>
        <p>Nuclear arms treaties deal with warheads, which are the actual nuclear bombs, rather than the missiles that carry them, because modern missiles can carry more than 10 warheads apiece. These missiles are considered dangerous or "destabilizing" because they are tempting targets for the other country's military planners.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 27, in announcing unilateral cuts in short-range nuclear weapons that are used on the battlefield, Mr. Bush offered to negotiate an elimination of multiple-warhead missiles with the Soviet Union. Cutting Soviet Arsenal</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mr. Bush proposed that Russia, Ukraine and Kazakhstan eradicate all of their huge, multiple-warhead missiles based on land. This would have the additional benefit to the United States of removing all intercontinental missiles from Ukrainian and Kazakh soil.</p>
        <p>The United States has in the past proposed eliminating multiple-warhead missiles fired from land and the Kremlin has always refused, because the United States was not willing to consider cuts in its submarine-launched missiles.</p>
        <p>This time, Mr. Bush offered to do just that if the other three countries accepted his proposal. He said he would eliminate about one-third of the warheads aboard American Trident submarines, reducing the force from 3,456 warheads to about 2,300.</p>
        <p>He went a step further by saying he would also destroy America's newest and most powerful land-based weapon, the 10-warhead MX missile, and lower the number of warheads aboard the Minuteman 3 missile to one from three.</p>
        <p>If these ideas are adopted, the United States would be left with about 2,800 warheads on its long-range missiles. The rest of the arsenal is composed of bombs dropped by aircraft and cruise missiles, similar to conventionally armed versions used against Iraq last year. It is not clear how many of each kind of missile Mr. Bush intends to keep.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
