<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; Yeltsin-Bush Summit</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="504247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS CONTROL AND LIMITATION AND DISARMAMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE WEAPONS (STAR WARS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COMMONWEALTH OF INDEPENDENT STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">YELTSIN, BORIS N (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDE1739F933A05752C0A964958260" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; Yeltsin-Bush Summit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Potus's key sherpas finessed the Sotu to zero in on the build-down at David.</p>
        <p>Translation of that pastiche of acronyms and bureaucratese: "The President of the United States' national security aides passed up much of the hype surrounding the State of the Union address to concentrate on proposals for nuclear-weapons reductions at his first summit meeting with the Russian President, Boris Yeltsin, at Camp David this weekend."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Potus's key sherpas finessed the Sotu to zero in on the build-down at David.</p>
        <p>Translation of that pastiche of acronyms and bureaucratese: "The President of the United States' national security aides passed up much of the hype surrounding the State of the Union address to concentrate on proposals for nuclear-weapons reductions at his first summit meeting with the Russian President, Boris Yeltsin, at Camp David this weekend."</p>
        <p>Early this week, the Russian leader slipped out of Moscow for 48 hours; The A.P. promptly reported "rumors about his health and about a drinking problem" and Washington mediadom was abuzz with talk of a drunken Boris lolling in the arms of a Russobimbo. (If President Yeltsin ever were to take a walk in the woods with a President Clinton, the supermarket media would go bananas.)</p>
        <p>It turns out that President Yeltsin's disappearance was on the most serious official business. In preparation for the summit, he visited the Black Sea Fleet, whose ownership is in dispute, to demonstrate to nervous Americans his control over the nuclear arsenal of the former Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin is abhorred by the Bush world-orderlies as a bumptious arriviste for having deposed their beloved Communist smoothie; it's always so awkward having to deal with elected leaders.</p>
        <p>But personality preferences have been set aside to get ready for the next giant leap for mankind: the destruction of nuclear arms at a pace undreamed of by negotiators.</p>
        <p>Some of the recent moves have been only newspaper talk. With much fanfare, the Russians announced their huge land-based missiles "were no longer targeted on American cities." Big deal; an arms expert tells me the missiles in silos could be re-targeted in less than 10 seconds. More significant would be the return to port of sea-based nuclear missiles.</p>
        <p>The real reductions in prospect are historic: in essence, turning the clock of the arms race back to the early 70's, when the MIRV'ing began. Today's restrictive motto is "one missile, one warhead."</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin has figured out a way to buy off the Red Army: Pay and house the troops by slashing arms spending. We provide Yeltsinites cover by reducing our own nukes.</p>
        <p>One brief defense item in President Bush's Sotu should become an integral part of the nuclear build-down. He called for "funding a program to protect our country from limited nuclear missile attack. . . . too many people in too many countries have access to nuclear arms."</p>
        <p>This call for S.D.I., the much-derided "Star Wars," was hooted at by Democrats who are still zigging while the nuclear threat has zagged. In the past, they opposed a space shield because they were sure it would not stop an all-out attack and it would be destabilizing.</p>
        <p>But now the threat is from a limited attack -- a missile or two, capable of killing only 10 million Americans -- and the space shield would help stabilize the lowering balance between the U.S. and Russia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin knows we will move ahead on anti-missile defenses, because of all the treaties we recently asked his Commonwealth to reaffirm, the ABM treaty was not one. We want that Anti-Ballistic Missile treaty to die quietly.</p>
        <p>To counter our unilateral work on S.D.I., he said in his own lengthy State of the Nuclear Non-Union yesterday: "Russia confirms its commitment to the ABM treaty."</p>
        <p>That was to restrain us from going it alone. Then he added: "We're prepared to design jointly, produce jointly and use jointly a global security system to replace the S.D.I. system."</p>
        <p>They all laughed at Ronald Reagan a decade ago, suggesting that Americans could share technology with Soviets in building a common shield. Mr. Gorbachev resisted, breaking up the Reykjavik summit; and our own technocrats did not want anybody to see the secrets of our Skonkworks.</p>
        <p>In his own version of a Trollope ploy, Mr. Yeltsin is responding to the old Reagan proposal. By buying into our nuclear shield in space; by assigning brains to it who might otherwise be drained, and by renaming it to save face, Mr. Yeltsin seeks more U.S. cover to accelerate his abandonment of the arms race.</p>
        <p>S.D.I.-nik would kill a terrorist or accidental launch, protecting millions. Seize the moment, Mr. Bush.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
