<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prowling in Paris For Chic Sofas, etc.</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="504442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FURNITURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PARIS (FRANCE)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOUIE, ELAINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D6163FF933A05752C0A964958260" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prowling in Paris For Chic Sofas, etc.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE LOUIE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LOUIE, ELAINE</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BUYING a hand towel or a sofa here can be a small cultural event. In a city where even dogs are allowed to eat baguettes at restaurants, the act of shopping is a social ritual, much more amusing than just spending money. It is best accomplished with well-cut clothes and posture that verges on arrogance.</p>
        <p>Prowling through boutiques is also a brief foray into French architecture. New shops, one quickly realizes, are tucked into former bathhouses or 18th-century saddle factories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BUYING a hand towel or a sofa here can be a small cultural event. In a city where even dogs are allowed to eat baguettes at restaurants, the act of shopping is a social ritual, much more amusing than just spending money. It is best accomplished with well-cut clothes and posture that verges on arrogance.</p>
        <p>Prowling through boutiques is also a brief foray into French architecture. New shops, one quickly realizes, are tucked into former bathhouses or 18th-century saddle factories.</p>
        <p>In the last two years, five shops have opened that sell furniture and accessories for the home. Their styles are diverse, ranging from American West (cactuses are the recurring motif) to contemporary French (curvaceous white sofas fit for Alphaville, but not for houses with children or black-haired dogs). But each has a singular point of view.</p>
        <p>Three stores are in the Marais district, near the Pompidou Center in the Beaubourg quarter, which continues its metamorphosis from shabby to chic. That is where the avant-garde spends its money for clothing and home accessories.</p>
        <p>At 4 rue de Thorigny is the airy shop of Frederic Mechiche, an interior designer who updates traditional furniture by making it overscaled and voluptuous. He opened his shop, across the street from the Musee Picasso, in March 1990.</p>
        <p>The 3,300-square-foot store in an 18th-century building comprises three rooms, each resembling a living room, with thick ficus trees looming over the furniture.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mechiche can make an old silhouette new, for example, by taking a camelback sofa, exaggerating its contours, filling it with lavish amounts of down and upholstering it in pristine white cotton. Chairs start at $1,850 and sofas at $5,550, excluding the price of the fabric.</p>
        <p>"What is important for me is the volume and the sinuous line," Mr. Mechiche said. "The furniture has an 18th-century inspiration, but looks modern." Telephone: 011-331-42-78-78-28.</p>
        <p>The American West, or at least the American West of cigar-store Indians and fringed pillows printed with cowboys and Indians, has come to Paris at Chevignon Trading Post, Guy Azoulay's two shops here. The stores are homages to Zona, the Manhattan shop that specializes in designs of the Southwest, according to Mitzi Sicart, the Trading Post's assistant buyer.</p>
        <p>"The stores are a mix of the American West and a Mexican trading post," Ms. Sicart said.</p>
        <p>The first Chevignon Trading Post opened in November 1990 at 49 rue Etienne Marcel. The second opened last May at 4 rue des Rosiers in the Marais, in what had been Hamman St.-Paul, a Turkish bathhouse.</p>
        <p>The newer store is a three-story, 19,000-square-foot emporium of Americana. On the first floor, there are Taos sofas of ponderosa pine ($4,250), bandanas ($6.50) and Pendleton blankets ($212). Upstairs there are leather bomber jackets, bluejeans and down-filled jackets, as well as a cafe that sells brownies, pecan pie and apple pie. Telephone: 011-331-42-72-42-40.</p>
        <p>Those who yearn for European designs can walk across the street to L'Eclaireur (the word means pathfinder), at 3 rue des Rosiers, where Martine and Armand Hadida sell furniture designed by Andre Dubreuil and Philippe Starck, along with clothing by Vivienne Westwood and Katharine Hamnett.</p>
        <p>Mixing fashion and furniture is the Hadidas' answer to the recession. "We have to get people to sit down and feel comfortable," Mr. Hadida said.</p>
        <p>From Mr. Starck, there is a multicolored sofa ($3,888). Two-thirds of it is pale green, the rest is covered in a fabric printed with pictures of perfume bottles. The seat is white.</p>
        <p>Herve Gambs, a furniture designer, does not upholster his wood-framed chairs ($1,777). They have transparent plastic seats filled with dried red roses. "The flowers will keep their color," Mr. Hadida said. "Only daylight will ruin it." Telephone: 011-331-48-87-10-22.</p>
        <p>Ines de la Fressange, who as a model was the symbol of Chanel from 1983 to 1989, now designs and sells clothes and accessories for the home. In October, she opened Ines de la Fressange at 14 avenue Montaigne, near the Champs-Elysees.</p>
        <p>The clothes are classic, but the design of the shop is not. "Why do stores have to be beige and mirrored?" Miss de la Fressange asked.</p>
        <p>In her store, the walls are green, blue, hot pink or yellow, and crystal chandeliers are in the shape of ships. The shop was designed by Alexis de la Falaise, a furniture designer.</p>
        <p>Miss de la Fressange's luxurious linen sheets, which have fagoting around the edges, cost $463 for a set of two sheets and two pillowcases (in pale blue or yellow). Thick towels are banded in grosgrain; a hand towel is $41, a bath towel $146.</p>
        <p>For the French, who take their dogs everywhere, she has designed a dog collar of brown leather and almond-green canvas with a matching leather leash ($126). Telephone: 011-331-47-23-08-94.</p>
        <p>Sybilla, a fashion designer who lives in Madrid, opened her shop at 62 rue Jean-Jacques Rousseau near Les Halles, last March in an 18th-century building where saddles were manufactured for Louis XIV. In the 19th century, pots and pans were made there.</p>
        <p>Designed by Sybilla and Kike Sirera, a furniture designer in Madrid, the shop has the original wood balcony, a 19th-century skylight and a concrete floor painted midnight blue. Even the pristine white bathroom has the designer's quirky touch. The bathtub is hung with patchwork curtains.</p>
        <p>Sybilla has reinvented the umbrella and the bathrobe. Her umbrella, which has a zigzagged edge, comes in blue, green, yellow, purple or orange and is $222. Her bathrobe ($292) has caped sleeves, so a woman can emerge from the shower with the same bravado that Sarah Bernhardt possessed when she took her bows on the Paris stage.</p>
        <p>Embroidered stars, snails or flowers in shades of green or terra cotta, embellish Sybilla's beige or gray sheets, as do mosaic patterns. Sets of two unfitted sheets and two pillowcases start at $160. Telephone: 011-331-42-36-03-63.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
