<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Iraq's Exiles Can, and Can't, Do</title>
    <meta content="29PHIL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/29/opinion/29PHIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1444480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Phillips, David L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7DF1538F93AA15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Iraq's Exiles Can, and Can't, Do</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What Iraq's Exiles Can, and Can't, Do</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David L. Phillips</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Phillips, David L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David L Phillips Op-Ed article on policies for post-Saddam Hussein Iraq; sees conference of exiled opposition groups likely to form advisory committee focusing on developing principles for federal democracy; holds Iraqis setting up conference have come to see need for mutual accommodation and for Iraqis inside Iraq to play key role in rebuilding nation; warns Iraqis who initially hail United States intervention will come to resent US unless they are allowed to lead transition (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In debating their role after a regime change in Iraq, Iraq's exiled opposition groups -- long riven by political disputes and personal grudges -- have wisely abandoned any plans to set up a national assembly or provisional government. That vision was unlikely to work anyway. Instead, it now seems that an advisory committee focusing on developing principles for a federal democratic Iraq post-Saddam Hussein will emerge from a conference of exile groups that will take place in London in early December.</p>
        <p>Simply setting up the conference has caused the various groups to realize that they have to allow for some mutual accommodation. More important, debate among them is beginning to focus on the need to have Iraqis inside Iraq play a prominent role in rebuilding the nation after Saddam Hussein is gone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iraq's exiled opposition groups are meeting in London in early December to develop principles for a federal democratic Iraq post-Saddam Hussein.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In debating their role after a regime change in Iraq, Iraq's exiled opposition groups -- long riven by political disputes and personal grudges -- have wisely abandoned any plans to set up a national assembly or provisional government. That vision was unlikely to work anyway. Instead, it now seems that an advisory committee focusing on developing principles for a federal democratic Iraq post-Saddam Hussein will emerge from a conference of exile groups that will take place in London in early December.</p>
        <p>Simply setting up the conference has caused the various groups to realize that they have to allow for some mutual accommodation. More important, debate among them is beginning to focus on the need to have Iraqis inside Iraq play a prominent role in rebuilding the nation after Saddam Hussein is gone.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, United States policy on how a post-Hussein Iraq should be governed has been evolving. In recent weeks officials have tempered their comparisons of America's future presence in Iraq to the occupation of Japan after World War II. Iraqis may initially roll out the welcome mat for American forces if a war takes place, but they will soon resent American intervention unless they are allowed to lead Iraq's transition.</p>
        <p>Certainly, a strong American-led international security force will be essential for public order. The force should have the authority to arrest Saddam Hussein's leadership circle and round up other war criminals. To these ends, the United States may find common cause with elements of the Iraqi Army. Brigade-level officers and Shiite rank-and-file soldiers have deep antipathy toward Saddam Hussein and resent decades of subordination to the elite Republican Guard.</p>
        <p>Like the Kurdish militia, Iraqi Army brigades could play a constabulary role or provide logistical support to humanitarian organizations. The military's regional command structure is also well placed to counter local militias that may try to take advantage of instability.</p>
        <p>Once the immediate dangers of disintegration and communal violence have passed, the advisory committee should be reconvened to discuss security arrangements and civilian administration. The advisory committee would represent the country's ethnic and religious groups and include prominent members of the Iraqi diaspora.</p>
        <p>It must not, however, be exclusively a body of exiles. The committee could also work with the international community to organize an orderly process of dismantling the apparatus of Saddam Hussein's Baath Party.</p>
        <p>A top priority has to be disbanding Saddam Hussein's security architecture, including the intelligence agencies. An Iraqi body should be established to investigate war criminals and publish a list that would include persons with command responsibility.</p>
        <p>While holding corrupt officials and criminals accountable, any transitional government cannot afford to dissolve the existing Iraqi civil service, which is dominated by Baath Party functionaries. Preserving a role for regional officials and administrators would be necessary to the continuity of essential governmental services, like providing sanitation and health care.</p>
        <p>A precedent for effective self-rule exists in Iraqi Kurdistan where, since 1991, enforcement of a no-flight zone has enabled northerners to ensure local security and administer regional affairs through a Kurdistan assembly.</p>
        <p>The next step in democratizing Iraq would involve a population census and internationally supervised elections for local government. Then a constituent assembly would draft a constitution and present it to Iraqis for ratification.</p>
        <p>The international community should not have to bear all the costs of securing and rebuilding Iraq. Instead, oil revenues should be used to capitalize an Iraqi reconstruction trust fund. Unspent funds in the United Nations oil-for-food program account could be used for quick-impact projects and to set up the trust fund.</p>
        <p>To avoid an open-ended commitment, the Bush administration must focus on fostering Iraqi leadership. Cooperative nation-building is the key to a smooth transfer of power. Without it, the Bush administration will find that getting into Iraq could prove far easier than getting out.</p>
        <p>David L. Phillips, a senior fellow and deputy director of the Center for Preventive Action at the Council on Foreign Relations, is assisting the democratic principles working group of the Iraqi opposition.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David L. Phillips, a senior fellow and deputy director of the Center for Preventive Action at the Council on Foreign Relations, is assisting the democratic principles working group of the Iraqi opposition.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
