<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Clinton's Grand Jury Testimony as Quoted in Starr's Report to Congress</title>
    <meta content="Y17JUR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1047155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TESTING OF A PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starr, Kenneth W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFD91F31F934A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Clinton's Grand Jury Testimony as Quoted in Starr's Report to Congress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Pres Clinton's grand jury testimony as quoted in independent counsel Kenneth W Starr's report to Congress</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from President Clinton's grand jury testimony as quoted in the report sent to Congress last week by Kenneth W. Starr, the Whitewater independent counsel. The quotations are grouped by subject matter and are not necessarily in the sequence in which the answers were given in the President's testimony on Aug. 17. At the start of his testimony, the President read a statement outlining his relationship with Monica S. Lewinsky. At various times in the four-hour session, he refused to elaborate on certain matters and referred back to his statement.</p>
        <p>On Defining Sexual Relations</p>
        <p>Prosecutors asked the President why he did not dispute his lawyer, Robert S. Bennett, in Mr. Clinton's deposition in the Paula Jones lawsuit on Jan. 17 when Mr. Bennett said, referring to Ms. Lewinsky's affidavit in the case, ''There is absolutely no sex of any kind in any manner, shape or form.''  Mr. Clinton said Mr. Bennett was speaking only in the present tense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from President Clinton's grand jury testimony as quoted in the report sent to Congress last week by Kenneth W. Starr, the Whitewater independent counsel. The quotations are grouped by subject matter and are not necessarily in the sequence in which the answers were given in the President's testimony on Aug. 17. At the start of his testimony, the President read a statement outlining his relationship with Monica S. Lewinsky. At various times in the four-hour session, he refused to elaborate on certain matters and referred back to his statement.</p>
        <p>On Defining Sexual Relations</p>
        <p>Prosecutors asked the President why he did not dispute his lawyer, Robert S. Bennett, in Mr. Clinton's deposition in the Paula Jones lawsuit on Jan. 17 when Mr. Bennett said, referring to Ms. Lewinsky's affidavit in the case, ''There is absolutely no sex of any kind in any manner, shape or form.''  Mr. Clinton said Mr. Bennett was speaking only in the present tense.</p>
        <p>At one point, Mr. Clinton explained: ''It depends on what the meaning of the word 'is' is. If the -- if he -- if 'is' means is and never has been, that is not -- that is one thing. If it means there is none, that was a completely true statement. . . . Now if someone had asked me on that day, Are you having any kind of sexual relations with Ms. Lewinsky, that is, asked me a question in the present tense, I would have said no. And it would have been completely true. . . .''</p>
        <p>Q. Do you mean today that because you were not engaging in sexual activity with Ms. Lewinsky during the deposition that the statement of Mr. Bennett might be literally true?</p>
        <p>A. No, sir. I mean that at the time of the deposition, it had been -- that was well beyond any point of improper contact between me and Ms. Lewinsky.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors asked Mr. Clinton about his interpretation of the definition of ''sexual relations'' presented at his deposition in the Jones case, which read as follows: ''A person engages in 'sexual relations' when the person knowingly engages in or causes contact with the genitalia, anus, groin, breast, inner thigh, or buttocks of any person with an intent to arouse or gratify the sexual desire of any person.''</p>
        <p>Q. Is oral sex performed on you within that definition as you understood it, the definition in the Jones ----.</p>
        <p>A. As I understood it, it was not; no. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. So touching, in your view then and now -- the person being deposed touching or kissing the breast of another person would fall within the definition?</p>
        <p>A. That's correct, sir.</p>
        <p>Q. And you testified that you didn't have sexual relations with Monica Lewinsky in the Jones deposition, under that definition, correct?</p>
        <p>A. That's correct, sir.</p>
        <p>Q. If the person being deposed touched the genitalia of another person, would that be -- and with the intent to arouse the sexual desire, arouse or gratify, as defined in definition (1), would that be, under your understanding then and now ----.</p>
        <p>A. Yes, sir.</p>
        <p>Q. ---- sexual relations?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, sir.</p>
        <p>Q. Yes, it would?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, it would. If you had a direct contact with any of these places in the body, if you had direct contact with intent to arouse or gratify, that would fall within the definition.</p>
        <p>Q. So you didn't do any of those three things ----.</p>
        <p>A. You ----.</p>
        <p>Q. ---- with Monica Lewinsky?</p>
        <p>A. You are free to infer that my testimony is that I did not have sexual relations, as I understood this term to be defined.</p>
        <p>Q. Including touching her breast, kissing her breast, touching her genitalia?</p>
        <p>A. That's correct. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. The question is, If Monica Lewinsky says that while you were in the Oval Office area you touched her breasts, would she be lying?</p>
        <p>A. That is not my recollection. My recollection is that I did not have sexual relations with Ms. Lewinsky, and I'm staying on my former statement about that. . . . My, my statement is that I did not have sexual relations as defined by that.</p>
        <p>Q. If she says that you kissed her breasts, would she be lying?</p>
        <p>A. I'm going to revert to my former statement.</p>
        <p>Q. O.K. If Monica Lewinsky says that while you were in the Oval Office area you touched her genitalia, would she be lying?</p>
        <p>And that calls for a yes, no, or reverting to your former statement.</p>
        <p>A. I will revert to my former statement on that. . . .</p>
        <p>If the deponent is the person who has oral sex performed on him, then the contact is with -- not with anything on that list, but with the lips of another person. It seems to be self-evident that that's what it is. . . . Let me remind you, sir, I read this carefully.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors asked Mr. Clinton about the  affidavit filed by Ms. Lewinsky in the Jones case, in which she denied having a sexual relationship with the President.</p>
        <p>A. I believe at the time that she filled out this affidavit, if she believed that the definition of sexual relationship was two people having intercourse, then this is accurate. And I believe that is the definition that most ordinary Americans would give it.</p>
        <p>Discussions With Lewinsky</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky appeared on the witness list in the Jones case in December 1997 and then received a subpoena to testify. In his grand jury testimony, the President acknowledged ''talking with Ms. Lewinsky about her testimony, or about the prospect that she might have to give testimony.''</p>
        <p>A. I did not want her to have to testify and go through that. And of course, I didn't want her to do that, of course not. . . .</p>
        <p>I remember a conversation about the possibility of her testifying. I believe it must have occurred on the 28th [of December].</p>
        <p>She mentioned to me that she did not want to testify. So, that's how it came up. Not in the context of, I heard you have a subpoena, let's talk about it. . . .</p>
        <p>She raised the issue with me in the context of her desire to avoid testifying, which I certainly understood; not only because there were some embarrassing facts about our relationship that were inappropriate, but also because a whole lot of innocent people were being traumatized and dragged through the mud by these Jones lawyers with their dragnet strategy. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. Do you agree that she was upset about being subpoenaed?</p>
        <p>A. Oh, yes, sir, she was upset. She -- well, she -- we -- she didn't -- we didn't talk about a subpoena. But she was upset. She said, ''I don't want to testify; I know nothing about this; I certainly know nothing about sexual harassment; Why do they want me to testify?'' And I explained to her why they were doing this, and why all these women were on these lists, people that they knew good and well had nothing to do with any sexual harassment. . . .</p>
        <p>I can tell you this: In the context of whether she could be a witness, I have a recollection that she asked me, ''Well, what do I do if I get called as a witness,'' and I said, ''You have to get a lawyer.'' And that's all I said. And I never asked her to lie.</p>
        <p>Q. Did you tell her to tell the truth?</p>
        <p>A. Well, I think the implication was she would tell the truth.</p>
        <p>Conversations With Betty Currie</p>
        <p>A. When I said, 'We were never alone, right?' I think I also asked her a number of other questions, because there were several times, as I'm sure she would acknowledge, when I either asked her to be around. I remember once in particular when I was talking with Ms. Lewinsky when I asked Betty to be in the, actually, in the next room in the dining room, and, as I testified earlier, once in her own office.</p>
        <p>But I meant that she was always in the Oval Office complex, in that complex, while Monica was there. And I believe that this was part of a series of questions I asked her to try to quickly refresh my memory. So, I wasn't trying to get her to say something that wasn't so. And, in fact, I think she would recall that I told her to just relax, go in the grand jury and tell the truth when she had been called as a witness.</p>
        <p>Q. So, when you said to Mrs. Currie that, I was never alone with her, right, you just meant that you and Ms. Lewinsky would be somewhere perhaps in the Oval Office or many times in your back study, is that correct?</p>
        <p>A. That's right. We were in the back study.</p>
        <p>Q And then ----.</p>
        <p>A Keep in mind, sir, I just want to make it -- I was talking about 1997. I was never, ever trying to get Betty Currie to claim that on the occasions when Monica Lewinsky was there when she wasn't anywhere around, that she was. I would never have done that to her, and I don't think she thought about that. I don't think she thought I was referring to that. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. If [Ms. Currie] testified that you told her, Monica came on to me, and I never touched her, you did, in fact, of course, touch Ms. Lewinsky, isn't that right, in a physically intimate way?</p>
        <p>A. Now, I've testified about that. And that's one of those questions that I believe is answered by the statement that I made.</p>
        <p>Q.  What was your purpose in making these statements to Mrs. Currie, if it weren't for the purpose to try to suggest to her what she should say if ever asked?</p>
        <p>A. Now, Mr. Bittman, I told you, the only thing I remember is when all this stuff blew up, I was trying to figure out what the facts were. I was trying to remember. I was trying to remember every time I had seen Ms. Lewinsky. . . .</p>
        <p>Discussions With Aides and Others</p>
        <p>Q. If all of these people -- let's leave out Mrs. Currie for a minute. Vernon Jordan, Sid Blumenthal, John Podesta, Harold Ickes, Erskine Bowles, Harry Thomasson, after the story broke, after Judge Starr's involvement was known on Jan. 21, have said that you denied a sexual relationship with them. Are you denying that?</p>
        <p>A. No.</p>
        <p>Q. And you've told us that you ----.</p>
        <p>A. I'm just telling you what I meant by it. I told you what I meant by it when they started this deposition.</p>
        <p>Q. You've told us now that you were being careful, but that it might have been misleading. Is that correct?</p>
        <p>A. It might have been. . . . So, what I was trying to do was to give them something they could -- that would be true, even if misleading in the context of this deposition, and keep them out of trouble, and let's deal -- and deal with what I thought was the almost ludicrous suggestion that I had urged someone to lie or tried to suborn perjury, in other words.</p>
        <p>TESTING OF A PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
