<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Cardinals Have Other Story Lines</title>
    <meta content="17BERK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1047125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drew, J D</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5DB1F31F934A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Cardinals Have Other Story Lines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow Sports of The Times discusses successful major league debut of St Louis Cardinals baseball player J D Drew; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HE'S a rookie, has been in the major leagues for all of one week, and already he has been booed vigorously. When he walked into the interview room after a pair of good games Tuesday night, virtually everyone in the crowd of reporters not only walked out, but also rushed out. ''I'll have no one to talk to,'' he said, fanned by the breeze of the swiftly departing.</p>
        <p>When he had come to bat in the ninth inning of the Cardinals' first game against the Pirates that night, the cheering by the crowd of 42,422 in Busch Stadium was so thunderous that, he said, he had trouble focusing on the pitcher. But the cheers were for the guy who had batted ahead of him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HE'S a rookie, has been in the major leagues for all of one week, and already he has been booed vigorously. When he walked into the interview room after a pair of good games Tuesday night, virtually everyone in the crowd of reporters not only walked out, but also rushed out. ''I'll have no one to talk to,'' he said, fanned by the breeze of the swiftly departing.</p>
        <p>When he had come to bat in the ninth inning of the Cardinals' first game against the Pirates that night, the cheering by the crowd of 42,422 in Busch Stadium was so thunderous that, he said, he had trouble focusing on the pitcher. But the cheers were for the guy who had batted ahead of him.</p>
        <p>The cheering was for Mark McGwire, who had just socked his 63d home run of the season. In that game, the rookie, J. D. Drew, who just seven days earlier had been called up from the minor leagues, hit two home runs -- the second and third of his terse big league career -- and in the second game of the doubleheader he struck a pair of doubles. He also threw out a runner at the plate from his station in left field.</p>
        <p>Despite the noise after McGwire's homer, the slugger paused for a moment to say something in the ear of young Drew, who was on deck. ''I'm happy to hit a home run for your first two-home run game,'' McGwire told him.</p>
        <p>Later, McGwire said: ''This kid's a talent. It's going to be nice to play with him in the years ahead. He's a lot more advanced than I was as a rookie.''</p>
        <p>After his two-homer night, Jonathan David Drew, 22 years old, took the quick exit of the scribes in stride, since he was following McGwire into the room. ''I would have got out of there, too,'' he said. ''McGwire's the reason everyone's showing up at the park.''</p>
        <p>For Drew, the McGwire spectacle has been remarkable. This season, after all, he had been toiling in the relative privacy of the independent Northern League, of Class AA Little Rock and Class AAA Memphis, his last stop before St. Louis -- and batting over .300 everywhere he materialized. ''My first day in the big leagues was when Mark hit his 62d homer,'' Drew said. ''And then came the 63d. It's being a witness to history.''</p>
        <p>And he stands in the outfield during batting practice and stops to watch McGwire hit his shots, which are hit so high and far they appear like little white satellites. But while respectful, he hardly seems awestruck.</p>
        <p>Going into last night's game against the Pirates -- he was scratched from the starting lineup because of a stiff back -- Drew was hitting .350 in eight games.</p>
        <p>''There's a calmness to him,'' said his manager, Tony La Russa. ''He doesn't play beyond himself. Like the way he got set for the fly ball and threw home. Full confidence.''</p>
        <p>In the middle of all the McGwire turmoil, there suddenly and almost furtively appears a star in the making. And the boos? They were heard when he made his first appearance in the big leagues in a game last week in Cincinnati. They issued from enemy fans who were happy to give grief to the 6-foot, 185-pound newcomer out of Valdosta, Ga., and Florida State, since he had refused to sign with the Phillies after being the second pick over all in the 1997 draft. Drew and his agent, Scott Boras, didn't like the money being offered and opted to try Drew's luck a second time around; he was drafted by St. Louis and signed a deal in July for $7.5 million for four years.</p>
        <p>''Baseball is a business, and the higher up you get the more of a business it is,'' Drew said.</p>
        <p>Some players expressed dissatisfaction at the amount of money Drew was able to command. Not that they were jealous, of course. ''Sure,'' said Willie McGee, the veteran Cardinal outfielder, ''maybe there was resentment by some players for his getting big money and never having played in a major league game, but I don't fault nobody for standing up for what he thinks is right.''</p>
        <p>Drew decided to buck the system, and that doesn't always make friends right away. But Busch Stadium fans have cottoned to him, and chant ''Drew! Drew!'' when he approaches the plate -- unless McGwire has just sent one soaring.</p>
        <p>''He just might be as good as everyone says he was,'' said Gene Lamont, the Pirate manager. ''He's got good power, especially for a small guy, and he looks like he's under control at bat. He runs the bases aggressively, though he's not a burner. Pitchers will see ways to throw to him, and he'll have to make his adjustments.'' In other words, time will tell.</p>
        <p>''He's just getting his feet wet,'' McGee said, ''but it seems like he's been here before.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
