<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Quietly, Alabama Troopers Escort Wallace for Last Time</title>
    <meta content="Y17WAL$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1047163"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alabama</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallace, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0D81F31F934A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Quietly, Alabama Troopers Escort Wallace for Last Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>MONTGOMERY, Ala., Sept. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Memorial servce held, Montgomery, Ala, for late Gov George Wallace; scene described (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The coffin, draped in the blood-red ''X'' on pure white that is Alabama's state flag, seemed almost too heavy to carry. Eight young, strong-looking Alabama state troopers bore the coffin foot by foot down the massive marble steps of the State Capitol, some of them having to place two hands on the rails of the coffin to steady it between them.</p>
        <p>It was not the weight of it -- George C. Wallace was just a small man, withered by paralysis and age -- but the distance. The troopers  carried his coffin some 100 steps, from the rotunda where thousands had viewed his body, down the steep walkway from the Capitol he had once used as a war room to preserve segregation, and off into history. It was eerily quiet, just footsteps on stone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The coffin, draped in the blood-red ''X'' on pure white that is Alabama's state flag, seemed almost too heavy to carry. Eight young, strong-looking Alabama state troopers bore the coffin foot by foot down the massive marble steps of the State Capitol, some of them having to place two hands on the rails of the coffin to steady it between them.</p>
        <p>It was not the weight of it -- George C. Wallace was just a small man, withered by paralysis and age -- but the distance. The troopers  carried his coffin some 100 steps, from the rotunda where thousands had viewed his body, down the steep walkway from the Capitol he had once used as a war room to preserve segregation, and off into history. It was eerily quiet, just footsteps on stone.</p>
        <p>Just minutes before the troopers carried the coffin to Mr. Wallace's funeral and burial here in Montgomery, Janel Bell, a 32-year-old black woman, spoke of the man who had once been shorthand for racism in America, and then, after begging for forgiveness, had won the black vote in his final campaign for governor.</p>
        <p>''A servant of the people,'' Ms. Bell said.</p>
        <p>A populist, if there has ever been one, he mirrored the will of the people no matter if it was cruel or compassionate, and won an unprecedented four terms as Governor from 1962 to 1986. But it was what he would call his greatest mistake -- his defense of segregation -- for which he will live on, in the history books.</p>
        <p>''He was the mouthpiece for what a lot of people thought,'' said Ms. Bell, a public relations director for the Montgomery Museum of Fine Arts, mirroring them at their worst, and when their hearts began to soften.</p>
        <p>It was what people said over and over here as Mr. Wallace, who had died Sunday night at the age of 79 from a heart attack after years of close calls, finally succumbed to time and the sickness and pain that had been his constant companions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wallace, people here said, did not lead Alabama anywhere it did not want to go. He was leading others in the United States there, too, before Arthur Bremer's five bullets left him crippled and in agony in 1972.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Cal Merrell, 50, drove from Atlanta, and had his picture made with the coffin in the background.</p>
        <p>''I heard him talk in Valdosta, Ga., when he was running for President,'' Mr. Merrell said, remembering that he was chilled.</p>
        <p>''How can he have my future in his hands,'' he recalled thinking then.</p>
        <p>Decades later, Mr. Wallace shook his hand and called him his brother.</p>
        <p>''I cried, when I went up there,''  Mr. Merrell said.</p>
        <p>Older white people mixed with older blacks in a steady but never overwhelming stream past the coffin, near a bust of Mr. Wallace's first wife, Lurleen, who was also elected Governor but died of cancer in her first and only term in the late 1960's. People said she ran so that Mr. Wallace could continue to run Alabama and build his power base, but she received more votes than he ever did. Alabamians loved Lurleen, and some of them said with a smile as they filed inside that now, at last, the two were together.</p>
        <p>''I think he's at peace now -- you can see it in his face,'' said Ruby Shirley Noonan, who used to run errands for the Wallaces when she was 15 years old. ''The pain is gone now.''</p>
        <p>One of those who came to say goodbye was James Hood, who was one of the black students whom the Governor had tried to turn away from the University of Alabama when he stood in the door in 1963, blocking their way.</p>
        <p>Like a lot of black people who lived through the civil rights movement, Mr. Wood said he believed that Mr. Wallace was sincere when he said he was sorry, though he could understand why some would doubt him.</p>
        <p>''I think he made peace with God,'' said Mr. Hood, now 56. He was 19 the day Mr. Wallace, surrounded by a sea of state troopers, blocked the door.</p>
        <p>Decades later, he met with a different Mr. Wallace.</p>
        <p>''Whom the Gods would destroy, they first make mad with power,'' Mr. Wallace told him, Mr. Hood recalled.</p>
        <p>''If any man understands the true meaning of pain and suffering, it is George Wallace,'' said Mr. Hood, who found himself again surrounded by state troopers, but this time some of them had skin the color of his own.</p>
        <p>It was not just the physical pain that Mr. Wallace endured, but the knowledge, he said, that no matter how many times he said he was sorry, there would always be those who would not believe, or accept.</p>
        <p>''The fact the people could not forgive him'' haunted Mr. Wallace, said Mr. Hood, who made a career in education administration and now lives in Madison, Wis.</p>
        <p>Dorethea Knight, 35, from Alexander City, was just a baby when Mr. Wallace left many black people terrified.</p>
        <p>''When you're scarred, you're always scarred,'' she said, and Mr. Wallace and the people he tried to suppress have that in common now. ''Is he at peace, truly? You have to wonder about that.''</p>
        <p>As she stood over the coffin, one word crept into her mind: ''Why?''</p>
        <p>''You forgive,'' she said. ''You don't forget.''</p>
        <p>As the last of the mourners and just curious trickled out, the honor guard of state troopers lifted the coffin and made its way, at least one on unsteady legs, down that tortuous stairway to the hearse.</p>
        <p>At the foot of the hill, 68-year-old John Watkins waited on the hot asphalt. Like a lot of older black people, he compared Mr. Wallace to David of the Bible.</p>
        <p>''God forgave him, in the 51st psalm,'' Mr. Watkins said. ''There's no reason he can't do it for the Governor.''</p>
        <p>As the funeral procession wove through Montgomery, high school students and black people from a housing project lined the streets, not a big crowd, but enough to show that someone important had passed their way.</p>
        <p>At his funeral, ministers emphasized that Mr. Wallace had found peace in his faith, and painted a picture of a very human husband and father, not the demagogue who put civil rights advocates at great risk with his fiery speeches that, some of those advocates have said, were like gasoline on a brush fire.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lester H. Spencer, the senior minister at the elegant First United Methodist Church, described how Mr. Wallace, who would be married three times in his life, reacted to the death of Lurleen.</p>
        <p>''He gently rubbed his fingers through her hair,'' Mr. Spencer said and recalled Mr. Wallace's words:  ''Oh, how much we loved you. Goodbye, sweetheart.''</p>
        <p>The legacy of George Wallace, the ministers at his funeral said, should be that he had the courage to admit he was wrong.</p>
        <p>The crowds were smaller than  those for Lurleen Wallace, after she died of cancer in 1968, and smaller than those who gathered to pray for Mr. Wallace when he was shot.</p>
        <p>The crowd was much smaller than those for beloved University of Alabama football coach Paul ''Bear'' Bryant, when people lined overpasses to catch a glimpse of his hearse after his death in the January 1983.</p>
        <p>But older people at today's funeral said there was a reason for that. Mr. Wallace outlived his cronies, and many of the people who put him in office.</p>
        <p>''God gave George Wallace a new heart,'' said Mr. Spencer, the minister. ''The legacy of George Wallace is not the schoolhouse door. The legacy of George Wallace is one of God and change.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
