<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reputation For Trouble Fills Portrait Of Boy's Life</title>
    <meta content="30CHIL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/30/nyregion/30CHIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1476537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Woodbridge (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kleinfield, N R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beeks, Amir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E5D91539F933A05750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="2617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reputation For Trouble Fills Portrait Of Boy's Life</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Life of a Young Troublemaker, and a Brief Life Taken Early</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By N. R. KLEINFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kleinfield, N R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles 10-year-old boy charged with killing 3-year-old Amir Beeks after they met at Woodbridge, NJ, library; boy lives with his blind father and has long history of aggressive behavior toward people and property; classmates characterize him as 'mean' and neighbors describe fierce outbursts; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He caused trouble. But he was 10. How much trouble could he cause?</p>
        <p>He yanked out shrubs, or pounded them with his bat. He peeled the siding off neighbors' houses. He pelted dogs with rocks. He shoved classmates, and hectored them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is impossible to entirely understand a life that is only 10 years old, especially when the 10 years culminated in an unfathomable and brutal act.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He caused trouble. But he was 10. How much trouble could he cause?</p>
        <p>He yanked out shrubs, or pounded them with his bat. He peeled the siding off neighbors' houses. He pelted dogs with rocks. He shoved classmates, and hectored them.</p>
        <p>Not pleasant behavior, certainly, not normal behavior. But he was a child, living alone with a blind father. How much trouble could he cause?</p>
        <p>The frightful answer may have come Thursday, when authorities took him into Family Court and accused him of molesting and murdering 3-year-old Amir Beeks, after spiriting him from a library in Woodbridge, N.J., the day before. Authorities said he beat Amir with a baseball bat, possibly in the older boy's backyard playhouse, and left the 3-year-old to die inside a storm drain at the edge of his yard.</p>
        <p>Investigators have not suggested a motive. The two boys, they said, were strangers. They just happened to bump into each other at the local library, days before the 3-year-old and his family planned to move to Georgia. Because of his age, the suspect is not being publicly identified by the police. Those in Woodbridge already know who he is. Many of his neighbors tell of having sampled his caustic nature.</p>
        <p>It is impossible to entirely understand a life that is only 10 years old, especially when the 10 years culminated in such an unfathomable and brutal act, but that is all there is. The boy's father refused to speak about his son, who is being held in the Middlesex County Juvenile Detention Center, and this story of his life was pieced together from interviews with neighbors, classmates and others familiar with the family, people who always knew he was trouble, just not this much trouble.</p>
        <p>He was born in Woodbridge, a placid middle-class township of about 97,000 people, about 30 miles from Midtown Manhattan, and raised in the modest red-brick Cape Cod house, with the sprawling backyard, the same house his mother grew up in. Her mother, who now lives in Florida, owns it. The house is in the Colonia section of town, and a tree-lined creek courses beside it, patrolled by ducks. The library is a couple of blocks away.</p>
        <p>The boy's mother was born blind, but she was full of pluck. As a child, she would merrily ride her bicycle or rollerskate up and down the block, and neighbors say they made a point of looking out for her.</p>
        <p>His father grew up in Atco, N.J., a small town about 30 miles southeast of Philadelphia, and he had been married before and has a daughter, now in college, from the earlier marriage. She periodically visited her father, and family friends said she was close to the 10-year-old.</p>
        <p>The boy's father has retinitis pigmentosa, the umbrella name for a group of disorders that cause progressive loss of vision. By the time he married, he apparently was completely blind. Various other members of his family have the same disorder. For years, he operated a newsstand, with the help of his wife, inside the central post office in Newark.</p>
        <p>The boy's mother had breast cancer and died in 1998, and friends said the boy was morose over her death. It became difficult, they said, for the father to raise him alone.</p>
        <p>''It would have to be hard for him to raise his son,'' said Dottie Owens, who has known him for years. ''I wouldn't want to be blind and have a child in the house and not be able to see what he was doing. To ask him what he was doing -- 'What are you doing in your room? What are you doing in the bathroom?' -- and he could say anything. As any parent will tell you, it's hard to raise a kid, even with eyes.''</p>
        <p>When his wife became ill, the father gave up the newsstand. Recently, friends said, he became a certified physical therapist and treated clients in his home. Ms. Owens said she was convinced he was ''a wonderful, caring person.''</p>
        <p>Refusing to be limited by his blindness, he pursued an array of outdoor activities -- jogging, boating, swimming, hiking, camping and mountain climbing -- and his son accompanied him on various expeditions. ''He did a lot of things you wouldn't think a blind person could do,'' Ms. Owens said. ''I used to tease him. I'd say, 'When God gave out brains, you thought he said trains and you ran for it.' ''</p>
        <p>Much of his energy was also funneled into fighting discrimination against the handicapped. He got about using a white cane. In 1995, he was hit by a car and several ribs were broken. On other occasions, he told friends he was nearly run over. He lobbied local and state officials to get the police to enforce the ''white cane'' law, which guarantees someone with a white cane or a guide dog the right of way when crossing the street. He called for things like bank checks and phone bills printed in Braille.</p>
        <p>It irritated him how disabled people were treated. ''He felt like a second-  or third-class citizen,'' said Ms. Owens, who herself suffers from multiple sclerosis. ''People would bump into him when they could see his cane. It would make him mad. He'd say, 'Hey, I'm the blind one, not you.' People don't respect you if you have a disability.''</p>
        <p>With some frequency, he filed lawsuits against stores and individuals who he thought endangered him by their negligence. Stores that left carts or bicycles where he might bump into them would find themselves defendants. In one case, he contended that in 1998 he walked into a truck that was illegally parked on a sidewalk outside a doughnut store and injured his right knee.</p>
        <p>He belonged to a number of advocacy groups for the disabled, including the Monday Morning Advocacy Network. About a year ago, he became one of the organization's three facilitators for Middlesex County. Ms. Owens is one of the other facilitators.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, both of them attended a retreat in Trenton with fellow facilitators. He plays the guitar and writes songs, and at the retreat he shared a song he had just written about love and war, and about how the country should not be at war.</p>
        <p>'He Had a Mean Look'</p>
        <p>The father and son were a familiar sight on the streets of Woodbridge, the boy gently guiding his father over curbs, locking hands with him as they crossed the street. Toni Kvist, who lives near them, often took in that sight. ''I thought, what a sweet kid,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The pair would visit the Super Foodtown. The manager remembered how the father would say ''beans'' and the boy would pluck the beans off the shelf. He'd say ''peas,'' and the boy would grab the peas. ''The boy was his father's eyes for a long time,'' the manager said.</p>
        <p>There was that, father and son, out and about. And there was the boy alone.</p>
        <p>''Since I knew him, he's always been bad,'' said a 10-year-old who had been a classmate of the boy. ''He had a mean look, like a mean grin. No one wanted to play with him because he was so mean.''</p>
        <p>He was the scourge of his neighborhood. Other children might annoy neighbors by tramping across their lawns. His neighbors said that he would yank out flowers or smack shrubs with his baseball bat. He would scrawl on fences. He would throw rocks at neighborhood pets. Any animal he saw would become a target.</p>
        <p>A woman who lived across the street said she was walking down the sidewalk with her 2-year-old, and the boy fired a rock at him. When she confronted him, she said he used profanity.</p>
        <p>Another woman said that five years ago, when the boy was 5, her 13-year-old grandson would pass the house and there he was, his face pressed against the front window, defiantly shaking his fist at the older boy as if he intended to charge out and pummel him.</p>
        <p>''Anything you could think of doing, he was already into,'' said Al Gabany, a retired machinist who lives across the street. He said the boy regularly threw bottles and rocks at neighborhood pets. One time, he said, he looked out his window and saw the boy standing on his porch peeling the veneer off the side of the house.</p>
        <p>Maria Barzallo, who lives a couple of houses away, said she used to let the boy play with her 8-year-old son, until she barred him from the house a couple of months ago. He had been breaking things in the house and was rude to her.</p>
        <p>Heather Palfi, who lives on the same street, said: ''He was unsupervised a lot. But I guess with a blind father, how are you going to watch what your son is doing?''</p>
        <p>Several neighbors said they had called the police and the state's Division of Youth and Family Services to complain about the boy's incessant misbehavior. Some of them wondered if he was abused or neglected. No one said they saw any signs of physical abuse on the boy, but neighbors said they often heard he and his father shouting at each other.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, they said they heard the father use language laced with profanity, calling his son to come in for the evening.</p>
        <p>Officials confirmed that a child welfare case on the boy had been opened, but that it had been closed last July. They indicated that no allegations of abuse or neglect had been substantiated, and that recent counseling of the boy was improving his behavior and grades. A state official said a vocational counselor from the State Commission on the Blind and Visually Impaired, who had been to the home numerous times, had informed the child welfare agency that the father was a fit parent.</p>
        <p>But the people who saw his son day after day continued to worry well after the state wrapped things up -- into last fall, into this year, into last week. Almost everyone picked up something that did not sit right. Even Doreen Harrison, whose only involvement was to cut the hair of the father and son at Headquarters Haircutters, sensed it. ''His kid had a free rein too much,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Linda Jones, who lives behind the boy's home and frequently complained to town officials about him, said she called the councilman for her ward two weeks ago because the boy was writing on her fence and beating her shrubs with a bat. She said she got into a shouting match with his father. She said she told the councilman, ''Something bad is going to happen to that family.''</p>
        <p>After he received the call, Robert G. Luban, the councilman, said he got the police to increase patrols of the street.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, the boy appeared to prefer his own company. He did not seem to have friends, or even desire them. Some neighbors said he often seemed sad. Joann Borelli, who lives two doors down and was among the neighbors who contacted the authorities about him, said she sometimes noticed him by himself, quietly crying.</p>
        <p>Problems at School</p>
        <p>His aberrant behavior carried over to school. He attended Pennsylvania Avenue School No. 27 in Colonia until last year, when he was transferred because of his persistent discipline problems.</p>
        <p>''In first grade I remember him as an angry little boy,'' said Judy Brenckman, who worked as a lunchtime aide for his first-grade class. ''He was rambunctious and did not want to listen to anyone. When kids are in first grade, they are always getting into a little bit of trouble, but he was always in a little more trouble than the rest.''</p>
        <p>A while ago, she said, he hit another boy with a baseball bat while they were playing, and the boy had to get stitches.</p>
        <p>''He's been bad since Day 1,'' a former classmate said. ''He always had detention, and some kids were afraid to come into school because he would threaten them.''</p>
        <p>The classmate said that last year he threw a small classroom desk at their teacher. It missed and hit the blackboard. ''After that happened, we did not see him in class anymore,'' the classmate said.</p>
        <p>Only in recent months, Ms. Owens said, did the father confide to her the extent of the problems he was having with his son. She learned that the boy had been expelled from his new school and was being tutored at home. The father told her that his son was happier not to be with other children.</p>
        <p>''I told him that's not healthy,'' she said. ''He needs to be with other kids.'' Last week, she said, the father and the boy had visited a military school in Wall Township, N.J., and he was supposed to start going there sometime in April. She did not think the boy was happy about that prospect.</p>
        <p>Peculiar Boarders</p>
        <p>Neighbors were also uneasy about scruffy boarders they said stayed at the house, in such frequency in recent years that they wondered if it had become a halfway house.</p>
        <p>''There were all these guys,'' Mr. Gabany said, ''and they'd go up to the corner and get liquor and bring it back there. So the boy was a loser from the start. You're raised in an environment with drunks and whatnot, and your father can't see what's going on.''</p>
        <p>Jim Tuzzo, an investment banker who lives across from the boy's house, said that between the police officers visiting the house and the seedy characters staying there, the place was a neighborhood sore spot. ''It's a quiet neighborhood,'' he said, ''so the place sort of stuck out like a sore thumb.''</p>
        <p>No boarders, however, appear to be currently living there.</p>
        <p>Ms. Owens said that the father recently told her that his mother-in-law intended to sell the house and that he needed to move out by September. She said he wanted to move back somewhere around Atco.</p>
        <p>When the father spoke about the boy's unruliness, Ms. Owens said, she advised him to be supportive. ''I told him not to be angry with him,'' she said. ''It will only make it worse. I told him that you still have to be his friend.'' She did not know whether he followed her advice. She had not seen the dark side of the boy. He was always polite to her, she said. No one knew all there was to know about one blind man and his son.</p>
        <p>Nobody knew why, the day his son was in court charged with murder, the father kept up his daily routine of going to Murphy's Spirit Shop to buy lottery tickets.</p>
        <p>Nobody knew why the boy, who did not seem to have any deep interest beyond making trouble, who was not a reader, who did not bother much with homework, happened to go to the library last week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
