<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agriculture Dept. Plans Hunt for Source of Tainted Beef</title>
    <meta content="Y23MEA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="952309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hamburgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">E Coli (Bacteria)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hudson Foods Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Agriculture Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">E Coli (Bacteria)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1D7133EF930A1575BC0A961958260" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agriculture Dept. Plans Hunt for Source of Tainted Beef</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Agriculture Department will undertake search for source of E. coli bacteria that led to recall of 25 million pounds of ground beef at Hudson Food meat plant in Columbus, Neb, but it will be hampered in this search by the fact that scientists are still uncertain how animals--before they are slaughtered--become contaminated with bacteria; some officials say Government has not developed a system to identify contaminated animals because of opposition from food industry and the inaction of agencies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the next several days, Agriculture Department officials across the country will pore over mounds of paperwork and interview people in an effort to determine the source of the E. coli bacteria that led to this week's recall of 25 million pounds of ground beef.</p>
        <p>But the officials acknowledge that their search will be hampered by one simple fact: For all their improved safeguards, they do not really know how bacteria get into the nation's food supply.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the next several days, Agriculture Department officials across the country will pore over mounds of paperwork and interview people in an effort to determine the source of the E. coli bacteria that led to this week's recall of 25 million pounds of ground beef.</p>
        <p>But the officials acknowledge that their search will be hampered by one simple fact: For all their improved safeguards, they do not really know how bacteria get into the nation's food supply.</p>
        <p>Most of the modernization has come in processing plants and slaughterhouses, where new Federal monitoring systems are to go into effect next year.</p>
        <p>The officials also said scientists were still uncertain how animals -- before they are slaughtered -- become contaminated with bacteria like E. coli 0157:H7, a potentially deadly organism that was discovered this month in ground beef processed at a plant in Nebraska.</p>
        <p>Some officials say that the Government has missed opportunities to develop a system to identify contaminated animals because of opposition from the powerful food industry, and inaction by agencies.</p>
        <p>Referring to the various possible ways E. coli and other organisms enter an animal before it is killed, Agriculture Secretary Dan Glickman said in an interview, ''We would like to expend more research resources on that.''</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the Agriculture Department announced that the plant, owned by Hudson Foods of Rogers, Ark., would suspend operations and recall 25 million pounds of ground beef that is possibly contaminated with the E. coli bacteria.</p>
        <p>The recalled meat had been distributed as frozen hamburger patties to fast-food chains like Burger King, a subsidiary of Grand Metropolitan of Britain, and Boston Market and retail outlets like Wal-Mart Stores and Safeway supermarkets.</p>
        <p>So far, the department has evidence that 16 people in Colorado became ill because of the bacteria in meat from the Hudson plant. But Thomas J. Billy, administrator of the Food Safety and Inspection Service, a branch of the Agriculture Department, said officials believed that those victims became ill after undercooking frozen patties they had bought in stores.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glickman said the Colorado outbreak highlighted the need for the Agriculture Department to work harder in educating the public how to prepare foods properly -- like insuring that meat reaches an internal temperature of 160 degrees Fahrenheit for at least 15 seconds.</p>
        <p>Undercooked hamburgers sold by Jack in the Box fast-food restaurants in 1993 and found to have the E. coli bacteria were blamed for killing four children and making hundreds of other people ill.</p>
        <p>Since then, restaurants have been advised to cook meat at temperatures that are sufficient to kill any harmful bacteria. In addition, it was largely as a result of the Jack in the Box outbreak that Government officials began devising new, more sophisticated protocols for inspecting meat, seafood and poultry while they are processed. The protocols were included in the Clinton Administration's food safety program that finally won Congressional approval this year as part of the 1998 budget.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Glickman, a former Democratic Representative from Kansas, said the contamination found in the meat from the Hudson plant underscored the need to learn how animals contract harmful bacteria before they reach the slaughterhouse.</p>
        <p>Bacteria enter an animal's system through a variety of ways, including drinking water or contact with fecal matter, which often clings to an animal's skin. But once they are slaughtered, skinned and deboned, it is impossible to determine which carcass might have contaminated others with the bacteria.</p>
        <p>With new inspection controls at the slaughterhouses, one way to help track the source, Mr. Billy said, would be to tag animals as they leave a particular farm or feed lot, where farmers often send livestock to be fattened before slaughter.</p>
        <p>Such a tracing system was proposed to Congress in 1980, said Carol Tucker Foreman, an Agriculture Department official in the Carter Administration. But it stalled under intense opposition from food industry groups and has never progressed in several subsequent efforts to get similar legislation though Congress.</p>
        <p>In legislation that the Administration could send to Congress as early as the fall, Mr. Glickman said he would probably include a proposal for a tracing system as well as a request that the Agriculture Department be given the authority to require food companies to recall products that might be contaminated. He said he would also ask for the authority to impose fines against companies that do not comply with Federal monitoring regulations.</p>
        <p>''Most Government agencies have that,'' he said. ''It would be a useful authority to use.''</p>
        <p>But the Administration's food safety plan, budgeted for $43.2 million, includes only $4.1 million for research on issues bearing directly on problems of animal contamination.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glickman added: ''Do we have all the resources we need? No. But that's life. We'll keep asking for more.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>No Burgers for Burger King</p>
        <p>MIAMI, Aug. 22 (AP) -- Burger King ran out of hamburgers today at its 700 restaurants in the United States after clearing its inventory of beef from Hudson Foods. Burger King, based in Miami, said all of its restaurants would have burgers back on the menu on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
