<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GOLF: Notebook;   Norman Remains Stoic As Fate Remains Cruel</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="349808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLF</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAZ, JAIME</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D7143CF930A35756C0A966958260" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GOLF: Notebook;   Norman Remains Stoic As Fate Remains Cruel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAIME DIAZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAZ, JAIME</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Greg Norman seems sure to be remembered as golf's Sisyphus. At this point, Norman himself would settle for being a logo-bearing Job who will at least come out ahead in the end.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Greg Norman seems sure to be remembered as golf's Sisyphus. At this point, Norman himself would settle for being a logo-bearing Job who will at least come out ahead in the end.</p>
        <p>Greg Norman seems sure to be remembered as golf's Sisyphus. At this point, Norman himself would settle for being a logo-bearing Job who will at least come out ahead in the end.</p>
        <p>David Frost became the latest player to push Norman's rock off the top of a tournament mountain when he holed a 50-foot sand shot on the 72d hole of the USF &amp; G Classic in New Orleans on Sunday to beat Norman by a shot.</p>
        <p>The defeat marked the fourth time that the Great White Shark has lost a tournament to a player who sank his final shot from off the green.</p>
        <p>The loss seemed particularly cruel because Norman had just birdied the difficult 18th by hitting a spectacular 2-iron to less than a foot from the hole.</p>
        <p>Telltale Roar</p>
        <p>Norman wasn't watching the television screen as Frost completed his bunker-to-bunker birdie. When he heard the roar and confirmed the worst, he turned to the tournament director, Tommy Wulff, and said stoicly, ''See you at dinner, mate.''</p>
        <p>Norman continued his brave front after arriving at this week's G.T.E. Byron Nelson Classic in Dallas. ''I forgot about it,'' he said Tuesday of his latest spectacular runner-up finish. ''A lot of people like to try and find a negative to it, but the most positive thing is that it probably happens more to me because I'm more in contention.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Norman has been there all year. He has five top-five finishes in seven tournaments, and won Doral with a sudden-death chip-in of his own. His only bad round was his most conspicuous, an opening 78 at the Masters.</p>
        <p>''I think Greg is just snakebit,'' Tom Watson said last year. ''There is nothing wrong with his game. It's just that you can't win without luck. I know Tom Watson has had more than his share of luck in his career. Greg hasn't. And there is no rule that says it will even out in the end.''</p>
        <p>Turnabout for Frost</p>
        <p>Nearly lost in Norman's defeat was the improbability of Frost's victory.</p>
        <p>Before New Orleans, Frost had missed eight cuts in a row, the longest such streak of his six years on the PGA Tour, and the most prolonged period of futility to precede a victory in memory.</p>
        <p>After finishing tied for eighth at Tucson, Ariz., in January, where he shot a torrid 60 in the second round, Frost decided to switch from the irons he had used since joining the tour in 1985 to a new set. He finished fifth at Pebble Beach with the new irons, but then began a string of 16 consecutive rounds of 71 or worse.</p>
        <p>Frost and his swing coach, David Leadbetter, filmed his swing and went over it carefully, but could find nothing wrong.</p>
        <p>Finally, after five successive missed cuts, Frost decided that the slightly different weight distribution in the heads of his new irons was causing him to think that he would hit the ball to the left. He switched back to his original set, and though he missed the next three cuts, he was encouraged.</p>
        <p>''I just needed a little time to settle down using my old clubs again,'' Frost said. ''It wasn't long before I felt I was hitting the ball well enough to win.''</p>
        <p>Frost didn't mention that he also switched putters before winning at New Orleans. Maybe because he didn't need one on the last hole.</p>
        <p>Driver Gaining Notice</p>
        <p>On the subject of clubs, the hottest implement in golf is the ''J's Professional Weapon,'' the driver being used by Jack Nicklaus, Raymond Floyd and Greg Norman, and tried by scores of other PGA Tour pros.</p>
        <p>Nicklaus first brought attention to the metal-headed, graphite-shafted driver when he used it to win the Tradition, hitting several drives more than 330 yards. Floyd used the driver to great advantage at the Masters, and Norman hit eye-popping drives at Hilton Head and New Orleans.</p>
        <p>''I not only hit it longer, I hit it straighter,'' said Norman, who along with Lon Hinkle leads the PGA Tour in driving distance with an average tee shot of 276.1 yards.</p>
        <p>The club was designed by Japan's leading player, Masashi (Jumbo) Ozaki, and the golf division of Bridgestone. It is named ''J's'' for the nicknames of the three Ozaki brothers, Jumbo, Naomichi (Joe) and Tateo (Jet).</p>
        <p>The company says the head is weighted more efficiently than is any other metal head, and combined with the graphite-fiber shaft produces a shot that jumps off the club face and rolls farther after landing than shots with other drivers.</p>
        <p>''We know it works,'' said Darryl Olson, national sales manager for Bridgestone. ''But there is still a lot of mystery about why it works.''</p>
        <p>The ''J's'' woods are available to the general consumer in Japan, but besides touring pros, only a chosen few Americans, including George Bush and Dan Quayle, have got their hands on the coveted driver. Olson said the clubs would be available for limited distribution in the United States this month. They will retail for $400, or $1,200 for a set of three.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
