<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Verses That Take a Cue From Famous Canvases</title>
    <meta content="06VIEW$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The View From: Bronxville" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="920753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="The View From: Bronxville"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bronxville (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westchester Arts Council</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EEDC1F3AF935A35757C0A961958260" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Verses That Take a Cue From Famous Canvases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>BRONXVILLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Focus on artists-in-the-schools program at Bronxville, NY, middle school that teaches students understanding of poetry by asking them to write it; program is sponsored by Westchester Arts Council; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE poems began as a classroom exercise at the middle school here and ended up hanging on the walls of the bookstore at the National Gallery in Washington.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mary Schenk, an eighth-grade English teacher, and Joanna Goodman, a poet visiting the school through the Westchester Arts Council's artists-in-the-schools program, decided to expand their pupils' understanding of poetry by asking them to write it. Rather than simply telling them to write about love, loneliness or insecurity, for instance, Ms. Schenk and Ms. Goodman gave the students specific examples.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE poems began as a classroom exercise at the middle school here and ended up hanging on the walls of the bookstore at the National Gallery in Washington.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mary Schenk, an eighth-grade English teacher, and Joanna Goodman, a poet visiting the school through the Westchester Arts Council's artists-in-the-schools program, decided to expand their pupils' understanding of poetry by asking them to write it. Rather than simply telling them to write about love, loneliness or insecurity, for instance, Ms. Schenk and Ms. Goodman gave the students specific examples.</p>
        <p>The teachers provided reproductions of paintings by artists like Picasso, Salvador Dali, Rene Magritte and Edward Hopper and instructed the students to write a poem about how they would feel if they were inside the painting, and to concentrate not so much on concepts as on that which can be received by the eye, ear and other senses. Ms. Goodman then read works by such well-known poets as Wallace Stevens and Pablo Neruda and allowed the students to emulate the sentence structure and the rhythms as they wrote their own poetry about the paintings.</p>
        <p>The result was a group of poems remarkably sophisticated for first-time 13-  and 14-year-old authors. The cadences mirrored those of some of the finest modern poets. (Asked about this particular practice, Ms. Goodman said she used the professionals' poems as models and prompts.) The students' own original imagery was vivid and evocative. Because some of the paintings used in the exercise hang in the National Gallery, and because the eighth grade makes a trip each year to Washington, Ms. Schenk and Ms. Goodman decided to take a chance on whether the gallery was interested in displaying the poems. After an initial refusal, the gallery administrators agreed to hang several in the bookstore, where they will remain through this month.</p>
        <p>''It's very exciting,'' Ms. Schenk said. ''With adolescents, it's often hard to get them to write about things other than their own feelings. But here, they're learning how to look and express themselves through poetic imagery.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Goodman said: ''Poetry is about looking at things in a different way, about how to see. In a sense, we are teaching these students to learn to see.''</p>
        <p>The students liked what Ms. Goodman called ''finding and describing a precise moment in time.'' Renata Machado, for example, said that in the past, in other classes, she had been asked to analyze poems, but with Ms. Goodman she could extract from a painting certain concrete information and turn it from evocative visual language into her own evocative verbal language.</p>
        <p>''I felt there was no real happiness, no real love anywhere,'' she said of Edward Hopper's moody ''Cape Cod Evening.'' The painting, with dark trees in the background, a grim-looking couple in front of a white house gazing distractedly at a collie that is turned away from them, exudes the sort of desolation often found in the most mundane of scenes. Renata said she sensed this: ''Even the trees look isolated, separated.''</p>
        <p>Her poem derived in part from ''Dangerous Cooks'' by Gerald Stern, which begins, ''I am serving my own head on a platter  . . .'' Renata writes:</p>
        <p>I am standing against the wall by myself as Hopper once did.</p>
        <p>I see the yellow field tossing at the rage of the wind.</p>
        <p>I hear rustling from the trees as they batter each other.</p>
        <p>I feel bitter as the time rolls by.</p>
        <p>I remember the sun that used to shine.</p>
        <p>Behind the house is my soul, hidden away.</p>
        <p>I ask the field why I'm so alone.</p>
        <p>Wherever I go I hear silence.</p>
        <p>Isolation and loneliness are also themes in Damien Scoditti's study of ''Gare Montparnasse (The Melancholy of Departure)'' by Giorgio de Chirico. The Surrealist's famous stark, long shadows inspired Damien to write: ''I remember the arches, the arches of a lost palace. Light cuts the stone evenly from the shadows. Wherever I go darkness follows close behind.''</p>
        <p>Damien said: ''I think I understand what this painting is saying. I've gone on vacation to Italy with my parents. The mood of a place changes when you're on vacation. When you're near the end, and you know it's your last day, the very same place looks different from the way you see it on your first day. On your last day it takes on a wistful look.''</p>
        <p>Still more desolation was apparent to Michael Feldman when he looked at ''The Tragedy,'' Picasso's painting of a man, woman and child at the water's edge, rendered in varying shades of blue. ''You get a chill just seeing it, it's amazing,'' he said, explaining why he ended his poem with the line, ''Wherever I go, I wander as a ghost.'' But Erik Gustafson found the painting he studied -- Winslow Homer's ''Breezing Up (A Fair Wind)'' exhilarating, writing of splashing water, full sails, screaming gulls. Writing itself is exciting, he said, calling it a ''freeing type of thing.''</p>
        <p>Marie Shelli, contemplating Magritte's whimsical ''Blank Signature,'' a play on perspective with a horse and rider positioned in an impossible optical illusion, wrote about being ''part of the horse and part of the forest.''</p>
        <p>Charles Walton looked at Georgia O'Keeffe's ''Jack in the Pulpit No. IV'' and saw ''burning white and purple phosphorous.''</p>
        <p>Then there was Clay Satenstein, who in a separate exercise without looking at a painting composed ''Ode to the Dream.'' Using Pablo Neruda's ''Ode to the Storm'' as a model, Clay wrote:</p>
        <p>Last night you squeezed out my thoughts</p>
        <p>and put them in the sky of night</p>
        <p>that is the eye for my lips.</p>
        <p>But now I can't reach my words</p>
        <p>because my mind is resting on a star</p>
        <p>that the tallest ladder can't reach.</p>
        <p>My eyes are broken up and</p>
        <p>scattered in the trees that I can't climb.</p>
        <p>You wanted room for yourself.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes it's like that -- the thoughts and pictures just get into your head,'' Clay said. ''I sat down to write a poem and all of these things just popped into my mind.''</p>
        <p>The View From: Bronxville</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
