<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A PERSONAL SIDE TO WAR IN ZAIRE</title>
    <meta content="06ZAIR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="921099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zaire</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mobutu Sese Seko (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tshisekedi, Etienne (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kabila, Laurent</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Congo, The Democratic Republic of</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Congo, The Democratic Republic of the</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6D7143CF935A35757C0A961958260" item-length="1233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A PERSONAL SIDE TO WAR IN ZAIRE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>KINSHASA, Zaire, April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zairian Govt and rebel aides meet in South Africa for first face-to-face talks as Pres Mobutu Sese Seko, Prime Min Etienne Tshisekedi and rebel leader Laurent Kabila struggle for power; diplomats fear rivals will do their utmost to prevail, regardless of consequences; Tshisekedi has launched assault on Mobutu's faltering authority instead of attacking rebels; has angered even own allies by dismissing Parliament, while failing to build ties with rebels; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As peace talks opened in South Africa today to resolve Zaire's civil war, political events here are hurtling toward a potentially explosive denouement, with the three leading political figures locked in a struggle for the power long held by the dictator Mobutu Sese Seko.</p>
        <p>With a rebel alliance that has already swept into control of the country's eastern regions now advancing through the mineral-rich zones of central and southern Zaire, President Mobutu's authority has been bluntly challenged on another front by a newly appointed Prime Minister.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As peace talks opened in South Africa today to resolve Zaire's civil war, political events here are hurtling toward a potentially explosive denouement, with the three leading political figures locked in a struggle for the power long held by the dictator Mobutu Sese Seko.</p>
        <p>With a rebel alliance that has already swept into control of the country's eastern regions now advancing through the mineral-rich zones of central and southern Zaire, President Mobutu's authority has been bluntly challenged on another front by a newly appointed Prime Minister.</p>
        <p>Within hours of taking office on Wednesday, Prime Minister Etienne Tshisekedi, a popular politician and Mr. Mobutu's longstanding rival, defied the President by dissolving the Parliament and naming a Government that included none of Mr. Mobutu's allies.</p>
        <p>In a bid to seal a peace that would exclude Mr. Mobutu from power, Mr. Tshisekedi offered the rebel leader, Laurent Kabila, six Government posts, including the ministries of defense and foreign affairs.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Tshisekedi expected these moves, which many here in the capital have likened to a civilian coup d'etat, to forge a power-sharing arrangement with Mr. Kabila, it has produced the opposite effect.</p>
        <p>As rebels took control of the country's diamond-mining capital, Mbuji-Mayi, on Friday, Mr. Kabila denounced Mr. Tshisekedi as a lackey who would go down to defeat with the system he says he is combating.</p>
        <p>As the rebels predicted new victories in the days ahead, Zairian Government and rebel officials met for their first face-to-face talks today in South Africa, but mediators played down any expectations that the meeting would end the fighting. Mr. Mobutu previously had demanded a cease-fire before peace talks, whereas Mr. Kabila insisted on holding talks to work out a truce.</p>
        <p>Making the situation in Kinshasa even more uncertain, lawmakers angered by Mr. Tshisekedi's legally questionable dissolution of Parliament and reportedly acting with the encouragement of Mr. Mobutu, have already begun moves to unseat the new Prime Minister.</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. Tshisekedi, anticipating such moves, are betting on their leader's popularity in the capital to protect his claim to power, and have already announced that ''a Parliament that no longer exists cannot affect us.''</p>
        <p>With Mr. Mobutu, Mr. Kabila and Mr. Tshisekedi facing off, what has emerged in Zaire in recent days, political analysts say, is a sort of zero-sum struggle for power among three determined men of approximately the same generation who have all enjoyed or fought for power in Zaire for more than 30 years.</p>
        <p>''What these events have shown is that there can be no give where these three are concerned,'' said one Western diplomat here. ''All of them see the days ahead as their last chance to win or to hold onto power. And what is to be feared here is that each of them will do his utmost to prevail, whatever the consequences.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mobutu, who has ruled this country for 31 years, reputedly becoming one of the world's richest men even as Zaire has sunk to the level of Africa's poorest countries, is said to be dying of prostate cancer, and yet shows no signs of acknowledging his fading grip on power.</p>
        <p>Just this week, after meeting with the newly appointed Prime Minister, Mr. Mobutu said that Mr. Tshisekedi's political problems were not his concern, and announced that if elections could be organized in his country, he would be a candidate for the presidency.</p>
        <p>In the past, Mr. Mobutu was fond of proclaiming, ''I will never be known as the former President of Zaire.'' Now, however, foreign diplomats say that years of profligate living, and the financial demands of a huge family and official entourage, have left Mr. Mobutu clinging more desperately than ever to his position.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tshisekedi, a senior official in Mr. Mobutu's early Governments who has been the President's most implacable civilian opponent for nearly 20 years, was appointed for the third time as Prime Minister in the hope that his popularity would somehow help blunt the rebels' advances.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tshisekedi's previous two stints as Prime Minister, in 1991 and 1993, came after a politically weakened Mr. Mobutu was forced by international and domestic pressure to allow multiparty politics and accept a Government formed by the opposition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tshisekedi, 65, known as a headstrong politician who nurses even minor slights for years, has never acknowledged or forgiven his last dismissal by Mr. Mobutu, in 1993.</p>
        <p>And instead of attacking the rebels, whom he hoped to seduce, Mr. Tshisekedi launched a frontal assault on Mr. Mobutu's dwindling authority, dissolving a Parliament that the President had packed with his own allies.</p>
        <p>After years of leading the opposition, Mr. Tshisekedi apparently sees Mr. Mobutu's faltering authority as his own last chance for power. And the moment has been made even more desperate by the rebellion's stunning battlefield advances, and the strong popularity Mr. Kabila seems to enjoy in areas he now controls.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for Mr. Tshisekedi, his gambit against Mr. Mobutu appears to be failing not only in terms of building bridges with the rebellion, but also in Kinshasa. In this ramshackle capital of 4.5 million, being a politician is one of the few certain paths to material comfort. And by dismissing the Parliament, Mr. Tshisekedi has angered even his own allies.</p>
        <p>Alexis Likango, a spokesman for Mr. Tshisekedi's party, said some party members ''acknowledge the grievances of Mr. Mobutu's movement'' against the Prime Minister. Many here now expect a parliamentary bid for Mr. Tshisekedi's formal removal within days.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Kabila, 56, a rebel who has spent 30 years underground or in exile, this too is something of a last chance.</p>
        <p>Few here could have imagined six months ago that Mr. Kabila would have come so far as to control 30 percent of Zairian territory. And the closer he has come to toppling Mr. Mobutu, the steelier Mr. Kabila has become toward potential rivals, like Mr. Tshisekedi.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, after winning Kisangani, the third-largest city, Mr. Kabila said that opposition parties would be banned in rebel-held areas. Once he takes over the capital, he told reporters, he plans to rule for a year at the head of an interim administration composed entirely of rebel officials. After this transition period, Mr. Kabila said there would be national elections.</p>
        <p>This week, the rebel spokesman Raphael Ghenda said that his movement would not allow international election observers to operate in the country.</p>
        <p>The fact that Mr. Mobutu, then army chief of staff, seized power amid similar pledges in 1965 has not escaped attention here. One senior aide to Mr. Tshisekedi responded to these plans by saying, ''We are not getting rid of one strongman to replace him with another.''</p>
        <p>But the rebel reply was as brutal as it was swift.</p>
        <p>''If Tshisekedi wants to pilot a ship that is going down,'' said Gaktan Kakudji, an associate of Mr. Kabila, ''he must learn how to swim, because it is going to sink.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
