<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Building Employees Go Out on Strike</title>
    <meta content="16home" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/16/realestate/16home.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060416T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1754689"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EFDF163FF935A25757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Building Employees Go Out on Strike</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">If Building Employees Go Out on Strike ...</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT midnight on Thursday the contract between property owners and Local 32BJ of the Service Employees International Union, which represents thousands of workers who keep New York City's residential buildings humming, will expire. If a new contract is not in place by then, the workers say they are prepared to strike.</p>
        <p>Here, then, is what building owners and managers, including co-op and condominium boards, can do to prepare for that possibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doormen may go on strike this week. What should building owners and managers do to prepare for that possibility?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT midnight on Thursday the contract between property owners and Local 32BJ of the Service Employees International Union, which represents thousands of workers who keep New York City's residential buildings humming, will expire. If a new contract is not in place by then, the workers say they are prepared to strike.</p>
        <p>Here, then, is what building owners and managers, including co-op and condominium boards, can do to prepare for that possibility.</p>
        <p>''Negotiations always come down to the last possible moment,'' said Dan Wurtzel, the chief operating officer of Cooper Square Realty, a Manhattan management company. ''So every building has to prepare as if there will be a strike.''</p>
        <p>The most important issue, Mr. Wurtzel said, will be security. ''For any of our buildings that have doormen, we need to go out an hire security guards,'' he said, adding that since guards are not unionized, they will cross picket lines.</p>
        <p>But the problem with hiring guards to replace doormen is that everyone else will be trying to do the same thing at the same time. Any building that waits until the last minute to hire a guard, he said, may not be able to find one.</p>
        <p>At times of peak demand, Mr. Wurtzel said, security companies usually pass along their costs to clients. ''The security companies have to go out and hire additional personnel, train them, put them in uniform and make sure they are licensed,'' he said. ''And that can result in an up-front cost, usually covered by the property owner, that ranges from $500 to $1,500 per guard.''</p>
        <p>Since the security guards will not know who lives in the building, residents should be issued passes, Mr. Wurtzel said, and should fill out a form for visitors. ''During a strike, the building is basically shut down to outsiders,'' Mr. Wurtzel said. ''You don't have a pass, you don't get in.''</p>
        <p>Buildings may decide to lock their front doors, which means that residents should be sure they have keys.</p>
        <p>After security, the next most important thing, Mr. Wurtzel said, is to keep residents informed of what is expected of them. For example, they should know that trash compactors will probably not be working and that they will have to bag their trash and take it to some central area, wherever building management wants the bags deposited.</p>
        <p>Residents should also expect to pick up their own packages in the lobby and to go down to the lobby for food and other deliveries.</p>
        <p>James Berg, the president of the Realty Advisory Board in Manhattan, said that building managers should test alarm systems to make sure they work and should check insurance policies to see if additional coverage is necessary, particularly if residents will be taking over duties of striking workers.</p>
        <p>Owners and boards should also ensure that their heating oil tanks have been topped off, since unionized fuel delivery drivers may refuse to cross picket lines, and they should make plans for basic cleaning services.</p>
        <p>Mary Ann Rothman, the executive director of the Council of New York Cooperatives and Condominiums, said that since co-op and condominium buildings are basically ''owner operated,'' residents can be enlisted to deliver mail and packages, monitor the front door, operate elevators, clean the building and help neighbors who may need special assistance.</p>
        <p>''A well-planned system of committees to deal with the particular needs of the building is advised,'' Ms. Rothman said, noting that residents who are willing to volunteer should make their names, e-mail addresses and telephone numbers available to committee leaders.</p>
        <p>''The most important thing to remember is that it would be unfair to feel animosity toward a loyal employee for walking a picket line,'' Ms. Rothman said, adding that striking employees will not be paid and that they will receive only a small stipend from the union. ''When the strike is over, the employees will be back at work.''</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 16, 2006, Sunday  A credit is omitted on Page 12 of the Real Estate section today for the Your Home column, about ways for residential buildings to prepare for a possible strike by service employees. The writer is Jay Romano.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 16, 2006, Sunday</p>
        <p>A credit is omitted on Page 12 of the Real Estate section today for the Your Home column, about ways for residential buildings to prepare for a possible strike by service employees. The writer is Jay Romano.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
