<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From the Smithsonian, A Modern Tasting Menu</title>
    <meta content="08GLUE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/08/arts/design/08GLUE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1365930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Academy of Design</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Smithsonian American Art Museum (Washington, DC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glueck, Grace</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Smithsonian American Art Museum</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Academy of Design Museum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5DB173CF93BA35751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From the Smithsonian, A Modern Tasting Menu</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From the Smithsonian, a Modern Tasting Menu</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRACE GLUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glueck, Grace</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Grace Glueck reviews 20th-century American art from Smithsonian American Art Museum on view at New York's National Academy of Design Museum; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It doesn't yet top a must-see list of 20th-century art in Washington. But thanks to some generous donors in recent years, the Smithsonian American Art Museum turns out to have accumulated an impressive if small collection of 20th-century American works. It is strongest in Modernism and Abstract Expressionism, but also has a few choice examples from earlier and later periods.</p>
        <p>Now, thanks to a renovation of the Old Patent Office Building where the museum is housed, a portion of the collection is on view in New York at the National Academy of Design Museum. Titled ''Modernism and Abstraction: Treasures From the Smithsonian American Art Museum,'' the group here is one of eight separate shows sent on tour around the country by the Smithsonian during the renovation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some of the Smithsonian American Art Museum's impressive 20th-century American works are on view at the National Academy of Design Museum in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It doesn't yet top a must-see list of 20th-century art in Washington. But thanks to some generous donors in recent years, the Smithsonian American Art Museum turns out to have accumulated an impressive if small collection of 20th-century American works. It is strongest in Modernism and Abstract Expressionism, but also has a few choice examples from earlier and later periods.</p>
        <p>Now, thanks to a renovation of the Old Patent Office Building where the museum is housed, a portion of the collection is on view in New York at the National Academy of Design Museum. Titled ''Modernism and Abstraction: Treasures From the Smithsonian American Art Museum,'' the group here is one of eight separate shows sent on tour around the country by the Smithsonian during the renovation.</p>
        <p>The more than 50 paintings and sculptures make up a somewhat incoherent exhibition, one that has more breadth than depth. But there are fine works by some well-known names, including Max Weber, Stuart Davis, Laszlo Moholy-Nagy, Arthur Dove, Marsden Hartley, Georgia O'Keeffe, Hans Hofmann, Clyfford Still, Robert Motherwell, Alma Thomas, Ellsworth Kelly, Josef Albers, William Baziotes, Milton Avery, Philip Guston, Willem de Kooning, Robert Rauschenberg, Richard Diebenkorn and David Hockney.</p>
        <p>Happily revived here, too, are a handful of American Modernists of the 1930's and 40's, among them Jan Matulka, Theodore Roszak, Esphyr Slobodkina, Suzy Frelinghuysen, Carl Holty, Ilya Bolotowsky, George L. K. Morris, Gertrude Greene and Albert Gallatin.</p>
        <p>But the collection makes no claim to comprehensiveness. There are notable gaps: no Pop, no Minimalism, few examples of sculpture. Some of the works fall outside the artist's most representative period, but sometimes that's all to the good. Still, going through the show, a viewer can have an illuminating glimpse of what went on in American art across a 75-year period.</p>
        <p>A lovely painting, ''Summer,'' Max Weber's vision of voluptuous nudes derived from African sculpture, goes all the way back to 1909, and ''The Thundershower,'' a lively Futurist-oriented work by a little-known Philadelphia artist, H. Lyman Sayen, dates from 1917-18.</p>
        <p>The overall feeling of the installation is of blazing light and color, from Dove's ''Sun'' (1943), a pulsating, rhythmic composition in yellows, greens and blues, to Hockney's big, superchromatic highway abstraction ''Double Entrance'' (1993-95). The color intensity gives greater effect to the few monochrome entries, like Mark Tansey's ''Interception'' (1996), an eerie interpretation of an ancient Greek legend.</p>
        <p>Surprises and discoveries include the work of William H. Johnson (1901-1970), an African-American painter, whose ''Harbor Under the Midnight Sun'' (1937), a highly Expressionistic Norwegian landscape, blazes with vitality; O'Keeffe's ''Only One'' (1959), an absolutely gorgeous aerial view of a river in purplish blue and earth tones that ranks with her very best; and Roszak's ''Recording Sound'' (1932), an ingeniously structured mix of painting and sculpture in which a miniature scene from an opera, carved in relief, is shown as the opera is being recorded by an intricate, very mechanistic phonograph.</p>
        <p>The show is installed more or less chronologically, starting in the National Academy's handsomely renovated F. Donald Kenney Gallery, a 19th-century space whose polished walnut walls form an enriching backdrop.</p>
        <p>The work here includes ''Yliaster (Paracelsus),'' an intense 1932 composition by Hartley done mainly in golden brown and blue. It melds Mayan, Aztec and Roman Catholic imagery to symbolize the moment of creation, occurring when a shaft of fire links the sun with an earthly volcano.</p>
        <p>There is also, believe it or not, a brightly colored untitled abstraction by Ad Reinhardt from 1940, in which the artist, later noted for his dark, close-valued monotones, piles on chromatics in a dynamic reinterpretation of Mondrian's grid, putting down horizontals and verticals that seem to go every which way.</p>
        <p>And in ''Composition'' (1943), a colorful mechano-morphic figure using geometric elements outlined in black, Lee Krasner can be seen as a well-versed early translator of French modern movements into an American idiom.</p>
        <p>Another standout in this section is Stuart Davis's smart, zippy ''Memo'' (1956), a brilliant orchestration of linear elements, letters and geometric shapes that plays off black and white against green and red in sophisticated spatial relationships.</p>
        <p>Abstract Expressionism is a presence in a later section of the show, with works by first and second-generation painters of the movement -- but, alas, no Jackson Pollock. Only two canvases are from the early period, de Kooning's ''Wave'' (1942-44), a tenderly worked painting that seems to combine an abstract landscape with the figure of a woman, and Still's ''1946-H (Indian Red and Black),'' a spacious abstract landscape of rough jagged forms in white, brown and black on a vast field of earthy red-brown.</p>
        <p>Motherwell is best represented by a huge canvas from 1959, ''Monster (For Charles Ives),'' an actual monster shape in earthy browns, a vision inspired by Ives's experimental music. Baziotes, a wonderfully subtle painter of unearthly creatures and ruminations, shines with ''Scepter'' (1960-61), a canvas in underwater green that seems to incorporate a fish and an intricate scepter suggesting a sea horse.</p>
        <p>The hearty, earthy paint handling of Hofmann dominates his ''Fermented Soil'' (1965), a chaotic but fertile-looking mud scape evoked by dragging, pushing, pulling and laying on paint in warm tones of red, ocher and yellow. The late musings of Philip Guston, perhaps the most tentative of the founding Abstract Expressionists, are represented by a wonderful painting, ''Transition'' (1975), made after he renounced abstraction for a deliberately clownish figuration. Mainly in blood reds and pinks, this poignant evocation contains suggestions of the Holocaust, the artist's calling, the passage of time and his earthly end.</p>
        <p>The pre-Pop era gets a nod with Rauschenberg's ''Reservoir'' (1961), one of his famous and influential ''combine'' paintings in which the materials of art flow around solid artifacts from life; clock faces, wheels, a wooden platform are stuck on or into the canvas.</p>
        <p>A scattershot of later works by William Christenberry, Jennifer Bartlett, Eric Fischl, Pat Steir and Mark Tansey enhance the show, by and large, but don't really give much idea of the current scene.</p>
        <p>Viewed as a serendipitous windfall, ''Modernism and Abstraction'' offers plenty of reasons for a visit.</p>
        <p>''Modernism and Abstraction: Treasures From the Smithsonian American Art Museum'' is at the National Academy of Design Museum, 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 369-4880, through April 7.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
