<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Confession in 1994 Case Evokes Pearl Abduction</title>
    <meta content="Y08OMAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/08/international/asia/08OMAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1366023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: A SUSPECT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dugger, Celia W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheikh, Ahmed Omar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pearl, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Partridge, Rhys</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India/New Delhi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buddhism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buddhism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Delhi (India)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Wall Street Journal</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E3DB143CF93BA35751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Confession in 1994 Case Evokes Pearl Abduction</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Confession in 1994 Case Evokes Pearl Abduction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELIA W. DUGGER with FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dugger, Celia W; Barringer, Felicity</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Feb. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pakistani and American officials say Ahmed Omar Sheikh, Islamic fundamentalist, is chief suspect in abduction of American journalist Daniel Pearl; cite 45-page account of kidnapping plan that Sheikh wrote 7 years ago after being jailed for kidnapping of three Britons and an American; that plan bears striking resemblances to Pearl's kidnapping; Rhys Partridge, one of Britons held captive by Sheikh, says he displayed mixture of intelligence, irrationality and intensity that led him, Partridge, to become convinced that Sheikh was psychopath (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 45-page account, written out in small, tight longhand seven years ago, could be called the confessions of a 20-year-old kidnapper. In it, a gregarious protagonist lays out a plan  that bears striking resemblances to the kidnapping of Daniel Pearl, a Wall Street Journal reporter, 15 days ago in Karachi, Pakistan.</p>
        <p>So it is perhaps not surprising that Pakistani and American officials on  Wednesday declared the author of that account, Ahmed Omar Sheikh, an Islamic fundamentalist who works with the craftiness of a predator, tailoring his lies to suit his victims' desires, as the chief suspect in Mr. Pearl's abduction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1994, Ahmed Omar Sheikh, the chief suspect in the kidnapping of journalist Daniel Pearl, authored an account that bears striking resemblances to Mr. Pearl's abduction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 45-page account, written out in small, tight longhand seven years ago, could be called the confessions of a 20-year-old kidnapper. In it, a gregarious protagonist lays out a plan  that bears striking resemblances to the kidnapping of Daniel Pearl, a Wall Street Journal reporter, 15 days ago in Karachi, Pakistan.</p>
        <p>So it is perhaps not surprising that Pakistani and American officials on  Wednesday declared the author of that account, Ahmed Omar Sheikh, an Islamic fundamentalist who works with the craftiness of a predator, tailoring his lies to suit his victims' desires, as the chief suspect in Mr. Pearl's abduction.</p>
        <p>In 1994, Mr. Sheikh, a British national of Pakistani descent who had dropped out of the London School of Economics, wrote that he had enticed three Britons and an American into a trap here with a fabulous tale. He said an Indian uncle had died and left him an entire village, then invited the men to climb into a van for a ride home to meet his relatives.</p>
        <p>''It seems amazing that the story was greeted with such credible enthusiasm,'' he wrote later from jail after his victims were rescued by the police, ''but the newly arrived traveler to India yearns to hear extraordinary stories which will increase his insight into this strange and colorful culture.''</p>
        <p>In Mr. Pearl's case, the kidnappers also lured him with something he wanted: a great story.</p>
        <p>There are other similarities. In both kidnappings, the victims were shackled at the ankle, and photographs of the victims were taken with a daily newspaper in the frame to fix the date. In both, ensnaring an American seems to have been the priority.</p>
        <p>The demands were also similar. The 1994 kidnappers wanted the freedom of Islamic militants jailed in India; Mr. Pearl's kidnappers are seeking the release of Pakistani prisoners from the Afghan war.</p>
        <p>While it remains to be seen whether Mr. Sheikh is involved in the kidnapping of Mr. Pearl, his account of the 1994 case, first reported by The Indian Express, and a confidential report on his interrogation, provided to The New York Times by an Indian official, offer a glimpse into his thoughts.</p>
        <p>One of his lawyers here, who refused to be named, confirmed that his client had written the account, though he said he maintained in court that it was done under duress. The document is now part of the court record of the 1994 case, which still drags on unresolved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheikh's path to fundamentalism began with a trip to the movies. In 1992, during ''Bosnia Week,'' he saw a documentary about the persecution of Bosnia's Muslims by the Serbs. It made a deep impression. He began attending rallies and lectures -- and went to Bosnia in 1993.</p>
        <p>There, he met Pakistanis who gave him a letter of introduction to militant circles in Pakistan and a training camp in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>In Pakistan, he signed on with Harkat-ul-Ansar, which was fighting Indian rule of Kashmir, and was recruited to lure Westerners in India to a safe house where they could be captured and traded for compatriots in Indian jails.</p>
        <p>He arrived in New Delhi in July 1994 and began haunting spots where he thought he might find young Westerners. He managed to scare off one American who suddenly got out of the van before they arrived at the safe house.</p>
        <p>But he did entice another -- Bela Nuss, a 43-year-old school teacher from San Francisco. ''I was eating at an outdoor restaurant,'' said Mr. Nuss, who was the last person captured and the first freed. ''I was alone at the table and he sat down and just started talking.'' Mr. Sheikh, whom Mr. Russ knew as Rohit, ''was very friendly. He asked lots of questions.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Nuss said he had never been invited into an Indian home, Mr. Sheikh immediately proffered a dinner invitation. En route, his confederates got in the car and pulled a gun on Mr. Nuss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheikh occasionally had twinges of conscience, never more so than with Rhys Partridge, a Briton with a bent for Buddhism, chess and travel. The kidnapper recalled in his  account that he had trembled as he explained ''the facts of life'' to his quarry, Mr. Partridge, with whom he also formed ''the strongest friendship I had made for a long time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Partridge said in telephone interviews this week: ''I was his first real captive. He gloated over me and  he opened up to me as well.'' The two men played long games of chess and talked about England.</p>
        <p>But when it came to religion and politics, Mr. Sheikh's analytic approach was replaced by simple slogans, Mr. Partridge said. ''He ranted about the atrocities that had taken place in Bosnia,'' and lapsed into anti-Semitic tirades and talked at length about Hitler. That mixture of intelligence, irrationality and intensity left Mr. Partridge convinced he was dealing with a psychopath.</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: A SUSPECT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
