<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Again, Mayhem at a Crowded Outdoor Market</title>
    <meta content="Y13BOM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/13/international/middleeast/13BOMB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1383583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="MIDEAST TURMOIL: THE SCENE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkley, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5D8153CF930A25757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Again, Mayhem at a Crowded Outdoor Market</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Again, Mayhem at a Crowded Outdoor Market</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL BRINKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brinkley, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Description of mayhem at Mahane Yehuda open-air market in Jerusalem, where suicide bomber strikes; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Body parts were mingled with shattered watermelons, bell peppers, apples and tangerines in the street today after a suicide bomber struck a crowded outdoor food market just as dozens of people were rushing to complete their shopping before the Sabbath fell.</p>
        <p>Ehud Olmert, the mayor of Jerusalem, was one of those in the crowd of shoppers today not long before the bomber struck the Mahane Yehuda open-air market, which has been the site of several recent bombs and many other attacks over the years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Body parts were mingled with shattered watermelons in the street on Friday after a suicide bomber struck a crowded outdoor food market in Jerusalem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Body parts were mingled with shattered watermelons, bell peppers, apples and tangerines in the street today after a suicide bomber struck a crowded outdoor food market just as dozens of people were rushing to complete their shopping before the Sabbath fell.</p>
        <p>Ehud Olmert, the mayor of Jerusalem, was one of those in the crowd of shoppers today not long before the bomber struck the Mahane Yehuda open-air market, which has been the site of several recent bombs and many other attacks over the years.</p>
        <p>He told Israeli state radio, ''I was wondering how to bring Colin Powell here to see that it is not fighters crushed by the bombs, but civilians, women and children.''</p>
        <p>Late on Friday afternoons, poor and elderly shoppers often visit the market, hoping for reduced prices on bread and vegetables just before the market closes until Sunday.</p>
        <p>The police said today that the bomber approached the market but turned away when she saw police officers guarding the entrance. She walked to a bus stop a few feet away and detonated her charge just as a bus pulled up.</p>
        <p>The windshield of the bus was blown off, though the driver, an Israeli Arab, was miraculously unharmed. A string of small Israeli flags hanging over the entrance to the market was left tattered.</p>
        <p>The bomb was obviously directional because shop windows across the street were shattered, and destruction rained on storefronts down a long block in front of the bomber. But 20 feet behind where she detonated her charge, pallets of eggs sat undisturbed on a market-stall counter.</p>
        <p>''Someone willing to send somebody to kill other people in this way is not a human being,'' said Yoshua Isler, a 37-year-old student whose hands were bandaged from burns.</p>
        <p>He added, ''If Arafat is willing to send these people, we must do at least the same to him.''</p>
        <p>Rachamin Cohen, 39, works at a vegetable stall just inside the market, but had finished work and was buying challah at a bakery when the bomb exploded, knocking him over. Part of a wall fell on him, and ''when I looked up, the first thing I saw was a friend without his arm,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He was taken to Bikur Holim Hospital a few blocks away, along with 37 other wounded.</p>
        <p>Shoshana Levy, 40, lying in an adjacent bed, said she was struck by the loud boom, the smoke, ''and the terrible smell -- of fire and of human flesh.''</p>
        <p>She said she had been a bit scared to shop in the market, ''but we are always living in fear now.''</p>
        <p>''You have to go on with your life,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The police reported that among the wounded were two Asian workers, women who are among the thousands brought to Israel to take the places of Palestinians who held the jobs before the uprising began.</p>
        <p>Both women lost both their legs, and one lost an arm as well, Israel Television reported.</p>
        <p>Police Chief Mickey Levy said the bomb was large and powerful and packed with shrapnel; the explosion could be heard loudly across the city. He added that he knew the bomber was a young woman because he saw her face, though her head ''was blown off.''</p>
        <p>As the rescue workers and others finished retrieving bodies and parts, six city workers, all of them Palestinians from East Jerusalem, quickly swept up shattered vegetables and other debris. Then they stood back leaning on their brooms, watching as rescue workers struggled to pull a man's dismembered corpse into a black plastic body bag.</p>
        <p>A white card with the number eight was taped to the outside. Asked how, as Palestinians, they felt being here this evening, they would not answer. One simply pursed his lips and shook his head.</p>
        <p>Vered Maman, 17, had been shopping when the blast blew her off her feet and back about 10 feet. Ms. Maman was recovering only from shock, compounded by the fact that today's bombing was the fifth that had caught her.</p>
        <p>Her family lives in central Jerusalem, near Jaffa Road and King George Street, where the largest number of bombings have occurred in recent months. One of them, in December, left her brother a quadriplegic who must use a respirator to breathe. But Ms. Maman has escaped all of them with nothing more than scratches. ''Near misses every time,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Asked if she felt fortunate, or unlucky, she thought for a minute and said: ''Lucky. I think God loves me.''</p>
        <p>MIDEAST TURMOIL: THE SCENE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
