<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Digest</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="837596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEEDE1739F93BA25750C0A960958260" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Digest</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>Budget Stalemate Hits Schools</p>
        <p>The budget stalemate in Washington is rippling through all levels of government -- from the corridors of state capitols to cities to classrooms.  The impasse is hitting school districts particularly hard because they now have to put together budgets for the next academic year without knowing exactly how much Federal and state aid they will receive. The looming school crises have also been compounded by stopgap measures, which were adopted by the Congress to  keep the Government running, that have reduced aid to school districts. In New York alone, these cuts have amounted to more than $300 million. [Page B1.]</p>
        <p>Getting Phones to Immigrants</p>
        <p>The percentage of houses without phones is higher in New York than in any other metropolitan area in the country. Tens of thousands of New Yorkers, most of them recent immigrants, go for long periods without a home phone. Many of these people flock to a growing number of phone parlors, storefront businesses that let customers call overseas from private booths. But now a tiny midtown telephone company that operates more than 150 phone parlors has begun installing phone lines in the homes of customers who have lost Nynex service or cannot get  it. [B1.]</p>
        <p>Officer Kills Himself at Concert</p>
        <p>An off-duty police officer committed suicide during a St. Patrick's Day concert in a mid-Manhattan theater, shooting himself once in the head as a local Irish rock band was playing an encore, the police said. Two women behind him in the theater's crowded balcony were hit by the bullet. [B3.]</p>
        <p>Injuries in Gay Bias Cases Drop</p>
        <p>Fewer homosexuals were injured in bias-related assaults in New York City last year than in 1994, according to a privately compiled report, but the overall number of incidents remained roughly the same. [B2.]</p>
        <p>Exhibitions to Honor The Times</p>
        <p>Four of New York's most prominent cultural institutions will join together to produce a series of exhibitions in June to commemorate the 100th anniversary of  the publisher Adolph S. Ochs's purchase of The New York Times. The unusual collaboration involves the New York Public Library, the Museum of Modern Art, the American Museum of Natural History and the Pierpont Morgan Library. The Arts. [C11.]</p>
        <p>REGION</p>
        <p>Mud Endangers Port Commerce</p>
        <p>Thousands of tons of riverborne silt sift into New York Harbor's shipping channels each day. But mud that was once considered just a nuisance was found to fail new standards covering contaminants and toxicity. As a result, less and less of the mud is being cleared from channels and berths. The harbor is choking in mud as port officials remain locked in debate with beachfront communities, fishermen and some environmental groups who oppose any further disposal of tainted silt in the ocean. [A1.]</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>A Writer on Every Block</p>
        <p>There is a saying heard around Princeton, N.J., that there's a real estate agent and a writer on every block. Writers have never been in short supply in Princeton, but these days they may be getting the upper hand. The area has become host to a dense concentration of novelists, poets, biographers, critics,  historians and others -- clusters of writers that occasionally resemble a kind of literary commune. [B1.]</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>An Era Falls With a Building</p>
        <p>Hundreds of people gathered in Bridgeport to watch a blast that destroyed a 73-year-old power plant that had once provided the electricity for more than a dozen factories. But the factories have long since closed, and in three seconds, the United Illuminating Company's 16-story Steel Point Generating Station collapsed with a muffled boom, disappearing in a black cloud of dust.  The land  has already become the source of dreams for Bridgeport's future. [B1.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
