<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Equity and Convertible Debt Offerings Scheduled for This Week</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="837523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5DE1739F93BA25750C0A960958260" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Equity and Convertible Debt Offerings Scheduled for This Week</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>ABR Information Services Inc., Palm Harbor, Fla., 3.1 million shares. Montgomery Securities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>ABR Information Services Inc., Palm Harbor, Fla., 3.1 million shares. Montgomery Securities.</p>
        <p>Advanced Tissue Sciences Inc., La Jolla, Calif., 3 million shares. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Ambac Inc., 3.8 million of preferred redeemable increased dividend securities due in 2001. Merrill Lynch &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Analogy Inc., Beaverton, Ore., an initial public offering of 2.5 million shares. Needham &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Biofield Corp., Roswell, Ga., an initial public offering of 1.8 million shares. Hambrecht &amp; Quist.</p>
        <p>Centennial Technologies Inc., Billerica, Mass., 1.35 million shares. Needham.</p>
        <p>Century Aluminum Co., Ravenswood, W. Va., an initial public offering of $488.75 million. The share size has not yet determined. Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>Cimatron Ltd., Givat Shmuel, Israel, an initial public offering of 1.85 million shares, including 1.7 million in the United States and Canada. Oppenheimer &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Cineplex Odeon Corp., Toronto, 45 million shares. CIBC Wood Gundy.</p>
        <p>Dawson Production Services Inc., San Antonio, an initial public offering of 2.275 million shares. Jefferies &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Eagle River Interactive Inc., Avon, Colo., an initial public offering of 3.65 million shares. Salomon Brothers.</p>
        <p>Elamex, S.A. De C.V., Chihuahua, Mexico, an initial public offering of 3.15 million shares. Goldman, Sachs.</p>
        <p>First USA Paymentech Inc., Dallas, an initial public offering of 5.1 million  shares. Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>Global Directmail Corp., Port Washington, L.I., 4 million shares, including 3.2 million in the United States and Canada. Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette.</p>
        <p>Guilford Pharmaceuticals Inc., Baltimore, 2 million shares. Oppenheimer.</p>
        <p>Intelligent Medical Imaging Inc., Palm Beach Gardens, Fla., an initial public offering of 3 million shares. Smith Barney Inc.</p>
        <p>Intelliquest Information Group Inc., Austin, Tex., an initial public offering of 1.925 million shares. William Blair &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Logal Educational Software and Systems Ltd., Kiryat Shmona, Israel, an initial public offering of 1.9 million ordinary shares. Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>Microware Systems Corp., Des Moines, an initial public offering of 2.5 million shares. Alex. Brown &amp; Sons.</p>
        <p>Nicollet Process Engineering Inc., Minneapolis, an initial public offering of 1.2 million shares. R. J. Steichen &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Omnicare Inc., Arlington, Va., 5 million shares, including 4 million in the United States and Canada. CS First Boston.</p>
        <p>Onyx Acceptance Corp., Irvine, Calif., an initial public offering of 2.5 million shares. Prudential Securities Inc.</p>
        <p>Panamerican Beverages Inc., Mexico City, 6 million of class A shares, including 4.8 million in the United States and Canada. Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Pioneer Financial Services Inc., Schaumburg, Ill., $65 million of convertible subordinated notes due in 2003. Bear, Stearns &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Praxair Inc., Danbury, Conn., 11 million shares, including 8 million in the United States and Canada.</p>
        <p>Qualmark Corp., Denver, an initial public offering of 1.35 million shares. Summit Investment Corp.</p>
        <p>Semiconductor Laser International, Vestal, N.Y., an initial public offering of 1.6 million shares and 1.6 million warrants. Whale Securities Co.</p>
        <p>Smartserv Online Inc., Stamford, Conn., an initial public offering of 1.5 million shares and 1.5 million warrants. Rickel &amp; Associates Inc.</p>
        <p>Thermoquest Corp., San Jose, Calif., an initial public offering of 3 million  shares. Natwest Securities.</p>
        <p>Vyrex Corp., La Jolla, Calif., an initial public offering of 1 million units, each unit represents one common share and one warrant. First Equity Corp. of Florida.</p>
        <p>Workgroup Technology Corp., Lexington, Mass., an initial public offering of 3.5 million shares. Alex. Brown.</p>
        <p>Xeikon N.V., Mortsel, Belgium, an initial public offering of 6.4 million American depository shares, each representing one share, including 4.48 million  in the United States and Canada. Alex. Brown.</p>
        <p>Source: MCM Corporatewatch.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
