<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils Lose Another To Their Florida Twin</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="837605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FLORIDA PANTHERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY DEVILS FLORIDA PANTHERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEYDEVILS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOBLES, CHARLIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Florida Panthers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E7DD1739F93BA25750C0A960958260" item-length="762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils Lose Another To Their Florida Twin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NOBLES, CHARLIE</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, March 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Martin Brodeur has scrutinized the Florida Panthers this season, it has  been a little like looking in the mirror. As with the Devils, Florida is a strong defensive team with solid goaltending.</p>
        <p>And that has added up to bad news for New Jersey, which lost tonight for the  fifth time in six games to the Panthers, 3-0, before 14,703 at Miami Arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Martin Brodeur has scrutinized the Florida Panthers this season, it has  been a little like looking in the mirror. As with the Devils, Florida is a strong defensive team with solid goaltending.</p>
        <p>And that has added up to bad news for New Jersey, which lost tonight for the  fifth time in six games to the Panthers, 3-0, before 14,703 at Miami Arena.</p>
        <p>Every time we play a team like us, we seem to run into a little trouble," the goaltender said, head down as he stood in a solemn visitors locker room.</p>
        <p>Trouble on this night came in the form of the former Rangers goalie John Vanbiesbrouck, who fashioned his second shutout of the season with 33 saves. And Florida's fresh injection of offensive talent -- right wing Ray Sheppard, acquired Saturday from San Jose, and the high-priced center Martin Straka, scooped up Friday off waivers from the Islanders -- caused the Devils some trouble, too.</p>
        <p>Sheppard assisted on Florida's first goal, while Straka scored the second goal and assisted on the third.</p>
        <p>"We picked up a couple of real strong players who made an immediate impact,"  Vanbiesbrouck said. "I think it's perfect timing by our management."</p>
        <p>Straka, who was Pittsburgh's first-round pick in 1992, has been with Ottawa and the Islanders this season. "I was so nervous before the game," he said, "because this is my fourth team and I want things to work out."</p>
        <p>They did.</p>
        <p>"I think the key for them is that Vanbiesbrouck has played unbeatably against us," Devils defenseman Ken Daneyko said. "Before, we haven't gotten too many scoring chances against him. Tonight we did, and he stopped them all."</p>
        <p>So much for momentum, or the lack of it: New Jersey hadn't lost in 10 games and Florida had won just once in its last 10. This was Florida's first victory in March, New Jersey's first defeat. But it made the Devils' sprint for the Eastern Conference playoffs a little more precarious. With 75 points, the Devils are only 3 points ahead of ninth-place Boston.</p>
        <p>Devils Coach Jacques Lemaire said he could identify just five of his players  for praise in tonight's game -- center Steve Sullivan, left wings Dave Andreychuk and Bobby Holik, right wing Randy McKay and Kevin Dean, for his defensive play.</p>
        <p>"I don't know where the other guys were," he said. "Just a bad game. Lack of  preparation."</p>
        <p>The coach thought a moment, then added: "I saw two guys right away in the warmup. With the way they warmed up, there was no way in the world they were going to play a good game."</p>
        <p>The Devils captain Scott Stevens said he detected no lack of effort. "I thought we had pretty good jump," he said. "This is a game we wanted, after the  way they've handled us this year. I don't know how you tell anything from a warmup, anyway."</p>
        <p>Florida's margin of victory could easily have been greater if not for a handful of stellar saves by Brodeur, who was replaced with 11 minutes 46 seconds left in the game after yielding a goal to left wing Bill Lindsay. In an oddity,  Vanbiesbrouck received the assist. A slap shot by Devils left wing Steve Thomas  had bounded almost halfway up the ice off Vanbiesbrouck. Straka then drove with  the puck until he found Lindsay swooping in from the left side.</p>
        <p>Florida opened the scoring 8:30 into the game, after a Sheppard steal near New Jersey's net. Sheppard flicked a pass to left wing Johan Garpenlov, who beat a diving Brodeur in the net's left corner.</p>
        <p>Next, Florida used Straka's individual brilliance to build a 2-0 cushion. Racing past the blue line with the puck, Straka faked left and then cut right, leaving defenseman Scott Niedermayer as flat-footed as if his skates were frozen in the ice. That put Straka in the open, and he beat Brodeur with another left-right fake.</p>
        <p>The closest New Jersey came to scoring was when Sullivan's first-period breakaway was blunted by Vanbiesbrouck.</p>
        <p>Now the Devils are left to regroup for a Wednesday home game against Boston.  "We have no choice but to be ready for that one," Brodeur said.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
