<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The City Budget: Still Gimmicky</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="613295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DD1031F936A35755C0A965958260" item-length="489" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The City Budget: Still Gimmicky</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a bow to reality, Mayor David Dinkins and his advisers have revised the New York City budget. They've deleted the worst examples of undue optimism and agreed to make deeper spending cuts. That's progress. But in what might be the administration's theme song, the revision doesn't go far enough. Like the first version, it relies too heavily on money that isn't likely to materialize, and on gimmicks that will raise money in the short run but cause pain down the road.</p>
        <p>The Mayor's budget for the fiscal year that begins July 1 now anticipates $150 million in Federal aid instead of $250 million, though even the $150 million is not guaranteed; $55 million from the sale of the Offtrack Betting Corporation, though no sale has been arranged, and $215 million from borrowing against property tax delinquencies, which robs the future to collect cash now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a bow to reality, Mayor David Dinkins and his advisers have revised the New York City budget. They've deleted the worst examples of undue optimism and agreed to make deeper spending cuts. That's progress. But in what might be the administration's theme song, the revision doesn't go far enough. Like the first version, it relies too heavily on money that isn't likely to materialize, and on gimmicks that will raise money in the short run but cause pain down the road.</p>
        <p>The Mayor's budget for the fiscal year that begins July 1 now anticipates $150 million in Federal aid instead of $250 million, though even the $150 million is not guaranteed; $55 million from the sale of the Offtrack Betting Corporation, though no sale has been arranged, and $215 million from borrowing against property tax delinquencies, which robs the future to collect cash now.</p>
        <p>Even with the new cuts of about $300 million and a partial hiring freeze, experts say the budget gap could range from $400 million to $700 million. Presumably the Mayor and the City Council -- both up for re-election in the fall -- will balance the budget after the elections, assuming it's still out of whack. By law, the budget must be in balance. But closing gaps on short notice forces the use of even more gimmicks as well as the imposition of hurtful cuts driven by panic.</p>
        <p>How did City Hall get itself into this fix in an election year? The economy didn't cooperate. Albany, particularly Gov. Mario Cuomo, didn't cooperate by providing more funds. Even worse, he suggested foolhardy ideas, like a fire sale of the land under the airports. Circumstances didn't cooperate -- storms and the World Trade Center bombing boosted overtime costs.</p>
        <p>The city didn't get the help it expected from a Democratic Administration in Washington. Most important, Mayor Dinkins did not take advantage of bad times and impose the structural changes the city must make if it is ever to live within its means. The only escape from the perennial crunch is to embrace difficult policy changes, from property tax reform to productivity savings from workers and even greater cuts in the labor force.</p>
        <p>The administration has reduced the work force from a high of 225,000 to about 212,000, and made some management reforms. But it hasn't done nearly enough, and it hasn't won significant concessions from the unions. A state takeover of Medicaid would provide significant help, but State Senate Republicans balked and the Governor didn't work hard enough to move them.</p>
        <p>Now, unfortunately, is not the time to make those reforms. Last-minute budget haggling cannot solve the city's fundamental budget imbalance -- the "permanent deficit" recently spotlighted by private members of the Financial Control Board. But it is not too late to make more service and staff cuts. Delaying tough decisions until the fall may be smart campaign politics, but it will not get the city anywhere.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
