<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton, in Solemn Speech, Chides Racists of All Colors</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="799086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARCH ON WASHINGTON: THE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTI-SEMITISM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATION OF ISLAM</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARRAKHAN, LOUIS H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURDUM, TODD S WILLIAMJEFFERSON 'BILL' CLINTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFD91039F934A25753C1A963958260" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton, in Solemn Speech, Chides Racists of All Colors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PURDUM, TODD S WILLIAMJEFFERSON 'BILL' CLINTON;</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., Oct. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Halfway across the country from the mass demonstration outside his own back door, President Clinton today sternly challenged white and black Americans to take responsibility for their attitudes and actions, reject discord and at last  "clean our house of racism."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton used a long-scheduled lecture at the University of Texas campus here to reflect on the state of race relations in the aftermath of O. J. Simpson's acquittal on murder charges, and the result was one of the most sweeping speeches of his Presidency. While he repeatedly summoned up solemn images of national unity, his indictment of the particulars of division spared neither side.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Halfway across the country from the mass demonstration outside his own back door, President Clinton today sternly challenged white and black Americans to take responsibility for their attitudes and actions, reject discord and at last  "clean our house of racism."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton used a long-scheduled lecture at the University of Texas campus here to reflect on the state of race relations in the aftermath of O. J. Simpson's acquittal on murder charges, and the result was one of the most sweeping speeches of his Presidency. While he repeatedly summoned up solemn images of national unity, his indictment of the particulars of division spared neither side.</p>
        <p>White racism may be black people's burden, but it's white people's problem," Mr. Clinton told a largely white audience. "We must clean our house."</p>
        <p>To black Americans, the President made the same demand, although in the subtler tone of the passive voice.</p>
        <p>"Your house, too, must be cleaned of racism," Mr. Clinton said. "There are too many today, white and black, on the left and the right, on the street corners and the radio waves, who seek to sow division for their own purposes. To them I say: No more. We must be one."</p>
        <p>His voice sober and often raspy after staying up most of the night rewriting  the speech with aides, the President said: "Recognizing one another's real grievances is only the first step. We must all take responsibility for ourselves, our conduct and our attitudes. America, we must clean our house of racism.</p>
        <p>"Long before we were so diverse," he said, "our nation's motto was 'e pluribus unum' -- out of many, we are one." Now, he said, "Whether we like it or not, we are one nation, one family, indivisible, and for us, divorce or separation are not options."</p>
        <p>Without mentioning either by name, Mr. Clinton made Louis Farrakhan and Mark  Fuhrman, the former Los Angeles police detective, into metaphors for the shortcomings of blacks and whites alike, challenging listeners to bridge the gulf of mistrust that persists a century and a half after Lincoln warned that "a house divided against itself cannot stand."</p>
        <p>Speaking of the march in Washington, Mr. Clinton said, "One million men are right to be standing up for personal responsibility." But he said, in an unmistakable reference to Mr. Farrakhan, "One million men do not make right one  man's message of malice and division."</p>
        <p>Referring to Mr. Fuhrman, the detective in the Simpson case, the President said, "The taped voice of one policeman should fill you with outrage." He urged whites to be heard "so loudly and clearly denouncing it that our black fellow citizens can hear us" and to "root out the remnants of racism" in the criminal justice system.</p>
        <p>In a speech of nearly 40 minutes, Mr. Clinton repeatedly found fault with both black and white attitudes. He chided whites who see blacks as "some sort of protected class" benefiting from advantages in employment and hiring, noting that "African-Americans still make on average about 60 percent of what white people do."</p>
        <p>"On the other hand," he said, "blacks must understand and acknowledge the roots of white fear in America." He added that "it isn't racist for a parent to  pull his or her child close when walking through a high-crime neighborhood" or "for whites to assert that the culture of welfare dependency, out-of-wedlock pregnancy and absent fatherhood cannot be broken by social programs unless there is first more personal responsibility."</p>
        <p>Indeed, the President said, while Government has a role to play, "the people  marching in Washington today are right about one fundamental thing: at its base, this issue of race is not about Government or political leaders, it is about what is in the heart and the minds and the life of the American people."</p>
        <p>He urged his audience to "seek out someone of a different racial or ethnic group and engage in the kind of conversations people think they have but don't really, in which people can be frank and brutally honest about what they honestly feel, but in which they have the discipline to listen and open their ears and their minds and their hearts and hear others."</p>
        <p>After the Simpson verdict, Mr. Clinton spoke of his unease at the apparent depth of the divisions that had been exposed by Mr. Simpson's acquittal, but he  and his aides debated for days the risks and merits of speaking out in greater detail, especially in light of today's march.</p>
        <p>One concern was that the President would be hard-pressed to offer many specific policy prescriptions that would satisfy either side. In the end, senior aides said, Mr. Clinton felt compelled to reflect more philosophically on a topic that has touched his life and career since his youth in the segregated South.</p>
        <p>In recent days, he and his speech writers went through draft after draft, with the President rewriting extensive passages in a blue felt-tip pen. The White House spokesman, Michael D. McCurry, said the President had been at work in his suite until about 3:30 A.M. today and had been up again at 7 to polish the final draft.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the President's tone this morning was more fatherly than fiery, as he recalled that his own father had died just before he was born and that his stepfather's alcoholism had made for perpetual turmoil at home. He warned that "the single biggest social problem in our society may be the growing absence of  fathers from their children's homes."</p>
        <p>"Building a family is the hardest job a man can do," Mr. Clinton said. "But it's also the most important."</p>
        <p>THE MARCH ON WASHINGTON: THE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
