<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Everything Goes The Patriots' Way</title>
    <meta content="12NFL.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1053621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="N.F.L.: WEEK 6 -- YESTERDAY'S GAMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Patriots</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas City Chiefs</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Buffalo Bills</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indianapolis Colts</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tennessee Oilers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Ravens</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Denver Broncos</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Seahawks</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Cowboys</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida Panthers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Eagles</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Redskins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Baltimore Ravens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Buffalo Bills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Dallas Cowboys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Denver Broncos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Indianapolis Colts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Kansas City Chiefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Philadelphia Eagles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Seattle Seahawks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Florida Panthers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DC163AF931A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="2302" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Everything Goes The Patriots' Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>FOXBORO, Mass., Oct. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New England Patriots defeat Kansas City Chiefs, 40-10; Buffalo Bills defeat Indianapolis Colts, 31-24; Tennessee Oilers defeat Baltimore Ravens, 12-8; Denver Broncos defeat Seattle Seahawks, 21-16; Dallas Cowboys defeat Carolina Panthers, 27-20; Philadelphia Eagles defeat Washington Redskins, 17-12 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHIEFS 10  PATRIOTS 40</p>
        <p>Let's figure what went wrong for Kansas City and what went right for New England in a 40-10 Patriots rout here this afternoon. It was a victory that left 59,749 fans at Foxboro Stadium giddy over what this means in the long run for the home team.</p>
        <p>The Patriots scored first on a 1-yard touchdown run by the rookie running back Robert Edwards with 4 minutes 53 seconds left in the first quarter. Two Chiefs penalties contributed to the 40-yard drive. And then later in the quarter, Kansas City tried a fourth-and-1 run near midfield that lost a yard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHIEFS 10  PATRIOTS 40</p>
        <p>Let's figure what went wrong for Kansas City and what went right for New England in a 40-10 Patriots rout here this afternoon. It was a victory that left 59,749 fans at Foxboro Stadium giddy over what this means in the long run for the home team.</p>
        <p>The Patriots scored first on a 1-yard touchdown run by the rookie running back Robert Edwards with 4 minutes 53 seconds left in the first quarter. Two Chiefs penalties contributed to the 40-yard drive. And then later in the quarter, Kansas City tried a fourth-and-1 run near midfield that lost a yard.</p>
        <p>Those were things that went wrong for the Chiefs.</p>
        <p>Seldom have Coach Marty Schottenheimer's Chiefs been thrashed so thoroughly.</p>
        <p>A lot went wrong and we have to be held accountable for it, Schottenheimer said. I mean, we can't blame it on the stars.</p>
        <p>New England's Adam Vinatieri hit a 32-yard field goal in the second quarter and then appeared to have another one, from 37 yards. But Donnie Edwards was penalized for delay of game, for flinching and waving illegally before the kick, and New England received a first down at the Kansas City 15 instead of the field goal. And the Patriots took that second chance and scored on Drew Bledsoe's 15-yard touchdown pass to Robert Edwards to make it 17-0 with 9:11 left before halftime.</p>
        <p>Minutes later, the Chiefs roughed the punter and gave New England another chance. The Patriots scored another touchdown instead of ending their series with a punt, and it was 24-0 with 2:48 left before halftime. It was 27-0 at halftime.</p>
        <p>Those were some of the things that went right for New England.</p>
        <p>Kansas City scored its only touchdown with 52 seconds left in the third quarter. By then, New England had scored the game's first 37 points.</p>
        <p>Throughout the game, little went right for Kansas City and little went wrong for New England. The Chiefs played as if their bodies were here but their minds were back in Kansas City. A mental funk. The Patriots sensed their vulnerability and pounded them mercilessly.</p>
        <p>We played a lousy game in their house, linebacker Derrick Thomas said. There were a lot of problems, but we have a lot of people with pride. We'll get 'em back.</p>
        <p>Receiver Andre Rison said payback was not the issue, but improvement was. They did look good, he said. Any time this happens you have to realize where you are. We have 10 games left. The future is the focus.</p>
        <p>And what about the Patriots? What does their future hold? Are they so good that they can whip a good team like the Chiefs? Do they have that kind of killer instinct? Is Bledsoe (17 for 26 for 226 yards and 3 touchdowns) reaching a new level of expertise? Is Edwards (23 rushes for 104 yards; 3 receptions for 32 yards) rising to become the running back who was so good last year at Georgia?</p>
        <p>Are the Patriots Super Bowl material? A 40-10 victory over Kansas City makes people ask those kinds of questions. We are not in shock, Patriots safety Willie Clay said.</p>
        <p>The numbers were stunning. New England led in first downs, 31-9. In total yards, 438-134. In plays, 82-44. And there were 54 New England rushing plays. That makes for a long, long day for the Kansas City defense.</p>
        <p>New England dominated in rushing yards, 206-14. It dominated in possession time, 41:48 to 18:12.</p>
        <p>Stunning.</p>
        <p>We had a lot of things go right, Patriots Coach Pete Carroll said. When it happens like that, how can you go wrong?</p>
        <p>BILLS 31  COLTS 24</p>
        <p>Back in the N.F.L. after eight years in the Canadian Football League, Doug Flutie passed for two touchdowns and set up two short scoring runs by Antowain Smith in Buffalo's victory yesterday at Indianapolis.</p>
        <p>I wish I was 28 years old right now, which is where I was when I left this league, but I'm not, Flutie said. But I still have my athleticism, I can still run and throw, and quarterbacking is about making decisions. I'm getting a little smarter in my old age, and a lot more comfortable.</p>
        <p>Flutie, 35, who signed with Buffalo as a free agent last January, entered the game in the first quarter after Rob Johnson was sacked and left with sore ribs. X-rays showed a separation of his rib cartilage, and the Bills did not know how long Johnson would be out.</p>
        <p>It's a matter of people giving me the opportunity, said Flutie, who also played in Buffalo's last-second loss at San Diego, when Johnson sustained a concussion.</p>
        <p>Flutie was 23 for 28 for 213 yards with no sacks or interceptions.</p>
        <p>Doug was fantastic, Buffalo Coach Wade Phillips said. He hit every pass, it looked like. The ones he didn't were still on the money.</p>
        <p>Peyton Manning, the top pick in this year's draft, threw for 235 yards but was intercepted twice. He has thrown an N.F.L.-high 14 interceptions.</p>
        <p>OILERS 12  RAVENS 8</p>
        <p>Tennessee snapped a three-game losing streak, but the victory could be attributed to a shoddy effort by host Baltimore and the Oilers' ability to overcome their own mistakes.</p>
        <p>The Oilers were penalized 13 times for 141 yards and scored the game's lone touchdown on a broken play. Tennessee was 4 for 16 on third-down conversions and could muster only two field goals in the final 46 minutes.</p>
        <p>The bottom line is that we won, Oiler Coach Jeff Fisher said. I don't even want to think about the alternative, based on the way we played.</p>
        <p>The Ravens were worse, converting 1 of 15 third downs and mustering a team-low 36 yards on the ground. Even punting was an adventure: Harper LeBel sent five bad snaps to Kyle Richardson.</p>
        <p>Ravens running back Priest Holmes, who ran for 173 yards in his starting debut against Cincinnati two weeks earlier, gained 29 yards on 14 carries.</p>
        <p>Eddie George ran for 121 yards, and quarterback Steve McNair had a 40-yard touchdown run for the Oilers. But that was the extent of Tennessee's offense.</p>
        <p>BRONCOS 21  SEAHAWKS 16</p>
        <p>John Elway, sidelined for two weeks, has not lost his winning touch. Especially with Terrell Davis on his side.</p>
        <p>After turning over Denver's offense to Bubby Brister because of hamstring and back injuries, Elway returned to the lineup and threw two touchdown passes at Seattle.</p>
        <p>Elway got a lot of help from Davis, who became the Broncos' career leader in rushing touchdowns with 44 to give Denver a 21-10 lead on the third play of the fourth quarter with a 2-yard run.</p>
        <p>Davis, the N.F.L.'s leading rusher, had his third career 200-yard rushing game.</p>
        <p>He carried 30 times for 208 yards, while Elway passed for 185 yards and 2 touchdowns, with 2 interceptions.</p>
        <p>The Broncos beat the Seahawks for the fifth straight time and for the 10th time in 12 meetings. Seattle lost its third consecutive game.</p>
        <p>But Elway was not perfect, throwing an interception that Seattle turned into a touchdown.</p>
        <p>The Seahawks made it interesting in the final quarter after John Friesz replaced Warren Moon, who played with a cracked rib. Friesz passed 50 yards to Mike Pritchard for a touchdown with 10:34 left, and it was hang-on time for the Broncos.</p>
        <p>Denver linebacker Glenn Cadrez ended Seattle's last threat with 1:49 to go when he intercepted a pass by Friesz intended for Joey Galloway on a third-and-9 play at the Denver 27.</p>
        <p>Davis followed that with a 70-yard run to the Seattle 5 with 1:26 left. The Broncos then ran out the clock.</p>
        <p>The Seahawks took Moon out of the game and replaced him with Friesz after Denver took a 21-10 lead on Davis's 2-yard touchdown run with 1:04 gone in the second half.</p>
        <p>PANTHERS 20  COWBOYS 27</p>
        <p>Carolina quarterback Steve Beuerlein threw three touchdown passes, but host Dallas stopped him when Deion Sanders intercepted one of his passes with less than two minutes left.</p>
        <p>Jason Garrett, subbing for the injured Troy Aikman, threw two scoring passes, giving the Cowboys a 13-point cushion that enabled them to survive Garrett's fumble, which gave the Panthers a chance to win.</p>
        <p>The victory was not secured until Beuerlein threw a deep pass out of the end zone as time expired.</p>
        <p>Beuerlein, a former Cowboy who was making his first appearance of the season because Kerry Collins did not make the trip to Dallas with the team, threw for 286 yards. He completed his first 12 attempts.</p>
        <p>Sanders intercepted Beuerlein's pass with 1:55 to play, but Carolina got the ball back with 51 seconds left for a last-ditch drive to the Dallas 37, where Beuerlein let fly on a desperate heave that overshot his three receivers with the clock showing 0:00. (AP)</p>
        <p>Garrett said he could not watch.</p>
        <p>I was just shaking my head, Garrett said. I have immense respect and admiration for him. He's a true competitor.</p>
        <p>Beuerlein said he thought Carolina could pull off the upset.</p>
        <p>We showed a lot of heart, never quit, and were in it to the end, Beuerlein said.</p>
        <p>Aikman, who will be out until early November with a broken collarbone, lost to the Panthers by  23-13 last year and by 26-17 in the N.F.C. divisional playoffs two years ago in the only meetings between the teams.</p>
        <p>REDSKINS 12  EAGLES 17</p>
        <p>Philadelphia won the first matchup of 0-5 teams in N.F.C. East history as Rodney Peete ran for a touchdown and threw for another. Washington is off to its worst start in 37 years.</p>
        <p>It is a low moment, Washington's Brian Mitchell said. I hate losing. We were the best team out there; we just didn't win.</p>
        <p>A Philadelphia spectator known as Sign Man captured the essence and gravity of this game with a banner. May the worst team lose, it proclaimed.</p>
        <p>It is up for debate whether that happened.</p>
        <p>I wouldn't say it's a relief. It's about time, that's what it is, Eagles receiver Irving Fryar said.</p>
        <p>Trent Green had a miserable day, falling down at midfield on a drive that led to the Eagles' first touchdown. Quarterback Gus Frerotte, benched in the opening loss to the Giants, did not fare much better, although he did direct a late touchdown drive that made it a 5-point game with 2:46 left.</p>
        <p>Peete, who replaced Bobby Hoying as the Eagle starter this week, rushed for the Eagles' first touchdown and sealed the victory with a 3-yard touchdown pass to Kaseem Sinceno.</p>
        <p>49ERS 31  SAINTS 0</p>
        <p>The game Coach Mike Ditka of New Orleans called his obsession turned into his nightmare, quickly erasing thoughts of his club's fast start and showing that San Francisco is still the class of the National Conference West.</p>
        <p>They're the best football team I've seen in this league, Ditka said. I don't care who else there is, what their records are. Certainly, the best against me when I coach, I know that.</p>
        <p>Steve Young had his fifth straight 300-yard passing game and became the 20th player in N.F.L. history to throw for 30,000 yards.</p>
        <p>Chris Doleman's four sacks moved him into fifth place on the career list, and the 49ers won by their second-largest margin against the Saints.</p>
        <p>Records are great, but I think it's about performing and keeping steady throughout the year, Young said. We have a standard and we want to keep it.</p>
        <p>Young, who left after one series in the fourth quarter, completed 21 of 40 passes for 309 yards and 3 touchdowns. He is tied with Joe Montana for most consecutive 300-yard passing games.</p>
        <p>The Saints showed no signs of the scrappy play that helped them open with three straight victories and take New England to the wire last week.</p>
        <p>CHARGERS 6  RAIDERS 7</p>
        <p>After 58 minutes of offensive ineptitude by both teams, the third-string quarterback Wade Wilson gave host Oakland an unlikely victory over San Diego.</p>
        <p>After the Raiders went the entire second half without making a first down, Wilson threw a 68-yard scoring pass to a wide-open James Jett with 1:28 left.</p>
        <p>Wilson, who replaced Donald Hollas early in the fourth period, was 0 for 6 until completing the long pass to Jett.</p>
        <p>The game included 27 punts and 5 interceptions. Oakland's Leo Araguz had 16 punts, one short of the N.F.L. record.</p>
        <p>BEARS 7  CARDINALS 20</p>
        <p>Linebacker Ronald McKinnon had three interceptions and returned a blocked punt 31 yards, and Mario Bates scored two touchdowns for host Arizona.</p>
        <p>McKinnon, who also caused a fumble, had one interception in the first quarter, another at the end of the second and the last in the third.</p>
        <p>Then he topped himself in the fourth quarter when Chicago's Ricky Bell blocked a punt by Scott Player. McKinnon grabbed it out of the air, shook off a tackler at the sideline, and cut back to midfield to gain a Cardinal first down.</p>
        <p>He's out there throwing himself around, doing great things, and when players are doing that, it's a domino thing: everybody gets fired up,'' defensive end Simeon Rice said.</p>
        <p>McKinnon got his first carry as a Cardinal in the first quarter and scored on a pair of 2-yard runs in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>N.F.L.: WEEK 6 -- YESTERDAY'S GAMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
