<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Starts of Housing Surged 3% in February</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="837914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMMERCE DEPARTMENT US DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DA1739F933A15750C0A960958260" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Starts of Housing Surged 3% in February</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bloomberg Business News</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Builders started work on new homes last month at the highest rate in more than a year as they prepared for a rush of buyers eager to lock in mortgage rates before the rates move higher.</p>
        <p>All regions except the Midwest reported increased construction, the Commerce  Department said today. The increases pushed national housing starts 3 percent above the January level, to an annual rate of 1.49 million. The February rate is the highest since December 1994, when the rate was 1.51 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Builders started work on new homes last month at the highest rate in more than a year as they prepared for a rush of buyers eager to lock in mortgage rates before the rates move higher.</p>
        <p>All regions except the Midwest reported increased construction, the Commerce  Department said today. The increases pushed national housing starts 3 percent above the January level, to an annual rate of 1.49 million. The February rate is the highest since December 1994, when the rate was 1.51 million.</p>
        <p>Relatively low mortgage rates, which remain below 8 percent even after a recent rise, and increases in employment are fueling demand for houses, analysts and home builders said. "Job growth is what drives the housing market," said Ted Mahoney, president of Windjammer Construction in Plainville, Mass.</p>
        <p>The report "fits the very optimistic tone" reflected in a survey by a home builders' group that was released today, said Raymond Worseck, chief economist with A. G. Edwards &amp; Sons in St. Louis. The National Association of Home Builders said its housing market index for March jumped 10 points, to 60, the highest level since May 1994.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mahoney said the survey was consistent with his experience recently. "I'm sold out," he said. "I put my last house under agreement this weekend."</p>
        <p>For the industry as a whole, these are still nervous times. Recent Government figures showed that new-home sales rose 4.2 percent in January, but the supply of new homes for sale rose eight-tenths of a percent, to the highest level in 16 years.</p>
        <p>If the economy stumbles and home sales wither in coming months, builders will find themselves saddled with the carrying cost of unsold homes that may require  price cuts to sell.</p>
        <p>Today's report showed that housing construction was not as strong in January  as earlier reported. The January increase was 1.5 percent, not the 4.4 percent that the Government had estimated a month ago.</p>
        <p>Economists surveyed by Bloomberg Business News had expected starts to decline about 2.6 percent in February, as winter storms slowed commerce on the East Coast. In fact, starts in the Northeast recorded the biggest gain, surging 33 percent, to 127,000. Starts increased 5.7 percent in the West, to 425,000, and rose 4.2 percent in the South, to 647,000. The Midwest was the exception, showing a decline of 11.6 percent, to 291,000.</p>
        <p>The outlook suggests an acceptable year for housing even though mortgage rates have surged since February, when the rate on a 30-year fixed mortgage averaged 7.08 percent. Last week, the rate was at 7.83 percent, a seven-month high, according to the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation.</p>
        <p>That is still relatively low, analysts said. At February's mortgage rate, the average monthly payment on a $100,000 loan was $670.68, up from $667.32 in December. By contrast that payment would have been $822.68 in December 1994, when mortgage rates were at their recent peak of 9.25 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
