<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; The Plumbers' Return</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEXUAL HARASSMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILL, ANITA F (PROF)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, CLARENCE (ASSOC JUSTICE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLEMING, PETER E JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDB1E3FF934A25751C0A964958260" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; The Plumbers' Return</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having embarrassed itself and the nation in its conduct of the Clarence Thomas hearings, the U.S. Senate is now bungling its investigation into the source of character-assassinating leaks.</p>
        <p>As I wrote at the time, I suspect that a trio of hotly partisan aides on the staffs of Senators Metzenbaum, Kennedy and Simon induced Prof. Anita Hill to submit allegations of sexual harassment against the nominee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Having embarrassed itself and the nation in its conduct of the Clarence Thomas hearings, the U.S. Senate is now bungling its investigation into the source of character-assassinating leaks.</p>
        <p>As I wrote at the time, I suspect that a trio of hotly partisan aides on the staffs of Senators Metzenbaum, Kennedy and Simon induced Prof. Anita Hill to submit allegations of sexual harassment against the nominee.</p>
        <p>In my opinion, they led her to believe she could make her charges without revealing her identity, suggesting to her that the very threat of embarrassing publicity would force the nominee to withdraw his name.</p>
        <p>After they persuaded Ms. Hill to submit an unsworn statement by fax, members of the Senate trio -- probably in cahoots with a team of high-powered Washington lawyers, lobbyists and public relations specialists out to "bork" the nominee -- caused the sensational Hill statement to be leaked to a couple of reputable reporters.</p>
        <p>Tim Phelps of Newsday and Nina Totenberg of National Public Radio then did what journalists are supposed to do: they checked the authenticity of the statement with a surprised Professor Hill, and checked sources who professed to have seen a follow-up F.B.I. interview with her that amplified her charges but did not make available the F.B.I. document. They then broadcast and published what they learned.</p>
        <p>The journalists did the right thing. I despised the story but had to respect the reporters: we are not in the business of withholding what we learn, especially when it concerns the conduct or qualifications of government officials.</p>
        <p>The Senate conspirators did the wrong thing. Though they committed no crime of revealing state secrets, their manipulation was unfair to the accuser, permanently damaging to the accused and faithless to their responsibilities to their Senate employers.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, to protect future nominees from unsubstantiated charges, the Senate voted to investigate the leak. A good idea; no matter what the ends, the wrong means are never right.</p>
        <p>Counsel was hired and given power of subpoena. Peter Fleming, a lawyer famed for his successful defense of John Mitchell, was given the assignment to discover the truth about the invasion of privacy -- not for the purpose of jailing anyone, but to make it clear that the Senate will not tolerate abuse of its procedures.</p>
        <p>Does he take sworn testimony from those who importuned Professor Hill to contact the committee; from Senate aides who urged her to send in a statement; from Ms. Hill and anyone to whom she showed copies of her document? Does he dare put senators under oath to discover what they knew about what their aides were doing in their name?</p>
        <p>No. The counsel appointed by Senators Ford and Stevens instead seeks sworn depositions from the reporters whose careers would be ruined if they betrayed the First Amendment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Phelps was grilled for five hours and of course resisted. Next week, so will Ms. Totenberg; her attorney, Floyd Abrams (of the firm of Uninhibited, Robust &amp; Wideopen), has informed the misdirected inquisitor that his client "will not respond to questions seeking the identification of her source or sources."</p>
        <p>With this position on the record in advance, why does the Senate counsel go through the charade of harassing the journalists? Does he really want to bring them before the Senate, have them repeat their stand and demand they be cited for contempt?</p>
        <p>Surely he is aware of the Schorr precedent in the House. Daniel Schorr went before a committee in 1976 and risked jail for contempt by saying: "To betray a source would mean to dry up many future sources for many future reporters. It would mean betraying myself, my career and my life." The committee wisely voted to respect his rights.</p>
        <p>The Senate's reason for laying the legal groundwork for a sleazy publicity stunt in bashing the press is unmistakable: Senators Ford and Stevens want to shift the focus away from unscrupulous Senators or staffers.</p>
        <p>That's a cover-up. The character assassins, who committed no prosecutable crime, are not likely to endanger their freedom by perjuring themselves. They risk, not jail, only dismissal; their bosses risk Senate censure.</p>
        <p>Don't prepare the phony excuse, Mr. Fleming, that because reporters would not talk, your hands were tied. You have a better way to get to the truth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
