<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Memo; Clinton's Handlers Admit, Whitewater Affair Overtook Them</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="662435"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPECIAL PROSECUTORS (INDEPENDENT COUNSEL)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WHITEWATER DEVELOPMENT CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">IFILL, GWEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, HILLARY RODHAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Prosecutors (Independent Counsel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D81E31F935A25752C0A962958260" item-length="1136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Memo; Clinton's Handlers Admit, Whitewater Affair Overtook Them</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GWEN IFILL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">IFILL, GWEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even by the White House's own accounting, its handling of questions about President Clinton's Arkansas real estate dealings has been a near fiasco.</p>
        <p>For now, Clinton aides say they have stemmed the flood of publicity about the role of Bill and Hillary Rodham Clinton in the Whitewater Development Company, a real estate investment company they formed with the owner of a failed Arkansas savings and loan. But first the aides had to persuade the Clintons, and their legal advisers -- as well as themselves -- that the only way out was to go along with the rising cry for an independent investigation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even by the White House's own accounting, its handling of questions about President Clinton's Arkansas real estate dealings has been a near fiasco.</p>
        <p>For now, Clinton aides say they have stemmed the flood of publicity about the role of Bill and Hillary Rodham Clinton in the Whitewater Development Company, a real estate investment company they formed with the owner of a failed Arkansas savings and loan. But first the aides had to persuade the Clintons, and their legal advisers -- as well as themselves -- that the only way out was to go along with the rising cry for an independent investigation.</p>
        <p>That took some time, and before the drama played out, it featured bouts of Presidential temper, battles with Congress and, finally, abrupt capitulation.</p>
        <p>All along, the issue was complicated by the involvement of Mrs. Clinton, who as a Little Rock lawyer had represented Madison Guaranty Savings and Loan, the failed institution owned by James B. McDougal, the Clinton's partner in Whitewater. 'Political Reality'</p>
        <p>As a matter of principle and legality, the Clintons had insisted that their private financial dealings before Mr. Clinton assumed the Presidency were not the public's business.</p>
        <p>But some of the President's political advisers watched with dread this week as news reports about Whitewater followed him abroad, threatening to drown out the themes of international stability they had worked so carefully to project during his 10-day trip to Europe and Russia.</p>
        <p>As one White House official said: "At some point, the principle of the issue got caught up in the political reality. So we called the President and talked about how he saw it."</p>
        <p>By announcing the decision to have the Attorney General appoint a special counsel, aides believe the White House -- at least for the moment -- short-circuited the debate and perhaps cut off the controversy before it began to drag Mr. Clinton down in opinion polls.</p>
        <p>"Every innocent little slip or lack of complete information was pounced on," moaned one White House official. "And when you get to that point, you have to face reality, look for a circuit breaker." Hillary Clinton's Role</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who left Washington to join her husband in Moscow on Thursday, represented her family's interest in determining what the circuit breaker would be, aides said.</p>
        <p>But when Mrs. Clinton is involved in any issue, most White House officials stand clear. While they acknowledged that her chief of staff, Margaret Williams, sat in on damage-control meetings on the Whitewater affair, aides were loath to discuss Mrs. Clinton's role in the discussions.</p>
        <p>Aides who traveled with the President on Air Force One this week said Mr. Clinton discussed the Whitewater situation with his wife by telephone, but they refused to provide details.</p>
        <p>While the two were ultimately convinced that they had to appoint a special counsel, everyone else at the White House thought it was bad idea. The President despised the idea of appointing someone to investigate behavior that not even his worst enemies would claim was criminal, aides said. Mrs. Clinton resisted the idea for similar reasons, and Bernard W. Nussbaum, the White House counsel, supported their contention.</p>
        <p>But aides who had studied President Jimmy Carter's handling of a Federal investigation into his family's peanut business concluded that a special counsel was the best tactic for putting the affair to rest. The Carter inquiry, which took seven months, found "no evidence whatsoever" that bank loans were diverted to Mr. Carter's 1976 Presidential campaign. 2 Years of Problems</p>
        <p>The stubborn and unpleasant Whitewater venture has plagued the Clintons for nearly two years. Questions about their investment in what was to have been a 200-acre retirement community in the Ozarks first arose during the 1992 Presidential campaign, dogged them for a short while and then faded. New questions arose late last year when it was disclosed, months after the fact, that White House officials had removed Whitewater files from the offices of Vincent W. Foster Jr., the White House deputy counsel and former law partner of Mrs. Clinton, shortly after he killed himself in July.</p>
        <p>White House officials began to realize they had lost their grip over the latest twists practically at the stroke of the New Year.</p>
        <p>George Stephanopoulos, the President's senior adviser, returned to Washington fresh from a ski holiday and declared on television that all of the pertinent papers in the matter had been turned over to the Justice Department, which was investigating Madison Guaranty and its dealings with Whitewater.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Stephanopoulos's remarks were premature at best; no papers had been delivered. Dee Dee Myers, the White House press secretary, spent the bulk of her first news briefing of the New Year correcting Mr. Stephanopopulos's misimpression. Mark D. Gearan, the communications director, later devoted even more time to explaining why the White House had failed to note that the papers were turned over to the Justice Department just in time to avoid a subpoena.</p>
        <p>Still later, it emerged that the Clintons had taken steps to make sure that the information would be subpoenaed, and thus shielded from the public and the news media. Fears of Paralysis</p>
        <p>When Mr. Clinton's mother died unexpectedly just before his European trip, and the President traveled to Arkansas for the funeral, White House aides expected that the Whitewater drumbeat would stop. They were wrong.</p>
        <p>Once the White House had begun to dissemble on the details of the Whitewater deal, Republicans immediately raised questions. White House efforts to label the attack as a partisan assault were undercut when important Democrats, along with leading newspaper editorials, joined the call for an independent investigation.</p>
        <p>For the White House, the major concern was that the issue would paralyze its staff first, then preoccupy members of Congress and move on to distract the President and the electorate from the important issues Mr. Clinton hoped to focus on, providing universal health care coverage and curbing crime.</p>
        <p>"I mean, I guess the media's been obsessed with this," Mr. Clinton said last week in an interview on ABC News' "Nightline." "But it never crosses my mind."</p>
        <p>It all boiled over in Europe, as was evidenced by Mr. Clinton himself, when he snatched off his microphone and stalked out of an interview with Jim Miklaszewski, an NBC reporter, who had asked him two Whitewater questions in a row.</p>
        <p>Asked about the encounter the next day in another television interview, Mr. Clinton said he had been misled about the topic of the interview and said he was tired as well as preoccupied with the tasks at hand.</p>
        <p>"There's no point in going into it now," he added. "I don't have to talk about it any more."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
