<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Controversy Aside, Owls Come Up Winners</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="662473"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TEMPLE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF RHODE ISLAND</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEED61E31F935A25752C0A962958260" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Controversy Aside, Owls Come Up Winners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>KINGSTON, R.I., Jan. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tipoff happened on time and the coaches did not walk off the court. On the birthday of Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., two black coaches, one of them leading a top-25 team, matched up as scheduled.</p>
        <p>But the players were flat and intensity was absent as Temple, ranked No. 13 by The Associated Press, defeated Rhode Island, 69-49, today in Keaney Gym.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The tipoff happened on time and the coaches did not walk off the court. On the birthday of Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., two black coaches, one of them leading a top-25 team, matched up as scheduled.</p>
        <p>But the players were flat and intensity was absent as Temple, ranked No. 13 by The Associated Press, defeated Rhode Island, 69-49, today in Keaney Gym.</p>
        <p>This could have been a great matchup. Both games last season between the two schools were decided by one basket. Until today, Temple had not had a rebounding advantage over the Rams in six games. But Temple's sophomore center, William Cunningham, had 8 of his 10 rebounds in the first half, and was a big reason why Rhode Island couldn't get second and third chances. Rams Stay in Game</p>
        <p>Still, the Rams trailed by just 7 points at the half. The Rams' senior guard, Carlos Cofield, hit 4 of 6 from 3-point range to keep his team close.</p>
        <p>Finally, Temple's senior forward, Aaron McKie, and guard Eddie Jones killed what was left of Rhode Island's second-half run.</p>
        <p>McKie drove inside for an easy 2 points and hit a 3-pointer. Then Jones added a baseline jumper to cap a 11-0 run and give the Owls a 62-44 lead with 3 minutes 58 seconds left in the game. Jones had a game-high 24 points, McKie had 21 and Cofield led the Rams with 19. The Topic Remains</p>
        <p>But after the game, neither coach talked about the top athletes, the scoring runs, the big play that made the difference. And neither was asked. There was no boycott, but the issues raised by the possible boycott remained a topic.</p>
        <p>"You would have seen a boycott today," said Temple's coach, John Chaney. "We will not go away, I promise you that. I'm prepared to walk out at anytime."</p>
        <p>So were his assistants. The Temple players, however, declined comment on the Black Coaches Association and the arguments for a 14th scholarship for Division I basketball programs. Chaney, however, was vehement about several issues.</p>
        <p>"There is a bigger symbol here than just a scholarship," he said. "There is an attitude that tends to permeate our society. I got mine, now you get yours. What kind of signals are we sending our students?"</p>
        <p>Rhode Island's coach, Al Skinner, said he was neither disappointed nor relieved that the boycott did not take place today. 'The Issues Still Exist'</p>
        <p>"We can still do that at a later date," he said. "The issues still exist."</p>
        <p>The past week has had an effect on the players, as well. The Rhode Island players didn't know until Friday afternoon whether they would have their head coach for today's game. A Ram senior forward, Abdul Fox, who has a minor in African-American studies, saw the past week as a necessity, not a distraction.</p>
        <p>"It would have been a tough decision, but I probably would have played, even though I support Coach Skinner," Fox said. "You can only do so much when you are just one person. I didn't want to walk off if it was going to be just by myself. But if I knew there was more support with other players out there, maybe I would do it."  PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
