<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pier 1 Finds Success Beyond Brass</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="359824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PIER 1 IMPORTS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARMASH, ISADORE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, CLARK A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DC1139F93AA35755C0A966958260" item-length="1174" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pier 1 Finds Success Beyond Brass</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISADORE BARMASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARMASH, ISADORE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The recent push by Pier 1 Imports Inc. into Manhattan caps a four-year overhaul that has transformed the company from a retailer of inexpensive imported goods into one selling moderately priced home furnishings for successful young professionals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The recent push by Pier 1 Imports Inc. into Manhattan caps a four-year overhaul that has transformed the company from a retailer of inexpensive imported goods into one selling moderately priced home furnishings for successful young professionals.</p>
        <p>The recent push by Pier 1 Imports Inc. into Manhattan caps a four-year overhaul that has transformed the company from a retailer of inexpensive imported goods into one selling moderately priced home furnishings for successful young professionals.</p>
        <p>Three weeks ago, the Fort Worth-based company opened a store at 40th Street and Fifth Avenue, the first of four locations planned in Manhattan in the next three years. Pier 1 expects to open more than 80 stores nationwide this year, expanding the chain to 582 outlets.</p>
        <p>Pier 1 is seeking new customers in new markets, but it also hopes to attract many of the same customers it had in the past - only now they have established careers and higher incomes.</p>
        <p>''These buyers, and there are a lot of them - about 79 million out of 230 million Americans - have about 67 percent of the discretionary income in this country,'' said Clark A. Johnson, chairman and chief executive of Pier 1. ''But they are hardly captive customers. We sell wants, as opposed to needs, so we have to earn our way into their hearts and pocketbooks.''</p>
        <p>The new outlet in Manhattan is similar to the nearly 300 that Pier 1 has opened since 1985, when Mr. Johnson joined the company and began to spruce up its image. With an all-glass exterior that exposes two floors of merchandise to the street, the new store is bigger and more elegant than those opened before 1986.</p>
        <p>Only one corner of the store is devoted to brass and wicker from Asia, a predominant offering in the early stores that appealed to college students in the 1960's and 70's. The rest of the space is filled with lamps, tableware, ceramics, rugs and sportswear.</p>
        <p>While the company views department stores and large specialty stores as its main competitors, its outlets sell many of the same items as chains like the Pottery Barn and Conran's.</p>
        <p>The repositioning has made Pier 1 one of the most closely watched and respected retail stocks on Wall Street. Today, the average customer spends $25.44 on a visit to a Pier 1 store, up from $17.46 a few years ago. In the last five years, the company's net income has grown almost 34 percent, compounded annually, and its sales have risen 24.4 percent a year.</p>
        <p>For the fiscal year ended March 3, 1990, the chain earned $25.5 million on sales of $516.9 million. Its 5.5 percent profit margin on sales compares with the industry average of 3.5 percent.</p>
        <p>With continued expansion, Mr. Johnson predicted, sales should double again by 1996. ''By the end of fiscal 1998,'' the tall, confident Mr. Johnson insisted, ''we will have opened our one-thousandth store.''</p>
        <p>Analysts are impressed with the improvements. ''The company's merchandising prowess and consumer franchise are vastly stronger than they were in 1986,'' said Donald I. Trott, a specialty retail analyst at Dean Witter Reynolds in New York.</p>
        <p>While Kenneth M. Gassman Jr., an analyst at Wheat First Securities in Richmond, views the company as a ''high-growth retailer,'' he is cautious about whether it would thrive in a recession.</p>
        <p>''Our only major concern is that Pier 1's merchandise appears to fill discretionary consumer needs,'' he said. ''Therefore, in an economic slowdown, it is possible that Pier 1 would feel a negative impact.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gassman promptly added, ''Pier 1 targets a higher-income consumer who traditionally has not cut back on overall spending in prior economic slowdowns.''</p>
        <p>Pier 1 now aims at a customer whose average family income is $50,000 a year. For years, the family income of its average customer was $39,000 a year.</p>
        <p>Began in California</p>
        <p>Conceived as an importer of inexpensive merchandise called Cost Plus, the company was formed in 1962 with a single store in San Mateo, Calif., featuring mostly wicker and rattan furniture. Charles Tandy, the founder of the Radio Shack chain, had made a loan to a rattan furniture wholesaler who owned a store by that name, and in return received the rights to operate shops under the name. The company expanded to 16 stores within three years.</p>
        <p>To express the stores' exotic foreign flavor, the company changed its name to Pier 1 Imports - a name picked in a contest for store managers.</p>
        <p>In 1966, the Tandy Corporation sold Pier 1 to a management group. The new owners continued to expand the business, and in 1970 made the 42-store chain, concentrated in the West and Southwest, a public company. Intermark Inc. purchased 58 percent of its shares and is still the biggest shareholder, with a 51 percent share.</p>
        <p>While Pier 1's formula worked well in the 60's and 70's, it proved less successful in the 80's. Its core following, the college students of the 60's and 70's, had tired of Pier 1's inexpensive merchandise.</p>
        <p>In 1985, management hired Mr. Johnson in hopes of putting the company back on track. Pier 1 was then operating 265 stores, each contributing almost $1 million in annual sales, and net profits were $15 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson, who has an entrepreneur's flair and a salesman's pitch, had been honed in the highly competitive home-improvement sector - he is a former top executive of the Wickes Companies, and later as a partner of Jack Nicklaus in a sporting-equipment company.</p>
        <p>Sought Advice of Customers</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson attacked the problems of Pier 1 head-on, by starting a series of consumer ''focus groups'' in five cities. Looking back on those discussions, in which customers were asked their perceptions of the stores and how they could be improved, Mr. Johnson said, ''They set the course for us.''</p>
        <p>The consumers said they wanted larger stores, where it would be more convenient to see and handle the goods. They liked the merchandise, they said, but would pay more for higher-quality, more fashionable goods. Despite the popularity of shopping malls, they said they preferred free-standing stores for their convenience and ease of parking.</p>
        <p>Putting many of these suggestions to work, Mr. Johnson urged his buyers to pick better goods and bring in additional foreign suppliers. (Today there are 44.) He also insisted that new stores be more accessible, with wider aisles and shorter shelving. Indeed, today's stores average 9,000 square feet, double the size of those opened before 1985. The company has been closing older stores and replacing them with larger ones.</p>
        <p>New Policy on Returns</p>
        <p>Hoping to insure customer satisfaction, he took the unusual step of giving store managers complete authority in handling returned goods, even on sales made months earlier. ''I know that some customers take advantage of us,'' Mr. Johnson said, ''but we feel it is a worthwhile public-relations effort on our part.''</p>
        <p>The real test has been in the financial results, which have steadily improved. Pier 1's stock closed yesterday at $11.375 a share, down 25 cents, on the New York Stock Exchange. It has traded as high as $13.25 a share this year, and as low as $9.50.</p>
        <p>''We look favorably on the company's stock,'' said Mr. Trott of Dean Witter. ''We estimate 1990 earnings of 90 cents a share, and $1.10 a share in 1991, against 1989's 71 cents a share.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
