<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Comptroller Urges Control Board To Press Dinkins on Fiscal Goals</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="491780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCKINLEY, JAMES C JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REGAN, EDWARD V (COMPTROLLER)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DA1F39F935A35751C1A967958260" item-length="475" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Comptroller Urges Control Board To Press Dinkins on Fiscal Goals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCKINLEY, JAMES C JR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The State Comptroller called yesterday on the State Financial Control Board to step up the pressure on Mayor David N. Dinkins to shrink New York City's government in more drastic ways than were outlined in the Mayor's long-term financial plan in November.</p>
        <p>The Comptroller, Edward V. Regan, asserted that a resolution by the board was needed because "there is a vacuum" of leadership at City Hall. Such a resolution would be largely symbolic but could be a prelude to a takeover of the city's finances by state, he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The State Comptroller called yesterday on the State Financial Control Board to step up the pressure on Mayor David N. Dinkins to shrink New York City's government in more drastic ways than were outlined in the Mayor's long-term financial plan in November.</p>
        <p>The Comptroller, Edward V. Regan, asserted that a resolution by the board was needed because "there is a vacuum" of leadership at City Hall. Such a resolution would be largely symbolic but could be a prelude to a takeover of the city's finances by state, he said.</p>
        <p>"We need to turn up the heat another notch," Mr. Regan, a Republican, said. "The Mayor said, 'I'll do it,' and then didn't do it. They produced a plan that comes nowhere near to obtaining the goals."</p>
        <p>Last month the Dinkins administration agreed to revise the plan it unveiled on Nov. 6 after state fiscal monitors and bond rating agencies complained that it lacked specifics, did not reduce the work force enough and relied too heavily on uncertain revenues and hard-to-negotiate labor concessions.  More Detailed Plan</p>
        <p>Responding to the criticism, Mr. Dinkins has promised to present a more detailed plan next month to close more than $7 billion in projected budget shortfalls over the next five years. He would present the plan at the Financial Control Board meeting in mid-January.</p>
        <p>The Mayor's spokesman, Leland T. Jones, said Mr. Regan's threat to push for a control board resolution amounted to an "unseemly" partisan attack because the Mayor has already committed himself to revising the plan.</p>
        <p>"You don't need to turn up the heat on us since we've already turned up the heat on ourselves," Mr. Jones said. "Now is not the time for partisan politics."</p>
        <p>The Financial Control Board was set up during the city's fiscal crisis of the mid-1970's to oversee the city's finances. Since the early 1980's it has had only advisory powers, but it can take control if the city fails to balance its budget. The board members include the Governor, the Mayor, the state and city comptrollers, and three private members.  Viewed as Premature</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, Charles Porcari, said: "The Comptroller is being premature. The Financial Control Board had asked the Mayor for more details on his plan and had asked him to report back in January. The Governor feels he should have the opportunity to do just that."</p>
        <p>Mr. Regan's remarks came as he released an analysis of the Mayor's plan that asserted that the administration's estimates of tax revenues were too optimistic and that the city was depending on highly uncertain labor concessions and $2 billion in state aid that was in doubt.</p>
        <p>The resolution will be considered at the board's next meeting on Dec. 13. Mr. Regan submitted a similar resolution in July, but it died because none of the other members of the board seconded it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
