<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York's Lobbying Law Is Ruled Unconstitutional</title>
    <meta content="19LOBBY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/19/nyregion/19lobby.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1605026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Temporary State Commission on Lobbying (NYS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coalition for Fairness (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simmons, Russell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chavis, Benjamin (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn for the Advancement of Colored People</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Public Interest Research Group</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E7DB1E3FF93AA2575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="650" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York's Lobbying Law Is Ruled Unconstitutional</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New York's Lobbying Law Is Ruled Unconstitutional</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Aug. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Bernard J Malone rules that parts of state's lobbying law are unconstitutional because they allow state to fine lobbyists without giving them due process; ruling leaves Temporary State Commission on Lobbying powerless to enforce laws, but it is expected to be stayed once appeal is filed; law was challenged by Coalition for Fairness, group that seeks reform of state's drug laws and includes hip-hop mogul Russell Simmons and Dr Benjamin Chavis, former NAACP president (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A state court ruled on Wednesday that parts of New York's lobbying law are unconstitutional because they allow the state to fine lobbyists without giving them proper hearings.</p>
        <p>The State Supreme Court ruling, which is expected to be appealed, leaves the entity in charge of monitoring lobbyists, the Temporary State Commission on Lobbying, briefly powerless to enforce the law, and leaves the lobbying industry, which is now a more than $100-million-a-year business in Albany, temporarily unregulated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALBANY, Aug. 18 - A state court ruled on Wednesday that parts of New York's lobbying law are unconstitutional because they allow the state to fine lobbyists without giving them proper hearings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A state court ruled on Wednesday that parts of New York's lobbying law are unconstitutional because they allow the state to fine lobbyists without giving them proper hearings.</p>
        <p>The State Supreme Court ruling, which is expected to be appealed, leaves the entity in charge of monitoring lobbyists, the Temporary State Commission on Lobbying, briefly powerless to enforce the law, and leaves the lobbying industry, which is now a more than $100-million-a-year business in Albany, temporarily unregulated.</p>
        <p>Once an appeal is filed, officials expect the ruling to be stayed, allowing the commission to continue its work as the case proceeds.</p>
        <p>The court ruled that the lobbying law, which is more than two decades old, deprives lobbyists of their due process rights. It found that the state's lobbying law allows the lobbying commission to determine on its own whether someone has violated the law, without an adjudicative hearing. And while the commission does hold hearings to weigh the guilt of lobbyists, and even adopted new guidelines for such hearings in April, the court said that a bad law cannot be fixed with administrative rules.</p>
        <p>In a 13-page decision, Justice Bernard J. Malone of State Supreme Court in Albany found that ''the statutory scheme does not provide due process because it allows an alleged lobbyist to be deprived of property upon a determination of guilt made without notice and the opportunity to be heard.''</p>
        <p>The case was brought by the Coalition for Fairness, a group including Russell Simmons, the hip-hop mogul, and Dr. Benjamin Chavis, the former head of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. The coalition was formed to urge reform of the state's strict Rockefeller-era drug laws. After the coalition held a rally to protest the drug laws, the lobbying commission began an inquiry into whether the group had lobbied without registering.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simmons and Dr. Chavis, who maintained all along that they were simply exercising their free speech rights and were not lobbying, praised the ruling. ''We will not be silenced and, with today's ruling, we will step up our pace, raising awareness on this issue,'' Dr. Chavis said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simmons is chairman of the Hip-Hop Summit Action Network, and Dr. Chavis is its president.</p>
        <p>David M. Grandeau, the executive director of the lobbying commission, acknowledged that the law was flawed and said that he hopes Gov. George E. Pataki and the State Legislature will pass a better, stronger law. ''Hopefully the Legislature and the governor will get together and remedy the defect in the act,'' he said. ''We have a good team in place here. What we need are balls and bats so we can play the game.''</p>
        <p>But civic groups worry about the prospects of getting a better law through the current gridlock in Albany and past a $100-million lobbying industry that would like to see many of the regulations simply go away.</p>
        <p>The appeal will be handled by the office of State Attorney General Eliot Spitzer. ''We continue to believe that the current law is sound and that it can be effectively enforced with due process protections,'' said Darren Dopp, a spokesman for Mr. Spitzer. ''We are consulting with the commission and expect that the judge's decision will be appealed. It is imperative that the protections against lobbyist abuses remain in place.''</p>
        <p>Civic groups worried that the ruling could further hobble a commission that they view as the only aggressive ethics monitor in Albany, one that is already under a great deal of political pressure.</p>
        <p>''With this ruling, the lobbying law becomes an honor system,'' said Blair Horner, a lobbyist for the New York Public Interest Research Group, who said the governor should call a special session so the Legislature can strengthen the lobbying law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
