<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stop Them Before They Overspend Again</title>
    <meta content="08REIS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/08/opinion/08REIS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1269189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reischauer, Robert D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFDE1731F93BA35751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stop Them Before They Overspend Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert D. Reischauer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reischauer, Robert D</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert D Reischauer Op-Ed article urges Congress to resist natural inclination to spend whatever it has on hand, in light of Congressional Budget Office projections that surpluses over next 10 years will amount to $5.6 trillion; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The table has been set. The Congressional Budget Office has projected that budget surpluses over the next 10 years will amount to $5.6 trillion. Alan Greenspan has offered his blessing for tax cuts. The president and Congress are poised to binge, not only on tax cuts, but on things like defense spending, prescription drugs for Medicare beneficiaries and education initiatives.</p>
        <p>Congress must resist its natural inclination to spend whatever it has on hand (and more). And new budget rules are the only sure-fire way to provide such restraint.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The table has been set. The Congressional Budget Office has projected that budget surpluses over the next 10 years will amount to $5.6 trillion. Alan Greenspan has offered his blessing for tax cuts. The president and Congress are poised to binge, not only on tax cuts, but on things like defense spending, prescription drugs for Medicare beneficiaries and education initiatives.</p>
        <p>Congress must resist its natural inclination to spend whatever it has on hand (and more). And new budget rules are the only sure-fire way to provide such restraint.</p>
        <p>After all, the legal restrictions on spending that Congress first enacted in 1990 are, in no small part, responsible for today's surpluses. Caps limited the amount that could be spent annually on discretionary programs like defense, medical research, law enforcement and community development. And pay-as-you-go rules forced lawmakers to offset any expansion in entitlement programs or tax relief with savings from the same areas of the budget.</p>
        <p>When the surprisingly strong economy and booming stock market suddenly transformed the large and seemingly intractable annual deficits into small but rapidly growing surpluses, lawmakers abandoned this discipline. Using a variety of budget gimmicks, they circumvented the spending caps and the pay-as-you-go limits by $16 billion in 1999, $53 billion in 2000 and $93 billion in 2001.</p>
        <p>There is nothing wrong with relaxing the spending caps and pay-as-you-go limits. Clearly, strict fiscal discipline is no longer a requirement. But we should be careful not to return to days of the all-you-can-eat buffet. Before throwing money around again, we need new legal restrictions that can guide budgeting in an era of surpluses.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress should first spell out that some of the future surpluses should not be considered available at all. For example, virtually everyone agrees that Social Security's surpluses -- some $2.5 trillion of the $5.6 trillion total surplus -- should be taken off the table. Congress should also agree to protect Medicare's projected $392 billion surplus, as both the Senate and the House voted overwhelmingly to do last year in a provision that was later dropped.</p>
        <p>Next, Congress should enact legislation that would limit how much of the surplus that remained after protecting Social Security and Medicare could be spent. Although the Congressional Budget Office projects that remaining surpluses will be $2.7 trillion over 10 years, these projections are notoriously uncertain. An unexpected slowdown in the growth of productivity combined with a surge in Medicare and Medicaid costs could easily transform surpluses projected five to 10 years out into deficits.</p>
        <p>Even if the budget projections were solid, it would be myopic to commit our entire surplus today. As the decade unfolds, new priorities will emerge and new crises will demand our attention. If all of the decade's fiscal reserves are committed this year, future lawmakers will be forced to cut critical programs or raise taxes to address problems.</p>
        <p>New legislation should limit the ability of Congress and the president to tie up future surpluses, especially those that are more than five years away. For example, over the next two years, Congress should be allowed to enact legislation that commits no more than 80 percent of the non-Social Security, non-Medicare surpluses projected for 2002 and 2003, no more than 70 percent for 2004 and 2005, and so on down to 40 percent for  2010 and 2011. When the next Congress convenes in 2003, it would be given a new budget allowance to spend, based on a new set of surplus projections.</p>
        <p>The new law should require that the president's budget and the Congressional budget resolution adhere to these limits. And if they don't, there should be automatic across-the-board cuts, like those that so effectively enforced the fiscal rules of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>With these rules, Congress would be free to cut taxes and boost spending -- but not too wildly. If all goes as projected, there should be some money left for tomorrow's lawmakers to use for new priorities and unforeseen emergencies. And if the surplus projections proved to be overly optimistic, the country would be saved from painful economic choices.</p>
        <p>Robert D. Reischauer, president of the Urban Institute, was the director of the Congressional Budget Office from 1989 to 1995.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert D. Reischauer, president of the Urban Institute, was the director of the Congressional Budget Office from 1989 to 1995.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
