<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ARTS ABROAD: A Camera-Shy Legend, Exposed and Indignant; Cartier-Bresson Chafes Over a Book Of Photographs of His Well-Guarded Face</title>
    <meta content="08ARTS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/08/arts/08ARTS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1269170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cartier-Bresson, Henri</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Duncan, David Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Faceless (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E6D61631F93BA35751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ARTS ABROAD: A Camera-Shy Legend, Exposed and Indignant; Cartier-Bresson Chafes Over a Book Of Photographs of His Well-Guarded Face</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Feb. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arts Abroad column on publication of Faceless, unauthorized book of portraits by David Douglas Duncan, celebrated for Korean War images, of his former friend and acclaimed photographer Henri Cartier-Bresson, arguably most famous photographer still alive; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Henri Cartier-Bresson is arguably the most famous photographer alive, a tall, elegant Frenchman who at 92 still accepts the occasional portrait assignment. Among colleagues, however, the master of the intimate ''decisive moment,'' as his photographic signature became known, is also famous for hating to be photographed himself. ''I spent all my life trying to be unknown, to disappear, to be able to observe,'' he explained some years ago.</p>
        <p>Yet as drawing has replaced photography as his principal occupation, he has become less elusive. He has given several television interviews, and 43 photographs of him, half taken by his wife, the photographer Martine Franck, are now available for publication from Magnum, the legendary photo agency he helped found in 1947. Even so, Mr. Cartier-Bresson is still known to growl at unsuspecting photographers who dare approach him with their cameras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Henri Cartier-Bresson is arguably the most famous photographer alive, a tall, elegant Frenchman who at 92 still accepts the occasional portrait assignment. Among colleagues, however, the master of the intimate ''decisive moment,'' as his photographic signature became known, is also famous for hating to be photographed himself. ''I spent all my life trying to be unknown, to disappear, to be able to observe,'' he explained some years ago.</p>
        <p>Yet as drawing has replaced photography as his principal occupation, he has become less elusive. He has given several television interviews, and 43 photographs of him, half taken by his wife, the photographer Martine Franck, are now available for publication from Magnum, the legendary photo agency he helped found in 1947. Even so, Mr. Cartier-Bresson is still known to growl at unsuspecting photographers who dare approach him with their cameras.</p>
        <p>Now, however, David Douglas Duncan, 85, the American photographer celebrated for his Korean War combat images and his long years of recording Picasso at work and at play, is publishing ''Faceless'' (Assouline), an unauthorized book of his portraits of Mr. Cartier-Bresson.</p>
        <p>The Frenchman is furious. Mr. Cartier-Bresson tried unsuccessfully to block the book's  publication in the United States this month, although in France stricter privacy laws may work in his favor. After being sent the finished book, he denounced it as ''mediocre.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Duncan explained why he turned a spontaneous photography session into a 48-page book. ''I think of the book as a homage to the world's greatest photographer,'' he said. ''I didn't shoot it in any confrontational way. I did it with great respect. The crime would have been if it had been buried. Imagine if there were pictures of van Gogh in Arles. It would have been a terrible loss not to publish this. I shot it with affection, respect and responsibility.''</p>
        <p>When he decided to publish his book, though, Mr. Duncan knew he risked the wrath of Mr. Cartier-Bresson, who wrote to ''Dear Dave'' last June saying he was appalled after seeing ''the contact sheet of snapshots of my head'' and asking Mr. Duncan ''again not to publish any of them anywhere.'' He signed his handwritten note with ''All the best'' and added a postscript: ''No hard feelings.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Duncan was not swayed. ''How can he object when he has made his fame and fortune out of taking photographs of people without their permission?'' he asked. To underscore this point, he pulled out the transcript of an interview last July on ''The Charlie Rose Show'' on PBS in which Mr. Cartier-Bresson variously described his technique as ''aim properly, shoot quick and scram'' and ''you don't ask permission or anything.''</p>
        <p>''He has been so much in control of his image for so long, and he ran into a stone wall with me,'' Mr. Duncan said during a recent visit to Paris from his home of 40 years in the south of France. ''Henri is a legend. I've known him since 1948. I have always admired him. But I thought his being recorded was more important than his ego.''</p>
        <p>A former United States Marine officer, Mr. Duncan is himself not without a place in the history of postwar photography. He spent 10 years with Life magazine, which included assignments to Korea that resulted in his first book, ''This Is War!'' In 1956 he met Picasso, who was taking a bath at the time and was immediately recorded doing so; from the long friendship that followed, Mr. Duncan published seven Picasso books. And because of a chance meeting with the Soviet leader Nikita S. Khrushchev, he was the first Westerner to photograph the inside of the Kremlin.</p>
        <p>The photo session with Mr. Cartier-Bresson unfolded on May 25, with Mr. Duncan perhaps grabbing a decisive moment of his own. For a planned article on famous veteran photographers and their work, Vanity Fair asked Mr. Cartier-Bresson to take portraits of Willy Ronis, Helmut Newton, Eve Arnold and Mr. Duncan. For Mr. Duncan's portrait, Mr. Cartier-Bresson proposed the Picasso Museum in Paris as an appropriate location.</p>
        <p>After the photo session, Mr. Duncan recalled, he and his wife, Sheila, and Mr. Cartier-Bresson and his assistant went to the museum's garden cafe for a refreshment. Mrs. Duncan took some color photographs of the two men (Mr. Duncan destroyed all but one image from this roll) and then joined them at a table. Mr. Duncan then took his wife's old Pentax, asked Mr. Cartier-Bresson's assistant for a roll of black-and-white film, and began taking close-up photographs of Mr. Cartier-Bresson, 37 in total.</p>
        <p>''We didn't exchange a word,'' Mr. Duncan recalled. ''I just framed them and shot away. It took less than five minutes. Near the end, Henri took his own camera and began taking pictures of me. At the time, I wasn't thinking of publication. I just took them. Only when I developed them did I think, 'This is a historic document.' That's when I showed them to Henri and Martine. At the time, they didn't say anything. Only later did they object.''</p>
        <p>On June 17, Mr. Duncan sent Mr. Cartier-Bresson a proposed layout for his book, noting in an accompanying letter that ''my lifetime as a photographer -- dominated by my respect and affection for you -- fill these pages.'' Mr. Cartier-Bresson immediately responded with his note asking that the ''snapshots'' not be published.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duncan replied that ''within these 37 frames an extraordinary man is seen in astonishing depth -- aloof, remote, curious, irritated, daydreaming, haughty, bored, benign, professional, mystical, noble, loving.'' He added that, if published, the book ''will bring nothing but honor to us both.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cartier-Bressson was not persuaded. In late August, Mr. Duncan said, the men had a heated telephone exchange. ''That was some explosion the day before yesterday on the phone, deserving a response,'' Mr. Duncan wrote to Mr. Cartier-Bresson. In the letter, he went over how the portraits came to be taken and urged Mr. Cartier-Bresson to ''start again with the sort of life and friendship which have made our shared years so rewarding.''</p>
        <p>By then, having been turned down by several publishers of Mr. Cartier-Bresson's work, Mr. Duncan's book proposal had been accepted by the Paris-based Éditions Assouline. On Aug. 31, Jean-Paul Oberthür, a French lawyer acting on behalf of Mr. Cartier-Bresson, wrote to Assouline Publishing Inc. in New York stating that ''none of these photographs can be used or published anywhere'' and warning that Mr. Cartier-Bresson would take ''the necessary steps to prevent the circulation of the book'' and would seek ''compensatory damages and punitive damages.''</p>
        <p>In response, acting for Mr. Duncan, a New York lawyer, Edward L. Smith of Hollyer Brady Smith &amp; Hines, argued that the book was ''clearly newsworthy as a documentary work of significant general interest'' and that it did not violate Mr. Cartier-Bresson's ''rights of privacy or publicity at all.'' Given that the photographs were of public interest, were not being exploited commercially and were not offensive or embarrassing, the lawyer wrote, Mr. Duncan's book constituted valid free expression.</p>
        <p>Subsequently, Mr. Cartier-Bresson abandoned his attempt to stop the book's publication in the United States. ''We didn't make an issue out of it because Henri did not have a leg to stand on because in the United States you can publish anything,'' Ms. Franck explained.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duncan said he sent the very first printed copy of ''Faceless'' to Mr. Cartier-Bresson with a handwritten dedication that read: ''Henri, perhaps you'll will find the man I've  admired among these pages. Dave.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cartier-Bresson had the book in front of him during a recent interview in a small office below his apartment on the Rue de Rivoli. But at first, distraught about last month's devastating earthquake in India, a country he knows and loves, he waved away discussion of the book. ''I'm living day by day,'' he said. ''My problem is what has happened in India.''</p>
        <p>Finally, he turned to ''Faceless.'' ''It's a bad book,'' he said. ''Absolutely uninteresting, mediocre, a series of snapshots. It's just what comes out of a camera when a camera works. There's not one portrait here. There's no eye behind this. He's not capable of making a choice. He used all the film. Why didn't he just pick one? A portrait is something else. I'm sorry because I have made a living taking portraits. Taking a portrait is very, very delicate. With the tiniest thing, the thin thread snaps and the moment has gone.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Franck, who participated in the interview, seemed just as angry about the book. To the suggestion that Mr. Cartier-Bresson objected to being photographed, she replied: ''That's not true. What he objected to was such a lousy book.'' She conceded that, in the past, when doing photo reportage, her husband felt that anonymity helped him do his work so he studiously avoided being photographed. ''But there are lots of photographs of him now,'' she said, adding, ''I don't have the monopoly on photos of Henri.''</p>
        <p>For a long time, though, Mr. Cartier-Bresson's obsession about not being photographed was legend among those who knew him. Until the mid-1980's, for instance, Magnum had only one picture of him in its files, a passport photograph. Around that time he granted a television interview on the condition that the camera showed only his legs and feet. One old friend said that, while normally courteous and good-humored, Mr. Cartier-Bresson would fly off the handle if confronted by a camera.</p>
        <p>In the introduction to ''Faceless,'' Mr. Duncan described witnessing a more recent incident. ''Once, during the annual Arles photo conference, he nearly impaled me upon his new umbrella-cane when I interceded on behalf of a starry-eyed young admirer who hoped for a close-up snapshot,'' Mr. Duncan wrote.</p>
        <p>Ms. Franck responded, ''Someone came at him with a flash.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cartier-Bresson added, ''A flash is like rape.''</p>
        <p>For all Mr. Cartier-Bresson's indignation, Mr. Duncan continues to insist that ''Faceless'' is an honorable tribute to a pioneer of photojournalism. He also noted that any royalties from the book will go to the D.D.D. Photojournalism Fund that he created at the University of Texas at Austin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cartier-Bresson and Ms. Franck, though, are clearly not appeased. ''Dave is an acquaintance, not a friend,'' he said. To which Ms. Franck added sharply: ''He was a friend.''</p>
        <p>As for the Vanity Fair article, it appeared in January with Mr. Cartier-Bresson's portraits of Mr. Ronis, Mr. Newton and Ms. Arnold along with a portrait of Mr. Cartier-Bresson by Ms. Franck. But there was no portrait of Mr. Duncan by Mr. Cartier-Bresson.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
