<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Horror and Despair in the Balkans</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="777637"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED61730F936A15754C0A963958260" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Horror and Despair in the Balkans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the takeover of Srebrenica to the assault on Zepa, television anchors and correspondents, by now masters of Serbo-Croat consonants, have been shelling the safe havens of America's living rooms with images of Serb aggression, Muslim despair and Western waffling. Night after night has brought fierce contrasts from the ferocious war:</p>
        <p>*Frightened, exhausted women and children, the sweepings of ethnic cleansing, set against polished emissaries exchanging phrases in the polished chambers of the United Nations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the takeover of Srebrenica to the assault on Zepa, television anchors and correspondents, by now masters of Serbo-Croat consonants, have been shelling the safe havens of America's living rooms with images of Serb aggression, Muslim despair and Western waffling. Night after night has brought fierce contrasts from the ferocious war:</p>
        <p>*Frightened, exhausted women and children, the sweepings of ethnic cleansing, set against polished emissaries exchanging phrases in the polished chambers of the United Nations.</p>
        <p>*Accounts of atrocities, difficult to verify but far from implausible, of rape, murder of prisoners and casual carnage ("I saw lots of blood. Then I saw a big hole full of men with their throats cut and their faces covered in blood.") set against Allied statesmen delivering diplo-lingo.</p>
        <p>*The endless assault on Sarajevo, another United Nations-guaranteed enclave, with its running residents and soldiers on the run set against the Serb military's cheerful entrance into Zepa. There's Gen. Ratko Mladic, the Bosnian Serb commander, pressing weights and throwing his weight around.</p>
        <p>*Fiery rhetoric on Capitol Hill (Newt Gingrich: "Bosnia is the worst humiliation for the Western democracies since the 1930's") set against an Administration refrain: "There's a sense that every day counts and that we can't sit idly by."</p>
        <p>In deference to its international audience, CNN has been carrying regular reports from the Serb side, by Peter Arnett, and its reporters on the Muslim side have been less impassioned or hyperbolic than the correspondents and anchors of the major networks.</p>
        <p>"We begin tonight with cruelty and outrage," said Peter Jennings on a not untypical evening on ABC. Dan Rather led off one CBS broadcast with the news that "Bosnia tonight is the scene of brutality without end."</p>
        <p>As a response to a catastrophe that has created peculiar political alliances, such indignation has no patented ideological cast; it expresses a mass medium's often admirable sympathy for victims wherever the camera finds them. In years past, pictures on the screen have moved audiences to help sufferers from acts of man and God around the world, and even to support the sending of troops.</p>
        <p>But this time the nation seems quiescent, perhaps because of dismaying experiences elsewhere or a resurgent isolationism, or because the whole complicated affair, with its mess of ancient hatreds and up-to-date ambitions, has been dragging on too long, or because of confusing signals from a shaky leadership. Even picturing the war in Bosnia as a straightforward, readily understandable case of brutal aggression, as the networks have been doing, has not stirred audiences. A CBS news employee says the feeling around her newsroom is that viewers seem to have a "low appetite" for the subject.</p>
        <p>Possibly out of disappointment at its failure to rouse Americans to demand action, network news has turned up the heat on the White House. On NBC, the relatively restrained Tom Brokaw said, "Another no-win for the White House: the nightmare scenario in Bosnia." The lead-ins by Mr. Jennings, who has done strong reports of his own from Bosnia, have been particularly pointed: "Once again Bosnian civilians forced to flee their homes in terror while the Western European nations and the United States do nothing about it."</p>
        <p>The Russian Foreign Minister, Andrei V. Kozyrev, who opposes heavy bombing of the Serbs, was putting into words what the Administration must be fearing when he predicted that "this operation will stop the first day CNN shows civilian casualties." President Clinton made a pre-emptive strike by saying he would not halt the proposed bombing even if American relief workers were killed or American air crews shot down. Perhaps. But for the White House, already in campaign throes and under bombardment by television on several fronts, there may be no safe haven from the camera.  CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
