<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ankle Injury Forces Roddick To Another Early Exit in Paris</title>
    <meta content="31tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/31/sports/tennis/31tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1765684"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">French Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Roddick, Andy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hingis, Martina</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DF1631F932A05756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ankle Injury Forces Roddick To Another Early Exit in Paris</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ankle Injury Forces Roddick to Another Early Exit in Paris</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, May 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the time Andy Roddick shook Alberto Martín's hand and made his customary quick exit from the French Open, Martina Hingis was well out of harm's way here, in the city that is such a sweet-and-sour part of her tennis past.</p>
        <p>Hours before the fifth-seeded Roddick retired from his opening match with an injured left ankle, losing to Martín by 6-4, 7-5, 1-0, Hingis offered the latest reminder that putting an end to her retirement was a fine idea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andy Roddick retired from his opening match with an injured left ankle. Martina Hingis offered the latest reminder that putting an end to her retirement was a fine idea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the time Andy Roddick shook Alberto Martín's hand and made his customary quick exit from the French Open, Martina Hingis was well out of harm's way here, in the city that is such a sweet-and-sour part of her tennis past.</p>
        <p>Hours before the fifth-seeded Roddick retired from his opening match with an injured left ankle, losing to Martín by 6-4, 7-5, 1-0, Hingis offered the latest reminder that putting an end to her retirement was a fine idea.</p>
        <p>On May 21 in Rome, she earned her first title since returning to the WTA Tour, winning the Italian Open. On Tuesday, she required less than an hour to stroke her way through her first match at Roland Garros since 2001, defeating Lisa Raymond, 6-2, 6-2.</p>
        <p>Raymond, 32, is one of the few players on the Tour who began her professional career before Hingis, who made her pro debut in 1994, at 14. But Raymond has never been mistaken for a clay courter.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I was totally tested today,'' Hingis said. ''It's hard to say something after 6-2, 6-2 against Lisa Raymond. I'm sure once you work yourself into the tournament, you can tell more.''</p>
        <p>At 25 and after a three-year break from the game, Hingis is not a model of diplomacy. That character trait makes her an intriguing interview, but it also got her into trouble on center court here in 1999, when she walked deep into Steffi Graf's side of the court to question a line call during the final, which she ended up losing.</p>
        <p>That day may not define her anymore, although it will always be part of her legacy. But Hingis, seeded 12th, sounds convinced that the crowd, which whistled her loudly, has long since moved on.</p>
        <p>''Coming here after five years, it's definitely a different story,'' Hingis said of the French Open, the only Grand Slam she has not won. ''I feel more mature as a player and as a person.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''Everybody probably expects me to say it's overwhelming to be back here. I wasn't really nervous going out there today because I felt confident.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps it will be easier for Hingis as an underdog. The Paris crowd has rarely warmed to dominant players, and it was difficult to warm to much of anything on Tuesday, when temperatures remained in the low to mid-50's.</p>
        <p>The conditions were no help to third-seeded Nadia Petrova, who became the first major upset victim here. She came to Paris having won three tournaments on clay and four over all this year, but she struggled with a leg injury she sustained in practice and lost to Akiko Morigami, 6-2, 6-2.</p>
        <p>The weather was also not what Roddick was hoping for when he decided to play after spraining two ankle ligaments last week in Düsseldorf, Germany.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I shouldn't have,'' Roddick said, ''but it's tough to pass on a Slam.''</p>
        <p>The big-hitting, quick-talking Roddick appeared to be covering the court well in the early stages against Martín, but he later said, ''I was definitely tentative sliding.''</p>
        <p>Martín, ranked 68th, is not a terrific clay-court player, but he played a clever, focused match. He broke Roddick's serve, the hallmark of his game, four times. He also made Roddick struggle on his forays to the net, ripping passing shots and occasional lob winners.</p>
        <p>Roddick recovered from an early break in the second set, but at 5-5, he said he felt pain in his ankle as he chased a lob. He lost the game with a double fault, and Martín closed out the set. Roddick lost the opening game of the third set at love, double-faulting twice and receiving a code violation for hitting a ball into the stands in anger.</p>
        <p>Roddick called for the trainer, Michael Novotny, with the intention of having the ankle retaped and playing on. But Grand Slam guidelines prohibit players from taking an injury timeout for retaping. After Novotny told him he would have to wait until the next changeover or perhaps even until the end of the set, Roddick decided to retire, and he heard a few whistles from the crowd.</p>
        <p>He acknowledged that he was concerned about compromising his chances at Wimbledon, where he has reached the final the last two years.</p>
        <p>''That definitely crossed my mind out there,'' said Roddick, who has never advanced beyond the third round of the French Open. ''Right now I just want to get healthy. It's been an extremely annoying last month or so.''</p>
        <p>Roddick has not reached a final this season, and he has performed poorly in his last three majors, losing in the first round at the United States Open and the French Open and in the fourth round at the Australian Open.</p>
        <p>''I think people are overreacting,'' said John Roddick, his brother and coach. ''Look at the history of tennis. There are one or two players, maybe three, without any drops ever. It's not something out of the ordinary.''</p>
        <p>Another former No. 1 player looking for answers is Marat Safin, who has dropped to No. 53 and was defeated by the ninth-seeded Fernando González, 6-3, 1-6, 6-3, 6-1, in the first round. Lleyton Hewitt won in four sets over Jan Hernych; Hewitt is seeded 14th and has not won a title since January 2005.</p>
        <p>Robby Ginepri, seeded 17th, has had a tougher time. Last summer, he reached the United States Open semifinals and moved to 15th in the rankings. This year, he is 4-12 and has not been past the second round of any tournament. He was eliminated in the first round here by Alberto Montañés, in a match that was interrupted by rain Monday with Montañés ahead, two sets to one and 3-0. On Tuesday, Montañés closed out the match, 6-4.</p>
        <p>''I'm questioning what shots to go for,'' Ginepri said. ''Usually, I just played and had no feeling out there. Now, I think I'm a little older and maturing and, unfortunately, I'm thinking a little more out there. I need to just play.''</p>
        <p>Of the seven men from the United States in the main draw, only two, James Blake and Kevin Kim, advanced to the second round. Kim faces the defending champion Rafael Nadal next.</p>
        <p>With his swashbuckling style and 54-match winning streak on clay, Nadal is a fan favorite in many places, including, apparently, the Kim household. Earlier this week, Kim said his mother, Ann, managed to get Nadal's autograph.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
