<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hershey to Sell Pasta Business And Focus on Sweeter Profit</title>
    <meta content="Y10HERS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1061002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DA113EF933A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hershey to Sell Pasta Business And Focus on Sweeter Profit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANA CANEDY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Hershey Foods Corporation is shopping for a buyer for its pasta business, saying it wants to stick to making chocolate and candy.</p>
        <p>Although Hershey has the leading share of the United States dry pasta business, the company said its resources would be best used making and selling sweets, such as Hershey's Kisses and Reese's peanut butter cups.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Hershey Foods Corporation is shopping for a buyer for its pasta business, saying it wants to stick to making chocolate and candy.</p>
        <p>Although Hershey has the leading share of the United States dry pasta business, the company said its resources would be best used making and selling sweets, such as Hershey's Kisses and Reese's peanut butter cups.</p>
        <p>''After a thorough review of our strategic direction, we believe that we can generate a better return for our shareholders by focusing our resources on our confectionery and related grocery and food-service businesses,'' said Kenneth L. Wolfe, the chairman and chief executive of Hershey Foods.</p>
        <p>Among the likely buyers for the pasta unit, which includes Ronzoni, San Giorgio, Mrs. Weiss and five other brands, are Borden Inc. in Columbus, Ohio, and the American Italian Pasta Company in Excelsior Springs, Mo.</p>
        <p>''The list of logical buyers is probably short,'' said Jeffrey G. Kanter, a financial analyst at Prudential Securities. ''If a pasta company buys it, they could get the synergies that justify paying a pretty decent multiple, but if a nonpasta company buys it, it could be tougher to get the synergies.''</p>
        <p>Borden, which is also a leader in the domestic dry pasta business, could run into antitrust problems with such an acquisition. But American Italian Pasta is strongest in generic brand pasta and could therefore have fewer regulatory problems acquiring best-selling brands, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Even so, Borden said it had not ruled out a possible acquisition. ''Pasta is certainly a large portion of our business, and if there are things out there that can add value to our portfolio, we would consider them,'' said Lynn Anderson, a spokeswoman for the company, which is controlled by the acquisition firm Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company. Representatives of American Italian Pasta could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>Shares of Hershey closed unchanged yesterday at $67.</p>
        <p>The $4.3 billion company, which is based in Hershey, Pa., has been selling pasta since 1966 and has expanded the business primarily by building strong regional brands. The pasta division has revenue of about $400 million, which is the price analysts said it was likely to fetch from a buyer, and it has a profit margin of about 10 percent.</p>
        <p>Recently, analysts have criticized the company for not shedding the division because margins are about half of what Hershey's confections generate. Moreover, the dry pasta business in the United States has suffered from price competition from store brands and from consumers' tendency to eat pasta away from home, the analysts said.</p>
        <p>''The only surprise is that they didn't do this years ago,'' said William Leach, an analyst who follows Hershey for Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette. ''Pasta has been a laggard at the company and is obviously not a fit for the basic confectionery business.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
