<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Testaverde and Johnson, the Play Was the Thing</title>
    <meta content="10JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1061021"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Buffalo Bills</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Testaverde, Vinny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Keyshawn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Buffalo Bills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7D7113EF933A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="1132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Testaverde and Johnson, the Play Was the Thing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Nov. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses play of New York Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde and receiver Keyshawn Johnson in victory over Buffalo Bills; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some of the current Jets think this has never happened before on this team -- a 6-3 record, a share of first place. And actually, first place has not been a place to look for the Jets at season's end in all the years since the National Football League and American Football League merged in 1970.</p>
        <p>Thus, the good feeling that permeated the locker room today. Four-game winning streaks will do that for any team, and especially one that has done it only one other time in the past 12 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some of the current Jets think this has never happened before on this team -- a 6-3 record, a share of first place. And actually, first place has not been a place to look for the Jets at season's end in all the years since the National Football League and American Football League merged in 1970.</p>
        <p>Thus, the good feeling that permeated the locker room today. Four-game winning streaks will do that for any team, and especially one that has done it only one other time in the past 12 years.</p>
        <p>The Jets' 34-12 trouncing of the Bills on Sunday not only solidified the team's growing sense of itself, that it can play well on any given Sunday, but it apparently forged a link between the team's quarterback and its most dynamic receiver.</p>
        <p>Not only did Vinny Testaverde and Keyshawn Johnson collaborate on 7 receptions for 95 yards, they were attuned to each other on the play that positioned the crushing touchdown late in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>They have been getting to know each other's moves since training camp. In fact, Johnson remembers when Testaverde arrived in the summer. ''I saw he was watching me, and he picked up pretty quickly what I could do,'' Johnson said.</p>
        <p>And it did not take Testaverde long to appreciate Johnson's love for the game, his practice habits, his willingness to hit. ''He is the toughest receiver I have ever seen,'' Testaverde said.</p>
        <p>Now, all those moments and practices came together on a fourth-and-6 in the closing moments of the third quarter. The Bills had just produced a field goal to cut the Jets' lead to 20-12. The momentum had not really turned Buffalo's way, but if the Bills could stop the Jets and score again, they might have been off and running.</p>
        <p>On fourth down from the Bills' 35, Testaverde backpedaled, looking for Johnson. The way Testaverde described that moment today, he was uncharacteristically animated. Standing in the locker room, Testaverde cocked his right arm and explained:</p>
        <p>''I'm dropping back. There's a linebacker in front of Keyshawn and one in back of him. I'm not worried about the one behind him because he can't get the ball. I try to help Keyshawn out. I look like I'm throwing the ball and that freezes the linebacker. That gave Keyshawn time to start moving. I threw it low and away, and he grabbed it.''</p>
        <p>That pass went for 7 yards, allowed the Jets to keep moving and eventually resulted in a fourth-quarter touchdown toss to Wayne Chrebet for the pivotal score of the game.</p>
        <p>''Vinny's believed in me since he came to camp,'' Johnson said. ''Now he trusts in me.''</p>
        <p>It has not been a perfect relationship; in the victory against Kansas City two Sundays ago, Johnson surprised Testaverde on one play by slightly altering his route and it resulted in an interception and a sideline admonishment from the quarterback. But that one misunderstanding has been overshadowed by all the good work the two have produced.</p>
        <p>In fact, the big play against the Bills was merely one of a number of critical connections between Johnson and Testaverde in the game. On four plays they collaborated to turn third-down passes into first downs.</p>
        <p>Asked today whether this four-game winning streak makes players feel better about one another, Coach Bill Parcells, alternately proud of what his players have done, alternately wary of the pitfalls ahead, said: ''Yes, I think they do. It feels more of a team to me.''</p>
        <p>To Parcells, it's not quite there yet. After all, the 1-8 Colts loom Sunday in Indianapolis. As Parcells wants everyone to know, the Colts are improved from the team the Jets trounced by a 44-6 score earlier this season.</p>
        <p>And he had this to say, too, of his own team: ''We're in the embryonic stages. I know the feeling and they like it. They're attentive. I think the more you win, the more businesslike you can become. You get into a routine. They're interested in what is next.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps no two players are looking to connect more than Testaverde and Johnson. The quarterback is a child of the suburbs, the South Shore of Long Island. The wide receiver is from South Central Los Angeles, where he had a problematic childhood -- at one point he and his mother slept in a car for several nights.</p>
        <p>Since they have hooked up, they have been impressed with the athleticism and attitude of each other. All told, Testaverde winged 9 of his 31 passes toward Johnson on Sunday.</p>
        <p>No wonder when the game was over, Johnson went over to Charlie Weis, the offensive coordinator, and Todd Haley, an assistant coach. He told them what a great game plan they had put together, how fabulous their play-calling was. They liked him, he all but said, they really liked him. ''You both called a perfect game,'' Johnson told them.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen a receiver before -- forget about all his commercials, forget the money -- who just loves to play the game,'' Testaverde said. ''I see that on an every-day basis. He's not afraid to play the game. He's got a passion for it.''</p>
        <p>And Johnson, who loves quarterbacks who throw to him, said of Testaverde: ''If I keep working, trying to get free, he'll find me. The touchdown I had Sunday, I wasn't the first guy on his checklist. I must have had three touchdowns this season where I was down the list, but he found me.''</p>
        <p>As a result, Johnson said, ''Vinny understands the deal.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>After the Jets disposed of the Colts in their first meeting, PEYTON MANNING had the following statistics through the first three games of his N.F.L. career: eight interceptions and three touchdowns. In the five games since, he has tossed 10 touchdowns to 10 interceptions. Manning has thrown at least one touchdown in six straight games. . . . LEON JOHNSON, the big-play back, will return to practice Wednesday after missing a game with a sprained knee. Coach BILL PARCELLS is hopeful Johnson can play next Sunday.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
