<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Petra Foundation Honors 3 New Yorkers for Human Rights Efforts</title>
    <meta content="26PETR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1065083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilmore, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ahmed, Gulnahar</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DD1439F935A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Petra Foundation Honors 3 New Yorkers for Human Rights Efforts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Gilmore, Gulnahar Ahmed and volunteer workers for AIDS Children Teaching Us About Love are honored by Petra Foundation for efforts to improve human rights in their communities (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three New Yorkers have been honored by the Petra Foundation for efforts to improve human rights in their communities.</p>
        <p>This year's Petra Fellows include James Gilmore, a detective in the New York Police Department; Gulnahar Ahmed of Workers' Awaaz, a group that supports immigrants' rights, and the volunteer members of AIDS Children Teaching Us About Love (known as Actual), who are advocates for children and families affected by H.I.V. and AIDS.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three New Yorkers have been honored by the Petra Foundation for efforts to improve human rights in their communities.</p>
        <p>This year's Petra Fellows include James Gilmore, a detective in the New York Police Department; Gulnahar Ahmed of Workers' Awaaz, a group that supports immigrants' rights, and the volunteer members of AIDS Children Teaching Us About Love (known as Actual), who are advocates for children and families affected by H.I.V. and AIDS.</p>
        <p>The Petra Foundation, a nonprofit organization, recognizes and encourages individuals and groups that advance social justice. It was formed in 1988 in memory of Petra Shattuck, a teacher and lawyer who devoted her life to social issues. Each fellow will receive a $7,500 stipend.</p>
        <p>James Gilmore, the son of a police officer, was recognized for challenging racism in the Police Department and for his work in the Sugar Hill neighborhood of Manhattan. In 1997, he was a founder of 100 Blacks in Law Enforcement, a fraternal organization that assists victims of police brutality. On Nov. 5, Mr. Gilmore received the Brooke Russell Astor Award for improving the quality of life in New York City.</p>
        <p>''Officer Gilmore is a remarkable person,'' said John Shattuck, Petra Shattuck's widower, the Ambassador to the Czech Republic and a former assistant secretary of state for human rights. ''He sees the role of police defined by treating people as individuals with hopes and dreams, not just as police action.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shattuck spoke at the awards ceremony here on Saturday. Julian Bond, chairman of the board of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People and a professor of history at the University of Virginia, was the main speaker.</p>
        <p>Gulnahar Ahmed immigrated to  Astoria, Queens, from Bangladesh five years ago and learned English  as a garment worker. She organized demonstrations outside the homes of abusive employers and conducted workshops on labor laws. In 1997, Ms. Ahmed formed Workers' Awaaz, an organization for South Asian domestic workers.</p>
        <p>''Gulnahar Ahmed's determination and crusading spirit has made an enormous difference to the lives of many exploited and vulnerable women who come to the United States in search of freedom and who find it all too elusive,'' said Drew S. Days 3d, a former Solicitor General and a member of the Petra Foundation's board.</p>
        <p>Actual was founded in 1987 by two mothers and a grandmother of H.I.V.-positive children. The group  offers family support at clinics and  provides information about treatment and services in New York City.</p>
        <p>Other new fellows are Susana Almanza, founder of an environmental group in East Austin, Tex., and Frank Bardacke, a community advocate in Watsonville, Calif.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
