<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Second Helpings Of Hollow Cheer</title>
    <meta content="17APRI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/17/movies/17APRI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1527782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hedges, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holmes, Katie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pieces of April (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Holmes, Katie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hedges, Peter</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clarkson, Patricia</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hayes, Sean</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Platt, Oliver</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Pieces of April (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D8173EF934A25753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Second Helpings Of Hollow Cheer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Second Helpings of Hollow Cheer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews movie Pieces of April, directed by Peter Hedges; Katie Holmes stars; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Hedges's intelligent and touching farce, ''Pieces of April,'' makes an important contribution to a small and insignificant subgenre: Thanksgiving Day failure. It does so by raising the bar. ''April'' focuses intently on the neuroses that Thanksgiving Day creates even for the inoffensively punky April Burns (Katie Holmes), who seeks a rapprochement with her family by preparing a holiday meal that looks like a serving-suggestion photo.</p>
        <p>April lives in downtown Manhattan with her boyfriend, Bobby (Derek Luke), a relaxed young hipster who puts the cool in Coolio. When he takes off to perform a few errands to make their first Turkey Day together special, she is left to prepare the meal. This is an occasion her suburban family -- manufacturing hollow cheer that no one really swallows -- needs to cling to as well. They are traveling into the city to dine at April's in what could be the last holiday they share as a group because April's mother is seriously ill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Hedgess intelligent and touching farce makes an important contribution to a small and insignificant subgenre: Thanksgiving Day failure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Peter Hedges's intelligent and touching farce, ''Pieces of April,'' makes an important contribution to a small and insignificant subgenre: Thanksgiving Day failure. It does so by raising the bar. ''April'' focuses intently on the neuroses that Thanksgiving Day creates even for the inoffensively punky April Burns (Katie Holmes), who seeks a rapprochement with her family by preparing a holiday meal that looks like a serving-suggestion photo.</p>
        <p>April lives in downtown Manhattan with her boyfriend, Bobby (Derek Luke), a relaxed young hipster who puts the cool in Coolio. When he takes off to perform a few errands to make their first Turkey Day together special, she is left to prepare the meal. This is an occasion her suburban family -- manufacturing hollow cheer that no one really swallows -- needs to cling to as well. They are traveling into the city to dine at April's in what could be the last holiday they share as a group because April's mother is seriously ill.</p>
        <p>So the emotional well-being of the Burns family is dependent on a brat who is slaving to find her inner decency and barely has the equipment for such an achievement, let alone to serve a meal whose salmonella potential could claim an entire borough.</p>
        <p>Yet it is her surliness, as well as her intransigent determination to make Thanksgiving work, that keeps the laughs coming. When her oven stops working on Thanksgiving morning, April gathers the strength to stave off an extravagant meltdown and find a solution, which comes down to borrowing a neighbor's oven to cook her turkey.</p>
        <p>Her willful naïveté is a great joke that the director doesn't overplay. It is evident that she probably hasn't even opened a can of cranberry sauce by herself before. Anyone ever involved in Thanksgiving Day maneuvers -- when trying to find an open store to buy a crucial stick of butter is like trying to decide whether to cut the red or blue wire on an explosive device -- will get empathetic itchy, sweaty palms just watching April dash around. The comedy of ''April'' is based on the all-American concept of suddenly buying into an ideal that no one thinks about for the other 364 days of the year, and being terrified by the consequences of possible defeat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hedges makes the territorial imperatives that Manhattan inspires an integral element in ''April.'' He escalates the anxiety by treating April's pleas for help from the neighbors in her downtown apartment building as a threat to their small spaces, something that makes each person react distinctively. They emerge like crustaceans forced out of their shells in a Disney cartoon, and April's predicaments heighten the trauma for everyone, like the Asian family that has no idea what she is asking.</p>
        <p>She gets aid from someone she proceeds to offend, and he withdraws his assistance in a way that makes things even more precarious. This overly wound specimen is played by Sean Hayes, more than credibly doing the polar opposite of what he exhibits weekly as the heat-seeking Jack on the television sitcom ''Will &amp; Grace.'' As April encounters each obstacle, her mouth falls into a snarl of disbelief; she would give her unhelpful neighbors a piece of April if she had the time.</p>
        <p>Currents of worry fill the air at her family's home, too. Her father, Jim (Oliver Platt), and siblings Timmy (John Gallagher Jr.) and Beth (Alison Pill) are already worn down by trying to keep their spirits up around April's mother, Joy (Patricia Clarkson), who is ill. Joy has found a breezy serenity to which everyone else seems oblivious, though her temper is still capable of solar flares; we can see where April's stubborn streak comes from.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hedges gently pokes at the dysfunction that increases exponentially during the holidays, when people stop paying attention to one another to live out some fantasy of blissful coexistence, a state that only aggravates their ability to get on one another's nerves.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hedges dances from one vignette to another with a mouthwatering finesse, though the scenes leading up to the finale feel a little forced -- rushed, actually. But they nevertheless manage to convey a desperation that drives everyone to try pathetically to make the best of an awkward situation.</p>
        <p>Each actor shines, even Ms. Holmes, whose beauty seems to have fogged the minds of her previous directors. In ''April,'' which opens today in New York and Los Angeles, she has a defined role and her hyperambition grows out of April's spiteful streak. Realism radiates from the tense relationship between Jim (whom Mr. Platt plays as a man trapped by his unwieldy body) and Joy (whom Ms. Clarkson portrays as a woman impatient over being treated like an invalid).</p>
        <p>The movie also shows the range of Mr. Luke, who contrasts the coarse volatility of his lead role in ''Antwone Fisher'' with a charming, polished ease.</p>
        <p>Bobby undergoes his own trials and comes through them bloody, bowed, but not beaten. Mr. Luke evinces a showtime-smooth accomplishment that indicates he is ready for a romantic-comedy lead.</p>
        <p>Most important, the cinematographer, Tami Reiker, treats digital video as its own form rather than trying to imitate the look of film, an approach that often hobbles moviemakers working in digital video. Among the visual effects achieved is making the gray drabness of the day hang over ''April'' like a potentially life-ending shroud.</p>
        <p>''April'' has the wonderful turn-on-a-dime drollery found in the delivery of ''Come On Home,'' by Everything but the Girl. Like that song, which deals with petit-bourgeois suffering during the holidays, this film is worth a few plays.</p>
        <p>''Pieces of April'' is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has minor silly violence and tantrumy blasts of strong language.</p>
        <p>PIECES OF APRIL</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Peter Hedges; director of photography, Tami Reiker; edited by Mark Livolsi; music by Stephin Merritt; production designer, Rick Butler; produced by John Lyons, Gary Winick and Alexis Alexanian; released by United Artists and IFC Productions. Running time: 81 minutes. This film is rated PG-13.</p>
        <p>WITH: Katie Holmes (April Burns), Patricia Clarkson (Joy Burns), Derek Luke (Bobby), Alison Pill (Beth Burns), John Gallagher Jr. (Timmy Burns), Alice Drummond (Grandma Dottie), Sean Hayes (Wayne) and Oliver Platt (Jim Burns).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
