<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A German Banker on Welfare Among Miami's Palms</title>
    <meta content="Y17GER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/17/international/europe/17GERM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1527830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">John, Rolf</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schroder, Gerhard (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5DD143EF934A25753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A German Banker on Welfare Among Miami's Palms</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A German Banker on Welfare Among Miamis Palms</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stories of German welfare recipients who own yachts and luxury cars are staple of country's news media, but recent articles on Rolf John, former banker whose welfare benefits pay for his apartment in Miami, Fla, as well as his housekeeper, may help Chancellor Gerhard Schroder in his effort to reform country's welfare system; system can make being unemployed more lucrative than working; Germany has only loosely regulated welfare benefits it extends to citizens living abroad; John gets $2,200 a month, and when German authorities tried to cut back his housing allowance his lawyer persuaded judge to overrule such action; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe it is the image of a former banker, deeply tanned and dipping his toes in the surf on a Miami beach, while people here trudge windswept streets in dismal burgs. Or maybe it is the notion of a housekeeper, paid for by the German government, to keep the fellow's apartment tidy.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, the curious case of Rolf John, 64, living in Miami on $2,200 a month in German welfare checks, has driven people here batty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The case of Rolf John, living in Miami on German welfare checks, has driven people batty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe it is the image of a former banker, deeply tanned and dipping his toes in the surf on a Miami beach, while people here trudge windswept streets in dismal burgs. Or maybe it is the notion of a housekeeper, paid for by the German government, to keep the fellow's apartment tidy.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, the curious case of Rolf John, 64, living in Miami on $2,200 a month in German welfare checks, has driven people here batty.</p>
        <p>''He's laughing at all of us,'' declared Bild, the mass circulation tabloid that broke the story of the man it nicknamed ''Florida Rolf.'' Chancellor Gerhard Schröder has condemned the case as ''a really horrible example of welfare abuse.''</p>
        <p>When the German Parliament votes Friday on a sweeping package of tax cuts and welfare reforms, it is not a stretch to say it will be responding, at least in part, to the anger aroused by people like ''Florida Rolf.''</p>
        <p>While his case is extreme -- and the German Health and Social Security Ministry has since said it will stop paying his benefits if he stays abroad -- it is not unusual. Stories of welfare recipients who own yachts and luxury cars are a staple of the German news media.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schröder is expected to win Friday's vote after trying for months to persuade left-wing members of his coalition that Germany must finally take a scalpel to its welfare system, which can make being unemployed more lucrative than working.</p>
        <p>As a symbol of the excesses, Mr. John played a role in spurring the debate.</p>
        <p>''It's the perfect case for everybody to get upset about,'' said Josef Joffe, the editor of the weekly Die Zeit. ''In a welfare state that was not collapsing under its load, you would just accept it and move on to the next case file. But we're living in another world in Germany today.''</p>
        <p>Mr. John is from the northern city of Osnabrück, but he has not lived there since 1979. When reached by telephone in Florida on Thursday, he sounded simply fed up with all the attention.</p>
        <p>''They've written a lot of lies about me,'' he said. ''I live a very simple life. I have a normal, one-bedroom, American-style apartment. When I moved here in the late 1980's, the rent was $450 a month.''</p>
        <p>Mr. John's apartment does not, according to German reporters who have visited it, command ocean views. But as a reporter for The New York Times found when trying to visit on Thursday, it is in a middle-class, gated complex with private security guards and located just 200 yards from the beach.</p>
        <p>Mr. John said he decided to move to Miami after his marriage fell apart in Germany in the late 1970's. He said he worked for a few years as a banker in Florida, but lost all his money because of onerous divorce payments and the failed business venture of a close relative.</p>
        <p>Later, he said, he became ill with diabetes and pancreatitis. After being turned away by a welfare agency in the United States, he filed for welfare benefits from the German government.</p>
        <p>Germany has only loosely regulated the welfare benefits it extends to German citizens abroad. Mr. John's package includes $1,023 a month for rent, an $854 living allowance and $170 to pay for a housekeeper, since Mr. John is considered disabled.</p>
        <p>When German authorities tried to cut back his housing allowance to $702, Mr. John's lawyer persuaded a court in Lower Saxony that he would fall into a depression if he were forced to leave his apartment and circle of friends in North Miami.</p>
        <p>Mr. John is similarly unmoved by outrage over the housekeeper. ''I have a cleaning woman, sure,'' he said. ''But I'm 90 percent disabled.'' Mr. John said he needs the housekeeper to clean his apartment, do his laundry and drive him to doctors' appointments, and he referred further questions to lawyers in Frankfurt and Miami, neither of whom would discuss the case.</p>
        <p>After Mr. John's case was publicized, the Health and Social Security Ministry researched other cases of Germans living abroad on welfare. They discovered that 1,055 people in more than 80 countries are claiming benefits at an annual cost to Germany of roughly $6.4 million.</p>
        <p>In September, Ulla Schmidt, Germany's health and social security minister, said the government would tighten the regulations allowing welfare benefits to German expatriates. Under the new rules, the only people to receive benefits will be Germans who are receiving long-term medical treatment outside the country or who are in foreign jails.</p>
        <p>''There won't be any more welfare under palm trees,'' Ms. Schmidt told German reporters in a comment that made widespread headlines in following days.</p>
        <p>Mr. John said he had written a letter of protest to Chancellor Schröder. In the meantime, he said he has no intention of pulling up stakes from Miami.</p>
        <p>''I've lived here for 25 years,'' Mr. John said in softly-accented English. ''I have a lot of friends here. My homeland is the United States.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
