<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Details His State Bill For Takeover Of City Airports</title>
    <meta content="22AIRP$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="952183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">La Guardia Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kennedy International Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Port Authority of NY and NJ</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onishi, Norimitsu</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DA123EF931A1575BC0A961958260" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Details His State Bill For Takeover Of City Airports</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Onishi, Norimitsu</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani, stepping up his campaign against Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, unveils state bill to take control of La Guardia and Kennedy Airports away from agency and give it to city; says bill, which would need to be sponsored in Albany, would allow city and state to acquire airports by condemning properties, buying up outstanding bonds and issuing new ones; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stepping up his campaign against the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani unveiled a state bill yesterday to take control of La Guardia and Kennedy Airports away from the agency and give it to the city.</p>
        <p>In his most detailed plan so far on the issue, Mr. Giuliani, who has long maintained that the Port Authority shortchanges the city in favor of New Jersey, said the bill would allow the city and state to acquire the airports by condemning the properties, buying up outstanding bonds and issuing new ones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stepping up his campaign against the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani unveiled a state bill yesterday to take control of La Guardia and Kennedy Airports away from the agency and give it to the city.</p>
        <p>In his most detailed plan so far on the issue, Mr. Giuliani, who has long maintained that the Port Authority shortchanges the city in favor of New Jersey, said the bill would allow the city and state to acquire the airports by condemning the properties, buying up outstanding bonds and issuing new ones.</p>
        <p>But the Mayor's bill, which would need to be sponsored in Albany, received a tepid response from the office of Gov. George E. Pataki, who under the plan would essentially relinquish his control over the airports and hand it to the Mayor, and from Gov. Christine Todd Whitman's top appointee on the Port Authority's board of commissioners.</p>
        <p>Under the proposal, announced yesterday at a meeting of the Kennedy International Airport Chamber of Commerce, the Mayor would appoint the seven members of the new agency that would operate the two airports. Now, the governors of New York and New Jersey appoint 6 commissioners each to the 12-member Port Authority.</p>
        <p>''The Port Authority was created by both states, both houses of the Legislature,'' said Zenia Mucha, Mr. Pataki's spokeswoman. ''It might take an act of Congress to do this. It's not a simple gesture. You can't just eradicate the Port Authority or its statutory obligations.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Giuliani said he would not renegotiate the airports' leases,  which expire in 2015. The city owns the land under both airports in Queens, and the authority has operated them under a series of leases since 1947.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the disagreement is the rent paid to the city, which is set as a portion of the airports' annual revenue, with deductions for operations and maintenance costs. The rents averaged $80 million in the late 1980's, but they fell as low as $3 million in 1993 because of capital improvements to both airports, authority officials said. In recent years, they have gradually risen, to $42 million last year.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Giuliani repeated complaints that the airports were used to subsidize money-losing parts of the authority's operations, like the PATH train system, which largely benefits New Jersey residents.</p>
        <p>''This is an issue that I think if I got out front and explain it to people, we will create the political climate in which we can make this happen,'' the Mayor said. ''But somebody's got to go out there and do it, and it seems to me the best person to do it is the Mayor of New York City.''</p>
        <p>Mark Hatfield, the Port Authority's director of communications, described Mr. Giuliani's plan as political posturing in an election season. ''This is unfortunately campaign strategists trying to carve public policy,'' Mr. Hatfield said.</p>
        <p>New York officials have also complained that although the Port Authority has let Kennedy and La Guardia deteriorate, it has refurbished Newark International Airport, which will be linked to the area's train routes by a light rail system.</p>
        <p>Lewis M. Eisenberg, who was appointed chairman of the authority's board of commissioners by Governor Whitman of New Jersey, said the authority's investments have historically run in cycles. He added that it was now New York's turn to receive major investments, including $3 billion at Kennedy.</p>
        <p>''We have said publicly that we'd like to sit down and renegotiate the leases,'' Mr. Eisenberg said. ''I happen to agree with the Mayor that some of the old leases could be updated to pay the city more money.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
