<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Young Conductor Accepts An Eclectic Assignment</title>
    <meta content="13MAAZEL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/13/arts/13maazel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1641654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CLASSICAL MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Turnage, Mark Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maazel, Lorin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zhang, Xian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Maazel, Lorin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Strauss, Richard</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Turnage, Mark-Anthony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Britten, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Antheil, George</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stravinsky, Igor</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Myers, Philip</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Szell, George</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DA1738F930A25752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Young Conductor Accepts An Eclectic Assignment</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Young Conductor Accepts an Eclectic Assignment</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allan Kozinn reviews New York Philharmonic program that includes world premiere of Scherzoid by British composer Mark Anthony Turnage; Lorin Maazel and Xian Zhang conduct; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lorin Maazel had a comparatively easy job last night in the first of this week's New York Philharmonic subscription programs. On the first half of the program, he led Mozart's Symphony No. 29 and the Horn Concerto No. 1 by Richard Strauss. He then ceded the podium to Xian Zhang, an assistant conductor at the Philharmonic since 2002, when she won first prize in the Maazel/Vilar Conductors' Competition. Ms. Zhang's task was more rigorous: she led the world premiere of ''Scherzoid,'' a vigorous work by the British composer Mark-Anthony Turnage, and closed the concert with Benjamin Britten's evocative ''Four Sea Interludes.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Zhang, who was born and trained in China but has lived in the United States since 1998, has led the Philharmonic in Young People's Concerts, but this was her first subscription concert. It was certainly a trial by fire: Mr. Turnage's work is, as its title suggests, essentially an extended scherzo, but with a decidedly split personality. Much of it is based on an insistent rhythmic underpinning that demands a steady level of energy, even as its tension level ebbs and flows. At times, it blossoms into passages of mechanistic writing in the style of the American composer George Antheil, or bursts of syncopation that call early Stravinsky to mind. But there are jazz turns here, too, including brass vamps that require a good measure of suppleness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lorin Maazel had a comparatively easy job in the first of this week's New York Philharmonic subscription programs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lorin Maazel had a comparatively easy job last night in the first of this week's New York Philharmonic subscription programs. On the first half of the program, he led Mozart's Symphony No. 29 and the Horn Concerto No. 1 by Richard Strauss. He then ceded the podium to Xian Zhang, an assistant conductor at the Philharmonic since 2002, when she won first prize in the Maazel/Vilar Conductors' Competition. Ms. Zhang's task was more rigorous: she led the world premiere of ''Scherzoid,'' a vigorous work by the British composer Mark-Anthony Turnage, and closed the concert with Benjamin Britten's evocative ''Four Sea Interludes.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Zhang, who was born and trained in China but has lived in the United States since 1998, has led the Philharmonic in Young People's Concerts, but this was her first subscription concert. It was certainly a trial by fire: Mr. Turnage's work is, as its title suggests, essentially an extended scherzo, but with a decidedly split personality. Much of it is based on an insistent rhythmic underpinning that demands a steady level of energy, even as its tension level ebbs and flows. At times, it blossoms into passages of mechanistic writing in the style of the American composer George Antheil, or bursts of syncopation that call early Stravinsky to mind. But there are jazz turns here, too, including brass vamps that require a good measure of suppleness.</p>
        <p>Apparently these changes were more frequent and more radical in the work's original form. Mr. Turnage wrote in his program note that he toned down the work after a Philharmonic trial reading last year. But the shifts are still plentiful enough to justify the score's title, not to mention Mr. Turnage's reputation for adventurous eclecticism.</p>
        <p>The Britten gave Ms. Zhang an opportunity to show what she can do in more conventional music, and she made the most of it, giving the string figures in the opening ''Dawn'' interlude an appealing spaciousness, drawing out the dynamic swells in ''Moonlight'' and leading a powerful rendering of the closing ''Storm.'' Ms. Zhang's conducting gestures were grand and sweeping in the Britten and kinetic in the Turnage, but a listener never had the feeling that she was engaging in showmanship for its own sake.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maazel's account of the Mozart suggested that he may have missed his calling by building his career on the big Romantic works. It was not a scholarly, period-instrument-style Mozart, by any means, but a performance packed with illuminating touches. One was the briefest hint of a pause before the exposition repeat in the opening Allegro moderato. Another was Mr. Maazel's emphasis of a more typically submerged viola response to the main violin line, later in the same movement. Throughout the performance, the string articulation was crisp and the textures were fully transparent.</p>
        <p>Mozart was 18 when he completed this symphony. Strauss was the same age when he wrote the Horn Concerto No. 1 (Op. 11). It isn't performed often, partly because Strauss's eventual accomplishments so clearly show it up as juvenilia, but also because its solo line is full of sudden leaps, flowing chromatic lines and fast passage work, all perilous moves for a hornist. Philip Myers, the Philharmonic's principal hornist, was in exceptionally good form. He played the exposed horn line with power, assurance and at times a lovely poetic lilt that made an eloquent case for the work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maazel and the orchestra contributed vividly as well. Some conductors -- George Szell, for example -- presented this piece as a work of restrained Neo-Classicism. Mr. Maazel pulled out all the stops, showing it as a broad-boned, fully Romantic score.</p>
        <p>The program repeats tonight at 7:30, Saturday night at 8 and Tuesday night at 7:30.</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
