<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="30CLAS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/30/arts/music/30CLAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1419612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DE143FF933A0575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="2577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Classical Music and Dance Listings</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC. With its view of the Manhattan skyline and its live, intimate acoustics, this barge floating on the East River is one of the finest places in the city to hear chamber music. Tonight Carmit Zori, a violinist, and Randall Hodgkinson, a pianist, play sonatas of Handel, Mozart and Beethoven and the Sonatina by Dvorak. Tomorrow and Sunday Ms. Zori and Mr. Hodgkinson are joined by Robert Rinehart, a violist, in a program of works by Bach, Mozart, Gershwin and Milhaud. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30; Sunday at 4 p.m. Fulton Ferry Landing, under the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083. Tickets: $35; $20 for students (James R. Oestreich).</p>
        <p>BEETHOVEN FESTIVAL. With relatively little competition for music festivals at this time of year, here is a fast-paced one on Long Island that competes with itself. Presented by Friends of the Arts, programs -- single works -- take place continuously from noon to 4 p.m. in Coe Hall and the Hay Barn in. But the festival finale stands alone at 4:25 p.m. in the Hay Barn, a substantial program featuring a new Beethoven ''symphony.'' Beethoven orchestrated one movement of his ''Funeral March'' Piano Sonata, and Dalit Warshaw, a pianist and composer, has orchestrated the three other movements, to form a symphonic work. Richard Owen conducts the Camerata New York in that oddity and in the ''Emperor'' Piano Concerto, with Agustin Anievas as soloist. Sunday from 12 to 6 p.m., Planting Fields Arboretum, Planting Fields Road, Oyster Bay, N.Y., (516) 922-0061. Tickets: $35, covering all events (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>MAVERICK CONCERTS. This enterprising series, founded by the novelist and poet Hervey White in 1916, offers its concerts in an open-sided barn where the sounds of nature and music interact. Its summer series ends this week with two appealing programs. Tomorrow night, Parthenia, a superb period-instrument ensemble, offers a program devoted mostly to what it normally does, with works by Pilkington, Byrd, Morley and Scheidt as familiar landmarks. The program also includes a selection of recent works by Brian Fennelly, including ''Variations on Watkins Ale,'' and ''Tombeau and Tango,'' composed in memory of Vincent Wagner, Maverick's longtime artistic director, who died in March. The Sunday afternoon performance is a benefit for Friends of Maverick, which helps support the annual series. The performers are Brian Zeger, pianist, and Serena Benedetti, soprano. The program offers keyboard works by Bach, Beethoven, Chopin and Cabrier, as well as Strauss songs. Tomorrow evening at 8; Sunday at 3 p.m. Maverick Road between Routes 28 and 375, West Hurley, N.Y., just outside Woodstock. (845) 679-8217. Tickets: $15, $5 for students tomorrow; a minimum contribution of $50 on Sunday. (Allan Kozinn).</p>
        <p>MUSIC MOUNTAIN. A high-powered constellation of performers gathers for the final concerts of the season for this Connecticut festival, which, founded in 1930 and run by volunteers, bills itself as the oldest active chamber music festival in the United States. This weekend the fine Shanghai Quartet joins the pianist Ruth Laredo in two programs that center on early Beethoven and Mozart, with an admixture of Shostakovich (the third quartet) and César Franck (the piano quintet in F minor). The quartet will play two of Beethoven's Op. 18 quartets, No. 3 and No. 6, on consecutive days, and follow the No. 3 with the same composer's Op. 16 piano quartet. Tomorrow night at 8; Sunday afternoon at 3. Sunday's concert will be preceded by a ''Canine Quadrille,'' a dance for dogs and their owners at 2 p.m. Gordon Hall, Music Mountain, Falls Village, Conn., (860) 824-7126. Tickets: $20; $10 for students (Anne Midgette).</p>
        <p>SKANEATELES FESTIVAL. There's not much classical music happening upstate this weekend, and even this, one of the latest-running summer festivals, is closing up shop. But it is doing so with a grand finale, featuring the superb violinist Hilary Hahn in both programs. Tonight the pianist Diane Walsh, the festival's artistic director, joins Ms. Hahn and others in chamber works by Strauss, Bloch, Poulenc and Robert Weirich. Tomorrow Ms. Hahn joins the festival orchestra in Bach's Violin Concerto in E. The program also includes Mendelssohn's ''Hebrides,'' Schubert's Symphony No. 3 and Fauré's Pavane. Tonight at 8, First Presbyterian Church, East Genesee Street; tomorrow night at 8, Brook Farm, Route 41A, south of Skaneateles, N.Y., (315) 685-7418. Tickets: tonight, $14 and $18, $12 and $15 for students and 60+; tomorrow, $15 and $20; free to children under 13 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>SOUTH MOUNTAIN CONCERTS. This chamber music series in the Berkshires was founded by Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge in 1918 and is presented in a 440-seat hall that she built for the purpose. Its 84th season opens on Sunday with a performance by the Kalichstein-Laredo-Robinson Trio playing a program that includes Mozart's Piano Trio in B flat (K. 502), Mendelssohn's Piano Trio in C minor (Op. 66) and a recent work by Richard Danielpour, ''A Child's Reliquary.'' Sunday at 3 p.m. South Mountain Concert Hall, Routes 7 and 20, two miles south of Pittsfield, Mass. (413) 442-2106. Tickets: $28 (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>EVA DEAN. A rubber-ball orchestra, a mini-punch ball opera, orbiting planets, and large and small balls under and over the feet will all figure in ''Oh Balls,'' a new piece by Eva Dean. Tomorrow and Sunday at 8:30 p.m. Here Arts Center, 145 Avenue of the Americas, at Dominick Street, SoHo, (212) 647-0202. Tickets: $15 (Jennifer Dunning).</p>
        <p>EVENING STARS. For three years, this free-wheeling dance and music festival was staged in the dramatic setting of the World Trade Center Plaza, with the two towers rising beyond. The festival's indomitable director, Liz Thompson, will reopen the free Evening Stars series this weekend with two programs in two new spaces. The Noh Drama Theater of Japan will perform in honor of New Yorkers and of 11 Japanese citizens who died on Sept. 11. Tomorrow night and Sunday night at 7. Schimmel Center, Pace University, Spruce Street between Park Row and Gold Street, south of City Hall, Lower Manhattan. The Merce Cunningham Dance Company will present an outdoor event, a collage of dances and excerpts. Sunday night at 7. Battery Park, Lower Manhattan, (212) 219-9401; www.rivertorivernyc.org (Dunning).</p>
        <p>REDWALL DANCE THEATER. In a program that focuses on the unpredictability of women, Mary Ann Wells, from Florida, will present dances set to music by the Tin Hat Trio, a suite of tunes sung by Patsy Cline, Tammy Wynette and Nancy Sinatra, a harp score composed and performed live by Katie Brennan. Zenobia Taylor, from Texas, will present dances that include ''Bowl of Cherries,'' set to bluegrass music, in which a preacher, a child and an overtly proper woman find themselves breaking the rules. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8. Chashama Theater, 135 West 42nd Street, Times Square, (212) 696-7892;www.chashama.org. Tickets: $10 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>PILAR RIOJA. Long one of New York's favorite flamenco dancers, the understated Ms. Rioja is back for the summer with a program featuring many classics of her repertory, through Sunday. Tonight at 8; tomorrow night at 8; Sunday afternoon at 3. Gramercy Arts Theater, 138 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 889-2850. Tickets: $25 to $40 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>TRAFFIC JAM: TAP JAM. Tap dancers, trapeze artists and jazz musicians will perform in a free program, put together by Laraine Goodman, on an eight-foot-high outdoor stage at the entrance to the Holland Tunnel. Bring your tap shoes (and gas masks) for a jam in which all dancers are welcome. Tonight from 6 to 10, at the Hub, 517 Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 475-0588 (Dunning).</p>
        <p>21ST ANNUAL DOWNTOWN DANCE FESTIVAL: CHINESE FOLK DANCE COMPANY. Take your salami sandwich to this free lunchtime program of folk dance. Today from 12:15 to 1:30 p.m. Chase Plaza, Nassau and Liberty Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 219-3910 (Dunning).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
