<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Capriati Comes Up Big Against a Sizable Foe</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="456858"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TENNIS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WIMBLEDON TENNIS CHAMPIONSHIP</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAPRIATI, JENNIFER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHULTZ, BRENDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DC1739F931A35754C0A967958260" item-length="518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Capriati Comes Up Big Against a Sizable Foe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England, July 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Women's Tennis Association guidebook says Brenda Schultz stands 6 feet 2 inches and weighs 170 pounds, which could be an understatement. The guidebook also says Schultz's serve has been clocked at 120 miles per hour, which sounds about right.</p>
        <p>Schultz was firing them high and hard today, but Jennifer Capriati showed uncommon wisdom for a 15-year-old, and hung in until the smoke subsided.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Women's Tennis Association guidebook says Brenda Schultz stands 6 feet 2 inches and weighs 170 pounds, which could be an understatement. The guidebook also says Schultz's serve has been clocked at 120 miles per hour, which sounds about right.</p>
        <p>Schultz was firing them high and hard today, but Jennifer Capriati showed uncommon wisdom for a 15-year-old, and hung in until the smoke subsided.</p>
        <p>Then Capriati came back for a 3-6, 6-1, 6-1 victory to bring her to the quarterfinals at Wimbledon, one step further than in her first season, when she lost to Steffi Graf, 6-2, 6-4, in the round of 16.</p>
        <p>Capriati must now play Martina Navratilova, whom she has labeled a "lege," as in legend, in the quarterfinals Tuesday. But just advancing to the quarterfinals is a positive step for Capriati. Sophomore Slump</p>
        <p>Last year, the most heralded 14-year-old in American sports won 42 matches and lost 11, winning her first tournament in Puerto Rico. This year, Capriati has won 19 matches and lost in all seven tournaments up to now without reaching a final.</p>
        <p>"The sophomore year is often harder than the freshman year," said Tom Gullikson, Capriati's coach. "You have to defend your position. People have watched you. Jennifer is still young. She's a big scalp."</p>
        <p>Tall and blonde and muttering in Dutch with an occasional "come on," Schultz was not necessarily looking for Capriati's millionaire scalp. She just hits hard, first and second serve.</p>
        <p>"There are a lot of men on the tour who'd like to serve like her," Gullikson said.</p>
        <p>For one set, Schultz backed up her serves with some nimble drop shots and volleys. But Capriati began moving around, even edging a few steps into the court for second serve, daring Schultz to knock her down. Schultz wound up with 11 double-faults and won only 28 percent of her second serves. 'It Was a Very Big Serve'</p>
        <p>"It was a very big serve," Capriati said. "It just takes a while to get used to it. I started returning better."</p>
        <p>Capriati admitted that "people are expecting more of you" this year, but she added: "I'm not frustrated. I have plenty of time ahead of me."</p>
        <p>She and Navratilova have met once before, at Hilton Head, S.C., a year ago, when Capriati made her now-famous statement about Navratilova being a "lege," before she lost, 6-2, 6-4, in the final of the Family Circle tournament.</p>
        <p>"I guess she's the queen here," Capriati said today. "I still have a lot of respect for her, but I'm not going to think about who she is. She's a lefty, but I don't think she'll serve as hard as Brenda."</p>
        <p>Capriati's coach, who is the left-handed member of the Gullikson twins, said he would have preferred a day off, so he could hit with his pupil. But he added, "She's been hitting against me for a year and a half."</p>
        <p>Gullikson recalled how, as a player, he had often been in demand as a hitting partner when somebody had a match with a left-hander coming up.</p>
        <p>For her part, the "lege" was going to slip over to Capriati's doubles match late this afternoon, "to see how she's hitting." Capriati's reaction to that news was a rather impressed "She is?"  TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
