<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Children</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="548431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEACHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEIMBACH, DULCIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DF153EF934A3575BC0A964958260" item-length="3232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dulcie Leimbach</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEIMBACH, DULCIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Very little can stop serious beachgoers. Bad weather and poor cash flow may keep some home, but never for long. You can tell them by the way they rattle off the names of every Jersey Shore town by heart (along with the parking rates in each town). They can describe the color and texture of sand with a geologist's expertise. To avoid traffic, they rise at dawn and get to the beach early, leaving at midday or staying late, past the time everyone else has left. They love to feel the water lap up against their skin, to luxuriate in the soft embrace of the sand, to keep up their tans, dangerously.</p>
        <p>Alex Johnson is a beachgoer on the weekend and a general contractor during the week. He grew up in Kentucky, but discovered the virtues of the beach when he was in college and found Virginia Beach, on the Virginia coast. He and his family live on the South Shore of Long Island, and visit nearby beaches regularly. In his opinion, a good family beach has concessions with lots of ice cream and other summery snacks, a playground and "medium-fine sand that's not too coarse and can hold the water well," for castle building. He says he is partial to Lido Beach on the South Shore, where he spends hours on the sand creating "low-lying buildings, like pyramids," while his children hop on boogie boards and let the waves toss them around.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Very little can stop serious beachgoers. Bad weather and poor cash flow may keep some home, but never for long. You can tell them by the way they rattle off the names of every Jersey Shore town by heart (along with the parking rates in each town). They can describe the color and texture of sand with a geologist's expertise. To avoid traffic, they rise at dawn and get to the beach early, leaving at midday or staying late, past the time everyone else has left. They love to feel the water lap up against their skin, to luxuriate in the soft embrace of the sand, to keep up their tans, dangerously.</p>
        <p>Alex Johnson is a beachgoer on the weekend and a general contractor during the week. He grew up in Kentucky, but discovered the virtues of the beach when he was in college and found Virginia Beach, on the Virginia coast. He and his family live on the South Shore of Long Island, and visit nearby beaches regularly. In his opinion, a good family beach has concessions with lots of ice cream and other summery snacks, a playground and "medium-fine sand that's not too coarse and can hold the water well," for castle building. He says he is partial to Lido Beach on the South Shore, where he spends hours on the sand creating "low-lying buildings, like pyramids," while his children hop on boogie boards and let the waves toss them around.</p>
        <p>Here is an assessment of five beaches, in and around New York City, that meet at least one of Mr. Johnson's criteria:  Manhattan Beach</p>
        <p>Oriental Boulevard, Manhattan</p>
        <p>Beach, Brooklyn, (718) 946-1373.</p>
        <p>THE BEACH: Manhattan Beach is crescent-shaped, defined by jetties on either side. People tend to flock to the eastern end of the cove to swim, so the shoreline can seem as jammed as the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway at rush hour. On days when the tar on the streets turns to goo, Manhattan Beach is crowded. There is a large contingent of Eastern Europeans re-creating the aura of a Black Sea resort. Some men wear thong bathing suits; the zaftig women wear matronly one-pieces. The beach, which is run by the New York City Department of Parks and Recreation, also has a high quotient of serious tanners, who probably don't worry about melanoma. In addition to the residents of Manhattan Beach, which is a pastoral suburban enclave, Russians and other Eastern Europeans seem predominant, while Hispanic and Caribbean visitors, their accents as lulling as the sea itself, stake out picnic tables under the trees and set up their hibachis. Children and older people are in the majority here, though teen-agers were sighted. The grace is in the water, of course, which keeps everyone cool.</p>
        <p>THE WATER: Pretty clean. It's part of Jamaica Bay and protected by the Rockaway peninsula, making waves gentle, just right for toddlers. Even the temperature seems balmy.</p>
        <p>THE SAND: Clean, beige and not too deep (the beach was man-made).</p>
        <p>THE FOOD: There are several concession stands and some small carts, keeping lines short. At the main concession area, you first buy tickets at one window and then give your ticket to the counter worker for your food. There are knishes, sodas, beer, ice cream, Sabrett hot dogs, pizza, french fries, burgers.</p>
        <p>THE EXTRAS: A concession also rents beach chairs and umbrellas ($3 a day, $10 deposit) and sells suntan lotion, pails and shovels. A baseball field is adjacent to the beach, as are basketball and handball courts and a playground. Picnic tables and benches are stationed under a grove of trees. Radios are banned, but that doesn't mean people don't play them. New York City police officers patrol the park and the beach.</p>
        <p>THE RESTROOMS: On the sandy side, but not seriously. There are two outside showers.</p>
        <p>THE PARKING: In a spirit of exclusivity, no parking is allowed on side streets near the beach on Saturdays and Sundays from May 15 to Sept. 15; during the week there is alternate-side parking. But there is also an enclosed parking lot at the beach, which charges $5 a car ($8 for trucks and buses; $10 on weekends). On really hot weekends, the wait for a space can be about a half-hour. On weekdays, the lot is open from 8 A.M. to 8 P.M.; on weekends, it is open from 7 A.M. to 8 P.M.</p>
        <p>THE HOURS: 10 A.M. to 7 P.M. (while lifeguards are on duty).</p>
        <p>HOW TO GET THERE: By subway, take the D or Q trains to the Sheepshead Bay station. Then walk along Sheepshead Bay Road as it angles toward Ocean Avenue (the El Greco diner, under construction, is a destination point), then cross the Ocean Avenue Bridge, which takes you to Shore Boulevard. Any parallel street (Falmouth Street, for example) will take you right to Oriental Boulevard and the beach, a half-hour walk altogether. The No. 49 bus, which stops at the Sheepshead station, goes to the beach. Cabs will also take you there, for about $3.50.</p>
        <p>Great Kills Park</p>
        <p>Staten Island Unit of Gateway National Recreation Area, Great Kills Park, Hylan Boulevard, Great Kills Harbor, S.I., (718) 351-8700.</p>
        <p>THE BEACH: Great Kills is a 900-acre national park, built on landfill, with dunes, a milelong beach, baseball fields, a model-airplane field, a nature area and a busy marina. The park, which became part of the National Park Service system in 1972, was conceived in 1928, when the state gave a strip of wetlands to New York City. The strip included Crookes Point, now a wildlife habitat with trails and fishing sites. The beach is divided in two; only Beach No. 2 has lifeguards. The one without them seems to attract teen-agers who have no interest in swimming. At Beach No. 2, families and people extremely concerned about tanning gather for the day with coolers full of food, umbrellas and beach chairs, as if they are about to camp for weeks. The beach is idyllically remote from the rest of Staten Island, surrounded by beautiful sand dunes and tall grass. (The landscape recalls another remote beach, Plum Island, north of Boston.) The vista, however, reminds visitors that they're not far from the city: looking north one sees the top of the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge.</p>
        <p>THE WATER : The foam on the waves at the shore was brownish because the sand on the beach is claylike. Manny Strumpf, Gateway's spokesman, said the water had never been cleaner. "We test all Gateway waters three times a week," he said. "This year the water's been very clean. It hasn't been closed yet this summer." The water is sheltered from the Atlantic by Crookes Point; you're essentially swimming in the confluence of New York Harbor and Raritan Bay. Indeed, the waves were really no more than ripples. Toddlers are eager to wade in, though along the shore the sand is so soft, one's feet sink unnaturally.</p>
        <p>THE SAND : In 1949, the beach was filled with local sand, which was brownish-red and claylike, making it uncharacteristically dark. On a recent visit, cigarette butts and pebbles were scattered throughout, although the beach had just been raked by a mechanical sweeper.</p>
        <p>THE FOOD : There are two concessions, one at each beach, hiding inside two brown cinder-block buildings that are so ugly you can lose your appetite. Tiny bits of broken glass (why can't they sweep that up?) are also around the concessions, so wear shoes. The food is cheap, compared with other beach concessions, and it's the usual fare: hot dogs ($1.25); hamburgers ($1.40); sodas (85 cents), and french fries ($1.25). Umbrellas are rented for $3 a day (with a $10 deposit).</p>
        <p>THE EXTRAS : If your children have forgotten their beach toys and don't want to swim, you can stroll through Crookes Point, where it's quiet and a breeze blows. Or you can check out all the cabin cruisers and speedboats at the marina. People fish at the designated areas.</p>
        <p>THE PARKING : Beaches No. 1 and 2 offer plenty of parking, though the latter fills up first on the weekends, so you may have a five-minute walk as opposed to a two-minute walk.</p>
        <p>THE HOURS : Daily, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M. (when lifeguards are present).</p>
        <p>HOW TO GET THERE : Driving is best. The beach is off Hylan Boulevard, one of the main roads in the borough (the Hylan Boulevard exit is right after the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge toll booths). Take Hylan to Buffalo Street, where the entrance to Gateway is clearly marked.</p>
        <p>Oakland Beach</p>
        <p>Rye Town Park, Dearborn Avenue, Rye, N.Y., (914) 967-0965.</p>
        <p>THE BEACH : This town beach, a neighbor to the Playland amusement park, acts as if it's a country club. It manages to be exclusive by charging nonresidents $5 a car to park, and $5 a person (nonresidents) to go on the beach (infants free). (Residents pay $25 for a seasonal permit; families pay $35.) For families eager for a day at this lovely beach, the price can be worth it, but it can also make visits rare. Indeed, the whole setting, including the white stucco beach buildings with red tile roofs, is so bucolic and pretty, you may wonder if you've ended up in California. Oakland Beach, which opened in 1907, belongs to the town of Rye. Who comes here? Mostly Rye and other Westchester County residents. The two covelike beaches are defined by jetties and a large rock outcropping. At both, teen-agers and college students off for the summer idly spend the day, as do mothers with toddlers and infants.</p>
        <p>THE WATER : Delightful, given Long Island Sound's somewhat tarnished reputation. The water along the shore was so warm that one young boy, dreading the beach, announced, "I like it here!" The water is also virtually waveless, so much so that you could fall asleep in it. (One beach veteran, her tan as dark as molasses, was on a beach chair in the water.) The shore is littered with clam and mussel shells and seaweed, but this is the Sound, after all.</p>
        <p>THE SAND : Grainy, very white; clean. Adequate for castle-building along the shore (though on the muddy side).</p>
        <p>THE FOOD : The Sand Bar attracts beachgoers as well as men and women on their lunch hours with a yen for a beachside meal. On Sunday nights, from 6 to 10 o'clock, there is karaoke. Service was ponderously slow the day we visited. The menu offers hot dogs, hamburgers, sodas, chips, beer, Evian water, frozen candy and fancier fare like a shrimp platter ($8.50).  The prices are higher than at most beach concessions (the sandwiches started at $3.50). Sand toys are for sale and umbrellas can be rented ($5 a day; $20 deposit).</p>
        <p>THE EXTRAS : The beach is on the grounds of a town park, and is surrounded by a manicured sloping lawn with a pond and weeping willows. A garden of roses of Sharon and hollyhocks brightens up the parking lot.  Playland's Ferris wheel can be seen from the beach, so if you want to go, it's not far away; if you don't, you can hope that your children don't spot it. A volleyball net is also set up on the beach; some young and restless types were playing the day we visited.</p>
        <p>THE RESTROOMS : Large, clean, orderly. Outdoor showers are nearby.</p>
        <p>THE PARKING : The lot fills up on weekends, but there are always spaces, the parking lot attendant promised. Nonresidents pay $5 a day. Residents with permits pay $1.50 on weekdays and $2.50 on weekends.</p>
        <p>THE HOURS : Daily, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M. (when lifeguards are there).</p>
        <p>HOW TO GET THERE : If driving, take Interstate 95 north to Exit 19, then follow the signs on Playland Parkway to Playland, until you reach Forest Avenue, where you turn right. Then turn left on Dearborn Avenue, to the park's entrance. The New Haven Line of Metro-North stops at Rye, where you can hop on the No. 76 Bee Line bus to Playland, from which Rye Town Park is a short walk. Bus fare is $1.15 one way (children 4 and under, free). The one-way adult fare on the train, from Grand Central Terminal, is $4.75 for off-peak hours. Children 5 to 12 are half price. For more information, call (800) METRO-INFO.</p>
        <p>Seaside Heights</p>
        <p>Ocean Terrace, Seaside Heights, N.J., (908) 793-4949.</p>
        <p>THE BEACH: Seaside Heights is an amusement park masquerading as a beach resort: the only reminder that you're beside the Atlantic Ocean, as you bob along the boardwalk, is the buoyant stream of young women in bikinis and young men in low-riding cut-off jeans. Not that people here are uninterested in the beach; they just want it all. But the beach is there, with the brilliant sapphire ocean edged with sand that radiates like a diamond necklace. Indeed, the white beach and ceaseless white-capped water present an image so lustrous and beautiful, so Riviera-like, that it's a shock when you first see it from the crude boardwalk. For families, Seaside Heights is a mixed blessing. The tackiness is both appealing and appalling. The sense of adventure is addictive, and visitors do get the feeling that they are one step removed from reality. The amusement parks at either end of the boardwalk and the string of arcades and food stalls in between provide plenty of entertainment for a day, if not a week (though after the third day, you might long for a trip to, say, Nepal). There are shooting galleries, carousels (with music like "Let Me Call You Sweetheart"), a roller coaster and Tilt-a-Whirl, kiddie rides and a Ferris wheel (seats enclosed). For all the rides, you need tickets, which are 25 cents each. Kiddie rides are two to three tickets; other rides are five to six tickets. To go on the beach, you also pay: $2 Monday through Friday, and $3 on Saturday, Sunday and holidays. Children 12 and under are admitted free at all times.</p>
        <p>THE WATER: On a clear day, the water is a transparent cerulean blue. On the day we visited, the temperature was an inviting 71 degrees, though the hearty surf still frightened some children.</p>
        <p>THE SAND: That fine ivory sand the Jersey Shore is renowned for.</p>
        <p>THE FOOD: Well, what can be said, except that the only food groups that seem to be missing are fresh fruit and whole grains (vegetables are on pizza). What is here? Sausages, cotton candy, frozen custard (the real thing), salt-water taffy, corn on the cob, shrimp, lobster, clams, steak, fresh-squeezed lemonade and snow cones.</p>
        <p>THE EXTRAS: The amusement parks break up a long day under the sun, but they also mean spending money. The Log Flume ride, for example, at $3, speeds through pretend rapids in which everyone shrieks and gets drenched, making you wonder why riding the real waves, free, doesn't incite the same thrill. If you're prepared to drop a lot of quarters in the arcades, on food and the rides, you'll be less resistant to Seaside Heights, or as one sign said, the "Home of Sun Fun."</p>
        <p>THE RESTROOMS: There aren't very many: the ones on the boardwalk were amazingly clean, however, given the volume, and there are usually lines, too, to get in. Pay toilets (25 cents) are on the piers. Showers are placed sporadically along the boardwalk.</p>
        <p>THE HOURS: Daily from 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. (when lifeguards are present).</p>
        <p>THE PARKING: Depending on how close you want to be to the beach, you can pay from $2 to $4 for the day. Some fees also include beach admission.</p>
        <p>HOW TO GET THERE: If you're not up to driving, N.J. Transit has daily buses to Seaside Heights from Manhattan, Jersey City and Newark. Prices vary, depending where you leave from; the round trip from New York is $27. Children 11 and under pay $12.50; toddlers who sit on your lap are free. The ticket entitles you to a beach pass (which you must ask for; if you don't have this special pass, you won't get onto the beach free). The ride is two hours each way.</p>
        <p>Lido Beach Town Park</p>
        <p>Lido Beach, L.I., 630 Lido Boulevard, (516) 431-6650.</p>
        <p>THE BEACH: The Town of Hempstead is not normally associated with beaches, but it does own a chunk of the primest, whitest and handsomest shorefront on the South Shore of Long Island. The nearby popular venues are Fire Island and Jones Beach, but lesser-known Lido, a gull's cry from the intense crowds, is just as resplendent as its famous relatives to the east. The beach is like a club. There is a picnic area (with open grills and mushroom-capped shelters for bad weather, available to groups of 50 or more), volleyball, handball, tennis, shuffleboard, boccie and basketball courts, horseshoe pitches, a softball field and two pools (one for children). The pools are open only on weekends; admittance is $1.75. The beach provides the sports equipment, except for tennis racquets and handballs; use of the courts is free, and all you have to do is sign up the day of play. There are also two playgrounds: one is marginal with hard pebbly sand, the other, a wooden village of tunnels, towers and bridges structured for disabled children, is open to the public after 3 P.M. during the week and all day on the weekends. Low dunes and sand-covered bridges separate the beach from the amenities, so you have to trek back and forth, unless you're superhuman and have taken everything with you, including Band-Aids and a portable toilet (or phone). Otherwise, plan to spend all day here without too much effort. And try to take a boogie board and shovels and pails. It could mean an entire day without one whine.</p>
        <p>THE WATER: The water was clean and soothing, for at least one family that had spent far too much time on the highway. Long after the lifeguards went home, a covey of young girls rode low waves that crashed close to shore, and fought the undertow with the grace of ballerinas. One 2-year-old, Hannah Rizzi, had never been to the ocean. She immediately stripped to her diapers and lay face down in the water as if she and the waves (and seaweed) were old friends.</p>
        <p>THE SAND: So soft it reminded us of our childhood velveteen dresses. Mr.  Johnson, the general contractor who takes his family to Lido Beach on weekends, rates it very high for sand-castle building (he should know: he's also a trained architect). There was plenty of litter by 6 P.M., perhaps because more trash cans are needed (some people dug holes for their trash), but Mike Pellegrino, the beach's assistant supervisor, said the sand was raked every morning.</p>
        <p>THE FOOD: The usual heavy-on-the-cholesterol fare: hot dogs, burgers, nachos with cheese, breakfast (muffins, pastries, juices), pizza, pretzels, Good Humor ice cream, sodas, iced tea, french fries.</p>
        <p>THE RESTROOMS: Plentiful, but not places you'd want to linger in too long. There are dressing stations as well (no boys over 5 years old are allowed in the women's area). Showers are near the picnic site.</p>
        <p>THE EXTRAS: The gulls that hang out at Lido (and there seem to be a whole country of them) are, one beachgoer remarked, as huge as watermelons. The birds are both disarming and eerie, recalling that Hitchcock movie. A spray pool for toddlers is near the more elaborate playground. Short black pines grow resolutely in this windswept setting, echoing Cape Cod beaches. And on the practical side, the concessions sell suntan lotion and children's beach toys.</p>
        <p>THE PARKING: For residents of the Town of Hempstead, $4 a car; for nonresidents, $12. People have been turned away on weekends because of space. Mr. Pellegrino says the most crowded time to arrive is from noon to 1:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>THE HOURS: Monday through Friday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M; Saturday and Sunday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. (when lifeguards are present).</p>
        <p>HOW TO GET THERE: It's best to drive. Take the Meadowbrook Parkway south, to Loop Parkway, Exit M-10, which is just before the tolls to Jones Beach. Take Loop to the end, where you veer right onto Lido Boulevard. The entrance to Lido Beach is about a mile.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
