<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Umbrellas' Closing Leaves Christo With Empty Palette</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19911204T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="486441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UMBRELLAS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHRISTO (ARTIST)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRIMES, WILLIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DE1E3BF931A25752C1A967958260" item-length="1233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Umbrellas' Closing Leaves Christo With Empty Palette</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRIMES, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The umbrella project that the artist Christo once called "a symphony in two parts" has become a tragedy in two acts. On Oct. 26, a sudden wind uprooted a 485-pound umbrella in the Tejon Pass north of Los Angeles and struck Lori Keevil-Matthews, 33 years old, of Camarillo, Calif., crushing her to death against a boulder.</p>
        <p>Christo ordered the entire project of 1,340 yellow umbrellas in California and 1,760 blue umbrellas in Japanto be taken down "out of respect to her memory." But during the dismantling in Japan, a 51-year-old worker, Masaaki Nakamura, died when the arm of the crane he was operating touched a 65,000-volt power line.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The umbrella project that the artist Christo once called "a symphony in two parts" has become a tragedy in two acts. On Oct. 26, a sudden wind uprooted a 485-pound umbrella in the Tejon Pass north of Los Angeles and struck Lori Keevil-Matthews, 33 years old, of Camarillo, Calif., crushing her to death against a boulder.</p>
        <p>Christo ordered the entire project of 1,340 yellow umbrellas in California and 1,760 blue umbrellas in Japanto be taken down "out of respect to her memory." But during the dismantling in Japan, a 51-year-old worker, Masaaki Nakamura, died when the arm of the crane he was operating touched a 65,000-volt power line.</p>
        <p>For the first time in years, the artist is without a current project. And his ability to forge the coalitions that have made his works possible may have been undermined by the two deaths in "The Umbrellas: Joint Project for Japan and U.S.A." To realize the California half of the project, Christo enlisted the cooperation of 24 state and county agencies. "Incidents like this assume mythic proportions," said James Clark, executive director of the Public Art Fund in New York City. "It can't help but have an impact when review boards and agencies look at proposals."</p>
        <p>No lawsuits have been filed on behalf of the California woman or the three people injured by the umbrella that killed her. Christo's attorney, Scott Hodes, a partner in the Chicago firm of Arvey, Hodes, Costello &amp; Burman, said, "We believe after a fairly thorough investigation that the accident was not the fault of the artist, or with the way the umbrella was constructed, designed or installed" Problem for the Future</p>
        <p>But insurance underwriting could prove more difficult to find in the future. "I doubt if any locality would entertain a Christo installation unless very substantial liability insurance was provided," said Huntington T. Block, whose Washington firm insures many museums, galleries and collectors. "He's going to face a much tougher sell. I cannot believe that if I were a liability underwriter that the umbrella project would not color my reaction."</p>
        <p>Christo's lawyer said that the umbrella project carried liability insurance "in excess of $2 million" but declined to give exact figures.</p>
        <p>Friends of the artist say that he was devastated when he heard of the death in California. According to Jeanne-Claude Christo, his wife and business partner, the couple paid a condolence visit to Ms. Keevil-Matthews's husband, Michael, who told Christo how much he and his wife had enjoyed the umbrella project. There was no answer to several calls to his home.</p>
        <p>Earlier, Albert Maysles, who recently finished filming the project, said Christo "broke down and cried" when he heard of Ms. Keevil-Matthews's death, adding "I've never seen that before."</p>
        <p>But the Bulgarian-born artist, interviewed in his SoHo home together with Ms. Christo, spoke in upbeat tones about the umbrella project and his plans. When asked how he viewed the project now, he characterized it as "stimulating and beautiful." And in imperfect but unstoppable English, he went on to explain the meaning of the deaths in relation to his work. 'Everything Is Possible'</p>
        <p>Christo said that a sculptor like Alexander Calder created an artificial space, "and the space belongs to Calder." Christo said his works, on the contrary, borrowed real space. "There is no make-believe, no theater, no spectacle," he said. "And for me, the real world involves everything: risk, danger, beauty, energy, all we meet with in the real world. This project demonstrated that everything is possible, because it is part of reality."</p>
        <p>Christo continued: "The work was designed to generate a confrontation with nature and everything that nature brings."</p>
        <p>Ms. Christo said solemnly, "Christo's art is like a marriage; it's for better and for worse."</p>
        <p>The artist and his wife both said they had feared traffic accidents on the Interstate highway that passed the project in California and the possibility of helicopters colliding as they carried spectators over the site. The possibility that a sudden wind might lift an umbrella seemed remote, they said, since the umbrellas had been tested in a wind tunnel to withstand gusts of 65 miles an hour when opened.</p>
        <p>Although the umbrellas were taken down earlier than planned, the documentation of the project continues with a book, the film by Mr. Maysles and museum shows in the works. This is standard practice for the artist, who regards the temporary display of his installations as only part of the total artwork, which he says exists from the moment it is planned. Question of Definition</p>
        <p>For this reason, his wife objected to a reference to Christo's "initiating" future projects. She pointed to the artist's typed resume, which lists three projects "in progress": the "Wrapped Reichstag," the "Mastaba of Abu Dhabi Project for the United Arab Emirates" and "The Gates: Project for Central Park" (1980).</p>
        <p>All three have been "in progress" for at least 10 years. According to the artist, none has any likelihood of being realized soon. Helmut Kohl announced in 1986 that the Reichstag would not be wrapped as long as he was Chancellor, and he still is. Although a member of the Parliament recently spoke in favor of the idea, no progress has been made toward wrapping it. Christo, who conceived the project in 1972, said he hoped that several coming European museum shows of his 1985 Pont Neuf project, in which he wrapped Paris's most famous bridge, would swing public sentiment to his side.</p>
        <p>The New York project, which envisions 15-foot-high fabric gates lining every path in Central Park, was given a resounding no in 1981 by the city's Department of Parks and Recreation, which Ms. Christo said cited overuse of the park and the danger of setting a precedent. Rejection came in the form of a three-inch-thick policy document that the Parks Department still uses to fend off other like-minded artists. Christo said the project was "on the back burner."</p>
        <p>The Abu Dhabi project, which calls for 390,500 barrels of oil to be joined in a structure larger than the pyramid of Cheops as "a symbol of the civilization of oil throughout the world," was derailed by the Iran-Iraq war and has never got back on track. Christo says the Mastaba is "on the back, back burner," and will probably have to wait "until the situation is sorted out in the Middle East."</p>
        <p>This will not come as a blow to many art critics and Conceptual Artists, who have long regarded Christo as the Norman Rockwell of Conceptual Art, and his wrapping projects as a one-note exercise. His popularity is undeniable, however. And like the late illustrator, he has put his stamp on the public mind so successfully that a building wrapped for renovation often brings thoughts of the School of Christo.</p>
        <p>Christo is working on the documentation of the "Umbrellas" project, sorting through the 19,000 slides and official papers that will eventually go into a book published by Harry N. Abrams and partly financed by Christo, whose wife said he intended to dedicate it to Ms. Keevil-Matthews. As with past projects, the artist plans to make the documentation available for museum shows.</p>
        <p>According to Ms. Christo, the couple has received many letters of support. "They say, 'Think only of the joy you have brought millions of people, ' and they say he must go on. They are beautiful letters."</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 4, 1991, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Nov. 12 about the artist Christo reversed the numbers of umbrellas erected at two sites in his recent work "Umbrellas Joint Project for Japan and U.S.A." There were 1,760 yellow umbrellas in California and 1,340 blue umbrellas in Japan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 4, 1991, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Nov. 12 about the artist Christo reversed the numbers of umbrellas erected at two sites in his recent work "Umbrellas Joint Project for Japan and U.S.A." There were 1,760 yellow umbrellas in California and 1,340 blue umbrellas in Japan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
