<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Loss Backs Up Criticism From Kidd</title>
    <meta content="24NETS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/24/sports/basketball/24nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1652491"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Milwaukee Bucks</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Milwaukee Bucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Milwaukee Bucks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFDF173DF937A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Loss Backs Up Criticism From Kidd</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Second Consecutive Loss Backs Up Kidd's Criticism</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>MILWAUKEE, Feb. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Milwaukee Bucks defeat New Jersey Nets, 100-81; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Nets skidded toward Thursday afternoon's 3 p.m. trading deadline with yet another demoralizing defeat, it was probably too early to assess the situation the way a former Net, Micheal Ray Richardson, did years ago: ''The ship be sinking.''</p>
        <p>But the holes were certainly evident again Wednesday night during a 100-81 loss to the Milwaukee Bucks. It was a game in which the Nets squandered a 12-point lead in the first half en route to their second consecutive loss to a team below them in the Eastern Conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The defeat came one day after Jason Kidd, the Nets' captain, blasted his teammates for caring more about statistics than winning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Nets skidded toward Thursday afternoon's 3 p.m. trading deadline with yet another demoralizing defeat, it was probably too early to assess the situation the way a former Net, Micheal Ray Richardson, did years ago: ''The ship be sinking.''</p>
        <p>But the holes were certainly evident again Wednesday night during a 100-81 loss to the Milwaukee Bucks. It was a game in which the Nets squandered a 12-point lead in the first half en route to their second consecutive loss to a team below them in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>The defeat came one day after Jason Kidd, the Nets' captain, questioned his teammates' motivation and effort. The Nets (23-32), who had crept back into playoff contention after a horrendous start, have lost five of their last seven games.</p>
        <p>Luckily for the Nets, no one is running away with the Atlantic Division. Because Boston lost in Denver, the Nets remained four games out of first place. But they fell three and a half games behind idle Philadelphia for the eighth and final Eastern Conference playoff berth.</p>
        <p>The Nets have 27 games remaining. But, as Kidd cautioned after Wednesday's rout, the time for giving up on the season ''could come very soon if we don't find a way to win.''</p>
        <p>''It could be here next week,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Before Wednesday's game, Kidd said he was not trying to make a statement with his highly uncharacteristic public criticisms after Tuesday night's disheartening 100-82 loss to the Toronto Raptors at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't really sending a message,'' Kidd said. ''That was just my outlook of the game. If we're thinking about making the playoffs, we have to show that. And we just didn't show it yesterday.''</p>
        <p>The Nets did not show it Wednesday, either.</p>
        <p>''If this is the way we're going to go and play, just go out here and get our stats, I'll sit down and watch the young guys,'' Kidd said Tuesday night. ''Give the young guys some time because it's no need to waste our energy if everybody's not going to show up.''</p>
        <p>Kidd, who sat out the fourth quarter Wednesday, did not name names after Tuesday's game. But Vince Carter, who has carried the Nets offensively for most of the last two months, missed 17 of his 25 field-goal attempts on Tuesday in his first game against Toronto since the Raptors traded him on Dec. 17.</p>
        <p>Against the Bucks (22-30), Carter started out as if he had something to prove. With 5 minutes 44 seconds remaining in the first quarter, Carter already had 10 points, as the Nets raced out to a 20-9 lead. But Carter, who made five of his first eight shots, picked up his second foul with 5:08 left and sat out the remainder of the first quarter. And when Carter returned, the misses started to outnumber the makes.</p>
        <p>Carter missed 7 of his 10 field-goal attempts in the second quarter, including his last four, before Coach Lawrence Frank sat him for the final 2:04 of the half. Carter's benching coincided with a 10-0 run by the Bucks, who turned a 12-point deficit into a 47-43 lead.</p>
        <p>Still, the Nets scored the final 5 points of the half, and took a 48-47 lead into the break. With 16 points, Carter was the only player on either side in double figures. In 15 minutes of playing time, however, Carter had already cranked up 18 shots -- and missed 10.</p>
        <p>Carter hit his first two shots of the second half as the Nets inched out to a 56-51 lead. But the Bucks made their first 10 shots of the second half, then outscored the Nets, 26-6, over the final 9:11 of the third quarter to take a 77-62 lead into the fourth.</p>
        <p>The run was punctuated by consecutive fast-break alley-oop dunks by Desmond Mason from Mike James, probably not the response Kidd had hoped for when he leveled his criticisms.</p>
        <p>''We can all see what's wrong,'' Kidd said. ''And that's playing defense.''</p>
        <p>Carter led all scorers with 26 points, but he missed 16 of his game-high 27 shots. The Nets shot just 37.1 percent.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
