<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. Sharon's Giant Step</title>
    <meta content="24THU3$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/24/opinion/24thu3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1652424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharon, Ariel (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Gaza Strip</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Sharon, Ariel</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Barnea, Nahum</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Abbas, Mahmoud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5D6163DF937A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. Sharon's Giant Step</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mr. Sharon's Giant Step</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says Prime Min Ariel Sharon of Israel has shown enormous political courage by agreeing to evacuate settlements in Gaza Strip without first wringing some concession out of Palestinians, even though he has coupled his plan wih further work on barrier blocking off Palestinian neighbors; notes barriers are easy to construct, and when peace talks are held they should be as easy to tear down</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This page has long been very wary of any moves by the Israeli government to further consolidate land it seized after the 1967 war without negotiations with the Palestinians. So we were a little queasy about the way Prime Minister Ariel Sharon coupled his plans to withdraw Jewish settlers from the Gaza Strip with further work on the barrier that Israel is constructing to block itself off from its Palestinian neighbors.</p>
        <p>Some Sharon observers are already likening the Gaza pullout to a chessboard-worthy move. Seen in that light, Mr. Sharon is sacrificing Gaza in return for the world's acceptance of Israel's ''de facto annexation of 7 percent of West Bank territory,'' as a political columnist, Nahum Barnea, theorized in Yediot Aharonot, a Hebrew-language daily. ''Sharon has not become a dove,'' Mr. Barnea wrote. ''He has remained what he always was: a pragmatic hawk.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It would be churlish to greet Prime Minister Ariel Sharon's historic decision to pull out of Gaza with anything other than enthusiasm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This page has long been very wary of any moves by the Israeli government to further consolidate land it seized after the 1967 war without negotiations with the Palestinians. So we were a little queasy about the way Prime Minister Ariel Sharon coupled his plans to withdraw Jewish settlers from the Gaza Strip with further work on the barrier that Israel is constructing to block itself off from its Palestinian neighbors.</p>
        <p>Some Sharon observers are already likening the Gaza pullout to a chessboard-worthy move. Seen in that light, Mr. Sharon is sacrificing Gaza in return for the world's acceptance of Israel's ''de facto annexation of 7 percent of West Bank territory,'' as a political columnist, Nahum Barnea, theorized in Yediot Aharonot, a Hebrew-language daily. ''Sharon has not become a dove,'' Mr. Barnea wrote. ''He has remained what he always was: a pragmatic hawk.''</p>
        <p>But whatever bird Mr. Sharon has chosen to emulate, it would be churlish to greet his historic decision with anything other than enthusiasm. The prime minister has risked enormous political capital in boldly going where his predecessors feared to tread: agreeing to evacuate settlements without first wringing something out of the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>Thanks to Mr. Sharon's efforts, optimism and hope is spreading throughout Israel, and that can only be a good thing. It gives a boost to the Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas, and it further isolates Mr. Sharon's right-wing Likud Party members, particularly the finance minister, Benjamin Netanyahu, and the minister for Jerusalem affairs, Natan Sharansky.</p>
        <p>The barrier remains troublesome. Its route was revised following a court order last year, which rightly said it imposed too many hardships on Palestinian civilians, many of whom were blocked from getting to work or visiting relatives. The new path of the barrier, Israeli officials say, will reduce the amount of West Bank land on the Israeli side of the fence to 7 percent from 15 percent. That's certainly better than the original plan. But the new path should not be treated as a permanent boundary when the time comes for peace talks about a final settlement with the Palestinians. The land that Israel has enclosed should remain on the bargaining table. Barriers are easy to construct, and should be just as easy to tear down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon has shown enormous political courage: he is keeping his majority coalition together by the skin of his teeth, and that coalition may not last to see the successful end of the Gaza withdrawal. We hope that it does, and that Mr. Sharon coordinates this historic withdrawal with the Palestinian Authority in a way that leaves impoverished Gaza with enough resources to allow the Palestinians to show the world that they can govern themselves.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
