<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anti-Abortion Movement Prepares to Battle Clinton</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="584856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABORTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RU-486 (DRUG)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSPLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TONER, ROBIN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ROE V WADE (1973 SUPREME COURT DECISION)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D91031F931A15752C0A965958260" item-length="965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anti-Abortion Movement Prepares to Battle Clinton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TONER, ROBIN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>These are grim days for the anti-abortion movement.</p>
        <p>For the first time in 12 years, opponents of legalized abortion do not have a sympathetic President in the White House. Many feel badly let down by a conservative Supreme Court. Perhaps most of all, they are fighting the idea that the courts and the political system reached a lasting consensus on abortion with the court cases and election of 1992, and that their side lost. Presidential Action</p>
        <p>There is no surer sign of the altered political climate than President Clinton's resolve to use executive orders to reverse some important victories the anti-abortion forces won under Republican rule. This turnaround will come only days after George Bush issued a proclamation declaring last Sunday National Sanctity of Human Life Day to "call attention to the tragedy of abortion."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>These are grim days for the anti-abortion movement.</p>
        <p>For the first time in 12 years, opponents of legalized abortion do not have a sympathetic President in the White House. Many feel badly let down by a conservative Supreme Court. Perhaps most of all, they are fighting the idea that the courts and the political system reached a lasting consensus on abortion with the court cases and election of 1992, and that their side lost. Presidential Action</p>
        <p>There is no surer sign of the altered political climate than President Clinton's resolve to use executive orders to reverse some important victories the anti-abortion forces won under Republican rule. This turnaround will come only days after George Bush issued a proclamation declaring last Sunday National Sanctity of Human Life Day to "call attention to the tragedy of abortion."</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Clinton's spokesman, George Stephanopoulos, suggested that it would be logical to expect the President to lift the ban on abortion counseling at federally financed clinics on Friday, the 20th anniversary of Roe v. Wade, the decision that established a constitutional right to abortion. Aides have said he may also reverse the ban on importing the French drug that induces abortion, RU-486, and the prohibition against Federal financing of research using fetal tissue.</p>
        <p>But as anti-abortion leaders mark the Roe v. Wade anniversary with their annual march on Washington, many say they are adjusting to their fall from power. They say it will make them tougher, stronger at the grass roots, more committed to the fundamentals of organizing, a skill that made their movement formidable in the first place.</p>
        <p>"What had happened to some extent over the last four years is that people had gotten into the habit of letting George do it," said Wanda Franz, president of the National Right to Life Committee, in an interview this week.  "We knew that George was going to veto things; we knew that he was going to take care of things. Now, they just have to get back to the business of pro-life grass-roots development."</p>
        <p>The anti-abortion leaders are delivering a message these days that is simple and oddly familiar, since it came from the other side for 12 years: abortion extremists have seized control of the White House and are dangerously strong in the Congress. Strategy on Legislation</p>
        <p>Mrs. Franz and her allies say they are focusing much of their fire on the Freedom of Choice Act, a priority of the National Abortion Rights Action League. That measure would prohibit states from enacting a variety of restrictions on abortion, like a 24-hour waiting period. President Clinton promised during the campaign that he would sign such a bill.</p>
        <p>Anti-abortion leaders assert that such a measure is squarely at odds with public opinion, arguing that most Americans consider such regulations to be utterly reasonable.</p>
        <p>"The fact is, we look forward to the Freedom of Choice Act debate, because FOCA is abortion in the raw," said Helen Alvare, director of planning and information for the National Council of Catholic Bishops' Pro-Life Secretariat. "If we do our public education job right, President Clinton will either not want FOCA to get to his desk in the first place, and send out the right signals to do that, or he will actually find a cogent reason to explain why, if it's on his desk, he won't sign it."  Defining the Question</p>
        <p>Kate Michelman, the president of the abortion-rights action league, countered, "We need to resolve the question of who should decide" whether a woman can have an abortion, "and that's what FOCA does." Still, she acknowledged, "There's no question that we have a very important education campaign to do on some of these issues like waiting periods, because, as I've said, they sound moderate until you examine the real-world impact on women's health and women's lives."</p>
        <p>The anti-abortion forces see that Mr. Clinton will almost certainly do much to change policy by executive order.</p>
        <p>They are also keenly aware that without an anti-abortion President willing to veto bills, thus requiring a two-thirds majority of the Congress to override him, it will be far harder to hold the line.</p>
        <p>Still, they say they are preparing for some bruising fights in Congress. "We want more than anything to support national health care," Ms. Alvare said, adding that the bishops have long urged such a measure. But "we could not support a health-care bill that generally included abortion as a required service," she said. Broader Political Fight</p>
        <p>Beyond the legislative struggle in Washington and the states is the broader political fight: anti-abortion leaders are battling the view, widely held in the Republican Party, that Mr. Bush paid a price for cultivating the religious right on issues like abortion.</p>
        <p>And beyond the political struggle is the struggle in the streets. Joseph Scheidler of the Pro-Life Action League, a longtime protester at clinics, predicted an upsurge in demonstrations. "A lot of people have decided activism is the only game in town," he said in an interview this week.</p>
        <p>The anti-abortion leaders say they will keep their spirits high. Phyllis Schlafly, who was prominent in the debate over the Republican Party's anti-abortion platform last year, noted, "There are those who think the fund raising will be better under Clinton."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Franz noted that many have been in the movement since Roe v. Wade was handed down; they often compare their struggle to the struggle to outlaw slavery, and note that the abolitionists were often counted out.</p>
        <p>She also said her movement had not given up the hope of someday completely eliminating it. "Abortion is so bad for the country, and so bad for women, that there will come a time when we have to do away with it," she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
