<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hundreds of New Yorkers Add Efforts to Police Hunt</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="856718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CENTRAL PARK (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">POGREBIN, ROBIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3D61639F933A25755C0A960958260" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hundreds of New Yorkers Add Efforts to Police Hunt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POGREBIN, ROBIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even as a frustrating sense of helplessness settles over the search for a suspect in the Central Park beating case, officers on the 13th floor of Police Headquarters find themselves on the front lines of hope. What otherwise would be considered cacophony is music to their ears: telephones ringing around the clock.</p>
        <p>The officers of the Police Department's Crime Stoppers Unit have been fielding calls from hundreds of people who believe they have information that might lead to an arrest in last Tuesday's near-fatal attack, a crime that has captured the city's attention as few others have.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even as a frustrating sense of helplessness settles over the search for a suspect in the Central Park beating case, officers on the 13th floor of Police Headquarters find themselves on the front lines of hope. What otherwise would be considered cacophony is music to their ears: telephones ringing around the clock.</p>
        <p>The officers of the Police Department's Crime Stoppers Unit have been fielding calls from hundreds of people who believe they have information that might lead to an arrest in last Tuesday's near-fatal attack, a crime that has captured the city's attention as few others have.</p>
        <p>The commanding officer, Lieut. Richard S. Kuberski, said that by midnight last night the unit had received 644 calls, more than the total received after the last such incident in Central Park, involving a Brazilian jogger, and after  the World Trade Center bombing.</p>
        <p>"It's been fantastic," he said. "I think this crime has struck a nerve with New Yorkers."</p>
        <p>While Crime Stoppers is usually closed from 1 to 5 A.M., the unit has been answering calls around the clock in the Central Park case, and is taking each one seriously, the lieutenant said. "We take calls about people who saw a man standing on the corner of 42d and Seventh last Wednesday," he said. "We're not going to blow off anything that people give us, because you never know."</p>
        <p>The more information that trickles out to the public, Lieutenant Kuberski said, the more calls pour in. When a sketch of the victim was released on Tuesday, "calls went up dramatically." It was three different calls to Crime Stoppers that led to the victim's identification, he said.</p>
        <p>When a sketch of the suspect was released on Wednesday, the calls doubled, he said.</p>
        <p>Half of the 14 officers manning Crime Stopper's phone lines speak Spanish and one speaks Chinese, Lieutenant Kuberski said. "The whole key to it is how to talk to people on the phone," Lieutenant Kuberski said. "Sometimes people call and they're really apprehensive and we have to form a relationship with that person and mutual trust, like: 'O.K., I know you're a little nervous now. We're  not going to trace your phone call, or ask your name. So just give us your information."</p>
        <p>Crime Stoppers, which is financed by the New York City Police Foundation, a nonprofit civilian group, was established in 1983. It stemmed from a 1976 murder case in Albuquerque, N.M., that was solved with the help of tips from the public.</p>
        <p>Since the unit's inception, it has helped solve 2,400 violent felony crime cases, the lieutenant said.</p>
        <p>People who call Crime Stoppers (577-TIPS) with information are promised anonymity and a possible reward. Any tip that leads to an arrest or indictment is eligible for a cash reward of $1,000. A reward of $10,000 offered by Mayor Giuliani in the Central Park case is to be given for information that leads to arrest and conviction, Lieutenant Kuberski said.</p>
        <p>Although the woman who first discovered the Central Park victim has complained that people in the park failed to respond to her pleas for help, Mr.  Kuberski said the calls to Crime Stoppers belies the notion that New Yorkers do  not like to get involved. They just like to be anonymous.</p>
        <p>"Some people feel that they don't want to be seen talking to a police officer," Mr. Kuberski said. "But there are people out there who have a conscience."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
