<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Interactive Enthusiasts Seen Tuning Out Cable</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="746114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABLE TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEPHONES AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SATELLITES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ODYSSEY (RESEARCH CO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LANDLER, MARK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DE1431F932A35750C0A963958260" item-length="535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Interactive Enthusiasts Seen Tuning Out Cable</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LANDLER, MARK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the television viewing public is willing to be led into the interactive age, many would apparently prefer to be led there by a telephone or satellite company rather than their cable providers.</p>
        <p>A new survey of 4,000 United States households, scheduled for release tomorrow, finds that more than half of cable-television homes are so unhappy with their existing cable service that if telephone or satellite carriers offered comparable services, they would switch. .</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the television viewing public is willing to be led into the interactive age, many would apparently prefer to be led there by a telephone or satellite company rather than their cable providers.</p>
        <p>A new survey of 4,000 United States households, scheduled for release tomorrow, finds that more than half of cable-television homes are so unhappy with their existing cable service that if telephone or satellite carriers offered comparable services, they would switch. .</p>
        <p>The findings could come as a rude awakening to cable television executives who like to say they are leading the charge toward a world of interactive services. Their industry could be hobbled by old complaints about shoddy customer service, according to the study of consumer attitudes toward television by the market-research company Odyssey.</p>
        <p>"The cable industry should look at this as a mild heart attack," said Nick Donatiello, president of Odyssey, based in San Francisco. "There's still time for them to change. But they're entering a period where they're going to face competition for the first time."</p>
        <p>The regional Bell phone companies hope to offer some form of video programming in the next several years. And nearly one million households have purchased small dish antennas and receiving equipment for direct-broadcasting satellite services that were started last fall by GM Hughes Electronics and Hubbard Broadcasting Inc. to offer a full complement of cable channels.</p>
        <p>According to the study, only 39 percent of households with cable TV rated the image of their cable provider as "very good." Fifty-five percent of households said they would be "very likely" to switch to a different TV provider if it were to offer competitive prices.</p>
        <p>Among the 4,000 households responding, the survey reports that cable penetration slipped to 62.8 percent in 1994 from 64.5 percent in 1993. Odyssey conducted the random-sample telephone survey in October and November.</p>
        <p>Consumer dissatisfaction with cable is most pronounced among people who are open to new technologies, according to the survey. Odyssey, which divides the consumer marketplace into six demographic segments, labels these groups as "new enthusiasts" and "surfers." Among surfers, 71 percent said they would drop cable for an affordable alternative. Among the new enthusiasts, 70 percent would make the switch. "The dissatisfaction is both with the programming, and the way it is provided," Mr. Donatiello said.</p>
        <p>The Government reduced basic cable rates by 17 percent last year. But Mr. Donatiello said consumers were still unhappy because, in some cases, the regulations forced cable companies to remove channels.  Some operators also began making up for the lost revenue by charging separately for services or items like program guides that had been included in the monthly charge.</p>
        <p>Cable executives acknowledged that their reputation was somewhat tarnished. "We recognize we have a credibility gap in the area of customer service," said Rich D'Amato, a spokesman for the National Cable Television Association. To address that gap, the association is starting a nationwide marketing program today that pledges timely service, including installation and repairs.  BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
