<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Steve Howe Attends Union Meeting</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="746073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CURRY, JACK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOWE, STEVE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DB163DF932A35750C0A963958260" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Steve Howe Attends Union Meeting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CURRY, JACK</byline>
      <dateline>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla., Feb. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Steve Howe, relief pitcher and Yankee player representative, attended the union meeting for minor league players tonight in West Palm Beach but had little to say afterward.</p>
        <p>Howe became the first striking major league player to walk into a replacement camp last Saturday when he accepted a job in the Yankees' ticket office, but he has maintained his support of the union.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Steve Howe, relief pitcher and Yankee player representative, attended the union meeting for minor league players tonight in West Palm Beach but had little to say afterward.</p>
        <p>Howe became the first striking major league player to walk into a replacement camp last Saturday when he accepted a job in the Yankees' ticket office, but he has maintained his support of the union.</p>
        <p>As a provision of his three-year probation from a drug conviction in 1992, Howe needed to secure a legitimate job and he asked the Yankees for assistance.</p>
        <p>Even though the union's leader, Donald Fehr, said the union would talk to Howe about the wisdom of working in the ticket office and about the possibility of having him work for the players association, Gene Orza, the associate counsel, said he would not confer with Howe.</p>
        <p>"No, I don't want to discuss his situation with him," said Orza, who invited Howe to tonight's session. "I understand why he's down here. It's not a big deal."</p>
        <p>After the meeting, Howe brushed past reporters. Asked if would talk, he said, "No." Asked how he thought the meeting went, he said, "We're alive." Kraft Working for Steinbrenner</p>
        <p>Dick Kraft resigned last summer as the Yankees' vice president for community relations after an article in New York magazine attributed racially insensitive remarks to him about the children who live and play around Yankee Stadium. Today, Kraft was back at his office here, sorting through boxes of caps, shirts and jackets, just as had in the past.</p>
        <p>First, the striking Steve Howe takes a ticket job. Then the resigned Kraft returns. Is Pascual Perez next?</p>
        <p>Arthur Richman, a team spokesman, said Kraft would not be working for the Yankees and was simply doing, "personal stuff" for George Steinbrenner, the owner. Kraft declined to comment on his return.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner had left for the day when Kraft was seen. Incredible, Shrinking Crowds</p>
        <p>Not even George Steinbrenner stayed at Fort Lauderdale Stadium long enough today to watch the beginning of a replacement intrasquad game. The owner left to buy a race horse, while 200 fans watched for free. He returned for the last inning of a 4-0 game.</p>
        <p>New York's first exhibition game is scheduled here Thursday against the Los Angeles Dodgers.</p>
        <p>In a typical season, the 8,340 tickets to the opener would be sold out, but the Yankees are bracing for a much smaller crowd to see Frank Eufemia start instead of Jimmy Key. Mark Zettelmeyer, the spring ticket director, is hoping for between 1,000 and 1,500 spectators.</p>
        <p>The Yankees, who have sold 1,200 spring season tickets, have reduced prices for box seats from $12 to $7, for reserved grandstand from $9 to $6 and for bleachers from $6 to $3, but Zettelmeyer said the most tickets sold for one game so far were 2,000 for the March 18 game with the Boston Red Sox. Salaries Are Down, Too</p>
        <p>All Yankee employees who do not belong to a union or do not have a contract were given a 10 percent pay cut, while those employees with contracts were asked to accept the cut.</p>
        <p>General Manager Gene Michael was unsure whether he, Manager Buck Showalter or the coaches would be affected by the new policy. If a settlement is reached, the 10 percent will be restored.  YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
