<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Only the Guilty Are Guilty, Not Their Sons</title>
    <meta content="05WIES$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/05/opinion/05WIES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1290705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Jewish Appeal</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bertelsmann Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wiesel, Elie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Middelhoff, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5DD1138F936A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Only the Guilty Are Guilty, Not Their Sons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Elie Wiesel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wiesel, Elie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Elie Wiesel comments on criticism of United Jewish Appeal's decision to honor Thomas Middelhoff, chief executive of Bertelsmann communications empire, and criticism of him, Wiesel, for agreeing to be keynote speaker at event; says remembering Holocaust does not justify intolerance; notes that Middelhoff, who was born in 1953, is being compared by some to Hitler's SS troops; says that to humiliate a German today just for having been born German and to boycott evening for him is not what Jewish ethos is about; says that unlike Hitler and his followers, Jews do not believe in collective guilt (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Let me begin with a confession. I was wrong to believe that 50-odd years after the most cruel of human tragedies, caused by Hitler's Germany, some passions had begun to cool. For the victims, their children and their friends, the wounds remain understandably raw. They still have nightmares, and they are sensitive to certain words. They remember a time when the very word ''German'' evoked terror.</p>
        <p>I became aware that I was wrong when I read about the criticism of the United Jewish Appeal's decision to honor Thomas Middelhoff, though it is the man Thomas Middelhoff who is being honored, and not the Bertelsmann communications empire of which he is chief executive. The event, to take place May 15 in New York, will probably be picketed by demonstrators.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Let me begin with a confession. I was wrong to believe that 50-odd years after the most cruel of human tragedies, caused by Hitler's Germany, some passions had begun to cool. For the victims, their children and their friends, the wounds remain understandably raw. They still have nightmares, and they are sensitive to certain words. They remember a time when the very word ''German'' evoked terror.</p>
        <p>I became aware that I was wrong when I read about the criticism of the United Jewish Appeal's decision to honor Thomas Middelhoff, though it is the man Thomas Middelhoff who is being honored, and not the Bertelsmann communications empire of which he is chief executive. The event, to take place May 15 in New York, will probably be picketed by demonstrators.</p>
        <p>Since I accepted the invitation to give the keynote address at the dinner, I personally have been fielding complaints from people I know and respect and from others whom I have never met.</p>
        <p>The critics have voiced objections to what they perceive as an unduly hasty act of forgiveness. Some of these recriminations come from people who firmly believe that no German ought to be honored by Jews. Surely not now, perhaps later --  though one letter writer told me ''even a hundred years will be too soon'' and condemned ''Jewish leaders willing to prostitute themselves'' for money. Another letter writer argued that just as I had pleaded with President Ronald Reagan in 1985 not to visit the German military cemetery in Bitburg because it contained SS graves, I should not attend the ''disgraceful event'' for Mr. Middelhoff.</p>
        <p>Thus Thomas Middelhoff, born in 1953 -- a man who has never been accused of saying or doing anything to hurt or offend Jews and is, in fact, contributing to Jewish causes like the publication of Holocaust survivors' testimonies -- is being compared to the SS! I read this argument with disbelief.</p>
        <p>Of course, Jews must never -- and will never -- forget the Jewish tragedy that marked the last century and will haunt all centuries to come. To forget would be a sin. To remember is essential; it is a worthy endeavor, a noble cause for which many of us have fought relentlessly. But does it justify intolerance?</p>
        <p>I know that to this day there are Jews, and not only Holocaust survivors, who refuse to set foot on German soil or even buy German cars. But to wish not to make Germany rich is one thing; to treat all Germans as guilty is another.</p>
        <p>If, tragically, one chose to indict all Germans for the Holocaust, that would inevitably lead to exclusion and discrimination. Jewish academies could never invite German intellectuals and scholars to their conferences; Jewish music lovers would be expected to boycott concerts with German orchestras; and Jews could never, ever befriend Germans, no matter how long after the war they were born.</p>
        <p>Over the years, countless German personalities, political figures, scientists and artists have been singled out for a variety of awards by Jewish institutions of higher learning, hospitals and charitable organizations in both Israel and the United States. Do all these institutions stand accused of forgetting or betraying the dead?</p>
        <p>Am I wrong to believe that to humiliate a German today just for having been born German and to boycott an evening for him is not what Jewish ethos is about? I would like to remind some of my fellow Jews that Hitler's Germany condemned all of us not for what we did or did not do, but solely for having been born Jewish.</p>
        <p>We Jews do not believe in collective guilt. I have repeated over and over my belief that only the guilty are guilty: the children of killers are not killers, but children. I know from my own experience with German students that their burden is, at times, difficult to carry, heavy as it is with painful memories and questions about their fathers' and grandfathers' roles in the most terrifying genocide in history.</p>
        <p>Relations between Jews and Germans will remain traumatized for a long time. That is to be expected. Auschwitz and Treblinka will never be eradicated from German history.</p>
        <p>And yet, hatred must never be an answer. It does not serve memory.</p>
        <p>Elie Wiesel, a professor of humanities at Boston University, was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1986.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elie Wiesel, a professor of humanities at Boston University, was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1986.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
