<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Posada at 34, It's Sooner Rather Than Later</title>
    <meta content="15yanks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/15/sports/baseball/15yanks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1739909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tampa (Fla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Posada, Jorge</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Tampa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Posada, Jorge</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4DD133EF936A25751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Posada at 34, It's Sooner Rather Than Later</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Posada at 34, It's Sooner Rather Than Later</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., Feb. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees catcher Jorge Posada trains privately in Tampa (Fla) before starting spring training with team; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jorge Posada was the first player to take the field Tuesday morning, honing his swing with his uncle at the Yankees' minor league complex. He stood at the plate beside a device called a Jet-Tee, which looked like a blowtorch pointed up. His uncle Leo Posada, a former major leaguer, would lob a ball above the machine, which spewed air, and the ball would hang there, spinning, before Posada swung and served it into the outfield.</p>
        <p>It is still winter for Posada, who wore a beard and does not technically report to spring training until Thursday. But he is taking this season seriously, eager to establish a rapport with the staff ace, Randy Johnson, and hoping to stay in the hitting groove he found late last season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jorge Posada is taking this season seriously hoping to stay in the hitting groove he found late last season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jorge Posada was the first player to take the field Tuesday morning, honing his swing with his uncle at the Yankees' minor league complex. He stood at the plate beside a device called a Jet-Tee, which looked like a blowtorch pointed up. His uncle Leo Posada, a former major leaguer, would lob a ball above the machine, which spewed air, and the ball would hang there, spinning, before Posada swung and served it into the outfield.</p>
        <p>It is still winter for Posada, who wore a beard and does not technically report to spring training until Thursday. But he is taking this season seriously, eager to establish a rapport with the staff ace, Randy Johnson, and hoping to stay in the hitting groove he found late last season.</p>
        <p>Posada finished with a .310 average after Aug. 31. He weighed 215 pounds then, and he weighs the same now. Normally, Posada gains 7 to 10 pounds every off-season because of inactivity. At 34, he cannot afford to do that anymore.</p>
        <p>''You don't want to get heavier and older,'' Posada said. ''That makes it tougher on you. I wanted to keep it off because I felt good at the end of the season. I wanted to feel that way at the start of this season and see what happens.''</p>
        <p>Keeping off the weight is only one of Posada's spring goals. Another is to work better with Johnson, who did not make any starts with Posada catching after July 1.</p>
        <p>The Yankees let go of John Flaherty, who was Johnson's personal catcher, and signed Kelly Stinnett, who worked with Johnson in Arizona. But Posada wants the responsibility.</p>
        <p>''I want to win, and that's our horse,'' Posada said. ''Flaherty's gone, Stinnett caught him before, but that's the guy I want. It comes with pride. There are a lot of things I want to get done, and obviously he's a No. 1. Him and Mussina are the guys we need to see out there on a consistent basis, and Randy was out there for us the most. You've got to keep him happy. Whatever it takes.''</p>
        <p>Posada said he would work with Johnson this spring to make him as comfortable as he was pitching to Flaherty. Johnson looked that way in the final game of the playoffs in Anaheim. The Yankees lost, but Johnson threw four and a third scoreless innings of relief to Posada.</p>
        <p>''There was something there,'' Posada said. ''We've just got to keep on building on it.''</p>
        <p>Johnson battled minor aches last season, but he ended up with 225 2/3 innings, the most of any pitcher in the American League East. His durability stood out against the rest of the rotation, including Mike Mussina, whose elbow problems cost him three weeks in September.</p>
        <p>The Yankees will have seven starters in camp, and three -- Shawn Chacon, Carl Pavano and Jaret Wright -- worked out at the minor league complex on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Pavano, who visited a back specialist last week and is recovering from a shoulder injury, could pitch off a mound on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Chacon showed up with a small bandage on his right index finger, but the Yankees were not alarmed; he scraped himself assembling a Thomas the Tank Engine toy for his son. Chacon, who will compete for a starting spot behind Johnson and Mussina, credited Posada for his success last season.</p>
        <p>''Especially his personality and the way he can relate to you, not necessarily in a serious way, but kind of joking around, it was a tremendous help,'' Chacon said. ''For me, as a catcher, he's the best one I've ever pitched to.''</p>
        <p>Praise like that means a lot to Posada, who values defense over offense. But Posada has been an offensive force over the years, and his decline last season was notable.</p>
        <p>Despite the late surge, Posada hit .262 with a .352 on-base percentage and a .430 slugging percentage. The figures were his lowest in each category since 1999, when he shared the job with Joe Girardi.</p>
        <p>Posada is signed through this season, but if he starts 81 games as a catcher, he triggers a $12 million option for 2007. He also gains veto power over trades on June 27, when he will accrue 10 years of major league service, including the last five with the same team.</p>
        <p>''I'm a Yankee,'' Posada said. ''I was born a Yankee. Being in this organization, playing in minor league games and stuff, I belong here. I take a lot of pride in putting that uniform on. It's the way I was taught. Hopefully, I can finish here.''</p>
        <p>Posada wanted to wear another uniform next month, in the World Baseball Classic. While players around the majors seem to back out of the tournament every day, Posada said he would have loved to represent Puerto Rico.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees petitioned the commissioner's office and the union to block him from playing, and Posada admitted that upset him. The fans in Puerto Rico do not understand, Posada said, and his family is feeling pressure for him to play.</p>
        <p>Posada said he knew he could challenge the decision, but he said he would not. The Yankees want to keep him fresh for the season, and ultimately, Posada wants the same thing.</p>
        <p>He is a decorated Yankee, but he is still an employee. That is why the beard will be gone by Thursday, in compliance with the principal owner George Steinbrenner's rules. And it is why Posada will stay a Yankee as the tournament goes on without him.</p>
        <p>''I look at it as a big season for me,'' he said. ''I don't want to get them mad.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
