<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shuttle Liftoff Postponed Because of a Bad Valve</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="342685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCOVERY (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HUBBLE SPACE TELESCOPE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELESCOPES AND OBSERVATORIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hubble Space Telescope</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DB1E3EF932A25757C0A966958260" item-length="573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shuttle Liftoff Postponed Because of a Bad Valve</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., April 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A defective valve in the steering system of the space shuttle Discovery halted the countdown within four minutes of the planned liftoff today and forced an indefinite postponement of the mission to carry the Hubble Space Telescope into orbit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A defective valve in the steering system of the space shuttle Discovery halted the countdown within four minutes of the planned liftoff today and forced an indefinite postponement of the mission to carry the Hubble Space Telescope into orbit.</p>
        <p>A defective valve in the steering system of the space shuttle Discovery halted the countdown within four minutes of the planned liftoff today and forced an indefinite postponement of the mission to carry the Hubble Space Telescope into orbit.</p>
        <p>Officials at the Kennedy Space Center said repairs would take at least one week and possibly two. They might be able to set a new launching schedule on Wednesday after further study of the problem and proposals for repairing it.</p>
        <p>''We're obviously disappointed,'' said Robert B. Sieck, the shuttle launching director.</p>
        <p>The $1.5 billion Hubble telescope program has known many technical and managerial setbacks and is already seven years behind the original launching schedule.</p>
        <p>Problem in a Power Unit</p>
        <p>After a preliminary engineering assessment, Mr. Sieck said the trouble was traced to a valve in one of the three power units in the shuttle's aft fuselage. The units operate the hydraulic system for swiveling the rocket engines during liftoff and the body flaps, rudder and other control devices during the launching and the landing.</p>
        <p>When these auxiliary power units were switched on at the five-minute mark in the countdown, sensors immediately detected an abnormal surge of power in the No. 1 unit. The astronauts tried adjustments to the fuel flow, but the problem persisted.</p>
        <p>Officials ordered a halt of the countdown at four minutes, huddled with engineers and decided to call off the launching. Liftoff had been scheduled for 8:47 A.M.</p>
        <p>If the failure had occurred in flight, engineers said, the two other power units could have handled all the shuttle's steering. But it is a mission rule not to start out with any key system less than fully operational.</p>
        <p>Engineers are not sure how long it will take to replace the malfunctioning unit with a spare, which must then be fully tested. Such a procedure has never been tried while a shuttle was on the launching pad. Mr. Sieck estimated it would take at least a week.</p>
        <p>Recharging of Batteries, Too</p>
        <p>In a complication, the delay will also necessitate recharging batteries in the Hubble telescope. Engineers will have to open the cargo bay doors and either recharge the batteries in place or remove them for recharging at a laboratory.</p>
        <p>Fred Wojtalik, project director for the Hubble telescope at the Marshall Space Flight Center in Huntsville, Ala., said the decision would hinge on whether replacing the power unit and recharging the batteries could be done concurrently by the two different teams of technicians.</p>
        <p>''We're still reviewing a lot of information,'' Mr. Sieck said at a news conference. ''We're not sure what the impact on the schedule is.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Wojtalik expressed concern that the work could cause some contamination of the telescope's delicate instruments, other engineers said a bulkhead separated the power units from the telescope in the cargo bay.</p>
        <p>Even if the launching is delayed two weeks, officials of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration said this should not set back the next scheduled shuttle mission. The Columbia is being prepared for liftoff on May 9 from the other shuttle launching pad.</p>
        <p>The Columbia will be carrying the Astro-1 observatory, which consists of four telescopes for examining astronomical phenomena in the ultraviolet and X-ray wavelengths. The telescopes will be operated from the shuttle's cargo bay and then returned to Earth at the end of the mission.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
