<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MEDIA BUSINESS;</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="694677"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABLE TELEVISION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMCAST CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MACLEAN HUNTER LTD</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE7D8123DF933A15755C0A962958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MEDIA BUSINESS;</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Comcast Corporation said yesterday that its $1.27 billion offer had won a bidding war for the United States cable television systems of Maclean Hunter Ltd.</p>
        <p>The acquisition would make Comcast the third-largest cable company in the United States with 3.5 million subscribers, behind Time Warner, with 7.3 million subscribers, and Tele-Communications, with 10.4 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Comcast Corporation said yesterday that its $1.27 billion offer had won a bidding war for the United States cable television systems of Maclean Hunter Ltd.</p>
        <p>The acquisition would make Comcast the third-largest cable company in the United States with 3.5 million subscribers, behind Time Warner, with 7.3 million subscribers, and Tele-Communications, with 10.4 million.</p>
        <p>Comcast, based in Philadelphia, will acquire 550,000 subscribers in regions close to where it already own systems -- in New Jersey, Florida and Michigan. In this respect, the deal is similar to the Times Mirror Company's agreement earlier this month to acquire Cox Communications's cable systems, some of which are contiguous to systems already owned by Times Mirror.</p>
        <p>"Cable operators are now attempting to form large regional companies to cut costs and boost revenues in their core business as well as to position for their coming entrance into the telephone industry," said Dennis Leibowitz, who follows the industry for Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette.</p>
        <p>The auction of the cable properties came as Maclean Hunter, based in Toronto, prepared to be acquired by Rogers Communications.</p>
        <p>In its takeover effort, Rogers had made it clear that it would sell Maclean Hunter's United States cable properties.</p>
        <p>The president of Comcast, Brian L. Roberts, has been extremely aggressive in positioning his company in the communications industry. Yesterday's deal, however, is by far Comcast's largest investment, far exceeding its commitments in Teleport, Nextel and QVC.</p>
        <p>The buyer and seller had slightly different analyses of the deal yesterday. A Rogers spokesman, Graham Savage, said his company was getting about 11 times 1994 cash flow, which he estimates at about $116 million.</p>
        <p>But John R. Alchin, Comcast's chief financial officer, said Comcast was paying only 10.5 times cash flow, arguing that the systems would generate $120 million in cash flow.  Bidding Was Heated</p>
        <p>In either case, analysts noted that the price was in line with what Times Mirror had paid for Cox's cable systems. But they added that prices were unlikely to rebound quickly to the levels of 12 and 13 times cash flow they had reached before the Bell Atlantic and Tele-Communications deal fell through. "It is a more traditional price," Mr. Leibowitz said.</p>
        <p>The bidding for the Maclean Hunter cable systems had apparently been heated. Charles F. Dolan, chairman of the Cablevision Systems Corporation, said yesterday that his company had offered $1.2 billion and had been willing to go as high as $1.225 billion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dolan, sounding somewhat annoyed at his defeat, added he planned to build a rival system in New Jersey, where Cablevision already has 350,000 subscribers.</p>
        <p>"We want to build a second system of fiber and 750 megaherz," he said, alluding to a 100-channel system. "We think that when you have as many subscribers in that area, it is our primary market."</p>
        <p>Continental Cablevision Systems, currently the nation's third-largest operator, had also been a bidder. There had been discussions between Continental and Comcast about a joint bid, several people involved in the negotiations said. Continental was anxious to acquire Rogers's systems in Michigan, but a joint bid would have created tax complications, and the talks fell apart. At the last minute, Continental matched Comcast's bid, a person involved in the negotiations said, but by then the talks between Comcast and Rogers had been virtually concluded. Other Bidders Involved</p>
        <p>Other companies believed to be bidders were TKR Media, a company owned by Tele-Communications Inc., Knight Ridder Inc. and the C-Tec Corporation of Wilkes-Barre, Pa.</p>
        <p>Comcast, which has an extremely strong balance sheet, has about $350 million in cash, and credit lines that allow it to use another $350 million. It will borrow the balance, for the deal, which is expected to be completed in early 1995. The companies must get regulatory approval in Canada and the United States.</p>
        <p>In buying Rogers's cable systems, Comcast has two goals, industry experts said yesterday. The purchase helps control costs in existing systems by reducing management and servicing expenses for contiguous systems. It can also increase revenues by allowing Comcast to sell local and regional advertisers a larger audience.</p>
        <p>"The purchase gives Comcast geographical muscle in competition with telephone companies, which already control whole states," said Paul Kagan, a media industry consultant. "The cable operators have scattered markets."  THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
