<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poles Dismayed by Unchecked Crime</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="769863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAPITAL PUNISHMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">POLAND</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERLEZ, JANE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DF1039F93AA25755C0A963958260" item-length="1250" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poles Dismayed by Unchecked Crime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PERLEZ, JANE</byline>
      <dateline>WARSAW, June 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like many Poles, Andrzej Tomaszewski had high hopes that after Communism the new justice system would transform the police from predators to protectors and give citizens swift access to impartial judges. Like many Poles, he has been jolted into a disappointing reality.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Tomaszewski, the last straw came when his station wagon was stolen from a downtown parking lot. As has become the practice here, he decided to take the law into his own hands and put an ad in a newspaper offering a reward for the return of his car.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like many Poles, Andrzej Tomaszewski had high hopes that after Communism the new justice system would transform the police from predators to protectors and give citizens swift access to impartial judges. Like many Poles, he has been jolted into a disappointing reality.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Tomaszewski, the last straw came when his station wagon was stolen from a downtown parking lot. As has become the practice here, he decided to take the law into his own hands and put an ad in a newspaper offering a reward for the return of his car.</p>
        <p>A week later he got a phone call and then met with two acknowledged thieves in a coffee shop. After some haggling they settled on a $1,500 ransom and told him where his car was.</p>
        <p>"Crime is a personal and private problem, not a problem for the police because they have no money, no resources," said Mr. Tomaszewski, who runs a travel agency. The police, he grumbled, are polite but ineffective, and judges have yet to win a general reputation for efficiency.</p>
        <p>Like many Eastern Europeans, Poles are disillusioned by rising street crime and seemingly insoluble civil disputes born of the capitalist opportunity to make a killing -- or lose a bundle -- in the buccaneer economy.</p>
        <p>The frustrations are underscored in recent surveys showing that the police, who were held in high regard after an almost clean sweep of their ranks in 1990, have slipped in popularity. In response to the huge numbers of unsolved crimes and increased violence, most Poles now believe that the death penalty should be restored.</p>
        <p>"I would give Poland a 2 out of 10 on the question of a civil society: genuine rule of law and speedy procedures," said Mark Brzezinski, an American lawyer who has taught at Warsaw University Law School. "They do have the procedures on the books, but they are not realistic when you consider the numbers of cases and the training of the judiciary."</p>
        <p>The police and court officials say they are hamstrung by skimpy budgets, eager but inexperienced police officers and judges, and the highly inflated expectations of a more open society. Retraining -- from police officers to police dogs -- is a monumental task.</p>
        <p>Last year there were 147 murders in Warsaw, compared with 418 in Washington. But in Warsaw the rate is rising while in Washington it has dropped. Surveys show most Poles are afraid to go out on the streets at night.</p>
        <p>Inspector Arnold Superczynski, Warsaw's police chief, offered an explanation of the new wariness. Before 1989 the police were silent about the murder rate. "Since then we've been telling the press about murder," he said. "That's why there is a feeling of cataclysm around here."</p>
        <p>At the 6 P.M. shift change, the police station at Belevardska 16 resembles a campus fraternity house as groups of muscular young men in svelte black paratrooper-style uniforms stride through the swinging doors to take up patrol duty.</p>
        <p>It is clear from the fresh faces that the front lines of Warsaw's anticrime squads are inexperienced troops. The ranks of the Communist police -- known as the militia -- were purged, and now nearly 50 percent of the city's police officers have less than three years' experience. One-third are under 25.</p>
        <p>Sgt. Adam Habrevicz, 29, is one of the senior patrol officers and is considered such a veteran that he trains recruits.</p>
        <p>"People trust us more than in the militia days," Sergeant Habrevicz said as he and his partner, Robert Ciechaniewicz, 22, nosed their blue and white police sedan toward the Praga neighborhood, one of this capital's high-crime districts.</p>
        <p>But trust has led to a new problem: "Now people call the police more and more to involve them in their family affairs."</p>
        <p>Indeed, the early stops on a recent evening were domestic squabbles.</p>
        <p>At the first, a mother and daughter were being beaten by the husband. "He was furious that five cats had soiled the furniture while they were away on vacation," the sergeant said with a shrug after emerging from the first dispute. The man was unhappy that the police had answered the call, and threatened to call the police chief to complain, the sergeant said.</p>
        <p>But this was mild compared with the past, Sergeant Habrevicz said, adding: "Then, if you went to a house, someone would say to you darkly, 'You won't be working tomorrow,' meaning they had political connections."</p>
        <p>Curbs on police powers have a lot to do with the increased respect, Sergeant Habrevicz said. Under the Communists, the police could round up 50 people and "pacify" a neighborhood to seize one suspect. Now arrest papers must be signed by the prisoner as well as the police officer, and the prisoner has the right to inform his family or workplace of his arrest.</p>
        <p>Complaints of unlawful arrest can be taken to the courts. In the police cells, there is a limit of two people in each lockup instead of five, and each person must be given a mattress.</p>
        <p>But there are other kinds of curbs -- fiscal ones -- that obstruct the rule of law.</p>
        <p>At the dilapidated neighborhood police building in Mokotow, the four detectives have only two cars and fuel is rationed.</p>
        <p>Like the police precincts, Warsaw's lower courts are staffed by people who are strikingly young for a society accustomed to crusty public faces. Some of the city's judges are not long out of law school.</p>
        <p>"It's a calling," said Monika Yaniec, a 34-year-old judge in the criminal courts. "We started off with idealistic ideas. That's why we're here."</p>
        <p>But both she and her boss, Maciej Schulz, 32, the administrative judge responsible for 67 judges in the city's criminal, civil and family courts, complained that they were overwhelmed with the volume of cases.</p>
        <p>In the criminal section of his court, Mr. Schulz said, there should be 20 judges but there are only 14 because 6 judges have quit over pay -- $580 a month compared with the $2,000 minimum that former judges can earn a month as lawyers in the private sector.</p>
        <p>The labor courts have been swamped with cases stemming from sweeping layoffs in the last five years and the family courts are backlogged with alimony cases caused by unemployed men unable to meet their obligations, he said.</p>
        <p>The Communist criminal code is still operative, and that frustrates both the police and citizens.</p>
        <p>Under the old law, joy riding is not a crime, even if it is not your car, so that is the defense of many thieves. And possession of narcotics is not illegal if they are for personal use, an easy case for criminals to make.</p>
        <p>Poland's pains with making the transition to a civil society are compounded, some lawyers say, by a lack of knowledge among Poles about the basics of the rule of law.</p>
        <p>The ignorance has been fostered by the failure of successive Governments in the last five years to agree on a constitution, which would decide which is supreme, the courts or the legislature.</p>
        <p>At the moment, Parliament has the power, with a two-thirds vote, to overturn rulings by the nation's highest court, the Constitutional Tribunal. In April, for example, Parliament overturned a decision by the court that declared last year's income tax rates illegal.</p>
        <p>"Parliament basically said: Go to hell with the highest court," said Grzegorz Domanski, a Warsaw University law professor. "In the minds of the average Pole, it was like an announcement that everything in this country is political. The idea that I am a citizen, I'm aware of my liberties and I will not allow anyone to violate them and I know where to find justice -- this is phantasmagoria in the eyes of the average Pole."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
