<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rising Storm on Hong Kong's Vanishing Harbor</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="769942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HONG KONG</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GARGAN, EDWARD A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED7163EF93AA25755C0A963958260" item-length="1159" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rising Storm on Hong Kong's Vanishing Harbor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD A. GARGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GARGAN, EDWARD A</byline>
      <dateline>HONG KONG, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When she was small, Romy Chiu remembers, the waters of Hong Kong harbor lapped against the sea wall at the end of Man Yuen Street, a claustrophic alley of noodle stalls, engine shops and her family's Vietnamese restaurant.</p>
        <p>"There was always the harbor there," she said, scrubbing a plastic table top with a damp rag before clapping down a pair of plastic bowls, chopsticks and a sheaf of paper napkins. "We ran down there as kids to watch the boats. It's long gone now."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When she was small, Romy Chiu remembers, the waters of Hong Kong harbor lapped against the sea wall at the end of Man Yuen Street, a claustrophic alley of noodle stalls, engine shops and her family's Vietnamese restaurant.</p>
        <p>"There was always the harbor there," she said, scrubbing a plastic table top with a damp rag before clapping down a pair of plastic bowls, chopsticks and a sheaf of paper napkins. "We ran down there as kids to watch the boats. It's long gone now."</p>
        <p>Now, vast dunes and plains of sand and rock stretch from the end of her street, far into Hong Kong's harbor. At the end of Man Yuen Street, a solitary concrete bollard stands. It will never again feel the tug of a ship's mooring line, for glass and cement towers are planned for these fields of sand.</p>
        <p>If there is one immutable legacy that British colonialism will leave when China takes over Hong Kong in two years, it is the radical reshaping of its harbor, which separates Hong Kong island from Kowloon. The reshaping is taking place with an accelerating fervor in the Government's dying days.</p>
        <p>"If this city is going to cope with pressures from over the border, it has got to have more land," said Edward G. Pryor, the principal Government planner who has overseen reshaping the harbor.</p>
        <p>But there has been little public discussion of the plan, and now legislators, urban planners and environmental groups are joining a rising storm of opposition.</p>
        <p>"The Government is ramming things down people's throats," said Winston K. S. Chu, a prominent lawyer and dissenting member of the Town Planning Board, a secretive body with absolute authority on many facets of Hong Kong's development. "Hong Kong people will lose their natural heritage for all time. The damage can never be undone."</p>
        <p>The harbor, formally called Victoria Harbor, has historically been a central feature of Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>Toward the end of the last century, the intellectual Wang Tao fled China to Hong Kong to escape rebel fighting.</p>
        <p>"The sea stretches out before you all the way to the endless horizon," he wrote of his new home. "Vast networks of mountains appear like little mounds. Ships and boats of every description lie at anchor in neat rows in the harbor. Such sights are a delight to the eye as well as the mind."</p>
        <p>David Lung is one of Hong Kong's most noted practitioners of the traditional Chinese art of geomancy, which assigns beneficial or malevolent qualities to the shape and positioning of buildings, land, mountains and water. He is deeply worried about the vanishing harbor.</p>
        <p>"It restricts the water flow and changes Hong Kong's natural shape," said Mr. Lung, who regularly advises the Hong Kong Shanghai Bank, the largest in the colony. "Traditionally, we think of water as bringing fortune to Hong Kong. And while I cannot give an accurate assessment yet since not all the reclamation is done, we can see this as restricting fortune from flowing into Hong Kong."</p>
        <p>The harbor, which in places is more than a mile wide, is to be shrunk to a narrow channel. The serrated, twisting shoreline is to be smoothed and straightened, its islands absorbed like errant globules of mercury.</p>
        <p>"The issue is very psychological," said Iris S. Y. Tam, the new president of the Hong Kong Institute of Planners, a professional association. "The water, the harbor itself, is part of our heritage."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pryor and other members of the tiny elite that governs this colony say they know what is best.</p>
        <p>"At the end of the day, you're going to have a far better city than we have now," said Mr. Pryor.  "When you know you're right, you have to stick to your guns."</p>
        <p>Increasingly, though, many people in Hong Kong not only believe that the Government is wrong, but they are also determined to do something about it.</p>
        <p>"We have an executive-led Government and a paternalistic Government," said Christine Loh, a member of the Legislative Council, which passes laws for the territory but has no oversight over planning.</p>
        <p>"It's come to a physical stage where people can see the sea disappearing and are now saying, 'What's going on?' They have a plan that changes the face of Hong Kong. There was never any debate or discussion for the whole plan, only bits and pieces."</p>
        <p>Over the last hundred years, nearly 21 square miles of land has been reclaimed from the sea around Hong Kong, including some along the harbor front. But the current plans to reclaim five square miles from the harbor for broad new highways, towering office buildings, housing and some park land have drawn public attention as never before. Many people charge that the details are tucked in huge planning documents that have not yet been made public.</p>
        <p>"Winston Chu recently showed me a map with the latest reclamation proposals in their entirety," said Peter Hills, who heads the Center for Urban Planning and Environmental Management at Hong Kong University. "It's staggering what's on the cards.</p>
        <p>"There is a growing concern among some groups that the harbor is disappearing. There is a feeling that Hong Kong without the harbor is not Hong Kong."</p>
        <p>Foreign urban planners are also concerned. "It's a fortress Hong Kong mentality," said Aprodicio Laquian, a professor of urban planning at the University of British Columbia in Canada and a frequent consultant to the United Nations and World Bank. "What the Government doesn't want to admit is that they don't want to expand toward the Chinese border.</p>
        <p>"They really need to rethink what they are doing here."</p>
        <p>Robert D. Pope, the director of lands for the Government, dismissed such criticism. "It's absolute rubbish," he said. "For Hong Kong to maintain its position as a finanical center, it has to provide facilities," he said. "We shouldn't wash our hands and say it all goes to southern China."</p>
        <p>Although nothing can be done about the two and a half square miles filled in already under current plans, there are increasingly strong signals of disapproval from China as well.</p>
        <p>"This is stupid," said David Chu, a member of the Beijing-appointed Preliminary Working Committee that is advising China on the turnover of sovereignty. "This is because of 150 years of British colonialism. We're doing everything possible to stop it."</p>
        <p>But the opposition has come principally from Hong Kong's own civic leaders. "We would like the Government to review the reclamation to leave more of the water," said Ms. Tam, the planning institute president. The Government says we don't need the water for Hong Kong's economy. We are saying that we are not talking only about economic activity."</p>
        <p>For Mr. Chu, of the Town Planning Board, who can see dredgers and land fillers from his office window, time is running short.</p>
        <p>"This time I have to stand up," he said. "The most important things in life are the things you cannot put your hands on. This is what Hong Kong lacks. It lacks a spirit, if I may say so, a soul. Filling in this harbor would be like filling in the Hudson River."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
