<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 9-Year-Old Suspect in Court: 'Traumatized,' Her Lawyer Says</title>
    <meta content="03GIRL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1677192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0DA1738F931A35755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 9-Year-Old Suspect in Court: 'Traumatized,' Her Lawyer Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WILSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 9-year-old girl accused of stabbing her 11-year-old friend to death in a tussle over a ball was taken from her round-the-clock suicide watch, dressed in a black dress with matching shoes and driven to Brooklyn Family Court yesterday, where her lawyer entered pleas of not guilty to charges of manslaughter.</p>
        <p>The killing happened on Monday in her family's seventh-floor apartment in the Linden Houses in East New York, Brooklyn. The police said the 9-year-old stabbed Queen Washington, 11, once in the chest with a steak knife.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 9-year-old girl accused of stabbing her 11-year-old friend to death in a tussle over a ball was taken from her round-the-clock suicide watch, dressed in a black dress with matching shoes and driven to Brooklyn Family Court yesterday, where her lawyer entered pleas of not guilty to charges of manslaughter.</p>
        <p>The killing happened on Monday in her family's seventh-floor apartment in the Linden Houses in East New York, Brooklyn. The police said the 9-year-old stabbed Queen Washington, 11, once in the chest with a steak knife.</p>
        <p>The girl has been charged with manslaughter, assault and weapons charges in a juvenile delinquency petition filed by the city's Law Department. She is being held at a nonsecure facility in Queens, said her lawyer, Nicole Barnum. She was returned there yesterday, with the next hearing in the case set for June 17.</p>
        <p>''She's very young, very immature, and has a very limited capacity to understand what happened and the magnitude of what happened and the process she's now in, and I think she's very traumatized by being separated from her mother because she's such a young girl,'' Ms. Barnum said after the hearing. ''She's very confused. I think it's important to remember she's a 9-year-old girl who is now separated from all emotional support from the people she has in her life and all the people who love her.''</p>
        <p>During the hearing, the prosecutor, Suzette Rivera, an assistant corporation counsel, asked that the child undergo a psychological evaluation. Ms. Barnum said she already had.</p>
        <p>''She is not a threat to herself at this time,'' Ms. Barnum said, adding that the girl is under a 24-hour watch. ''She's not alone at any time.''</p>
        <p>The girl's mother stood silently with two relatives during the hearing. On Monday, the mother had gone upstairs in her building to borrow a comb for the girl when the fight with Queen took place. Neighbors said she had been gone only a few minutes.</p>
        <p>At the end of the hearing, Judge Jane Pearl leaned forward, spoke the girl's name, and told her, ''Take care of yourself.''</p>
        <p>The viewing for Queen will take place from 6 to 9 p.m. today at Holy Tabernacle Church of Deliverance in Bushwick. The funeral will be at 9 a.m. tomorrow at the church, with burial to follow at Rosehill Cemetery in Linden, N.J.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
