<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drabek Aims to Wrap It Up, but Avery Has Own Plan</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="480791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PITTSBURGH PIRATES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL LEAGUE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ATLANTA BRAVES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DRABEK, DOUG</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Pittsburgh Pirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DA123AF935A25753C1A967958260" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drabek Aims to Wrap It Up, but Avery Has Own Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doug Drabek, an ice pack bound to the back of his left leg, sat on a sofa in the Pirates' clubhouse today, having a catch with his 3-year-old son, Kyle.</p>
        <p>Only a few feet away, Randy Tomlin, 5 feet 11 inches tall, was playing one-on-one basketball with 6-6 Roger Mason, on the players' makeshift clubhouse court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Doug Drabek, an ice pack bound to the back of his left leg, sat on a sofa in the Pirates' clubhouse today, having a catch with his 3-year-old son, Kyle.</p>
        <p>Only a few feet away, Randy Tomlin, 5 feet 11 inches tall, was playing one-on-one basketball with 6-6 Roger Mason, on the players' makeshift clubhouse court.</p>
        <p>This was an off day in the National League Championship Series, and the Pittsburgh pitchers lingered after a voluntary workout, playing their own kind of games instead of pondering their playoff status. They lead the Atlanta Braves three games to two, and they will try to join the Minnesota Twins in the World Series by winning the sixth game Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Drabek will pitch the sixth game for the Pirates against Steve Avery. Tomlin pitched the fourth game in Atlanta, the one in which the Pirates turned the playoff around. They had lost the third game, 10-3, and the Braves had peppered Tomlin for two runs in the first inning the next day, indicating another rout.</p>
        <p>"That was one time coaches and the manager didn't have to say anything," Ray Miller, the Pirate pitching coach, said today, playing neither catch nor basektball. "The players came into the dugout screaming. Everybody was frustrated. The general consensus was that's enough."</p>
        <p>The players were not speaking specifically to or of Tomlin, but he nevertheless felt the sting of their words.</p>
        <p>"Anytime I give up runs, I take it personally," he said after his game, still breathing hard. "I do my best to keep us in the game, give us a chance to win. The feeling was we couldn't afford to let this happen again. We had to bear down and do whatever it took to win."</p>
        <p>In the next five innings against Tomlin and two each against Bob Walk and Stan Belinda, the Braves did not score any more runs. In nine innings against Zane Smith and Mason on Monday, the Braves scored no runs. For the first time this year, the Braves had failed to score a run in 18 innings over 2 games. Blunt Pirates</p>
        <p>And in their own park, where after their 10-3 victory, Greg Olson, the Braves catcher, said: "We knew we'd come here and hit the ball well. We didn't know we would score that many runs, but coming here was the key."</p>
        <p>But the maligned Pirates' pitchers blunted the key, wiping out the advantage the Braves felt they had. A series that seemed headed in the definite direction of the Braves suddenly veered sharply toward the Pirates.</p>
        <p>"That's why you can't say those things," Miller said, referring to Olson's comments. "You got to keep your mouth shut. I picked up the paper and Olson has a column saying they're going to the World Series."</p>
        <p>It wasn't the words, which appeared in a column Olson is writing for an Atlanta newspaper, that served as a wakeup call. It was that two-run burst in the first inning against Tomlin.</p>
        <p>"I think everybody got mad," Miller said. "It was the first time in the series they were teed off. We won a lot of games this year and we're proud of ourselves. It was like a boxer who trains hard for a fight, then gets hit on the nose early in the fight and is stunned and just standing there. He needs something to get him going. I guess we did, too. It was like a trainer throwing a cold bucket of ice in our face." Stifle the Opposition</p>
        <p>Except for the 10-run game, the Braves have not scored many runs. They got one each in splitting the first and second games, two in the fourth game and none in the fifth. It is now up to Drabek to continue stifling the Braves.</p>
        <p>Drabek pitched six shutout innings in the first game, leaving only after he strained his left hamstring trying to turn a double into a triple. He would normally have pitched the fifth game, but the injury forced a delay.</p>
        <p>"I'm a lot better," he said. "As of now, there's no question I'll pitch tomorrow."</p>
        <p>Drabek experienced a positive sign Monday when he threw seriously for the first time since hurting himself. In his pitching delivery, his right knee touched the ground.</p>
        <p>"I always do that," Drabek said. "That was one thing I wanted to see if I could do yesterday, and I was able to do it."</p>
        <p>Miller explained that for Drabek's knee to scrape the ground, he has to be able to extend his left leg fully. If the hamstring were not healed, he wouldn't be able to extend the leg.</p>
        <p>The Braves won't be watching Drabek's legs. His right arm will be difficult enough. They could use more frequent hitting from such players as Terry Pendleton (.190 and one run batted in), Lonnie Smith (.222 and two runs scored), Ron Gant (two r.b.i.) and David Justice (two r.b.i.). Olson has been the Braves' only consistent hitter, batting .353 and driving in three runs.</p>
        <p>The Pirates, on the other hand, have Jay Bell hitting .476, Steve Buechele .375 and Bobby Bonilla .353. They do not have Barry Bonds hitting at all. The man who batted .167 in last year's playoff against Cincinnati has three hits, two of them infield singles, in 20 times at bat for a .150 average. He has driven in no runs and he has not had a hit in 13 times at bat with runners on base.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
