<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peggy Guggenheim's Grandsons Challenge Museum's Managers</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="480768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GUGGENHEIM, SOLOMON R, FOUNDATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GUGGENHEIM, PEGGY, COLLECTION (VENICE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIDING, ALAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUGGENHEIM, PEGGY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D8163BF935A25753C1A967958260" item-length="1333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peggy Guggenheim's Grandsons Challenge Museum's Managers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIDING, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The question might well have amused Peggy Guggenheim as she held court in Venice in her later years: Would she like to be remembered most for her stormy life as a lover of art and artists, or for her extraordinary collection of Cubist, Surrealist and modern paintings?</p>
        <p>Now the question has become topical because, 12 years after her death at the age of 81, her three grandsons have decided to protest the way the owners of the collection, the New York-based Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation, are treating her memory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The question might well have amused Peggy Guggenheim as she held court in Venice in her later years: Would she like to be remembered most for her stormy life as a lover of art and artists, or for her extraordinary collection of Cubist, Surrealist and modern paintings?</p>
        <p>Now the question has become topical because, 12 years after her death at the age of 81, her three grandsons have decided to protest the way the owners of the collection, the New York-based Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation, are treating her memory.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the grandsons, Nicolas and David Helion and Sandro Rumney, children of her only daughter, Pegeen, are planning legal action unless the foundation agrees to run the Peggy Guggenheim Museum in the Palazzo Veneir dei Leoni in Venice according to what they contend were her wishes.</p>
        <p>"If it's just going to be one more modern art museum, who cares?" Mr. Rumney, himself an art dealer, said in a recent interview at his Paris home. "The only purpose is to show her life and personality. But the museum has lost all its originality now. Half the pieces are missing. Its spirit has gone."  Museum or House?</p>
        <p>The Guggenheim Foundation disagrees, insisting that in managing the museum, in what for 30 years served as Peggy Guggenheim's home, it has remained faithful to her intentions. "It is clear she intended it to be a museum rather than kept as a house," said Michael Govan, the foundation's deputy director.</p>
        <p>That, then, is the issue in contention: What were her wishes and what were her instructions? Has the Guggenheim Foundation simply swallowed up her collection as part of its own ambitious growth strategy? Or are the grandsons trying to exercise a power over the collection that Peggy herself surrendered?</p>
        <p>The grandsons do not challenge her intention to donate both the palazzo and the collection to the foundation that carries her uncle's name. But they note that, in her memoirs, "Out of This Century: Confessions of an Art Addict," she wrote: "The terms were that the collection remain in Venice intact in my name to be administered by them. Nothing was to be removed."</p>
        <p>The foundation, in contrast, argues that nothing in the terms of the donation prohibits it from storing some of the collection or from including other paintings in temporary exhibitions organized by the foundation abroad, as it has done this year while the New York museum is undergoing restoration. (In addition to the $24 million renovation of the museum's building by Frank Lloyd Wright, the Guggenheim also plans to create a branch museum in the SoHo section of New York City and to build branch museums in Salzburg, Austria, and Bilbao, Spain. It has also offered to operate the Massachusetts Museum of Contemporary Art in North Adams, Mass.)  Advanced Standards Cited</p>
        <p>The foundation's director, Thomas Krens, has written that the museum in Venice was transformed in the 1980's "from a private collection housed in an unfinished Venetian palazzo into a modern art museum operating in accordance with the most advanced professional standards of museum operation."</p>
        <p>On one thing, at least, the two sides do agree: Peggy Guggenheim bequeathed a 326-piece collection that brings together works by a dazzling array of the best European and American artists and sculptors who were active between the 1930's and 1950's.</p>
        <p>Although she only became an art patron in 1938 at the age of 40, by the time she installed herself in the 18th-century palazzo beside Venice's Grand Canal in 1949, her collection was already huge, the result of a flurry of buying -- "one painting a day" -- before Paris fell to German troops in May 1940.</p>
        <p>With leading artists as friends and lovers and, in one case, Max Ernst, a former husband, Peggy Guggenheim turned her palazzo into an avant-garde salon that more than once shocked Venice's Renaissance soul. When she died, she was buried in the small garden of the museum.</p>
        <p>In looking to bolster their case that she had planned the palazzo as her memorial, her grandsons have gathered statements from various people who knew Peggy Guggenheim. And these were mentioned in a draft lawsuit the grandsons sent to Peter Lawson Johnston, the foundation's chairman, in July. 'Sadness and Disappointment'</p>
        <p>"The numerous notorious changes to Peggy Guggenheim's clearly expressed wishes have proved a source of great sadness and disappointment to us over the years," the grandsons said in an accompanying letter. "We had, of course, hoped that by bringing our unhappiness to your attention you would seek to bring the collection back in line with Peggy's wishes."</p>
        <p>They also recalled they had been "deeply shocked" by the earlier removal of what they described as their own mother's "memorial," a room dedicated by Peggy Guggenheim to her daughter after she died in 1967, in which 12 of Pegeen's own paintings, glass sculptures and personal objects had been collected.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rumney said that the downstairs room had disappeared to make room for office space and that, while he agreed that the building needed modernization to serve as a museum, he and his brothers objected that Pegeen's paintings were rarely on display.</p>
        <p>Other causes for complaint, he went on, were the "disappearance" of furniture and many African and Asian primitive objects; the foundation's decision not to display the whole art collection; frequent loans of important paintings to special exhibitions, and the transformation of the entrance to the museum.</p>
        <p>"The entrance was where Peggy liked to be photographed," the 33-year-old Mr. Rumney said. "It had Picasso's 'Girls With a Toy Boat,' Giacometti's 'Piazza' and a Calder mobile. Now it's used for selling catalogues, postcards and T-shirts."</p>
        <p>Responding to the letter addressed to Mr. Johnston, Mr. Krens wrote that he had been "quite surprised and shocked" to learn of the threatened legal action. The current installation in the museum was only temporary, he continued, while some works from the collection were traveling.</p>
        <p>"We expect to reinstall the palazzo in its more familiar form as soon as that exhibition tour is concluded," he said, adding that once this was done, "I hope that this issue can be resolved."</p>
        <p>Speaking on behalf of Mr. Krens, who did not make himself available to be interviewed, Mr. Govan said that the foundation had always sought to maintain good relations with Peggy Guggenheim's family and noted that some of Pegeen's paintings had been displayed from time to time. "Some are up now," he added.</p>
        <p>He also said he hoped that primitive objects now in storage would soon be on display again and he recalled that Mr. Krens had himself indicated that he would like to see the commercial activities of the museum removed from its entrance.</p>
        <p>But he stressed that the idea was never to re-create Peggy Guggenheim's house as a homage to her, not least because she had always expressed pleasure that her collection had found a home in an institution that was associated with her family and that could handle it professionally.  A Government Guarantee</p>
        <p>"The foundation has spent close to $20 million preserving the collection over the past 12 years," Mr. Govan went on. "That's a measure of our commitment. From a technical point of view, the museum is one of the best in Italy, which is not easy if you remember it is sitting on the Grand Canal."</p>
        <p>He said the integrity of the collection was guaranteed not only by the foundation but also by the Italian Government. "We work very closely with the Italian authorities," he said. "But it's clear that Peggy expected the works to travel from time to time. She herself showed the collection in New York."</p>
        <p>The grandsons, though, say they are not satisfied with the response and insist they will start legal action this month unless the foundation shows willingness to change its management of the museum. "I maintain that Peggy's collection is a creation in itself," Mr. Rumney said, "and it should be treated as such."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
