<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fixing Social Security Should Come Before Any Surplus Free-for-All, President Says</title>
    <meta content="28SOCI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="STATE OF THE UNION: DOMESTIC PLANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">State of the Union Message</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Family Leaves</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Institutes of Health</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Family Leaves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">State of the Union Message (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E7D71F3BF93BA15752C0A96E958260" item-length="1919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fixing Social Security Should Come Before Any Surplus Free-for-All, President Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton outlines domestic programs in State of Union address; urges Congress not to spend any budget surplus until resolving Social Security's looming financial problems; seeks to avoid partisan fight on issue; asks Congress to extend reach of 1993 law to guarantee family and medical leave for 10 million more workers; proposes major spending increases by National Institutes of Health on biomedical research; proposes raising institute's budget by $1.15 billion next year and 50 percent over five years; urges Congress to let people age 55 to 64 buy Medicare coverage; urges Congress to back his new package of child care proposals; graphs (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Edging into one of the most politically combustible issues facing the nation, President Clinton urged Congress tonight not to spend any budget surpluses the Federal Government might enjoy in coming years until the two parties solve the Social Security system's looming financial problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton proposed no specific remedies for Social Security, and he stopped short of insisting that the entire fiscal windfall go toward shoring up the retirement program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Edging into one of the most politically combustible issues facing the nation, President Clinton urged Congress tonight not to spend any budget surpluses the Federal Government might enjoy in coming years until the two parties solve the Social Security system's looming financial problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton proposed no specific remedies for Social Security, and he stopped short of insisting that the entire fiscal windfall go toward shoring up the retirement program.</p>
        <p>But he sought to convince Republicans of his intention to avoid partisan warfare over an issue that has economic implications across the generations and a tendency to expose vast ideological divides about the responsibilities of the Government and citizens.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton pledged to work with Congress to enact legislation next year to deal with the retirement system's potential insolvency. And he argued that the responsible course for the nation would be to address Social Security before indulging in a free-for-all of new spending and tax cuts made possible by the coming era of fiscal plenty.</p>
        <p>''Let us say to all Americans watching tonight, whether you're 70 or 50 or whether you just started paying into the system, Social Security will be there when you need it,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''Let us make this commitment: Social Security first. Let's do that, together.''</p>
        <p>As a symbol of his willingness to tackle the issue and share any political pain, Mr. Clinton said he would lead public meetings around the country this year to discuss why Social Security has to be changed and to stimulate a debate over which of a host of options would be best.</p>
        <p>Republicans said they welcomed the President's fiscally conservative approach and his willingness to speak out on Social Security. But they saw a political motive in Mr. Clinton's call to postpone using any  surplus for tax cuts.</p>
        <p>And with memories still fresh of how Democrats have made political weapons out of previous Republican-led efforts to address financial problems in entitlement programs, they remained wary that the President and Congressional Democrats would turn the Social Security issue against them in this year's elections.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's proposals on Social Security were among an array of domestic policy initiatives he outlined, including raising the minimum wage, expanding Medicare health care coverage to people ages 55 to 64 and improving access to child care. He called for a new push to reach a settlement with tobacco companies over liability for the health damage caused by smoking, and he signaled a plan that the Administration will unveil on Wednesday to overhaul the  Internal Revenue Service.</p>
        <p>Social Security will pay out about $100 billion less in benefits this year than it takes in from payroll taxes and interest income on the Government bonds it holds, and on the Government's books the system has about $650 billion set aside to pay future benefits.</p>
        <p>But when the 76 million-member baby boom generation begins retiring in large numbers in 2010, Social Security's financial strength will erode rapidly. By 2019 the system will begin eating into its reserves to pay benefits. By 2029 it will exhaust all its reserves, and the revenues it will take in from payroll taxes are projected to meet only 75 percent of its promised benefit payments, leaving the system technically insolvent.</p>
        <p>White House officials have been debating for months how they could use the rapidly improving fiscal situation to begin dealing with Social Security. Gene Sperling, the White House economic policy adviser, said the Administration now expected  budget surpluses totaling $200 billion over the next five years.</p>
        <p>Allocating the entire surplus to shoring up Social Security could add 8 to 15 years to the system's solvency, studies by the White House have shown. But Administration officials have concluded that solving Social Security's problems would ultimately have to involve a national debate over a variety of possible fixes.</p>
        <p>The fixes include increasing payroll taxes, raising the retirement age and cutting benefits. But the debate will also encompass proposals to rethink Social Security's structure and the nature of the Government's commitment to providing retirement security.</p>
        <p>One camp, which includes many Democrats and organizations representing the elderly, wants to preserve the current system. Another, made up largely but not exclusively of conservatives, wants to give more freedom and responsibility to individuals for their retirement savings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's advisers have made clear that he will not accept the most radical proposals for changing the system into something like a giant 401(k) program. But they said he had  not ruled out a compromise that would allow individuals to put part of their payroll taxes into a personal account.</p>
        <p>Family Leave</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton asked Congress to expand the reach of a 1993 law to guarantee family and medical leave for 10 million additional workers.</p>
        <p>Under the law, an eligible worker may take a maximum of 12 weeks of unpaid leave each year to recover from an illness or to care for a newborn child or a seriously ill relative. The law applies to companies with 50 or more employees, covering 58 percent of the private labor force, or 55 million workers. Administration officials said Mr. Clinton wanted to extend the requirements to companies with 25 to 49 employees.</p>
        <p>Donna R. Lenhoff, general counsel of the Women's Legal Defense Fund, welcomed the proposal and said it would not hurt small businesses. But Lonnie P. Taylor, senior vice president of the Chamber of Commerce of the United States, said: ''This proposal is ridiculous. It would impose a new burden, a new mandate, on small employers. The President is responding to the unions. He's throwing them a bone.''</p>
        <p>Health</p>
        <p>Saying that America was on the brink of breakthroughs in biomedical research, President Clinton tonight proposed major increases in spending for the National Institutes of Health.</p>
        <p>Congress provided $13.6 billion for the agency this year. Mr. Clinton asked for an increase of $1.15 billion, or 8.5 percent, next year. Moreover, Mr. Clinton said he wanted an increase of about 50 percent over the next five years, raising the agency's  budget to more than $20 billion in 2003. In Congress, there is bipartisan support for such an increase. Representative John Edward Porter, the Illinois Republican who is chairman of the Appropriations subcommittee responsible for biomedical research, said he wanted to double spending for the health institute in the next five years, and many lawmakers shared that goal.</p>
        <p>Congress has appropriated more than the President requested for the health institute in each of the last few years. Mr. Clinton's request thus becomes a floor on which Congress will build.</p>
        <p>''It's very heartening that the President has indicated his support for increased investment in science,'' said Dr. Jordan J. Cohen, president of the Association of American Medical Colleges. ''An even greater investment in biomedical research could be justified.''</p>
        <p>Within a decade, Dr. Cohen said, the fruits of such research will be available in new drug therapies to treat arthritis, childhood diabetes and multiple sclerosis. Moreover, he said, ''we will be able to counteract many of the genetic changes that lead to colon cancer and other major cancers before they accumulate and cause malignancy.''</p>
        <p>Even as researchers discover new cures, many patients have difficulty getting access to basic medical care. Mr. Clinton said that this year Congress should pass legislation to protect the rights of patients, especially those in health maintenance organizations.</p>
        <p>Noting that 160 million Americans were enrolled in H.M.O.'s and other managed care plans, Mr. Clinton said: ''These plans save money, and they can improve care. But medical decisions ought to be made by medical doctors, not insurance company accountants.''</p>
        <p>He urged Congress to enact a bill of rights for patients, stipulating: ''You have the right to know all your medical options, not just the cheapest. You have the right to choose the doctor you want for the care you need. You have the right to emergency room care, wherever and whenever you need it. You have the right to keep your medical records confidential.''</p>
        <p>H.M.O.'s, insurance companies and employers of all sizes have banded together to block such legislation, and they plan a $1 million advertising campaign to publicize their concerns. They contend that the guarantees proposed by Mr. Clinton would increase the cost of health care and health insurance, so that many employers would cut back coverage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton challenged Congress to pass comprehensive bipartisan legislation to reduce teen-age smoking. Such legislation, he said, should raise the cost of a pack of cigarettes by $1.50 over the next decade, ''with penalties on the tobacco industry if it keeps marketing to our children.''</p>
        <p>Medicare</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton called on Congress to open Medicare, which finances health care for people who are elderly or disabled, to people 55 to 64 years old.</p>
        <p>''It won't add a dime to the deficit,'' Mr. Clinton said of his Medicare proposal, ''but the peace of mind it will provide will be priceless.''</p>
        <p>Under the President's proposal, people 62 to 64 could buy Medicare coverage for premiums of $300 a month. They would have to pay a surcharge of $10 to $20 a month on top of the regular premiums they must pay on reaching 65 to help offset the costs of earlier coverage.</p>
        <p>People 55 and older who lose their health benefits because they are laid off from their jobs would also be allowed to buy into Medicare. They would have to pay premiums of $400 a month, considered sufficient to cover their costs, until they reach the current age of eligibility for Medicare, which is 65.</p>
        <p>Finally, the President would offer a new insurance option to retirees 55 and older who have lost health benefits promised by former employers. Such retirees could participate in the health plan of the company where they worked, but might be required to pay the full premium paid by the company and active workers, plus 20 percent to 25 percent.</p>
        <p>Child Care</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton asked Congress to support a package of child care proposals that he unveiled on Jan. 7.</p>
        <p>Under the proposals, which would cost $21.7 billion over five years, the Government would increase Federal subsidies for day care, so that two million children would eventually receive Federal aid. That is more than double the number who now benefit from such subsidies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also urged Congress to increase the income tax credit that parents can take for child care expenses. The White House said this proposal would eliminate income tax liability for most families with substantial child care expenses and with incomes less than twice the official poverty level (less than $33,000 a year for a family of four).</p>
        <p>The President also asked Congress to provide $800 million over the next five years to finance after-school care for up to 500,000 children a year.</p>
        <p>STATE OF THE UNION: DOMESTIC PLANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
