<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Meno and Sand Earn Right to Skate</title>
    <meta content="28OLYM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS: NAGANO 1998 -- 10 DAYS TO GO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1998)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Winter Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nagano (Japan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litsky, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meno, Jenni</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sand, Todd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Nagano</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4DF1F3BF93BA15752C0A96E958260" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Meno and Sand Earn Right to Skate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jenni Meno and Todd Sand will skate in Nagano Olympics in pairs for US figure skating team; other olympic notes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jenni Meno and Todd Sand will skate in the Nagano Olympics after all.</p>
        <p>Meno and Sand, who are married, are three-time United States champions and two-time world bronze medalists in pairs figure skating. They were heavy favorites to win one of the two Olympic berths by finishing first or second in the national championships.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jenni Meno and Todd Sand will skate in the Nagano Olympics after all.</p>
        <p>Meno and Sand, who are married, are three-time United States champions and two-time world bronze medalists in pairs figure skating. They were heavy favorites to win one of the two Olympic berths by finishing first or second in the national championships.</p>
        <p>But in warm-ups for those championships in Philadelphia on Jan. 9, Meno, on a throw double salchow, landed awkwardly on her right ankle and fell. The ankle was badly bruised and doctors feared it would fracture if not allowed to heal.</p>
        <p>Sand carried her from the building, and she received medical treatment. Later, they returned to the arena, and Meno's ankle was taped. They skated their final warm-up before their coach, John Nicks, persuaded them to withdraw.</p>
        <p>Kyoko Ina and Jason Dungjen won the national championship for the second consecutive year and automatically made the Olympic team. Officials from the United States Figure Skating Association gave the remaining berth to Meno and Sand rather than Shelby Lyons and Brian Wells, the inexperienced runner-ups, but they told Meno and Sand that they had to prove they would be competitive in the Games next month in Nagano, Japan.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, in Costa Mesa, Calif., Sand and Meno skated before five association judges. Nicks said that Meno had no problems landing a throw double axel and a throw triple salchow. She and Sand did so well that the officials approved them for the Olympics.</p>
        <p>''We did our long program for the committee,'' Meno said. ''We were able to do the throws, which have the most impact on the ankle. I wouldn't say I'm back to normal, but I'm getting stronger every day. I'm getting therapy two times a day. I know it may hurt when we compete in Japan.''</p>
        <p>Meno is 27 and Sand is 34. They have skated together for six years and finished fifth in the 1994 Olympics in Lillehammer, Norway. This season, they decided they had been traveling too much, so they competed only once before the nationals. ''We were probably skating better than we ever had,'' Meno said, ''so it was very disappointing in the nationals.''</p>
        <p>Now the disappointment has melted.</p>
        <p>''We took the doctor's advice,'' Nicks said, ''and reduced Jenni's impact work -- jumping, landings, lifts. Only in the last three or four days has Jenni let out. We are all very happy. We feel six teams can win the Olympic title.'' He made it clear that he was coaching one of those six teams.</p>
        <p>Freestyle Skiing Team Is Set</p>
        <p>Donna Weinbrecht of West Milford, N.J., who won a gold medal in the 1992 Olympics in Albertville, France, and Liz McIntyre of Winter Park, Colo., who won a silver in 1994 in Lillehammer, were named yesterday to the United States freestyle skiing team for the Nagano Olympics. They were among the five women and six men named for the moguls and aerials competitions. The team includes Eric Bergoust of Missoula, Mont., and Nikki Stone of Westborough, Mass., World Cup leaders who won aerials competitions last weekend in Canada.</p>
        <p>The 11 Olympians qualified by their showing in this season's World Cup and Gold Cup competitions.</p>
        <p>The team:</p>
        <p>Men's aerials -- Bergoust; Matt Chojnacki of Aurora, Colo.; Mariano Ferrario of Winston-Salem, N.C., and Britt Swartley of Blue Bell, Pa. Women's aerials -- Stone and Tracy Evans of Hornell, N.Y. Men's moguls -- Jonny Moseley of Tiburon, Calif., and Alex Wilson of Buffalo. Women's moguls -- Weinbrecht, McIntyre and Ann Battelle of Steamboat Springs, Colo.</p>
        <p>A Concerted Effort to Recruit Volunteers</p>
        <p>When is a volunteer a volunteer? A report from Japan says that Nagano's local government and private companies have drafted 13,000 employees to work as unpaid Olympic volunteers. The report from Kyodo News, published in the newspaper Yomiuri Shimbun, said that Olympic organizers asked for the help and even told some employers how many people to send.</p>
        <p>An unidentified local government official was quoted as having said, ''It is difficult to say no when you are asked to do something by your boss.''</p>
        <p>But an official from the organizers insisted that all the workers had agreed to work free.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS: NAGANO 1998 -- 10 DAYS TO GO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
