<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Governor Ignores Tradition In Replacing Appellate Judge</title>
    <meta content="28JUDG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991100"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Francis (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lerner, Alfred D (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E0DC1F3BF93BA15752C0A96E958260" item-length="323" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Governor Ignores Tradition In Replacing Appellate Judge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Jan. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George Pataki, after forcing out Francis T Murphy as chief appeals court judge for Manhattan and Bronx because of his liberal rulings, makes unusual reach across jurisdictional boundaries to appoint Queens Judge Alfred D Lerner to post (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After forcing out the chief appeals court judge for Manhattan and the Bronx because of his liberal rulings, Gov. George E. Pataki made an unusual reach across jurisdictional boundaries today to appoint a Queens judge to the post.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki's handling of the transition has been criticized by some lawyers as an unusually overt bid to steer the court in a more conservative direction, and also because the Governor ignored tradition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After forcing out the chief appeals court judge for Manhattan and the Bronx because of his liberal rulings, Gov. George E. Pataki made an unusual reach across jurisdictional boundaries today to appoint a Queens judge to the post.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki's handling of the transition has been criticized by some lawyers as an unusually overt bid to steer the court in a more conservative direction, and also because the Governor ignored tradition.</p>
        <p>For 20 years, Francis T. Murphy was presiding justice of the Appellate Division, First Department, one of four regional appellate courts. He reached the mandatory retirement age of 70 last year. Governors have usually allowed appellate justices to serve past 70 with a succession of  two-year appointments, though not as presiding justice. Mr. Pataki, who objected to Justice Murphy's decisions in criminal cases, did not exercise that option.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Pataki, a Republican, selected Justice Alfred D. Lerner, the top administrative judge in Queens, to replace Justice Murphy, a rare selection of an appellate judge from outside the court's region. Justice Lerner becomes the sole Republican on the 12-judge appellate bench in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''The Governor made the appointment on the basis of Justice Lerner's strengths,'' James McGuire, counsel to Mr. Pataki, said.</p>
        <p>Because Justice Lerner is 69, his term will be short.</p>
        <p>Last month, Michael A. Cardozo, president of the City Bar Association in New York, called forcing Justice Murphy into retirement ''a very unfortunate effort at judicial cleansing.'' But today he said there was ''no basis for criticism of the appointment'' of Justice Lerner.</p>
        <p>Justice Lerner has served since October on the Appellate Division, Second Department, which includes Queens, Brooklyn, Staten Island, Long Island and five counties north of New York City. He has been a Supreme Court justice in Queens since 1973, and the administrative judge since 1987. He was a state assemblyman for 14 years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
