<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Contempt From an Apartheid Leader</title>
    <meta content="28WED2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Botha, P W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DB1F3BF93BA15752C0A96E958260" item-length="493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Contempt From an Apartheid Leader</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds South Africa is right to try ex-Pres P W Botha for ignoring subpoenas to appear before panel probing apartheid-era abuses (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The apartheid regime that P. W. Botha ruled from 1978 to 1989 never permitted black South Africans to become judges. Now, in what must be one of his worst nightmares come to life, Mr. Botha is a defendant in a black magistrate's court. His trial, for ignoring subpoenas to testify before the Truth and Reconciliation Commission, has been criticized by Mr. Botha's supporters as an act of revenge on apartheid's most reviled and least repentant living figure. But Mr. Botha has defied the law and should be brought to justice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Botha filed 1,700 pages of written answers to questions by the Truth Commission, which is investigating apartheid-era abuses. But he is the only person who has ignored subpoenas to appear before the panel. He has said the Truth Commission is trying to humiliate him and that he will not apologize for apartheid, defending it as a ''struggle against the Marxist revolutionary onslaught.'' In a long speech to reporters after a court appearance last week he called on those ''opposed to the forces of chaos, Communism and Socialism'' to unite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The apartheid regime that P. W. Botha ruled from 1978 to 1989 never permitted black South Africans to become judges. Now, in what must be one of his worst nightmares come to life, Mr. Botha is a defendant in a black magistrate's court. His trial, for ignoring subpoenas to testify before the Truth and Reconciliation Commission, has been criticized by Mr. Botha's supporters as an act of revenge on apartheid's most reviled and least repentant living figure. But Mr. Botha has defied the law and should be brought to justice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Botha filed 1,700 pages of written answers to questions by the Truth Commission, which is investigating apartheid-era abuses. But he is the only person who has ignored subpoenas to appear before the panel. He has said the Truth Commission is trying to humiliate him and that he will not apologize for apartheid, defending it as a ''struggle against the Marxist revolutionary onslaught.'' In a long speech to reporters after a court appearance last week he called on those ''opposed to the forces of chaos, Communism and Socialism'' to unite.</p>
        <p>Mr. Botha's lawyers have also sought to have the judge handling this case, who is one of very few nonwhite judges in South Africa even today, replaced. They argue that the judge's command of the Afrikaans language may be insufficient. Their real motive appears to be to get a white judge who might be more sympathetic to Mr. Botha.</p>
        <p>Mr. Botha, who is 82, had a stroke in 1989, which led to his ouster by F. W. de Klerk, who presided over the dismantling of apartheid. Last September the commission's chairman, Archbishop Desmond Tutu, temporarily excused Mr. Botha from appearing because of a hip operation and the recent death of his wife. But Mr. Botha ignored two later subpoenas, even though he was walking with a cane by that time. Still, his health problems mean that if he is convicted he will probably receive only a fine. Since the case has been postponed until mid-April and the Truth Commission's mandate expires in June, it is possible he will never be made to testify.</p>
        <p>The Truth Commission is not a court, but it can compel witnesses to testify. It sought to question Mr. Botha about questions its members say he did not fully answer in his written submission. These include his knowledge of and possible complicity in state-sponsored acts such as the bombing of a church, torture in prisons and raids into neighboring countries. His testimony would be crucial for the historical record and for evaluating claims by lower officials that they were carrying out Government orders. Beyond that, South Africa must show that Mr. Botha is not above the law. He is not being tried for his oft-expressed contempt for the new South Africa, but for his contempt of court.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
