<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Politics Of Upper Manhattan</title>
    <meta content="l25city-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1704953"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E6DA1430F936A1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="320" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Politics Of Upper Manhattan</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It's difficult to sort through the conflicting emotions raised by the conflicting stories about Washington Heights and Inwood you featured on the front page of your Sept. 18 City section. But as the editor of the community newspaper for those neighborhoods, I feel it is my responsibility to try.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It's difficult to sort through the conflicting emotions raised by the conflicting stories about Washington Heights and Inwood you featured on the front page of your Sept. 18 City section. But as the editor of the community newspaper for those neighborhoods, I feel it is my responsibility to try.</p>
        <p>On the right side of the page was a terrific photo of the community gadfly George Espinal who, at 18, has already earned the moniker ''Mayor of Inwood.'' The portrait, with eyebrow cocked, brilliantly captured his driven sense of purpose. The corresponding article, ''Peach-Fuzz Pols,'' built on the image, filling out George's personality -- caught between caprice and conviction -- in three-dimensional strokes. The article also evoked a sense of life at the crossroads of Dyckman Street and Payson Avenue, where race and class mingle in uneasy gentrification.</p>
        <p>''A Race Lost, but a Bit of Lace Reveals a Latin Future,'' the ''Street Level'' column on the left side of the page, seemed to have been observed in a different neighborhood, written in a different era and published by a different newspaper. It purported that a Latino City Council candidate who held as a fund-raiser a party with erotic dancers at a local nightclub was a sign of the neighborhood's ''Latinization.''</p>
        <p>Tell me and my readers how this points to Northern Manhattan's ''Latin future.'' Is it because Latinos succumb to sexy politicking more than other voters, or can only Latino candidates get away with pitching sex at the polls?</p>
        <p>I have never seen a car hopping on its hydraulics on St. Nicholas Avenue or anywhere else in Washington Heights and Inwood. The new immigrant group affecting Northern Manhattan is not identified by the color of its skin but by the size of its down payment.</p>
        <p>Mike Fitelson  Washington Heights</p>
        <p>The writer is the editor of Manhattan Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
