<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Knows When to Fold 'Em</title>
    <meta content="25njBASHAW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1704823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E2D91730F936A1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Knows When to Fold 'Em</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRIAN P. MURPHY</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE MAY</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CURTIS BASHAW, who surprised many state officials several weeks ago when he announced that he was stepping down as executive director of the Casino Reinvestment Development Authority, will leave with his winnings intact despite his brief tenure and Democratic infighting over his successor.</p>
        <p>For one thing, the 45-year-old Mr. Bashaw, an owner of the tradition-rich and trendy Congress Hall Hotel in Cape May, is keeping a big toe in the water. He plans to parlay the experience he gleaned at the reinvestment agency as the chairman of a new nonprofit group, the Jersey Shore Tourism Corporation. About half of its $1 million budget for the next year will come from the casino authority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CURTIS BASHAW, who surprised many state officials several weeks ago when he announced that he was stepping down as executive director of the Casino Reinvestment Development Authority, will leave with his winnings intact despite his brief tenure and Democratic infighting over his successor.</p>
        <p>For one thing, the 45-year-old Mr. Bashaw, an owner of the tradition-rich and trendy Congress Hall Hotel in Cape May, is keeping a big toe in the water. He plans to parlay the experience he gleaned at the reinvestment agency as the chairman of a new nonprofit group, the Jersey Shore Tourism Corporation. About half of its $1 million budget for the next year will come from the casino authority.</p>
        <p>''I want to see my work bear fruit, and this will be one way I can do that,'' Mr. Bashaw said in a recent telephone interview from Tuscany, where he was on vacation. In his new position, he said, he will be able to continue to work ''to make the Jersey Shore a brand and destination that will compete with the Hamptons, Cape Cod and the Outer Banks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bashaw will serve without a salary as the chairman, but as he well knows, a rising tide lifts all boats. Work that creates a more economically vibrant Shore will probably enhance the profitability of his real estate business, Cape Advisors Inc., a partnership established with a financier, Craig D. Wood. The two partners are also involved in a hotel-to-condominium conversion adjacent to Congress Hall, along with David Von Savage, a co-owner of Congress Hall and the chairman of the Cape May County Republican Party.</p>
        <p>''I promised Craig that I would not do this job for more than a year or so, and it's been a year and a half now,'' Mr. Bashaw said of his role at the reinvestment authority. ''We have a lot to work on.''</p>
        <p>Contrary to rumors in the State House and among his supporters, Mr. Bashaw emphatically denied he would seek a position in the next administration in Trenton.</p>
        <p>''I've had a great time doing this, but I'm not in a financial position at this stage of my career when I can do this kind of work long term,'' he said. ''I am not putting my name out there. It would be presumptuous.''</p>
        <p>And although Mr. Bashaw, a Republican, left Democrats and Republicans alike praising his work at the reinvestment authority, he did create something of a political quandary by resigning, effective Sept. 30, rather than waiting until the end of the year, when a newly elected governor would have been able to make his own appointment to the influential $137,500-a-year post.</p>
        <p>With $180 million in assets, the Casino Reinvestment Development Authority is one of the three most important and best financed agencies in the state, along with the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey and the New Jersey Sports and Exposition Authority, which operates the Meadowlands.</p>
        <p>''That Democrats can't agree on who should replace me isn't really my problem,'' Mr. Bashaw said. ''My decision to resign was completely personal. I didn't think about the election. Governor Codey didn't ask me to step down. In fact, I think he would have been happy to have me stay.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey probably would have, since Mr. Bashaw's premature departure touched off a new and sharp-edged round of political gamesmanship between him and one of the most powerful Democrats in the state, George E. Norcross III, the putative party leader in South Jersey with whom he has tangled in the past.</p>
        <p>''There's no love lost between Codey and Norcross, and they both want to be able to control this appointment.'' said David Rebovich, a professor of political science at Rider University.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mr. Codey named the current labor commissioner, Thomas D. Carver, as the executive director of the reinvestment agency. His administration began circulating Mr. Carver's name as a potential successor within days of Mr. Bashaw's announced departure, drawing the criticism of several members of the agency. On Sept. 7, a day after Mr. Bashaw announced his intention to step down, some members of the 17-member authority board with ties to Mr. Norcross sent the agency's chairman, Vincent Giblin, a letter asking him to delay Mr. Bashaw's departure until the end of the year and allow a new governor to appoint an executive director in consultation with them.</p>
        <p>But last Monday, Mr. Codey tried to dismiss one of the board members who signed the letter, Linda Kassekert, a Camden County Democratic leader and the chairwoman of the state Casino Control Commission. In response, a Camden County Superior Court judge issued a temporary injunction to prevent her ouster, saying the governor could not dismiss an authority board member without a hearing; one has been set for Friday.</p>
        <p>The attorney general, Peter Harvey, has appealed that order. A spokesman for his office declined to comment on the judge's decision.</p>
        <p>Stirring the pot even more, 13 South Democratic legislators from South Jersey, led by State Senator John Adler, who is chairman of the Judiciary Committee, sent Mr. Codey a letter defending Mrs. Kassekert.</p>
        <p>''Linda sent an innocuous letter,'' said her lawyer, William Tambussi. ''This is nothing but political retaliation by the acting governor as a way to bully someone onto the board.''</p>
        <p>Declining to elaborate on the squabbling, Kelly Heck, a spokeswoman for Governor Codey, said simply, ''The governor felt it was time for a change.''</p>
        <p>The infighting provided a reminder of what made Mr. Bashaw an attractive appointment for Gov. James E. McGreevey in 2004: his business savvy and political independence.</p>
        <p>''Curtis was the perfect candidate,'' said Paul Fader, who was reviewing potential appointments to the state's boards and authorities at the time and is now Mr. Codey's chief counsel. ''We all knew his work.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bashaw got his start as Cape May hotelier with the Virginia Hotel, a venerable Victorian that he bought in 1989 and turned into a boutique hostelry.</p>
        <p>But the renovation of Congress Hall, a 107-room hotel at the southern end of Cape May's pedestrian mall, established Mr. Bashaw's reputation. The colonnaded Congress Hall is a Shore icon, with a 200-year history as a favorite vacation hideaway for senators, governors and several presidents.</p>
        <p>Although an intraparty battle is not one that Democrats relish in the middle of a gubernatorial campaign, that, as Mr. Bashaw said, is not his worry. But at the end of the day, politics is to Congress Hall what witches are to Salem.</p>
        <p>The hotel's name stems from the election of its founder, Thomas Hughes, to Congress in 1828. Later in the century, Congress Hall was host to Presidents James Buchanan, Franklin Pierce and Ulysses S. Grant; Benjamin Harrison made it his summer White House.</p>
        <p>Guests like Assemblyman Bill Baroni, a Republican from Hamilton, unblushingly call Congress Hall a ''great addition to the political world of New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>''Nobody sticks around in Trenton anymore, so you don't get to know people,'' Mr. Baroni said. ''But if I go down there, I can chat with people in this political oasis.''</p>
        <p>Dale Florio, a lobbyist and chairman of the Somerset County Republican Party, says he has made valuable contacts at Congress Hall. ''I can see someone there and get to know them a bit, and since I'm on vacation I keep it light, but I can follow up with a phone call later,'' Mr. Florio said. ''Curtis and David have done a great job of attracting people of both parties. I guess you could call it Trenton South.''</p>
        <p>Leonard Lance, the Senate Republican leader, recalls visiting the hotel as a child in the 1950's, when his father served in the State Senate with Charles Sandman, one of the hotel's owners at the time. ''He would invite the entire Senate to come down there for a weekend,'' Mr. Lance said. ''My brother and I learned to swim in their pool.''</p>
        <p>Political guests continue to find Mr. Bashaw's hotel a magnet. Just how much of one was illustrated in July when Mr. McGreevey, who is scarcely seen in public these days, strode into Congress Hall with a few friends during the Fourth of July weekend and headed to a corner of the Brown Room bar -- a high-ceilinged room right out of 1950's Havana, with rich chocolate walls and zebra-print rugs.</p>
        <p>Most bar patrons were too taken with their mojitos to notice the former governor along with James Fox, his onetime chief of staff and current deputy executive director of the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey; Mr. Fader; and Susan Bass Levin, who days earlier had left the State Department of Community Affairs, where she was commissioner, to become the chairwoman of Senator Jon S. Corzine's gubernatorial campaign.</p>
        <p>Like his guests, Mr. Bashaw has witnessed firsthand the value of a legacy.</p>
        <p>Another former governor, Christie Whitman, whose administration provided public financing for Congress Hall's seven-year $22 million renovation, came from Washington, where she headed the Environmental Protection Agency after stepping down as governor, to cut the ribbon at the hotel in the spring of 2002. Mr. Bashaw suggested inviting Mr. McGreevey, who had recently been sworn in as governor. But Mr. Von Savage, Mr. Bashaw's business partner, warned that would risk offending Ms. Whitman.</p>
        <p>After Mr. McGreevey learned he would not be invited, he booked a room at the hotel.</p>
        <p>When the new governor finally visited that October, Mr. Bashaw showed off Congress Hall. But by then, the dining room adjacent to the Harrison Room had been christened the Whitman Room.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
