<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Extend Control In Nassau and Suffolk</title>
    <meta content="09nassau" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/09/nyregion/09nassau.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1716269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2005 ELECTIONS: LONG ISLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">County Executives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comptrollers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sheriffs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brookhaven (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hempstead (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Kathleen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dillon, Denis (Dist Atty)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Steve (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suozzi, Thomas R (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foley, Brian X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tisch, Alfred (Sheriff)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DeMarco, Vincent F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weitzman, Howard S (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murray, Kate (Supervisor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Suozzi, Thomas R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Levy, Steve</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7D7153EF93AA35752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Extend Control In Nassau and Suffolk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Democrats Score Gains in Nassau and Suffolk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT; Reporting for this article was contributed by Faiza Akhtar, Peter C. Beller, Linda F. Burghardt, Valerie Cotsalas, Vivian S. Toy, Paul Vitello and David Winzelberg,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democrats score major election breakthroughs across Long Island, extending control of suburbs once solidly Republican; win county executive races in Nassau and Suffolk and majorities in county legislatures; Democrat Kathleen Rice leads longtime Nassau District Attorney Denis Dillon; Suffolk Democrats win Brookhaven with Brian X Foley for town supervisor and replace sheriff Alfred G Tisch with Conservative/Democrat Vincent F DeMarco; wins capitalize on County Exec Steve Levy's soaring popularity; photo; Nassau County Exec Thomas R Suozzi sweeps to victory along with Comptroller Howard Weitzman; Kate Murray re-elected supervisor of Hempstead, nation's most populous town and Republicans' last remaining bastion in Nassau (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Democrats scored major breakthroughs in local elections all across Long Island on Tuesday, extending their control of suburbs that for decades were almost exclusively Republican.</p>
        <p>Based on nearly complete returns, the Democrats appear to have won simultaneous control of both Nassau and Suffolk for the first time in history, with two Democratic county executives and Democratic majorities in both county's Legislatures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Democrats appear to have won simultaneous control of both Nassau and Suffolk for the first time in history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Democrats scored major breakthroughs in local elections all across Long Island on Tuesday, extending their control of suburbs that for decades were almost exclusively Republican.</p>
        <p>Based on nearly complete returns, the Democrats appear to have won simultaneous control of both Nassau and Suffolk for the first time in history, with two Democratic county executives and Democratic majorities in both county's Legislatures.</p>
        <p>A major upset appeared likely in Nassau, where the Democratic candidate for district attorney, Kathleen Rice, held a narrow but steady lead in nearly complete returns, apparently ousting the 30-year Republican incumbent, Denis Dillon.</p>
        <p>In Suffolk, the Democrats won a majority of the County Legislature for the first time in years. And for the first time in three decades they also took control of Brookhaven, the most populous town in Suffolk, long the seat of countywide Republican officials and power brokers.</p>
        <p>The possibility of Long Island as a statewide power base for Democrats, once unthinkable, emerged as Nassau's County executive, Thomas R. Suozzi, swept to a wide re-election victory that bolstered his hopes of propelling an expected bid for governor next year.</p>
        <p>''Either get on board or get out of the way,'' Mr. Suozzi said in his victory speech to cheering supporters, calling on them ''to help shake up Albany.''</p>
        <p>Nearly complete returns showed the Nassau Democrats keeping their slim 10 to 9 control of the County Legislature, though in a few districts the margins between apparent winners and losers were only a few hundred votes.</p>
        <p>In adjacent Suffolk, Democrats were savoring three big upsets.</p>
        <p>Nearly complete returns showed their party capturing control of the Suffolk County Legislature, with 10 Democratic seats to 8 for the Republicans. The Republicans currently control the legislature with 11 seats to 7 for the Democrats.</p>
        <p>In Brookhaven, the Democrat, Brian X. Foley apparently won the race for town supervisor, and three running mates were leading for Council seats, with the other three staying in Republican hands. Since the supervisor presides over Council meetings and votes, the Democrats would control, four to three.</p>
        <p>The Democrats campaigned on a theme of cleaning up corruption, after decades of scandals that led Brookhaven to be nicknamed Crookhaven.</p>
        <p>The third upset was the defeat of the Republican sheriff, Alfred C. Tisch, by Vincent F. DeMarco, a Conservative backed by the Democrats.</p>
        <p>Suffolk's Democratic candidates capitalized on County Executive Steve Levy's soaring popularity, based on his reputation for budgetary thrift and a hard line on illegal immigration. Though he is in the middle of his term and was not on the ballot, his party's candidates made liberal use of his picture, name and endorsement.</p>
        <p>In television commercials, Mr. Levy appealed to voters to give his party a majority in the Legislature to help enact more of his proposals.</p>
        <p>Demonstrating coattail strength in Nassau, Mr. Suozzi led the Democratic ticket, boosting Ms. Rice for district attorney.</p>
        <p>The incumbent, Mr. Dillon, a Democrat who years ago turned Republican because of his opposition to abortion, has been in office for three decades, Long Island's equivalent of Manhattan's long-time district attorney, Robert M. Morgenthau.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice, a former federal prosecutor, accused Mr. Dillon of being soft on drunk drivers, too easy in giving criminals -- including the disgraced superintendent in the Roslyn school corruption scandal -- plea deals, and compromised by his personal views on cases involving abortion protesters, all of which he denied. He was also criticized for not being more forceful on the Catholic church sex scandals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suozzi's running mate for county comptroller, Howard Weitzman, who was elected with him four years ago, scored a comfortable re-election. He beat back a stiff challenge from Republican Donald Clavin, who accused Mr. Weitzman of not scrutinizing the Suozzi administration, which had fiscal scandals that forced the resignations of two deputy county executives. But Mr. Weitzman said he had critiqued the administration and uncovered waste.</p>
        <p>With almost all of the vote counted, Mr. Suozzi had a margin of more than 20 points over his Republican opponent, Gregory Peterson -- an impressive showing, since Republicans still hold an enrollment edge.</p>
        <p>Nassau's police unions, frustrated by bitter contract bargaining and a reduced workforce, spent more than $500,000 on harsh television commercials and mailings aimed against Mr. Suozzi and his running mates.</p>
        <p>The battle for control of Nassau's Legislature came down to a few battleground districts, with furious campaigning and heavy spending by both sides and by the police unions. The targets were two Democratic incumbents, David Mejias in the Farmingdale area and Jeffrey Toback in Oceanside and the Five Towns. The Democrats went after two incumbent Republican candidates, Denise Ford in the Long Beach area and John Ciotti in the Elmont area. All four were re-elected.</p>
        <p>Despite his county victory, Mr. Suozzi was facing a rebuke from voters in his hometown, Glen Cove, the small city where he got his start as mayor. His choice for mayor, the Democratic incumbent Mary Ann Holzkamp, was threatened by a strong challenge by the county executive's own cousin, Ralph Suozzi, who ran as an independent. Ms. Holzkamp was Thomas Suozzi's hand-picked successor as mayor.</p>
        <p>In other local Nassau elections, Kate Murray handily won re-election as supervisor of Hempstead, the most populous town in America and the Republicans' remaining major bastion in Nassau. She defeated the Democrat, Harvey Levinson, the elected chairman of the Nassau Board of Assessors, who continues in that job.</p>
        <p>THE 2005 ELECTIONS: LONG ISLAND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
