<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; The success of 'Four Weddings' rings bells for Polygram's stock.</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="688394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">POLYGRAM NV</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FOUR WEDDINGS AND A FUNERAL (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DA1238F933A15756C0A962958260" item-length="692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; The success of 'Four Weddings' rings bells for Polygram's stock.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Geraldine Fabrikant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON March 18, Polygram used an unusual gimmick to lure audiences: the company gave moviegoers free admission to "Four Weddings and a Funeral" at a Manhattan theater if they showed up in wedding attire.</p>
        <p>Only a handful donned appropriate dress. But Polygram had no need to worry. "Four Weddings" is a certifiable hit. The humorous tale of a young man who endlessly attends his friends' weddings but eschews marriage for himself, has already taken in $34.8 million at the box office in the United States. Of that total, Polygram keeps roughly half, while theater owners receive the balance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON March 18, Polygram used an unusual gimmick to lure audiences: the company gave moviegoers free admission to "Four Weddings and a Funeral" at a Manhattan theater if they showed up in wedding attire.</p>
        <p>Only a handful donned appropriate dress. But Polygram had no need to worry. "Four Weddings" is a certifiable hit. The humorous tale of a young man who endlessly attends his friends' weddings but eschews marriage for himself, has already taken in $34.8 million at the box office in the United States. Of that total, Polygram keeps roughly half, while theater owners receive the balance.</p>
        <p>Using the Hollywood rule of thumb, Harold Vogel, who follows the company for Merrill Lynch &amp; Company, estimated that "Polygram will take in another $17 million overseas and about $35 million in video, cable and broadcast" revenues.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Polygram could make in excess of $20 million from the picture. If so, it will be the first major film hit from the Dutch company, which is still best known as a record company even though it has been making films for nearly three years. Last year, the film division of Polygram, which accounted for 5 percent of its total sales of $3.8 billion, lost $30 million. Philips Electronics N.V. owns some 79 percent of Polygram.</p>
        <p>The film business means large capital and risks. Companies can spend hundreds of millions to make movies. The average cost of a film today is $20 million and marketing is another $15 million. Unless a film does well at the box office in its first release, it rarely recovers even a small portion of the investment.</p>
        <p>That explains why Polygram's announcement in September 1991 that it was entering the film business prompted broad skepticism on Wall Street.  Lisbeth R. Barron, who follows media companies for S. G. Warburg &amp; Company, issued a report at the time that was highly critical of the move.</p>
        <p>But there are few film companies left to invest in these days now that Paramount is part of Viacom Inc. and Universal Pictures and Columbia are divisions of Japanese corporations. That means investors with an addiction to show business are looking more closely at Polygram and may be more willing to gamble on its venture in movies.</p>
        <p>The success of "Four Weddings and a Funeral" has had an important impact on the company's stock, analysts said. Its American depository receipts closed up 50 cents yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange, at $42.625, just off its 52-week of $42.875.</p>
        <p>David Londoner, a media analyst at Wertheim Schroder &amp; Company, says the hit has let investors feel that Polygram can at least tread water in the treacherous movie business. And Mr. Vogel of Merrill Lynch said, "More than anything, it is psychological."</p>
        <p>The usual fear among investors is that executives who lead their companies into the movie business have been lured by the glamour and are bound to fail. Companies like Cannon Pictures have done exactly that.</p>
        <p>So far, however, Polygram has managed to maintain a fairly disciplined approach. Its various production companies have stuck to low-budget films, and while Polygram has had no hits until now, it has had no expensive disasters. "Four Weddings," which was produced by Polygram's Working Title Pictures of Britain, cost a modest $5 million to make. It has also opened impressively in Britain, France and Australia. Comedies generally do not do well outside their native country because humor rarely travels, but "Four Weddings" appears to have to have caught the public's imagination in France and in Australia.</p>
        <p>With its record business remaining strong, Polygram can afford to take some chances with movies. Sales rose 12 percent last year, to $3.8 billion from $3.4 billion, and net income jumped 21 percent, to $316 million from $262 million.</p>
        <p>But not everyone is convinced that Polygram is doing well in the film business. Ms. Barron of S. G. Warburg says the company has no real game plan for its film division and may wind up in serious trouble. While Mr. Londoner is still impressed, he notes that the company's stock is already trading at about 20 times 1994 estimated earnings, putting a high multiple on the company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
