<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of Africa, and Back</title>
    <meta content="04WATC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980805T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1036670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENCE WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monkeys and Apes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Current Biology (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Nicholas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Caro-Beth (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Disotell, Todd R (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monkeys and Apes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E3DE163BF937A3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of Africa, and Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Nicholas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Caro-Beth Stewart and Dr Todd R Disotell conclude that early ape-like species dispersed out of Africa 20 million years ago, giving rise to gibbons, orangutans and other ape lineages; they think one of these descendant ape species moved back to Africa 10 million years ago, speciating into gorilla, chimp and hominid line that led to humans; they say their theory explains absence of ape fossils in Africa from 12 million to 10 million years ago, and predict that Arabian peninsula would be good place to explore for ape-like remains; their theory is in latest issue of Current Biology; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE human line has emerged from Africa not once but twice.</p>
        <p>That is the ingenious and far-reaching surmise proposed in the latest issue of Current Biology by Caro-Beth Stewart of the State University of New York at Albany and Todd R. Disotell of New York University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE human line has emerged from Africa not once but twice.</p>
        <p>That is the ingenious and far-reaching surmise proposed in the latest issue of Current Biology by Caro-Beth Stewart of the State University of New York at Albany and Todd R. Disotell of New York University.</p>
        <p>Their conclusion emerges from an attempt to make sense of the geographical distribution of living and fossil apes and Old World monkeys. This special branch of the mammalian tree originated in Africa but spread through Europe and Asia. The orangutan, for example, is found only in southeast Asia but its close cousins the chimpanzee and the gorilla live only in Africa.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stewart and Dr. Disotell drew up an evolutionary tree according to the best current evidence from molecular clocks and cladistics and then searched for the simplest pattern of dispersal that would explain the known distribution of the species.</p>
        <p>Their conclusion is that an early ape-like species dispersed out of Africa about 20 million years ago, giving rise to the gibbons, orangutans and other ape lineages. One of these descendant ape species must then have moved back to Africa about 10 million years ago, speciating into the gorilla, the chimp and the hominid line that led to humans.</p>
        <p>This scheme, the two scientists note, requires only two migrations, whereas the alternative of keeping the ape line permanently in Africa postulates six migrations out of Africa and the implausible condition of a continuously open, forested land bridge linking Africa and Asia via Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>The theory explains the absence of ape fossils in Africa from 12 million to 10 million years ago, and predicts that the Arabian peninsula would be a good place to explore for ape-like remains.</p>
        <p>The theory is not yet gospel, however. Its authors note that in earlier presentations their ideas have ''aroused vehement discourse.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Stewart said that similar proposals had been made before, but had been ignored. Paleoanthropologists who believed in a direct lineage between extinct African ape species like kenyapithecus and the hominids, she said, were deeply opposed to her thesis that ape evolution was occurring outside Africa at this period.</p>
        <p>SCIENCE WATCH  Correction:  August 5, 1998, Wednesday  Because of an editing error, an article in Science Times yesterday about the migration of early ape species omitted the final line. The last sentence, referring to Caro-Beth Stewart of the State University of New York, should have read, ''Paleoanthropologists who believed in a direct lineage between extinct African ape species like kenyapithecus and the hominids, she said, were deeply opposed to her thesis that ape evolution was occurring outside Africa at this period.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 5, 1998, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in Science Times yesterday about the migration of early ape species omitted the final line. The last sentence, referring to Caro-Beth Stewart of the State University of New York, should have read, ''Paleoanthropologists who believed in a direct lineage between extinct African ape species like kenyapithecus and the hominids, she said, were deeply opposed to her thesis that ape evolution was occurring outside Africa at this period.''</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
