<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="03DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1381023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DB103AF930A35757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>F.D.A. Permits Others To Re-Inspect Factories  Even if government inspectors have found widespread problems in pharmaceutical factories, the Food and Drug Administration sometimes approves new medicines to be made in those factories without inspecting them again by relying on company employees or consultants to verify that the problems have been fixed, the agency said.</p>
        <p>The practice came to light after a trade journal reported that the F.D.A. had approved Clarinex, Schering-Plough's new allergy drug, based on factory inspections done by consultants hired by the company. [Page C3.]</p>
        <p>Credit Suisse Unit Cuts 300 Jobs  Credit Suisse First Boston eliminated 300 executive jobs, including those of about 50 managing directors, as part of its aggressive campaign to trim costs. The job cuts, which the investment banking group's new chief, Adebayo Ogunlesi, left, had said last month were imminent, come amid a continuing slump on Wall Street. All told, Wall Street fired 43,300 people in the year ended in February. [C10.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>F.D.A. Permits Others To Re-Inspect Factories  Even if government inspectors have found widespread problems in pharmaceutical factories, the Food and Drug Administration sometimes approves new medicines to be made in those factories without inspecting them again by relying on company employees or consultants to verify that the problems have been fixed, the agency said.</p>
        <p>The practice came to light after a trade journal reported that the F.D.A. had approved Clarinex, Schering-Plough's new allergy drug, based on factory inspections done by consultants hired by the company. [Page C3.]</p>
        <p>Credit Suisse Unit Cuts 300 Jobs  Credit Suisse First Boston eliminated 300 executive jobs, including those of about 50 managing directors, as part of its aggressive campaign to trim costs. The job cuts, which the investment banking group's new chief, Adebayo Ogunlesi, left, had said last month were imminent, come amid a continuing slump on Wall Street. All told, Wall Street fired 43,300 people in the year ended in February. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Auto Sales Dropped 1.5% in March  Industry auto sales in the United States fell 1.5 percent in March from a year earlier, according to Ward's AutoInfoBank, a result that was on the optimistic side of most analysts' expectations in a healing economy. [C5.]</p>
        <p>$5 Billion Deal by Royal Dutch/Shell  Royal Dutch/Shell agreed to buy Enterprise Oil for $5 billion in cash. Royal Dutch/Shell is trying to catch up after sitting out a wave of consolidation. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Technology Drags Wall St. Lower  Technology stocks dragged Wall Street lower after Goldman, Sachs voiced caution on big-name companies like Microsoft. The Nasdaq composite index declined 58.22 points, or 3.1 percent, to 1,804.40. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 48.99 points, or 0.5 percent, to 10,313.71. The broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index decreased 9.78 points, or 0.9 percent, to 1,136.76. [C11.]</p>
        <p>The escalation of violence in the Middle East is undermining investor confidence that the recovering economy will lead to higher stock prices. Market Place. [C11.]</p>
        <p>Big Layoff Is Expected at WorldCom  WorldCom is expected to announce plans this week to cut about 7,000 jobs as it seeks to recover from a slowdown in sales and a federal inquiry into its accounting. [C11.]</p>
        <p>Monsanto and DuPont Settle Suits  Monsanto and DuPont agreed to settle 11 lawsuits over genetically modified seeds and gave each other licenses to their patents. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Factory Orders Eased in February  The Commerce Department said the value of orders for manufactured goods eased 0.1 percent, to a seasonally adjusted $323.8 billion in February, in contrast to Wall Street economists' expectations of a 1.0 percent pickup in factory orders. The report was a sign that the economy might be recovering at a little less robust pace than some had thought. [C4.]</p>
        <p>A Ratings Lift for Cable News  The latest ratings from Nielsen Media Research provide most all of the cable news networks something to brag about. Fox News widened its lead over CNN. Advertising. [C10.]</p>
        <p>MSNBC is expected today to sign Phil Donahue to host a prime-time discussion program starting this summer. [C10.]</p>
        <p>A Bitter Standoff at Cablevision  James L. Dolan, president of Cablevision, is locked into a bitter standoff with the YES Network, created by the Yankees. The dispute is depriving three million Cablevision subscribers in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut of access to most Yankees games. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Expanded Real Estate Coverage  Today Business Day introduces expanded coverage of commercial real estate. This week: the nationwide convention center race, and Pittsburgh's new entry. [C8-C10.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
