<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toronto Journal;Down These Frigid Streets: Homeless in Canada</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="831212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMELESS PERSONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECESSION AND DEPRESSION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TORONTO (ONTARIO)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TORONTO, ON, CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario/Toronto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D91339F93AA25751C0A960958260" item-length="1444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toronto Journal;Down These Frigid Streets: Homeless in Canada</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Feb. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Warily, he walked into the Moss Park Armory of the Canadian Armed Forces in downtown Toronto, spotted a large cardboard box filled with pile and down jackets and tried one on for size. Other homeless men and women were doing the same.</p>
        <p>His eyes sunk in dark pools on a furrowed face, his hands slightly shaking, he gave his name only as Matt and said he was 53, a former construction worker,  living on the street for the last three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Warily, he walked into the Moss Park Armory of the Canadian Armed Forces in downtown Toronto, spotted a large cardboard box filled with pile and down jackets and tried one on for size. Other homeless men and women were doing the same.</p>
        <p>His eyes sunk in dark pools on a furrowed face, his hands slightly shaking, he gave his name only as Matt and said he was 53, a former construction worker,  living on the street for the last three years.</p>
        <p>Construction went down the tubes," he said, his voice cracking. "There was  nothing else out there for me."</p>
        <p>His wife found another man, he said, and took their five children.</p>
        <p>Matt kept the jacket, as he was meant to, then helped himself to coffee, soup and doughnuts and spent the night on a cot -- benefits of an unusual military mission. For the first time, the Canadian Army has swung into action to try to stop deaths of the homeless from the numbing cold on Toronto streets.</p>
        <p>Winters are always cold here, with temperatures plunging sometimes well below zero Fahrenheit and the wind off Lake Ontario something else again. But this year's harsher than usual Arctic blasts, on top of a 22 percent cut in provincial welfare allowances and the failure of employment to pick up after the longest recession since the 1930's, has created emergency conditions that are straining the resources of Canada's biggest metropolis.</p>
        <p>"I can safely say I'm shocked at the condition of some of the people coming in here," said Lieut. Col. Tony Welsh, commander of the armory regiment, the Queen's Own Rifles of Canada, which this month responded to an emergency appeal  from the Toronto City Council to host the homeless. "A lot of the skills we're using aren't regular soldiering skills."</p>
        <p>"Or if they are," he added with a smile, "they are being used in different ways."</p>
        <p>Three homeless men have frozen to death so far this winter, more than in any  other winter in recent memory. One, in a plywood lean-to under an expressway, could not be identified for days because his hands had frozen solid over his face. A second was huddled by the door of a beauty college in a Chinese district, the third curled inside an unheated bus shelter.</p>
        <p>Intensely proud of their Scandinavian-like social safety net, Canadians usually identify homelessness with the United States, or the third world. Yet here in Toronto, often held out as one of the best-functioning cities of North America, a surge of homelessness is not only testing compassion but setting off  a political storm.</p>
        <p>"It's a shock to see three people die here like this," said David Hutcheon, a city councilor who worked with Mayor Barbara Hall to persuade the army to open the armory to the homeless. "It's like watching somebody die in your living room."</p>
        <p>Until the army came on the scene, hostels and churches were struggling to meet the demand. Some 4,500 hostel beds are available on any one night, up 700 over last year, and 26 churches have opened their doors.</p>
        <p>The best estimate of the total number of homeless comes from Anishnawbe Health Toronto, an Ojibway Indian organization that looks after street people, about a fifth of whom are Indian.</p>
        <p>Anishnawbe, which operates a health center downtown and sends out street patrols with sandwiches, coffee and soup for all the homeless, not just Indians, has gathered statistics that show the number of homeless in this city of three million rose from 11,500 in 1992 to 19,500 in 1995.</p>
        <p>The executive director, Barbra Nahwegahbow, noted a 43 percent increase in just the last nine months of 1995. "The social conscience that Canadians seem to think they have is not really there," she lamented. "The concept still exists, but resources needed to make it fully work are harder to come by."</p>
        <p>Spurred by the deaths of the homeless, Toronto's City Council has just approved a crisis fund amounting to $450,000 in United States currency to provide a 24-hour telephone line with information on available hostel beds, to help with psychiatric problems, to pay salaries at day drop-in centers and to increase sources of food.</p>
        <p>"No more funerals," a demonstrator shouted as the council voted for the package this month. A sign held by another activist read, "Westinghouse and Frigidaire do a better job housing the homeless than the province of Ontario and Metro" -- a reference to shelters made by street people out of the cardboard containers that wrap refrigerators.</p>
        <p>Easing the plight of the homeless is not high on the political screen of the  new Progressive Conservative government of Ontario's Premier, Mike Harris. It was elected last June on a platform of eliminating the province's swollen budget deficit and cutting high tax rates that it says impede economic growth. Mr. Harris says the way to solve the basic problem of homelessness is through faster economic growth.</p>
        <p>Jack Layton, chairman of the Toronto City Council's newly created Homelessness Task Force, said what frightens him the most are large numbers of people arriving at homeless shelters as part of families led either by a mother  or two parents.</p>
        <p>"Out of a total of 4,500 in the hostels, we now have more than 1,000 children and an increasing number of single mothers," he said. "We've just never seen anything like this before."</p>
        <p>A recent report by the Toronto city government's hostel division notes that there are more women among the homeless. "Life on the streets is dangerous for women and not an option that many would choose. It naturally follows that those  women who do become homeless are exceptionally vulnerable and needy."</p>
        <p>Mr. Layton and the municipal report both cite as an important factor the shrinking stock of cheap rental apartments in the wake of a provincial government decision to halt housing projects for the poor.</p>
        <p>The sharp cuts in welfare allowances are also taking their toll. "The poor are getting poorer," said Maj. Ronald Bowles of the Salvation Army, which runs three Toronto shelters. "We like to think this kind of thing doesn't happen on our doorstep, but it does."</p>
        <p>Roger Hunter, chaplain at the 75-year-old Scott Mission, which also serves the homeless, lauds public donations of sleeping bags, blankets and boots. "The  deaths," he said, "have raised the awareness of the community and challenged people's comfort levels."</p>
        <p>Comfort levels are most directly challenged during a ride with an Anishnawbe  street patrol. Every night, two vans loaded with hot food and drink, sleeping bags and blankets make the rounds of downtown sites frequented by the homeless.</p>
        <p>Despite the low temperatures and availability of the armory and other refuges, many of the homeless prefer to remain outdoors, citing unsafe conditions and restrictive regulations in the shelters. It is considered a violation of their basic rights to move them indoors forcibly, as is done is some American cities.</p>
        <p>One homeless man encountered by the patrol was Marty, 30, who sat in front of a bookstore wearing a sweatshirt, sweater, winter coat, knitted hat and scarf. He was inside a goose-feather sleeping bag and covered with blankets.</p>
        <p>A street person for the last three years, he said: "I have no job and no education. So this is the only way I know how to stay out of trouble and survive without money." Why wouldn't he go into a shelter? "They're too far away and they make you do things."</p>
        <p>Katt, 42, who is part Indian, lives on a grate across the street from the United States Consulate. She used to work in an auto body shop. Cataracts have impaired her sight and she has not been able to work for the past six years. How does she survive? "I've been out in Regina where it's minus 70. This is paradise."</p>
        <p>An element of pride creeps in as people talk. Frank, 42, sleeps in front of a restaurant in Chinatown. "Last night that wind was cutting through like crazy, but I lasted it," he said. "If it goes below minus zero, it doesn't matter. I'm  still there."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
