<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Quiet Rookie Lets Game Say It All</title>
    <meta content="28knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/28/sports/basketball/28knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1720971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia 76ers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beck, Howard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frye, Channing</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Philadelphia 76ers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia 76ers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Frye, Channing</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Beck, Howard</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Curry, Eddy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Marbury, Stephon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EFDD1431F93BA15752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Quiet Rookie Lets Game Say It All</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Quiet Rookie Lets Game Say It All</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <dateline>GREENBURGH, N.Y., Nov. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knicks player Channing Frye posts first career double-double with 21 points and 11 rebounds in win against Philadelphia 76ers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Channing Frye is 14 inches taller than Nate Robinson and was drafted 13 picks ahead of him, but in their corner of the locker room, Robinson looms largest.</p>
        <p>The two are rookies, but by virtue of his swagger, his flair and his motor mouth, Robinson tends to eclipse just about everyone. So it was hardly surprising that his buzzer-beating 3-pointer Saturday overshadowed Frye's best game as a professional.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Channing Frye is 14 inches taller than Nate Robinson and was drafted 13 picks ahead of him, but in their corner of the locker room, Robinson looms largest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Channing Frye is 14 inches taller than Nate Robinson and was drafted 13 picks ahead of him, but in their corner of the locker room, Robinson looms largest.</p>
        <p>The two are rookies, but by virtue of his swagger, his flair and his motor mouth, Robinson tends to eclipse just about everyone. So it was hardly surprising that his buzzer-beating 3-pointer Saturday overshadowed Frye's best game as a professional.</p>
        <p>The Knicks beat the Philadelphia 76ers, 105-102, when Robinson's shot dropped through at the end of overtime. They got to that point largely because Frye, in his first N.B.A. start, posted his first career double-double -- 21 points and 11 rebounds.</p>
        <p>But as the more modest member of the Knicks' vaunted 2005 draft class, Frye is comfortable operating beyond the spotlight and on the perimeter of the Knicks' offense.</p>
        <p>''I'm definitely all about what the Knicks need, and I just want to be aggressive on the boards,'' Frye said Sunday.</p>
        <p>While Robinson had a breakout game, scoring a career-high 17 points, Frye continued what has been a breakout half-month. He has averaged 19.2 points and 8.6 rebounds over the past five games, becoming the Knicks' best big man.</p>
        <p>The success has made Frye an indispensable member of Coach Larry Brown's rotation and a possible permanent starter. Frye got his chance because of injuries to Eddy Curry and Jerome James and the limitations of the Knicks' other big men. But when Curry returns, Frye could stay as his new frontcourt partner.</p>
        <p>''He's there,'' Brown said of Frye as a starter, before softening his stance slightly. ''I want to be sensitive to certain matchups, because you saw the first start, he gets two early fouls. And I'm a little nervous about that. But in terms of getting close to playing starting minutes, he's there.''</p>
        <p>The combination of Frye and Curry, both 22, would give the Knicks the most intriguing young forward-center pairing in the league. Making Frye a starter would allow Brown to use 37-year-old Antonio Davis more sparingly, in a bench role. Although Davis brings a calming influence to the starting lineup, Brown said he envisioned a steady Frye-Curry combination ''if you look at the long range.''</p>
        <p>''I'm talking about long range in January,'' Brown clarified. ''I would hope Channing's there and Eddy's fighting with Jerome.''</p>
        <p>Before that happens, Frye will have to contend with the usual rookie obstacles. Defenses may start to key on him, and there is the matter of maintaining stamina over an 82-game season.</p>
        <p>But Frye works as hard as any of the Knicks, often staying after practice to develop his post moves. Frye's steady play, steady demeanor and burgeoning statistics inspired Stephon Marbury to compare him to Tim Duncan. Hearing that comparison caused Brown to step back and chuckle.</p>
        <p>''That's not fair,'' Brown said, although he said Frye was ''certainly at the top of the list'' of great young players in the league.</p>
        <p>Frye lists Duncan as a role model -- ''He's always under control, he's an unselfish player, he's extremely fundamental, and he's kind of quiet, like I feel I am'' -- but he recoils a bit too at the analogy.</p>
        <p>''Oh man, that's just kind of lofty right now,'' Frye said. ''I got here by staying humble and working hard every day and staying afterwards. That's what I'm going to continue to keep doing.''</p>
        <p>For a day, Robinson was grounded, too. The victim of a practical joke by teammates, Robinson left Madison Square Garden on Saturday wearing a profoundly wrinkled suit.</p>
        <p>''I had to,'' Robinson said, shaking his head. ''Tie my suit up, tie my tie and just get downstairs to my car as fast as I could, so nobody could see me.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Eddy Curry will not play Monday night at Miami, and it sounds as if he will be out for several more days. He could miss Wednesday's game against the Chicago Bulls, his former team. ''He's not close right now,'' Coach Larry Brown said. Curry has missed two games because of a strained calf muscle. The Knicks will catch a break in their first game against the Heat. Shaquille O'Neal is out with a sprained right ankle and is not expected to return for about two weeks.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
