<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>General Instrument Up As New Interest Arises</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="368133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL INSTRUMENT CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORSTMANN LITTLE &amp; CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBB, GREGORY A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DB133DF937A25754C0A966958260" item-length="284" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>General Instrument Up As New Interest Arises</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREGORY A. ROBB, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROBB, GREGORY A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The shares of the General Instrument Corporation rose today on the expectation that a new offer might arise to top the friendly bid of $1.6 billion made earlier this month by Forstmann Little &amp; Company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The shares of the General Instrument Corporation rose today on the expectation that a new offer might arise to top the friendly bid of $1.6 billion made earlier this month by Forstmann Little &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>The shares of the General Instrument Corporation rose today on the expectation that a new offer might arise to top the friendly bid of $1.6 billion made earlier this month by Forstmann Little &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>General Instrument, a New York-based electronics concern, disclosed in a Securities and Exchange Commission filing that a second company had expressed interest in receiving financial and other information. The party's identity was not disclosed.</p>
        <p>The company's shares rose 75 cents each today, to $46.875, on the New York Stock Exchange, after reaching a new high for the year of $47.125.</p>
        <p>Forstmann Little's offer, made on July 2, is $44.50 a share in cash, but General Instrument's stock has traded above that level since the deal was announced, signaling that traders expect a higher bid.</p>
        <p>After being reached by the third party on Wednesday, a move that General Instrument said was unsolicited, a special committee of the company's board directed managers to provide the information, subject to an agreement to keep it confidential, the filing said.</p>
        <p>E. Magnus Oppenheim, the president of E. Magnus Oppenheim &amp; Company, an New York advisory firm, said Forstmann's bid ''left a lot to be desired.'' He added, ''There is room for a higher bid.''</p>
        <p>Other analysts said they were not surprised by the indication of interest because General Instrument's cable television equipment business is an attractive target for acquisition.</p>
        <p>''There is probably more money than deals out there, and they have an attractive core business,'' said Robert Anastasi of the Robinson Humphrey Company in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Forstmann Little, a private investment firm, had no immediate comment on the filing.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
