<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Welcome Back Mota as One of Their Own</title>
    <meta content="27mota" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/27/sports/baseball/27mota.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1836065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mota, Guillermo</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFD71230F934A15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Welcome Back Mota as One of Their Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets Welcome Back Mota as One of Their Own</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN SHPIGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shpigel, Ben</byline>
      <dateline>PORT ST. LUCIE, Fla., March 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Guillermo Mota moseyed into the Mets clubhouse a few minutes after 2 p.m. Monday and could not walk two steps without being intercepted by a teammate, a coach or a clubhouse attendant.</p>
        <p>He greeted everyone with a hug or a handshake -- or both -- and when he rounded a corner and yelled, ''Flaco,'' -- Shawn Green's nickname -- Green was waiting with a huge smile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of the major leaguers suspended for violating baseball’s performance-enhancing drug policy, few received the attention that Guillermo Mota did.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Guillermo Mota moseyed into the Mets clubhouse a few minutes after 2 p.m. Monday and could not walk two steps without being intercepted by a teammate, a coach or a clubhouse attendant.</p>
        <p>He greeted everyone with a hug or a handshake -- or both -- and when he rounded a corner and yelled, ''Flaco,'' -- Shawn Green's nickname -- Green was waiting with a huge smile.</p>
        <p>Of the 15 major leaguers suspended for violating baseball's performance-enhancing drug policy over the past two years, few were prominent enough to have received the attention that Mota did.</p>
        <p>Rafael Palmeiro never returned to the Baltimore Orioles, for instance, and Matt Lawton never played another game in Yankees pinstripes. But Mota's teammates rallied behind him, saying that his immediate owning up to a mistake overrode the 50-game suspension that makes him unavailable for about one-third of the season.</p>
        <p>''You can't turn back time,'' catcher Paul Lo Duca said. ''He realizes that, and we recognize that as a team. You don't hold grudges on people and you go on. Your friends, your family, you forgive them just like anybody else. We're all family here.''</p>
        <p>Mota will begin spring training six weeks late, although he said he had been throwing bullpen sessions twice a week in the Dominican Republic. In mid-May, he is scheduled to begin a 16-day rehabilitation assignment that will probably leave him in good position to rejoin the Mets.</p>
        <p>Mota arrived on the same day that the Mets received a visit from Donald Fehr, the executive director of the players' association, who had grudgingly agreed with baseball's decision for tougher testing. It was an odd coincidence.</p>
        <p>During a brief interview with reporters, Mota declined to say why or when he took the substance. He said he had nothing to say that was not in his statement of apology issued Nov. 1, the day his suspension was announced.</p>
        <p>Almost immediately afterward, he said, teammates reached out to offer encouragement. He received phone calls from, among others, Lo Duca, Green and Pedro Martínez.</p>
        <p>''They're nice people, nice teammates, and I'm glad that they supported me,'' Mota said.</p>
        <p>The Mets internally debated the potential public relations fallout of re-signing Mota, but they were impressed with how readily he apologized and how he did not offer excuses. Mota, who was a free agent, said he received interest from San Francisco, Pittsburgh and Philadelphia, but he was thankful that the Mets were still interested in him.</p>
        <p>''If he had not apologized and handled it differently than he did, it would have been different,'' General Manager Omar Minaya said.</p>
        <p>The Mets also understood how much of an asset Mota was to the bullpen after he was acquired from Cleveland on Aug. 20. In 18 regular-season games, he went 3-0 with a 1.00 earned run average and provided Manager Willie Randolph another late-inning option in addition to Aaron Heilman.</p>
        <p>Mota was perhaps at his most valuable in the postseason, when he pitched in 7 of the Mets' 10 games, including five in the seven-game National League Championship Series against the Cardinals. Performance-enhancing drugs aid in a pitcher's recovery, and Minaya said that he did not know whether Mota's durability would be affected this season. Mota pitched on consecutive days five times last season.</p>
        <p>''No, I'm not smart enough to know what the effects are of steroids,'' Minaya said. ''I just don't know that.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
