<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Refrigerator Art Maybe, but Buyers See Local Resonance</title>
    <meta content="27art" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/27/nyregion/27art.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1836044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="LIVINGSTON MANOR JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Livingston Manor (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Peez Leweez (Livingston Manor, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santos, Fernanda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foster, Arley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foster, Ayla</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1D71230F934A15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Refrigerator Art Maybe, but Buyers See Local Resonance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Refrigerator Art Maybe, but Buyers See Local Resonance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FERNANDA SANTOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santos, Fernanda</byline>
      <dateline>LIVINGSTON MANOR, N.Y., March 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peez Leweez, coffee shop in Livingston Manor, NY, that showcases work of local artists, exhibits painting by Ayla Foster, 4, and Arley Foster, 2, whose father and uncle own shop, after a scheduled show falls through; proceeds of silent auction of their artists, are going to local charity; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The little girl stood on the tips of her toes, pointing at the large blue figure floating on the canvas. The figure had the shape of a teardrop and was hollow, save for three specks aligned like a capsized triangle on its fat upper edge.</p>
        <p>''This,'' the little girl said, ''is a kitty-cat.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a coffee shop that showcases local artists, the works of two preschoolers are causing a sensation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The little girl stood on the tips of her toes, pointing at the large blue figure floating on the canvas. The figure had the shape of a teardrop and was hollow, save for three specks aligned like a capsized triangle on its fat upper edge.</p>
        <p>''This,'' the little girl said, ''is a kitty-cat.''</p>
        <p>The painting -- a jumble of swirling brushstrokes depicting elements of uncertain meaning -- bore the girl's signature and the simple title she gave it at the end of the few minutes it took to make: ''Flowers 2.''</p>
        <p>The work is of distinctive preschool character, much like the 28 other paintings on the mauve walls of the Peez Leweez coffee shop on Pearl Street, at the southern tip of the minuscule downtown in this picturesque hamlet abutting the Catskills. The artists are sisters who share a passion for pink and an odd taste for cookies paired with slices of ham and cheese.</p>
        <p>The creator of the kitty-cat is Arley Foster, age 2. Ayla Foster, 4, favors colorful flowers and dolls with big heads. Their 29 oil, highlighter and crayon creations have fetched bids from $5 to $100 in a silent auction over the last month.</p>
        <p>Since it opened in 2002, Peez Leweez has showcased the work of local artists in six- to eight-week rotations, from photographers to painters and multimedia performers. About three months ago, however, the latest planned exhibit fell through after the artist, an abstract painter, moved out of state. The coffee shop's owners -- Ryan and Sims Foster, brothers who are, respectively, the girls' father and uncle -- found themselves scrambling for a last-minute substitute.</p>
        <p>Then one morning in January, the shop's manager, Sherri Sessions, suggested: ''How about we hang the girls' drawings on the walls?''</p>
        <p>''A lot of kids draw, but these girls draw a lot, and their stuff is all over the house,'' Ryan Foster said. ''But if we were going to do this, we had to do it right.''</p>
        <p>First, Mr. Foster, 33, purchased the canvases and added a few sheets of scrap paper that his wife, Claudia, had at home. Then, he laid out the rules: Let the girls draw, with no disruption or interruption and no guidance from adults. Once each piece was done, whoever was around the girls was to ask them to name their work.</p>
        <p>The result is a collection of titles at once intriguing and amusing: ''Elephant Ask,'' ''Mommy Found Giant's Baby'' and ''Alien (with light-up tummy),'' which Ayla painted in about three minutes, her father said, perhaps drawing inspiration from one of her favorite movies, ''E.T.''</p>
        <p>''All aliens have lights up their tummies,'' the artist said dismissively, as if her work needed no explaining.</p>
        <p>It took the girls three weeks to complete the 29 paintings, which have been hanging in the coffee shop since late February and will be up until Sunday. Mr. Foster said he was tempted at first to sell the girls' work and use the profits to help pay for their college education, although he never expected the paintings would fetch much.</p>
        <p>''These girls are not prodigies,'' he said with a chuckle. ''Their work is just, you know, kids' stuff.''</p>
        <p>The owners eventually decided to take silent auction bids and give the proceeds to a local charity; $700 has been raised so far.</p>
        <p>''The beauty of these paintings is in their simplicity,'' said Ann Krupski, 64, a retired piano teacher who has lived here for more than a decade and who bid on at least three works. ''There's something spontaneous about it, something natural that these girls were able to capture and that only a child could express.''</p>
        <p>Holding a cup of coffee, Bob Cady, 59, looked at the largest of the paintings -- an explosion of red, green and purple about the size of a briefcase -- and exclaimed, ''There's something behind it, like a hidden picture, or like Livingston Manor after a very colorful snowstorm.''</p>
        <p>That work, entitled ''Rocks,'' was a collaboration by the sisters and is Arley's favorite because, she said, ''It's the big one.''</p>
        <p>Ryan and Sims Foster grew up here and graduated from the Livingston Manor Central School, housed in the imposing 1930s building off Main Street. Both left town for college, with no initial plan to return.</p>
        <p>Ryan, who had worked in restaurants since he was a teenager, washing dishes and wiping tables, used his degree in business administration to land a job managing an Italian restaurant in Orange County. Sims had a degree in trumpet performance and moved to Manhattan, where he worked as general manager of the nightclub Lotus, in Chelsea.</p>
        <p>Then, in visits back home to Livingston Manor, they began to notice the changes. The downtown, which Sims used to call ''tumbleweed town'' because of its shuttered stores, started to show signs of life about six years ago. New Yorkers started buying weekend homes in the area, and the abandoned buildings were being spruced up, with some new businesses moving in.</p>
        <p>The brothers pulled together their savings and opened Peez Leweez in October 2002.</p>
        <p>''I think we've become sort of a cultural and emotional hub here,'' Sims Foster, 30, said, ''just like some coffee shops are to certain neighborhoods in New York.''</p>
        <p>LIVINGSTON MANOR JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
