<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Medical Turns Political</title>
    <meta content="19POLS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/19/national/19pols.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1658176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="News Analysis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulse, Carl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiavo, Terri</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delay, Tom (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiavo, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schindler, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schindler, Mary</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Schiavo, Terri</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EED8113CF93AA25750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Medical Turns Political</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Medical Becomes Political for Congress</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carl Hulse analysis holds that while Congressional lawmakers of both parties justified their effort to try to prevent removal of feeding tube from Terri Schiavo as matter of fundamental rights and due process, political motivations have figured in as well; says for Republicans, it was chance to carve out new territory in 'culture of life' issues so paramount to religious conservatives; says for Democrats, case offers way to portray their newfound willingness to move to center on such issues; maintains that for Rep Tom Delay, taking prominent role in rallying conservatives to Schiavo cause also provided distraction from his troubles (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fevered Congressional intervention in a single individual's health crisis is being driven in significant part by powerful political forces that have converged at the bedside of Terri Schiavo.</p>
        <p>While lawmakers of both parties justified their effort to try to prevent removal of the feeding tube from the brain-damaged woman as a matter of fundamental rights and due process, political motivations have figured in as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fevered Congressional intervention in Terri Schiavo's health crisis is being driven in significant part by powerful political forces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The fevered Congressional intervention in a single individual's health crisis is being driven in significant part by powerful political forces that have converged at the bedside of Terri Schiavo.</p>
        <p>While lawmakers of both parties justified their effort to try to prevent removal of the feeding tube from the brain-damaged woman as a matter of fundamental rights and due process, political motivations have figured in as well.</p>
        <p>For Republicans, it was a chance to try to carve out new territory in the ''culture of life'' issues so paramount to passionate religious conservatives, who have flooded Congressional offices with messages beseeching help in keeping Ms. Schiavo alive. For Democrats still struggling in the wake of their defeat in the November elections, the case offered a way to portray their newfound willingness to move to the center on such issues.</p>
        <p>And for Representative Tom DeLay, the House majority leader facing inquiries into fund-raising improprieties in Texas and potential violations of House travel rules in Washington, taking a prominent role in rallying conservatives to the Schiavo cause also provided a sudden distraction from his troubles.</p>
        <p>''To friends, family and millions of people praying around the world this Palm Sunday weekend: do not be afraid,'' said Mr. DeLay, who interjected himself forcefully into the case, in a pointed religious reference during a Friday news conference. ''Terri Schiavo will not be forsaken.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DeLay and other lawmakers appeared to be affected emotionally by the life-and-death subject of Ms. Schiavo. Some have long held religious beliefs opposing such things as assisted suicide or the disruption of life-sustaining medical care.</p>
        <p>But there also is little question that this matter would not have risen so far and so fast in Congress without the standard hearings and review -- and kept lawmakers after midnight on the eve of their recess -- were not their own ambitions and constituencies at issue. They drove that point home with a blizzard of subpoenas and calls for Senate hearings in what critics viewed as an excessive use of Congressional authority.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeLay is clearly relishing the change in subject from House travel rules and lobbying ties to a conservative crusade, even appearing on television to make the case for Congressional involvement after ducking cameras most of the week. And his dedication is showing results. Representative Mike Pence of Indiana, leader of a wing of House conservatives, told reporters that he and his colleagues ''are so grateful for the heart of our majority leader.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. DeLay is not the only potential Republican beneficiary. Senator Bill Frist, the majority leader, is a potential presidential candidate also courting the conservative wing of the party. His determined press on behalf of Ms. Schiavo -- with a heavy accent on his professional expertise as a physician -- could resonate powerfully with that constituency. Other possible White House contenders are involved as well, including Gov. Jeb Bush of Florida and Senator Rick Santorum of Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Democrats quickly recognized they had a political stake in this as well, particularly with a handful of Senate seats coming open in states won by President Bush last year, including Florida.</p>
        <p>Led by their new leader, Senator Harry Reid, an anti-abortion Democrat from Nevada, Senate Democrats did not stand in the way of a bill aimed directly at the Schiavo case as they might have in the past, though disagreement between the House and Senate on the specific approach has stalled a final piece of legislation.</p>
        <p>Senator Sam Brownback, Republican of Kansas, said he thought the willingness of Senate Democrats to move forward reflected a new attitude within the party.</p>
        <p>''Yesterday Ted Kennedy and I had a press conference on a pro-life bill on Down syndrome,'' Mr. Brownback said. ''I don't think would have happened two years ago, and I welcome it. I think it is fabulous.''</p>
        <p>But as the Republican majorities in the House and Senate issued subpoenas and pondered the prospect of a hearing at Ms. Schiavo's hospice, some Democrats were appalled.</p>
        <p>''Congress is turning the Schiavo family's personal tragedy into a national political farce,'' said Representative Henry A. Waxman of California, the senior Democrat on the House Government Reform Committee who objected to the subpoenas issued by the panel's chairman, Representative Tom Davis of Virginia.</p>
        <p>And George Felos, the lawyer for Ms. Schiavo's husband who had fought for nearly two years to allow his wife to die, blistered both parties in Congress for what he portrayed as a politically motivated, 11th-hour interference in a case that has existed for years without previously attracting much attention from Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>''It was odious, it was shocking, it was disgusting and I think all Americans should be alarmed,'' Mr. Felos told reporters in Florida.</p>
        <p>And he had a warning for Democrats who would deign to veer from longstanding opposition to federal intrusion in such intimate medical decisions: ''If they don't stand up for Terri Schiavo, they deserve to be the minority party.''</p>
        <p>Many Congressional Democrats were biting their tongues Friday as they witnessed what they considered an egregious misuse of power by Republicans. They pointed to public opinion polls that show support for Mr. Schiavo's right to decide his wife's fate, but they also fear the power of the mobilized right.</p>
        <p>Plus, lawmakers of both parties say they have been moved by the videotapes they have seen of Ms. Schiavo, viewing themselves as the last barrier between her and a death sentence.</p>
        <p>Yet, as Senator Dianne Feinstein, Democrat of California, warned her colleagues this week as they considered a bill that would move the case to federal court, the mix of politics and mortality can be volatile.</p>
        <p>''We change the nature of all these things to put this in the political arena,'' she said.</p>
        <p>News Analysis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
