<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Weapons to Assault an Epidemic</title>
    <meta content="24KATZ$23" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Men &amp; Health" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/24/health/24KATZ-MH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1303993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ARTHRITIS UPDATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arthritis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katzenstein, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Arthritis and Rheumatism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arthritis and Rheumatism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E0DC1631F937A15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2131" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Weapons to Assault an Epidemic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Weapons to Assault an Epidemic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY KATZENSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Katzenstein, Larry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>About 21 million Americans are afflicted with osteoarthritis; figure is expected to soar to more than 30 million by 2020, as baby boomers grow older; women stand greater chance than men of developing disease, but some arthritis experts are seeing more men developing severe cases, and earlier, in their 50's rather than 60's or 70's, which may be attributed to more participation in strenuous sports; description of variety of promising treatments and technological advances; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS a New York Knick, Fred Crawford suited up with Bill Bradley and Willis Reed. Later he was a member of the Los Angeles Lakers when Elgin Baylor and Jerry West were the stars of that team. He ended his career with the Milwaukee Bucks, whose center was Kareem Abdul-Jabbar. That was three decades ago.</p>
        <p>Late last month, as he entered a medical office on the Upper East Side of Manhattan, Mr. Crawford moved in what must have seemed like slow motion to him. Decades of constant pounding had taken their toll on his left hip. Pain and weakness prevented him from walking more than three blocks at a time. ''Basketball is a tough business, but you're not thinking about that at the time,'' Mr. Crawford said. His diagnosis: moderately severe osteoarthritis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some arthritis experts are noticing a change in their patients: more men developing severe cases, and earlier, in their 50's</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS a New York Knick, Fred Crawford suited up with Bill Bradley and Willis Reed. Later he was a member of the Los Angeles Lakers when Elgin Baylor and Jerry West were the stars of that team. He ended his career with the Milwaukee Bucks, whose center was Kareem Abdul-Jabbar. That was three decades ago.</p>
        <p>Late last month, as he entered a medical office on the Upper East Side of Manhattan, Mr. Crawford moved in what must have seemed like slow motion to him. Decades of constant pounding had taken their toll on his left hip. Pain and weakness prevented him from walking more than three blocks at a time. ''Basketball is a tough business, but you're not thinking about that at the time,'' Mr. Crawford said. His diagnosis: moderately severe osteoarthritis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crawford is not alone. About  21 million Americans are afflicted with osteoarthritis. (According to a federal study, the figure will soar to more than 30 million by 2020, as the baby boomers grow older.) Women stand a greater chance than men of developing the disease, especially women over 65. But some arthritis experts are noticing a change in their patients: more men developing severe cases, and earlier, in their 50's rather than in their 60's and 70's, which may be attributed to more participation in strenuous sports.</p>
        <p>At the same time, however, a variety of promising treatments and technological advances, from new drugs to viscous injections to high-tech prostheses, are keeping pace with the epidemic, offering relief to those who suffer from the nation's leading cause of disability.</p>
        <p>Lube Job for Joints</p>
        <p>While osteoarthritis affects the entire joint -- be it knee, hip, wrist or fingers -- its primary target is cartilage, the tough, slippery coating at the ends of bones that lets them glide over each other when you bend your knees or throw a baseball. With osteoarthritis, the protective cartilage wears away (which is why it is sometimes referred to as ''degenerative'' arthritis). As the cushioning cartilage erodes, bone eventually rubs against bone, causing the pain and stiffness that Fred Crawford knows all too well.</p>
        <p>The 60-year-old Mr. Crawford had been scheduled for hip-replacement surgery in April. But he canceled after hearing about a less drastic but more controversial alternative known as visco-supplementation -- a lube job for arthritic joints.</p>
        <p>In visco-supplementation, a clear, thick liquid is injected into the joint in three weekly injections costing about $1,000 for the series. (Some health insurance plans cover the cost.) The relatively painless injections are intended to provide temporary relief for arthritic pain and stiffness. The key ingredient is hyaluronic acid, a chemical found naturally in the fluid of the knee and other joints that aids in lubrication.</p>
        <p>The Food and Drug Administration approved two visco-supplementation products, Synvisc and Hyalgan, in 1997 and a third, Supartz, earlier this year. They are currently approved for treating symptoms of osteoarthritis of the knee that have not responded to drugs or other treatments. (None has yet been approved for osteoarthritis of the hip, so Mr. Crawford's injections, using Synvisc, are an ''off-label'' but permissible treatment.)</p>
        <p>Visco-supplementation has drawn attention, not all favorable, partly from how it has been promoted. Full-page ads in magazines and newspapers contend that Synvisc offers ''drug-free relief for osteoarthritis knee pain,'' which is technically true, as the products are classified as medical devices rather than drugs. But experts are also split over visco-supplementation's effectiveness.</p>
        <p>''I think it doesn't work, and there's actually pretty strong evidence from clinical trials that it doesn't work,'' said Dr. David Felson, the director of the Arthritis Center at the Boston University School of Medicine. He said that the three large-scale clinical trials of visco-supplementation for knee osteoarthritis ''show no effect compared with placebo injections of saline.''</p>
        <p>But visco-supplementation has its proponents, too. One is Mr. Crawford's doctor, Vijay Vad, a rheumatologist at the Hospital for Special Surgery in New York. Dr. Vad has ''visco-supplemented'' nearly 600 knees and 70 hips -- the first 25 as part of a recently completed clinical trial. For best results, he emphasizes, ''careful selection of patients is essential.''</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Vad, the prime candidates for visco-supplementation are men in their 40's or 50's with moderately severe osteoarthritis of the hip or knee who have failed to improve with oral medications, physical therapy or cortisone injections. Following the injections, Dr. Vad insists that patients engage in a rehabilitation program that includes exercise and aquatherapy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crawford, for one, is a believer. ''I have less pain and have already noticed improvement in my range of motion,'' he reported shortly after the last of his three Synvisc injections. He said he was looking forward to playing doubles tennis and taking his bicycle out of storage. But as for basketball, ''I'm going to leave that to Kobe and Shaq.''</p>
        <p>The Surgical Solution</p>
        <p>Dr. Richard Laskin, an orthopedic surgeon and co-chief of the knee service at the Hospital for Special Surgery, recently reviewed his hospital's database for the last 20 years, tallying up the numbers of men who had been candidates for hip or knee replacement surgery and noting their ages. One finding stood out: between 1980 to 1990 and 1990 to 2000, male patients in their 50's had tripled.</p>
        <p>''Why am I seeing so many more men in their 50's when I used to see them much later?'' Dr. Raskin asked. ''It's because when they were in their 20's, they skied or played rugby or soccer or whatever and damaged their knees -- tore their anterior cruciate ligament or their medial meniscus, for example, and more men tended to do that than women.'' (Ligaments are bands of tissue that help stabilize a joint by binding together the bones within it; meniscuses are pads of tissue that help to cushion the knee joint.)</p>
        <p>Even without directly damaging cartilage, traumatic injury to a joint  greatly increases the risk of developing osteoarthritis years later. Tearing a ligament or meniscus makes the joint unstable, creating abnormal stresses on cartilage during movement. Athletes who suffer a major injury to the knee or hip, for example, are up to seven times more likely to develop osteoarthritis in that joint than the average person.</p>
        <p>Often, the best solution is to replace the knee. A quarter of a million such operations are done each year for severe arthritis, and the results are striking, with almost total relief in most cases. Until recently, though, the drawback for younger patients was that these artificial joints often wore out after about 20 years, so orthopedists preferred to delay surgery until 65.</p>
        <p>But thanks to an implant introduced earlier this year, patients may not need to wait. Laboratory comparisons show that the new knee, with a surface of oxidized zirconium ceramic, a highly durable material, wore down only about one-tenth as fast as standard implants.</p>
        <p>''If they can last 30 to 35 years, then even for my 50-year-old patients you're talking about their lifetime,'' Dr. Laskin said. ''That's what we've been looking for all these years.''</p>
        <p>The Cox-2 Breakthrough</p>
        <p>For more than three decades, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs -- aspirin, ibuprofen, naproxen and others -- have been mainstays of medical treatment for the pain, stiffness and inflammation of osteoarthritis. But these drugs, referred to by doctors as Nsaid's, can also cause major gastrointestinal problems, including ulcers and bleeding.</p>
        <p>In 1998, the food and drug agency approved celecoxib (Celebrex), the first of a new class of anti-inflammatories known as Cox-2 inhibitors. A second, rofecoxib (Vioxx), was approved in 1999. Celebrex and Vioxx cost much more than standard drugs and are no better at relieving arthritis symptoms. Their crucial advantage is that they inhibit the Cox-2 enzymes that cause pain and inflammation while, in contrast to standard anti-inflammatories, largely sparing the ''good'' Cox-1 enzymes that protect the stomach lining.</p>
        <p>''Celebrex and Vioxx aren't immune from causing the same nasty side effects as other Nsaid's,'' said a rheumatologist in New York, Dr. Mark Eberle. ''But in well-conducted studies comparing Cox-2's with traditional Nsaid's such as ibuprofen, naproxen and diclofenac, the Cox-2's were only about 25 percent as likely to cause such problems.''</p>
        <p>But because of their specificity, Cox-2's lack a useful side effect that standard anti-inflammatories have, which is the ability (because these drugs interfere with blood platelets) to reduce the risk of clots that can cause heart attacks. So people who rely on aspirin for its anti-clotting effect cannot depend on Celebrex or Vioxx to provide the same benefit.</p>
        <p>The Sunshine Treatment</p>
        <p>A connection between vitamin D and osteoarthritis might seem unlikely. But since vitamin D is important for strong bones, and bones are joined to cartilage, it makes sense. Now, mounting evidence suggests that osteoarthritis is likely to worsen for those who are deficient in vitamin D -- a common deficiency affecting nearly 60 percent of adults, according to one recent survey.</p>
        <p>Initial reports of a link emerged from the Framingham Heart Study, best known for revealing risk factors for heart disease but also a source of valuable information on other diseases. Residents of Framingham, Mass. who had osteoarthritis of the knee were periodically monitored for vitamin D intake, blood-serum levels of vitamin D, and changes in the severity of their disease.</p>
        <p>In a study of 556 people over a period of about 10 years, people who consumed little vitamin D and had low levels in their serum were three times more likely to experience a worsening of their knee osteoarthritis than those with high intakes and high serum levels. Low serum levels of vitamin D were also associated with loss of cartilage in the knee.</p>
        <p>''When we initially published that data, I frankly was a little bit nervous as to whether we were correct,'' said Dr. Felson of the Boston University medical school, an author of the study. But he added that a very large study on osteoarthritis of the hip, published in 1999, corroborated their findings ''almost exactly.''</p>
        <p>Based on the Framingham results, the amount of vitamin D in a typical multivitamin -- 400 International Units -- should keep carilage healthy. An eight-ounce glass of milk fortified with vitamin D contains about 100 units, and occasional exposure to sun can help too.</p>
        <p>The Arthritis 'Cure'</p>
        <p>After ''The Arthritis Cure'' became a best seller in 1997, even its principal author, Dr. Jason Theodosakis, agreed that ''cure'' was too strong a term for the effects of glucosamine and chondroitin sulfate, the two dietary supplements whose properties were lauded in the book. (Both are basic building blocks of cartilage and have anti-inflammatory properties.) But while claims for their ability to rebuild cartilage remain to be proven, recent studies provide further evidence for the safety and effectiveness of these supplements: They work against symptoms of osteoarthritis and may prevent the further breakdown of cartilage.</p>
        <p>''I tell my patients, 'I believe in God, the Tooth Fairy and glucosamine,' '' said Dr. Steven K. Magid, a rheumatologist at the Hospital for Special Surgery. ''I've just had so many patients tell me that they do get pain relief from these supplements.''</p>
        <p>Five physicians interviewed for this article were asked about ''The Arthritis Cure'' supplements, and all said they had recommended them to patients. Two were particularly impressed with a study done in Belgium and published this year in The Lancet, the London-based medical journal.</p>
        <p>The Belgian study involved 212 patients with knee osteoarthritis who took either 1,500 milligrams of glucosamine sulfate or a placebo daily for three years. Their knees were X-rayed at the start of the study and again after one and three years. The 106 patients on placebo experienced progressive loss of cartilage, while those on glucosamine experienced no significant cartilage loss. Also, symptoms of placebo users worsened slightly during the study but improved among glucosamine users.</p>
        <p>The best choice may be a combination product, since chondroitin sulfate, glucosamine's partner, may work even better. In a review of 15 clinical studies of glucosamine and chondroitin published last year in the Journal of the American Medical Association, the authors reported finding ''moderate'' treatment effects for glucosamine and ''large effects'' for chondroitin. A federally sponsored clinical trial of glucosamine and chondroitin sulfate, now under way, may provide a clearer idea of the supplements' benefits.</p>
        <p>ARTHRITIS UPDATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
