<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eastern Philosophy for a Quiet Holiday Respite</title>
    <meta content="18ctdine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/18/travel/18ctdine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1725947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="DINING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E1D61630F93BA25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eastern Philosophy for a Quiet Holiday Respite</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Eastern Philosophy for a Quiet Holiday Respite</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR a change of pace this season, it is nice to find an oasis of quiet where you can have a quick, reasonably priced meal and a little relief from the shopping hassle. I found such a place in a strip mall on Route 7 in Wilton recently. It is the East Cafe, which is usually tranquil, with a small menu and prices to match.</p>
        <p>East Cafe subtitles itself ''the food of Asia,'' which somewhat overstates its geographic range. In essence, it is primarily Chinese with a few Thai dishes, one Indonesian and one Malaysian. Japanese elements consist of miso soup, tempura shrimp (too heavily breaded) and edamame (boiled soy beans in their shells) for nibbling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The East Cafe, with a small menu and prices to match, offers diners a nice change of pace this season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR a change of pace this season, it is nice to find an oasis of quiet where you can have a quick, reasonably priced meal and a little relief from the shopping hassle. I found such a place in a strip mall on Route 7 in Wilton recently. It is the East Cafe, which is usually tranquil, with a small menu and prices to match.</p>
        <p>East Cafe subtitles itself ''the food of Asia,'' which somewhat overstates its geographic range. In essence, it is primarily Chinese with a few Thai dishes, one Indonesian and one Malaysian. Japanese elements consist of miso soup, tempura shrimp (too heavily breaded) and edamame (boiled soy beans in their shells) for nibbling.</p>
        <p>Of all the Asian cuisines, Chinese is most compatible with Thai, Malaysian, Indonesian and Vietnamese, all of which share some ingredients and cooking styles. But the only Vietnamese item on the menu is beer.</p>
        <p>As a Thai food enthusiast, I naturally gravitated at once to those items on the menu. First I tried the Thai egg roll, which was packed with bean sprouts and other veggies inside a deep-fried wrapper. While the stuffing was tasty, it was much denser and the wrapper heavier than the usual Thai version. I had better luck with tom yam goong, a clear Thai soup sparked by lemon grass and hot pepper, with a generous assortment of shrimp, mushrooms and onions. It was not as diabolically fiery as it can be, but it took the chill off the wintry evening.</p>
        <p>For entrees, East Cafe has a winning, economical system. There is a list of sauces -- spicy mango, sambal, black bean, ginger glaze, coconut curry and Szechwan peppercorn -- and then a choice of chicken, tofu, pork, beef, scallops or prawns to be mixed with the chosen sauce.</p>
        <p>I chose Thai coconut curry combined with chicken and tofu. It was a zesty match, arriving in a sizzling hot casserole, packed with slices of white meat, hunks of tofu, thin slices of squash, red and green peppers, onions and other vegetables. While the curry was not as rich-textured as such a curry can be, it worked well enough and made a generous entree.</p>
        <p>My companion tried the Thai seafood casserole with equally happy results. It was a sizzling hot mélange of lobster tail, scallops and shrimp in a sauce with a coconut-milk base, wafting into the air aromas of coriander, fennel seeds, turmeric and lemon grass.</p>
        <p>On a later lunch visit, having worked our way through most of the Thai items on the menu, three of us concentrated mostly on Chinese dishes, all of which were freshly cooked and full of savory flavors. A won ton watercress soup consisted of a clear broth full of plump won tons and a goodly quantity of watercress. It really hit the spot.</p>
        <p>Just as pleasing were the Szechwan dumplings, six of them steaming and oversize in a sauce both subtle and tangy. Crispy calamari had a well-seasoned batter and, more intriguing, a mound of crisp salted glass noodles that was delicious. My only complaint: While the dumplings were hot, the plate was icy cold. This was the case with all the plates and bowls at East Cafe. Keeping them at room temperature would be an improvement.</p>
        <p>Best of our entrees was the Szechwan peppercorn sauce combined with pork strips, fried tofu chunks, onions, scallions, mushrooms, carrot slivers and asparagus. Both peppery and hot in temperature, it was a great way to warm up for the afternoon ahead.</p>
        <p>Pad Thai, the national noodle dish, had the requisite accouterments -- cooked egg strips, ground peanuts and scallions -- and was pleasingly profligate with shrimp, bean sprouts and onions. Sambal sauce with shrimp and a wide assortment of vegetables delivered a zesty wallop, too.</p>
        <p>There is an inconsequential wine selection, but, in my view, the Chinese, Thai and Vietnam beers make better companions than wine to this mildly spicy Asian food.</p>
        <p>East Cafe is unpretentious, but accomplishes what it promises, making it just the invigorating lunch or dinner break this tired shopper needed.</p>
        <p>East Cafe</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>920 Danbury Road (Route 7), Wilton, (203) 544-8878.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Narrow storefront, artfully arranged with banquettes, tables and chairs, spot lighting and Asian artifacts.  NOISE LEVEL -- Moderate.  SERVICE -- Cheerful and quick, if perfunctory.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Crispy calamari, Thai coconut curry, Thai seafood casserole, Szechuan noodles, tom yam goong soup, Szechuan peppercorn sauce with pork and tofu, Thai curry, sambal sauce with beef.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch: entrees, $6 to $7.50, includes soup and rice. Dinner: appetizers, $2 to $8; entrees, $10 to $20; desserts, $5.  CREDIT CARDS -- Most accepted.  HOURS -- Lunch: weekdays, 11:30 a.m. to 3 p.m. Dinner: Monday through Thursday, 3 to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 3 to 11 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 10 p.m. (no lunch).  RESERVATIONS -- Accepted, but usually unnecessary.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Street level; restrooms the same.  REVIEWED BY THE TIMES -- Dec. 18, 2005.  RATINGS -- Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Fair, Poor. Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
