<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Expelling the Ghost Of A.I.G. Past</title>
    <meta content="18aig" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/18/business/yourmoney/18aig.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1725838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American International Group</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenberg, Maurice R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EFDC1630F93BA25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="2843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Expelling the Ghost Of A.I.G. Past</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Expelling the Ghost of A.I.G. Past</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY ANDERSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LESS than two weeks after Hurricane Katrina ravaged New Orleans, Scott Tramel, an insurance executive, was sitting in a makeshift office -- a former filing room in a sales office -- in Baton Rouge when he saw a shock of white hair cross the hallway. He turned to his colleague, a fellow underwriter at the American Home Insurance Company, a subsidiary of the American International Group, with a look of surprise. ''I think that's Martin Sullivan,'' he said, referring to A.I.G.'s chief executive.</p>
        <p>Less than a week after the storm, Mr. Sullivan, along with his wife, Antoinette, and a small group of employees, loaded the company's Bombardier Global Express, a high-speed business jet, with $5,600 in consumer goods, $1,000 worth of polo shirts and $1,300 in battery-operated electronics, which he delivered, unannounced, to offices in the region struck by the hurricane. ''They weren't just worried about us being on the job; they were honestly concerned about our well-being as people,'' Mr. Tramel said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Investors wonder whether Martin Sullivan, who took over A.I.G. after accounting problems, will be able to match the performance of the company's former patriarch, Maurice R. Greenberg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LESS than two weeks after Hurricane Katrina ravaged New Orleans, Scott Tramel, an insurance executive, was sitting in a makeshift office -- a former filing room in a sales office -- in Baton Rouge when he saw a shock of white hair cross the hallway. He turned to his colleague, a fellow underwriter at the American Home Insurance Company, a subsidiary of the American International Group, with a look of surprise. ''I think that's Martin Sullivan,'' he said, referring to A.I.G.'s chief executive.</p>
        <p>Less than a week after the storm, Mr. Sullivan, along with his wife, Antoinette, and a small group of employees, loaded the company's Bombardier Global Express, a high-speed business jet, with $5,600 in consumer goods, $1,000 worth of polo shirts and $1,300 in battery-operated electronics, which he delivered, unannounced, to offices in the region struck by the hurricane. ''They weren't just worried about us being on the job; they were honestly concerned about our well-being as people,'' Mr. Tramel said.</p>
        <p>Katrina is not the only storm that Mr. Sullivan has had to weather this year. After 34 years at A.I.G., the world's largest insurance company, he took over the top job in March amid a decidedly man-made disaster. Regulators had discovered accounting problems at A.I.G., and the board swiftly ousted the chairman and chief executive, Maurice R. Greenberg, who over the course of 38 years had built the insurer into a behemoth with a market capitalization of $170 billion.</p>
        <p>Last week, regulators lashed out at Mr. Greenberg again, issuing a report accusing him and others of having cheated a foundation he runs 35 years ago. No charges have been brought, and Mr. Greenberg, who is known as Hank, denies any wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Sullivan, 51, took the reins of A.I.G. -- whose 2004 revenue, $98 billion, exceeded the current gross domestic product of Venezuela -- the company's lawyers and regulators were running it temporarily; its former boss and mentor was in exile (with acrimony between Mr. Greenberg and A.I.G. growing by the day); and investors were wondering whether they might have the next Enron on their hands.</p>
        <p>Nine months later, it is clear that A.I.G. is no Enron. It has survived the restatement of five years' earnings and has reported three quarters of solid profit, and its army of lawyers is close to hammering out the final details of a civil settlement with federal and state regulators over allegations that ranged from bid-rigging to improper reinsurance arrangements.</p>
        <p>LIKE some other chief executives catapulted into power amid crisis -- Richard D. Parsons at Time Warner comes to mind -- Mr. Sullivan has steadied the ship. He has done this through the force of his personality -- he can be charming and ingratiating -- and by the simple fact that he is not the manager accused of creating the problems. But with the skies clearing, investors are left wondering whether the nice, new chief executive will be able to match the performance of the company's former patriarch, architect and bully-in-chief.</p>
        <p>''The big question they have is: What kind of growth rate can they achieve?'' said David Schiff, the editor of Schiff's Insurance Observer, an industry newsletter. ''In the old days, investors believed they'd have 15 percent growth year after year. If you are going to grow at 15 percent forever, that growth can make up for anything.''</p>
        <p>Andrew S. Kligerman, an analyst at UBS, added: ''Hank Greenberg is a genius, he knows A.I.G. like the palm of his hand and he can speak to any detail of his company without the assistance of any executive. Martin's certainly a capable executive, but whether he can master the intricacies of A.I.G. is another question.''</p>
        <p>Those kinds of comments, which are common, suggest that A.I.G. is Mr. Greenberg. Mr. Sullivan declined to discuss Mr. Greenberg, but he did make clear that he planned to keep A.I.G.'s entrepreneurial spirit and thought that the company could continue to grow at double-digit rates. ''The single biggest question I get is, 'Will the culture change?' And candidly my answer is no,'' he said in his holiday-adorned 18th-floor office in Lower Manhattan. ''The culture is the entrepreneurial culture, and my view is, it's in the organization.''</p>
        <p>As for whether he is tough enough, Mr. Sullivan said, ''I would not be able to be in this position without tough choices.'' After all, Mr. Greenberg was ready to name him heir apparent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sullivan exudes a kind of ruddy optimism that, when combined with his broad smile and stocky stance, has a certain Santa Claus-like cheer to it. In conversation he laughs easily and does not shy away from jokes: he recently asked an analyst who was host for a lunch conference at the Pierre Hotel in Manhattan whether he could get some gin in his water glass. His warmth appears irrepressible and he seems to have charmed even the most irascible regulators. When he met the New York attorney general, Eliot Spitzer, who was leading the investigation into A.I.G., Mr. Sullivan, who is British, cheekily asked if he was part of the O'Spitzer clan.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Greenberg also had a famous wit, it often appeared in public when he was using it against someone. He loved to deride analysts for what he felt were stupid questions, and managers for what he thought were lackluster results.</p>
        <p>The contrast is lost on few: if Mr. Greenberg ordered, Mr. Sullivan asks. If the former chief knew more than everyone, Mr. Sullivan asks to be educated. Mr. Greenberg surrounded himself with a tight circle of senior executives, while Mr. Sullivan eats lunch with midlevel employees who are permitted to submit anonymous questions ahead of time, lest they be intimidated. And if the former chief executive and chairman took pride in how he built A.I.G., Mr. Sullivan loves to tell midlevel employees that if he can be chief executive, anyone can be chief executive.</p>
        <p>''Martin's the first to find out, to listen and to get different points of view,'' said Frank G. Zarb, the chairman of A.I.G.'s board. ''It's a great quality for a young C.E.O. He doesn't have his mind made up before he has the facts.''</p>
        <p>A native of London's gritty East End, Mr. Sullivan joined American International Underwriters as a clerk in 1971, when he was 17. It was his second job in insurance, and he earned £850 a year, or a bit more than $2,000 at the time, in his first year. He admired his boss, who he said taught him, ''Always have standards; never let them slip.'' Within three years he had become an underwriter, and by 1983 he was running the insurance-property department for all of Britain.</p>
        <p>A.I.G. has diversified over the years, but underwriting -- writing premiums and estimating the risk underlying them -- is the heart of its business and where Mr. Sullivan made his career. He rose quickly through the European ranks, taking over AIG Europe in 1993. He was brought to New York three years later to become the chief operating officer of all foreign property and casualty operations, and in 2002, Mr. Greenberg chose him and Edmund Tse, then senior vice chairman of life insurance, to be co-chief operating officers. It was a clear horse race to succeed Mr. Greenberg.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sullivan had to put his experience to the test last February. That month, federal and state authorities issued subpoenas to A.I.G. over questionable accounting transactions, one of which Mr. Greenberg initiated himself, according to a lawsuit filed later by Mr. Spitzer.</p>
        <p>It was not A.I.G.'s first round with regulators. In 2003, A.I.G. paid $10 million to settle a civil suit brought by the Securities and Exchange Commission contending that it had helped Brightpoint, a struggling cellphone distributor, mask losses with certain insurance products. A year later A.I.G. paid $126 million to settle all criminal and regulatory liabilities with state and federal regulators over the Brightpoint deal and similar allegations about products it sold to the PNC Financial Services Group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg made clear that he did not welcome regulatory scrutiny. In the Brightpoint settlement, the S.E.C. cited a lack of cooperation by A.I.G. in determining the fine, and Mr. Greenberg famously ended one earnings call by accusing regulators of turning foot faults into murder charges. ''Hank's attitude was that we were interfering with his running of the business,'' said one regulator who was prohibited from talking on the record about continuing investigations.</p>
        <p>While A.I.G. had tussled with federal regulators, it was the February subpoenas that catalyzed A.I.G.'s board, which was already concerned about the handling of Brightpoint and other matters. After eight hours of contentious debate on a Sunday in March, the board decided to ask Mr. Greenberg to resign and to promote Mr. Sullivan.</p>
        <p>Oddly enough, Mr. Sullivan had already been picked for the job. Earlier in the year, members of the board, with Mr. Greenberg's blessing, had decided that Mr. Sullivan would succeed Mr. Greenberg, though not right away, say two people briefed on the discussions. But the escalating investigation accelerated the timing of the transition and the heir apparent became king in the most unceremonious of coronations.</p>
        <p>The conditions for Mr. Sullivan's arrival could not have been worse: the firm was virtually paralyzed by the investigations. Lawyers were running the company, his mentor of many years was in exile and Mr. Sullivan suddenly had one of the most complex financial-services companies on his hands. He knew the property and casualty business, which accounts for about one-third of A.I.G.'s revenue, but there were divisions, including capital markets and aircraft leasing, that he had to learn from scratch.</p>
        <p>Both easing and complicating the transition was Mr. Sullivan's long tenure at the company. ''I've grown up with these guys,'' he said of the management team around him. ''We've worked together for so many years, it's not like I'm the new kid on the block.'' But there was also his personal relationship with Mr. Greenberg, for whom he had worked for decades. ''I've put a lot of the feelings to one side,'' he said. ''From Day 1, I have stayed focused on what's good for A.I.G.''</p>
        <p>One senior A.I.G. executive said he had assumed that Mr. Sullivan was upset by what happened to Mr. Greenberg, but added that ''he would feel it was poor form to show it.'' Others agreed that Mr. Sullivan has concealed his feelings about Mr. Greenberg's fate, focusing instead on what the senior executive said was a simple message: ''We don't have the luxury of emotion. No matter how we feel we have to move forward.''</p>
        <p>He certainly had plenty to distract him in his first eight weeks on the job. Federal and state investigations widened, and investors feared that Mr. Spitzer might indict the company. It was unclear whether A.I.G.'s bizarrely consistent results were just a fiction.</p>
        <p>As A.I.G.'s stock plummeted -- it fell more than 30 percent from Feb. 10 to April 25 -- Mr. Sullivan met personally with Mr. Spitzer and told him that he and A.I.G. would cooperate, negating the need for any more subpoenas, according to someone briefed on the meeting. Mr. Spitzer put out a statement saying that he anticipated a civil resolution with A.I.G. The stock's free fall halted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sullivan, meanwhile, had to move to get A.I.G. out of the mess it had landed in. He oversaw an internal review of all of the company's businesses, which was no small challenge. A.I.G. operates in 130 countries and has 92,000 employees. Domestic brokerage, for instance, which is just one unit of one business, has 49 companies.</p>
        <p>The company's profile reads like a financial services yellow pages. It has four major businesses, and it is a giant in each of them. A.I.G. is, for example, the largest underwriter of commercial and industrial insurance in the United States, as well as the top underwriter of director and officer insurance, professional liability insurance and environmental and aviation insurance, to name a handful. It is the top life insurer in Japan, the largest corporate investor in United States Treasury bonds and has the second-largest consumer finance business in the world.</p>
        <p>The entire colossus had to be examined under a microscope. Thirty-seven internal teams were formed, reporting back to the board's outside counsel as well as to Mr. Sullivan and the company's chief financial officer, Steven J. Bensinger, who was also new to his post. They worked 15 to 18 hours a day, seven days a week, for two and a half months, Mr. Bensinger said. The message to employees was this: cooperate -- or else. Many did. Some cooperated and then stopped; they were fired. Others cooperated and lost their jobs anyway.</p>
        <p>''The sole objective of every person involved in this effort was to make the best reasoned judgments, get it right and put it behind us,'' said Mr. Bensinger, who, along with Mr. Sullivan, would have to sign the company's financial statement. The process took a toll. ''No one involved in this process would ever want to repeat it,'' said Mr. Bensinger.</p>
        <p>THE internal investigation revealed widespread wrongdoing, much of which it laid on the doorstep of Mr. Greenberg and A.I.G.'s former chief financial officer, Howard I. Smith. On May 26, after the internal investigation was completed, Mr. Spitzer sued the company, along with Mr. Greenberg and Mr. Smith, accusing them of using accounting gimmickry to mask A.I.G.'s true financial condition. Both men deny any wrongdoing and say they plan to fight the charges.</p>
        <p>Three days later, A.I.G. restated five years' worth of earnings. Net income for 2004 was cut by $1.32 billion, or 12 percent, to $9.73 billion. Over all, the restatement reduced A.I.G.'s net income from 2000 through 2004 by $3.9 billion, or 10 percent.</p>
        <p>The regulatory clouds have not cleared. The company is expected to settle civil charges filed by state regulators and the S.E.C. early next year, said two people briefed on the negotiations. The Justice Department continues to weigh potential criminal charges against Mr. Greenberg, and the United States Attorney's office in Manhattan is investigating whether Mr. Greenberg orchestrated an effort to manipulate the company's stock price, according to people officially briefed on the inquiry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg has not faded into the background. He continues to control two former A.I.G. affiliates -- one that controls $25 billion worth of A.I.G. stock and another that operates insurance brokerage agencies.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Greenberg considers what to do in the ninth decade of his life, the company he built is thriving without him. A.I.G. reported a profit of $1.72 billion in the third quarter, including after-tax catastrophe-related losses of $1.57 billion. ''We've demonstrated a real resilience,'' Mr. Sullivan said.</p>
        <p>There have been awkward moments. In October, Mr. Sullivan was in China meeting with government and business leaders when he ran into Mr. Greenberg, whose relationships in China are long and deep. ''It was sad,'' one senior executive said, referring to the meeting of former friends halfway around the world. ''It should not have come to this.''</p>
        <p>The challenges for Mr. Sullivan are formidable. He must prove that being different from Mr. Greenberg does not mean being not as good. He must deliver the double-digit growth that he has said is possible. And he would like to see more of his family. (At a recent dinner, he joked that he had not anticipated that an industry event would constitute a ''date night'' with his wife.)</p>
        <p>Regardless of Mr. Greenberg's fate, the future of A.I.G. is in the hands of a chief executive with deep loyalties and roots in the business. Mr. Schiff, the industry analyst, said that while Mr. Greenberg was certainly central to A.I.G., the company's future was not lost without him. ''It's just one person,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There is already a lot of work for the next person. Mr. Sullivan heads back to China for one last trip before Christmas. Is he concerned he might miss the holiday?</p>
        <p>''Christmas? I haven't celebrated Easter,'' he laughed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
