<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Children</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="442686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENTERTAINMENT AND AMUSEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEIMBACH, DULCIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD8113BF930A35756C0A967958260" item-length="1484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>Dulcie Leimbach</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Walking Tour:  'The Great Brooklyn Bridge'</p>
        <p>Fulton Ferry Landing dock  Old Fulton Street and East River  Brooklyn Heights  (718) 788-8549  Recommended ages: 7 and up  Tomorrow</p>
        <p>Maybe you have driven over the Brooklyn Bridge enough times to think that you know it like the back of your hand. But have you been under it? The Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment, a private nonprofit educational organization that focuses on Brooklyn's history, architecture and future, is sponsoring a walking tour for children and adults that covers the technical, historical and social aspects of the bridge. The tour, which is to begin at 1 P.M. today, is to be conducted by Phil and Muriel Bayer, Brooklyn Bridge historians and residents of Park Slope for 25 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Walking Tour:  'The Great Brooklyn Bridge'</p>
        <p>Fulton Ferry Landing dock  Old Fulton Street and East River  Brooklyn Heights  (718) 788-8549  Recommended ages: 7 and up  Tomorrow</p>
        <p>Maybe you have driven over the Brooklyn Bridge enough times to think that you know it like the back of your hand. But have you been under it? The Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment, a private nonprofit educational organization that focuses on Brooklyn's history, architecture and future, is sponsoring a walking tour for children and adults that covers the technical, historical and social aspects of the bridge. The tour, which is to begin at 1 P.M. today, is to be conducted by Phil and Muriel Bayer, Brooklyn Bridge historians and residents of Park Slope for 25 years.</p>
        <p>Tourgoers will meet at the Fulton Ferry Landing dock and start at the foot of the bridge. Tourgoers will walk under the bridge to the tower, which holds the cables. The last stop underneath will be at the anchorage, the 1883 building that supports the cables. If the anchorage is open, parents and strollers can go into its dark, slightly dank and vaulted rooms, which carry the faint air of a fairy tale. The group will then head up to the bridge walkway, where the history of Brooklyn itself will be plumbed. The final stop will be at the tower again, approached via the bridge's walkway. The tour, rain or shine, lasts about two hours.</p>
        <p>'Mantis' Sculpture</p>
        <p>Riverside Park at 84th Street  Manhattan  Recommended ages: 2 and up</p>
        <p>Sitting on the back of a praying mantis may not be every child's fantasy. But who can pass it up? This mantis has a colorful pedigree: Robert Ressler, a Brooklyn sculptor, chiseled the bug out of a 100-year-old ash tree that had been struck by lightning at Riverside Park about a year ago. The tree was salvaged, and Mr. Ressler carved it with a chain saw to create a yellow-green mantis that is 12 feet high, 18 feet long and weighs 2,500 pounds. And though the forelimbs of this mantis, which was financed by the Public Art Fund of the New York City Parks and Recreation Department, look as if they are held up in prayer, the sculpture also calls to mind a skinny rearing horse or a leggy fluorescent monster. Whatever it evokes, children are encouraged to climb on it, pet it and say hello. It won't bite.</p>
        <p>Skateboarding and Bicycling Park</p>
        <p>John Mullaly Park  Mullaly Recreation Center  164th Street and River Avenue  Highbridge section of the Bronx  (212) 822-4191  Recommended ages: 10 and up  Fridays through Sundays</p>
        <p>Ask any skateboarders around New York where the best place to skateboard is and they will probably reply, "Mullaly's." Sure, there are other places, tougher maybe, but few are as popular as this one, built on a former ice-skating rink. In this clean tree-shaded city park beneath elevated subway tracks and within shouting distance of Yankee Stadium, children come to test their skateboarding skills. As 12-year-old Joshua Marrero said, "You never know what to expect, or how you're going to do something." What is often tried on the half pipe, a wide 10-foot-high ramp, is the grind: riding on the skateboard's rear axle along the top edge of the incline. On lower ramps, bicyclists pop wheelies or flirt bodaciously with flips. Balancing bicycle tricks are performed on the ground; the best bicyclists could pass for aerialists. Mullaly's is easy to reach: take the No. 4 train to 161st Street, walk down the stairs to River Avenue and head north, three blocks. The area is supervised by two park staff members and is open from 4 to 7 P.M. on Fridays and from noon to 7 P.M. on Saturdays and Sundays. Participants will be asked to fill out a registration form, and be advised to wear pads and a helmet. For now, the rink is free, but beginning on May 11, a $10 donation for a yearlong membership will be requested.</p>
        <p>Children's Radio Show and Contest:  'Mike and Me'</p>
        <p>WNYE-FM, 91.5  112 Tillary Street  Downtown Brooklyn  (718) 935-4480  Recommended ages: 3 and up  Weekdays</p>
        <p>"Mike and Me" refers not only to the radio station's microphone and listeners, but also inadvertently to the program's affable host, Mike Pollack, who approached this station, which is owned by the New York City Public Schools, to produce shows for children. With his raspy, almost Pete Fornatale-like voice, Mr. Pollack says he talks to children as if they are just "short, not young." Indeed, during "Mike and Me," which is broadcast 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. Mondays through Fridays, even adult listeners get into the swing of it, calling in to request such songs as "My Dog Bernard." The program mostly focuses on children's music and it features such performers as Tom Chapin and the Chenille Sisters. Tapes of stories, like "The Three Billy Goats Gruff," also fill in the hours, as does a segment called "Chatter," in which Mr. Pollack takes calls from listeners and discusses such topics as the environment or parents and discipline. His other call-in program is "Call, Talk or Listen," which is broadcast 3 to 4 P.M. on Tuesdays and 3 to 5 P.M. on Fridays. The show on Tuesdays also focuses on issues and the show on Friday offers live entertainers. The station has other children's programs. "Kids Alive," with Jamie Deming as the host, is broadcast 2 to 3 P.M. on Tuesdays; it consists of theme-based interviews with children in the studio and other locations. Recently, several 9-year-old boys held an intense discussion about baseball-card collecting. The station also features two musical programs on Fridays, "Dancing Dog Radio" (2 to 2:30 P.M.) and "Secret Clubhouse" (2:30 to 3 P.M.). On Wednesdays, "Knock on Wood" (2 to 2:30 P.M.) and "We Like Kids" (2:30 to 3 P.M.) are broadcast. "Sports Guys," 3 to 5 P.M. on Thursdays, is a call-in show covering local and national sports. And the contest? It's called the "Funniest Kid in the World" and is open to anyone 14 years old and under. Contestants may send jokes or write what their performances would be on a postcard, in a letter or on a cassette tape by June 15. Winners, who will be announced the first week in July, are to be recorded, performing, at WNYE.  Keep in Mind</p>
        <p>32D ANNUAL CHILDREN'S MAYFAIR, featuring games, rides, refreshments and clowns and other performers. From 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. tomorrow at Westland's Lawn, Sarah Lawrence College, Glen Washington Road, Yonkers, N.Y. Admission is free; tickets are 50 cents to $1.50 for the games and rides. Information: (914) 395-2575.</p>
        <p>"THE BROOKLYN BASEBALL CANTATA" and "CITY CHILDREN: A NEW YORK MUSICAL REVUE," the annual spring performance by the Children's Downtown Musical Theater, starring 40 youngsters ages 2 to 6 who sing, dance and act in both plays. The first is about a Brooklyn Dodgers-New York Yankees game, and the revue is about living in a big city. At 1:30 and 3 P.M. on Sunday at Public School 19, 185 First Avenue, at 11th Street, Manhattan. Tickets, $2 for adults and $1 for children. Information: (212) 477-1594.</p>
        <p>"COTTON CLUB REVUE," featuring the most accomplished students from the Harbor Performing Arts Center, who will present skits, play music by Duke Ellington and perform ballet. At 3 P.M. on Sunday at Davis Hall, City College, West 134th Street and Convent Avenue, Manhattan. Tickets, $5. Information: (212) 427-2244.</p>
        <p>"THE EARLY SHOW," a nightclub featuring children, including Danny Gerard, who is performing in Neil Simon's "Lost in Yonkers." At 11 A.M. tomorrow, at Steve McGraw's, 158 West 72d Street, Manhattan. Tickets, $8 cover charge and a $6 minimum for brunch. Reservations: (212) 595-7400. TREE PLANTINGS, with children learning about gardening by planting baby evergreens and beeches, along with flowers. From noon to 4 P.M. tomorrow, at the Lower East Side Recycling Center, 209 East Seventh Street.  Free. Information: (212) 420-0621.</p>
        <p>"GREAT AMERICAN QUILT FESTIVAL FAMILY DAY," featuring fabrics created by children; "Dollmaker's Magic," a vignette with crafted dolls in quilted clothing, and children's workshops. Sponsored by the Museum of American Folk Art, the event is to be at Pier 92, at West 52d Street at the Hudson River. Free shuttle buses will leave from the museum, at 2 Lincoln Square. As part of a weekend quilt festival, family day will be Sunday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. Admission, $10. Information: (212) 977-7170.</p>
        <p>"JOHANNES DOKCHTOR FAUST," a troupe of antique marionettes starring in a six-act English adaptation of "Faust." At 6 P.M. today and tomorrow, Jan Hus Church, 351 East 74th Street, Manhattan. Tickets, $4 for children and $8 for adults. Reservations: (212) 777-3891.</p>
        <p>"RAINBOWS, RABBITS AND RIDDLES," a Theaterworks/USA production featuring Marshall Izen, who is to present three puppet shows for ages 5 to 10. At 11 A.M. tomorrow and on Sunday, at the Paper Mill Playhouse, Brookside Drive, Millburn, N.J. Tickets, $5 and $4. Information: (201) 376-4343.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
