<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beijing's Account of Trial And Sentence in Wei Case</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="815978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="VERDICT IN BEIJING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICAL PRISONERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SENTENCES (CRIMINAL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BEIJING, CHINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEI JINGSHENG</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Beijing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E3DE1739F937A25751C1A963958260" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beijing's Account of Trial And Sentence in Wei Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, Dec. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a Chinese Government statement about the conviction of Wei Jingsheng today, as issued by the official New China News Agency and Chinese television and translated by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>Beijing's No. 1 Intermediate People's Court today reached a verdict in the case of Wei Jingsheng, sentencing him to 14 years in prison and revocation of political rights for 3 years for plotting to overthrow the Government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a Chinese Government statement about the conviction of Wei Jingsheng today, as issued by the official New China News Agency and Chinese television and translated by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>Beijing's No. 1 Intermediate People's Court today reached a verdict in the case of Wei Jingsheng, sentencing him to 14 years in prison and revocation of political rights for 3 years for plotting to overthrow the Government.</p>
        <p>In 1979, Wei was sentenced to 15 years in prison and was deprived of political rights for 3 years by the Beijing Intermediate Court for providing foreign nationals with important military information and for engaging in activities that jeopardized state security and whose aim was overthrowing state  power. On Sept. 14, 1993, he was released on parole in accordance with law.</p>
        <p>During the period of his parole and the time when he was deprived of political rights, he continued to plot to overthrow the Government. With the approval of a branch of the Beijing Procurate, the Beijing Public Security Bureau arrested Wei Jingsheng in accordance with law on Nov. 21, 1995.</p>
        <p>After investigations by the Beijing Public Security Bureau, the Wei Jingsheng case was sent to a branch of the Beijing Procurate for examination. Based on Article 100 of the Chinese Criminal Law, the branch of the Beijing Procurate instituted a legal proceeding against him on Dec. 1 at the Beijing No. 1 Intermediate People's Court.</p>
        <p>The prosecution charged Wei with engaging in activities aimed at overthrowing the Government. His activities have already violated Chinese laws and therefore  should be punished in accordance with law.</p>
        <p>"The court's investigation showed that Wei, in attempting to overthrow the Government, developed a plan of action," the Government statement said, "which included establishing an organization to raise funds to support democratic movement activities, purchasing newspapers, setting up a company in charge of organizing cultural activities, and organizing nongovernmental painting exhibitions, performances and publications with the aim of setting up a propaganda and liaison base, attempting to raise a storm powerful enough to shake up the present Government."</p>
        <p>Wei Jingsheng worked actively to implement the above plans. He bought 12.5 percent of the shares of an urban credit cooperative in Beijing to start setting up a so-called democracy movement bank, and wrote and set an "introduction to projects for assistance" to people in charge of an overseas organization and asked for hundreds of thousands of U.S. dollars to fund his activities.</p>
        <p>He also registered a company . . . in Hong Kong and used the name of the company to prepare art exhibitions in Beijing so as to recruit people and organizations that would be sympathetic to him.</p>
        <p>Wei Jingsheng also secretly connected some people both in China and abroad to study struggle strategies, conspiring to unite the illegal organizations in China and act when the the right moment comes.</p>
        <p>He also use illegal means and published a series of articles overseas to slander and attack the Chinese Government, the leadership of the Chinese Communist Party and the socialist system and to advocate the independence of Tibet.</p>
        <p>He and the enemy forces overseas echo each other and try to create publicity  to overthrow the people's democratic dictatorship, sabotage the socialist system and to separate the country. . . .</p>
        <p>The court also announced the testimony of witnesses. Wei Jingsheng admitted all the evidence collected by the court. Based on Article 90, 92, 52 and 60 of the China criminal law, the court made the above verdict.</p>
        <p>Wei was defended by a lawyer hired by Wei's relatives, and was allowed to represent himself fully. After debate between the opposing lawyers, Wei made his closing statement. Dozens of people from different walks of life, his family and the media attended the trial.</p>
        <p>VERDICT IN BEIJING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
