<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tyco to Pay $3.3 Billion In Stock for U.S. Surgical</title>
    <meta content="26TYCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1019929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">US Surgical Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tyco International Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holson, Laura M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E5DF1438F935A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tyco to Pay $3.3 Billion In Stock for U.S. Surgical</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA M. HOLSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holson, Laura M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tyco International Ltd will acquire US Surgical Corp for $3.3 billion in stock (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tyco International Ltd., an international manufacturing and service company on an acquisition spree, announced yesterday that it would acquire the U.S. Surgical Corporation for $3.3 billion in stock.</p>
        <p>Tyco is one of the world's largest makers of fire protection systems, a major provider of electronic security services and a leader in disposable medical products and underwater telecommunications systems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tyco International Ltd., an international manufacturing and service company on an acquisition spree, announced yesterday that it would acquire the U.S. Surgical Corporation for $3.3 billion in stock.</p>
        <p>Tyco is one of the world's largest makers of fire protection systems, a major provider of electronic security services and a leader in disposable medical products and underwater telecommunications systems.</p>
        <p>The acquisition would help round out its line of medical products and help it leverage its existing sales force by allowing it to sell more items to hospitals. U.S. Surgical's roster includes surgical staplers, sutures, electro-surgical products and disposable laparoscopic instruments. These products account for 90 percent of the company's revenues, which totaled $1.4 billion last year. By comparison, Tyco has expected revenues of about $13 billion.</p>
        <p>''With this transaction, Tyco will have $4.5 billion in medical product sales, a solid presence in the operating room and a greatly expanded array of products for use throughout the hospital,'' said L. Dennis Kozlowski, chairman and chief executive of Tyco, which is based in Bermuda and has domestic headquarters in Exeter, N.H.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Kozlowski's leadership, Tyco's spending spree reached $10.5 billion last year. Since then, it has put several more notches in its belt. Just last week, it agreed to acquire a majority stake in CIPE France S.A., a French security alarm company, and said it would make a tender offer for the remainder of the company's shares.</p>
        <p>Makers of medical products have been frequent targets of Tyco. In December, it said it would buy the Sherwood Davis &amp; Geck unit, a maker of needles, syringes and surgical sutures, for $1.77 billion in cash from the American Home Products Corporation. In April it said it would acquire the closely held Confab, a maker of adult diapers and hygiene products.</p>
        <p>U.S. Surgical had attracted takeover speculation for some time. It is without a clear heir apparent for Leon C. Hirsch, the chairman and chief executive, who is 70 years old. And in the field of medical products, where many companies are trading at vast multiples of earnings, U.S. Surgical ended Friday at a rather conservative 23 times expected 1998 earnings, in line with the overall market.</p>
        <p>Several companies besides Tyco were said to be interested in U.S. Surgical, including Medtronic, Boston Scientific and Johnson &amp; Johnson. Stock and options volume in U.S. Surgical surged on Friday as its shares closed up $2.3125 at $39.25.</p>
        <p>U.S. Surgical shareholders are being offered 0.7606 share of Tyco for each of their shares. At Tyco's closing price on Friday of $55.875, the shareholders would get around $42.50 a share, or an 8 percent premium.</p>
        <p>Anne P. Malone, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, said in a recent research report that her target price for U.S. Surgical stock was only $38 a share under the company's current leadership. ''We do admit that a purchaser could look to a higher value,'' she wrote, ''since there is the opportunity to recognize synergies.''</p>
        <p>Tyco, which has a market capitalization of $32 billion, said it expected the merger to lead to cost savings of $150 million over three years, with a third of the total coming from consolidation in manufacturing and distribution.</p>
        <p>Shares of Tyco, a hands-down favorite on Wall Street, have risen 24 percent this year, while the stock of U.S. Surgical, viewed tepidly by analysts, has risen 34 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hirsch will remain head of U.S. Surgical, which is based in Norwalk, Conn. The company will keep its name and will be merged with other Tyco subsidiaries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
