<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Observer; Blocking Promising Students From City University</title>
    <meta content="26TUE3$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1019944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Equal Educational Opportunities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (Ethnic, Racial, Religious)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">City University of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Staples, Brent</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Equal Educational Opportunities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1DE1438F935A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Observer; Blocking Promising Students From City University</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENT STAPLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Staples, Brent</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brent Staples's Editorial Observer column opposes proposal by Mayor Rudolph Giuliani to scuttle open admissions at City University; says proposal is more destructive than similar plan enacted in California's outlawing of race in public college admissions, since it will depress graduation rates for every ethnic group and be subsequently bad for city's work force and economy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>California's decision to outlaw the use of race in public college admissions has barred most black and Latino students from the elite campuses and raised the specter of a whitening professional class in a steadily browning state. Politicians elsewhere have recognized the potential for harm and have backed away from proposals that would limit minority access to higher education. But a different and more destructive plan has emerged in New York City, where Mayor Rudolph Giuliani is pushing a proposal that would scuttle open admissions at the City University of New York. This would depress graduation rates, not just for blacks and Latinos but for every ethnic group. Such a result would be terrible for the city's work force and economy.</p>
        <p>Open admissions at the City University began in 1970, when the trustees allowed high school graduates who finished in the top half of their classes into the four-year colleges and anyone who graduated at all to attend the two-year junior colleges. CUNY's freshman class nearly doubled in a single year, with the largest increases occurring among ethnic whites who, like blacks and Latinos, had traditionally gone to worse public schools and done poorly on entrance exams.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>California's decision to outlaw the use of race in public college admissions has barred most black and Latino students from the elite campuses and raised the specter of a whitening professional class in a steadily browning state. Politicians elsewhere have recognized the potential for harm and have backed away from proposals that would limit minority access to higher education. But a different and more destructive plan has emerged in New York City, where Mayor Rudolph Giuliani is pushing a proposal that would scuttle open admissions at the City University of New York. This would depress graduation rates, not just for blacks and Latinos but for every ethnic group. Such a result would be terrible for the city's work force and economy.</p>
        <p>Open admissions at the City University began in 1970, when the trustees allowed high school graduates who finished in the top half of their classes into the four-year colleges and anyone who graduated at all to attend the two-year junior colleges. CUNY's freshman class nearly doubled in a single year, with the largest increases occurring among ethnic whites who, like blacks and Latinos, had traditionally gone to worse public schools and done poorly on entrance exams.</p>
        <p>Critics saw the new plan as radical. In truth, it was already common practice around the country -- most notably in California, which had historically offered broad access while maintaining the best public university system in the nation.</p>
        <p>CUNY's version of open admissions has been called the most studied program in higher education history. The history of that research is summarized in the recently published book ''Changing the Odds: Open Admissions and the Life Chances of the Disadvantaged,'' by the sociologists David Lavin and David Hyllegard. Nearly a quarter of a million New Yorkers who would otherwise have been shut out of college have gone on to receive degrees from CUNY. ''Changing the Odds'' documents significant income differences between students who took advantage of open admissions and their peers who did not.</p>
        <p>Despite its obvious success, Mayor Giuliani has termed open admissions ''a mistake.'' One alternative to that policy would forbid the senior colleges to offer the remedial courses that make open admissions work. Mr. Lavin calculates that the new policy would bar 38 percent of whites, 67 percent of African-Americans, 70 percent of Latinos and 71 percent of Asians from the four-year schools. Half of these students are immigrants, many of them better educated than their American peers but in need of schooling in English. Many of the rest are native New Yorkers whom the city schools have cheated of full educations.</p>
        <p>The junior colleges that would supposedly catch these students are overcrowded and vocationally oriented, and tend to steer students away from more valuable, four-year degrees. In addition, junior college students are about half as likely to complete bachelor's degrees as are students who begin their educations on senior campuses.</p>
        <p>The junior college system would smother many of the students who aspire to careers in science, medicine and engineering. This is clear from what happens at CUNY's most prestigious school, the City College School of Engineering, which is recognized as one of the country's best and ranks as one of the top producers of minority engineers nationwide. A significant number of engineering graduates begin with remedial calculus. Those who take this course at the engineering school thrive. But those who get it at junior colleges struggle.</p>
        <p>Enemies of open admissions call it a blight on the university. But students who need one or two remedial courses are consistently among the system's most distinguished and highest-earning graduates, and graduate at only a slightly lower rate than students who do not need remediation.</p>
        <p>Open admissions is not to blame for New York City's education problems. The trouble lies with a public school system that has consistently cheated the students whom CUNY must accept. Killing open admissions will not make the public schools better.</p>
        <p>Californians pleaded ignorance after passing a seemingly innocuous law that proved catastrophic. But if the CUNY trustees pass this remedial plan, they will do so with full knowledge of the damage it portends.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
