<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Line, Universities Link To Alumni and Their Wallets</title>
    <meta content="26ALUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1004920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="DOWNTIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0D61038F935A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="1237" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Line, Universities Link To Alumni and Their Wallets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Colleges are offering alumni services like lifelong personal E-mail accounts, home pages for each graduating class and regional alumni newsgroups on Internet, making it easier for former students to keep in touch and for college fund-raisers to find them; many schools are using Internet to offer graduates on-line classes, mentoring opportunities and career placement; table; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COLLEGE students used to say their goodbyes at graduation and hope to catch up at five-year intervals ever after. But now colleges are offering alumni services like lifelong personal E-mail accounts, home pages for each graduating class and regional alumni newsgroups on the Internet, making it easier than ever for former students to keep in touch -- and for college fund-raisers to find them.</p>
        <p>The alumni fund-raisers are planning to ride the information superhighway all the way to the bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COLLEGE students used to say their goodbyes at graduation and hope to catch up at five-year intervals ever after. But now colleges are offering alumni services like lifelong personal E-mail accounts, home pages for each graduating class and regional alumni newsgroups on the Internet, making it easier than ever for former students to keep in touch -- and for college fund-raisers to find them.</p>
        <p>The alumni fund-raisers are planning to ride the information superhighway all the way to the bank.</p>
        <p>Scads of schools are using the Internet to offer graduates on-line classes, mentoring opportunities and career placement for life. Such activities fall under the rubric of ''university advancement,'' and even colleges that do not offer such services  are debating proposals to give alumni free permanent E-mail addresses that their mail can be forwarded through, even if they change their Internet service providers.</p>
        <p>The Massachusetts Institute of Technology offers alumni on-line conferences that allow groups to have discussions over the course of several weeks. That is particularly handy in planning reunions with classmates who live all over the world.</p>
        <p>''I think it gets alums to have more M.I.T. mindshare,'' said Maggy Bruzelius, director of alumni network services, ''and that helps us in the long term.''</p>
        <p>Farrokh K. Captain, a 1967 M.I.T. graduate who lives in Karachi, Pakistan, said his university E-mail had  helped him keep in touch with classmates. ''Previously, I was quite disconnected,'' he said via E-mail.</p>
        <p>And Tor Jakob Ramsoy, an M.I.T. graduate and strategy consultant in Oslo, took a negotiations course offered on line to alumni last year; it featured live video conferences with 30 students in 10 nations and 6 time zones. He said he has received useful business tips through fellow alumni on the Internet and is glad to avoid international phone charges and time-zone calculations while staying in touch.</p>
        <p>Some colleges and universities offer E-mail service to only some of their alumni. At the University of Pennsylvania, the service is offered to Wharton School and engineering graduates, but the program might be broadened in the future. ''It's certainly something we all want to move toward,'' said Martha Z. Stachitas, director of alumni relations.</p>
        <p>An alumni E-mail address is a virtual sheepskin hanging on the wall behind one's laptop and can carry a certain cachet. Polly Whitney, a mystery novelist from Boca Raton, Fla., who said she got 300 E-mail messages a day from readers, relies on her Yale address to keep her from losing messages when her I.S.P. fails her (a common occurrence, she said). Further, she is moving to New Jersey, and the E-mail account will keep her in touch during the move.</p>
        <p>Another Yale graduate, Travis Stansbury, said of the service (via E-mail): ''Given the significantly smaller number of users (compared to most I.S.P.'s), there is a greater chance of getting a 'friendly' user name . . . i.e., 'travis@aya.yale.edu' rather than 'travis756@earthlink.net' or something. Not that big of a deal, but it is a lot easier for people to remember.'' The only problem is that people sometimes think the owner of a university E-mail address is still an undergraduate, users report.</p>
        <p>Harvard Business School's alumni join forums on line about acquiring capital, making the transition from entrepreneurial management to professional management, and class reunions.</p>
        <p>Reunion attendance is expected to rise as classmates keep up with one another electronically. ''Last year, the fifth reunion broke attendance records by quite a margin,'' said Ricardo Chavira, assistant director for information technology at the Association of Yale Alumni. He said attendance had been good largely because the head of the reunion committee had used the alumni E-mail service to publicize the event, arrange carpools and find classmates.</p>
        <p>Universities are also using computer networks to help graduates find jobs. For alumni who sign up before the end of this month, the University of Pennsylvania is offering free lifetime help with career placement through University Pronet, which has 110,000 members and is run cooperatively by 16 schools. Companies looking for employees pay to search the database of alumni, who usually spend $50 to post their resumes on line.</p>
        <p>All this computer-based contact will probably strengthen old school ties and loosen alumni purse strings, fund-raisers say.</p>
        <p>''It keeps people connected to the university, and that's what fund-raising is all about, keeping people connected who want to contribute,'' said Mary Gresch, a fund-raising official at Washington State University in Pullman. Soon, alumni will be able to donate on line, a service already available at other universities.</p>
        <p>Colleges are investing in staff and hardware with such hopes in mind. For Yale's on-line alumni services, the university employs two people full time and has spent about $100,000 on extra computers, servers and software. Wake Forest University, in Winston-Salem, N.C., employs 10 people, not counting support staff, for a similar program that serves people with university ties.</p>
        <p>''It takes people from the time they pay their deposit and become students all the way through their college experience, through life as an alum, till death do we part -- it's seamless,'' said Bob Mills, associate vice president for fund raising and communications at Wake Forest.</p>
        <p>''Nothing we've ever done has been able to bring people closer to the university than this technology,'' said Mr. Mills, who has worked with alumni for 26 years. ''It has personalized and extended our communications.</p>
        <p>''Keeping in touch with Wake Forest people who mean something to them is really what warms their hearts,'' he said. ''If they feel fulfilled in that way, then the money follows.''</p>
        <p>ON-LINE services for alumni can take many forms. The University of Missouri at Columbia schedules chat-room events for alumni, including discussions with the university chancellor, according to CASE Currents, a trade publication for the Council for Advancement and Support of Education.</p>
        <p>The Internet has helped bring in donations and bolstered school spirit for Washington State University. The school's fight song is one of the more commonly downloaded features of the alumni site. Alumni can get E-mail addresses that end in @gocougs.wsu.edu to pay homage to the cougar mascot.</p>
        <p>Last fall, the Coug-gear section of the alumni Web site opened two days before the football team made it to the Rose Bowl. Income from the site, projected at $10,000 in its first year, jumped to $60,000 in the first six weeks, Ms. Gresch said. Of the 12,000 alumni requests that were sent in for a chance at tickets to the big game, 8,000 came through the Internet.</p>
        <p>''We think all of it relates to fund-raising,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Site-Seeing: Alumni</p>
        <p>Alumni association resources can often be found on the Web site of the particular college or university. Here are some other useful sites:</p>
        <p>www.case.org/lnkctr.htm  Links for various alumni groups and related information compiled by the Council for Advancement and Support of Education.</p>
        <p>www.yahoo.com/education/</p>
        <p>organizations/alumnae</p>
        <p>iassociations  Links to alumni association pages.</p>
        <p>www.rutledge.com/stoner/mags.html  A list of links to alumni magazines on line.</p>
        <p>DOWNTIME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
