<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Drama; The Summer of '63: A Teen-Age Girl's Coming of Age at Camp</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="569089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WPA THEATER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUSSOW, MEL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CAMP PARADOX (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D71038F93AA35752C1A964958260" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Drama; The Summer of '63: A Teen-Age Girl's Coming of Age at Camp</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEL GUSSOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUSSOW, MEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four teen-age girls gather in their cabin at summer camp, giggling and comparing notes on boyfriends. Cory, who is a heavy reader and would-be author, remains standoffish until she notices that her counselor is staring at her. It takes no leap of the imagination to diagnose the reason for the counselor's interest. In Barbara Graham's "Camp Paradox," the footlockers are crammed with detritus from adolescent fiction. In the course of the play (at the WPA Theater), Cory comes of age in the summer of 1963 and has her first sexual experience while saying things like "I was a trespasser on foreign soil without a map."</p>
        <p>The play's one claim to distinction, or at least to difference, is that Cory's initial liaison is not with a boy in a neighboring camp but with that counselor, a 28-year-old lesbian still sulking after an aborted romance with a woman during her college days. Except for the older woman's unhappiness, it is difficult to see what draws her into an affair with the young girl, with whom she apparently has nothing in common.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four teen-age girls gather in their cabin at summer camp, giggling and comparing notes on boyfriends. Cory, who is a heavy reader and would-be author, remains standoffish until she notices that her counselor is staring at her. It takes no leap of the imagination to diagnose the reason for the counselor's interest. In Barbara Graham's "Camp Paradox," the footlockers are crammed with detritus from adolescent fiction. In the course of the play (at the WPA Theater), Cory comes of age in the summer of 1963 and has her first sexual experience while saying things like "I was a trespasser on foreign soil without a map."</p>
        <p>The play's one claim to distinction, or at least to difference, is that Cory's initial liaison is not with a boy in a neighboring camp but with that counselor, a 28-year-old lesbian still sulking after an aborted romance with a woman during her college days. Except for the older woman's unhappiness, it is difficult to see what draws her into an affair with the young girl, with whom she apparently has nothing in common.</p>
        <p>In the narrative approach, Ms. Graham seems to have been overly affected by plays and movies from "The Glass Menagerie" to "Dirty Dancing." Cory tells the story to the audience, interrupting the action for sidelong comments. As the play moves through the camp's daily activities, complete with a chorus of "On Top of Old Smoky" and a glimpse of an end-of-season variety show, the atmosphere becomes stifling.</p>
        <p>In the background is Cory's mother writing letters to her daughter and talking on the telephone. As played raucously by Alix Korey, she is a cartoon of a Jewish mother. Faced with such a parent, it is easy to see why the 15-year-old daughter would want to go back to summer camp, even at her advanced age. It is less easy to understand why the WPA would have thought this play was worthy of production.</p>
        <p>Considering the limitations, Melia Bensussen's direction is relatively smooth (except for the scenes with the mother). Meredith Scott Lynn invests the protagonist with a certain sensitivity and Danielle Ferland adds peppiness as her longtime best friend. In the role of the counselor, Christina Haag manages to play down the awkwardness of scenes that call for her to look soulfully at the young camper and then jump into a narrow cot with her.</p>
        <p>"Camp Paradox" plods a predictable course to an obligatory flash forward when Cory brings us up to date on what has happened to the characters in the intervening years. As for herself, she confesses, "I didn't become a writer," words that one is not eager to contradict. CAMP PARADOX</p>
        <p>By Barbara Graham; directed by Melia Bensussen; setting by Edward T. Gianfrancesco; lighting by Craig Evans; costumes by Mimi Maxmen; sound by Aural Fixation/Guy Sherman; hair by Bobby H. Grayson; production stage manager, John Frederick Sullivan. Presented by the WPA Theater, Kyle Renick, artistic director; Donna Lieberman, managing director. At 519 West 23d Street, Chelsea. Cory . . . Meredith Scott Lynn Edith . . . Alix Korey C. J. . . . Emily Schulman Renee . . . Danielle Ferland Iris . . . Russell Koplin Donna . . . Christina Haag Carla . . . Liann Pattison</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
