<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raanana Journal;   State of Israel Just Now: A Big Welcome Wagon</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="336524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND EMIGRATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOLUNTEERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL, STATE OF</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHARTRAND, SABRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB153BF932A15750C0A966958260" item-length="981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raanana Journal;   State of Israel Just Now: A Big Welcome Wagon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRA CHARTRAND, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHARTRAND, SABRA</byline>
      <dateline>RAANANA, Israel</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: On a quiet, tree-lined street in this affluent town, Binyamin Krivonosov sat in his new apartment and surveyed three couches and armchairs, two coffee tables, two dinette sets and two refrigerators crowding the room.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: On a quiet, tree-lined street in this affluent town, Binyamin Krivonosov sat in his new apartment and surveyed three couches and armchairs, two coffee tables, two dinette sets and two refrigerators crowding the room.</p>
        <p>On a quiet, tree-lined street in this affluent town, Binyamin Krivonosov sat in his new apartment and surveyed three couches and armchairs, two coffee tables, two dinette sets and two refrigerators crowding the room.</p>
        <p>''Everything you see in this house, people gave to us as presents,'' said Mr. Krivonosov, 68 years old, a retired Soviet Army colonel who arrived in Israel from Leningrad six months ago.</p>
        <p>A few blocks away in a sunny park, Ella Tsvayer gently rocked a carriage in which her two-month-old daughter slept.</p>
        <p>''Everybody is giving me things,'' said Mrs. Tsvayer, 38 years old, also from Leningrad, who came in October. ''I've got three carriages and five cribs.'' She has only two children.</p>
        <p>Legions of Volunteers</p>
        <p>Mr. Krivonosov, his wife and their 23-year-old son now live in a large, airy two-bedroom apartment that was rented for them by Raanana's recently created immigrant absorption committee. Mrs. Tsvayer and her family live in a similar apartment nearby.</p>
        <p>For the new Israelis arriving since the beginning of the year, unlike the Soviet immigrants who arrived here in the 1970's, or for that matter, unlike any other group of Jewish immigrants, the transition into society is being eased by the enthusiastic response to their arrival from Israeli cities, institutions and thousands of individual volunteers.</p>
        <p>Until this wave of Soviet Jews, new immigrants to Israel were traditionally left to fight their way through a tangle of Government bureaucracies, often with nothing more than occasional help from immigrant societies set up for different national groups. But all that is rapidly changing, as citizens, businesses and community organizations step in to help new immigrants while the Government agencies traditionally responsible for them continue to stumble.</p>
        <p>The Government's problems are likely to worsen: Soviet Jewish organizers here who have been in contact with others still in the Soviet Union say many more have requested immigration visas to Israel. [Government officials said Tuesday that a record 6,000 Soviet Jews are expected to move here this month. About 4,000 of those have already arrived.]  Transition Is Swift As a result of the torrent of new immigrants, private programs to help Soviet Jews have spread across the country as part of a broad, grass-roots movement of volunteers.</p>
        <p>Because many of the new immigrants have friends or relatives already here, they come aware of the problems with the Government's efforts. So thousands of families are bypassing the Government, going straight from the airport to apartments with fully stocked refrigerators.</p>
        <p>''Direct absorption,'' as this is called, has been long in coming to Israel. For years, Government officials have sent most new immigrants to teeming Government absorption centers.</p>
        <p>Bypassing the Dormitories</p>
        <p>Now, the Government says, 80 percent of the new Soviet arrivals are choosing to move directly into their own apartments, paid for with rental subsidies given to them by the Government and the quasi-governmental Jewish Agency. Traditionally, new immigrants have been housed in dormitory-like places.</p>
        <p>Housing is not the only problem with which Soviet immigrants are finding Israelis waiting to help. Many Israeli food manufacturers have started including Russian on product labels, and some big Hebrew dailies have begun publishing weekly supplements in Russian.</p>
        <p>The articles are about basics -medicines, grocery shopping, price lists for essential foods. Of course, the papers are also full of ads for cars, banks and appliance manufacturers, all in Russian. The two largest Hebrew dailies have also set up Russian language telephone hot lines for new immigrants who have questions about life in Israel.</p>
        <p>In Raanana, a small city of 52,000, 10 miles north of Tel Aviv, the Mayor's office was flooded with donations of furniture and appliances, and by applications from residents who wanted to take part in another part of the city's absorption plan: adopting a Soviet immigrant family.</p>
        <p>Kibbutz Movement Helps</p>
        <p>''To live in Israel you have to know how to be Israeli,'' Mayor Zeev Bielski said. ''You can't just pick up the phone and ask for something. The adoptive families are teaching the immigrants how to shop, how to get a driver's license, how to find a job. We've got more requests to adopt families than we have immigrants.''</p>
        <p>About 200 Soviet families have moved to Raanana. Other communities around Israel are coming up with absorption plans of their own, many in an effort to attract badly needed new residents as much as to help the immigrants.</p>
        <p>One of the first to announce an absorption plan was Israel's kibbutz movement, which calls its plan ''first home in the homeland.'' About 10,000 Soviet Jewish immigrants are being invited to live for six months on a kibbutz.</p>
        <p>In Jerusalem, Hadassah Hospital also announced plans for a direct absorption program, hoping to attract Soviet nurses and medical technicians.</p>
        <p>Informal Ways to Settle In</p>
        <p>Many cities, including Jerusalem, have no ''direct absorption'' plan like Raanana's. But many new Soviet immigrants are finding their way into apartments in the capital anyway, with the help of friends, as well as several private real estate agencies and information offices.</p>
        <p>Irina and Igor Liner came to Israel as Soviet tourists, decided to stay, and found an apartment through a real estate office run by former Soviet immigrants. They were in the apartment less than a day, Mrs. Liner said, ''when the phone rang and we were told not to leave the house because someone was bringing over hot food.''</p>
        <p>''And this was before we even had a stove,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Liner, waiting in a long line at the Absorption Ministry, said: ''It's still a mystery to us how they found out about us. Our landlady told her brother, and he told someone, and it got to these volunteer organizations.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
