<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coslet Barks Orders: Forward, March, Jets</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="336544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COSLET, BRUCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESKENAZI, GERALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DF133BF932A15750C0A966958260" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coslet Barks Orders: Forward, March, Jets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ESKENAZI, GERALD</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, L.I., March 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The transformation of the Jets has begun without a backward glance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The transformation of the Jets has begun without a backward glance.</p>
        <p>The transformation of the Jets has begun without a backward glance.</p>
        <p>''We're going forward, anyone wants to come along, keep up,'' Coach Bruce Coslet said at the team's first meeting Monday night. ''We're not going to wait around for anyone.''</p>
        <p>At the first workout today, Coslet whistled and shouted, ''Hey, quiet!'' when players were talking. ''When I'm talking, nobody talks!''</p>
        <p>The Jets are here for what Coslet calls a three-day ''introductory camp.'' And there is one word he will not abide.</p>
        <p>Forget the Past</p>
        <p>''I don't want to hear any more 'before' here,'' Coslet said, referring to comparisons to the Joe Walton years.</p>
        <p>The 43-year-old Coslet said he was aware that some players were apprehensive with the new regime.</p>
        <p>''They were kind of nervous, especially the older guys,'' Coslet said. ''They've never had a change like this. I tried to alleviate some of their fears.''</p>
        <p>Yet he said that his ''going forward'' speech is what they wanted to hear.''</p>
        <p>Coslet said that he had spoken to both Ken O'Brien and Tony Eason about the starting quarterback position.</p>
        <p>Quick Solution</p>
        <p>''We straightened that out in a hurry,'' he said. Coslet knew that Eason had balked last season when he was traded to the Jets, where his good friend, O'Brien, has been the starter since 1984.</p>
        <p>''My best friend on Cincinnati was Bob Trumpy,'' Coslet said of the former Bengals' tight end. ''I played behind him. It's going to take the best player.''</p>
        <p>Coslet said that the Jets had no plans to trade either quarterback, and that neither player had an advantage. If both remain, the Jets will have to pay them $2.55 million in salary. O'Brien will earn $1.3 million this season and Eason $1.25 million.</p>
        <p>''They're both quality starting quarterbacks,'' Coslet said. ''I'd be crazy to get rid of one of them. There's going to be open competition, man-to-man. The best player is going to play.''</p>
        <p>Last season, Eason said that a quarterback competition ''wouldn't work out.''</p>
        <p>Embraces New System</p>
        <p>''It's pretty much of a reality now,'' Eason said today. ''It's different now. When I came in last year, I didn't know what my role with Joe Walton was going to be, what his plans were. There was no rhyme or reason to some things Joe Walton did. This system is much more original, much cleaner. It gives you more branches to go to. It's updated. It's the 1990's.''</p>
        <p>Eason even described Coslet's talk to the team as ''a breath of fresh air. They enjoyed it, not being talked down to.''</p>
        <p>O'Brien said the quarterback competition was ''something we look forward to. It's fortunate we're friends.''</p>
        <p>Would O'Brien remain with the team if Eason wins the starting job?</p>
        <p>''I don't plan on losing the job, but I'll do whatever it takes,'' O'Brien said.</p>
        <p>O'Brien's Shoulder Improving</p>
        <p>O'Brien's right shoulder, which underwent surgery before the season finale, is progressing well and he may be allowed to throw at mini-camp in May.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
