<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television;   CBS's 'America Tonight' in the Magazine Style</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="389823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KURALT, CHARLES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STAHL, LESLEY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">AMERICA TONIGHT (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE1530F93BA35753C1A966958260" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television;   CBS's 'America Tonight' in the Magazine Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Middle East, known for its exports to the United States of oil and trouble, has also produced two network news programs. ABC's ''Nightline'' started up about 10 years ago in response to the taking of American hostages in Iran; and last week, aroused by the Iraqi crisis, CBS delivered ''America Tonight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Middle East, known for its exports to the United States of oil and trouble, has also produced two network news programs. ABC's ''Nightline'' started up about 10 years ago in response to the taking of American hostages in Iran; and last week, aroused by the Iraqi crisis, CBS delivered ''America Tonight.</p>
        <p>The Middle East, known for its exports to the United States of oil and trouble, has also produced two network news programs. ABC's ''Nightline'' started up about 10 years ago in response to the taking of American hostages in Iran; and last week, aroused by the Iraqi crisis, CBS delivered ''America Tonight.'' What will it take to stir NBC? .</p>
        <p>''America Tonight,'' like ''Nightline,'' comes on at 11:30 P.M. Mondays through Fridays (except when delayed by the baseball playoffs) and lasts for 30 minutes. The resemblance does not go much deeper. Ted Koppel made his mark on ''Nightline'' by offering an extended discussion each time of a single significant issue or an interview with one significant figure. He brought to network television five nights a week the sort of journalism that the networks had relegated to Sunday mornings or to public television.</p>
        <p>''America Tonight'' is less venturesome. Presided over by Charles Kuralt and Lesley Stahl, CBS veterans, it adopts a now common magazine format: three main segments of about five minutes each plus snippets of news and chitchat guaranteed to strain no viewer's attention span. Mr. Kuralt promised at its debut last Monday that the new program would offer ''some insights, some arguments, some fun.'' A modest promise, which has not yet been surpassed. On that first night, for example, Ms. Stahl talked with Richard Perle, an Assistant Secretary of Defense in the Reagan Administration, who wants the United States to bomb Iraq, and James Webb, who was President Reagan's Secretary of the Navy, and who opposes a military strike. Ms. Stahl's questions, as usual, were to the point, and the positions were clearly laid out. But with little time to press and probe, she could not elicit much beyond a rudimentary ''I say strike!'' ''I say don't!'' sort of encounter. Addressing her guests by their first names, in the late-night celebrity-buttering mode, did not help. (By way of contrast, on yesterday's edition of ''Face the Nation'' Ms. Stahl showed what she could do given 15 minutes. A tough interview with the Federal Budget Director, Richard G. Darman, on the Administration's responsibility for the budget fiasco, exposed her guest's evasions.) The budget was also treated on last Monday's ''America Tonight,'' through an analysis by Robert Krulwich of CBS. He was engagingly skeptical as he pointed out a certain looseness in President Bush's use of figures, but his own use of cartoons of the President was on the cute side. Had a producer warned Mr. Krulwich that viewers would not sit still for five minutes of budget talk without some sort of entertaining prop?</p>
        <p>And, speaking of cartoons, there was a tribute to ''Peanuts'' by Mr. Kuralt, in the self-satisfied tone of a man who has just finished a hearty meal. The 40th anniversary of the comic strip was given equal time with the budget and whether to bomb Iraq. Charles M. Schulz's drawings were fun, of course, but did not benefit much from Mr. Kuralt's exegesis. ''Charlie Brown is you and me,'' he said, and then a few moments later, lest anyone might have missed the point, ''He is us.'' Speak for yourself, sir. Tuesday brought a new segment, ''Other Voices,'' which turned out to be a restless-camera interview in a restaurant with an editor of Harper's magazine who declared himself in favor of free speech. Since Mr. Kuralt did, too, they sounded pretty much like the same voice.</p>
        <p>On Fridays, Mr. Krulwich shares the anchoring duties with Edie Magnus; both are determinedly cheery. Their first program, evidently meant as a respite from the heavy intellectual demands of the rest of the week, bubbled along with a treatment of the budget crisis that combined information and gags, remarks about mob movies and a quickie interview with Dennis Barrie, the director of the Contemporary Arts Center in Cincinnati, who had been acquitted that day of obscenity charges. He was in favor of free speech, too.</p>
        <p>So went the first week of ''America Tonight,'' with small subjects getting as much attention as big ones and the big ones being reduced to small ones. The main stories on Wednesday had to do with sports. Ms. Stahl, to her credit, seemed a touch uncomfortable at spending half her time on the commotion over the presence of female reporters in locker rooms.</p>
        <p>''Nightline'' has been criticized for being so chopped up by commercial breaks that sustained discussion is difficult. ''America Tonight'' does not go out of its way to sustain anything. The best one can say about the new program is that it is better than nothing, which as late-night news goes, is something.</p>
        <p>America Tonight</p>
        <p>A half-hour news-magazine program; with Charles Kuralt and Lesley Stahl, anchors, and Robert Krulwich and Edie Magnus as anchors on Fridays. Week nights at 11:35 P.M. on Channel 2.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
