<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Before Mrs. Peel, Mrs. Gale Could Avenge With the Best</title>
    <meta content="09cosg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/09/arts/television/09cosg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1774647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="DVD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cosgrove, Vincent</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blackman, Honor</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Avengers, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DVD (Digital Versatile Disk)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Arts &amp; Entertainment Network</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2DE1230F93AA35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="636" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Before Mrs. Peel, Mrs. Gale Could Avenge With the Best</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On 'The Avengers," Catherine Gale Was a Proto-Emma Peel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT COSGROVE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cosgrove, Vincent</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vincent Cosgrove discusses four-DVD set of first 14 episodes of second season of tevision show The Avengers, featuring Honor Blackman as Mrs Catherine Gale; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEATHER-CLAD. Stunningly attractive. Mensa I.Q. Able to toss diabolical villains deftly over her shoulder while trading quips with an umbrella-toting secret agent named John Steed. Did we mention leather-clad?</p>
        <p>Ah, you think, Mrs. Emma Peel, one of the first emancipated female characters on television, deliciously played by Diana Rigg on the 60's spy classic ''The Avengers.'' Think again. For before Emma Peel and Diana Rigg there was Mrs. Catherine Gale -- and Honor Blackman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Catherine Gale, armed with a Ph.D. in anthropology and a talent for judo, steals the show in the "The Avengers '62" series, now on DVD.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEATHER-CLAD. Stunningly attractive. Mensa I.Q. Able to toss diabolical villains deftly over her shoulder while trading quips with an umbrella-toting secret agent named John Steed. Did we mention leather-clad?</p>
        <p>Ah, you think, Mrs. Emma Peel, one of the first emancipated female characters on television, deliciously played by Diana Rigg on the 60's spy classic ''The Avengers.'' Think again. For before Emma Peel and Diana Rigg there was Mrs. Catherine Gale -- and Honor Blackman.</p>
        <p>First broadcast in Britain in 1961, ''The Avengers'' focused on David Keel (Ian Hendry), a doctor whose fiancée is mistakenly gunned down by drug dealers. As Keel seeks to avenge her murder, a mysterious operative named Steed (Patrick Macnee) appears. The two solve the crime, and Keel and Steed team to crack more cases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hendry left the series at season's end. An inspired producer decided to match Steed with a strong female partner. Enter Mrs. Gale, armed with a Ph.D. in anthropology and a talent for judo that James Bond might envy.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gale -- along with two brief, forgettable substitutes, Venus Smith (Julie Stevens) and Dr. Martin King (Jon Rollason) -- can be seen in ''The Avengers '62,'' a four-DVD set of the first 14 episodes of the second season (A&amp;E Home Video, $59.95).</p>
        <p>For fans of the Emma Peel era, with its outrageous plots, swinging London modishness, Dickensian supporting characters and flirtatious banter, these earlier episodes stand as a fascinating curiosity. Steed is a rougher, less sophisticated character, a bit more Bulldog Drummond than Scarlet Pimpernel. Although he dons his familiar bowler and wields his equally familiar umbrella, this Steed is several waistcoats removed from the full-fledged Edwardian dandy who looked ready to save the empire without spilling a drop of Moët. In the Mrs. Gale era Steed's gentility seems a ploy to disguise his more ruthless nature.</p>
        <p>Ms. Blackman clearly set the stage for her famous successor. An independent woman, Mrs. Gale was a widow (like Emma Peel, until her presumed-dead test-pilot husband returned in Ms. Rigg's final episode). On Mrs. Gale's CV: experienced mechanic, skilled driver (cars and motorcycles), gifted photographer and expert shot, unique talents for a female character on television then. While Steed and Mrs. Peel play an ''are they or aren't they?'' game, Mrs. Gale is strictly professional when it comes to her occasionally leering partner.</p>
        <p>With each episode videotaped over two frenetic days (the series switched to film with the arrival of Ms. Rigg), the Steed-Gale series often displays a breathlessness reminiscent of television's golden age. Some scenes look murky. Dialogue can be muffled, the camera shaky. Actors sweat under the studio lights. They blow their lines now and then. Claustrophobic sets limit action sequences. Yet there are glimmers of the wit and ingenuity that characterized much of the Steed-Peel years. In ''Mr. Teddy Bear,'' the first Steed-Gale adventure, she steals the villain's cigarette case, only to discover that the fingerprints on it belong to a chimpanzee. No further explanation is offered. And in ''Bullseye'' she chats up a suspicious mogul (is there another kind?): Mrs. Gale: ''How would you describe your taste in décor?'' Mogul: ''Vulgar.'' Mrs. Gale: ''I see you are a frank, straightforward man.'' Mogul: ''No, I'm cunning and devious.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Blackman abandoned the leather in 1964 to play Pussy Galore in ''Goldfinger.'' Outraged fans wondered who could replace her. But Ms. Rigg's rapport with Mr. Macnee quickly beguiled viewers, and ''The Avengers'' took off internationally. (In the United States ABC began running the series in 1966.)</p>
        <p>One reason for such popularity was the show's tongue-in-cheek cheek. The year after Ms. Blackman left to dally with 007, an episode showed Steed opening his Christmas cards. ''Mrs. Gale -- how nice of her to remember me,'' he says, then glances at the postmark. ''What can she be doing at Fort Knox?''</p>
        <p>VINCENT COSGROVE</p>
        <p>DVD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
