<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Power Flower</title>
    <meta content="09goodyear" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/09/books/review/09goodyear.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1774587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="'Tales of the Rose Tree,' by Jane Brown"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Brown, Jane (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0DB1430F93AA35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Power Flower</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Power Flower</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANA GOODYEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodyear, Dana</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TALES OF THE ROSE TREE</p>
        <p>Ravishing Rhododendrons and Their Travels Around the World.</p>
        <p>By Jane Brown.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 308 pp.</p>
        <p>David R. Godine. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jane Brown traces the rhododendron through history, myth, art and literature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TALES OF THE ROSE TREE</p>
        <p>Ravishing Rhododendrons and Their Travels Around the World.</p>
        <p>By Jane Brown.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 308 pp.</p>
        <p>David R. Godine. $35.</p>
        <p>There is a passionate debate about rhododendrons raging in England right now. An ''anti-rhododendron'' press decries the incursions of an alien invader under inciting headlines like ''Death to the Menace'' and ''Sick Rhododendrons Threaten the English Oak,'' while botanists and biologists explain that the natural habitat of the rhododendron extends from East Asia to the Eastern United States and once may have covered Central and Western Europe, too. As Jane Brown points out in ''Tales of the Rose Tree,'' her detailed genealogy of the large and varied plant group -- the genus, whose name literally means ''rose tree,'' is descended from the magnolia and the tea families and contains more than 1,000 species, including all azaleas -- the question of what makes a native is contentious not only when it comes to human beings.</p>
        <p>Brown sees the plants, probably first brought to England in the 17th century and now so common that they are looked down upon as ''mother-in-law's shrubbery,'' as a deracinated tribe of ''glorious and scented strangers,'' and exodus and migration is her central metaphor. Quoting the British scientist Richard Dawkins, she says her goal is to adopt ''a less human-centered view of the natural world.'' This heightened empathy, with its postcolonial discourse and attention to ''otherness,'' is superimposed upon an oddly 19th-century cast of mind. Rhododendrons, Brown writes, ''have an oriental mystique -- for most of them come from China -- and more than a tinge of that fabled inscrutability.'' She then asks the reader to ''imagine yourself a rhododendron. Imagine you have been kidnapped, plucked from home, imprisoned in dark and sulphurous airs, prinked and poked by ugly hands, mated with strangers and given an alien name.'' It's an odd (not to mention utterly unappealing) command, and not particularly helpful as a literary device.</p>
        <p>Brown has written many sociological studies of gardening -- including ''Vita's Other World,'' a wonderful ''gardening biography'' about Sackville-West's Sissinghurst -- and her scholarship is impressive. Painstakingly, she tracks the rhododendron through history, myth, art, literature, offering up the story of the poison honey from a yellow ''yolk of egg'' azalea that sickened the troops in Xenophon's ''Anabasis,'' the Abominable Snowman spotted eating rhododendrons in the Himalayas in 1925 and the fashionable midcentury textile designs of Marion Dorn. Brown, apparently an inexhaustible researcher, also sees rhododendrons where they are not. The olive branch that signified the end of the biblical flood, she suggests, could just as well have been a sprig of rhododendron from the densely covered peaks near Mount Ararat, and a John Wootton painting of a girl in a landscape of dark green, pink-flowered bushes might depict rhododendrons rather than roses, as is commonly believed. This has a way of making what is actually bountiful feel slight, a late entry into the now tiresome competition to chart the cultural history of a single natural resource, be it saffron, nutmeg, salt or cod.</p>
        <p>The ugly-handed human traffickers are more interesting. Brown gives us ''the first rhododendron martyr,'' an early American botanist ''accidentally shot whilst plant collecting along the Roanoke River in May 1692''; Marianne North, a painter and the ''high priestess of the Victorian passion for rhododendrons''; Charles Sprague Sargent, the cousin of John Singer, who was the director of the Arnold Arboretum at Harvard and ''the linchpin in America's rhododendron story''; Johnny Millais, the English adventurer and an eventual founder of the Rhododendron Society who ''brought the thrill of the chase to the rhododendron world.'' Among these rhododendron notables is Lionel de Rothschild, whom Brown names ''the chief rhododendronophile'' of the 20th century. At Exbury, the Hampshire estate where he moved in 1922, Rothschild, a playboy who endearingly named his yachts Rhodora 1 and 2, employed 60 gardeners and 15 greenhousemen.</p>
        <p>A banker by week, Rothschild was an avid Sunday hybridizer -- he tried more than 1,000 combinations -- and he gave his Exbury guests the tools to do the same (a sable-haired brush for transferring pollen, pencils and labels to keep track of parentage). Rothschild once wrote that ''the real art of gardening is to make a plant that has come from distant lands not only look at home but feel at home.'' Brown is determined to see Rothschild, too, as ''an exotic being in a world of gray compromise,'' and asks speciously, ''Was it purely coincidental that the maker of Exbury, the doyen of rhododendron gardeners, was the great-great-grandson of a Jew from the Frankfurt ghetto?'' Such connections don't enter in when she writes of ''English'' enthusiasts.</p>
        <p>THE best chapter is about the terrain that English plant-hunters named ''the Rhododendron heartland,'' along the southern edge of the Himalayan massif. Here, in the early 20th century, Rhododendron sinogrande -- an ''imperially despotic'' plant with a ''cult status'' whose flowers are ''pale yellow, translucent globes springing from the ruffs of glossy leaves, lighting the dark woods like the lamps at the feast table'' -- was discovered by an Englishman and shipped home to become a Royal Horticultural Society prize-winner. Brown, in a lovely turn, draws out the line of association in Chinese poetry that made the red azalea ''symbolic of the warm south, of the eternal poetic longing for the mountains and the compensating warmths of fiery and beautiful women.'' Hence, no respectable woman would ever wear a red azalea.</p>
        <p>In the post-Enlightenment era, the riotous flowers brought other things to mind. A botanist named Joseph Hooker, collecting in the heartland in 1849, wrote to Charles Darwin that ''the blaze of Rhod. Flowers &amp; various coloured jungle proclaims a differently constituted region in a naturalists eye &amp; twenty species here, to one there, always are asking the vexed question, where do we come from?'' His is a question for all time.</p>
        <p>'Tales of the Rose Tree,' by Jane Brown Dana Goodyear is an editor at The New Yorker and the author of ''Honey and Junk,'' a book of poems.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dana Goodyear is an editor at The New Yorker and the author of ''Honey and Junk,'' a book of poems.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
