<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Latin Bishops Reopen Debate on Church Role</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">DOMINICAN REPUBLIC</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LATIN AMERICA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">POPE (JOHN PAUL II)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINFELS, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Dominican Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Dominican Republic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DC1F3CF930A25753C1A964958260" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Latin Bishops Reopen Debate on Church Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER STEINFELS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEINFELS, PETER</byline>
      <dateline>SANTO DOMINGO, Dominican Republic, Oct. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pope John Paul II opened a major meeting of Latin American bishops today that was called to assess the Roman Catholic Church's work in the region, including its deep involvement in social and economic issues.</p>
        <p>Church leaders in Latin America and Rome have been struggling behind the scenes for two years to set the agenda for the deliberations of the Latin American Episcopal Conference here. At issue is whether the church should maintain the course it has taken.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pope John Paul II opened a major meeting of Latin American bishops today that was called to assess the Roman Catholic Church's work in the region, including its deep involvement in social and economic issues.</p>
        <p>Church leaders in Latin America and Rome have been struggling behind the scenes for two years to set the agenda for the deliberations of the Latin American Episcopal Conference here. At issue is whether the church should maintain the course it has taken.</p>
        <p>The meeting, scheduled to coincide with the 500th anniversary of Columbus's arrival in the New World, has taken on extra significance as a time for assessing not just decades, but centuries of Catholicism's role.</p>
        <p>The working document for the sessions, which will continue until Oct. 28, places deepening poverty and social injustice at the forefront of problems that the church must address. The bishops had reacted strongly to drafts in 1990 and 1991 that played down poverty and described modern culture and secularism as the major threats to Christianity. Major Turning Point</p>
        <p>The Latin American church's shift toward offering a message of liberation for poor and oppressed people was signaled in 1968, at a meeting of the bishops in Medellin, Colombia.</p>
        <p>Their organization, which coordinates 22 national bishops' conferences in South and Central America and the Caribbean, met again in 1979 in Puebla, Mexico.</p>
        <p>Despite efforts then by conservative church leaders and an ambiguous stance by the recently elected Pope John Paul II, the bishops at Puebla reaffirmed the themes of Medellin.</p>
        <p>Today the Pope, despite speculation that he might set a new agenda or revive the priorities of the rejected preparatory documents, spoke passionately about the gap between rich and poor: "In continuity with Medellin and Puebla, the church reaffirms the preferential option for the poor."</p>
        <p>This morning he traveled by helicopter to Higuey, where he said Mass at the national shrine of Our Lady of La Altagracia and appealed for better living conditions for rural workers.</p>
        <p>The proposed conference document treats Latin American culture not as simply Christian but as a blend of European Christianity, Indian and African-American culture. It was produced after the leadership of the conference, which had distributed the earlier documents, changed hands. A new general secretary, Auxiliary Bishop Raymundo Damasceno Assis from Brasilia, was elected in April 1991. Vatican Picks Pinochet Backer</p>
        <p>The outcome of the meeting may depend on appointments to key positions. Already, the Vatican has reduced Bishop Damasceno's role, appointing Bishop Jorge Arturo Medina Esteves of Rancagua, Chile, to share the duties of secretary.</p>
        <p>Among questions the bishops are expected to address is the rapid growth of evangelical Protestantism. The working document acknowledges that this development has complex causes, but speaks of a "fanatic and growing proselytism."</p>
        <p>Pope John Paul used even stronger language today, urging the bishops to defend their flocks against "rapacious wolves."</p>
        <p>And, in a passage that appeared in a widely distributed advance text but which he did not deliver, John Paul echoed traditional Latin American suspicions of some American missionaries. Without naming a target, he warned:</p>
        <p>"We must not underestimate a certain strategy whose objective is to weaken the links that unite the countries of Latin America. . . . Important economic resources are allocated toward this goal, to finance proselytizing campaigns aimed at destroying Catholic unity."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
