<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D71F38F930A25753C1A964958260" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HORSE RACING  November Snow Wins</p>
        <p>November Snow won her third stakes race in a row and also raced to the head of the class of 3-year-old fillies yesterday when she outran Vivano by a neck and Easy Now by more than six lengths in the Rare Perfume at Belmont Park. It was the fourth victory in five starts for November Snow, who raced into prominence at Saratoga in August when she won the Test Stakes and the Alabama. This was her first race since then, and she came back with a powerful performance, carrying 124 pounds and spotting 12 to Vivano in a small but select field of four fillies. "I think we ran into a champion today," said Jimmy Pascuma, who trains Vivano. "We got weight from her, but she beat us." November Snow, who is owned by Earle I. Mack and trained by Allen Jerkens, stalked Vivano for three-quarters of a mile, but Easy Now seemed to be laboring in the heavy track. In the homestretch, Chris Antley edged November Snow into the lead, but she lost it, then won it back and held off her challenger in a duel to the wire. Vivano had six and a half lengths on Easy Now, the half-sister to Easy Goer, who in turn had six on Perfect Gem. The winner ran the mile in 1:354/5 , paid $4 for $2 to win as the even-money favorite and earned $66,480. "We'll see about the Breeders' Cup," Jerkens said afterward. "She cut herself a little on the left hind leg, but I don't think it bothered her." TENNIS  Shelton Advances</p>
        <p>Bryan Shelton of the United States and Goran Prpic of Croatia used accurate service games yesterday to advance to the second round of the Seiko Super tournament in Tokyo. Shelton, ranked 76th in the world, was successful on 79 percent of his first serves, and beat Patrik Kuhnen of Germany, 7-6 (7-4), 6-2, at Tokyo Metropolitan Gymnasium. Prpic, successful on 83 percent of his first serves, outlasted Byron Black of Zimbabwe, 6-4, 4-6, 6-4. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HORSE RACING  November Snow Wins</p>
        <p>November Snow won her third stakes race in a row and also raced to the head of the class of 3-year-old fillies yesterday when she outran Vivano by a neck and Easy Now by more than six lengths in the Rare Perfume at Belmont Park. It was the fourth victory in five starts for November Snow, who raced into prominence at Saratoga in August when she won the Test Stakes and the Alabama. This was her first race since then, and she came back with a powerful performance, carrying 124 pounds and spotting 12 to Vivano in a small but select field of four fillies. "I think we ran into a champion today," said Jimmy Pascuma, who trains Vivano. "We got weight from her, but she beat us." November Snow, who is owned by Earle I. Mack and trained by Allen Jerkens, stalked Vivano for three-quarters of a mile, but Easy Now seemed to be laboring in the heavy track. In the homestretch, Chris Antley edged November Snow into the lead, but she lost it, then won it back and held off her challenger in a duel to the wire. Vivano had six and a half lengths on Easy Now, the half-sister to Easy Goer, who in turn had six on Perfect Gem. The winner ran the mile in 1:354/5 , paid $4 for $2 to win as the even-money favorite and earned $66,480. "We'll see about the Breeders' Cup," Jerkens said afterward. "She cut herself a little on the left hind leg, but I don't think it bothered her." TENNIS  Shelton Advances</p>
        <p>Bryan Shelton of the United States and Goran Prpic of Croatia used accurate service games yesterday to advance to the second round of the Seiko Super tournament in Tokyo. Shelton, ranked 76th in the world, was successful on 79 percent of his first serves, and beat Patrik Kuhnen of Germany, 7-6 (7-4), 6-2, at Tokyo Metropolitan Gymnasium. Prpic, successful on 83 percent of his first serves, outlasted Byron Black of Zimbabwe, 6-4, 4-6, 6-4. (AP)</p>
        <p>Sanchez Vicario Gains: Second-seeded Arantxa Sanchez Vicario struggled to overcome Pascale Paradies-Mangon of France in the opening round of the Porsche Grand Prix tournament in Filderstadt, Germany yesterday. The Spaniard, ranked No. 4 in the world, won by 7-5, 6-4. (AP) CROSS-COUNTRY  Fairleigh Runner Wins</p>
        <p>Vin Markovina, a senior at Fairleigh Dickinson, won the Metropolitan Intercollegiate Cross-Country Championship yesterday, finishing the five miles at Van Cortlandt Park in 25 minutes 17.7 seconds. Markovina, who was eighth last year, finished 80 yards ahead of Alex Hernandez, who led Seton Hall to the team title with 37 points. Fairleigh Dickinson was runner-up with 46 points, followed by defending champion Columbia, third with 49, followed by Rutgers, 108, and Manhattan, 143. Lauren Gubicza of Fordham captured the women's 3.1-mile race for the third consecutive year, with a time of 17:34.44. The Lady Rams' 38 points were good for the team title for the sixth straight year. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
