<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>USX to Issue Stock Linked to Steel Unit</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="419498"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STEEL AND IRON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">USX CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED STEELWORKERS OF AMERICA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HICKS, JONATHAN P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ICAHN, CARL C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DF173EF932A35751C0A967958260" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>USX to Issue Stock Linked to Steel Unit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HICKS, JONATHAN P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The USX Corporation may be preparing an exit from its traditional role as a steel producer. In a move viewed as a step in that direction, it said yesterday that its board had approved a plan to separate the company's vast energy business from its steel operations by issuing new common stock linked to its steel business.</p>
        <p>The Pittsburgh-based company, which operates the nation's largest steelmaker, also said it had entered into an agreement with Carl C. Icahn, its largest shareholder, under which the investor would not purchase additional shares for seven years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The USX Corporation may be preparing an exit from its traditional role as a steel producer. In a move viewed as a step in that direction, it said yesterday that its board had approved a plan to separate the company's vast energy business from its steel operations by issuing new common stock linked to its steel business.</p>
        <p>The Pittsburgh-based company, which operates the nation's largest steelmaker, also said it had entered into an agreement with Carl C. Icahn, its largest shareholder, under which the investor would not purchase additional shares for seven years.</p>
        <p>For more than a year, Mr. Icahn, who holds 13.4 percent of USX shares, has pushed the company to separate its energy operations, which include the Marathon Oil Corporation, from its steel holdings. Mr. Icahn has maintained that USX would be more attractive to investors if its operations reflected just one industry, making it a "pure play" company.</p>
        <p>The New York investor, who also controls Trans World Airlines, fought a protracted and unsuccessful proxy battle last year to force the company to split its operations.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's announcement came amid vigorous negotiations in the hours before the midnight expiration of a contract between the company and 18,000 members of the United Steelworkers union. After the announcement, negotiators extended the contract's deadline until midnight tonight and talks continued. Before the extension, many analysts and steel customers had predicted that a strike was likely.</p>
        <p>Some analysts speculated that yesterday's announcement was intended to persuade union leaders to forgo their demands for higher wages and benefits. They said USX might be making the case that a separate steel business could not afford increased labor costs because it would no longer have profits from the oil business to rely on. Steel demand has been weak in the last year and several steel companies had lower earnings in 1990. USX's steel operations also showed lower earnings last year.</p>
        <p>But Don H. Herring, a spokesman for the company, said, "We can't see that there is any linkage between the two issues."</p>
        <p>The union has been seeking increases in wages and benefits equal to those of workers at rival steel companies, who signed new pacts two years ago. But USX has sought to keep its labor costs lower than those of other companies, as it has done since 1989.  New Shares in the Spring</p>
        <p>USX said it would issue one new share in the steel business for each outstanding share of the existing company sometime in the late spring. Existing common stock at that time would come to reflect only USX's energy business.</p>
        <p>It said the new stock, which would be listed on the New York Stock Exchange, would also represent the company's small diversified holdings, mostly in real estate.</p>
        <p>Dividends would be paid based on the performance of each separate business. The company said it anticipates that the initial dividend would be $1.60 for both shares combined, 20 cents more than the rate currently paid by USX stock.</p>
        <p>Mr. Herring, the USX spokesman, said the structure of the company would be similar to that of the General Motors Corporation, which has separate stock for its Electronic Data Systems and Hughes Aircraft subsidiaries.</p>
        <p>The company's plan is subject to a shareholders' vote at the annual meeting in May. Mr. Icahn has agreed to vote in favor of the proposal and not engage in any proxy battles against management.</p>
        <p>Charles A. Corry, USX's chairman, said the plan was intended to allow the company' shareholders the chance to "have separate securities for its two major businesses without restricting USX's future restructuring options." Mr. Corry added that the company's objective "is to achieve pure-play investment opportunies for our shareholders."</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Icahn said that he was in support of the new steel stock. "This is exactly what we have been after," he said. "We are very pleased by the proposed restructuring at USX and will give it our full support."</p>
        <p>Officials of the United Steelworkers union were in negotiations with USX executives last night and were not available for comment.</p>
        <p>Analysts said the issuance of a separate stock for steel was likely to be the last step before selling the steel operations outright.  "This certainly facilitates a sale of the company's steel business," said John Jacobson, an analyst with AUS Consultants in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>USX's shares rose sharply yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange, although the announcement was made after the close of trading. The shares rose $2.375 each, closing at $31.25. Volume exceeded one million shares.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
