<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Party Line</title>
    <meta content="03LECLAIR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/03/books/review/03LECLAIR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1661745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Vollmann, William T</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Europe Central (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EFDF173FF930A35757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1262" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Party Line</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Europe Central'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom Leclair</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE CENTRAL</p>
        <p>By William T. Vollmann.</p>
        <p>811 pp. Viking. $39.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vollmann's fiction eavesdrops on the midcentury struggle against totalitarianism in Central Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE CENTRAL</p>
        <p>By William T. Vollmann.</p>
        <p>811 pp. Viking. $39.95.</p>
        <p>William T. Vollmann's 12th book of fiction, ''Europe Central'' -- almost a novel in stories -- is his most welcoming work, possibly his best book. Vollmann has often been an off-putting writer, sometimes intentionally so. There is the seamy (and admittedly autobiographical) subject matter -- living with prostitutes, using drugs -- of too many early works, and also of his novel ''The Royal Family'' (2000). There is the remote North American history of the four published novels in his ''Seven Dreams'' series. And, of course, there is his vaunting ambition: since 1987 Vollmann has released 14 books, 20 if one counts as separate works the seven volumes of ''Rising Up and Rising Down'' (2003), his valiant attempt to comprehend worldwide violence.</p>
        <p>In ''Europe Central,'' the history he is dealing with is more familiar and more dramatic; most of the stories are set in Germany and the Soviet Union during World War II. The major recurring characters here are actual influential people -- artists like the German painter K* the Kollwitz, the Russian composer Dmitri Shostakovich and the Russian filmmaker Roman Karmen; military men like the Russian general A. A. Vlasov and the German field marshal Friedrich Paulus; and Hitler and Stalin, whom Vollmann calls ''the sleepwalker'' and ''the realist.'' Vollmann has previously entered his fictions as a poorly disguised character or an ironic editorializer, but here he restricts his appearances to some 50 pages of notes on biographical sources and his fictionalizing of them.</p>
        <p>His writer's ambition remains intact. ''Europe Central'' gives us 37 stories, five of them more than 50 pages long, to represent Central European fanaticism and to recover little-known acts of conscientious resistance to Nazi and Communist totalitarianism. What sets ''Europe Central'' apart from Vollmann's other large-scale historical productions is its strong narrative lines. The pieces are dated and arranged chronologically to give the book a plot that arcs from prewar political machinations to Germany's surge east to Russia's counteroffensive, and that ends with cold war politics in divided Berlin.</p>
        <p>Stories about Shostakovich and his intimates or rivals -- his lover Elena Konstantinovskaya; her husband, Roman Karmen; the poet Anna Akhmatova -- recur often enough to make the collection a suspenseful near novel about the composer and his times. Shostakovich is so fascinating -- in his musical ideas, his often failed defenses against Stalinist demands, his nearly suicidal wit and his bumbling speech -- that you may be tempted to skip the intervening stories to see how his treacherous life turns out. Vollmann's pell-mell telling of Shostakovich's last years -- 1943 to 1975 -- in the almost 110-page story called ''Opus 110'' is a tour de force. As the composer jams the horrible sounds of his life into his summary opus, Vollmann compacts the themes and motifs of his book into its emotional climax.</p>
        <p>In his notes, Vollmann identifies Shostakovich as one of his two heroes in ''Europe Central.'' Like Vollmann, Shostakovich lived dangerously, wrote quickly and voluminously, rejected mainstream art and alienated many listeners. Soviet authorities censured Shostakovich for ''formalism,'' not a quality one associates with Vollmann's sprawling works. But ''Europe Central'' is carefully formed and tightly controlled. In the prologue, ''Steel in Motion,'' Vollmann introduces a telephone exchange -- ''Europe Central'' -- that appears throughout the collection, connecting the overheard voices of numerous narrators and providing a unifying metaphor of central authority that sacrifices peripheral and marginal people.</p>
        <p>The stories come as ''pincer movements,'' as pairs that give readers manageable units to ponder between segments of the Shostakovich ''novel.'' The pairings are almost always set in the same approximate time and usually in opposing spaces -- Germany and the Soviet Union. Often one story sketches a minor political character or articulates an ideological position, and the paired story will be longer, more personal, more subtle. (Think of Hemingway's ''In Our Time'' with its alternating World War I brief interchapters and stories.)</p>
        <p>In ''Zoya,'' Vollmann tells in five pages how the executed Russian partisan Zoya Kosmodemyanskaya became a propaganda heroine for her statement that ''you can't hang all 190 million of us.'' Vollmann pairs Zoya with Kurt Gerstein, a German SS officer whom Vollmann identifies as the other historical hero in the collection. ''Clean Hands'' devotes 55 pages to Gerstein's desperate attempts to retard the Final Solution by interfering with shipments of Zyklon B for the gas chambers and by alerting unbelieving officials from Switzerland, Sweden and the Vatican. Failed propagandist and tortured moralist, Gerstein commits suicide when accused of genocide.+</p>
        <p>At the very center of ''Europe Central,'' Vollmann modifies the interchapter-story pattern with matched novellas, ''Breakout'' and ''The Last Field-Marshal,'' about the Russian general Vlasov and the German field marshal Paulus. Attempting to save their defeated men from massacre, both officers ignored their dictators' orders. Vlasov encouraged his troops to break out or escape in small units on the Volkhov front meant to liberate Leningrad, and Paulus surrendered at Stalingrad; both were called traitors. Captured by the Germans, Vlasov offered to lead disaffected Russians against Stalin; captured by the Russians, he was executed. Paulus survived the war but in disgrace. Vollmann's intimate, detailed and compelling portraits provide a moral center for his book and represent its achievement as heroic historical recall.</p>
        <p>Although Vollmann has composed and arranged this whole opera of mostly doomed souls, he speaks in his own voice only in the notes. Like an intelligence agent tapped into the telephone exchange, he records narrators both sympathetic and repugnant, authentic and propagandistic, fumbling and crazed. This ventriloquizing creates a challenging disorientation when the narrator and the facts are at odds. Kurt Gerstein's heroic story, for example, is told by a condescending hard-core Nazi. Although in wartime Central Europe political bombast often drowned out the personal voice, Vollmann finds figures like Gerstein whose actions resist ideological blat and blather.</p>
        <p>''Europe Central,'' despite the qualities I've emphasized, requires considerable patience and has some flaws. The scrupulosity with which Vollmann notes the trivial ways he rewrites sources implies the essential truth of his historicizing, but I will need several years of research before I can report on that. One major departure from fact that Vollmann admits is his Shostakovich's lifelong obsession with Elena, briefly his mistress in the early 1930's. Vollmann associates Elena with Europe (Europa), but the connection is forced, and Shostakovich's long-carried torch for Elena seems fabricated to no end except the author's desire for a love story amid all the violence.</p>
        <p>Vollmann is a master of atmosphere, expanding a trivial detail into a metaphor, then wiring that metaphor to others, as he does with a black rotary telephone that ultimately extends into ''Europe Central.'' He is not so adept at dialogue. Perhaps recognizing the difficulties of creating historical and translated speech, Vollmann has his narrators expatiate much, much more than they eavesdrop on conversations. The narrators' ideological rant in some interchapters also becomes repetitive and can be oppressive.+</p>
        <p>But these quibbles are like an occasional wrong number in the vast cross-cultural switchboard of ''Europe Central.'' Part novel and part stories, virtuoso historical remembrance and focused study of violence, ''Europe Central'' orchestrates the best of Vollmann's past impulses into one large-minded and bighearted ''Opus 15.'' Or ''Opus 21.''</p>
        <p>Tom LeClair's fourth novel, ''The Liquidators,'' will be published in December.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tom LeClair's fourth novel, ''The Liquidators,'' will be published in December.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
