<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On a Night Unfit for Scoring, The MetroStars Slog to a Tie</title>
    <meta content="03STAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/03/sports/soccer/03stars.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1662186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Real Salt Lake</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dicker, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Soccer</org>
        <org class="online_producer">MetroStars</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DE1E3FF930A35757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On a Night Unfit for Scoring, The MetroStars Slog to a Tie</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On a Night Unfit for Scoring, the MetroStars Slog to a Tie</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON DICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dicker, Ron</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>MetroStars play Real Salt Lake to scoreless tie; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The weather was deemed unfit for horse racing on Saturday night, but the humans played on in the Major League Soccer opener between the MetroStars and Real Salt Lake, an expansion team.</p>
        <p>While harness racing was canceled next door at Meadowlands Racetrack, Giants Stadium played host to a bizarre match in which hard rain and wind seized the feature role and kept the teams scoreless.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Giants Stadium played host to a bizarre match in which hard rain and wind seized the feature role and kept the teams scoreless.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The weather was deemed unfit for horse racing on Saturday night, but the humans played on in the Major League Soccer opener between the MetroStars and Real Salt Lake, an expansion team.</p>
        <p>While harness racing was canceled next door at Meadowlands Racetrack, Giants Stadium played host to a bizarre match in which hard rain and wind seized the feature role and kept the teams scoreless.</p>
        <p>The elements created more a folly than a match. Balls kicked straight into the wind blew back. Players chased errant passes as if the ball were being guided by the remote control of a sadistic teenager. On free kicks, one teammate would have to stabilize the ball as if he were a holder for a place-kicker.</p>
        <p>The 12,657 ticket holders, 95 percent of whom apparently skipped the match, will be given tickets to one of the next two home games, the MetroStars announced.</p>
        <p>''It was the worst I've played in,'' MetroStars midfielder Eddie Gaven said.</p>
        <p>MetroStars Coach Bob Bradley said: ''I don't think anyone has played under those conditions. It's difficult to string together any real soccer.''</p>
        <p>The game ended with players shoving one another. But the weather was surely the impetus for the anger.</p>
        <p>At the 40-minute mark, a partial power failure delayed the game for a few minutes before the referees decided to allow play in a half-lighted stadium. Full wattage returned in the second half, but no offense accompanied it.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars, who struggled on offense last season, were unable to capitalize with the wind at their backs in the first half. Forward John Wolyniec said the team felt more comfortable advancing the ball against the wind, and that showed at times.</p>
        <p>In the 59th minute, Wolyniec took a crossing pass from Gaven inside the box and fired right at Salt Lake goalie D.J. Countess, one of six former MetroStars on the Salt Lake roster. Countess blocked the shot with both hands.</p>
        <p>Real Salt Lake had one good chance in the second half. In the 71st minute, the former MetroStars player Clint Mathis lofted a 25-yard free kick high over the goal.</p>
        <p>Players tried to gauge how to best deal with the elements as the second half trudged on. Neither side looked comfortable.</p>
        <p>''Between the wind and wet turf, you never knew where it was going to go,'' Wolyniec said.</p>
        <p>Case in point in the first half: a wind-aided free kick by MetroStars goalie Zach Wells sailed far downfield to the waiting left leg of Amado Guevara. But again, Countess did not have to move to make the stop.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars did not mount another threat in the first half.</p>
        <p>''It was tough, but good, we got a shutout,'' Gaven said.</p>
        <p>Defender Eddie Pope made his first start against the MetroStars since they traded him to Real Salt Lake in January, and Mathis was making his return to M.L.S. after playing in Germany.</p>
        <p>Real Salt Lake, under its owner Dave Checketts, the former president of Madison Square Garden, has supposedly assembled enough talent to be competitive in its debut season.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars, who have gone nine years and counting without an appearance in the M.L.S. Cup, were out to show that they were good enough to overcome preseason injuries.</p>
        <p>But the elements upstaged everyone.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
