<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Region; The City Strains to Hit A Financial Target That May Be Too Small</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="443472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DA1F30F936A35756C0A967958260" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Region; The City Strains to Hit A Financial Target That May Be Too Small</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH BARTLETT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IMAGINE a huge 747 jetliner trying to land on a dirt strip that ends abruptly after 200 feet and you will have some idea of the financial exercise the Dinkins administration is currently engaged in.</p>
        <p>One of the provisions of a state law that was passed in 1975 in response to the city's last fiscal crisis was that New York must have no more than a $100 million deficit at the end of each fiscal year. If it exceeds that target, the Financial Control Board automatically assumes responsibility for overseeing the city's finances, with powers that are Draconian compared with those the Mayor normally has.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IMAGINE a huge 747 jetliner trying to land on a dirt strip that ends abruptly after 200 feet and you will have some idea of the financial exercise the Dinkins administration is currently engaged in.</p>
        <p>One of the provisions of a state law that was passed in 1975 in response to the city's last fiscal crisis was that New York must have no more than a $100 million deficit at the end of each fiscal year. If it exceeds that target, the Financial Control Board automatically assumes responsibility for overseeing the city's finances, with powers that are Draconian compared with those the Mayor normally has.</p>
        <p>This provision was one of several designed to encourage financial discipline on the part of the city. However, some leading political figures are beginning to question whether it is having that effect. At the time the law was passed, New York City's budget was about $13 billion, and the $100 million target encouraged strict discipline. Today, with the budget just under $30 billion, it tends to produce wild fiscal contortions as the June 30 end of each fiscal year approaches.</p>
        <p>Not all of these contortions can be attributed to poor financial planning. The city is only now getting a reading on how much personal income tax to expect from the raft of filings that were sent in on April 15, and the tax is one of its largest sources of revenue for this period. The city won't know how much it will receive in bank and corporation taxes until June 25, and the state won't distribute the final sales tax revenue for the fiscal year until July 12 -- after the all-important fiscal-year cutoff has passed. There are few steps the city can take so late in the fiscal year to make up for any unexpected shortfalls.</p>
        <p>"It's going to be close right to the end," said Allen J. Proctor, executive director of the Control Board, which is made up of the Governor, the Mayor, the City and State Controllers, and three private members.</p>
        <p>Of course the city tries to anticipate these final payments by making projections based on revenues from previous periods and its outlook for the economy. But with the economy still sinking, such projections are even more perilous than usual. The Dinkins administration set aside a $150 million reserve fund in anticipation of potential year-end problems. But that fund was quickly earmarked for shortfalls that had already arisen. In the last few weeks as the estimate of the budget deficit has grown from about $340 million to $465 million the city has had to scramble to find other ways to end the year with a balanced budget.</p>
        <p>Several weeks ago the city shut down some of the computers that generate its checks in order to see what purchases were in the pipeline. It then canceled $90 million worth of those purchase orders and will submit another $200 million to a committee that is to decide which ones are truly essential. Since the city's target of $100 million is based on generally accepted accounting principles, products or services not received before July 1 don't have to be counted as expenses in the current fiscal year. It is also considering issuing new bonds to pay interest on old ones, a proposal that the City Comptroller, Elizabeth Holtzman, has not yet approved.</p>
        <p>For the city to be taking steps that may only worsen next year's fiscal picture in order to meet an artificially set target strikes some as a questionable exercise. On April 16, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo suggested that perhaps the $100 million target should be raised. Bond investors promptly registered their lack of enthusiasm for the idea by forcing yields on New York City bonds higher, an indication that they thought such a change would make New York City more of an investment risk.</p>
        <p>The Governor quickly withdrew his suggestion. But some other political leaders are saying quietly that they think the idea is a legitimate one deserving more consideration.</p>
        <p>Ms. Holtzman points out that $100 million is now equal to less than one-third of 1 percent of the budget, a target that is unrealistic for even the nimblest of financial managers. "It's too small a margin of error," she said. "The number ought to be changed to reflect modern-day facts."</p>
        <p>Ms. Holtzman has suggested that the target be based on a reasonable percentage of the budget, rather than a specific dollar figure. She has not said what that percentage figure should be.</p>
        <p>The frequent rejoinder is that nothing can be done about this problem because bond covenants would prohibit it. However, Mr. Proctor of the Control Board says the purpose of the law was to provide a package of measures that reassure bond investors. Changes can be made, he said, as long as the sum of the measures enhances bondholder protection. If there is further review, he said, another issue that deserves reconsideration is the Financial Control Act's prohibition of stabilization, or rainy-day, funds, a financial tool he considers essential at the local governmental level. As part of a broader package, he said, "bond covenants would be a surmountable issue," although the law would have to be amended.</p>
        <p>One group that would have no problem with changes to the workings of the Financial Control Board is labor. Barry Feinstein, the influential leader and president of Local 237 of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, thinks it would be appropriate to amend the law. But then, he added, "I think it would be a good idea if there was no Control Board at all." He noted that a "sunset" provision calls for it to expire of its own accord by the year 2008. And that, he said, taking the long view, "is just around the corner."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
