<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Neilson May Try The Goalie Shuffle</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="342143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK ISLANDERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEXTON, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED81F3BF93AA35757C0A966958260" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Neilson May Try The Goalie Shuffle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SEXTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SEXTON, JOE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: John Vanbiesbrouck, stuck at the end of the bench because he has been denied the privilege to start in goal, has watched Mike Richter take the stage and steal the thunder by winning the first two games against the Islanders. Richter, the Ranger rookie who if he isn't yet a playoff phenom has certainly been fairly fabulous, has won a lot of hearts in the process.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: John Vanbiesbrouck, stuck at the end of the bench because he has been denied the privilege to start in goal, has watched Mike Richter take the stage and steal the thunder by winning the first two games against the Islanders. Richter, the Ranger rookie who if he isn't yet a playoff phenom has certainly been fairly fabulous, has won a lot of hearts in the process.</p>
        <p>John Vanbiesbrouck, stuck at the end of the bench because he has been denied the privilege to start in goal, has watched Mike Richter take the stage and steal the thunder by winning the first two games against the Islanders. Richter, the Ranger rookie who if he isn't yet a playoff phenom has certainly been fairly fabulous, has won a lot of hearts in the process.</p>
        <p>Vanbiesbrouck has looked on in wonder and admiration and stood in applause and affection. He has not, he insists, ached with jealousy.</p>
        <p>''He's really captured the forefront,'' Vanbiesbrouck said of Richter. ''It's good to see someone overcome the pressure, the nervousness.''</p>
        <p>Vanbiesbrouck, who had about as good a run on the playoff stage as anyone back in 1986, added, ''I remember that pressure.''</p>
        <p>Defying Conventional Wisdom</p>
        <p>He could feel that pressure tonight at Nassau Coliseum. Coach Roger Neilson, who has maintained for weeks that he would keep both goaltenders working in the playoffs, appeared yesterday ready to name Vanbiesbrouck as the starter for the third game of the four-of-seven-game Patrick Division semifinal.</p>
        <p>Neilson defies conventional playoff wisdom, which dictates riding a hot goaltender. He wants both his goaltenders hot, and if that means asking the one currently on fire to cool his heels, so be it.</p>
        <p>''I can't comment on his philosophy,'' Vanbiesbrouck said of Neilson, who stuck with his basic rotation system down the stretch in the regular season. ''I basically don't know what it is.''</p>
        <p>Richter smiled at the notion of figuring Neilson out. ''I try not to think out Roger's thought pattern,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Got It? Flaunt It</p>
        <p>Switching to Vanbiesbrouck might be a bit of psychological gamesmanship. By treating Richter's sensational play in the opening games as a matter-of-fact development unworthy of star treatment, Neilson could be flaunting his arsenal to further dispirit the Islanders.</p>
        <p>''Absolutely, there could be something to that,'' Richter said.</p>
        <p>There was something both magical and masterful about Richter's performance in the 2-1 and 5-2 triumphs by the Rangers at Madison Square Garden. He was equal to every task: up to the challenge of Randy Wood's penalty shot in Game 1 and on top of almost every scramble around his net in Game 2, blanking the Islanders from the halfway point on.</p>
        <p>''You always wonder how a kid will do in the playoffs,'' Neilson said of the 23-year-old Richter. ''He's done everything. Big saves. Right times.''</p>
        <p>Reservoir of Confidence</p>
        <p>In the process, he has brought the Garden crowd to its feet again and again and has brought his team a deep, revivifying reservoir of confidence.</p>
        <p>''When Wood was in on the breakaway again tonight,'' said James Patrick, the Ranger defenseman, ''I was on the bench, and as I watched - I don't know it was strange - but I saw it as this repeat, this showcase, Mike saying to him, 'Go on, try something else.' That's how much confidence I have in the guy.''</p>
        <p>Richter, who is not wanting for confidence, said: ''It's no coincidence how I've played. And there hasn't exactly been trouble getting up for the games.''</p>
        <p>Vanbiesbrouck has been a model of public support for Richter.</p>
        <p>''No, there's not an ache,'' said Vanbiesbrouck, who started every game against the Islanders in the regular season. ''What there's been has been a sense of accomplishment. Mike's got such great basics, such good technique, it's taught me something.''</p>
        <p>''I'd like to think it's an edge,'' he said of the strategy of confidence. ''But it's all proven on the ice.''</p>
        <p>Physical and Disciplined</p>
        <p>What the Rangers have proved through the first two games is that they have been the better team at meeting one of the top mandates of the playoffs. They have played physically, but with discipline, drawing far more penalties than they have taken while at the same time taking the body at almost every opportunity.</p>
        <p>The Islanders, having paid the heavy cost of suspensions for their loss of composure in the opening game, paid another huge price in the second for their indiscretions, with the Rangers cashing in three of nine chances on the power play.</p>
        <p>''They got themselves in trouble,'' said Bernie Nicholls, whose second goal in two games, a power-play goal after Mark Fitzpatrick's unprovoked major penalty for butt-ending, put Game 2 out of reach at 5-2. ''They had us doubled in shots and were outplaying us.</p>
        <p>''They can't do what they did. But that's discipline. And you don't win in the playoffs without it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
