<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In This Case, All That Glitters Is Gold. Just Don't Call Them Coins.</title>
    <meta content="12coins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/12/nyregion/12coins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1694163"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gold</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United States Mint</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6DF153EF931A2575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In This Case, All That Glitters Is Gold. Just Don't Call Them Coins.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">They're Gold, but Don't Call Them Coins</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Mint announced yesterday that it had recovered 10 more of its fabled 1933 double eagle $20 gold pieces and stored them in Fort Knox. But the family that sought to authenticate them at the Mint claims that the government had no right to take them.</p>
        <p>Beth Deisher, the editor of Coin World, said that ''it has been rumored for years that more of these coins were being held by private citizens.'' The Mint's announcement on its Web site caused a sensation in coin circles yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Mint announced yesterday that it had recovered 10 more of its fabled 1933 double eagle $20 gold pieces and stored them in Fort Knox. But the family that sought to authenticate them at the Mint claims that the government had no right to take them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States Mint announced yesterday that it had recovered 10 more of its fabled 1933 double eagle $20 gold pieces and stored them in Fort Knox. But the family that sought to authenticate them at the Mint claims that the government had no right to take them.</p>
        <p>Beth Deisher, the editor of Coin World, said that ''it has been rumored for years that more of these coins were being held by private citizens.'' The Mint's announcement on its Web site caused a sensation in coin circles yesterday.</p>
        <p>A 1933 double eagle that surfaced in 1996 is on exhibition at the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, at 33 Liberty Street in Manhattan. The Treasury declared it a coin as part of a legal settlement, and in 2002 it was sold at Sotheby's for $7.59 million -- the most ever publicly paid for a coin. The anonymous buyer has lent it for display.</p>
        <p>''We are pleased that these 10 double eagles have been recovered,'' David Lebryk, the Mint's acting director, said in the statement. ''These double eagles were never lawfully issued, but instead, were taken from the United States Mint at Philadelphia in an unlawful manner more than 70 years ago. They are, and always have been, public property belonging to the United States.''</p>
        <p>The Mint said that the Treasury would not declare them legal coins, or auction them. They came to light last September when, the Mint said, the government was approached by a lawyer for the family of a Philadelphia jeweler.</p>
        <p>The lawyer, Barry H. Berke of Manhattan, said the gold pieces were ''voluntarily'' revealed to the government by Joan Langbord, the daughter of the jeweler, Israel Switt, who died in the early 1980's. He added: ''The Mint has responded to their good-faith efforts to amicably resolve any issues relating to their coins by seeking to keep the coins. The Langbord family fully expects that their coins will be returned to them so they can be freely traded like every other numismatic treasure with a colorful history. I expect that if they are not returned there will be litigation.''</p>
        <p>When the United States came off the gold standard in 1933, President Franklin D. Roosevelt ordered the destruction of all but two of the pieces -- called double eagles because they were twice the value of a $10 eagle gold piece. But some left the Mint under murky circumstances that are still debated; any that have turned up have been claimed by the Secret Service. Mr. Berke said that the government had never established that the pieces were stolen.</p>
        <p>In 2002, ''the Mint guaranteed that no other double eagles would be monetized, and that none other could be sold,'' said Ute Wartenberg Kagan, executive director of the American Numismatic Society, so this discovery would not lower the value of the Sotheby's coin.</p>
        <p>''This notoriety might tend to increase the value of the coin,'' said David Tripp, the author of ''Illegal Tender: Gold, Greed and the Mystery of the Lost 1933 Double Eagle.''</p>
        <p>Of the possibility of a lawsuit, Dr. Wartenberg Kagan said: ''The family has to come up with an argument about why United States law doesn't apply in this case, since the government holds that these coins cannot be legally owned.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
