<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Clears 9 Candidates to Run Against Mubarak in Egypt</title>
    <meta content="12egypt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/12/international/africa/12egypt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1694119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slackman, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mubarak, Hosni (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Egypt</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Mubarak, Hosni</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7D6143EF931A2575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Clears 9 Candidates to Run Against Mubarak in Egypt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Panel Clears 9 Candidates to Run Against Mubarak in Egypt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL SLACKMAN; Mona el-Naggar contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slackman, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>CAIRO, Aug. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Egypt's presidential commission says nine candidates would have chance to challenge Pres Hosni Mubarak in nation's first multicandidate race for office in Sept; election has been hailed as first step toward democracy by some and vilified as hoax and sham by others (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Egypt's presidential commission announced Thursday that nine candidates would have the chance to challenge President Hosni Mubarak in the nation's first multicandidate race for the office in September, an election that has been both hailed as a first step toward democracy and vilified as hoax and a sham.</p>
        <p>The commission, which had disqualified 19 other candidates -- including the nephew of former President Anwar el-Sadat -- without specifying why, allowed two relatively well-known challengers to run. They are Ayman Nour, of the Tomorrow Party, who made international headlines when he was arrested in February on charges many deemed politically motivated, and Noman Gomaa, whose left-leaning Wafd Party is long established and had considered boycotting the race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The race for the presidency in September has been both hailed as a first step toward democracy and vilified as hoax and a sham.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Egypt's presidential commission announced Thursday that nine candidates would have the chance to challenge President Hosni Mubarak in the nation's first multicandidate race for the office in September, an election that has been both hailed as a first step toward democracy and vilified as hoax and a sham.</p>
        <p>The commission, which had disqualified 19 other candidates -- including the nephew of former President Anwar el-Sadat -- without specifying why, allowed two relatively well-known challengers to run. They are Ayman Nour, of the Tomorrow Party, who made international headlines when he was arrested in February on charges many deemed politically motivated, and Noman Gomaa, whose left-leaning Wafd Party is long established and had considered boycotting the race.</p>
        <p>But the 800-pound gorilla among challengers may well be an organization that is illegal and not even on the ballot -- the Muslim Brotherhood, the most organized of the nation's opposition groups. The Brotherhood, a nearly 80-year-old organization that rejects violence and wants to put Shariah, or Islamic law, into effect in Egypt, is negotiating with the two better-known candidates about a possible endorsement.</p>
        <p>While it is unlikely that throwing its support to Mr. Nour or Mr. Gomaa would do anything to undermine Mr. Mubarak's expected victory, it could at least attract attention to a race that might otherwise be dismissed as a foregone conclusion, political analysts said.</p>
        <p>''If they do, I think they will persuade the country to go on a heavy vote,'' said Dr. Mohammed al-Sayed Said, deputy director of the government-financed Ahram Center for Political and Strategic Studies, Egypt's premier research organization. ''At least they will manage to shake the stagnation in the situation and at least get some heat into the presidential elections.''</p>
        <p>Since President Sadat was assassinated in 1981, Mr. Mubarak, 77, has run for re-election three times, in each case as the sole candidate. This year, under increasing domestic and international pressure, Mr. Mubarak made a gesture toward opening up the political process, by seeing to it that the Constitution was amended to allow multicandidate elections. But restrictions on who can run, and the abbreviated nature of the one-month campaign season -- the election is Sept. 7 -- has led many people to dismiss the race as nothing but window dressing. The government also controls all of the major media outlets in Egypt, and some political analysts say it is already using those outlets to promote Mr. Mubarak's re-election.</p>
        <p>''Frankly, I think it is a farce,'' said Dr. Mostafa Kamel al-Sayed, a political science professor at American University in Cairo. ''One has only to look at national papers, which have become electoral campaigns for the National Democratic Party.''</p>
        <p>Two of the nation's larger leftist parties have announced plans to boycott the race. One of the parties is the Tagamou Party, whose chairman, Refaat al-Said, said, ''To participate in the experience is to conceal the mistake.''</p>
        <p>But supporters of the president, while acknowledging that the contest is sorely one-sided, say that it will still help build a political culture in Egypt, by giving new parties a chance to promote themselves and their platforms around the country, even if briefly. Each candidate is eligible for 500,000 Egyptian pounds, about $87,000, for the campaign.</p>
        <p>Dr. Said, of the Ahram Center, said the elections themselves were, at best, a small step forward, but also were part of a trend of political awakening that seemed to be spreading across Egypt. He said there was a growing call for wholesale change to the Constitution, a theme Mr. Mubarak touched on in his speech announcing his candidacy.</p>
        <p>While the election will be severely restricted in many ways, he said, ''there is a consensus that it can be a beginning.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
