<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spare Times</title>
    <meta content="02spar" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/02/arts/02spar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1765964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6D91631F931A35755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="2187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spare Times</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spare Times</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attractions</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>HISTORIC RICHMOND TOWN, Staten Island Historical Society, 441 Clarke Avenue, Richmond Town. More than 25 buildings, from the late 17th to the 19th centuries, restored and furnished. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., Community Day 2006, with demonstrations by quilters, blacksmiths, tinsmiths, basket-makers and others. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; 62+, $4; students and ages 5 to 17, $3.50; children under 5 and members, free. (718) 351-1611.</p>
        <p>MERCHANT'S HOUSE MUSEUM, 29 East Fourth Street, East Village. Sunday at 1:30 and 3 p.m., ''Where Pinkies Find Their Purpose,'' a traditional tea; $50 per couple ($40 for members); additional guests per couple, $20; reservations required: (212) 777-1089. Self-guided tours are available on weekdays, guided tours on Saturdays and Sundays. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $8; students and 65+, $5; members and children under 12, free.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, 1120 Fifth Avenue, at 103rd Street. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., a performance by Flamenco Latino. Sunday at 2 p.m., a walking tour of El Barrio's art scene. Sunday at 3 p.m., ''Confessions of a Municipal Bond Salesman,'' a talk by Jim Lebenthal, a well-known bond salesman and former Hollywood reporter and filmmaker. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $9; 62+ and students, $5; under 12, free; families, $20; Sundays, 10 a.m. to noon, free for everyone. (212) 534-1672.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF TELEVISION AND RADIO, 25 West 52nd Street, Manhattan. Today at 6 p.m., ''Holy Frak! Battlestar Galactica at the Museum of Television and Radio,'' a screening of an episode from the series, followed by a discussion with cast members and producers; $15 ($12 for members). Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, to 8 p.m. $10; students and 62+, $8; children under 14, $5; (212) 621-6800.</p>
        <p>Gardens</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BOTANIC GARDEN, 1000 Washington Avenue, Crown Heights. Sunday, noon to 5:30 p.m., a celebration, ''Jazz and Roses,'' to open June Is Rose Month, which will include jazz concerts, tours and rose-themed events. Tuesdays through Fridays, 8 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and holidays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. $5; students and 65+, $3; under 16, free; free for everyone Tuesdays and Saturdays from 10 a.m. to noon; (718) 623-7200.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN, Southern Boulevard and 200th Street, Bedford Park, the Bronx. Through Sunday, ''Spring Sensations: The Conservatory Flower Show,'' an exhibition that changes with the season's new blooms. Through July 9, ''Dutch Watercolors: The Great Age of the Leiden Botanical Garden'' includes more than 60 pieces of art and rare books. Also on view, ''Plants and Fungi,'' a multimedia exhibition with items from around the world. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Garden grounds admission: $6; 62+, $3; students, $2; children 2 to 12, $1; under 2, free. Combination ticket, including all admissions and a tram tour: $13; 62+ and students, $11; children 2 to 12, $5; under 2, free. Tram tours daily, every 30 minutes. Conservatory admission: $5; students and 62+, $4; 2 to 12, $3; under 2, free. Grounds admission free on Wednesdays, and 10 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. Parking: $7. (718) 817-8700; nybg.org</p>
        <p>WAVE HILL, Independence Avenue and West 249th Street, Riverdale, the Bronx. Tomorrow and Sunday at 1 p.m., a family art project that involves making a nest out of natural items. Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Garden Discovery,'' a watercolor workshop using the garden's blooms as inspiration; $20 ($15 for members); registration required: (718) 549-3200, Ext. 305. Tuesdays through Sundays, 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; till 9 p.m. on Wednesdays in July. $4; students and 65+, $2; under 6, free; Tuesdays, free all day; Saturdays, free 9 a.m. to noon; (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>New York City</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON SQUARE OUTDOOR ART EXHIBIT, on the sidewalks north, south and east of Washington Square Park, Greenwich Village. Tomorrow and Sunday, noon to sundown.</p>
        <p>VILLAGE COMMITTEE JEFFERSON AREA MARKET FEST, Greenwich Avenue, between Avenue of the Americas and Seventh Avenue. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>2006 SORRENTO CHEESE SUMMER IN LITTLE ITALY FESTIVAL, Mulberry Street, between Canal and Hester Streets. A summerlong series of entertainment and other activities continues on Sunday with a bocce tournament at 2 p.m. Sponsored by Sorrento Cheese and other businesses. (212) 302-0551; littleitalynyconline.org.</p>
        <p>PATHMARK MULTICULTURAL ARTS FESTIVAL, South Street Seaport, Pier 16, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan. A free festival of music, drama and other arts sponsored by Pathmark. Tomorrow, AsiaFest; Sunday, Latin Dance Spectacular. Both noon to 5 p.m. pathmark.com.</p>
        <p>RIVER TO RIVER FESTIVAL Free summerlong series of events south of Chambers Street. Tonight at 7, a rock concert with Super Furry Animals at South Street Seaport, Pier 16, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan. Sunday, 11:30 a.m. to 10 p.m., ''Bang on a Can Marathon,'' with a variety of musical performances. rivertorivernyc.com.</p>
        <p>30TH AMERICAN CRAFTS FESTIVAL, Lincoln Center. Tomorrow, noon to 9 p.m.; Sunday, 11 a.m. to 9 p.m. Sponsored by the American Concern for Art and Craftsmanship. Also next weekend. Free.</p>
        <p>SECOND AVENUE STREET FAIR, from 66th to 86th Streets. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>GALERIA 106th STREET ART FESTIVAL, between Third and Park Avenues. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>SIXTH PRECINCT COMMUNITY COUNCIL FESTIVAL, Bleecker Street, between Seventh and Eighth Avenues, West Village. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>BELLEVUE SOUTH COMMUNITY ASSOCIATION FESTIVAL, Second Avenue, between 23rd and 34th Streets, Manhattan. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>RIVERSIDE CHURCH ART FESTIVAL, Broadway, between 116th and 120th Streets, Morningside Heights. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>FIFTH AVENUE BOARD OF TRADE STREET FESTIVAL, between 69th and 92nd Streets, Sunset Park, Brooklyn. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>'CHANGE YOUR MIND DAY,' the Great Hill, West 106th Street, Central Park. Music, meditation and yoga. Tomorrow, noon to 5 p.m. Free. Sponsored by the Tricycle Foundation. (800) 950-7008; tricycle.com.</p>
        <p>FAIGELE FILM FESTIVAL, JCC in Manhattan, 334 Amsterdam Avenue, at 76th Street. A ''cinematic exploration into the convergence of Jewish and gay identities,'' according to the center, with screenings tomorrow through Tuesday. Discussions with filmmakers will follow each program. $7 to $15. (646) 505-5708. Schedule: jccnyc.org.</p>
        <p>29TH PLANTATHON AND FOLK AND BLUES MUSIC FESTIVAL, Broadway, between 73rd and 86th Streets. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Broadway Mall Association.</p>
        <p>ANNUAL SALUTE TO ISRAEL PARADE, Fifth Avenue, from 54th to 79th Streets. Sunday at noon.</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINE INDEPENDENCE DAY PARADE AND FESTIVAL, Madison Avenue, from 41st to 23rd Streets. Sunday at noon.</p>
        <p>'TARGET FIRST SATURDAY,' Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park. A monthly series of free cultural activities. Tomorrow the Brooklyn International Film Festival continues with screenings at 5, 7 and 9 p.m.; the festival runs through June 11. brooklynfilmfestival.org. or (718) 388-4306. Also klezmer music by Golem at 6 p.m.; salsa dance lessons at 8 and a dance party at 9. Some events require tickets; lines form 30 minutes before the event. (718) 638-5000.</p>
        <p>36TH PROSPECT LEFFERTS GARDENS HOUSE AND GARDEN TOUR, in Brooklyn, featuring nine brownstone and limestone houses from the late-19th and early-20th centuries. Sunday, noon to 5 p.m. Sponsored by the Lefferts Manor Association. $15 in advance, $20 Sunday. (718) 462-0024 or (718) 284-6210; leffertsmanor.org.</p>
        <p>QUEENS LESBIAN AND GAY PRIDE PARADE, 37th Avenue, from 89th to 75th Street, Jackson Heights, Queens. Sunday at noon.</p>
        <p>ARTWALK 06, Atlantic Avenue, from Fourth Avenue to Hicks Street, Brooklyn. Free open-studio visits and other cultural activities. Tomorrow and Sunday, 1 to 6 p.m. Sponsored by COlab Projects, the Atlantic Avenue Local Development Corporation and other organizations. artwalk06.com.</p>
        <p>Walking Tours</p>
        <p>New York City</p>
        <p>MARILYN MONROE TOURS  Several tours will celebrate what would have been this actress's 80th birthday (her actual birth date was June 1, 1926). Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m. and Sunday at noon, a tour will be sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours; $13; reservations and meeting place: (212) 465-3331. Tomorrow at 3:30 p.m., a tour sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring will meet on the northeast corner of First Avenue and 57th Street, Manhattan; $5. (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>EIGHTH STREET AND ST. MARKS PLACE, meeting tomorrow at 11:30 a.m. on the northwest corner of Second Avenue and St. Marks Place, East Village. Free. Sponsored by the Village Alliance Business Improvement District. (212) 777-2173.</p>
        <p>IN-DEPTH WALKING TOURS Tomorrow at 10 a.m., a tour that passes places of importance in the life and work of Ayn Rand, meeting at the southeast corner of Lexington Avenue and East 45th Street. $15. (917) 607-9019.</p>
        <p>THE MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY OF NEW YORK Sunday at 10 a.m., the 12th Hamilton Heights House and Garden Tour, meeting at the lower level of the Hamilton Grange National Monument, at Convent Avenue and West 141st Street. Fee: $45; members, $40. Reservations: (212) 935-2075.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK TRAIL WALK to celebrate National Trails Day, tomorrow at 1 p.m., meeting in the lobby of the Time-Warner Center, Broadway and 60th Street. Sponsored by the Urban Trail Conference. Free. (718) 352-0381; www.urbantrails.org.</p>
        <p>'MURRAY HILL; J. P. MORGAN AND TALES OF THE GILDED AGE,' meeting Sunday at 1 p.m. in front of the Kitano Hotel, Park Avenue and 38th Street. Sponsored by Joyce Gold History Tours. $12. (212) 242-5762.</p>
        <p>UPPER EAST SIDE, meeting Sunday at 1 p.m. in front of the statue of General Sherman at Columbus Circle. Sponsored by Walkabout New York. $15. (718) 789-7291.</p>
        <p>I'LL TAKE MANHATTAN TOURS Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Literary Greenwich Village,'' meeting at the southeast corner of Fifth Avenue and 12th Street; $15; (732) 270-5559.</p>
        <p>HARLEM HERITAGE TOURS Today at 1 p.m., Spanish Harlem Walking Tour, meeting on the southwest corner of Fifth Avenue and 110th Street. $20. (212) 280-7888.</p>
        <p>RED HOOK, brooklyn, is the focus of two tours this weekend, both meeting tomorrow at 11 a.m. at the street level entrance to the Smith/Ninth Street stop on the F and G subway lines. ''Last Exit to Brooklyn: Red Hook'' is offered by the Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment; $11; $9 for members and students; (718) 788-8500, Ext. 238. The ''Red Hook Experience'' is sponsored by Shorewalkers; $3; (718) 781-1228. Both include a visit to the waterfront and a stop at an arts festival.</p>
        <p>GREEN-WOOD CEMETERY, a tour of this historic Brooklyn cemetery with its president, Richard J. Moylan, and its historian, Jeff Richman, meeting Sunday at 1 p.m. at the Victorian Archway at Fifth Avenue and 25th Street, Green-Wood Heights. Sponsored by the Green-Wood Historic Fund. $15; members, $10. (631) 549-4891.</p>
        <p>STREET SMARTS N.Y. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Crimes of Old New York,'' meeting at the National Museum of the American Indian, United States Custom House, 1 Bowling Green, Lower Manhattan. $10. (212) 969-8262.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK CONSERVANCY Free weekend tours of Central Park: Tomorrow at noon, ''Waterways and Vistas,'' meeting at the Dairy, midpark at 65th Street. Sunday at 11 a.m., ''The Castle and Its Kingdom'' focuses on Belvedere Castle, meeting at the castle, midpark at 79th Street. centralparknyc.org.</p>
        <p>historic broadway theater district walking tour Tomorrow and Sunday at 10 a.m. $20. Meeting place: (212) 629-8813.</p>
        <p>'SIDEWALK SURPRISES IN LINCOLN SQUARE' Meets every Saturday at 11 a.m. through Nov. 11 inside Columbus Circle, 59th Street and Broadway Free. Sponsored by the Lincoln Square Business Improvement District. (212) 581-3774.</p>
        <p>DR. PHIL: NEW YORK TALKS AND WALKS Sunday at 3:30 p.m., ''Welcome to the Neighborhood: Bill Clinton's Harlem,'' meeting in front of his office at 55 West 125th Street. $15. (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>METRO TOUR SERVICE visits Brooklyn Heights, Fort Greene and Clinton Hill, today through Sunday at 2 p.m., meeting in front of the Marriott, Adams and Tillary Streets, downtown Brooklyn; $25; (718) 789-0430.</p>
        <p>BIG ONION WALKING TOURS Tomorrow at 1 p.m., ''Immigrant New York,'' meeting on the southeast corner of Broadway and Chambers Street, at City Hall Park, Lower Manhattan. Fee, $15; 63+, $12; students, $10; (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>Recreation</p>
        <p>New York City</p>
        <p>ANNUAL CENTRAL PARK CHALLENGE OF YAI NATIONAL INSTITUTE FOR PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES  Tomorrow, with a five-kilometer run at 9 a.m. (registration, 7:30 a.m.; fee, $20), followed by a three-kilometer walk at 9:45 a.m. (registration, 8:30 a.m.; fee, $10), near the Naumberg Bandshell, midpark at 72nd Street. Also, children's races and activities from 9 a.m. to 12:30 p.m.; fee, $20. Proceeds benefit programs for people with developmental and learning disabilities. yai.org.</p>
        <p>A.S.P.C.A. CENTRAL PARK DOG WALK, a half-mile walk for pets and their owners, followed by a festival. Tomorrow at 9:30 a.m. in the East Meadow, Fifth Avenue and East 99th Street; check-in, 7:30 a.m. Registration fee, $20. www.aspca.org.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK ROAD RUNNERS ANNIVERSARY RUN, Central Park. A 4.8-mile run, Sunday at 9 a.m., beginning on the West Drive, north of Columbus Circle. Advance registration fees: $25; $17 for members; $13 for 18 and younger and 62+. Race-day registration: $35, $25 and $15. (212) 860-4455.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attractions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Attractions</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>HISTORIC RICHMOND TOWN, Staten Island Historical Society, 441 Clarke Avenue, Richmond Town. More than 25 buildings, from the late 17th to the 19th centuries, restored and furnished. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., Community Day 2006, with demonstrations by quilters, blacksmiths, tinsmiths, basket-makers and others. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; 62+, $4; students and ages 5 to 17, $3.50; children under 5 and members, free. (718) 351-1611.</p>
        <p>MERCHANT'S HOUSE MUSEUM, 29 East Fourth Street, East Village. Sunday at 1:30 and 3 p.m., ''Where Pinkies Find Their Purpose,'' a traditional tea; $50 per couple ($40 for members); additional guests per couple, $20; reservations required: (212) 777-1089. Self-guided tours are available on weekdays, guided tours on Saturdays and Sundays. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $8; students and 65+, $5; members and children under 12, free.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, 1120 Fifth Avenue, at 103rd Street. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., a performance by Flamenco Latino. Sunday at 2 p.m., a walking tour of El Barrio's art scene. Sunday at 3 p.m., ''Confessions of a Municipal Bond Salesman,'' a talk by Jim Lebenthal, a well-known bond salesman and former Hollywood reporter and filmmaker. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $9; 62+ and students, $5; under 12, free; families, $20; Sundays, 10 a.m. to noon, free for everyone. (212) 534-1672.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF TELEVISION AND RADIO, 25 West 52nd Street, Manhattan. Today at 6 p.m., ''Holy Frak! Battlestar Galactica at the Museum of Television and Radio,'' a screening of an episode from the series, followed by a discussion with cast members and producers; $15 ($12 for members). Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m.; Thursdays, to 8 p.m. $10; students and 62+, $8; children under 14, $5; (212) 621-6800.</p>
        <p>Gardens</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BOTANIC GARDEN, 1000 Washington Avenue, Crown Heights. Sunday, noon to 5:30 p.m., a celebration, ''Jazz and Roses,'' to open June Is Rose Month, which will include jazz concerts, tours and rose-themed events. Tuesdays through Fridays, 8 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and holidays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. $5; students and 65+, $3; under 16, free; free for everyone Tuesdays and Saturdays from 10 a.m. to noon; (718) 623-7200.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN, Southern Boulevard and 200th Street, Bedford Park, the Bronx. Through Sunday, ''Spring Sensations: The Conservatory Flower Show,'' an exhibition that changes with the season's new blooms. Through July 9, ''Dutch Watercolors: The Great Age of the Leiden Botanical Garden'' includes more than 60 pieces of art and rare books. Also on view, ''Plants and Fungi,'' a multimedia exhibition with items from around the world. Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Garden grounds admission: $6; 62+, $3; students, $2; children 2 to 12, $1; under 2, free. Combination ticket, including all admissions and a tram tour: $13; 62+ and students, $11; children 2 to 12, $5; under 2, free. Tram tours daily, every 30 minutes. Conservatory admission: $5; students and 62+, $4; 2 to 12, $3; under 2, free. Grounds admission free on Wednesdays, and 10 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. Parking: $7. (718) 817-8700; nybg.org</p>
        <p>WAVE HILL, Independence Avenue and West 249th Street, Riverdale, the Bronx. Tomorrow and Sunday at 1 p.m., a family art project that involves making a nest out of natural items. Sunday at 2 p.m., ''Garden Discovery,'' a watercolor workshop using the garden's blooms as inspiration; $20 ($15 for members); registration required: (718) 549-3200, Ext. 305. Tuesdays through Sundays, 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.; till 9 p.m. on Wednesdays in July. $4; students and 65+, $2; under 6, free; Tuesdays, free all day; Saturdays, free 9 a.m. to noon; (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>New York City</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON SQUARE OUTDOOR ART EXHIBIT, on the sidewalks north, south and east of Washington Square Park, Greenwich Village. Tomorrow and Sunday, noon to sundown.</p>
        <p>VILLAGE COMMITTEE JEFFERSON AREA MARKET FEST, Greenwich Avenue, between Avenue of the Americas and Seventh Avenue. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>2006 SORRENTO CHEESE SUMMER IN LITTLE ITALY FESTIVAL, Mulberry Street, between Canal and Hester Streets. A summerlong series of entertainment and other activities continues on Sunday with a bocce tournament at 2 p.m. Sponsored by Sorrento Cheese and other businesses. (212) 302-0551; littleitalynyconline.org.</p>
        <p>PATHMARK MULTICULTURAL ARTS FESTIVAL, South Street Seaport, Pier 16, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan. A free festival of music, drama and other arts sponsored by Pathmark. Tomorrow, AsiaFest; Sunday, Latin Dance Spectacular. Both noon to 5 p.m. pathmark.com.</p>
        <p>RIVER TO RIVER FESTIVAL Free summerlong series of events south of Chambers Street. Tonight at 7, a rock concert with Super Furry Animals at South Street Seaport, Pier 16, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan. Sunday, 11:30 a.m. to 10 p.m., ''Bang on a Can Marathon,'' with a variety of musical performances. rivertorivernyc.com.</p>
        <p>30TH AMERICAN CRAFTS FESTIVAL, Lincoln Center. Tomorrow, noon to 9 p.m.; Sunday, 11 a.m. to 9 p.m. Sponsored by the American Concern for Art and Craftsmanship. Also next weekend. Free.</p>
        <p>SECOND AVENUE STREET FAIR, from 66th to 86th Streets. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>GALERIA 106th STREET ART FESTIVAL, between Third and Park Avenues. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>SIXTH PRECINCT COMMUNITY COUNCIL FESTIVAL, Bleecker Street, between Seventh and Eighth Avenues, West Village. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>BELLEVUE SOUTH COMMUNITY ASSOCIATION FESTIVAL, Second Avenue, between 23rd and 34th Streets, Manhattan. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>RIVERSIDE CHURCH ART FESTIVAL, Broadway, between 116th and 120th Streets, Morningside Heights. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>FIFTH AVENUE BOARD OF TRADE STREET FESTIVAL, between 69th and 92nd Streets, Sunset Park, Brooklyn. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>'CHANGE YOUR MIND DAY,' the Great Hill, West 106th Street, Central Park. Music, meditation and yoga. Tomorrow, noon to 5 p.m. Free. Sponsored by the Tricycle Foundation. (800) 950-7008; tricycle.com.</p>
        <p>FAIGELE FILM FESTIVAL, JCC in Manhattan, 334 Amsterdam Avenue, at 76th Street. A ''cinematic exploration into the convergence of Jewish and gay identities,'' according to the center, with screenings tomorrow through Tuesday. Discussions with filmmakers will follow each program. $7 to $15. (646) 505-5708. Schedule: jccnyc.org.</p>
        <p>29TH PLANTATHON AND FOLK AND BLUES MUSIC FESTIVAL, Broadway, between 73rd and 86th Streets. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Broadway Mall Association.</p>
        <p>ANNUAL SALUTE TO ISRAEL PARADE, Fifth Avenue, from 54th to 79th Streets. Sunday at noon.</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINE INDEPENDENCE DAY PARADE AND FESTIVAL, Madison Avenue, from 41st to 23rd Streets. Sunday at noon.</p>
        <p>'TARGET FIRST SATURDAY,' Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park. A monthly series of free cultural activities. Tomorrow the Brooklyn International Film Festival continues with screenings at 5, 7 and 9 p.m.; the festival runs through June 11. brooklynfilmfestival.org. or (718) 388-4306. Also klezmer music by Golem at 6 p.m.; salsa dance lessons at 8 and a dance party at 9. Some events require tickets; lines form 30 minutes before the event. (718) 638-5000.</p>
        <p>36TH PROSPECT LEFFERTS GARDENS HOUSE AND GARDEN TOUR, in Brooklyn, featuring nine brownstone and limestone houses from the late-19th and early-20th centuries. Sunday, noon to 5 p.m. Sponsored by the Lefferts Manor Association. $15 in advance, $20 Sunday. (718) 462-0024 or (718) 284-6210; leffertsmanor.org.</p>
        <p>QUEENS LESBIAN AND GAY PRIDE PARADE, 37th Avenue, from 89th to 75th Street, Jackson Heights, Queens. Sunday at noon.</p>
        <p>ARTWALK 06, Atlantic Avenue, from Fourth Avenue to Hicks Street, Brooklyn. Free open-studio visits and other cultural activities. Tomorrow and Sunday, 1 to 6 p.m. Sponsored by COlab Projects, the Atlantic Avenue Local Development Corporation and other organizations. artwalk06.com.</p>
        <p>Walking Tours</p>
        <p>New York City</p>
        <p>MARILYN MONROE TOURS  Several tours will celebrate what would have been this actress's 80th birthday (her actual birth date was June 1, 1926). Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m. and Sunday at noon, a tour will be sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours; $13; reservations and meeting place: (212) 465-3331. Tomorrow at 3:30 p.m., a tour sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring will meet on the northeast corner of First Avenue and 57th Street, Manhattan; $5. (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>EIGHTH STREET AND ST. MARKS PLACE, meeting tomorrow at 11:30 a.m. on the northwest corner of Second Avenue and St. Marks Place, East Village. Free. Sponsored by the Village Alliance Business Improvement District. (212) 777-2173.</p>
        <p>IN-DEPTH WALKING TOURS Tomorrow at 10 a.m., a tour that passes places of importance in the life and work of Ayn Rand, meeting at the southeast corner of Lexington Avenue and East 45th Street. $15. (917) 607-9019.</p>
        <p>THE MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY OF NEW YORK Sunday at 10 a.m., the 12th Hamilton Heights House and Garden Tour, meeting at the lower level of the Hamilton Grange National Monument, at Convent Avenue and West 141st Street. Fee: $45; members, $40. Reservations: (212) 935-2075.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK TRAIL WALK to celebrate National Trails Day, tomorrow at 1 p.m., meeting in the lobby of the Time-Warner Center, Broadway and 60th Street. Sponsored by the Urban Trail Conference. Free. (718) 352-0381; www.urbantrails.org.</p>
        <p>'MURRAY HILL; J. P. MORGAN AND TALES OF THE GILDED AGE,' meeting Sunday at 1 p.m. in front of the Kitano Hotel, Park Avenue and 38th Street. Sponsored by Joyce Gold History Tours. $12. (212) 242-5762.</p>
        <p>UPPER EAST SIDE, meeting Sunday at 1 p.m. in front of the statue of General Sherman at Columbus Circle. Sponsored by Walkabout New York. $15. (718) 789-7291.</p>
        <p>I'LL TAKE MANHATTAN TOURS Sunday at 1 p.m., ''Literary Greenwich Village,'' meeting at the southeast corner of Fifth Avenue and 12th Street; $15; (732) 270-5559.</p>
        <p>HARLEM HERITAGE TOURS Today at 1 p.m., Spanish Harlem Walking Tour, meeting on the southwest corner of Fifth Avenue and 110th Street. $20. (212) 280-7888.</p>
        <p>RED HOOK, brooklyn, is the focus of two tours this weekend, both meeting tomorrow at 11 a.m. at the street level entrance to the Smith/Ninth Street stop on the F and G subway lines. ''Last Exit to Brooklyn: Red Hook'' is offered by the Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment; $11; $9 for members and students; (718) 788-8500, Ext. 238. The ''Red Hook Experience'' is sponsored by Shorewalkers; $3; (718) 781-1228. Both include a visit to the waterfront and a stop at an arts festival.</p>
        <p>GREEN-WOOD CEMETERY, a tour of this historic Brooklyn cemetery with its president, Richard J. Moylan, and its historian, Jeff Richman, meeting Sunday at 1 p.m. at the Victorian Archway at Fifth Avenue and 25th Street, Green-Wood Heights. Sponsored by the Green-Wood Historic Fund. $15; members, $10. (631) 549-4891.</p>
        <p>STREET SMARTS N.Y. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Crimes of Old New York,'' meeting at the National Museum of the American Indian, United States Custom House, 1 Bowling Green, Lower Manhattan. $10. (212) 969-8262.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK CONSERVANCY Free weekend tours of Central Park: Tomorrow at noon, ''Waterways and Vistas,'' meeting at the Dairy, midpark at 65th Street. Sunday at 11 a.m., ''The Castle and Its Kingdom'' focuses on Belvedere Castle, meeting at the castle, midpark at 79th Street. centralparknyc.org.</p>
        <p>historic broadway theater district walking tour Tomorrow and Sunday at 10 a.m. $20. Meeting place: (212) 629-8813.</p>
        <p>'SIDEWALK SURPRISES IN LINCOLN SQUARE' Meets every Saturday at 11 a.m. through Nov. 11 inside Columbus Circle, 59th Street and Broadway Free. Sponsored by the Lincoln Square Business Improvement District. (212) 581-3774.</p>
        <p>DR. PHIL: NEW YORK TALKS AND WALKS Sunday at 3:30 p.m., ''Welcome to the Neighborhood: Bill Clinton's Harlem,'' meeting in front of his office at 55 West 125th Street. $15. (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>METRO TOUR SERVICE visits Brooklyn Heights, Fort Greene and Clinton Hill, today through Sunday at 2 p.m., meeting in front of the Marriott, Adams and Tillary Streets, downtown Brooklyn; $25; (718) 789-0430.</p>
        <p>BIG ONION WALKING TOURS Tomorrow at 1 p.m., ''Immigrant New York,'' meeting on the southeast corner of Broadway and Chambers Street, at City Hall Park, Lower Manhattan. Fee, $15; 63+, $12; students, $10; (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>Recreation</p>
        <p>New York City</p>
        <p>ANNUAL CENTRAL PARK CHALLENGE OF YAI NATIONAL INSTITUTE FOR PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES  Tomorrow, with a five-kilometer run at 9 a.m. (registration, 7:30 a.m.; fee, $20), followed by a three-kilometer walk at 9:45 a.m. (registration, 8:30 a.m.; fee, $10), near the Naumberg Bandshell, midpark at 72nd Street. Also, children's races and activities from 9 a.m. to 12:30 p.m.; fee, $20. Proceeds benefit programs for people with developmental and learning disabilities. yai.org.</p>
        <p>A.S.P.C.A. CENTRAL PARK DOG WALK, a half-mile walk for pets and their owners, followed by a festival. Tomorrow at 9:30 a.m. in the East Meadow, Fifth Avenue and East 99th Street; check-in, 7:30 a.m. Registration fee, $20. www.aspca.org.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK ROAD RUNNERS ANNIVERSARY RUN, Central Park. A 4.8-mile run, Sunday at 9 a.m., beginning on the West Drive, north of Columbus Circle. Advance registration fees: $25; $17 for members; $13 for 18 and younger and 62+. Race-day registration: $35, $25 and $15. (212) 860-4455.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
