<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Aid for Birth Control Found to Save Money</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="329977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRTH CONTROL AND FAMILY PLANNING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATE AND LOCAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GUTTMACHER, ALAN, INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIN, TAMAR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D91538F935A15751C0A966958260" item-length="446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Aid for Birth Control Found to Save Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TAMAR LEWIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIN, TAMAR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Taxpayers save $4.40 for every public dollar spent to provide birth control to women who might otherwise not have access to contraceptives, a new study has found.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Taxpayers save $4.40 for every public dollar spent to provide birth control to women who might otherwise not have access to contraceptives, a new study has found.</p>
        <p>Taxpayers save $4.40 for every public dollar spent to provide birth control to women who might otherwise not have access to contraceptives, a new study has found.</p>
        <p>The study, by the Alan Guttmacher Institute, a nonprofit policy group concerned with reproductive health, found that the publicly financed family-planning services used by 4.5 million American women prevent 1.2 million unintended pregnancies a year.</p>
        <p>Those pregnancies, according to estimates in the study, would result in about 516,000 abortions and about 509,000 unwanted births. Those births, in turn, would require government spending on prenatal and obstetric care, pediatric care for the baby's first two years, welfare payments, food stamps and other mandated support programs.</p>
        <p>All told, the study estimates that in the fiscal year 1987 the $412 million in public funds spent for family planning services saved taxpayers $1.8 billion in short-term costs.</p>
        <p>Programs Called Tax Savings</p>
        <p>A quarter of all American women who use contraceptives each year receive services from publicly financed clinics and hospitals. And for poor women, the percentage is much higher. More than three-quarters of Medicaid recipients rely on publicly financed family planning, as do more than half of all women with family incomes below the Federal poverty line.</p>
        <p>''These are programs that simultaneously help individuals take control of their lives, save the taxpayers money and clearly reduce the need for and recourse to abortion - all objectives which are both worthy and popular,'' said Jeannie I. Rosoff, president of the Alan Guttmacher Institute, named for a pioneer in the family-planning movement. The institute has offices in New York and Washington.</p>
        <p>The analysis, by Dr. Jacqueline Darroch Forrest and Susheela Singh, provides the first data since 1979 on the cost-effectiveness of publicly financed family-planning programs. The two analyses published in the 1970's found that publicly financed contraceptive services saved less than two dollars for every dollar spent.</p>
        <p>Since the late 1960's, the Federal Government and most states have subsidized contraceptive services for women who might not be able to afford them. But government spending for contraceptive services declined from 1980 to 1987, and there has been great political conflict about public spending on family planning.</p>
        <p>''The fact that so many American women depend on government-supported sources of contraceptive care is remarkable in itself,'' said Dr. Rosoff. ''The fact that relentless opposition to the very existence of these programs, let alone their expansion, is not ignored by policymakers out of hand is also remarkable.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
