<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Role For Bank In Germany</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="330023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GERMANY, REUNIFICATION OF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAST GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BUNDESBANK (WEST GERMANY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DC1F38F935A15751C0A966958260" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Role For Bank In Germany</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The rapid move toward the unification of the two Germanys is pushing the West German Government and the country's renowned central bank, the Bundesbank, to the center of the world's economic stage alongside the United States and Japan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The rapid move toward the unification of the two Germanys is pushing the West German Government and the country's renowned central bank, the Bundesbank, to the center of the world's economic stage alongside the United States and Japan.</p>
        <p>The rapid move toward the unification of the two Germanys is pushing the West German Government and the country's renowned central bank, the Bundesbank, to the center of the world's economic stage alongside the United States and Japan.</p>
        <p>And the change, which is coming much faster than anticipated, has led to more volatility in the financial markets. In the last few weeks the rising interest rates in West Germany have precipitated falls in the world's bond and stock markets or have helped feed declines started by other forces.</p>
        <p>The addition of West Germany as a third lever in moving markets up or down had generally been expected to happen as part of the European Community's move in 1992 to drop internal trade barriers and create a single market. While the country's economic presence has been felt more and more because of its dominant role in the European Monetary System, the Bundesbank has played a purposefully muted role in the last several years, some economists say.</p>
        <p>Faster Timetable</p>
        <p>But the reunification of Germany - and the naturally larger role that its larger economy would play in Eastern and Western Europe - has brought the timetable forward.</p>
        <p>''These developments certainly accelerate this process,'' said John Lipsky, director of international bond trading for Salomon Brothers in London. ''And it is likely to keep volatility relatively high.''</p>
        <p>Giles Keating, the chief economist at Financiere Credit Suisse First Boston in London, said: ''For several years Germany has been in a position to do this. But now Germany has been catapulted into the open by these events.''</p>
        <p>This emergence of West Germany means there is likely to be even more pressure on the Bundesbank to prove that it will sustain its role as a staunch fighter of inflation. That might prove difficult if economists are right in expecting a burst in price increases as a result of the economic merger of the two Germanys.</p>
        <p>Inflationary Pressures</p>
        <p>''There is a perception - but it is very difficult to quantify - that the rebuilding of Eastern Europe will be inflationary,'' said Peter Rona, president of IBJ Schroder Bank and Trust Company in New York. ''Therefore, Germany will have to cope with the inflationary effect of that.''</p>
        <p>The Bundesbank will be watched closely. Its president, Karl Otto Pohl, recently had to do a sudden about-face: he had called the idea of a quick union of the two Germanys ''a very fantastic idea,'' but once the Government made a commitment to proceed quickly, he was obligated to support that position.</p>
        <p>To assert itself, the Bundesbank could raise interest rates, which would show that it is committed to holding down inflation, said Jonathan Hoffman, the European economist at Credit Suisse First Boston. But the Bundesbank may be more likely to wait until there is some more specific economic data to react to, especially since wholesale inflation in West Germany dropped two-tenths of 1 percent in January.</p>
        <p>Difficult Period</p>
        <p>Yet without some move by the Bundesbank, the period between now and the March 18 elections in East Germany could be especially difficult for the bond and stock markets. One issue that is stirring the markets is the rate of exchange for the East German mark, the ostmark, into West German marks. In the last week, German officials said they might set several different rates for converting ostmarks in an effort to balance social and economic needs.</p>
        <p>The fear that inflation will rise sharply as a result of reunification of the two Germanys intensified last week with some new estimates that prices could rise by as much as 6 percent in West Germany this year. Some economists dismiss the estimates. Salomon Brothers, for instance, predicts the increase will be 4 percent. But the higher estimates are still affecting the market.</p>
        <p>In addition, estimates of the immediate cost to the West German Government of reunification have risen sharply, pushing estimates of its budget deficit from seven billion marks to as high as 50 billion marks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rona of IBJ Schroder also said the threat of large bankruptcies in Poland, Hungary, Czechoslovakia and East Germany was pushing interest rates higher.</p>
        <p>Since Comecom Collapsed</p>
        <p>He said those bankruptcies would reflect the collapse of the East bloc trading system, known as Comecom. Because of that, many companies have not been paid for their goods. In addition, the conditions for loans from the International Monetary Fund are also putting a strain on these economies.</p>
        <p>In Japan, interest rates were rising as well. That reflected investors' expectations that the Bank of Japan would again raise the important discount rate soon to fight inflation and help a sagging yen. This expectation was heightened when the country's money supply rose sharply in January and the yen continued to decline.</p>
        <p>These developments helped push the West German bond yields to 9 percent on Tuesday, the highest in more than seven years, and to more than 7 percent in Japan.</p>
        <p>With the uncertainty on reunifification underpinning interest rates in West Germany, a rise in rates in Japan or the United States could send the bond and stock markets tumbling again. The Bank of Japan is still expected to push interest rates higher to fight inflation and support the sagging yen. In the United States, Alan Greenspan, the chairman of the Federal Reserve Board, said last week that interest rates would not decline soon because the weakest point in the economic slowdown may have passed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
