<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid the Publishing Slump, Norton Thrives</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="330044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK TRADE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTON, W W, &amp; CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCDOWELL, EDWIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAMM, DONALD S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDF123BF935A15751C0A966958260" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid the Publishing Slump, Norton Thrives</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWIN McDOWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCDOWELL, EDWIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: At a time when many publishing houses are complaining about declining revenues and even losses, W. W. Norton &amp; Company is not only profitable, but also independent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: At a time when many publishing houses are complaining about declining revenues and even losses, W. W. Norton &amp; Company is not only profitable, but also independent.</p>
        <p>At a time when many publishing houses are complaining about declining revenues and even losses, W. W. Norton &amp; Company is not only profitable, but also independent.</p>
        <p>And unlike other houses, it has never conducted sweeping layoffs or bought other publishing concerns to strip them of their backlists before disbanding them. Indeed, Norton is the only major house owned entirely by its employees.</p>
        <p>''I think they're the best there is,'' said Roger W. Straus, president of Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, another quality independent house. ''They're absolutely first rate.''</p>
        <p>Two Best Sellers</p>
        <p>Two Norton books are riding high on the best-seller lists: ''Liar's Poker'' by Michael Lewis and ''The T-Factor Diet'' by Martin Katahn. Earlier this year it had three best sellers at the same time. But the fortunes of Norton, which has a rich backlist of about 2,500 titles, do not rise and fall on best sellers.</p>
        <p>''We're happy to have them, because they're good for the morale of our authors, editors and sales force,'' said Donald S. Lamm, Norton's chairman and president. ''But our aim is to publish good books as well as we can. We don't see this as a trendy publishing house. In fact, I always say you can tell a trend has passed when Norton publishes a book on the subject.''</p>
        <p>Actually, Norton publishes many books on many subjects - about 250 titles a year, of which 30 percent are college textbooks. Mr. Lamm will not disclose revenues, but he said the college divison accounts for most profits. He also said the 67-year-old house has been profitable for the last 25 years, although for a couple of years profits were ''razor thin.''</p>
        <p>'Very Open and Very Smart'</p>
        <p>''Norton has very little bureaucracy,'' said Thomas C. Wallace, a literary agent and former Norton editor. ''Don runs the company, but he consults with others and he listens. He's very open and very smart.''</p>
        <p>Educated at Yale and Oxford, Mr. Lamm, 58 years old, is partial to what he calls ''undermanagement.'' While there is a weekly editorial meeting, Mr. Lamm said he could not remember ever having a vote on whether to acquire a book. ''We aim for a meeting of the minds,'' he said, ''but there's a strong predilection on my part to let an editor with a passion for a book go ahead with it.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, there is no end-of-the-year tally of how much money an editor's books made or lost, now common in some houses.</p>
        <p>Norton editors calculate the size of advances on the basis of what the house alone can earn on a book - not from potential earnings from the sale of paperback or book-club rights. While that policy has kept the house from having to write off substantial unearned advances, it has also cost it an occasional name author.</p>
        <p>Norman Cousins, for example, wrote two best sellers for Norton, ''Anatomy of an Illness'' and ''The Healing Heart.'' But when Norton decided the asking price was too high for ''Head First,'' the house and the author reluctantly parted company. That book recently published by E. P. Dutton.</p>
        <p>Norton is best known in educational circles for books on economics and psychology, and for its anthologies and critical editions of literary classics. It also publishes an extensive list of music and science books.</p>
        <p>Its longtime slogan is ''Books That Live,'' and Norton has in fact published many such books, including ''The Feminine Mystique'' by Betty Friedan, ''The Revolt of the Masses'' by Jose Ortega y Gasset, ''The Greek Way'' by Edith Hamilton and ''Philosophy'' by Bertrand Russell.</p>
        <p>A Norton speciality is the ''crossover'' book, published for both general and academic markets. A leading crossover author is Stephen Jay Gould, the Harvard paleontologist who has written nine books for Norton.</p>
        <p>''Probably three-quarters of the books I personally edit have double markets,'' said Edwin Barber, the editorial director, who has edited textbooks for about one-half of his 33-year publishing career.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lamm, who has spent his entire 34-year professional career at Norton, was also an editor in the college department.</p>
        <p>Value of Continuity</p>
        <p>''The thing Norton has, and I think we have, is continuity,'' Mr. Straus said. ''Don Lamm and many other Norton people have been there for years, and they consider themselves part of a team.''</p>
        <p>In 1973, when independent houses were considered fair game for takeovers, George P. Brockway - Mr. Lamm's predecessor as chairman -vowed that Norton ''has never been for sale and is not likely to be.'' Mr. Lamm has also spent many hours discouraging potential suitors.</p>
        <p>After five years, employes are eligible to buy stock that under a 38-year-old ''joint stockholders' agreement'' must be tendered back to the company by retiring employes. The stock is currently held by about two-thirds of the 160 employees on the New York payroll. The company says that arrangement is the best safeguard against a takeover.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
