<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Monica, but Still Some Drama In Rowland Impeachment Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="07IMPE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/07/nyregion/07impeach.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1587675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowland, John G (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reich, Steven F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Rowland, John G</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E2DD1E31F934A35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Monica, but Still Some Drama In Rowland Impeachment Inquiry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Monica, but Connecticut Impeachment Case Still Has Drama</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, William</byline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, June 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Drama at public hearings of Connecticut legislative committee investigating Gov John G Rowland will not come from star witnesses, but from checks, bank statements, bills, letters and deeds that are among hundreds of documents that will be shown on giant screen; Steven F Reich, committee's lawyer, will question witnesses during first week of testimony; Rowland and most high-profile people associated with case are not expected to testify; most committee members have no experience in impeachment proceedings, so they are studying past cases; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is no stained blue dress. There are no secret tapes. And there are no plans to haul in the hot tub that Gov. John G. Rowland's longtime scheduler bought as a gift for the governor's vacation cottage.</p>
        <p>Sensationalism may seem in short supply when public hearings begin Tuesday in front of the House committee deciding whether the governor should be impeached for conduct relating to gifts he received from people doing business with the state. The governor has refused to appear and the two part-time politicians presiding over the hearings are so low-profile that they answer their own telephones and brush up on impeachment by checking out books from the library.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sensationalism may seem in short supply when public hearings begin deciding whether Connecticut Gov. John G. Rowland should be impeached.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is no stained blue dress. There are no secret tapes. And there are no plans to haul in the hot tub that Gov. John G. Rowland's longtime scheduler bought as a gift for the governor's vacation cottage.</p>
        <p>Sensationalism may seem in short supply when public hearings begin Tuesday in front of the House committee deciding whether the governor should be impeached for conduct relating to gifts he received from people doing business with the state. The governor has refused to appear and the two part-time politicians presiding over the hearings are so low-profile that they answer their own telephones and brush up on impeachment by checking out books from the library.</p>
        <p>But there will be big-screen drama.</p>
        <p>Canceled checks, bank statements, bills, letters and deeds are among hundreds of documents that will be magnified on a giant screen for the scrutiny of the 10-member bipartisan committee -- a high-tech parade of paper intended to shed light on the sometimes mysterious intersections between the governor's personal and political lives that are at the center of the scandal.</p>
        <p>''The documents that we've collected tell a story,'' Steven F. Reich, the lawyer for the House Select Committee of Inquiry, said last month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reich and a private investigator, James B. Mintz, will be among the principal narrators. In the months since the impeachment inquiry began they likely have learned more about Mr. Rowland's affairs than anyone in Connecticut, except perhaps for the federal investigators who are examining his conduct.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Reich and Mr. Mintz are New Yorkers, reverse commuters who found fruitful work seeking the roots of scandal across state lines. Mr. Reich earns $500 an hour. Mr. Mintz makes $330. On Friday afternoon, their commuting stopped for the near future. They carted in a few last boxes of documents to the Capitol and settled in to temporary offices on the fifth floor.</p>
        <p>''We're staying,'' Mr. Reich said. ''This is it.''</p>
        <p>The hearings, which are scheduled to begin at 12:30 p.m. Tuesday and will be covered live by Connecticut Network television, are expected to last less than two weeks. The committee then must recommend to the full House, by June 30, whether the governor should be impeached. The House is expected to follow whatever the committee recommends. If the vote -- by simple majority -- is to impeach, Mr. Rowland would relinquish his duties to Lt. Gov. M. Jodi Rell while he is tried in the Senate. He has insisted he will not resign.</p>
        <p>This week, Mr. Reich will lead the committee through questioning of no more than a dozen witnesses, often calling Mr. Mintz and other investigators to explain connections between documents to the committee.</p>
        <p>Contractors paid by Rowland aides to do renovations to the cottage are among the witnesses who may appear. A Washington real estate agent may be called to testify about a Capitol Hill condominium the governor sold and rented at inflated prices, through an arrangement with a state contractor, Robert V. Matthews.</p>
        <p>But none of the high-profile witnesses most closely associated with the scandal will testify -- from members of the Tomasso family, whose construction companies have earned more than $100 million from the state under the Rowland administration, to Mr. Matthews and former aides to the governor who are now under investigation themselves. Most have claimed their Fifth Amendment rights.</p>
        <p>What flair the remaining witnesses will bring is hard to predict. During the Senate Watergate hearings, Anthony T. Ulasewicz, a onetime New York City police detective, provided comic relief even as he gave a revealing account of his experience as a ''bagman'' carrying cash between the White House and Watergate defendants.</p>
        <p>The most colorful character in the Rowland impeachment inquiry so far has been Kurt C. Claywell, an electrical contractor who has told investigators he showered the governor with gifts of Champagne and Cuban cigars to ease his access to state work. But Mr. Claywell, a convicted felon, has not been named as a witness.</p>
        <p>What had been the most anticipated moment of the hearings -- the testimony of the governor -- is no longer considered a possibility. The governor, a Republican in his third term, has filed a lawsuit saying the legislature lacks authority to issue a subpoena it served last month ordering him to testify. The case will be heard in Superior Court on Monday, the day before impeachment hearings begin two blocks away in the Old Judiciary Room at the Capitol.</p>
        <p>Although the governor has refused to testify, his lawyers will participate in the impeachment hearings. William F. Dow III, the governor's private attorney, said Friday that he and Ross H. Garber, the lawyer for the governor's office, planned to cross-examine witnesses called by the committee. The lawyers would not say whether they would call their own witnesses or present a case after the committee hears from Mr. Reich. ''We're going to wait and see what Mr. Reich presents,'' Mr. Garber said.</p>
        <p>The governor's lawyers have repeatedly complained that the committee has not adopted clear standards for impeachment or defined the burden of proof by which the governor will be judged. But after weeks of public volleying with the committee, they spent late last week secluded in Mr. Garber's Capitol office, reviewing thousands of pages the committee's investigators had packaged into 421 exhibits contained in eight binders.</p>
        <p>Adding further intrigue and work for the governor's lawyers, Mr. Garber is also scheduled to be in federal appeals court in New York on Friday. That case involves whether or not federal prosecutors can force a former lawyer for the governor's office to testify in their investigation of Mr. Rowland.</p>
        <p>Public focus, however, will be on the impeachment hearings. Connecticut Network, a cable channel funded by the state that functions as a sort of statewide C-Span, has seen a spike in viewers since the impeachment committee was formed in January, according to a company spokesman, Bill Bevacqua.</p>
        <p>One of the network's regular viewers is now among its newest stars. Representative Arthur J. O'Neill, a Republican from Southbury who is the committee co-chairman, has served in the legislature since 1988. His Democratic counterpart, Representative John Wayne Fox of Stamford, has served since 1981 and was one of the lawmakers involved in the state's only other impeachment proceeding, the investigation of a probate judge in the 1980's who resigned before he could be impeached. Both are lawyers.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Fox has direct experience with impeachment, Mr. O'Neill has spent the spring reading books and articles on impeachments dating from 17th-century England to the Senate impeachment trial against President Bill Clinton in 1999.</p>
        <p>On Friday, as public hearings loomed, he was asked what he had learned from his reading.</p>
        <p>''It's made it easier for me to understand that there are no easy answer to questions like 'what is impeachable?''' he said.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he continues to study. He said he expected to spend the weekend with ''The Breach,'' an account of the Clinton impeachment by a Washington Post reporter, Peter Baker.</p>
        <p>''I went to the library,'' he said. ''I will probably take a skim through that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
