<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN A SHIFT BY U.S., AID WILL BE SPED TO SOUTH KOREANS</title>
    <meta content="25RESC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="982968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">South Korea-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DB113EF936A15751C1A961958260" item-length="1644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN A SHIFT BY U.S., AID WILL BE SPED TO SOUTH KOREANS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton Administration, in an about-face, joins other major industrial nations in supplying South Korea with $10 billion in emergency aid and in asking major commercial banks to extend the deadlines by which Korean banks must repay their debts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an about-face, the Clinton Administration joined other major industrial nations today in supplying South Korea with $10 billion in emergency aid and in asking major commercial banks to extend the deadlines by which Korean banks must repay their debts.</p>
        <p>While American officials sought to cast the decision today as an acceleration of aid already committed to South Korea, it appeared to represent a failure of the Clinton Administration's original approach to the Asian financial crisis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an about-face, the Clinton Administration joined other major industrial nations today in supplying South Korea with $10 billion in emergency aid and in asking major commercial banks to extend the deadlines by which Korean banks must repay their debts.</p>
        <p>While American officials sought to cast the decision today as an acceleration of aid already committed to South Korea, it appeared to represent a failure of the Clinton Administration's original approach to the Asian financial crisis.</p>
        <p>Two months ago, just before the Korean markets began to plunge, the Administration was privately warning officials in Seoul to get their house in order.</p>
        <p>When a $57 billion bailout plan was announced under International Monetary Fund leadership on Dec. 3, Secretary of the Treasury Robert E. Rubin said that American taxpayer dollars would only be used as as part of a $5 billion ''second line of defense'' if South Korea exhausted funds provided by the I.M.F. and the World Bank.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Mr. Rubin summarily rejected a request by the South Korean Finance Minister to speed up aid, saying he thought that the step was unnecessary.</p>
        <p>Today he did just that.</p>
        <p>The United States has now agreed to lend $1.7 billion to Seoul by the second week of January, and such loans may yet prove necessary to stabilize the South Korean currency, the won, which has fallen 37 percent in value this month alone.</p>
        <p>For its part, South Korea has agreed to further open its markets in return for this latest cash infusion.</p>
        <p>''This decision is overwhelmingly in our economic and national security interest,'' Mr. Rubin told reporters today, justifying a decision that the Administration fears could renew debate in Congress over the use of American funds to bail out failing foreign economies and banks. ''If you have economic instability, you run the risk of political and social instability.'' And South Korea, he said, is a country where ''there are still enormous security concerns for the United States.''</p>
        <p>The new money for the Koreans will come from the Emergency Stabilization Fund, a currency reserve fund under the control of the President and the Treasury Secretary.</p>
        <p>Created by the Administration of Franklin D. Roosevelt in the 1930's to support the American dollar, the fund was tapped during the bailout of Mexico two and a half years ago, and disbursements do not require Congressional approval. But while Mexico agreed to put up the revenue it reaped from oil production as collateral for the $12 billion it borrowed -- all of which has since been repaid, with interest -- South Korea is offering nothing except its word.</p>
        <p>There was no immediate reaction from Congressional leaders or from junior members who complained most bitterly about the Mexican bailout. Most of their offices were closed for the holidays.</p>
        <p>American officials said they were not concerned about repayment, citing the ''deep relationship'' of the United States with South Korea, an allusion to the more than 35,000 American troops stationed there as a defense against the Communist leadership of North Korea. The unstated assumption is that Seoul would pay any debts to its critical military ally before it repaid other lenders.</p>
        <p>''The uncertainty of getting paid back,'' Mr. Rubin said, ''is very low.''</p>
        <p>For the Treasury Secretary, however, today's announcement is an admission that his strategy for containing the Asian economic crisis -- and keeping it from leaping to Japan and other big industrial nations -- has so far failed to work.</p>
        <p>Cutting short a Christmas week bone-fishing expedition, he returned to a frenzy of meetings at the White House that have included Secretary of Defense William S. Cohen; President Clinton's national security adviser, Samuel R. Berger; the White House chief of staff, Erskine Bowles, and at times the President.</p>
        <p>Yet Administration officials said they were unsure whether the bailout plan would persuade private investors and lenders to resume lending to the South Koreans.</p>
        <p>''We always recognized there was some risk the stabilization plan wouldn't work,'' Mr. Rubin said today. ''It was a good program that should have worked.'' But the flight of money out of South Korea and the relentless selloff of its currency continued unabated, he noted. The new plan, he said, ''should work,'' though he acknowledged that ''there are no guarantees.''</p>
        <p>Korean markets were mixed today, with stocks losing a little more than 4 percent but the currency improving to an exchange rate of 1,836 won to the dollar.</p>
        <p>American and Japanese officials characterized the emergency aid as an effort to buy time. While South Korea has enough cash to repay debts due by the end of next week, it is likely that its banks would default in January. The rapid $10 billion infusion -- including $3.3 billion from Japan, $2 billion from the I.M.F. and contributions from a variety of European nations -- is something of a stopgap while American, Japanese and European banks negotiate a way to relieve South Korean banks -- and thus Korean industry -- of $30 to $40 billion in short-term debt.</p>
        <p>That effort began even as Mr. Rubin was announcing his decision. Six major American banks met today at the Federal Reserve Bank of New York and agreed to come up with a plan to help the Koreans, prodded along by the Administration and the Federal Reserve. The banking companies included J. P. Morgan, Bankers Trust, BankAmerica, the Bank of New York, Chase Manhattan and Citicorp. Of those, Citicorp has lent the most to South Korea, though American banks are far less exposed to the Korean crisis than banks in Japan and Europe.</p>
        <p>''The idea here was to show some American leadership because the American banks are the healthiest,'' said a senior Administration official involved in the negotiations, which are beginning to resemble how the Latin American debt crisis was resolved in the 1980's. On Thursday, a similar meeting of Japanese banks is expected in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>While the United States and Japan are casting the negotiations between South Korea and the private banks as voluntary, it is clear that this is part of the package Mr. Rubin has assembled with the Federal Reserve chairman, Alan Greenspan, and their Japanese counterparts.</p>
        <p>The fact that the meeting today took place at the New York Federal Reserve -- which handles most international transactions for the Fed -- seemed to emphasize that the whole package of government and private aid was being carefully orchestrated.</p>
        <p>The choices for private bankers range from agreeing to extend their loans, to forgiving some portion of the debt and writing it off as a loss, to finding ways to raise new money for South Korea that could ultimately insure repayment of the old money.</p>
        <p>Another possibility, officials said, is for the Seoul Government to guarantee some of the debt of the private banks. But that would run counter to an American objective to insure that the rescue plan forces weak banks and weak Korean companies to go bankrupt, purging the economy and forcing the losses on foreign and domestic investors who provided those banks with cash.</p>
        <p>Indeed, today's action opens the Administration to criticism that in the the name of bailing out South Korea it is also bailing out investors -- including major American, Japanese and European banks that made bad investments.</p>
        <p>Only a few months ago, Mr. Rubin was warning of the ''moral hazard'' created by such bailouts, because private investors around the world would come to expect that if huge investments in an emerging market like Korea went bad, the United States and the I.M.F. would ride to the rescue.</p>
        <p>''Look, I wouldn't spend a nickel to bail out investors or creditors,'' Mr. Rubin insisted to reporters today. ''The purpose of this is not to help creditors; the purpose is to help Korea.''</p>
        <p>But he acknowledged that it was  virtually impossible to save the country from default without saving those who invested in it.</p>
        <p>American officials said that the South Korean President-elect, Kim Dae Jung, a onetime dissident who last week became the first opposition leader to be elected to run the country, had agreed to a number of concessions in return for the fast help.</p>
        <p>Korea had agreed to dropping a series of restrictions on imported goods and on foreign investment there, both issues that American trade negotiators have sweated over for years. For example, Seoul is to lift the restrictions on foreign acquisition of Korean companies, if the takeovers are friendly mergers. It has also lifted the ceilings on foreign investments in bonds issued by Korean companies.</p>
        <p>Lawrence H. Summers, the Deputy Secretary of the Treasury, told reporters that Seoul had also agreed to stop providing cheap, dollar-denominated loans to banks to pay off their debts. A new, high interest rate on such loans puts pressure on the weakest banks to pay off their debts or close their doors. President-elect Kim has also agreed to allow Korean companies to lay off workers, ending one of the practices that has kept companies bloated.</p>
        <p>That agreement could easily turn into a major political problem for Mr. Kim. South Korea's enormously strong labor unions have already promised street demonstrations to protest layoffs, and American officials are concerned that much of the anger will be directed at the United States.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
