<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making Over the Central Intelligence Agency</title>
    <meta content="26SUN3$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/26/opinion/26SUN3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1320262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial Observer"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taubman, Philip</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Agency, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McVeigh, Timothy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4D61031F935A1575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making Over the Central Intelligence Agency</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Making Over the Central Intelligence Agency</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP TAUBMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Taubman, Philip</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philip Taubman Editorial Observer column sees new television program The Agency reflecting uncharacteristic tranquillity and popularity currently enjoyed by Central Intelligence Agency; notes CIA, welcoming good publicity, offers show rare degree of cooperation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You know the image of the Central Intelligence Agency is changing when Ally McBeal's former lover turns up as a daring C.I.A. secret agent in a new prime-time dramatic series on CBS.</p>
        <p>''The Agency,'' which will debut next month as the fall television season begins, presents a C.I.A. crammed with brave and gorgeous spies, including Gil Bellows, the actor who played Billy, Ally's old partner and ex-boyfriend. As Matt Callan, a nervy, skilled operative, he helps thwart a terrorist plot to blow up Harrods, the London department store, in the opening episode. Though Mr. Bellows does his best to look the part of a heroic defender of civilized society, viewers may find themselves wondering how Billy got over the fatal brain tumor he was suffering from on the Fox network.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>While the F.B.I. reels from misfortune, the C.I.A. enjoys a period of uncharacteristic tranquillity and popularity</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You know the image of the Central Intelligence Agency is changing when Ally McBeal's former lover turns up as a daring C.I.A. secret agent in a new prime-time dramatic series on CBS.</p>
        <p>''The Agency,'' which will debut next month as the fall television season begins, presents a C.I.A. crammed with brave and gorgeous spies, including Gil Bellows, the actor who played Billy, Ally's old partner and ex-boyfriend. As Matt Callan, a nervy, skilled operative, he helps thwart a terrorist plot to blow up Harrods, the London department store, in the opening episode. Though Mr. Bellows does his best to look the part of a heroic defender of civilized society, viewers may find themselves wondering how Billy got over the fatal brain tumor he was suffering from on the Fox network.</p>
        <p>''The Agency'' is more than the latest entry in the network ratings game. It is part of the long and often unfriendly rivalry between the C.I.A. and the Federal Bureau of Investigation. Over the more than five decades in which the two security agencies have coexisted uneasily in Washington, the bureau has generally eclipsed the agency in public relations and public esteem.</p>
        <p>That was certainly true during most of J. Edgar Hoover's long reign at the F.B.I., a time when the bureau assiduously cultivated an undeserved image as an infallible and incorruptible crime-busting enterprise. That perception was enhanced by a fawning television series, ''The F.B.I.,'' starring Efrem Zimbalist Jr.</p>
        <p>Lately, there has been a reversal of images. The F.B.I. is reeling from misfortune, most of its own making. The calamities include the deadly siege of the Branch Davidian compound in Waco, Tex., the betrayal of Robert Hanssen, the F.B.I. agent who sold secrets to the Russians for years, and the mishandling of investigative documents during the prosecution of Timothy McVeigh, who was executed in June for the Oklahoma City bombing. Congress is justifiably demanding that the bureau's newly confirmed director, Robert Mueller, overhaul the organization.</p>
        <p>The C.I.A. is enjoying a period of uncharacteristic tranquillity and popularity. That could change in an instant if there is some new disclosure of C.I.A. misconduct or one of the agency's covert operations misfires.</p>
        <p>For the moment, however, George Tenet, the director of central intelligence, may well be enjoying the most unruffled tenure of any spy chief since the agency's creation more than half a century ago. The roster of intelligence directors who ended their careers in controversy or disgrace is long and memorable. It includes Allen Dulles, Richard Helms, William Colby and William Casey.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tenet's good fortune is evident in the fall television schedule, which looks like the best advertisement for the agency since Bill Cosby and Robert Culp went undercover in ''I Spy'' in the 1960's. Prime-time television programming may say more about the culture of Hollywood than the country at large, but it can offer a rough indication of public attitudes. During the years of C.I.A. disrepute, the image of a rogue agency was common in television and movies. This season, the C.I.A. will largely be defined on television by ''The Agency.'' Judging by the pilot episode, it promises to be an exercise in hagiography.</p>
        <p>Recognizing the potential for good publicity, the C.I.A. has offered a rare degree of cooperation to the show, vetting scripts for verisimilitude and allowing limited filming at the C.I.A. headquarters in northern Virginia. It will be interesting to see if the mutual blandishments keep the show from eventually veering into a more critical vein.</p>
        <p>Two other new prime-time shows -- ''Alias'' on ABC and ''24'' on Fox -- offer more ambivalent portraits of the C.I.A. But even in these dramas, there are at least some good guys on the job.</p>
        <p>Hollywood's gentler treatment of the C.I.A. will no doubt boost Mr. Tenet's effort to rebuild the agency with a new generation of analysts and operatives. With the help of generous budget increases from Congress in recent years, Mr. Tenet has begun an aggressive recruiting campaign. By 2005, he says, 30 percent of the agency's work force will have been employed there for five years or less. That's a striking -- and potentially culturally transforming -- infusion of new people into one of the government's most insular organizations. The agency receives 50,000 résumés a year.</p>
        <p>To recruit prospective spies, the C.I.A. has settled on a new advertising slogan that will soon start appearing in magazines and newspapers: ''Quite possibly, the most demanding job in the world.''</p>
        <p>That's not bad. But as a personal slogan, Mr. Tenet may prefer a line that Matt Callan delivers near the end of the first episode of ''The Agency,'' after the terrorists have been killed, just seconds before they planned to blow up Harrods.</p>
        <p>''Every day we're not in the news,'' he says, ''is a day we've won.''</p>
        <p>Editorial Observer</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
