<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First Lady Opens a Festival To Promote National Literacy</title>
    <meta content="08READ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/08/arts/08READ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1323257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Library of Congress</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sciolino, Elaine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">White House (Washington, DC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Library of Congress</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, Laura</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DE1E39F93BA3575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First Lady Opens a Festival To Promote National Literacy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">First Lady Opens a Festival to Promote National Literacy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sciolino, Elaine</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First lady Laura Bush helps kick off literacy program at Library of Congress (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first lady, Laura Bush, started the Library of Congress's first national book festival today by reading to 20 fourth-grade students at the library. But the nation's readers wouldn't have known about the event unless they were watching television.</p>
        <p>That's because CBS's ''Early Show'' had arranged exclusive access with the White House, library officials said. ''The White House basically decided this was a TV thing,'' one official said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>CBS's "Early Show" arranged exclusive access to Laura Bush's opening of the Library of Congress's first national book festival.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first lady, Laura Bush, started the Library of Congress's first national book festival today by reading to 20 fourth-grade students at the library. But the nation's readers wouldn't have known about the event unless they were watching television.</p>
        <p>That's because CBS's ''Early Show'' had arranged exclusive access with the White House, library officials said. ''The White House basically decided this was a TV thing,'' one official said.</p>
        <p>The televised kickoff underscores just why the first lady and James H. Billington, the librarian of Congress, joined forces in the first place to serve as hosts of a book festival in the nation's capital this weekend.</p>
        <p>''Illiteracy is a persistent problem in America, and it's steadily growing,'' said Mr. Billington in an interview. ''Thirty-eight percent of fourth graders don't have very much of an understanding of a simple, ordinary paragraph. You can't even use the Internet if you can't read the instructions.''</p>
        <p>A former librarian and schoolteacher from West Texas who arranges her personal library according to the Dewey Decimal system, Mrs. Bush began her crusade for national literacy during the presidential inauguration, when she invited a group of authors to read from their works at Constitution Hall. The festival is a national version of the Texas Book Festival, which Mrs. Bush created when she was first lady of Texas and which raised hundreds of thousands of dollars for the state library system.</p>
        <p>''This festival is family-oriented and it's free and it's a first,'' said Noelia Rodriguez, Mrs. Bush's press secretary. ''And it's the biggest book-friendly event she has done so far as first lady.''</p>
        <p>The daylong festival on Saturday, which is open to the public, brings 60 award-winning authors and illustrators of books for adults and children to the east lawn of the Capitol, where six huge tents have been erected, and to the Library of Congress. Many of them will read from their books. But there is a commercial angle as well: authors and illustrators get to sign and sell their books as well.</p>
        <p>''It's a great time to buy -- do some Christmas shopping or holiday shopping and get your favorite authors to sign books for your friends and your family,'' Mrs. Bush said on  ''The Early Show'' today.</p>
        <p>The festival will also feature musical performances, storytelling and a panel discussion. Mr. Billington said the event cost about a million dollars and was underwritten by several organizations including AT&amp;T, WorkPlaceUSA and the library's James Madison Council, its private donor group.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
