<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connecticut Tax Hearing: What, No Rage?</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="433139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAXES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEICKER, LOWELL P JR (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, KIRK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D6103FF934A15750C0A967958260" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connecticut Tax Hearing: What, No Rage?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, KIRK</byline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, March 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By 5 P.M. the barricades set up to contain the crowds stood empty, and the State Capitol police officers assigned to guard the doors to Room 2C had long since wandered off. The signs warning people against cheering or other "public demonstrations" were superfluous in a room that had been largely empty of spectators since midday.</p>
        <p>It was near the end of a long-anticipated one-day public hearing on Gov. Lowell P. Weicker Jr.'s tax plan, which had been expected to go late into the night, but little opposition to a state income tax had appeared: only half a dozen people out of 62 speakers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By 5 P.M. the barricades set up to contain the crowds stood empty, and the State Capitol police officers assigned to guard the doors to Room 2C had long since wandered off. The signs warning people against cheering or other "public demonstrations" were superfluous in a room that had been largely empty of spectators since midday.</p>
        <p>It was near the end of a long-anticipated one-day public hearing on Gov. Lowell P. Weicker Jr.'s tax plan, which had been expected to go late into the night, but little opposition to a state income tax had appeared: only half a dozen people out of 62 speakers.</p>
        <p>More important, the powerful voices of organized labor, big business and private welfare agencies, which usually agree on nothing, had all supported a broad-based personal income tax on wages in one form or another.  Individual Protests Heard</p>
        <p>There were individual voices of anguish. Theater owners protested that the Governor's plan to extend the sales tax to movie tickets would hurt them. Lawyers said that extending the sales tax to legal services would provoke a constitutional challenge. State employees said the cuts in their benefits proposed by Mr. Weicker were too harsh.</p>
        <p>But three of the state's largest business lobbying groups, which announced on Monday that they would support an income tax if it were linked to controls on state spending, found themselves in the unusual position of being criticized by the Finance, Revenue and Bonding Committee's Republicans, their usual allies.</p>
        <p>One citizen group calling itself the Taxpayers Alliance to Serve Connecticut distributed income-tax tea bags to evoke the Boston Tea Party as a way of supporting, not opposing, an income tax.</p>
        <p>People who remembered Connecticut's last big experiment with the income tax -- in 1971, when the General Assembly enacted the tax and then repealed it under a storm of protest, including a rally of 10,000 people on the Capitol lawn -- wondered aloud if Connecticut's taxpayers were whipped, or apathetic, or just lying in wait.</p>
        <p>"It seems like times have changed," said one committee member, Representative Geri W. Langlois, a Democrat from Thompson, in questioning one witness. "Where's the outcry?"</p>
        <p>The witness didn't know.</p>
        <p>Some income-tax opponents said the hearing was irrelevant and that those opposed were smart to stay home.</p>
        <p>"It's a meaningless dog and pony show," said former State Senator Thomas Scott, the chairman of the Connecticut Taxpayers Committee, which opposes an income tax. "Eighty percent of my members are factory workers. They don't have time for this." Protest Petitions Promised</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott, a Republican who formed his committee this year after an unsuccessful run for the United States House of Representatives against Rosa DeLauro, said he had obtained 40,000 signatures on petitions condemning an income tax and would return to the Capitol when he had 100,000. One day's testimony, he said, will change no minds.</p>
        <p>But the finance commitee's co-chairman, Representative Richard T. Mulready, a Democrat from West Hartford, said he thought the low turnout itself would send a message as the General Assembly grinds through the tax debate this spring.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulready, who supports a broad-based personal income tax, had been prepared to work well into the night, hearing the complaints and accusations of hundreds of people. Instead he was back in his office, files packed away, well before 6:30.</p>
        <p>Of the more than 115 people on the sign-up sheet, only 62 had stepped up to the table to speak. Resigned Feeling Detected</p>
        <p>"That suggests to me -- though I think it may be a little premature to draw conclusions -- that the people of the state of Connecticut are resigned," Mr. Mulready said. "Not apathetic, but resigned is probably the best way to look at it."</p>
        <p>What perhaps also discouraged some would-be speakers were the questions from the finance committee members, who invariably asked every speaker how the state's projected $2.4 billion revenue shortfall should be addressed if an income tax were rejected.</p>
        <p>Some opponents of the income tax did not have an answer, while others said the budget was still full of fat despite the $1.2 billion in spending reductions identified by Mr. Weicker in a preliminary budget of about $8.5 billion.</p>
        <p>One speaker, Elizabeth Gillern, said she had formed her group, Citizens Against an Income Tax, only three weeks ago and had not had the time or resources to find the answers yet.</p>
        <p>"The reality of it is, there is just no more money to give," she said. A Happy Taxpayer Speaks</p>
        <p>More representative of the hearing's tone was the testimony -- and sharp questioning -- of Sharon Palmer, representing the 20,000-member Connecticut Federation of Teachers. She spoke passionately in favor of a progressive income tax as the best way to raise revenue to support education.</p>
        <p>"How much taxes are you personally willing to pay?" asked one committee member, Representative Arthur O'Neill, a Republican from Southbury.</p>
        <p>"Whatever it takes," Ms. Palmer said.</p>
        <p>"You willing to pay an extra $1,500 a year in taxes?" Mr. O'Neill asked.</p>
        <p>"Yes, I am," she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weicker, an independent third-party governor with no members of his own Connecticut Party on the finance commitee or in the General Assembly as a whole, proposed last month a flat 6 percent tax on all income over $25,000 for a family or $12,500 for an individual. The wage tax, he said, would allow other taxes to be lowered -- especially those paid by business -- to stimulate the state's flagging economy. Flat vs. Variable Tax</p>
        <p>The corporate profits tax would be cut from 13.8 percent to 11.5 percent, the sales tax from 8 percent to 4.25 percent, and the separate taxes on dividends, interest and capital gains would be eliminated, with all income treated equally under the new tax.</p>
        <p>One of the main side debates in today's lopsided discussion was whether the flat rate was best or whether the income-tax rate should go up with income, the way New York State's does, for example.</p>
        <p>John R. Rathgeber, an executive vice president of the Connecticut Business and Industry Association, said his 7,000-member group would support only a flat tax.</p>
        <p>The president of the State A.F.L.-C.I.O., John W. Olsen, said he would make the tax steeply progressive, hitting upper-income earners with a 10 percent wage tax and sparing the middle class.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
