<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Analysts Split On G.M.'s Fate</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="433056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL MOTORS CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D7133BF934A15750C0A967958260" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Analysts Split On G.M.'s Fate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Doron P. Levin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVIN, DORON P</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AUTO MAKERS typically lose money in sour economies, then make it back in spades during prosperity. But the General Motors Corporation's $1.6 billion loss in the fourth quarter of 1990 was so staggering that it has split Wall Street over whether the No. 1 auto maker can recover its earning power when the economy improves.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s profitability and dividend payout are critical issues for millions of investors. As one of the most widely held stocks and an institutional favorite, G.M. is the subject of much debate and strongly held opinions among financial analysts. The auto maker tracks the recommendations of 13 leading analysts; currently, 7 are recommending purchase of the stock, 3 are neutral and 3 are recommending sale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AUTO MAKERS typically lose money in sour economies, then make it back in spades during prosperity. But the General Motors Corporation's $1.6 billion loss in the fourth quarter of 1990 was so staggering that it has split Wall Street over whether the No. 1 auto maker can recover its earning power when the economy improves.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s profitability and dividend payout are critical issues for millions of investors. As one of the most widely held stocks and an institutional favorite, G.M. is the subject of much debate and strongly held opinions among financial analysts. The auto maker tracks the recommendations of 13 leading analysts; currently, 7 are recommending purchase of the stock, 3 are neutral and 3 are recommending sale.</p>
        <p>The case against G.M. rests on disappointment among the analysts who expected narrower losses given the number of cars and trucks sold. They fear that the industry's three-year labor contract signed last fall, which guarantees most of the pay of hourly workers even if they are laid off, has turned a variable expense into a fixed expense. In past years, when sales slid, auto makers could reduce expenses by laying off workers.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the North American production capacity of foreign auto makers continues to grow, making competition tougher. Consequently, auto makers have resorted to paying stiff consumer rebates to maintain sales volume. And the industry is facing soaring costs to meet new clean-air, safety and fuel-efficiency regulations.</p>
        <p>True, G.M. is introducing a slew of new models, but the auto maker's overall market share has not gained, meaning that its models are cannibalizing sales from one another.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, there was more negative news when Fitch Investors Service said it might downgrade its ratings on debt securities of G.M. and the Ford Motor Company, citing concern about their profitability.  [ Page D17. ]</p>
        <p>The cost and profit problems are affecting Ford and the Chrysler Corporation as well, but neither of those stocks is as significant as G.M. to institutional portfolios.</p>
        <p>James L. Alexandre, automotive analyst at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette in New York, suggests that G.M. is in danger of dropping to about $30 a share over the next year, as the company fails to turn profitable this year or next. Based on its earning power, it probably should not be trading higher than the mid-20's. Yesterday, the stock rose $1.75 to close at $39.50 on volume of 893,000 shares.</p>
        <p>"G.M. simply can't generate the cash in an up automotive cycle to justify a raise in the dividend," said Ronald A. Glantz, automotive analyst for Dean Witter Reynolds in San Francisco. G.M. sliced its dividend almost 50 percent in February, and Mr. Glantz contends it cannot raise the payout before 1994, suggesting that the stock "should be trading in the 20's." He theorizes that G.M. stock is a favorite investment alternative to bonds and therefore trades mostly on its yield, rather than on growth prospects.</p>
        <p>Citing a monitoring service to which he subscribes, Mr. Glantz said the large institutions had mostly remained on the sidelines as buyers of G.M. stock, while some smaller ones had become buyers.</p>
        <p>The opposing view is that "it's dangerous to extrapolate from fourth-quarter results," in the words of Harvey Heinbach, automotive analyst for Merrill Lynch in New York. Although he was surprised by the magnitude of G.M.'s losses and has lowered his expectations for G.M. stock, he remains positive.</p>
        <p>Scott Merlis, automotive analyst for Morgan Stanley &amp; Company in New York, is one of Wall Street's bulls on G.M. In his view, the United States automotive market seems to be near its trough and should recover by 1992. While he agrees that G.M.'s recent losses are worrisome, he says, "You can't let the crisis obscure the long-term fundamental progress."</p>
        <p>G.M. has been cutting costs, and the new labor contract, although expensive, has given the auto maker the flexibility to shut down underused capacity, he said. Rebates are down in the current quarter, and G.M. has joined Ford in promising to scale back market-glutting sales to rental fleets, which are no better than marginally profitable and hurt resale values.</p>
        <p>David Healy, automotive analyst for Barclays de Zoete Wedd, agrees that G.M.'s profitability has been hurt, but he sees the situation as temporary. Weak demand, not excess capacity, is the big problem; it will disappear by 1992 or 1993, he projects, accompanied by higher capacity utilization, firmer pricing, better profits and, finally, a dividend increase.</p>
        <p>G.M. will keep the $1.60 annual dividend through 1991, raise it to $2.40 in 1992 and $3 in 1993, he predicted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
