<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leave Those Nose Tackles Alone, Lloyd</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="208029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES AND SALARIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKOW, IRA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D71139F933A15751C1A96E948260" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leave Those Nose Tackles Alone, Lloyd</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKOW, IRA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Maybe more than at any other time of the year, this is the season for the nose tackle, the guy in the literal middle of the belligerence that rages in the football game, where the collision of helmets and shoulder pads is a sound akin to bombs bursting in air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Maybe more than at any other time of the year, this is the season for the nose tackle, the guy in the literal middle of the belligerence that rages in the football game, where the collision of helmets and shoulder pads is a sound akin to bombs bursting in air.</p>
        <p>Maybe more than at any other time of the year, this is the season for the nose tackle, the guy in the literal middle of the belligerence that rages in the football game, where the collision of helmets and shoulder pads is a sound akin to bombs bursting in air.</p>
        <p>The nose tackle is in the front line, running over people when he isn't being run over himself.</p>
        <p>And millions of people all across this favored land sit bundled up in the stands or wrapped in their robes at home and root with all their heart for their nose tackle of choice to either give it or get it.</p>
        <p>And so when recently we read that the average salary of a nose tackle, this most industrious and clamorous of working stiffs, was being held up in negative comparison in order to hike the salaries of members of the executive, legislative and judicial branches of the Government, we were quite naturally taken aback.</p>
        <p>Lloyd N. Cutler, chairman of the commission looking into what he states are the relatively low salaries of some of our top Federal officials, said during recent public hearings in Washington, ''To illustrate in terms most citizens will understand, we will have to decide whether the Chief Justice of the United States should continue to be paid less than half of the average salary of an N.F.L. nose tackle.''</p>
        <p>With all due respect to the Chief Justice, and to some of the other judicial, legislative and executive souls, the nose tackle who earns an average of $254,000 a year makes it the hard way - by the sweat of his brow and the valor of his nose.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, as the Giants prepared to enter the playoffs that led to a Super Bowl triumph, Jim Burt, the team's nose tackle - known as Sluggo for his grit - said of the trench warfare on the gridiron: ''It's a good time to be there. The team is gelled. We're in the groove.''</p>
        <p>Burt won't be sharpening his beak for the playoffs this year, nor will any of the other Giants, of course, since they were eliminated on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Other nose tackles will be at it instead, like Fred Smerlas of the Bills, Tim Krumrie of the Bengals and Bob Golic of the Browns. Guys who are, as the saying goes, generally household names only in their own household. But who after a game are usually in need of half the contents of a well-stocked medicine cabinet to relieve the welts and bruises, not to mention the funny little ding-a-ling sound that won't shut up somewhere in a corner of the brain.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Cutler did not say that nose tackles don't deserve the money they're getting, but there was an implication that something must be upside-down in the society if such disparity in salary between a brute like a Burt and a Chief Justice exists, or continues to.</p>
        <p>Surely, Mr. Cutler does not mean to return Burt and company to previous salaries - low by most standards, lower by half, in fact, than what the Chief Justice earns - before the players' union fought the monolithic owners with strikes and other bargaining weapons to gain a better wage.</p>
        <p>Surely, Mr. Cutler understands that in a free enterprise sysytem people are paid what the traffic will bear - if they can get it, that is. And the football players wouldn't be getting it if the gate and TV and ancillary receipts wouldn't allow the owners to give it.</p>
        <p>Interesting, though, that Mr. Cutler will use the nose tackle, or, as he did in other moments, the baseball player (''Don Mattingly is earning $2 million a year!'') to illustrate that the Federal officials are being underpaid ''in terms most citizens will understand.''</p>
        <p>Most citizens have played football as boys, and baseball (as boys and girls), and perhaps can identify in a way that they can't with other entertainers - for the professional athlete is an entertainer, with a career life expectancy that is not only relatively short, but precarious, too.</p>
        <p>It's harder to identify with movie stars and TV stars and rock stars. But they often earn incredibly more than nose tackles, or even first basemen. In the last two years, according to Forbes magazine, Bill Cosby, for example, earned $84 million; Sylvester Stallone $74 million; Bruce Springsteen $56 million; Madonna $47 million and Johnny Carson $40 million. Even that bag of bones, Arnold Schwarzenegger, did better than Burt, with $26 million over the previous two years.</p>
        <p>In 1930, when Babe Ruth received the fantastic salary of $80,000, he was asked, ''How do you feel making more money than the President of the United States?' Ruth supposedly said, ''I had a better year than he did.''</p>
        <p>Burt and Smerlas and Krumrie and Golic had better years than some of those seeking more pay on The Hill. But if, as Mr. Cutler believes, heftier wages will lure better people into government, then we should give it serious consideration.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, leave Jim Burt out of it. He's got enough problems.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
