<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets See Long Drive as a Harbinger</title>
    <meta content="Y27JET$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/27/sports/football/27JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1435521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Browns</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Vikings</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Cleveland Browns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Minnesota Vikings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Browns</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Martin, Curtis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pennington, Chad</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EEDE163FF934A15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1227" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets See Long Drive as a Harbinger</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jets See Long Drive as a Harbinger</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets will attempt to continue momentum of last game against Minnesota Vikings in game against Cleveland Browns (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jets point to one drive as the standard by which all others will be judged, an example of how to use multiple offensive threats to maximum advantage -- something that has been a year and a half in the making.</p>
        <p>The Jets began a drive at their own 10 midway through the third quarter of the game last Sunday against the Vikings. Ninety yards and some three and a half minutes:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jets point to one drive this season as an example of how to use multiple offensive threats to maximum advantage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Jets point to one drive as the standard by which all others will be judged, an example of how to use multiple offensive threats to maximum advantage -- something that has been a year and a half in the making.</p>
        <p>The Jets began a drive at their own 10 midway through the third quarter of the game last Sunday against the Vikings. Ninety yards and some three and a half minutes:</p>
        <p>1-10, NYJ 10: Curtis Martin, 1-yard run. Groans from the crowd.</p>
        <p>2-9, NYJ 11: Vikings crowd the line. Chad Pennington to Martin, screen pass, 6 yards.</p>
        <p>3-3, NYJ 17: Pennington to Santana Moss, quick slant. Moss leaps, then lashes through the middle of the defense for 34 yards.</p>
        <p>1-10, MIN 49: Pennington has a lot of time. Slant to Laveranues Coles, 28 yards.</p>
        <p>1-10, MIN 21: Empty backfield, Pennington to Wayne Chrebet, a quick pass to the right side. Chrebet runs for a 16-yard gain.</p>
        <p>1-goal, MIN 5: Martin 5-yard run.</p>
        <p>In only 3 minutes 25 seconds, the Jets had run their longest drive of the season, giving their fans a glimpse of what has been percolating in Paul Hackett's head all this time.</p>
        <p>''This is what we all had in mind, the three of us, 250 yards, that's what we think we're capable of,'' Chrebet said of the combined total for the Jets wide receivers last week. ''And we hope it continues.''</p>
        <p>Even if it means, in Chrebet's case, fewer snaps because the Jets want to get Moss on the field more and have determined it does not work to have all three wideouts in the game at the same time. Eventually, the speed of Moss and Coles -- and the desire to get the two young receivers on the field together -- will squeeze Chrebet even more, Hackett said, but ''his experience on the field, his ability to do multiple things, will preclude that for a while.''</p>
        <p>But the three receivers, who combined for 15 receptions and 250 yards against the Vikings, will surely get plenty of work again today. The Cleveland secondary is rated higher than those of the Vikings or the Chiefs, who are the two worst in the league. But the Browns have been hit with injuries there, with one starting cornerback out (Corey Fuller), the strong safety out (Robert Giffith) and the other starting cornerback (Daylon McCutcheon) questionable.</p>
        <p>No matter who the opponent is, however, the Jets seem to have tentatively found their identity on offense. They have essentially scrapped the spread offense, which was added last off-season because it was a favorite of Vinny Testaverde. They will still use it occasionally as a tantalizing changeup to the revived two-back, more conservative scheme that the Jets ran -- and were roundly criticized for -- last season.</p>
        <p>On the day the Jets told Pennington the starting job was his, he told Hackett not to worry, that the coordinator should call the plays. So Hackett has. And the result is that in the three games Pennington has played (he replaced Testaverde after one series against Jacksonville), 43 passes -- 63.2 percent of his completions -- have been to the wide receivers. By contrast, in the first three games, only 20 of 58 completions (34.7 percent) were to receivers.</p>
        <p>The two-back set may sound conservative, but Pennington has had more success stretching the field with the receivers than Testaverde did.</p>
        <p>''When you spread people out, you don't really become a vertical team,'' Coach Herman Edwards said. ''When your edges are open, you like to get the ball out of your hand, especially if you are going to empty sets where you don't have anybody in the backfield. On a lot of these plays, we have two backs in the backfield with some play action, we attack a little bit better and get down the field a little bit further.''</p>
        <p>The Jets were moving away from the spread formation before the quarterback change because the offense had sputtered. But, even after only two full games with Pennington, who is in his third year, it is clear that he has embraced Hackett's preferred offense with greater ease than Testaverde did. Also, although he will not say so, Hackett must feel more comfortable with Pennington.</p>
        <p>Testaverde seemed to be most comfortable throwing the ball to Chrebet and Richie Anderson, but Chrebet said this week that that is what the plays called for. Pennington, who is particularly adept at the play fake, is more comfortable stepping up in the pocket and is more likely to hold the ball longer to look for a receiver downfield than to go to his second or third options.</p>
        <p>''When you make a change of the magnitude we made, you go back and try to figure which things are going to fit our strengths and you try to minimize our weaknesses,'' Hackett said. ''We had some things exposed early in the year that in retrospect we shouldn't have been doing. We're trying to build a foundation with a guy who has played two games. The comfort zone is to start in simplistic form. Let's go back to what we did the very first day I arrived here. Put two guys in the I-formation. Don't get enamored with these wonderful plays you have. Once the decision was made, that shifts everything and in a lot of ways it makes you refocus and say 'What do we do best?' ''</p>
        <p>Right now, it is exploiting the speed of Coles and Moss. Put simply, even if they are not the target of the pass, their speed sets defenses back on their heels and leaves the middle open for Chrebet.</p>
        <p>''When you've got a guy running through the defense, the spaces to throw the ball into get bigger,'' Hackett said. ''Defenses do a great job of squeezing those holes and making the quarterback put the ball exactly where he has to put it. That's the thing that just having them on the field gives you.''</p>
        <p>It was only a month ago that the offense was moribund and the Jets first began to talk about reverting to basics. The Jets had apparently lost enough confidence in their offense that Pennington has felt it necessary to enter the huddle on occasion and, after telling teammates what the call is, announce that if they don't like it, ''Don't complain about it.''</p>
        <p>When asked if he thought players had lost confidence, Pennington replied, ''Probably.''</p>
        <p>''It's important that we trust as players the ability of coaches to put us in the right position to be successful and trust their feel,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There will certainly be days when the offense is not as smooth and successful as it was last week, but the public soul-searching has been laid to rest, buried by a single drive of perfect balance.</p>
        <p>''Just doing something like that lets teams know you can't fall asleep, you have to be ready for this,'' Moss said. ''It's just great. It's fun.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
