<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Liberty Is Ready to Open Its Season Saturday</title>
    <meta content="19HOOP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="PRO BASKETBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="938081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Liberty</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Bashir, Tarik</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DF143EF93AA25755C0A961958260" item-length="394" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Liberty Is Ready to Open Its Season Saturday</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TARIK EL-BASHIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">El-Bashir, Tarik</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Outlook for New York Liberty in initial Women's National Basketball Association season (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For months, the New York Liberty and seven other teams in the Women's National Basketball Association have brashly been saying, ''We Got Next.''</p>
        <p>Well, this weekend, they finally will get it. With the N.B.A. done, its players gone for the summer, during the next two months, June 21-Aug. 30, the arenas and spotlight will belong to the W.N.B.A., its sister league.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For months, the New York Liberty and seven other teams in the Women's National Basketball Association have brashly been saying, ''We Got Next.''</p>
        <p>Well, this weekend, they finally will get it. With the N.B.A. done, its players gone for the summer, during the next two months, June 21-Aug. 30, the arenas and spotlight will belong to the W.N.B.A., its sister league.</p>
        <p>For the Liberty, which defeated the Cleveland Rockers twice in the preseason, the 28-game regular season will begin Saturday at Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Then the Liberty heads to Sacramento and Houston before making its debut at Madison Square Garden on June 29 against Phoenix.</p>
        <p>From the first time the Liberty stepped on the court at its practice facility in Manhattan on May 28, the team has improved markedly, according to point guard Teresa Weatherspoon.</p>
        <p>''We have definitely gotten better,'' said Weatherspoon, who played the last nine seasons in the Italian professional leagues. ''There are some areas where we can improve, and we are working on them.''</p>
        <p>Turnovers are at the top of the list. In the two preseason games, the Liberty turned the ball over 37 times. That sloppiness, as Weatherspoon pointed out, is the fault of the players who are still unfamiliar with one another.</p>
        <p>''We are ready,'' Weatherspoon said. ''But we have had a very small time to prepare. As a playmaker, it was especially hard for me. I had to get to know the other players pretty fast.''</p>
        <p>Even with the turnovers, all indications are that the Liberty is going to have a successful first season. With players like Rebecca Lobo, the former University of Connecticut standout and 1996 Olympic gold medal winner, and Weatherspoon, two of the most recognizable names in the game, the Liberty should not have much trouble putting the ball in the basket.</p>
        <p>Kym Hampton, a forward who played the last 11 years in Italy; Sophia Witherspoon, a guard who has played in Italy, Hungary, France and Switzerland, and Vickie Johnson, who played a season in Spain, will join Lobo and Weatherspoon in the Liberty's starting lineup. Sue Wicks, the former Rutgers standout, will be the first player off of the bench.</p>
        <p>''All that stuff about we got next,'' said Weatherspoon, referring to the commercial theme, ''now it's time. It is time for us to get on the floor and let it flow.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
