<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Beaches Are Closed By Sewage</title>
    <meta content="19BEAC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19970621T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="938144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcquiston, John T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4D8143EF93AA25755C0A961958260" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Beaches Are Closed By Sewage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN T. McQUISTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcquiston, John T</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Westchester County closes all 26 of its beaches on Long Island Sound because of lingering effects of 100,000-gallon sewage spill early this week near City Island; officials say beaches might not reopen for weekend; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Westchester County closed all 26 of its beaches on Long Island Sound yesterday because of the lingering effects of a 100,000-gallon sewage spill early this week near City Island, and officials said the beaches might not reopen for the weekend.</p>
        <p>Winds and the tide have so far confined the spill to the northwest corner of Long Island Sound and held it to the Westchester shoreline, sparing New York City beaches in the Bronx and those along the North Shore of Long Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Westchester County closed all 26 of its beaches on Long Island Sound yesterday because of the lingering effects of a 100,000-gallon sewage spill early this week near City Island, and officials said the beaches might not reopen for the weekend.</p>
        <p>Winds and the tide have so far confined the spill to the northwest corner of Long Island Sound and held it to the Westchester shoreline, sparing New York City beaches in the Bronx and those along the North Shore of Long Island.</p>
        <p>The spill began shortly after 3 P.M. on Sunday when a pipe that carries raw sewage from City Island to the Bronx developed a crack beneath Eastchester Bay.</p>
        <p>The leak was reported to the State Department of Environmental Conservation three hours later, said Jennifer Post, a department spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Ms. Post said repairs on the pipe were completed by late Tuesday afternoon, but by that time state and county officials had been forced to close 12 of Westchester's beaches closest to the spill.</p>
        <p>The Westchester County Health Commissioner, Dr. Harold Adel, said the closings were extended to all the county's beaches -- from Glen Island Park in Pelham Manor to the Westchester Country Club beach in Rye -- because of the potential health risk to bathers. He said it might be necessary to keep the beaches closed through the weekend, which includes the first day of summer on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Officials said they planned to continue to test the waters in the Sound for bacteria levels so they can determine the size and direction of the slowly moving spill, and to determine how long it might take to dissipate.</p>
        <p>''Pending the receipt of further visual observations and sampling data, and watching the weather over the next 24 to 48 hours, we will keep the Westchester beaches closed,'' Dr. Adel said.</p>
        <p>One of the beach areas affected was in the City of Rye. Mayor Ted Dunn said that on a good day, a couple of thousand people use the Rye Town Beach and Playland Beach.</p>
        <p>''There is a short-term affect which is very upsetting,'' said Mr. Dunn, a Republican running for Westchester county executive. ''The long-term problem is the one that concerns me the most.</p>
        <p>''The sewer systems all along the Sound are old and we've been talking for years about upgrading them, but all we've done is talk,'' he said. ''We need to upgrade the pipes that run underground and the sewage treatment plants themselves.''</p>
        <p>The Westchester County Executive, Andrew P. O'Rourke, who is not running for re-election, described the incident as unfortunate. ''These things do happen, even though people try to prevent it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Of the 26 beaches in Westchester, 20 are private, 2 are county-owned and 4 are operated by towns. A spokesman for the County Executive said the two county beaches are used by up to 50,000 people a year and generate about $150,000 a year in revenue for the county.</p>
        <p>The beach closings, which included 13 in New Rochelle and Larchmont, had little effect yesterday because of gray and damp weather. Today, however, was expected to be less cloudy with more sunshine and temperatures in the 80's.</p>
        <p>By late yesterday, the dissipating spill appeared to be isolated in the waters off Westchester. Although the winds and tides could eventually carry the water eastward toward Connecticut, officials there said that, so far, the pipe break had not affected their beaches.</p>
        <p>In Greenwich, however, one of three beaches was closed yesterday, not because of the break in the City Island pipeline, but because of an accidental discharge of sewage from a sewage treatment plant near Byram Shore Beach.</p>
        <p>Orchard Beach in the Bronx, which is west of the City Island spill, remained open yesterday. Tests at Orchard Beach showed that bacteria levels were safe, said Cathy DelliCarpini, a spokeswoman for the New York City Department of Environmental Protection.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 21, 1997, Saturday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Thursday about the closing of beaches in Westchester County because of a sewage spill misidentified one shown. It was Hudson Park in New Rochelle, not the Glen Island Park beach in Pelham Manor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 21, 1997, Saturday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Thursday about the closing of beaches in Westchester County because of a sewage spill misidentified one shown. It was Hudson Park in New Rochelle, not the Glen Island Park beach in Pelham Manor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
