<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Jets Won This One With Stifling Defense</title>
    <meta content="05GEOR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/05/sports/football/05GEOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1340340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Orleans Saints</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New Orleans Saints</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Walton, Joe</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6DB1539F936A35752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Jets Won This One With Stifling Defense</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Jets Won With Stifling Defense</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas George</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article analyzes New York Jets victory over New Orleans Saints, noting impressive defensive play; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last time the Jets played here in the Superdome, Coach Joe Walton was about to be booted. Ken O'Brien, Al Toon and Johnny Hector were the offense and Erik McMillan, James Hasty and Jeff Lageman were the defense. The Jets lost the game, 29-14, fell to 1-5 and were crashing toward a 4-12 season.</p>
        <p>That was 1989, and what followed were four seasons of Bruce Coslet, one of Pete Carroll, two of Rich Kotite, three of Bill Parcells and one of Al Groh. What also followed were seven straight seasons in which the Jets could not manage a winning record, let alone a playoff appearance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW ORLEANS The last time the Jets played here in the Superdome, Coach Joe Walton was about to be booted. Ken O'Brien, Al Toon and Johnny Hector were the offense and Erik McMillan, James Hasty and Jeff Lageman were thedefense. The Jets lost the game, 29- 14, fell to 1-5 and were crashing toward a 4-12 season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last time the Jets played here in the Superdome, Coach Joe Walton was about to be booted. Ken O'Brien, Al Toon and Johnny Hector were the offense and Erik McMillan, James Hasty and Jeff Lageman were the defense. The Jets lost the game, 29-14, fell to 1-5 and were crashing toward a 4-12 season.</p>
        <p>That was 1989, and what followed were four seasons of Bruce Coslet, one of Pete Carroll, two of Rich Kotite, three of Bill Parcells and one of Al Groh. What also followed were seven straight seasons in which the Jets could not manage a winning record, let alone a playoff appearance.</p>
        <p>It was not until the Parcells years, beginning in 1997, that the Jets grew sharper teeth. Parcells instilled a new defensive mentality, a defensive dose of courage and confidence that provided a foundation on which to rattle a sleeping franchise.</p>
        <p>Herman Edwards arrived in New York this year with similar hopes. Edwards, an former defensive back, chose the West Coast offense and all the trinkets that make it the glitzy offense of our time. The first draft choice during his watch was receiver Santana Moss.</p>
        <p>But make no mistake, Edwards envisions the days when his defense dominates, when his defense wins. For Edwards, offense may be sexy, but defense is tried and true. Which is why what happened last night must have made Edwards feel that his Jets may have grown the sharp defensive bite he has sought.</p>
        <p>This Jets victory, a 16-9 physical mauling of the New Orleans Saints, a physical domination over a team accustomed to doing just that, was impressive and gave the Jets plenty of hope.</p>
        <p>For the players, it was a breakthrough. For the defensive coordinator, Ted Cottrell, a proud moment. For the Jets organization, now with a 5-3 record, the first tangible evidence that it is not an impossibility that the Jets could wind up right here, back in the Superdome in February, in the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>O.K., calm down! It's not that the Jets are on their way to the Super Bowl. The point is, this is how you get there: rock-solid, denying defense; a running game in the fourth quarter; winning games on the road. The Jets are 4-0 in road games this season, which shows a resolve and fortitude that is rare in the N.F.L.</p>
        <p>This Jets defense seemed light-years away from the defense that was torched in the air in the season opener against Indianapolis and torched on the ground by San Francisco in that Monday night free fall. There was the embarrassment and trickery of the Rams that followed those two games, but all of that was put aside last night by the Jets' defense.</p>
        <p>Especially at the finish.</p>
        <p>Edwards took a risky but gutsy shot on a fourth-and-inches call near midfield that the Jets failed to convert. In the game's final seconds, the defense was asked to rise again -- and it did. It stopped the Saints cold on three tries from near the Jets' 20. It finished the game with a sack of quarterback Aaron Brooks.</p>
        <p>On New Orleans's first possession, the Jets forced a three-and-out. The second time the Saints had the ball, they drove from their 39 to the Jets' 10, but cornerback Aaron Glenn ended that threat with an interception in the end zone.</p>
        <p>After Vinny Testaverde threw a second-quarter interception, the Jets' defense rendered it harmless and forced a Saints punt. Just before halftime, with the Saints marching to the Jets' 12, Mo Lewis intercepted a pass in the middle of the field, just in front of the goal line. The Jets' 13-0 halftime lead was preserved.</p>
        <p>It kept going that way: Saints opportunity, Jets denial.</p>
        <p>After the Saints finally scored in the third quarter to cut the lead to 13-7, they tried a successful onside kick. But the Jets' defense held. After the Saints scored a safety, the Jets' defense held. Even in the fourth quarter, when the Jets missed a close field-goal attempt, the Jets' defense got the ball right back, with nose tackle Steve Martin recovering a fumble and setting up another Jets field-goal attempt that, this time, worked.</p>
        <p>Martin played his best game. Glenn was persistent and aggressive in his coverage. End John Abraham displayed speed and energy and persistence in creating havoc for the Saints' offense and particularly Brooks. It helped that the Saints' Pro Bowl tackle, Willie Roaf, was injured and out, but give Abraham credit for seizing the moment and the spotlight.</p>
        <p>Remember, this Saints offense hung 34 points on St. Louis last week and held a 25-point third quarter. By halftime, when the Saints had rushed for only 29 yards and Brooks had passed for just 77, the trend was set. And it was an ugly one for the Saints' offense, which entered averaging 325.8 yards a game and ranked second in the N.F.C. in rushing offense (116.2 yards a game).</p>
        <p>Brooks hurt the Jets early with scrambles for third-down conversions, but as the game wore on, the Jets curtailed that, too. They adjusted on the fly while performing the initial game plan adeptly. Over all, it was a smart game by the defense, a disciplined and tenacious game.</p>
        <p>With the season half gone, with games up next against Kansas City at home and Miami on the road before a bye, the Jets have put themselves in playoff position. By winning in this fashion, they may have established a defensive presence that could carry them further than most had dreamed.</p>
        <p>ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
