<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garden Events: Tours, Photos and an Auction</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="617389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D8123CF937A15755C0A965958260" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garden Events: Tours, Photos and an Auction</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Flowers Through a Lens  Gottesman Exhibition Hall, New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue at East 42d Street; (212) 869-8089.</p>
        <p>"Flora Photographica: The Flower in Photography From 1835 to the Present," an exhibition of 180 works in color and black-and-white, starts Saturday and runs through Aug. 21. The show is divided into sections that explore the history of flowers as photographic subjects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Flowers Through a Lens  Gottesman Exhibition Hall, New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue at East 42d Street; (212) 869-8089.</p>
        <p>"Flora Photographica: The Flower in Photography From 1835 to the Present," an exhibition of 180 works in color and black-and-white, starts Saturday and runs through Aug. 21. The show is divided into sections that explore the history of flowers as photographic subjects.</p>
        <p>Photographers represented include Ansel Adams, Imogen Cunningham, Dennis Hopper, Andre Kertesz, Helen Levitt, Edward Steichen and William Henry Fox Talbot. Open Tuesday and Wednesday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Thursday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. No charge.</p>
        <p>William A. Ewing, the curator of the exhibit, will give an illustrated lecture on Monday at 6 P.M. at the Mid-Manhattan Library, 455 Fifth Avenue (East 40th Street). There is no charge; admission is on a first-come, first-served basis.  Benefit and Auction  Christie's East, 219 East 67th Street; (212) 606-0440.</p>
        <p>Christie's will auction garden statuary, ornaments and furniture on Monday at 2 P.M. Tonight, starting at 6:30 P.M., there will be a preview and reception to benefit the New York Botanical Garden, with a lecture by the author C. Z. Guest. Tickets are $25. Reservations are required.  The Garden Behind the Library  Bryant Park, Avenue of the Americas and West 42d Street; (212) 983-4142.</p>
        <p>Michael Levine, the gardener for Bryant Park, will offer guided tours of the gardens adjacent to the New York Public Library on Wednesday evenings through Aug. 25. A redesign of the perennial gardens was completed in April 1992 by the garden designer Lynden B. Miller. Those interested are to meet at the Lowell Fountain at 6 P.M. No charge.  One Park's Design  Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment, Tennis House in Prospect Park, enter at Ninth Street and Prospect Park West; (718) 788-8549.</p>
        <p>On Sunday at 1 P.M., the center will sponsor a walking tour in Prospect Park about the design of the park by Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux in 1868, along with subsequent changes in landscaping and buildings. No charge.  Children and Gardens  American Horticultural Society, River Farm Garden Park, 7931 East Boulevard Drive, near George Washington Parkway, Alexandria, Va.; (703) 768-5700.</p>
        <p>The society has opened 12 children's gardens that will be in place through October. The gardens, some designed by children, include a mini-ecosystem built around a waterfall, a dinosaur garden with footprint fossils and a garden featuring a maze and foliage tunnel. Open Monday through Friday, 8:30 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. No charge.</p>
        <p>From Aug. 12 through 14 in Chevy Chase, Md., the society will sponsor a symposium about children's gardens. Fee, including meals and garden tours, is $165. For information, call Maureen Heffernan: (800) 777-7931.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
