<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jail Threat Ends 13-Month Sit-In To Save Church</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="617306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WORCESTER (MASS)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ST JOSEPH'S CHURCH (WORCESTER, MASS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIMER, SARA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARRINGTON, TIMOTHY (BISHOP)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD71038F937A15755C0A965958260" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jail Threat Ends 13-Month Sit-In To Save Church</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARA RIMER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIMER, SARA</byline>
      <dateline>WORCESTER, Mass., June 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group of 45 middle-age men and woman walked out of St. Joseph's Church today, ending a 13-month sit-in, after their Bishop obtained a court order to evict them from the 65-year-old building, which he says is unsafe.</p>
        <p>The parishioners, who had taken turns sleeping on the pews and floors for more than a year to protest the closing of the church, left only after their long legal battle with the Diocese of Worcester came to a close. Judge Thomas Connolly of Superior Court found them in contempt of court earlier in the day and threatened them with fines or jail sentences if they did not leave. The judge said he was saddened to have to intervene in what he called an "unbelievably unfortunate and sad situation."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A group of 45 middle-age men and woman walked out of St. Joseph's Church today, ending a 13-month sit-in, after their Bishop obtained a court order to evict them from the 65-year-old building, which he says is unsafe.</p>
        <p>The parishioners, who had taken turns sleeping on the pews and floors for more than a year to protest the closing of the church, left only after their long legal battle with the Diocese of Worcester came to a close. Judge Thomas Connolly of Superior Court found them in contempt of court earlier in the day and threatened them with fines or jail sentences if they did not leave. The judge said he was saddened to have to intervene in what he called an "unbelievably unfortunate and sad situation."</p>
        <p>At 1 P.M., under police escort, the members of the French Canadian parish walked out holding hands and vowing to continue to do what they could to keep their church alive.  'The One Constant'</p>
        <p>"We built this church," said Giselle Desroches, a third-generation parishioner, who was baptized, confirmed and married at St. Joseph's, where her parents were also married, and where her two sons were baptized not long ago. "My mother can remember putting a penny in an envelope every Sunday. Everything else changes. This church was the one constant."</p>
        <p>Last year Bishop Timothy Harrington of the Worchester Diocese ordered the inner-city church with German stained-glass windows closed, saying it was unsafe. He ordered the parish to merge with the city's other French Canadian parish, Notre Dame, about a mile away.</p>
        <p>The working-class parishioners of St. Joseph's responded by raising more than $600,000 in pledges for the structural repairs. But St. Joseph's was built by people who labored in textile mills and shoe factories that have long since shut down, and Bishop Harrington said he believed the cost was too high for them to bear.</p>
        <p>"That's pledged money, not cold cash," the Bishop said today at his office in the chancery, about a mile from St. Joseph's. "The Diocese of Worcester, to use street language, is not rolling in dough."</p>
        <p>The Bishop told the parishioners that he was "reluctant to impoverish the people of St. Joseph's with a debt I did not feel you could handle."</p>
        <p>But the parishioners would not move, and they continued to hold prayer services in the church led by their deacon, Joseph T. DuVarney, and occasionally by the members. They stayed to the last possible moment, even after the Bishop had the telephone lines inside the church cut, the locks on the doors changed and the windows boarded up on Tuesday. Marching from the church to the chancery today, the parishioners jeered the bishop when he tried to explain his decision. Bishop Harrington, who is 74, is scheduled to retire next December.</p>
        <p>"It is painful for me to hear the shouting and jeering of the people for whom I am Bishop," he told reporters later. "Closing parishes is not only happening here in Worcester. It is happening all over the country. I'm not the ogre I've been painted to be."</p>
        <p>Inner-city Catholic churches across the country have closed over the years as parishioners have migrated to the suburbs. Parishioners in many communities have filed lawsuits and staged fasts and sit-ins to keep churches open.</p>
        <p>The sit-in had its beginnings on May 25, 1992, when Ron Fortin, 65, an expediter at a forging and casting shop, who went on to become the leader of the protest, suggested to 14 others that they occupy the church.</p>
        <p>"We said we'd go home and pray and think about whether or not we wanted to take such a drastic step," said Mrs. Desroches, who is 32 and a nurse. "I said to my husband, 'I don't know if I can do this.' I was brought up in parochial school to be obedient -- except we were also taught to fight injustice."</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Desroches and the others decided they would defy their Bishop. One of the senior members of the group was 70-year-old Mary Scano, who for the past 13 months has been juggling her two jobs, as a city councilor and the owner of Scano's Bakery, with an overnight vigil at the church.</p>
        <p>The protesters knew last Friday that their fight was ending when their last court appeal was lost. All that was left was the eviction hearing today. At 2:30 A.M., while others slept, Mrs. Scano talked about the bitterness she felt.  "I'm having a problem right now with my religion," she said.</p>
        <p>At 5:30 A.M., the parishioners began rolling up their sleeping bags and air mattresses. They prayed. Then they carried out the coffee urn that had sustained them, and all their trash. For the last time, they vacuumed the red carpet, and walked outside.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
