<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Administration May Cut Growth Forecast to 2.5%</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="617361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYSON, LAURA D'ANDREA (CHMN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DA153DF937A15755C0A965958260" item-length="387" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Administration May Cut Growth Forecast to 2.5%</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton Administration is likely to cut its forecast for this year's economic growth to around 2.5 percent from the 3.1 percent prediction it made in January, the Administration's chief economist said today.</p>
        <p>Laura D'Andrea Tyson, head of the Council of Economic Advisers, said the Administration was contemplating a downward revision in the forecast because of the defeat of President Clinton's $16 billion jobs program and slower-than-anticipated growth in the first quarter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton Administration is likely to cut its forecast for this year's economic growth to around 2.5 percent from the 3.1 percent prediction it made in January, the Administration's chief economist said today.</p>
        <p>Laura D'Andrea Tyson, head of the Council of Economic Advisers, said the Administration was contemplating a downward revision in the forecast because of the defeat of President Clinton's $16 billion jobs program and slower-than-anticipated growth in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>"We're talking somewhere between 2.5 percent and 3 percent, and probably on the soft side of 3," she said at a lunch with reporters, suggesting that numerous factors were pushing the forecast toward 2.5 percent.</p>
        <p>Many economists say that growth needs to be at least 2.5 percent to make an appreciable dent in the nation's unemployment rate, now running at 6.9 percent. Smaller Debt Service</p>
        <p>Ms. Tyson predicted that notwithstanding the slower-than-anticipated growth, this year's budget deficit would not be larger than the $322 billion the Administration forecast in January. The reason: interest rates have fallen more than the Administration had forecast, causing large savings in servicing the Federal debt.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tyson said that in light of the strong rise in business inventories in the first quarter, growth in the second quarter would probably remain moderate. She said she agreed with private forecasters who suggested growth of 2.3 to 2.4 percent.</p>
        <p>But she predicted faster growth in the second half, saying that once the President's economic package was approved and many uncertainties removed, businesses would feel more willing to expand, invest and hire new workers.</p>
        <p>She added that "the lagged effects" of low interest rates would also help speed growth later this year. For example, homeowners who paid $1,000 to refinance their mortages may take several extra months to feel the effects of their lower mortgage payments.</p>
        <p>Other factors that suggested faster growth, she said, were interest-rate cuts in Germany and an expected economic rebound in slumping Japan. Stronger growth abroad would help increase American exports, which have been weak in recent months.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tyson said the Senate's defeat of the President's stimulus program would subtract three-tenths of 1 percent from this year's growth rate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
