<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Microsoft Plays Down A Sales Lift From Vista</title>
    <meta content="16soft" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/16/business/16soft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1826549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ballmer, Steven A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EED6173EF935A25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="436" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Microsoft Plays Down A Sales Lift From Vista</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Microsoft Plays Down a Sales Lift From Vista</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Feb. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wall Street analysts are being too optimistic about sales of Windows Vista, Steven A. Ballmer, Microsoft's chief executive, told financial analysts in New York on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Vista, the latest version of the Windows operating system, was released to corporate customers late last year and to retail customers last month. Analysts have said industry growth was slowed by repeated delays in Vista's introduction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wall Street analysts are being too optimistic about sales of Windows Vista, Steven A. Ballmer, Microsoft’s chief executive, said on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wall Street analysts are being too optimistic about sales of Windows Vista, Steven A. Ballmer, Microsoft's chief executive, told financial analysts in New York on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Vista, the latest version of the Windows operating system, was released to corporate customers late last year and to retail customers last month. Analysts have said industry growth was slowed by repeated delays in Vista's introduction.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ballmer suggested that Vista's release would generate only a ''small surge'' in PC sales. He said forecasts for sales in the fiscal year beginning in July were too high, noting that the analysts' spreadsheet models called for strong growth in Vista sales, while at the same time predicting slower growth for the rest of the personal computer industry.</p>
        <p>''These things are out of whack,'' he said at an analyst conference that was broadcast on the Internet. ''If Vista is growing, there should be a lot of people participating,'' he said, referring to other companies in the PC industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ballmer suggested that PC industry growth would not reach the 12 to 15 percent annual rates that some analysts have been predicting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ballmer's comments also suggest that customers will not rush to upgrade existing machines to the new software, which is reported to be both memory-hungry and less compatible with existing software and hardware than Microsoft had indicated.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Ballmer said he was optimistic about the role that the new Windows software would play in the company's profit growth, in the long run. He listed Windows as the company's leading growth business in a list of nine that could potentially create more than a half-billion dollars in profit growth during the next three years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ballmer spoke after the stock market closed. Microsoft stock fell about 1.7 percent in after-hours trading, to $28.95.</p>
        <p>During his hourlong presentation, Mr. Ballmer reiterated that the company's business strategy called for patience and persistence, even in businesses where the company does not find success over a long period of time. He noted that for the first 13 years after the company began selling corporate server software in 1989, it was told that its products were not reliable enough for that market.</p>
        <p>He acknowledged that Microsoft was trailing both Google and Yahoo in the Web portal and search markets, which are supported by online advertising, and said the company was unhappy being in a trailing position.</p>
        <p>''We need a strong services platform,'' he said, pointing to the infrastructure the company is now building under its Live brand in a development effort being led by its chief technology officer, Ray Ozzie.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
