<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lucian Freud as a Boy Wonder Still Learning to Draw</title>
    <meta content="09RUSS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/09/arts/design/09RUSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1470799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freud, Lucian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russell, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Freud, Lucian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6DB143FF93AA35750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lucian Freud as a Boy Wonder Still Learning to Draw</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lucian Freud as a Boy Wonder Still Learning to Draw</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RUSSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Russell, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Russell reviews Matthew Marks Gallery exhibition of drawings by Lucian Freud; drawings (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE has just opened at the Matthew Marks Gallery in Chelsea a show that for idiosyncrasy would be hard to beat. It consists of 168 drawings, most of them 8 1/2 inches by 5 3/4 inches, that were made in 1940 by a longtime friend of mine, Lucian Freud, when he was 17 years old.</p>
        <p>Even at 15 and 16, Lucian was spoken of as a boy wonder. In 1933, when he and his parents left Germany for London, he was already said to be ''drawing all the time.'' He attended art school briefly in 1937, having gained entry with a sandstone sculpture of a horse. By 1939, he was so magnetic that just to see him in the street in London was an event.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lucian Freud worked with fierce regard, singular determination and a real manic gleam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE has just opened at the Matthew Marks Gallery in Chelsea a show that for idiosyncrasy would be hard to beat. It consists of 168 drawings, most of them 8 1/2 inches by 5 3/4 inches, that were made in 1940 by a longtime friend of mine, Lucian Freud, when he was 17 years old.</p>
        <p>Even at 15 and 16, Lucian was spoken of as a boy wonder. In 1933, when he and his parents left Germany for London, he was already said to be ''drawing all the time.'' He attended art school briefly in 1937, having gained entry with a sandstone sculpture of a horse. By 1939, he was so magnetic that just to see him in the street in London was an event.</p>
        <p>Lucian lived on Charlotte Street (where, as people liked to remember, Rimbaud and Verlaine had once lodged). And he was working very hard, in the belief that if he concentrated enough, he would end by drawing well. At that time, according to his painter-friend Lawrence Gowing, he ''drew with a sharp literalness that seemed naïvely to defy what people expected art to look like. His defiance, like his drawings, was real enough.''</p>
        <p>Early in 1940, when World War II had not really begun, Lucian went with a school friend to stay in the house of a retired miner in Capel Curig, Wales. Before long they were joined by the poet Stephen Spender, who became a favorite and ever-present subject for drawings. (There are 15 portraits of Spender in the Matthew Marks exhibition.)</p>
        <p>Throughout the catalog of the 168 drawings, published by the gallery, one is aware of the fierce regard, singular determination and real manic gleam with which Lucian went to work. But to be sure, at 17, he was not yet fully formed. Of the drawings, he said not long ago to his friend Sebastian Smee: ''They're from a very distant self. For instance, drawing naked women before I'd even seen one, that feels a very long way off!''</p>
        <p>But the drawings also emit an irresistible sense of fun. Titles like ''Horse Smiling,''  ''Elephant in Town'' and ''Whale Having Tea'' give the general idea.</p>
        <p>These drawings, which are on view for the first time, speak for a relatively tranquil moment in history that all too soon came to an end. Neville Chamberlain was still England's prime minister, and there was time for fun, and time for fancy, in a countryside hardly touched by the war. Running jokes were many in Capel Curig, and teasing of one kind or another powered many of the drawings.</p>
        <p>(By the way, Lucian smuggled himself into the British Merchant Marine in 1941 and was invalided out a year later.)</p>
        <p>After the end of World War II, Lucian moved back to London but did not head for the agreeable quarters in Chelsea that most artists preferred. For quite some time he lived in Paddington, where people chose not to go if they could find anything better. Before long he had his choice of agreeable and carefree subjects to paint, but he was more interested in people who lived on the edge of illegality. To those people he gave a disquieting actuality; their looks, their way of life and their feelings about one another were not made obvious or caricatured, nonetheless they look sinister.</p>
        <p>At the same time he was sought after in all societies, while never identifying himself with any one of them. He was remarkable for his manner of speech: he never hesitated, dissembled or prevaricated. Clear and direct, he was his own self wherever he was. If he was asked a question, his answer was never ambiguous.</p>
        <p>He was also a true friend. Anyone who was with him in times of trouble could count on advice that, though not always welcome, was the best. I remember an occasion on which he took care of a looming altercation in a restaurant between Francis Bacon and his friend George Dyer. With just two or three sentences, Lucian turned the world around, and Dyer, good-natured at heart, saw sense.</p>
        <p>From time to time, Lucian's passion for horses led him to back his fancy at the bookmakers. Quite often he lost a colossal sum. He never complained, but said only: ''My attitude toward money is mainly expressed through gambling. Losing as much money as I can get hold of is an instant solution to my economic problems. It frees you from the distraction that investment might involve.''</p>
        <p>He told Leigh Bowery, the monumental performance artist whom he painted many times: ''However stupid consistent losing is, it makes you concentrate on serious things. It's not gambling that's so stupid. It's losing.''</p>
        <p>Bowery asked him why he didn't stop gambling.</p>
        <p>''I like the sensation,'' Lucian said. ''But love and art are the only serious things for me.''</p>
        <p>And so it is to this day. Long may it be so.</p>
        <p>Lucian Freud: Drawings 1940  Matthew Marks, 523 West 24th Street.  Through April 12.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
