<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coming Apart</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="475411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOFFMAN, ROY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHERNOFF, MAXINE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PLAIN GRIEF (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DD143BF931A1575AC0A967958260" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coming Apart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Roy Hoffman;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOFFMAN, ROY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PLAIN GRIEF</p>
        <p>By Maxine Chernoff. 222 pp. New York: Summit Books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PLAIN GRIEF</p>
        <p>By Maxine Chernoff. 222 pp. New York: Summit Books.</p>
        <p>To the skeptical eye of the contemporary American storyteller, holidays, with their expectations of warmth and closeness, frequently set the stage for disaster. One thinks, for example, of Barry Levinson's movie "Avalon," in which an immigrant family's Thanksgiving feast arouses a feud between brothers, or Sue Miller's novel "Family Pictures," in which Christmas morning finds a son cutting his foot on a broken ornament and being driven to the emergency room by his father.</p>
        <p>In her first novel, "Plain Grief," the poet and short-story writer Maxine Chernoff uses a disastrous Thanksgiving weekend as the means of exploring the shattering marriage of Sarah and Larry Holm and the anxiety of their teen-age daughter, Carrie.</p>
        <p>Just as the table is set for the holiday "when butter was spread liberally as housepaint, when thanks were given for the idea of families," Carrie runs away from home with her downbeat, more rebellious cousin, Deenie, who is visiting Chicago from her home in California. Moments later, Larry socks Sarah in the eye; she too flees the house, seeking consolation from her lover. So much for the comforts of chestnut stuffing and cranberries in orange sauce.</p>
        <p>The "idea of families" is at the center of this slowly evolving, thoroughly detailed novel. Judging by the story's opening fiasco, it is an idea, in Ms. Chernoff's view, that has seen sunnier days. The Holms' airless marriage could well have inspired an airless book, but Ms. Chernoff avoids this fate through the vigorousness of her writing. After all, what reader wants to bunk in for too many nights with depressed and quarrelsome people? Here, though, we are persuaded to do just that by the essential clarity of perception the author brings to the nuances of domestic struggle.</p>
        <p>In fact, Ms. Chernoff's literary verve is sometimes more winning than her characters themselves -- at least, the grown-ups. A reader may have limited sympathy for 39-year-old Sarah, who quickly finds renewal in the sensitivity and erotic heat of her lover, Jeremy Bone Shoulder, a better match for her anyway. Her husband, Larry, is clearly happiest when philandering with his art history students.</p>
        <p>But there are teen-agers here, and the pain of fractured homes impinges unrelievedly on their lives. Carrie, wearing "little pink socks with tartan-plaid cuffs and brand-new deck shoes," is left only with baby-sitting money and a rumbling stomach on the Greyhound bus headed for Los Angeles. She tries to act as tough as anorexic, green-haired Deenie, whose plans include fleeing to Costa Rica with her boyfriend. In a telling gesture, Carrie makes sure to call home from the road, leaving a message on the answering machine to let her parents and her younger brother know she's O.K.</p>
        <p>One wishes there were more of Carrie and Deenie. Not only do they make a colorful and sympathetic pair, but their story enables Ms. Chernoff to sketch a footloose America. They meet oddball tale spinners while on the bus or hitchhiking, and their escape turns into an escapade. Carrie's reflections, rightly so, are both acute and naive: "How would she make anyone believe the purplish night sky and the flood of jack rabbits that had poured across the road just in front of the bus headlights? She was seeing for the first time. Being with her parents had blurred her vision."</p>
        <p>Sarah, who takes up the bulk of the book, lapses often into memories -- episodes from her marriage, a trip to a petting zoo with her children, a bizarre incident on a family vacation. There are involved flashbacks to a grief therapy group she attended while mourning her father and where, as novelistic luck would have it, she met Jeremy, a Native American who told the group, a bit self-righteously, that he was "mourning the fate of his people."</p>
        <p>Ms. Chernoff labors to show the theme of loss that runs through the lives in this book, but casting so much of the story in flashback acts as a drag on the narrative. There are even a few reveries that take place while a character goes in or out of sleep, or watches another slumber. This first novel tests Ms. Chernoff's ability to keep scenes developing: in the stories in her well-received collection, "Bop," there was freer movement.</p>
        <p>But there is an emotional weight to this book, a gradual accrual of sadness that comes from so many people, isolated inside their own lives, still worrying about one another's needs. In the family's final reunion, these divisions have become irrevocably deep. "Plain Grief" may come together slowly, yet in doing so it leaves an unavoidable, and lingering, impact.</p>
        <p>Roy Hoffman, the author of the novel "Almost Family," has just completed a new novel, "Last Flight Home."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Roy Hoffman, the author of the novel "Almost Family," has just completed a new novel, "Last Flight Home."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
