<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Memories of Revolutions Distant and Near</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="475712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MOISEYEV DANCE CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNNING, JENNIFER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOISEYEV, IGOR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DD1E31F931A1575AC0A967958260" item-length="1169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Memories of Revolutions Distant and Near</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNNING, JENNIFER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The world-renowned Moiseyev Dance Company first glided out of the dark, mysterious Soviet Union and across the United States in 1958, in exactly the kind of stirring folk-dance program it will present when it comes to Radio City Music Hall for a three-week season beginning Tuesday.</p>
        <p>There will be several pieces new to American audiences, including "Tsam" ("Masks"), a story dance based on an ancient Mongolian legend, "Sirtaki" ("Greek Suite"), created at the request of the Greek composer Mikis Theodorakis, and "Tatarotchka," a humorous, athletic Tatar dance from Crimea. But the dances will be performed by a familiar contingent of pretty women and handsome men dressed in an array of colorful costumes, who will also dip obligingly into such beloved Moiseyev staples as "The Dance of the Buffoons," "Old City Quadrille," the high-flying "Gopak" and that unfailing show-stopper "Partisans."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The world-renowned Moiseyev Dance Company first glided out of the dark, mysterious Soviet Union and across the United States in 1958, in exactly the kind of stirring folk-dance program it will present when it comes to Radio City Music Hall for a three-week season beginning Tuesday.</p>
        <p>There will be several pieces new to American audiences, including "Tsam" ("Masks"), a story dance based on an ancient Mongolian legend, "Sirtaki" ("Greek Suite"), created at the request of the Greek composer Mikis Theodorakis, and "Tatarotchka," a humorous, athletic Tatar dance from Crimea. But the dances will be performed by a familiar contingent of pretty women and handsome men dressed in an array of colorful costumes, who will also dip obligingly into such beloved Moiseyev staples as "The Dance of the Buffoons," "Old City Quadrille," the high-flying "Gopak" and that unfailing show-stopper "Partisans."</p>
        <p>After eight national tours, the Moiseyev has become synonymous with folk dance to a good many Americans, who might be surprised to discover that there is actually a Mr. Moiseyev. He founded the company in 1937, returning to a childhood interest in folk arts when the cultural and political chaos of the time threatened his career as a Bolshoi Ballet dancer, choreographer and ballet master.</p>
        <p>In person, Igor Moiseyev is a comfortably dapper man who, at the age of 85, has the look of a shrewd but genial survivor. There is a grayness about him that recalls the faces of longtime Soviet political functionaries. After half a century of answering journalists' questions, Mr. Moiseyev has developed a repertory of small set pieces, resolutely delivered, about his company and his own life in dance.  But pressed about his work and his recollections of the Russian revolutions he has lived through, he begins to speak with a flinty passion edged with poignancy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moiseyev was a child studying ballet in Moscow when World War I broke out. "Then came the February Revolution, in 1917, and in the fall the Great October Revolution that brought our country and our people much despair and hardship," he said in a recent interview in New York, speaking through an interpreter. "And now, in essence, we have gone back to where we were prior to the first World War. We are at the beginning."</p>
        <p>He pleads memory lapses about those early days but smiles when asked about the recent coup attempt. "Amazingly enough, I get the same questions from Russian journalists," he said, "because I am a witness to the century."</p>
        <p>Mr. Moiseyev's memoir about life under Stalin was published in two installments in July in Literary Gazette, a prestigious Moscow cultural journal. "It was quite a hit," he said. "I talked about Stalin, Beria, and about those moments when I met them. We were often invited to dance in closed performances inside the Kremlin."</p>
        <p>At the time of the latest coup attempt, the Moiseyev troupe had just returned from a Greek tour and was not performing. "Walking the streets was normal," Mr. Moiseyev said of the atmosphere in Moscow during those days. "The frightening thing was that, all of a sudden, there was a situation that might take us back to Stalinist times, when everyone's lives hung by a string. An individual's fate could change because of the smallest, most petty infraction. It was enough just to talk to someone and say any little criticism, and your life would be destroyed.</p>
        <p>"So, when we heard the announcement that there had been a coup, I had the strong feeling that continuing to live had no point. To endure for a second time what we had endured for so long would be impossible. It was the most wonderful thing that we were able to avert this danger.</p>
        <p>"During the 54 years I directed the ensemble, I was asked to join the Communist Party at least 18 times. And not once did I agree," continued Mr. Moiseyev, whose work nonetheless passed Government scrutiny.</p>
        <p>"All of us, not only I, believed that something like this would happen, but we didn't know when or what form it would take. And we were all afraid that they would win. They had the power of the army. But apparently the soldiers did not want to repeat history. And every soldier had someone in the family who suffered under Stalin no less than we had suffered from Hitler's hand."</p>
        <p>It doesn't take an appreciation of Soviet history to enjoy the Moiseyev, now on an 11-city American tour. Why does a number like "Partisans," with its cloaked Nazi-fighters from the Caucasus region riding through the night on imaginary horses, never fail to rouse American audiences? Mr. Moiseyev has made the point, over the years, that what his company performs is not unadulterated folk dance but an art, much of it still created by him, that grows out of folk cultures.</p>
        <p>"I never photograph folklore," he said. "I re-create it. But my first rule is that the choreographer does not have the right to change the character of the folk culture. He must create a true and strong view of what the people are. Language -- folk language -- should be expressed correctly and properly. You cannot write Japanese in English."</p>
        <p>There has been a strong and distinctive bond, traditionally, between classical and folk elements in Russian ballet. "The Russian ballet was dependent on the folk and the classical," Mr. Moiseyev said. "If we were talking about real life, then the ballet depended on folk. When we were talking about fantasy, then the classical came into play. And this enhanced the classical ballet."</p>
        <p>In Mr. Moiseyev's youth, ballet students were also required to train in folk or character dance, as it is also called in ballet. "There was a great deal of emphasis on folk training in Moscow, though less in Leningrad," he said. His own dancers learn ballet as well as a wide variety of folk styles. "Classical dance is the grammar of physical movement," he said. "We cannot ignore the exercises of classical training. Thanks to that training, you can jump higher than any normal person, bend lower."</p>
        <p>That fertile crossover training, Mr. Moiseyev said, no longer exists in Russian ballet schools. "I get the feeling that if we requested the dancers in one of our ballet companies to do a Russian folk dance, they would not be able to. There is perhaps an error made by Russian choreographers, who are too far away from their Russian folklore and folklore in general."</p>
        <p>For Mr. Moiseyev, it is the balance between fantasy and reality, represented in that traditional training, that makes "Partisans" such a success. "Essentially, 'Partisans' is not folklore at all," Mr. Moiseyev said. "It is out of my imagination. But I used my imagination to create something that is characteristic of that area and people. The men are perceived as heroes, because they are perceived as real people, not dreamed up or artificial. And this is the strength of folk dance." Will the Moiseyev triumph yet another time in America? "It is much easier the first time," Mr. Moiseyev said wryly. "It is easier to be a lover than a husband."</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
