<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Already Lining Up Support for Zionism Move</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="475721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIDDLE EAST-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DA1730F931A1575AC0A967958260" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Already Lining Up Support for Zionism Move</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As President Bush considers calling for a repeal of the resolution equating Zionism and racism in his address here on Monday, American diplomats have already begun seeking support for such a move at the General Assembly session now under way, officials involved in the effort say. But they add that it is uncertain whether a repeal move would succeed.</p>
        <p>The 12 European Community countries told the United States they would support such an effort, but warned that securing a convincing repudiation of the resolution at the current session would be difficult and carried political risks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As President Bush considers calling for a repeal of the resolution equating Zionism and racism in his address here on Monday, American diplomats have already begun seeking support for such a move at the General Assembly session now under way, officials involved in the effort say. But they add that it is uncertain whether a repeal move would succeed.</p>
        <p>The 12 European Community countries told the United States they would support such an effort, but warned that securing a convincing repudiation of the resolution at the current session would be difficult and carried political risks.</p>
        <p>A repeal by any margin might help President Bush mend fences with Israel and its supporters in their dispute over housing loan guarantees. But many countries have warned the Administration that if it wishes to demonstrate that the United Nations as a whole has rejected the position it took in 1975, it would need to muster a substantial majority in favor of repeal. Officials have also warned that a repeal measure would run the risk of being watered down by amendments.</p>
        <p>But some lawyers argue that as the "Zionism is racism" resolution is one of the few that have never been reaffirmed or recapitulated by the General Assembly in subsequent votes, the organization has already shown that it no longer believes in it.</p>
        <p>The measure, one of the most controversial the Assembly has adopted, was passed on Nov. 19, 1975, as Resolution 3379, at the urging of Arab and other third-world countries with support from what was then the Soviet bloc.</p>
        <p>The resolution identified Zionism as "a form of racism and racial discrimination" and "most severely condemned" it as "a threat to world peace and security."</p>
        <p>That denunciation was supported by 72 members, with 35 opposed, 32 abstaining and 3 countries not taking part in the vote. The United States and all Western countries voted against it, as did a number of developing countries including the Bahamas, Honduras, the Ivory Coast and Uruguay.</p>
        <p>The resolution was adopted at a time when third-world members of the General Assembly, backed by the Soviet bloc, were taking an aggressive anti-Western stance, securing the adoption of numerous resolutions critical of Western political and economic beliefs and practices.</p>
        <p>Diplomats argue that the collapse of Communism and the more moderate and chastened attitude taken by most developing countries these days is an important reason for pushing for repeal now.</p>
        <p>Another is that Israel recently scored a significant political victory at the United Nations when the 54-member Economic and Social Council, representing a cross section of the world's countries, voted overwhelmingly to admit it to the Economic Commission for Europe.  Israel Gaining Support</p>
        <p>To the surprise of many Western observers, only the Arab members of the Economic and Social Council voted against Israel, which appled to join the European commission because the Arabs had already refused to admit it to the Economic Commission for Western Asia. Geographically Israel belongs on the Western Asian panel, but the panel's Arab majority has kept it out.</p>
        <p>The recent vote was seen by some diplomats as a sign that many developing countries were no longer prepared to vote against Israel on principle and a warning to the Arabs they might find themselves embarrassingly isolated if they opposed repeal of Resolution 3379.</p>
        <p>Just how the United States might try to repeal the resolution is also a matter of debate within the Bush Administration, officials say.</p>
        <p>A new resolution rescinding or canceling the Assembly's assertion that Zionism is racism would run the risk of being amended in ways that weakened its impact. An alternative approach would be to reintroduce the original resolution equating Zionism and racism and ask the General Assembly to vote it down. But while few countries would vote for such a resolution today, to be convincing this tactic would require a huge no vote and not simply a large body of abstentions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
