<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Stocks End Steady Amid Inflation Anxiety</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="690995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DF113BF931A35755C0A962958260" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Stocks End Steady Amid Inflation Anxiety</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks dropped sharply in Europe overnight and on Wall Street in the morning yesterday, but United States stocks recovered strongly by the closing gavel as an unusual and confusing confluence of inflation anxieties swept through American, European and Japanese stock and bond markets.</p>
        <p>What is unquestionably clear is that international stock traders are becoming increasingly worried. Like their counterparts in America, they seem to growing more concerned about inflation because of the convergence of an ebullient American economy, a surprisingly resurgent Europe and a recession-racked Japan that seems to be showing unexpected strength.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks dropped sharply in Europe overnight and on Wall Street in the morning yesterday, but United States stocks recovered strongly by the closing gavel as an unusual and confusing confluence of inflation anxieties swept through American, European and Japanese stock and bond markets.</p>
        <p>What is unquestionably clear is that international stock traders are becoming increasingly worried. Like their counterparts in America, they seem to growing more concerned about inflation because of the convergence of an ebullient American economy, a surprisingly resurgent Europe and a recession-racked Japan that seems to be showing unexpected strength.</p>
        <p>The Financial Times 100 index in London dropped 1.3 percent, and the French CAC-40 index fell 2.47 percent; the German DAX index rose slightly, up .09 percent.</p>
        <p>Even Japan, locked in a three-year recession, saw bond yields soar, but without setting records, after better-than-expected industrial production figures surprised analysts. The Nikkei index of 225 issues rose slightly, up 0.38 percent. Deadlock for the Dow</p>
        <p>In the end, however, deadlock was the word, at least for now. The major American stock indexes barely moved. After falling more than 26 points shortly after 10 A.M., the Dow Jones industrial average zigzagged the rest of the day before recovering to 3,760.83, up 2.46 points.</p>
        <p>The other indexes wandered, too, before ending barely higher. After falling more than 2.50 points, the broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500 rose 1.12 points, to 457.63. The Nasdaq composite index fell as much as 4.50 points before recovering to 735.52, up 0.33 point.</p>
        <p>Blue chips like International Paper and Chevron rose on no immediate news. Semiconductor companies like Intel and big banks like Citicorp also rose on no immediate news. But U S Surgical gained 2 3/4, to 21 3/4, on takeover speculation, and IDB Communications fell 7 3/8, 7 1/8, over a dispute with its auditors. IDB Communications was the most active stock yesterday as 32.5 million of its shares changed hands.</p>
        <p>Volume on the New York Stock Exchange was near normal at 278.5 million shares, about 7 percent below this year's average of 300 million shares. The near-normal day followed six consecutive sessions of below-average trading volume. 'It Just Got Worse'</p>
        <p>As in recent months, a falling bond market has been driving down the stock market. "We walked in this morning and found most of the European bond markets down and then it just got worse," said Chris Madell, head of Government bond trading at First Chicago Capital Markets.</p>
        <p>In the end, bonds recovered, too. The yield on the benchmark 30-year Treasury bond fell to 7.39 percent from 7.43 percent the day before.</p>
        <p>For the American side of the markets, the immediate downdraft for stocks and bonds came from a closely watched index that implied that United States factory activity, and possibly inflation, was still growing.</p>
        <p>The National Association of Purchasing Management index was unchanged in May but showed the economy expanding for the ninth straight month, despite recent economic data that suggested the possibility of a slowdown.</p>
        <p>But at the same time traders noticed that the daily Commodity Research Bureau index was falling convincingly throughout the day on weakness in futures contracts for silver, coffee, lumber and live cattle. The index had been sparking inflation concerns recently as it rose in response to fears about a possible drought involving soybeans and other agricultural products.</p>
        <p>As American traders struggled with these conflicting reports, European and Japanese bond markets were trading sharply down on inflation concerns. Germany, Europe's largest economy, appeared to be rising out of recession faster than analysts expected, with industrial production up 4.1 percent from a year earlier.</p>
        <p>But a rare public disagreement by members of the policy council of the Bundesbank confused traders about the central bank's inflation-fighting strategy. German bond yields soared to a 17-month high. German Money Supply</p>
        <p>"The story I heard was that there was also increasing concern about German money-supply growth, which has been pretty high," Fred Leiner, fixed-income market strategist at Continental Bank, said. That would mean that the Bundesbank would hesitate to cut German interest rates further, maintaining downward pressure on United States bonds and the dollar.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
