<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Hopes, Budget Eludes Lawmakers</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="691016"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, IAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2DE113BF931A35755C0A962958260" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Hopes, Budget Eludes Lawmakers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISHER, IAN</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York State's $33 billion budget is now two months late, and despite a week of close calls and optimistic smiles, no one could say today exactly how close the Governor and legislative leaders here were to finally striking a deal.</p>
        <p>Though the budget fight is now the second longest in more than a decade, it is unclear what impact the delay has had on cities, towns and school districts that depend on state aid. Thanks to $5.5 billion in emergency appropriations from the Legislature over the last two weeks, there has apparently been little borrowing and few layoffs or delays in public projects or in meeting payrolls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York State's $33 billion budget is now two months late, and despite a week of close calls and optimistic smiles, no one could say today exactly how close the Governor and legislative leaders here were to finally striking a deal.</p>
        <p>Though the budget fight is now the second longest in more than a decade, it is unclear what impact the delay has had on cities, towns and school districts that depend on state aid. Thanks to $5.5 billion in emergency appropriations from the Legislature over the last two weeks, there has apparently been little borrowing and few layoffs or delays in public projects or in meeting payrolls.</p>
        <p>But New York City has felt a cash crunch that led officials to temporarily suspend payments to its thousands of vendors, which provide goods and services ranging from pencils to drug treatment. It has also delayed payment of $100 million to the city workers' pension fund, and the city may face another shortfall in the next week if the state budget is not passed.</p>
        <p>Across the state, localities and school districts have been forced to draft their own budgets without knowing how much the state will ultimately provide. Education officials said today that uncertainty has in part led voters this year to reject a greater number of school budgets, which depend on state aid for an average of 40 percent of their funds.  'The Upside'</p>
        <p>On the other hand, while the final details have not been settled, this year's state budget -- in an election year with a surplus as high as $1.5 billion -- is expected to include more money for schools, localities and spending programs than any state budget in the last five years.</p>
        <p>"The upside of this is that this promises to be the best state aid package that schools have experienced in quite a number of years," said James J. O'Connell, executive director of the New York State Council of School Superintendents. "But we still don't know what it is."</p>
        <p>Since the legal deadline passed on April 1, budget negotiations have often progressed at the pace of weary men sipping iced tea on the veranda. But last week talks among Gov. Mario M. Cuomo; Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, Democrat of Manhattan, and the State Senate majority leader, Ralph J. Marino, Republican of Oyster Bay -- picked up and all sides say their differences have now narrowed substantially.</p>
        <p>The broad outlines have been settled for nearly a month. Barring last-minute collapse, the final version seems certain to include roughly $410 million in tax cuts, mostly for businesses; more aid to schools and localities, including money to close New York City's budget gap; an expanded program for fingerprinting welfare recipients, and projects around the state aimed in part at helping incumbents keep constituents satisfied.</p>
        <p>Though the leaders seemed on the verge of a deal last week, the momentum has slowed again and it is uncertain when the pieces will fall into place. All three sides have been pointing fingers of blame for this latest delay, and all agreed that while nearly every issue had been settled, any stray detail could pull their tentative agreements apart.  Outstanding Issues</p>
        <p>The major outstanding issues, according to aides on all sides, are a final agreement on spending cuts, which counties will be included in the fingerprinting program, and the details of a debt reform package Mr. Cuomo has emphasized over the last week. A similar package, which would restrict how the state can borrow money, was passed last year.</p>
        <p>"We are very close now," said Anne W. Crowley, Mr. Cuomo's spokeswoman. "This could close down very quickly."</p>
        <p>The impact of the late budget, which this week caused a minor delay in checks reaching some state workers, has been softened by the emergency appropriations. On Tuesday, the Legislature approved $1.5 billion for a major school aid payment that was due today and lawmakers have approved payments for welfare, transportation and medical costs, as well as $660 million to New York City.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
