<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>KREMLIN HITS BACK AT YELTSIN DEMAND</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="425043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGISLATURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIAN SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLIC (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FEIN, ESTHER B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">YELTSIN, BORIS N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D9123CF932A15751C0A967958260" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>KREMLIN HITS BACK AT YELTSIN DEMAND</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ESTHER B. FEIN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FEIN, ESTHER B</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Feb. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Kremlin began a full-scale attack against Boris N. Yeltsin today, devoting television programs, front-page articles and press-agency dispatches to denunciations of the Russian leader's call for the resignation of President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>Breaking with the recent practice of showing only delayed broadcasts of Supreme Soviet sessions, national television broadcast live, midday coverage of repeated condemnations of Mr. Yeltsin, who demanded in a nationwide television appearance Tuesday that Mr. Gorbachev step down for deceiving the country and bringing it "to dictatorship."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Kremlin began a full-scale attack against Boris N. Yeltsin today, devoting television programs, front-page articles and press-agency dispatches to denunciations of the Russian leader's call for the resignation of President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>Breaking with the recent practice of showing only delayed broadcasts of Supreme Soviet sessions, national television broadcast live, midday coverage of repeated condemnations of Mr. Yeltsin, who demanded in a nationwide television appearance Tuesday that Mr. Gorbachev step down for deceiving the country and bringing it "to dictatorship."</p>
        <p>The Parliament voted overwhelmingly to censure Mr. Yeltsin, as 292 representatives approved a resolution saying that his remarks violated the Soviet Constitution and created "an extreme situation in the country." Twenty-nine legislators voted against the measure and 27 abstained.</p>
        <p>The resolution declared support for Mr. Gorbachev, but also called on him to address the Soviet people directly.</p>
        <p>One after another, lawmakers stepped to the microphone to lambaste Mr. Yeltsin, whose televised appeal was his bluntest challenge yet to the Soviet President. The legislators' statements were a response not only to Mr. Yeltsin's comments on Tuesday, but to the growing rivalry and confrontation between him and Mr. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>Since his election as president of the vast Russian federated republic, Mr. Yeltsin has been fighting for greater independence for the republic politically and economically.  State of Emergency Suggested</p>
        <p>"Yesterday's statement by Yeltsin was tantamount to a declaration of civil war," said Anatoly G. Chekhoyev, a leading member of the conservative Soyuz faction from the region of South Ossetia. "When the union is disintegrating, the time has come to talk about a state of emergency throughout the country."</p>
        <p>Another hard-line legislator, Yuri K. Sharipov, described Mr. Yeltsin's comments as "a call to a coup," and he said of the Russian President that "when a person has many problems, he himself becomes a problem."</p>
        <p>The official propaganda fusillade began in this morning's Pravda, which reproved Mr. Yeltsin for denouncing Mr. Gorbachev's attempts to restructure the Soviet economy without having "a formidable, alternate program of his own to offer."</p>
        <p>The front-page article accused him of "resorting to all possible means in order to pursue his own personal ambitions and pretensions, which are a far cry from the goals of democratization, from the renewal of our society, from perestroika."</p>
        <p>A conciliatory plea was made by the former Soviet Foreign Minister, Eduard A. Shevardnadze, who resigned in December warning that the country faced an approaching dictatorship. He said today:</p>
        <p>"We must end this war of Parliaments, this war of laws and this war of Presidents. We must find a path to constructive dialogue. It seems to me that tomorrow -- better even today -- the two Presidents, Gorbachev and Yeltsin, should meet and discuss all the existing problems." Rebuke in Prime Time</p>
        <p>The main evening news program Vremya devoted the first 17 minutes of its broadcast to anti-Yeltsin features, a use of time usually reserved for only the most critical news events. It used the occasion of the signing of an economic agreement between the republics of Kazakhstan and the Ukraine for further criticism of the Russian leader.</p>
        <p>The Ukrainian President, Leonid M. Kravchuk, said Mr. Yeltsin's speech was "hasty, ill-considered and irresponsible" and "might be used for the further destabilization of the country."</p>
        <p>The program also showed a congress of the heads of Soviet industries, who issued a statement rebuking Mr. Yeltsin.</p>
        <p>But while official voices railed against the Russian chief, some people on the streets rallied behind him.</p>
        <p>"If Gorbachev doubts what Yeltsin says is true, let him come into this very store and show me where the better future he promised us is," said Nadya Luchenok, as she stood in a cheerless dairy store here with dozens of other disgruntled people waiting for a promised delivery of margarine.</p>
        <p>Fatima Prudnikova, a 53-year-old factory worker from the Russian city of Kazan, waiting today in the capital for a train home, said: "Everything Yeltsin said is absolutely, without a doubt, the truth. But it is not only Gorbachev who deceived us. We deceived ourselves by being fool enough to ever believe him that he would change our lives. It's time for somebody else to have a chance."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
