<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parcells Promotes 3 Aides and Hires 2 Others</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="425131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COACHES AND MANAGERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LITSKY, FRANK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDB1131F932A15751C0A967958260" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parcells Promotes 3 Aides and Hires 2 Others</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LITSKY, FRANK</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Feb. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three weeks after the Giants won Super Bowl XXV, they realigned their coaching staff today by promoting three assistants and adding two. In so doing, they kept Ray Handley and Al Groh, who had been reported leaving, by making them coordinators.</p>
        <p>Ron Erhardt, the offensive coordinator for nine seasons, was promoted to assistant head coach. At a news conference at Giants Stadium, Bill Parcells, the head coach, said Erhardt would remain active in the offense and would also help with the defense and special teams. Before Erhardt joined the Giants, he was the head coach of the New England Patriots for three seasons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three weeks after the Giants won Super Bowl XXV, they realigned their coaching staff today by promoting three assistants and adding two. In so doing, they kept Ray Handley and Al Groh, who had been reported leaving, by making them coordinators.</p>
        <p>Ron Erhardt, the offensive coordinator for nine seasons, was promoted to assistant head coach. At a news conference at Giants Stadium, Bill Parcells, the head coach, said Erhardt would remain active in the offense and would also help with the defense and special teams. Before Erhardt joined the Giants, he was the head coach of the New England Patriots for three seasons.</p>
        <p>Handley will replace Erhardt as offensive coordinator. He will continue to coach the running backs, which he has done for seven years. Before that, he was associate head coach at Stanford. Groh Replaces Belichick</p>
        <p>Groh will become the Giants' defensive coordinator, replacing Bill Belichick, the newly named head coach of the Cleveland Browns. Groh will continue to coach the linebackers, which he has done in his two seasons with the Giants. He was the head coach at Wake Forest from 1981 to 1986 and the defensive coordinator at Virginia, North Carolina, the Air Force Academy and Texas Tech.</p>
        <p>Handley had previously announced that he would leave coaching to enter George Washington University Law School. Belichick was said to have been interested in hiring Groh as the Browns' defensive coordinator.</p>
        <p>Handley and Groh are 46 years old. Erhardt will become 59 next Wednesday. Looking for 'New Blood'</p>
        <p>Parcells said he did not necessarily promote Handley and Groh to keep them. And he dismissed a suggestion that Erhardt was being kicked upstairs.</p>
        <p>"I wanted to inject new blood," Parcells said, "to get things in place to keep the status quo for some time. Ron isn't getting any younger, and at some point he's going to decide he's not going to coach. "I want Ron Erhardt to be with me as long as I coach."</p>
        <p>In 1979, when Parcells spent one year as the head coach at the Air Force Academy, he hired Groh as his defensive coordinator.</p>
        <p>"I knew that Bill Belichick at some time would have an opportunity to move on," Parcells said, "so when we got Al two years ago I had this in mind."</p>
        <p>Parcells also hired Jim Fassel as quarterback coach and Fred Bruney as defensive backfield coach. Last season, Erhardt coached the Giants' quarterbacks and Belichick, in addition to his duties as defensive coordinator, coached the defensive backs.</p>
        <p>Fassel is 41. In five seasons (1985-89) as Utah's head coach, his teams compiled a25-33 record, including 4-8 in 1989. He did not coach last year. At Stanford (1978-83), where he worked with Handley, he coached John Elway.</p>
        <p>Bruney is 59. He was a pro cornerback from 1953 to 1962 and has been a pro coach since. Last season, he was assistant head coach and defensive coordinator for the Tampa Bay Buccaneers. Parcells said he wanted an experienced coach for the secondary to take a burden off Groh.</p>
        <p>The Giants are still one man short because Tom Coughlin, their wide receivers coach for three years, has become the head coach at Boston College. Parcells said he hoped to name a successor by Friday.</p>
        <p>Except for Belichick and Coughlin, the assistant coaches have just signed two-year contracts.</p>
        <p>Parcells, in the final year of his contract, will be back this year too. His future is unsettled. More Surgery for Bavaro</p>
        <p>Mark Bavaro, the Giants' starting tight end, who underwent reconstructive knee surgery in January 1990, will have another operation on the knee. Eric Dorsey, the defensive end, underwent arthroscopic knee surgery.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
