<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Training Against Pollution Crimes</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="634009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLORIO, JAMES J (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOOLEN, TOM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MADONNA, STEVEN J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D6133DF931A2575AC0A965958260" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Training Against Pollution Crimes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM TOOLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TOOLEN, TOM</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE driver pulled his tank truck into the deserted park, backed to the edge of the river and opened a spigot at the rear of the vehicle to unleash a stream of slimy green liquid. Within minutes, state police officers converged on the truck by car and boat to arrest the driver for polluting the Delaware River with chemicals.</p>
        <p>It all looked real enough, but in this case the officers were acting out a scene for a videotape that will be used to train the state's police officers to spot and respond to environmental crimes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE driver pulled his tank truck into the deserted park, backed to the edge of the river and opened a spigot at the rear of the vehicle to unleash a stream of slimy green liquid. Within minutes, state police officers converged on the truck by car and boat to arrest the driver for polluting the Delaware River with chemicals.</p>
        <p>It all looked real enough, but in this case the officers were acting out a scene for a videotape that will be used to train the state's police officers to spot and respond to environmental crimes.</p>
        <p>The training tape will become part of the curriculum at New Jersey's 21 police academies and the State Police Academy in Sea Girt. Eventually, it will be shown to all 3,300 of the state's state, city and county law-enforcement officers.</p>
        <p>The environmental classes, which will involve about 10 training tapes, will begin next month at Sea Girt.</p>
        <p>Environmental crimes have become a top priority for Gov. Jim Florio, who appointed Steven Madonna to be State Environmental Prosecutor, the point man to deal with pollution in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>After watching the filming at the Delaware River on a recent morning, Mr. Madonna said, "The new training for police officers will give us eyes out there on the street 24 hours a day, and it won't cost the state anything extra, because the officers are on patrol, anyway."</p>
        <p>Mr. Madonna said that New Jersey was the first state to undertake an environmental-crime training program for police officers and that other states were now copying it.</p>
        <p>"In previous years, the officers across the state were not sure how to deal with pollution," Mr. Madonna said. "Now they will know."</p>
        <p>Governor Florio, who has made environmental initiatives an issue in his re-election campaign, said the training program would "add a strong green shield to the thin blue line that we talk about all the time."  Oil Drums and Medical Waste</p>
        <p>The training tapes, about two hours' worth in all, cover an assortment of pollution cases that officers might encounter, like oil drums left scattered along the side of a road or medical waste discarded in a landfill. The tapes will be incorporated into the curriculum for police recruits, and all officers in the state will be required eventually to attend the courses.</p>
        <p>Sgt. Edward Thornton of the state police, who narrates the training tapes, said the added curriculum would offer needed guidance to officers who "may have on occasion observed acts of illegal discharges of waste or pollution, but weren't sure how to deal with the situation."</p>
        <p>In one videotape, Sergeant Thornton tells the recruits: "We make a stop of automobiles for routine traffic violations and observe narcotics or weapons, and we recognize the presence of a crime and take appropriate action. You are learning to recognize a different type of criminal activity related to the environment."</p>
        <p>The State Police Chiefs Association recently voted to endorse and support the antipollution training. Chief Joseph Batten of Berlin Township, the former head of the association, called the new effort "very promising" and predicted that it would provide a more efficient link between state and local environmental enforcement efforts. Crucial Link in Chain</p>
        <p>Local police departments have selected experienced officers to act as liaisons with the state in deterring environmental crime. With only several hours of training, Mr. Madonna said, these local officers can become a crucial link in the environmental protection chain.</p>
        <p>He said there had already have been dozens of instances of local police officers' helping to track down polluters by notifying state environmental authorities.</p>
        <p>As an example, he mentioned the case of a southern New Jersey man caught pouring large quantities of gasoline down a sewer drain, which could have exploded. The officer notified the state liaison, and within a short time agents from the Division of Criminal Justice and the Department of Environmental Protection and Energy arrived and arrested the polluter.</p>
        <p>"He received a very heavy fine," Mr. Madonna said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
