<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Treasury Bonds Show An Upturn</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="698992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER
PRICE INDEX</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TREASURY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0DC1E3BF930A25754C0A962958260" item-length="554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Treasury Bonds Show An Upturn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Bloomberg Business News</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Treasury bonds rose for the first time in a week yesterday as a Government report surprised investors with the news that inflation was nonexistent in June.</p>
        <p>The benchmark 30-year bond rose 13/32 , or $4.06 for each $1,000 bond, to yield 7.68 percent, four basis points lower than Monday. A basis point is one-hundredth of a percentage point. Bonds gained as much as 3/4 point after the inflation report.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Treasury bonds rose for the first time in a week yesterday as a Government report surprised investors with the news that inflation was nonexistent in June.</p>
        <p>The benchmark 30-year bond rose 13/32 , or $4.06 for each $1,000 bond, to yield 7.68 percent, four basis points lower than Monday. A basis point is one-hundredth of a percentage point. Bonds gained as much as 3/4 point after the inflation report.</p>
        <p>While there is now less pressure for the Federal Reserve to raise interest rates to contain inflation, many traders are concerned the falling dollar will discourage foreign investors from buying dollar-denominated assets such as bonds, limiting the market's advance.</p>
        <p>Earlier yesterday, the Labor Department said prices paid to producers in June were unchanged for the third month. Economists surveyed by Bloomberg Business News had predicted an increase of three-tenths of 1 percent for the month.</p>
        <p>Federal Reserve officials are "breathing a sigh of relief," said Alan McClymonds, a trader at CS First Boston, who added that he did not think the central bank's officials wanted to raise rates. "They're looking for a reason not to," he said. Producer Prices Report</p>
        <p>The producer prices report is the first of four important reports on the economy scheduled for release this week. The June Consumer Price Index is due today, and tomorrow the Government is scheduled to release its report on June retail sales.</p>
        <p>The bond market's initial rally was reversed as the dollar tumbled to a post-World War II low against the Japanese yen. As the dollar recovered, the bond market advanced.</p>
        <p>The two-year note yield was 6.21 percent, down from 6.25 percent. The bond's yield was 6.3 percent when the Federal Reserve began raising rates Feb. 4. The record low yield is 5.77 percent, set on Oct. 15.</p>
        <p>As benign as the inflation report was, it was not enough to convince some bond investors, said Mr. McClymonds at CS First Boston. "We still go back to the reality of a weak dollar and the potential inflation pressures in the future," he said.</p>
        <p>The crumbling dollar makes it riskier to bet on which direction bonds will take, even in the face of economic reports that signal inflation is under control, said Steven Van Order, who helps manage $3.5 billion in fixed-income securities at Calvert Asset Management in Bethesda, Md.</p>
        <p>"If the dollar stays weak and people keep hiding from the 30-year bond, we could hit 8 percent by August," Mr. Van Order said. "It's the kind of summer that makes it difficult to take a vacation. It even makes it difficult to go down the hall to see someone." Even though the economy grew 3.4 percent in the first quarter and 7 percent in the last quarter of 1993, the Government's inflation statistics show little sign of rising prices, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Inflation "doesn't necessarily have to show up, because there's a lot of competitiveness out there" between businesses, said Kevin Flanagan, an economist at Dean Witter Reynolds. "Consumers are balking at higher prices."</p>
        <p>In another price report yesterday, the Federal Reserve Bank of Atlanta said its index of business activity rose to 18.1 in June, from 16.1 in May. Raw material prices paid fell to 29.4, from 33.6 in May, and the Atlanta Fed's index of prices received dropped to 4.5 last month, from 14.4 in May.  CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
