<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Open to All Music and Unafraid to Serve a Smorgasbord</title>
    <meta content="10MOSH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1052774"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ROCK REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Plastilina Mosh (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spooky, D J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE0D7103BF933A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="541" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Open to All Music and Unafraid to Serve a Smorgasbord</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles reviews performance by D J Spooky and Plastilina Mosh at Irving Plaza (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was genre-splicing night when D.J. Spooky and Plastilina Mosh performed at Irving Plaza on Monday night. D.J. Spooky lives in New York City; Plastilina Mosh got started in Monterrey, Mexico. But they'd rather be known as information-age world citizens, with access to all kinds of music and the nerve to mix them at whim.</p>
        <p>While television monitors showed random images, D.J. Spooky plucked a riff on upright bass while an Iranian singer, an Indian tabla player, a Swiss drummer, an Israeli keyboardist and an American disk jockey all traded phrases and bounced around syncopations. ''D.J.'s are remixing the whole planet,'' proclaimed D.J. Spooky, whose original name was Paul Miller. ''Multicultural futuristic.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was genre-splicing night when D.J. Spooky and Plastilina Mosh performed at Irving Plaza on Monday night. D.J. Spooky lives in New York City; Plastilina Mosh got started in Monterrey, Mexico. But they'd rather be known as information-age world citizens, with access to all kinds of music and the nerve to mix them at whim.</p>
        <p>While television monitors showed random images, D.J. Spooky plucked a riff on upright bass while an Iranian singer, an Indian tabla player, a Swiss drummer, an Israeli keyboardist and an American disk jockey all traded phrases and bounced around syncopations. ''D.J.'s are remixing the whole planet,'' proclaimed D.J. Spooky, whose original name was Paul Miller. ''Multicultural futuristic.''</p>
        <p>The capacity is there; the question is what to do with it. D.J. Spooky used his eclecticism for texture, momentum, coalition-building and ancestor worship. He set featured guest after guest and quoted music from John Cage, Jimi Hendrix, K.R.S.-1 and Pauline Oliveros. In contrast to Spooky's New York earnestness, Plastilina Mosh had a West Coast flippancy akin to Beck. It aimed for humor, hipster cachet and a sly subversion of consumer culture on both sides of the Mexican border. Its single, a Southern-rock stomp called ''Monster Truck,'' boasts, ''I can destroy you.''</p>
        <p>Both groups are making a sometimes awkward transition from recording studio to stage. Plastilina Mosh -- the duo of Alejandro Rosso on keyboards and Jonas on guitar, joined by a disk jockey, Gerardo Akira Honda Hatadi, and Luis Eduardo Flores Valdez on bass -- worked through songs from its album, ''Aquamosh'' (Capitol). It jumped from vintage funk to lounge jazz to near-industrial rock, lacing most songs with hip-hop drumbeats and raps in English and Spanish: ''It's la revolucion/Let's do it again,'' Jonas chanted.</p>
        <p>The harder the beat, the better the song. The set dragged when Plastilina Mosh lingered in lounge territory, although Mr. Rosso proved he knows his jazz harmonies. Still, Plastilina Mosh put across its determination to have fun while it annexes whatever it wants from the United States, tacky or not.</p>
        <p>Plastilina Mosh's set was a model of pacing compared to the D.J. Spooky set that followed it. The first part explored extremes: from ominous, nearly motionless ambient music to eerie Miles Davis-style funk (with Dan Yashiv's sparse keyboard lines) to hurtling jungle rhythms. In fast stretches, the band rode Jojo Mayer's indefatigable drumming, bridging jungle's doubletime sputtering and the quick articulations of Karsh Kale's tabla drumming, while D.J. Wiz scratched chirping sounds from his turntables. Sussan Deyhim sang like Iran's answer to Diamanda Galas, moving between Middle Eastern-sounding phrases and abstract ululations. The music sounded both tense and exhilarated, the classic urban combination.</p>
        <p>But then the set became a kind of talent show, as D.J. Spooky brought on guest instrumentalists and rappers of widely varying abilities while the audience trickled away. On his recordings, D.J. Spooky understands that timing is everything, but he didn't bring the same discipline to the live musicians. It was as if he had too many friends, all digressing in the same Internet chat room.</p>
        <p>ROCK REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
