<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Robbers' Bullets Take an Immigrant's Family</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="801064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBBERIES AND THEFTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOSSITER, ADAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BATISTA, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BATISTA, MARIAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BATISTA, ARELIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BATISTA, WILLIAM JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3DA1139F932A15753C1A963958260" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Robbers' Bullets Take an Immigrant's Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NOSSITER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NOSSITER, ADAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For some 20 years, William Batista had struggled to shield his family from Harlem's everyday dangers, working the night shift at a midtown Manhattan hotel  and setting aside his earnings at home, for safekeeping. Early yesterday morning, he returned home from work to find the horror he had never foreseen: his wife and teen-age son were lying face down in the master bedroom, both shot  once in the head. His daughter, whom he discovered in her room, had also been shot in the head.</p>
        <p>The ground-floor apartment, in a well-kept brick building on West 152d Street near Riverside Drive, had been ransacked, said the Rev. Robert Ritchie, the family priest, who came later to anoint the bodies. Drawers had been pulled out  everywhere. "The worst situation I've ever seen," he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For some 20 years, William Batista had struggled to shield his family from Harlem's everyday dangers, working the night shift at a midtown Manhattan hotel  and setting aside his earnings at home, for safekeeping. Early yesterday morning, he returned home from work to find the horror he had never foreseen: his wife and teen-age son were lying face down in the master bedroom, both shot  once in the head. His daughter, whom he discovered in her room, had also been shot in the head.</p>
        <p>The ground-floor apartment, in a well-kept brick building on West 152d Street near Riverside Drive, had been ransacked, said the Rev. Robert Ritchie, the family priest, who came later to anoint the bodies. Drawers had been pulled out  everywhere. "The worst situation I've ever seen," he said.</p>
        <p>The police said money was missing but would not say how much. Mr. Batista, a native of the Dominican Republic, told them he didn't trust banks and kept as much as $20,000 at home. A police official who spoke on the condition of anonymity said that the motive appeared to be robbery and that there were no suspects.</p>
        <p>To relatives and neighbors, who spoke warmly of the close-knit, religious family, the reason for the killings seemed clear: someone had found out about the money Mr. Batista, 40, had saved up from his long hours sweeping outside the Drake Hotel on Park Avenue and bringing towels and linens to the chambermaids. "My uncle had money in the house," said Sonia Rodriguez, 20. "Probably someone knew. He doesn't put money in the bank. He doesn't trust the bank."</p>
        <p>Like others, she said the Batista children, William, 15, and Arelis, 18, had  steered clear of the neighborhood's darker temptations. "They're very religious," she said. "The only place they go out is to go to church."</p>
        <p>The police said they do not consider the husband a suspect in the case. "They appear to be legit," a detective who insisted on anonymity said of the family. Of Mr. Batista, he said: "He's obviously a hard-working individual."</p>
        <p>Several neighbors described the solid, six-story apartment building where they lived, at 631 West 152d Street, as a relative haven in the neighborhood. While drug sales at the corner, at Broadway, are common, they said, the building itself seemed free of them. No graffiti scars the building, the outside doors are always locked and neighbors keep inside doors open in the summer.</p>
        <p>"Our building, to me, is a clean building," Felicia Moria said.</p>
        <p>Neighbors said that Mr. Batista devoted all his energies to his family. He often telephoned St. Catherine of Genoa School, a grammar school, to make sure William was in class. When his daughter, a senior at Mother Cabrini High School  in Washington Heights, was a student at St. Catherine, he would visit her there  during recess.</p>
        <p>"He's a very hard-working man," said Father Ritchie, who said he had known the Batista children almost all their lives. "He spent all his time doing things to make himself better for his family." Mr. Batista, he added, was also attending school in his off hours.</p>
        <p>"He loved his family very much," said Alfonso Tynes, 64, a fellow employee at the Drake Hotel. "That was his heart."</p>
        <p>The young William had been an altar boy and sacristan, Father Ritchie's pride at St. Catherine of Genoa Church, on West 153d Street. Arelis Batista, who was passionate about her new computer, was planning on attending college soon. Father Richie remembered how William helped out at the church. "Every Sunday he  would set up everything for the Masses," he said. "He was very proud of the fact that he was picked to work at the church. He was one of the most warm and loving 15-year-olds you could find."</p>
        <p>He loved basketball and had a "wonderful sense of humor," said his sixth-grade teacher, Dennis Figueroa, whom the youth delighted in calling Mr. Fig.</p>
        <p>The consensus among neighbors was much the same. "Those kids got along with everybody," Alex Rodriguez, 20, said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Batista was less outgoing than her brother, proud of her new class ring and focused on keeping a promise she had made in 1991 to attend the senior prom  with a certain friend.</p>
        <p>Mr. Batista's wife, Marian, 41, frequently picked her children up at the end  of the day. "She was very interested in her children," said the priest. "She was on the street every day when they finished school."</p>
        <p>Yesterday morning, Father Ritchie's phone began ringing. Neighbors were calling to tell him the news.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
