<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Salomon Earnings Declined From 3d Quarter to the 4th</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="825079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY REPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SALOMON INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEAN WITTER, DISCOVER &amp; CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SALOMON BROTHERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STROM, STEPHANIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAUGHAN, DERYCK C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3DC1F39F937A15752C0A960958260" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Salomon Earnings Declined From 3d Quarter to the 4th</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STROM, STEPHANIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Salomon Inc., the parent of Salomon Brothers, the beleaguered investment bank, reported a steep decline in profits yesterday from the third to the fourth quarter of last year.</p>
        <p>Investors responded to the decline, largely attributable to the investment bank, by sending the parent company's stock down 87.5 cents, or 2.3 percent, to close at $36.625.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Salomon Inc., the parent of Salomon Brothers, the beleaguered investment bank, reported a steep decline in profits yesterday from the third to the fourth quarter of last year.</p>
        <p>Investors responded to the decline, largely attributable to the investment bank, by sending the parent company's stock down 87.5 cents, or 2.3 percent, to close at $36.625.</p>
        <p>Salomon's stock declined even though the company's earnings of $168 million, or $1.42 a share, in the fourth quarter reversed a loss of $157 million in the corresponding period of 1994.</p>
        <p>But analysts and investors consider quarter-to-quarter changes a better gauge of a securities firm's performance, because markets can change dramatically from year to year.</p>
        <p>The slide in earnings, from $268 million in the third quarter, also renewed speculation about how much longer Deryck C. Maughan will continue as chairman and chief executive of Salomon Brothers. "I've spoken to at least 18 investors about Salomon," said Perrin H. Long Jr., a securities industry analyst at Brown  Brothers Harriman &amp; Company, "and at least half of them have asked, 'What about  Deryck Maughan?' "</p>
        <p>Mr. Long and other analysts said the quarter-to-quarter slide in Salomon's results was not surprising in and of itself. The fourth quarter is typically the slowest period for Wall Street firms, and Merrill Lynch and Morgan Stanley also  reported slight declines in profits from the third to the fourth quarters.</p>
        <p>Also, many analysts noted that trying to predict Salomon's earnings was akin  to playing a game of craps. The company's fortunes rely heavily on Salomon Brothers' trading for its own account, or proprietary trading, which is volatile.</p>
        <p>Guy Moszkowski, a securities industry analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, noted that the firm's trading strategies might not play out for a year  or more but that the value of the inventory it held as part of those strategies  was marked up or down to reflect the actual market value every quarter, which amplified the company's earnings swings. "No matter how big the earnings surprise, either positive or negative, I'm never surprised," he said. "Because Salomon's earnings are always a surprise, they should never come as a surprise to anyone."</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the magnitude of Salomon's drop in profits -- 37.3 percent from  the third to the fourth quarter -- caused concern among investors, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Much of the swing came from a 48.3 percent drop in revenue from fixed-income  sales and trading, the bulk of Salomon Brothers' business.</p>
        <p>Operating profits at Salomon Brothers plunged 45.7 percent from the third to  the fourth quarter, to $207 million from $381 million.</p>
        <p>Phibro, Salomon's commodities-trading business, continued a yearlong downward spiral. Its operating profits declined 17.7 percent, to $56 million in the fourth quarter from $68 million in the third. Phibro USA, the company's oil-refining and marketing business, continued to suffer from competition, pushing operating losses to $32 million from $9 million in the previous quarter.</p>
        <p>Separately, Dean Witter, Discover &amp; Company, which operates the Dean Witter Reynolds brokerage firm and the Discover credit card business, said yesterday that profits in the fourth quarter had jumped about 27 percent, to $178.1 million, or $1.01 a share, from $140 million, or 81 cents a share, in the corresponding period of 1994. Because much of Dean Witter's earnings involve the consumer business of credit cards, analysts focus on the company's year-to-year  comparisons.</p>
        <p>Dean Witter's securities business, which accounted for 65 percent of earnings in the fourth quarter, had a 31 percent increase in profits, thanks largely to investors' strong appetite for stocks and mutual funds. Profits from the credit  card business rose 20 percent.</p>
        <p>"Dean Witter is probably the most underappreciated of all the firms in the securities business," said Samuel G. Liss, a securities industry analyst at CS First Boston. "Their secret is a recurring revenue stream that covers 82 percent of their fixed costs, and no one else is anywhere near that kind of coverage."</p>
        <p>COMPANY REPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
