<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking to Recapture Glory, Department Stores Revamp</title>
    <meta content="29SHOP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/29/business/29SHOP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1523413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rozhon, Tracie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Bloomingdale's</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bergdorf Goodman</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EEDE113DF93AA1575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1383" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking to Recapture Glory, Department Stores Revamp</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Looking to Recapture Glory, Department Stores Revamp</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>America's department stores, after years of losing customers, are embarked on reconstructions and recalculations that are unprecedented in country's retailing history; nation's stores are expected to spend more than $1 billion over next three years on renovations alone, having already spent between $75 million and $100 million in last five years; stores are trying to recapture their past glory; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>America's department stores are ripping themselves apart.</p>
        <p>At Marshall Field's here, the noise is ear-splitting: a metal saw screeches through the air, accompanied by the tom-tom of hammers on plywood. Boarded-up stairwells are being uncovered and paint is being stripped off store windows that have not seen the light of day since World War II.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After years of losing customers, department stores are trying to become destinations again by making "the shopping experience" more pleasant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>America's department stores are ripping themselves apart.</p>
        <p>At Marshall Field's here, the noise is ear-splitting: a metal saw screeches through the air, accompanied by the tom-tom of hammers on plywood. Boarded-up stairwells are being uncovered and paint is being stripped off store windows that have not seen the light of day since World War II.</p>
        <p>Throughout the huge store are scattered canvas-shrouded alcoves, similar to the canvas-shrouded booths and alcoves on every floor at Bloomingdale's in New York. Just a few weeks ago, Bergdorf Goodman, the upper-crust emporium near the Plaza Hotel in New York, removed the last of its own construction barriers to show off new parquet de Versailles floors and showcases made of shagreen, the nubby sharkskin used in Art Deco furniture. How much did this renovation cost? ''So much I can't possibly tell you,'' said Robert Burke, the store's manager. One analyst estimated the cost of Bergdorf's remodeling at $75 million.</p>
        <p>After years of losing customers, the department stores are trying to become destinations again by making ''the shopping experience,'' a phrase repeated like a mantra among store owners, more pleasant. So besides trying to upgrade and freshen the merchandise they sell, department stores are getting out the hammers in an attempt to reclaim the distinctive architecture that marked the era when white-gloved ladies lunched in roof gardens, eating Waldorf salads while models paraded by, price tags hanging, and honeymooning couples picked out their first mattresses.</p>
        <p>The reconstructions and recalculations, analysts and bankers say, are unprecedented in the country's retailing history.</p>
        <p>According to research by the NPD Group, the nation's stores will spend more than $1 billion over the next three years on renovations alone. In the last five years combined, the stores spent ''at most, between $75 million and $100 million on renovations,'' said Marshal Cohen, a senior analyst for NPD.</p>
        <p>''The last decade was all about growth, about building more new stores,'' Mr. Cohen said. ''This year, it's all about renovations.''</p>
        <p>To some, the efforts are misplaced. ''What are they doing,'' asked Britt Beemer, founder of America's Research Group, a retail polling firm, ''building retail museums?'' Even store executives confess that, all too often, department store shopping has become a drag: over the years, as growth slowed, the stores started blacking out their windows, painting their old carved wood white -- or covering the walls with Sheetrock.</p>
        <p>Instead of displaying their wares in a palace of commerce, they created a maze of sale racks and partitions, turning themselves into dingy wannabe malls without the free parking.</p>
        <p>And when these department stores ventured into the malls, they began to look more alike. Lord &amp; Taylor started looking more like Macy's, which, in turn, was trying to look more like the Gap.</p>
        <p>Now they are trying to recapture their past glory.</p>
        <p>''We call it a restoration,'' said Ronald L. Frasch, the chief executive of Bergdorf Goodman.</p>
        <p>Saks Fifth Avenue is also restoring, spending $100 million on its flagship store at 50th Street and Fifth Avenue in Manhattan. Like Bergdorf's, it is keeping the Art Deco architectural gems: moldings and cherry wood have been duplicated in curving counters. Brass elevator doors have been replaced with reproductions of the earlier beveled-mirrored ones.</p>
        <p>At Bloomingdale's flagship store at 59th Street and Lexington Avenue in Manhattan, the whole second floor has been -- ''Let's face it, gutted,'' said Anne Keating, the spokeswoman for the store -- to create a more ''contemporary'' environment that caters to young shoppers. Only a year ago, cramped-looking cubicles enclosed messy racks, now replaced by an esplanade of sorts, with a 230-foot straight shot from the escalator to the shoe department and gleaming white tile floors.</p>
        <p>Federated Department Stores budgeted $100 million last year, $100 million this year and $100 million next year to refurbish its aging Macy's stores, said Tom Cole, the company's chairman of logistics and operations. By the end of the year, 120 Macy's around the country will have been altered, with new dressing rooms, computerized price checkers, and flooring. At the store in Herald Square, both the main floor's jewelry counters and the shoe department were just rebuilt.</p>
        <p>Terry J. Lundgren, the chief executive of Federated, takes credit for developing the chain's ''Store of the Future,'' as it is called, a branch of Lazarus-Macy's in Columbus, Ohio, and then using this store as a prototype for other Federated stores. The lessons? Elaborately designed computer kiosks did not work out. But the snazzy-looking shopping carts did. So did 25 to 40 percent bigger fitting rooms with entrance lounges -- for bored husbands or nannies with the children.</p>
        <p>The two most successful innovations were ''street signs'' giving directions within the store, and price verification scanners that give the latest markdown. The winners are ''quickly rolling out to all stores,'' said Jean Coggan, a spokeswoman for Federated.</p>
        <p>Nowhere is the restoration and revamping more apparent than at Marshall Field's 800,000-square-foot flagship store in Chicago. Near the State Street entrance, a carpenter was using an old-fashioned hand plane on a black walnut railing for a long-forgotten staircase. The staircase, buried beneath wallboard and paint, will once again allow shoppers to wend their way from the main floor to the basement -- in this case, a completely reconstructed basement featuring Barbara's Bookstore and the Downtown Dog, local institutions that have established outposts here.</p>
        <p>Along with the renovations, Marshall Field's has adopted a system used so successfully in European department stores like Selfridges and Galleries Lafayette: they have leased out (or licensed, as they prefer to say) roughly 10 percent of the floor space, working with the vendors to choose their own merchandise and design their boutiques. At State Street alone, the store has introduced 30 boutiques, many of them found nowhere else in the Midwest, or in a few cases, in the United States.</p>
        <p>Despite the clean lines and cabinets being cut to fit in America's department stores, some analysts and some clothing manufacturers interject a note of caution. All the reinvention strategies are fine, said Paul R. Charron, the chief executive at Liz Claiborne, which does 45 percent of its total $3.7 billion-a-year business with department stores.</p>
        <p>''But most of them aren't moving fast enough,'' he said. A store executive criticized the kind of department store reconstructions that fill the ground floor with what are called ''shop-in-shop'' boutiques -- miniature Chanel, Dior, St. Laurent and Gucci booths -- as ''airport duty-free shops.''</p>
        <p>Gilbert W. Harrison, an investment banker who specializes in retail, is generally skeptical, fearing that the changes are merely cosmetic. ''Department stores need to move much more strongly to rejuvenate their business,'' he said. ''They've got to bring in whole product categories they've dropped -- like home and electronics.''</p>
        <p>The store executives say they need more time before shoppers are polled on the changes. Many of the most dramatic makeovers -- like Marshall Field's and Bergdorf's -- are not fully completed. Shoppers have become accustomed to the whine of jack-hammers. At Bergdorf's, the construction was particularly intrusive. For months, customers had to walk through a plywood corridor inside the front doors.</p>
        <p>Everything is still not finished. Inside the 58th Street entrance, new glass cases and furniture covered with exotic wood still have not arrived.</p>
        <p>''Business actually improved during the construction, '' Mr. Burke, of Bergdorf's, said. ''I guess people wanted to see what was going on.''</p>
        <p>It seems like there is only one up-to-date change the stores have not tried yet. Macy's was reported to be testing robots which would greet shoppers at the door. Mr. Cole of Federated denied that.</p>
        <p>''But we're prepared to do anything it takes,'' he added. ''If somebody proves that robots will work, we won't rule them out.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
