<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Confusion, Kickers Make Difference</title>
    <meta content="29COLLEGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/29/sports/ncaafootball/29college.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1523462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E6DC113DF93AA1575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Confusion, Kickers Make Difference</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amid Confusion, Kickers Make Difference</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Drape</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joe Drape Inside College Football column discusses importance and increased visibility of kickers so far this season in college football; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the eve of Minnesota's opening game when Coach Glen Mason got some unexpected good news: the eligibility papers of his place-kicker, Rhys Lloyd, had finally cleared, and Lloyd, a native of Dover, England, would be available for the season. But the next day on the sideline, when it was time to send Lloyd out for the opening kickoff, Mason had a problem.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't remember his name,'' Mason recalled. ''I knew he was a Brit, and I'm a big admirer of Winston Churchill. So I just called out for 'Winston' until I got his attention.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kickers - an often embattled and always anonymous breed - made an odd college football season even stranger this weekend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the eve of Minnesota's opening game when Coach Glen Mason got some unexpected good news: the eligibility papers of his place-kicker, Rhys Lloyd, had finally cleared, and Lloyd, a native of Dover, England, would be available for the season. But the next day on the sideline, when it was time to send Lloyd out for the opening kickoff, Mason had a problem.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't remember his name,'' Mason recalled. ''I knew he was a Brit, and I'm a big admirer of Winston Churchill. So I just called out for 'Winston' until I got his attention.''</p>
        <p>Mason certainly knows his name after Lloyd booted two field goals Saturday in a 20-14 victory over Penn State. That made Lloyd 6 for 6 this season and helped stake the Gophers to a 5-0 start, moving them up to No. 21 in the Associated Press news media poll.</p>
        <p>Farther south, the whole state of Arkansas should know who the sophomore backup Chris Balseiro is after he converted a 19-yarder in double overtime to defeat Alabama, 34-31, keeping the Razorbacks undefeated and moving them to No. 8.</p>
        <p>And finally there is Tyler Fredrickson of California, who kicked a 51-yarder and had two attempts blocked before knocking through a 38-yarder that stunned No. 3-ranked Southern California in triple overtime, 34-31.</p>
        <p>It has been an odd college football season, marked by last week's powerhouses becoming this week's disappointments. So it was fitting that kickers -- an often embattled and always anonymous breed -- made it even stranger.</p>
        <p>The Trojans (3-1) were supposed to be the class of the West. They had an 11-game winning streak and national championship aspirations, and had provided Cal (3-3) with enough bulletin-board fodder that the Golden Bears believed they were being overlooked. ''They always take us lightly,'' the senior receiver Jonathan Makonnen said. ''They really don't respect us.''</p>
        <p>In racing to a 21-7 lead, Cal got the attention of the Trojans, who rallied for 17 points and a 24-24 tie to force overtime. Near the end of regulation, U.S.C. blocked a 51-yard attempt by Fredrickson. In the first overtime, the Trojans broke through to bat down a 29-yard effort that would have won the game.</p>
        <p>While kickers' quirky personalities are a part of football lore, the kickers are often quite smart, as Fredrickson demonstrated on his game winner. A 6-3 senior, he looked like a quarterback, barking last-minute instructions to his teammates.</p>
        <p>''We moved the ball back about a yard,'' said Fredrickson, a former walk-on. ''It's not the way you'd do things ideally, but they had blocked two kicks. It got to the point where I was going to do anything necessary to end this game. I never doubted that last kick.''</p>
        <p>Arkansas (4-0) turned to Balseiro after the first-string kicker David Carlton missed two early field goals and the Razorbacks fell behind by 31-10 midway through the third quarter. In the second overtime, however, Arkansas' improbable comeback looked futile when Crimson Tide kicker Brian Bostick lined up for a 38-yard potential game winner. It went wide left.</p>
        <p>Instead of being daunted by a raucous crowd at Alabama's Bryant-Denny Stadium, Balseiro, a walk-on, assuredly made good on his chance to end the game. ''It's an amazing feeling,'' he said. ''I dream about this every day.''</p>
        <p>In a topsy-turvy season in which Oregon looked like a worldbeater one week, upsetting Michigan, only to be trounced the next by Washington State, a national title may ride on the toe of an overlooked place-kicker.</p>
        <p>For evidence, look no further than the top three spots in the polls: Trey DiCarlo is 7 of 8 for top-ranked Oklahoma, Jon Peattie is 5 of 6 for No. 2 Miami and Mike Nugent, an all-American last year, is 7 of 8 for No. 3-ranked and defending national champion Ohio State.</p>
        <p>This is not lost on Mason. He has found an extraordinary talent in Lloyd, who did not begin kicking a football until his senior year in a Minneapolis-area high school and spent two years in junior college refining his technique. Lloyd is the first Gopher to handle kicking and punting duties since Gino Cappelletti did in 1954.</p>
        <p>Lloyd already has two field goals from beyond 50 yards, is 25 of 25 on point-after attempts and is averaging 42 yards a punt with a continental panache. In a nod to his soccer-playing roots, he rolls to his right and sidewinds his punts. Against Penn State, he recovered his own onside kick to open the game and later pinned the Nittany Lions on their own 6-yard line with a 51-yard punt.</p>
        <p>''He's a musician with the ball and he's earning his scholarship, I can tell you that,'' Mason said. ''But I still call him Winston.''</p>
        <p>Lloyd shrugs off his coach's nickname. ''I don't mind as long as he calls me when we need points,'' he said.</p>
        <p>No doubt that in the coming Saturdays, Mason will be calling on his kicker at critical times. So will every other college coach. How these specialists respond may be the difference between earning a spot in the national title game. Or not.</p>
        <p>INSIDE COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
