<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>France Is to Pay 80% of Cost of Abortion Pill</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="330477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABORTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RU-486 (DRUG)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GROUPE ROUSSEL UCLAF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIDING, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA173FF93BA15751C0A966958260" item-length="414" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>France Is to Pay 80% of Cost of Abortion Pill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIDING, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Feb. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The French Government announced today that it would subsidize the cost of using a pill that induces abortion, known as RU 486, after 34,000 abortions were carried out free of charge with the method in the last 21 months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The French Government announced today that it would subsidize the cost of using a pill that induces abortion, known as RU 486, after 34,000 abortions were carried out free of charge with the method in the last 21 months.</p>
        <p>The French Government announced today that it would subsidize the cost of using a pill that induces abortion, known as RU 486, after 34,000 abortions were carried out free of charge with the method in the last 21 months.</p>
        <p>In an agreement between the Health Ministry and the pill's manufacturer, Groupe Roussel Uclaf, the cost of a drug-induced abortion in any of 793 authorized clinics was set at the equivalent of $256, of which 80 percent is to be reimbursed by the Government.</p>
        <p>''France has today become the first country to make RU 486 officially and truly available to women who have made the painful decision of interrupting their pregnancy,'' a statement from the Health Ministry said.</p>
        <p>When the pill was first authorized for use by the Government in September 1988, protests by anti-abortion groups in Europe and the United States at first prompted Roussel to take the drug off the market. But the Government stepped in and ordered the company to resume distribution.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Roussel said that between April 1988 and September 1989, 20,000 sets of pills were distributed free of charge to selected clinics, where doctors provided detailed information on the results of their use. Another 14,000 sets of pills have been distributed without charge since last September, she said.</p>
        <p>The spokeswoman said the pill, which has the trade name Mifegyne, will now be marketed for the first time, although it will still be available only in France. Hoechst A.G. of West Germany owns 54.5 percent of Roussel and the French Government owns 36.25 percent.</p>
        <p>In 1988, the last year for which statistics are available, 163,000 abortions were carried out in France, where women need no legal or medical permission to terminate a pregnancy. An abortion by traditional surgical means costs the equivalent of $247, 80 percent of which is also reimbursed by the Government.</p>
        <p>While surgical abortions can take place in France up to 12 weeks after the last menstrual period, the pill can only be used up to the 47th day.</p>
        <p>The RU 486 method requires the patient to take three pills, usually followed by an injection or suppository of the hormone prostaglandin, which enhances the pills' effectiveness. The result in more than 90 percent of cases is a miscarriage, with bleeding comparable to a heavy menstrual period considered the most serious side effect.</p>
        <p>The Government set the cost of the three pills at the equivalent of $48, about half the price originally proposed by Roussel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
