<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metropolitan Diary</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="330616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALEXANDER, RON</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">METROPOLITAN DIARY (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D8113EF93BA15751C0A966958260" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metropolitan Diary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON ALEXANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ALEXANDER, RON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>AFTER FEBRUARY</p>
        <p>When winter winds prevail</p>
        <p>and rain comes down to soak us,</p>
        <p>And all our dreamings fail,</p>
        <p>And life slips out of focus.</p>
        <p>What I would give to have</p>
        <p>The chutzpah of the crocus!</p>
        <p>DORIS KLEIN</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>AFTER FEBRUARY</p>
        <p>When winter winds prevail</p>
        <p>and rain comes down to soak us,</p>
        <p>And all our dreamings fail,</p>
        <p>And life slips out of focus.</p>
        <p>What I would give to have</p>
        <p>The chutzpah of the crocus!</p>
        <p>DORIS KLEIN</p>
        <p>AFTER FEBRUARY</p>
        <p>When winter winds prevail</p>
        <p>and rain comes down to soak us,</p>
        <p>And all our dreamings fail,</p>
        <p>And life slips out of focus.</p>
        <p>What I would give to have</p>
        <p>The chutzpah of the crocus!</p>
        <p>DORIS KLEIN</p>
        <p>OVERHEARD by Susanne Schwarzkopf on the Columbia University campus, a gathering ground for Upper West Side mothers and their youngsters:</p>
        <p>''This little piggy went to market, this little piggy stayed home, this little piggy had tofu, this little piggy had none, this little piggy . . .''</p>
        <p>Several Metropolitan Diaries ago, it was reported that Laura Fries, the director of the Empire State Building observatories, received a call for help from Doris Goller Hagberg of Port Angeles, Wash. Mrs. Hagberg had come across a personal-message recording her mother had made on an observatory visit in 1937. Mrs. Hagberg's 1990 difficulty: the envelope containing the record warned that only wooden needles should be used to play it. Where, Mrs. Hagberg wondered, could she find such a needle, so she could hear her mother's voice once again? Could anyone offer suggestions? Indeed! Among the many: try a toothpick (sharpen, insert, tighten and play); a tapered sliver of bamboo; a needle from a large cactus, or from a bougainvillea. Steel needles had their advocates, too, although they warned that the number of plays be limited and advised that the record be transferred to tape on the first or second play.</p>
        <p>One reader recalled growing up in Australia in World War II, when gramophone needles were impossible to obtain. The solution: a thorn from a lemon tree or a shrub like barberry, slowly dried in an oven and then sanded smooth and cut to the right length to fit into the needle holder. Mrs. Hagberg even received some authentic wooden needles.</p>
        <p>She said she was ''amazed and delighted'' at the response. She is also investigating the possibility that two of the letter-writers are long-lost relatives.</p>
        <p>Overheard at the Music Box Theater during an intermission in ''A Few Good Men'' (agitated woman to companion): ''I certainly don't intend to apologize for living in New Jersey. For me, it's the light at the end of the tunnel.''</p>
        <p>Message spotted by Jean Robbins of Briarcliff Manor, N.Y., on the bulletin board on the front lawn of the Briarcliff Congregational Church, Westchester:</p>
        <p>FRANKLY,</p>
        <p>MY DEAR TRUMPS,</p>
        <p>I DON'T GIVE A DAMN</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>On a recent Caribbean vacation, I managed to pick up an English-language radio station in San Juan, P.R. Listening on the first day, I was told to stay tuned for the one-word Spanish lesson five minutes after the hour. Eager to enlarge my limited Spanish vocabulary, I tuned in at the appointed time.</p>
        <p>A mellifluous voice announced that the word for the day was ''emboscada.'' Then it gave the translation: ''ambush.''</p>
        <p>Fortunately, we found no need for it during our stay.</p>
        <p>ALVIN BORETZ</p>
        <p>SALUTING GEORGES de MESTRAL, INVENTOR OF VELCRO, DEAD AT 82</p>
        <p>Please take a brief moment, putting aside your daily woes, to honor the man who gave the world Velcro, which, according to his recent obituary, a group of international inventors voted one of the century's 50 most important independent inventions, surpassing even his asparagus peeler.</p>
        <p>It has been rumored that when Dr. Jonas Salk heard tales of Velcro emanating from Europe, he unabashedly declared, ''Gee, I wish I had thought of that.'' Albert Einstein, upon first inspection of the product, quizzically inquired, ''Was ist dass?'' And Ezra Pound is said to have stated with certainty, ''There is nothing quite so lyrical as the sound of ripping Velcro.''</p>
        <p>More, how many children have been spared the pain and embarrassment of having to learn to tie their shoelaces because of this marvelous material?</p>
        <p>Perhaps the only challenger to de Mestral as Supreme Inventor of the 20th Century could be the creator of Teen-Age Mutant Ninja Turtles. There is no telling what a mind so fertile might next concoct. Georges de Mestral, we honor you. You are indeed worthy of a 21 Velcro-ripping salute.</p>
        <p>STEVE SCHECHTER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
