<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fed Urged Caution on Reserves</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="111902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL RESERVE BANK OF NEW YORK</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNETT, ROBERT A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D81E31F931A15752C0A96E948260" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fed Urged Caution on Reserves</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. BENNETT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BENNETT, ROBERT A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Federal Reserve Bank of New York told the leading New York banks last month that it did not necessarily want them to increase reserves against their loans to third-world countries, despite sharp increases in such reserves by some large regional banks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Federal Reserve Bank of New York told the leading New York banks last month that it did not necessarily want them to increase reserves against their loans to third-world countries, despite sharp increases in such reserves by some large regional banks.</p>
        <p>The Federal Reserve Bank of New York told the leading New York banks last month that it did not necessarily want them to increase reserves against their loans to third-world countries, despite sharp increases in such reserves by some large regional banks.</p>
        <p>The Fed confirmed yesterday that it had held the discussions, which were described by banking industry experts.</p>
        <p>Analysts said they believed the Fed was concerned about the effect of an increase in loan reserves by any of the leading New York-based bank companies. Such an increase would place immense pressure on the other New York banks, some with relatively weak balance sheets, to do the same.</p>
        <p>It was at least partly for this reason, the analysts said, that the strongest New York banking companies -like J. P. Morgan &amp; Company, the Bankers Trust New York Corporation and Citicorp - refrained from increasing their reserves, which would have slashed their earnings.</p>
        <p>Although the stronger banks could easily have tolerated big fourth-quarter losses, the analysts said the Federal Reserve apparently was concerned that similar actions by financially weaker banks would cause the public perception of their soundness to deteriorate. Worries About Bank Equity</p>
        <p>It would cost the Manufacturers Hanover Corporation, for example, more than $2 billion to bring its reserves against its loans to financially troubled developing countries to about the 50 percent level. A loss of that magnitude in the fourth quarter would have erased the company's shareholder equity, which stood at $2.06 billion at the end of last year, according to a recent report by Montgomery Securities of San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The banking experts stressed that the Federal Reserve did not dictate to the banks what should be done, and in its customary fashion, the Fed's ''guidance'' was oblique. The experts said that the Fed, in telephone calls, made it clear that it would not fault banks that did not necessarily increase their reserves against the third-world loans.</p>
        <p>A New York Fed spokesman, Peter Bakstansky, said; ''The subject arose in the course of normal conversations with banks. We've always made it clear that banks have to make their own decisions and that we do not view the actions of one bank as necessarily precedential for other banks. We continue to stress the importance of banks' strengthening their capital and reserve positions over time, taking into account the condition of the organization as a whole.''</p>
        <p>The sources said the Fed began making its phone calls after the Bank of Boston announced in mid-December that it would set up a $430 million reserve against its $800 million in loans to troubled Latin American countries, representing about 50 percent of the total.</p>
        <p>Until then, most large American banks had set up reserves equivalent to only 25 percent or so of their third-world loans, a process that began last June when Citicorp said it had put aside $3 billion in case its Latin American loans needed to be written off. Banks Flex Muscles</p>
        <p>The Bank of Boston's move last December to a 50 percent reserve set off a spate of such actions by regional banks around the country. In the eyes of many investors, a 50 percent reserve became a sign of a banking company's financial strength.</p>
        <p>For that reason, some of the stronger New York banks were eager to flex their financial muscles - which would have highlighted the weakness of the others. Consequently, the Federal Reserve entered the scene to offer its quiet guidance.</p>
        <p>Analysts stress that a bank's basic strength is not changed by establishing reserves and that the Fed's concern is largely one of public perceptions.</p>
        <p>Setting up reserves merely represents a shifting of money from one account to another, from shareholders' equity to the reserve against loan losses. But funds moved into the loan-loss reserve come out of a bank's current profits, so that establishing a reserve causes a bank to take an immediate loss instead of waiting until the loans must actually be written off, if ever.</p>
        <p>Many banks have hidden assets on their balance sheets that can be called upon in emergencies. Manufacturers Hanover, for example, could probably raise at least $600 million by selling its Park Avenue headquarters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
