<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turning Up the Volume With New Songs and Old</title>
    <meta content="27BELL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1034803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watrous, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belle, Regina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E7D81E39F934A15754C0A96E958260" item-length="420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turning Up the Volume With New Songs and Old</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER WATROUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Watrous, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Watrous reviews pop singer Regina Belle at Blue Note; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Putting the singer Regina Belle in a small club like the Blue Note is a bit like trying to fit a thunderstorm in a suburban living room; it doesn't really work.</p>
        <p>Ms. Belle is a shouter, of the head-thrown-back, mouth-wide-open variety, and on Tuesday night she was oversize, full of burly power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Putting the singer Regina Belle in a small club like the Blue Note is a bit like trying to fit a thunderstorm in a suburban living room; it doesn't really work.</p>
        <p>Ms. Belle is a shouter, of the head-thrown-back, mouth-wide-open variety, and on Tuesday night she was oversize, full of burly power.</p>
        <p>Ms. Belle, a jazz-trained gospelish rhythm-and-blues singer, had a good career going as hip-hop was cresting, and for the last several years she more or less vanished, as if her sort of raw, charged virtuosity had been swamped by more modern pop.</p>
        <p>But she has a new record out, ''Believe in Me'' (MCA), and at the Blue Note she was working on some of the new songs and others from over her career, and it showed that her sort of excitement doesn't have to stand back to any style of pop. Ms. Belle and what she called her ''blackground singers,'' using extreme dynamics, made the music raucous.</p>
        <p>Ms. Belle sang unaccompanied, stretching out vowels until the words were lost completely, looping and falling, pierced by melismas that unerringly landed on pitch, finally. She and her three singers also sang together, tossing ideas back and forth on the small stage. Ms. Belle brought the volume down to a hiss, orchestrating the performance.</p>
        <p>But mostly the show was about volume. On her records, Ms. Belle uses a controlled, tight voice, which gets powdered when she is showing intimacy. The music, slow and trying to impart an aching emotionality, love as a tennis elbow, has its value. What the records don't have is Ms. Belle's extroversion; she sounds like a nice, quiet person.</p>
        <p>In concert the loveliness vanishes, thumped by the virtuosity. And the virtuosity works; she's like a jazz musician having a good night, improvising and improvising, using the material as a background for what she's feeling at the moment.</p>
        <p>It doesn't do the songs much good, but the audience likes it.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
