<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Living Life by the Numbers Can Give a Guy a Headache</title>
    <meta content="10ARON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1030661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Directors/new Films (Festival)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aronofsky, Darren</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pi (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D71F3EF933A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="480" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Living Life by the Numbers Can Give a Guy a Headache</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Stephen Holden's April 3 review of Darren Aronofsky film Pi, which was part of 1998 New Directors/New Films festival; film opens at Angelika Film Center in Manhattan on July 10 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Pi'' was shown as part of this year's New Directors/New Films series. Following are excerpts from Stephen Holden's review, which appeared in The New York Times on April 3. The film opens today at the Angelika Film Center, Mercer and Houston Streets, Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>You don't have to be a math whiz to appreciate the heady notions Darren Aronofsky tosses around in his homemade debut film, ''Pi.'' The movie, made for just $20,000, offers a brash horror-comic variation on a familiar type, the paranoid wild-eyed genius who is so obsessed with proving a theory that he goes mad. Before he's finished experimenting on his home computer, Maximilian Cohen (Sean Gullette), the film's central character, has shaved his head in order to plug his computer into a specific area of his brain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Pi'' was shown as part of this year's New Directors/New Films series. Following are excerpts from Stephen Holden's review, which appeared in The New York Times on April 3. The film opens today at the Angelika Film Center, Mercer and Houston Streets, Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>You don't have to be a math whiz to appreciate the heady notions Darren Aronofsky tosses around in his homemade debut film, ''Pi.'' The movie, made for just $20,000, offers a brash horror-comic variation on a familiar type, the paranoid wild-eyed genius who is so obsessed with proving a theory that he goes mad. Before he's finished experimenting on his home computer, Maximilian Cohen (Sean Gullette), the film's central character, has shaved his head in order to plug his computer into a specific area of his brain.</p>
        <p>If ''Pi'' suggests a zany spoof of the Frankenstein myth, the movie poses age-old questions about the relationships between genius and insanity, mathematics and numerology, mysticism and scientific truth. Such questions may have no clear-cut answers, but considering them forces you to contemplate what exactly is meant by the word intelligence.</p>
        <p>But as smart as it is, ''Pi'' is awfully hard to watch. Filmed with hand-held cameras in splotchy black-and-white and crudely edited, it has the style and attitude of a no-budget midnight movie. Its ink-stained cinematography and jarring electronic score by Clint Manswell can be extremely grating.</p>
        <p>Maximilian is the furthest thing from an advertisement for the superiority of the intellect. Plagued by migraine headaches that he treats by popping fistfuls of painkillers, he lives in a squalid apartment in Chinatown and spends every moment  frantically trying to prove that the gyrations of the stock market are mathematically predictable.</p>
        <p>Just as he has a breakthrough, he is besieged by representatives from two different groups. A greedy Wall Street brokerage house that has somehow gotten wind of his experiments offers to give him a high-powered computer chip if he will go into business with them. At the same time, he is approached by a Hasidic rabbi who is convinced that the same set of numbers that can unlock the patterns of Wall Street is also a code for uncovering the secrets of the universe and learning the name of God.</p>
        <p>The thoughts tossed around in ''Pi'' couldn't be more opposed to the movie's chaotic style, but that might be the point. We live in a world where an obsessive irrationality may be a necessary prerequisite to penetrating the cool logic of numbers.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
