<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jackson Calmly Chalks Up Another Victory</title>
    <meta content="10WISE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/10/sports/basketball/10WISE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1399537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Celtics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Phil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Auerbach, Red</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Boston Celtics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jackson, Phil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE7DE113DF933A25755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1154" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jackson Calmly Chalks Up Another Victory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jackson Calmly Chalks Up Another Victory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Wise</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Wise On Pro Basketball column contends that it is Los Angeles Lakers coach Phil Jackson's composure during postseason games that has brought him within one game of tying former Boston Celtics coach Red Auerbach's record for postseason victories, which he hopes to accomplish in Game 4 of NBA finals against New Jersey Nets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''UNO MAS,'' read the message on the board in the visiting locker room -- one more to best Pat Riley and tie Red Auerbach.</p>
        <p>Phil Jackson penned it in reference to his team needing one more victory for its third straight championship, something only teams led by George Mikan, Bill Russell and Michael Jordan have managed to do in more than a half century of pro basketball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Game 3 was another victory orchestrated by the serenity of a coach who does his best work in the middle of the madness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''UNO MAS,'' read the message on the board in the visiting locker room -- one more to best Pat Riley and tie Red Auerbach.</p>
        <p>Phil Jackson penned it in reference to his team needing one more victory for its third straight championship, something only teams led by George Mikan, Bill Russell and Michael Jordan have managed to do in more than a half century of pro basketball.</p>
        <p>But if the Los Angeles Lakers were on the verge of something historical, so too was their bespectacled, graying coach, who weathered a nasty second-half storm last night the way he has weathered every storm of every season:</p>
        <p>By sitting there almost uninterested, like a retiree waiting in the park for his turn at dominoes.</p>
        <p>''We didn't panic, kept it cool,'' Jackson said after he tied Riley for the most playoff victories (155) in league annals and moved within one victory of equaling Auerbach's nine titles with the Boston Celtics.</p>
        <p>Shaquille O'Neal and especially Kobe Bryant won this game, but Jackson kept a team in trouble as poised and composed as a two-time defending champion, and that is why the Nets and their noisy legions walked out of the building deflated from a 106-103 loss in Game 3 of the N.B.A. finals.</p>
        <p>Did anyone look at Jackson when the pandemonium began at the end of the third quarter, and the Nets had put some life back into a dying series before they fell hard? He sat there, motionless. When Kenyon Martin hit a pretty, left-handed layup to draw the Nets even, Jackson looked off in the distance and waited for four minutes or so before going to his players.</p>
        <p>The arena was pulsating, loud and boisterous, like all the afternoons at Madison Square Garden when the Knicks were in the game, like the night in Salt Lake City when the old dynasty was trying to keep the peasants from crossing the moat. And Jackson, who does his best work in the middle of the madness, looked without a care.</p>
        <p>''That's Phil; he just doesn't get rattled,'' said Lakers forward Rick Fox, who approached Jackson between quarters, inquiring about Jason Kidd turning the corner on a pick-and-roll defense and basically baffling the Lakers.</p>
        <p>''The decision came down to, 'Are we going to shut off the middle or are we going to stay with the shooters?' We decided to stay with the shooters.''</p>
        <p>He made other crucial moves. It was Jackson's belief in staying with seldom-used Devean George in the fourth quarter -- his rebound dunk off a miss by Bryant was a huge possession -- that made a difference. His decision to rest O'Neal while the Nets built a 7-point lead with 6 minutes 43 seconds left rather than rush him back into the game was big, too.</p>
        <p>Mostly, he weathered the monsoon that was brewing inside Continental Arena the way he always does, like a prophet who knew the ending.</p>
        <p>Jackson, the old Knick, tied Riley and moved within one of Red in front of some of his former teammates, Bill Bradley, Earl Monroe, Dave DeBusschere and Willis Reed, the Nets' vice president.</p>
        <p>Auerbach, the octogenarian, still has enough energy left to chide Jackson about his ''ready-made'' teams, the idea that Jackson has had Jordan and Bryant to make all those game-winning shots, and O'Neal to move anyone he wants out of the way, and he never drafted or acquired any of those players like Auerbach, the team president, had to go out and get Boston's best players.</p>
        <p>But enough jealously and vindictiveness already. No one hired Jackson to build teams. He was hired to coach them to titles, and in that measure, he has only one equal today. A victory on Wednesday by the Lakers in Game 4 would give him six titles with Chicago and three with the Lakers. He still has two years left on his contract and plans to finish it out.</p>
        <p>''It's great, but it's all about those teams that won it,'' Jackson said tonight. ''I've got a mentor over there in Tex Winter,'' he said to the longtime assistant. ''He says, 'You're only a success at the time you perform a successful task. So until that task is performed, there's a moment of feeling that exuberance of performing it. After that, you can't get a cup of coffee with it.''</p>
        <p>When the Continental Basketball Association was as close he could get to the N.B.A., Jackson would invariably turn on the television and catch the marquee team of that era.</p>
        <p>He loved to watch the rhythm and grace of Magic, Kareem and those great Laker clubs. But he paid special attention to the omnipotent man running Showtime, Riley.</p>
        <p>''I watched him for quite a while from a distance in the C.B.A., and really, it was remarkable career that he's had as a coach,'' Jackson said. He finished the thought by saying how great an honor it was even to be approaching Riley's record.</p>
        <p>Like the stylish taskmaster before him, Jackson would once again prove that he can take a system, apply it to different egos and players, and still see it result in incredible success.</p>
        <p>Jackson is still thought of as the Obi-Wan Kenobi character, whose old-world wisdom makes his players see an inner peace within. Yet the New Age perception grows older and more tired by the game.</p>
        <p>Like Riley, the one thing he does better than anyone is challenge men who have everything they could want in the world -- fame, financial security and adulation -- and make them understand they still have something left to prove.</p>
        <p>At one point in Game 7 of the Western Conference finals against Sacramento, he called a timeout and looked at Bryant, Robert Horry and Rick Fox in the eye, according to the NBC replay.</p>
        <p>''You and you and you,'' he said sternly, pointing to each player on the bench. He sprinkled in some profanity and demanded, ''Get back!''</p>
        <p>''That was classic Phil,'' Fox said in the locker room afterward. ''He pulled us in and made us focus. Just like tonight. When things were out of control, he brought structure and focus to the proceedings.</p>
        <p>''So he tied Riley, and he's got one to go to tie Red,'' Fox added. ''Sounds like a lot of unfinished business. He's got to distance himself from everyone who's chasing him. Riles is still out there, and he's still got to catch Red.''</p>
        <p>Nine is not an altogether perfect number.</p>
        <p>ON PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
