<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sad Letter To St. Nick Gets a Reply At Apt. 26A; Anthrax Fears and All, Mail to the North Pole Does Not Go Ignored</title>
    <meta content="25SANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/25/nyregion/25SANT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1354246"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anthrax</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Santa Claus</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wakin, Daniel J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Santa Claus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anthrax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington Heights (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Operation Santa Claus</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFDD1531F936A15751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1387" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sad Letter To St. Nick Gets a Reply At Apt. 26A; Anthrax Fears and All, Mail to the North Pole Does Not Go Ignored</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Sad Letter to St. Nick Gets a Reply at Apt. 26A</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL J. WAKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wakin, Daniel J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Postal Service program called Operation Santa Claus remains in service despite terrorist attacks and anthrax scares; several letters that were answered discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The letter was signed ''A Santa beliver'' and made a simple request: ''Give us a good reason to smile in this wonderful season.''</p>
        <p>How could Julie Taylor say no?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The letter was signed "A Santa beliver" and made a simple request: "Give us a good reason to smile in this wonderful season." How could Julie Taylor say no?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The letter was signed ''A Santa beliver'' and made a simple request: ''Give us a good reason to smile in this wonderful season.''</p>
        <p>How could Julie Taylor say no?</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor was sorting through the letters to Santa Claus from needy children collected at Manhattan's General Post Office, which for more than 70 years has made them available to the public under the auspices of a program called Operation Santa Claus.</p>
        <p>The tone intrigued her. ''The whole feeling of the letter was so genuine,'' she would later say. ''It was honest and straight from the heart.''</p>
        <p>It began, ''My name is Ashley. I am 6 years old.'' It said she was writing because Mom could not, and added, ''My brother Melvin can't talk.'' There was no explanation. Nor was there a last name. ''This family is very needed,'' the writer went on in prose beyond the years of a 6-year-old. ''We wouldn't have Christmas if you don't reach us.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor, a matter-of-fact woman, made up her mind, folded up the piece of ruled paper and went off to shop.</p>
        <p>And so a letter from a child brought together Ms. Taylor, the daughter of missionaries from Oregon, and the Azcona family, children of the Dominican fields living on public assistance in Washington Heights. Briefly, during one of the darkest holiday seasons in memory, a ray of . . .</p>
        <p>Hold on, you might be saying. Not another dose of Christmas treacle.</p>
        <p>All right, then: Thanks to anthrax, letters to Santa are irradiated these days. Mailed presents cannot just say ''From the North Pole,'' but must have a return address. The number of letters is down to an estimated 200,000, from 280,000 last year. Fewer volunteers are walking in to take part in Operation Santa Claus, though many people are participating by phone.</p>
        <p>And the program's office has a new computer program to guard against savvy children who send numerous letters to increase their chances (more than half are duplicates).</p>
        <p>But none of that crossed Ms. Taylor's mind, a good thing for the Azcona children, and perhaps for the treacle lovers of the world.</p>
        <p>As a chill gathered on the last day of fall, Ms. Taylor drove her creaky 1984 Jeep Wagoneer uptown and parked on, yes, St. Nicholas Avenue. Wearing a red Santa hat, she walked up a flight of stairs and saw the door of apartment 26A open. A sticker declared that inside was P.S. 115's ''Student of the Month.''</p>
        <p>The student, as it turns out, is Ashley Hidalgo, actually 5 years old. Her brother is Milvio, 3, whose name was anglicized in the letter. Milvio is tumbling about on a worn linoleum floor. Ashley, a girl of large eyes and long lashes, sits on a plastic-covered couch with her favorite book, ''My Silly Snowman.''</p>
        <p>A moment of panic seizes Ms. Taylor as she enters the one-bedroom apartment -- there are three children instead of two. She worries that she misread the letter. But she finds out that one of the children is a cousin, Carlos Lopez, 5.</p>
        <p>''I'm not quite Santa, but close,'' she says to no one in particular as Ashley and Milvio's mother, Francisca Azcona, and her sister Lucila Azcona look on, puzzled.</p>
        <p>''Are you Ashley? I brought you some presents you were asking for,'' Ms. Taylor says to the girl.</p>
        <p>''I know a bunch of folks,'' Ms. Taylor continues, trying to break the ice. ''You know, Rudolph.''</p>
        <p>Ashley and Milvio examine the packages. ''This is mine, this is my Mom's,'' Ashley says, reading the labels.</p>
        <p>Ms. Azcona, a gentle, 28-year-old woman, does not speak. She does not know English, and can barely read or write in Spanish, her native language.</p>
        <p>Because she grew up as ''granddaddy's girl,'' her family says, in a rural area around San Jose de las Matas in the Dominican Republic, she was never made to go to school. So she is taking a basic English class at P.S. 115. Ashley helps her with homework, and when Ashley needs help, Ms. Azcona calls the girl's father, Milvio Hidalgo, who lives elsewhere.</p>
        <p>As the letter said: ''Mom can't write.''</p>
        <p>And Milvio cannot talk because he has not learned to. He suffers from learning disabilities. Ms. Azcona is not sure exactly why, but she blames the problems on a stressful pregnancy, or maybe on the bite on Milvio's head from a rat when he was 2 months old. But the boy is making progress. He can say words like ''Mommy'' and ''tio'' (uncle). Ms. Azcona's nickname, Lillian, comes out ''Giggia.'' She keeps careful track of records of his care, signing forms in a shaky print.</p>
        <p>The children's toys consist mainly of some stuffed animals, a toy computer, a doll's bed. Money is tight. Ms. Azcona survives on $290 a month in public assistance, $50 a month in child support and $186 in food stamps. Outside, there are drug dealers on the corner.</p>
        <p>''This Christmas is worse because I have nothing to give,'' Ms. Azcona said in an interview before Ms. Taylor's unexpected arrival. ''I don't have the money to buy what they want.'' She begins to cry and turns her face away.</p>
        <p>Ms. Azcona came to New York in 1990, two years after the arrival of another 18-year-old, Ms. Taylor, who came from Salem, Ore., to study acting at New York University.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor's father was an independent missionary. She lived on Indian reservations until age 10, and then on the top floor of a halfway house called Chemawa Chapel run by her parents. For a time in the early 1970's, she, her parents and her brother and sister survived on $500 a month in donations.</p>
        <p>''One year on Christmas Eve, a Sears truck pulled up to the chapel and out came three brand-new bicycles from a supporter in Canada,'' Ms. Taylor said. ''We never had new bicycles before. It comes full cycle.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor works as a clown and as a home-interior painter. Times are slow, after Sept. 11. In past holiday seasons companies like Cantor Fitzgerald and Aon Risk, tenants of the World Trade Center, would hire her clown agency for Christmas parties.</p>
        <p>Back in the Washington Heights apartment, there is no holding back. The children start tearing open the presents. A set of Hot Wheels cars captivates Milvio, and he makes ''whoo whoo'' sounds as he pushes them around. Ashley struggles to detach a Beyond Pink Barbie doll from its packaging. Ms. Azcona takes out a set of winter gloves and a hat.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor, who bought the gifts in league with her friend Allison Farrow, also gave each child an outfit of clothes and an extra shirt. And she  brought a large stuffed lion and a stuffed elephant, and Play-Doh, which starts to squish underfoot.</p>
        <p>Lucila Azcona puts her hand on Ms. Taylor's arm. Her sister says thank you in English, shyly.</p>
        <p>Then the unexpected happens. The doorbell rings. It is the postman. An anonymous donor has sent a box of toys and clothes, also addressed to Ashley and ''Melvin.'' No one can figure out how this has happened, since Ms. Taylor kept the letter from Ashley. Unfazed, Ashley tears open the box.</p>
        <p>Soon, it emerges that Ms. Azcona heard about Operation Santa Claus from a social worker. Because she cannot write, she passed on the program address to her sister's 11-year-old daughter, Tiffany Vazquez, so that she could send a letter for herself. But Tiffany, possibly in cahoots with Ashley, wrote on behalf of her cousins instead.</p>
        <p>''I hope that God repays you,'' Ms. Azcona tells Ms. Taylor.</p>
        <p>''He already has,'' Ms. Taylor says, nodding at the children amid the wrapping paper. ''This is my repayment.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
