<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pop Life; Arista's Formula: Country and Film Music</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="574026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAP MUSIC</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ARISTA RECORDS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOGIC RECORDS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SNAP (ROCK GROUP)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAVIS, CLIVE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RULE, SHEILA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/The Pop Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rap Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D71330F931A35751C1A964958260" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pop Life; Arista's Formula: Country and Film Music</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHEILA RULE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RULE, SHEILA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About three years ago, Clive Davis was looking around for ways to break new ground with his label, Arista Records.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis, who is the president of Arista, said he had noticed that some of the new stars of contemporary music were record producers. So he struck a deal with the pop-soul writing and producing team of Antonio (L.A.) Reid and Kenneth (Babyface) Edmonds, and gave them money to start their own label, LaFace Records. He said he also saw "great songs" being minimized by the explosion of hard rock, heavy metal and rap, which led him to open a country music branch in Nashville. And it was his view that young film makers and Hollywood studio executives appeared to be hipper than ever about the possibilities of integrating music and film to please contemporary tastes. So he decided that the time was right to produce soundtracks in a big way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About three years ago, Clive Davis was looking around for ways to break new ground with his label, Arista Records.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis, who is the president of Arista, said he had noticed that some of the new stars of contemporary music were record producers. So he struck a deal with the pop-soul writing and producing team of Antonio (L.A.) Reid and Kenneth (Babyface) Edmonds, and gave them money to start their own label, LaFace Records. He said he also saw "great songs" being minimized by the explosion of hard rock, heavy metal and rap, which led him to open a country music branch in Nashville. And it was his view that young film makers and Hollywood studio executives appeared to be hipper than ever about the possibilities of integrating music and film to please contemporary tastes. So he decided that the time was right to produce soundtracks in a big way.</p>
        <p>These days, those decisions are paying off for Arista, which was built in 1975 on the ashes of the defunct Bell Records. Its soundtrack from the film "The Bodyguard" entered Billboard's top-albums chart this week at No. 2. Whitney Houston's hit single from the soundtrack, "I Will Always Love You" -- the fastest-breaking single of Ms. Houston's career and Arista's 17-year history -- is at the top of the singles chart. The LaFace label participated in two hits in that chart's top 10, including P. M. Dawn's "I'd Die Without You," from the "Boomerang" soundtrack. "Brand-New Man," Brooks and Dunn, and "A Lot About Livin' (and a Little 'Bout Love)," by Alan Jackson, are nestled among the top-10 country albums.  Other Arista artists are also high on various charts.</p>
        <p>"The blueprint for this is spotting trends three years ago and acting on them," Mr. Davis said in a recent interview. "As we continued with our existing artists' roster, including Whitney Houston, Aretha Franklin, Carly Simon, the Grateful Dead, we wanted to make new paths for ourselves."</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis, who has long been credited with a hands-on approach to running his company, is known in the business as a song man with a golden ear for commercial ballads. When looking for artists, he said, "you have to look for uniqueness."</p>
        <p>"I began in this business by finding unique artists, by discovering Janis Joplin, Billy Joel, Blood, Sweat and Tears," said Mr. Davis, whose label also produced the original soundtrack album for the film "Home Alone 2." "When you're looking, if it's someone who can write, like Springsteen or Patti Smith, they have to have a point of view and something to say that's special. If it's a performing artist that doesn't write -- look at the genius of Aretha, Dionne -- they have to bring songs to life in a manner never thought of." A Duo Undone</p>
        <p>The dance-music duo Snap -- made up of the rapper Turbo B and the vocalist Thea Austin -- has broken up, partly because Logic Records didn't see the logic in Turbo B performing live.</p>
        <p>Snap's "Rhythm Is a Dancer" (Arista) is No. 6 on Billboard's top-100 singles chart. But Turbo B left the act several weeks ago in what he says was frustration after the duo's Frankfurt-based label, Logic Records, tried to "keep me in check."</p>
        <p>"It was a control thing," Turbo B said on Monday about executives at Logic. "They wanted me to write my lyrics, do vocals and videos and then sit at home and wait for them to call me to do TV appearances and so forth. I had to pay for my own tours; I got no tour support from the record company. What I want to do is perform for the people who buy my records. I think I owe it to them."</p>
        <p>But Luca Anzilotti, a co-owner of Logic, says the problem lies in the way Turbo B views himself.</p>
        <p>"He sees himself more as a rock star than a dance-music star," Mr. Anzilotti said in a telephone interview yesterday from Frankfurt. "He felt his touring was much more important than getting tracks right in the studio, which we believe is the essence of success. Our position is you don't really need to go out and tour in the live sense because all of the promotion is being done in the clubs, with 12-inch singles and D.J.'s liking your tracks and playing them."</p>
        <p>At any rate, Turbo B said he was going solo and would release an album early next year. Unlike the more directly technological aura of Snap's music, he said, his new work will "have a lot more feeling, a lot of soul and heart."</p>
        <p>Mr. Anzilotti, meanwhile, said Logic Records would continue Snap and was looking for a replacement for Turbo B, someone who will "get along with us." '800' Number to Fight AIDS</p>
        <p>MCA Records' 800 number in the fight against AIDS -- (800) 695-AIDS -- has brought in about $25,000 since it was announced in October, said a spokeswoman for MCA, Caroline Prutzman. Callers can buy a special three-song cassette, the proceeds from which are to be donated to charities battling the disease.</p>
        <p>One song on the cassette is "The Last Song," by Elton John. Mr. John and MCA have said that profits from the single and its video will be donated to six AIDS charities, with MCA contributing an initial $100,000 advance against the proceeds. In addition, Mr. John says all of his artist's royalties from the sale of any future singles released in the United States will be donated to AIDS charities here.</p>
        <p>Al Teller, the chairman of MCA Music Entertainment Group, said: "It's just a simple fact of life that artists who are also celebrities are paid very close attention to by the public.</p>
        <p>"They have a significant public platform from which they can convey messages of importance and, frankly, that's the point of this. If an artist of Elton's stature makes an important statement about AIDS education, the message will be heard by many more people than if the statement was delivered by a knowledgeable medical person."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
