<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eating Well</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="574029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURROS, MARIAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBBINS, JOHN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EATING WELL (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DD1130F931A35751C1A964958260" item-length="1306" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eating Well</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marian Burros</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURROS, MARIAN</byline>
      <dateline>SANTA CRUZ, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOHN ROBBINS, crusader, animal-rights activist and idealist, shares household chores with his wife, Deo, and their 18-year-old son, Ocean. He does about 40 percent of the cooking and washes the dishes.</p>
        <p>"Deo does the bathrooms," Mr. Robbins said as he sat in the study of his 1950's house, with 1950's carpet that was probably orange and yellow and brown when it was new. "That's because I weasel out of that."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOHN ROBBINS, crusader, animal-rights activist and idealist, shares household chores with his wife, Deo, and their 18-year-old son, Ocean. He does about 40 percent of the cooking and washes the dishes.</p>
        <p>"Deo does the bathrooms," Mr. Robbins said as he sat in the study of his 1950's house, with 1950's carpet that was probably orange and yellow and brown when it was new. "That's because I weasel out of that."</p>
        <p>Mr. Robbins, who has an audience of hundreds of thousands for his animal-rights, pro-environment, vegetarian message, said he did not feel guilty about leaving this work for his wife, "because I love her and she loves me."</p>
        <p>"Guilt is a negative emotion," he said.</p>
        <p>Psycho-speak comes naturally to this former psychotherapist who wrote "Diet for a New America" (Stillpoint Publishing) in 1987 and "May All Be Fed," a cookbook (William Morrow), in 1992. He has been preaching his three-pronged gospel ever since. While health professionals talk about the need for better nutrition and environmentalists about the importance of cleaning up the planet, Mr. Robbins has combined both ideas and tacked on a third, animal rights. They are all connected, he says.</p>
        <p>The inclusion of the animal-rights message with nutrition and the environment has provoked concern. Dr. Dean Ornish, author of "Dr. Dean Ornish's Program for Reversing Heart Disease" (Ballantine, 1992), admires Mr. Robbins's work, but sees problems with the inclusion of animal rights. "I respect what he's doing in terms of raising awareness about the healthful effects of a vegetarian diet," Dr. Ornish said. "But it goes beyond what I write about. His approach and mine differ; he tends to polarize people, I tend to build bridges."</p>
        <p>Mr. Robbins's lectures are heard by thousands, particularly by young people, and sales of his first book are over 300,000, his publisher says.</p>
        <p>Part hippie, part charismatic leader, Mr. Robbins, 44 years old, an heir to the Baskin-Robbins fortune, has gone from the home of his childhood in Hollywood, with an ice-cream-cone-shaped swimming pool, to a tiny rented house whose interior may not have been painted in decades.</p>
        <p>"Around here the three of us share housework," said Deo Robbins, who was born Annette. (The name came to her in a dream.) "None of us particularly like it, but we do what we have to do." These mundane pursuits are not high on the Robbinses' list of things to do. Saving Americans from themselves is.</p>
        <p>Admirers compare Mr. Robbins's impact with that of Rachel Carson, using adjectives like extraordinary and compelling to describe his work.</p>
        <p>Detractors use adjectives like hyperbolic.</p>
        <p>"Every so often a book comes along which has the capacity to awaken the conscience of a nation," wrote Cleveland Amory in promotional material accompanying Mr. Robbins's book. Mr. Amory, the author and animal-rights advocate, is a board member of Earthsave, the group founded by Mr. Robbins. " 'Silent Spring' was one such book," Mr. Amory wrote. "John Robbins's volume is destined to be another."</p>
        <p>Mr. Robbins's message is not always clear. In his books, better nutrition and a cleaner environment flow from animal rights. In person and in videos, Mr. Robbins appears to have reversed the order: if people had healthier diets and cared more about their environment, animals would be treated more humanely.</p>
        <p>"I think in an ideal society there is going to be some animal agriculture, but organically raised and humanely slaughtered," Mr. Robbins said in an interview in his home just outside of Santa Cruz.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robbins disapproves of the militant animal-rights advocates. "I have very strong feelings you don't fight violence with violence," he said.  "I am not cutting out animal agriculture. If people are saying that, that's their problem."</p>
        <p>"Diet for a New America," with Lassie-type stories about cows and chickens, dolphins and pigs, wastes little time in getting down to basics: scenes of cruelty in factory farming practices, complete with graphic photographs. Few people fail to be touched. Then, it is easy to make the point that meat and dairy products are not essential for an adequate diet, and from there to argue that factory farming destroys the environment. Much of what Mr. Robbins has to say about diet in this country is unremarkable: we eat too much meat and dairy products. Much of what Mr. Robbins has to say about the inhumane treatment of animals on factory farms is correct. But Mr. Robbins undermines his case by exaggerating; facts mix with factoids and anecdotes. He contends, for example, that cattle raising is responsible for the deforestation of America.</p>
        <p>Wrong, says Alan R. Durning, a senior researcher at Worldwatch Institute, an environmental research center in Washington, and co-author of "Taking Stock: Animal Farming and the Environment." "I don't know of any significant expansion of farmlands taking over forests," Mr. Durning said.</p>
        <p>Charles Benbrook, a consultant on food safety in Dickerson, Md., and former executive director of the National Academy of Sciences Board of Agriculture, disagrees with Mr. Robbins's contention that meat and dairy products contain more pesticides than plant foods. "There's no way analytically to come up with numbers," Mr. Benbrook said.</p>
        <p>Even some who should be allies worry about Mr. Robbins's exaggerations.</p>
        <p>"I applaud his stand," said Debra Blake Weisenthal, formerly of Vegetarian Times. "It certainly tells the whole story, but the figures are probably overblown. We have to come up with accurate figures if we expect to be taken seriously."</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Robbins's admirers think the emphasis on animal rights detracts from the message.</p>
        <p>Greg Drescher, president of Gifford, Drescher &amp; Associates, a Boston firm that plans conferences on food, health and the environment, says the message is right. But he added: "What's being missed is an opportunity to support a strong position for reduced meat consumption from a nutrition and environmental perspective without the other baggage. By putting all of the issues together he makes it harder for a broad group of people to support the issues."</p>
        <p>Mr. Robbins concedes that his message can be confusing. "It makes it a little complicated for the bumper-sticker mind and the sound bite," he said.</p>
        <p>In the 60's, Mr. Robbins rebelled against his family's materialism. "In my family, roughing it meant room service was late," he said. He had mixed feelings about his father, who was one of the founders of the Baskin-Robbins ice-cream business. "I wished he would spend more time with me and less on business," he said. "I sometimes thought my primary importance to him was that I would carry on the business." Today, he says, he has a good relationship with his father.</p>
        <p>"I could have gone to Harvard, Yale or Stanford," he said, "but part of my rebellion was to go to a public college." He chose the University of California at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>"I was reading Emerson when I was 11 years old," he said. "I was reading Thoreau and Whitman. I think my destiny, my potential came from my soul."</p>
        <p>Though he would accept no money from his father, he allowed him to hire a lawyer to keep himself out of the Vietnam War and today justifies it this way: "I realized my father, by purchasing the attorney's services, was helping lawyers to do pro bono work, keeping other people out of the war."</p>
        <p>Mr. Robbins' first book was published in 1987 and, in the beginning it was reviewed only in the fringe press. Television appearances brought it into the mainstream. Michael Jacobson, executive director of the Center for Science in the Public Interest, a Washington-based advocacy group, thinks Mr. Robbins knows young people. "I can see animal rights and humane treatment of animals being a major influence on the direction of the American diet in the next 10 or 20 years," Dr. Jacobson said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
