<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.L. Embarks on Stepped-Up Effort to Deal With Head Injuries</title>
    <meta content="16FOOT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="PRO FOOTBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="944061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Head</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Timothy W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0D91238F935A25754C0A961958260" item-length="1445" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.L. Embarks on Stepped-Up Effort to Deal With Head Injuries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Timothy W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>10 National Football League teams, under enhanced program that will begin this season, hope to gain more insight into head injuries by using neuro-psychological examinations on players who are at risk; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As National Football League training camps open this week, concussions will again be at the forefront of medical problems that bedevil players and confound team physicians. But under an enhanced program that will begin this season, 10 N.F.L. teams hope to gain more insight into head injuries by using neuro-psychological examinations on players who are at risk.</p>
        <p>Under the neuro-psychological testing, players will be given a psychological evaluation, which includes a neurological examination and tests that measure concentration, motor skills, focus and short-term and long-term memory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As National Football League training camps open this week, concussions will again be at the forefront of medical problems that bedevil players and confound team physicians. But under an enhanced program that will begin this season, 10 N.F.L. teams hope to gain more insight into head injuries by using neuro-psychological examinations on players who are at risk.</p>
        <p>Under the neuro-psychological testing, players will be given a psychological evaluation, which includes a neurological examination and tests that measure concentration, motor skills, focus and short-term and long-term memory.</p>
        <p>By doing these evaluations before players get concussions, team doctors can better assess whether players are ready to return to the field.</p>
        <p>In the last two years, the N.F.L. has stepped up its study of concussions. Neuro-psychological exams, which might be the broadest movement yet, are just part of what teams are doing to help deal with concussions. And while it is more controversial, neuro-biofeedback is also being used on a limited basis by some teams in an attempt to help athletes strengthen their brains after concussions. In addition, Dr. John McShane, a Philadelphia Eagles physician, will study eight Eagles players who incur concussions during games over the next two seasons in hopes of coming away with information that will make it easier for doctors to treat football players who have suffered concussions in games.</p>
        <p>''Dr. McShane's study is just the tip of the iceberg in terms of what we're doing in the study of concussions among athletes,'' said Dr. Elliot Pellman, a team physician with the Jets and the Islanders and the chairman of the N.F.L.'s subcommittee on mild traumatic brain injury.</p>
        <p>Pellman's group is focusing on whether the number of concussions could be reduced by improving the equipment that players wear. It is developing a design for a new helmet to replace the one that was developed in the 1970's. The group is also studying the mouthpieces players use and whether force of impacts generated through the jaw could contribute to concussions.</p>
        <p>Concussions are the dangerous byproduct of the violent collisions in football. If a hit is violent enough, it can cause the brain to bounce against the inside of a player's skull, resulting in a concussion. The symptoms include headaches, nausea, fatigue, memory loss, confusion and irritability. For years the N.F.L. viewed concussions as a distressing, but accepted, fact of the sport. Coaches shrugged when a player got his ''bell rung'' and team doctors sent him home to sit in a dark, quiet room to recuperate.</p>
        <p>With the recent retirement of Jets receiver Al Toon, Bears running back Merril Hoge and Rams quarterback Chris Miller, who all suffered from post-concussion syndrome, and with high-profile quarterbacks such as the 49ers' Steve Young and the Cowboys' Troy Aikman being sidelined with head injuries, the N.F.L. has taken an active interest in the study of concussions. While the league has not made much progress in eliminating them, it is on the way to finding better means of prevention and treatment.</p>
        <p>Although it is not a cure for concussions, the neuro-psychology testing might be the most promising advance in helping players avoid a succession of concussions. Toon estimated that he suffered nine concussions during his career with the Jets, and team doctors believe that the cumulative effects of those concussions might have compounded Toon's problems. Doctors believe that players who completely recover from a concussion are not increasingly susceptible to subsequent ones. That is where the neuro-psychological testing will come in.</p>
        <p>''This helps the team doctors make decisions on an athlete's readiness to play,'' said Dr. Mark Lovell, a neuro-psychologist at Henry Ford Hospital in Detroit and one of the innovators of neuro-psychological testing. ''We think sending someone back in when they still have symptoms from a previous concussion puts them at greater risk for another concussion. Prevention is the whole idea.''</p>
        <p>Since the tests are done on players who have had concussions in the past but are symptom-free, doctors have a measure to go by if such players suffer another concussion. They would be able to tell when those players return to normal.</p>
        <p>Lovell and Dr. Joe Maroon, a Steelers team physician for 15 years and the chairman of neurosurgery at the Allegheny University Health Center in Pittsburgh, began using neuro-psychological testing with the Steelers in 1989. Maroon said the neuro-psychological testing came out of his need to give Chuck Noll, then the Steelers' coach, objective information on when a player with a concussion could safely return to playing.</p>
        <p>Since then, Lovell estimates that 80 percent of the Steelers' players and about 150 N.F.L. players have had neuro-psychological exams. Dr. Maroon said Hoge's baseline psychological evaluation was one of the determining factors in his decision to retire from the league two years ago. Hoge was with the Steelers before joining the Chicago Bears as a free agent.</p>
        <p>''We were able to document everything with objective data,'' Maroon said. ''It was completely unbiased. If there is a playoff game and there's a question of whether a player with a concussion should or shouldn't play, we have objective information to help the coach make a better decision.''</p>
        <p>The use of neuro-biofeedback to treat players with a concussion has gained limited acceptance in the N.F.L. The Jets used it to treat quarterback Boomer Esiason's concussion in 1995 and the Indianapolis Colts used it last season.</p>
        <p>Neuro-biofeedback, which uses light and sound to help stimulate certain brain wave- activity that is supposed to strengthen brain function, is somewhat controversial. There are arguments on both sides as to whether it is effective for treating concussions.</p>
        <p>''I'm very suspicious of it,'' said John Norwig, the Steelers' trainer. ''Once we've ruled out catastrophic problems, we let Mother Nature take over and wait for the baselines to return to normal.''</p>
        <p>The Colts confirmed that they used neuro-biofeedback last year on one player, but refused to say if it was effective. The team said it would consider using the treatment again on a case-by-case basis.</p>
        <p>Bob Reese, who spent 25 years as the Jets' trainer and is now the director of Pyramid Peak Performance, uses neuro-biofeedback in his work with the Alexandria Institute of Hastings-on-Hudson, N.Y., an outpatient clinic that treats disorders ranging from migraine headaches and strokes to addictions. Reese has used neuro-biofeedback on football and hockey players. He believes it was instrumental in getting Islanders defenseman Dennis Vaske, who suffered two concussions in a 12-month span, back on the ice.</p>
        <p>Biofeedback is typically used for stress management or altering behavior, like helping people to quit smoking. Reese said his method is actually a strengthening of the brain. Electrodes are attached to a player's head and then to an electro-encephalograph, which records electrical activity of the brain. The player tries to move two colored bands up and down the monitor purely through concentrating. Through this effort, Reese believes, the brain is strengthened, much the way weight lifting strengthens muscles.</p>
        <p>Reese became familiar with neuro-biofeedback when he was with the Jets. After Esiason suffered a concussion in a game against Buffalo during the 1995 season, Reese and Pellman used neuro-biofeedback in an attempt to help the quarterback. After 15 sessions, Esiason improved. But Reese and Pellman still are not sure that neuro-biofeedback was the reason.</p>
        <p>''It allowed Boomer to be pro-active with his treatment just like a guy rehabbing a knee injury,'' Reese said. ''For years the treatment for a concussion was to go home and rest. When you've got a well-tuned athlete that's used to working, it's depressing for him to be away from his teammates doing nothing. In the sense that Boomer felt better after he did it, neuro-biofeedback helped him.''</p>
        <p>Esiason is not sure whether the neuro-biofeedback got him back any quicker, but he is glad he tried it.</p>
        <p>''I felt like when Dr. Pellman and Bob Reese came to me at least they were trying to do something,'' Esiason said. ''It actually helped my concentration and it helped me mentally to be around the team and doing something. It's difficult to say whether it was the biofeedback, because I was highly motivated to come back. That may have had something to do with it.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
