<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kansas State Doesn't Want to Let Them Slip Away</title>
    <meta content="12KSUU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/12/sports/ncaabasketball/12KSUU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1375194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ncaa Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huntington, Anna Seaton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Kansas State University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EFD81439F931A25750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kansas State Doesn't Want to Let Them Slip Away</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kansas State Gets Players to Stay Home</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA SEATON HUNTINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Huntington, Anna Seaton</byline>
      <dateline>MANHATTAN, Kan., March 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Efforts to recruit hometown high school talent pay off as Kansas State University women's basketball team receives No.3 seeding in NCAA tournament; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometimes even university presidents need a little schooling. Five years ago, Jackie Stiles, the best high school girls' basketball player to come out of Kansas, slipped past Kansas State's recruiting machinery and landed across the border at Southwest Missouri State, where she set the N.C.A.A. scoring record and was the talk of Midwest basketball.</p>
        <p>''I told my basketball coaches that kind of thing could never happen again,'' said Kansas State's president, Jon Wefald, a sports devotee who helped engineer the university's football turnaround 10 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kansas State has built one of the country's most promising collegiate women's basketball teams with homegrown talent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sometimes even university presidents need a little schooling. Five years ago, Jackie Stiles, the best high school girls' basketball player to come out of Kansas, slipped past Kansas State's recruiting machinery and landed across the border at Southwest Missouri State, where she set the N.C.A.A. scoring record and was the talk of Midwest basketball.</p>
        <p>''I told my basketball coaches that kind of thing could never happen again,'' said Kansas State's president, Jon Wefald, a sports devotee who helped engineer the university's football turnaround 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>So when three exceptionally talented Kansas high school players emerged within 90 miles of Manhattan in the past few years, Kansas State jumped in early. Center Nicole Ohlde, guard Laurie Koehn and forward Kendra Wecker received hundreds of e-mail messages, letters and phone calls from Wefald and the basketball staff. The players were invited to informal lunches at Wefald's house and played games of basketball in his backyard. He agreed to speak to their hometown Rotary clubs, but only if he could be seated with their parents.</p>
        <p>Ohlde, a 6-foot-4 sophomore who plays forward and center, arrived first. She made a middling program more inviting by playing well enough to be selected as Big 12 freshman of the year for 2000-1. The two freshmen -- Koehn, a 5-foot-8 guard, and Wecker, a 5-foot-11 forward -- signed for this season. Megan Mahoney, a 6-foot forward who was the 2001 high school player of the year in South Dakota, saw where the parade was headed and fell into step.</p>
        <p>Instantly, Kansas State had built one of the country's most promising collegiate women's basketball teams. With a core of homegrown fans, the women's team sold out the university's arena, turning heads in this football-crazy town for the first time.</p>
        <p>The sporting goods store near campus is selling T-shirts with the logo of the Kansas State women's basketball team for the first time. ''We can't keep the autographed balls in stock,'' said Becky Ballard, the store's manager, whose father-in-law was once a basketball star at Kansas State. She said her mother-in-law always pooh-poohed women's basketball, at least until this season.</p>
        <p>''We took her to a game, and she said, 'My, this is wonderful,' '' Ballard said.</p>
        <p>Another first this season: 10,000 Kansas State fans resplendent in purple and white packed the field house of a longtime rival, the University of Kansas, for a women's game. ''Every great program has a fanatical following,'' Kansas State Coach Deb Patterson said. ''That is part of our dream.''</p>
        <p>Koehn, the freshman guard, called the fan support unbelievable. ''I don't think the fans realize how much their rowdiness and cheering helps us win games,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Wildcats (24-7) had their first season with more than 20 victories in 10 years. With Ohlde, the three freshmen and Kristin Rethman, a senior guard/forward, playing nearly every minute of every game, Kansas State was ranked in or near the top 10 all season. Patterson was selected as Big 12 Coach of the Year.</p>
        <p>''The team has played beyond their years and gives us a lot of hope for next year,'' said Patterson, a former Vanderbilt assistant who has a record of 95-82 in six years at Kansas State.</p>
        <p>Wefald, who describes himself as the team's No. 1 recruiter, said that while the basketball program reaches coast to coast for good players, it continues to focus on developing a core of players from Kansas.</p>
        <p>The four youngsters show flashes of brilliance. Koehn made 105 3-pointers during the regular season, tops in the N.C.A.A., and she was named freshman of the year by ESPN.com. Ohlde averaged 17.9 points and 7.9 rebounds a game. Mahoney and Wecker do a little of everything.</p>
        <p>But the team's youth has been revealed in the number of turnovers it makes, averaging more than 17 a game. On average, the team gives up 2.4 turnovers a game more than the opposing team does.</p>
        <p>Manhattan, a town with a population of slightly fewer than 50,000 people in the northeast corner of the state, has long been obsessed with sports. Over the last decade, the area has been under the spell cast by the football team's nine straight appearances in bowl games.</p>
        <p>But by the end of the regular season, the women's basketball team had sold out Bramlage Coliseum three times. For the season, the team drew 100,017 fans, more than doubling the previous record set two seasons ago. Average attendance increased to 7,694, from the previous record of 3,774.</p>
        <p>The team's hard-core fan base did not originate in Manhattan. Ohlde, Wecker and Koehn brought thousands of fans who had followed them for years.</p>
        <p>''The towns pretty much shut down for games,'' said Scoot Anderson, who is from Ohlde's hometown, Clay Center, Kan. ''Just about everyone has a connection to these girls. We never miss the games.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
