<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Streets, Shopping Spree and Gridlock</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="802906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THE U.N. AT 50: AROUND TOWN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURDY, MATTHEW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDA153DF937A15753C1A963958260" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Streets, Shopping Spree and Gridlock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PURDY, MATTHEW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Her husband was tied up in meetings yesterday, so Naina Yeltsin took care of some of her own business.</p>
        <p>"Any concerns about your skin?" the cosmetologist at Estee Lauder asked Mrs. Yeltsin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Her husband was tied up in meetings yesterday, so Naina Yeltsin took care of some of her own business.</p>
        <p>"Any concerns about your skin?" the cosmetologist at Estee Lauder asked Mrs. Yeltsin.</p>
        <p>"It's all right," the first lady of Russia responded.</p>
        <p>"Is it oily or dry?"</p>
        <p>"Normal."</p>
        <p>"How often do you have oily blemishes?"</p>
        <p>War and peace and everything in between were on the official United Nations agenda, but in the city outside, it was a day of shopping and dining for the world leaders' spouses, and gridlock and grumbling for New Yorkers. More than a few of the motorcades screeching through the city, holding up traffic, were carrying Very Important Purchasers, shuttling between shops and official luncheons, political fund-raisers and the evening's performance of Beethoven's Ninth at Avery Fisher Hall.</p>
        <p>On Fifth Avenue, a small security force waited patiently outside the Salvatore Ferragamo boutique while Amelita Ramos, the wife of President Fidel V. Ramos of the Philippines, was shopping for shoes. As Mrs. Ramos sat in a cushy chair, a salesman settled on his haunches, showing her a parade of pumps and presumably refraining from Imelda Marcos jokes.</p>
        <p>And at Tiffany's, Sumanee Guma-Kasem, wife of an adviser to the Prime Minister of Thailand, surveyed the jewlery. "I've been everywhere: Bergdorf's, Lord &amp; Taylor and The Forgotten Woman," she said.</p>
        <p>City officials estimate that the world leaders and their delegations will have spent between $28.5 million and $39.5 million in five days by the time they return to their homelands on Wednesday. Starting Saturday, the city's hotel rooms were virtually all booked, making it "a weekend unlike any other weekend in our history," said Jeanine Moss, a spokeswoman for the New York City Convention and Visitors Bureau.</p>
        <p>Broadway shows were reporting heavy diplomatic interest; "Smoky Joe's Cafe" was expecting both Prime Minister Gro Harlem Brundtland of Norway and President Carlos S. Menem of Argentina .</p>
        <p>And restaurants, particularly expensive ones with hot reputations, were jammed. Secretary of State Warren Christopher was initially turned down for a reservation at Nobu, the downtown Japanese restaurant, but was squeezed in last night. "Someone from Australia or Austria" called, said Demethress Gordon, the restaurant's reservation manger. "They said, 'The President wants to come here,' and we are trying to get him in."</p>
        <p>Some visitors actually ventured out of Manhattan. Ortwin Windmuller, the general manager of Peter Luger's Steak House in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, seated the president of El Salvador over the weekend. "And we had a few here today for lunch, from Brazil or something," Mr. Windmuller said.</p>
        <p>Tim Zagat, publisher of the Zagat restaurant guides and chairman of NY 95, a partnership devoted to increasing tourism, compared the United Nations event to the 1992 Democratic Party convention at Madison Square Garden, generally thought to be a watershed event for New York tourism in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>"But anybody who thinks this is about how much business we do in these four days just doesn't get it," Mr. Zagat said. "It's the image that New York gets to present around the world -- that it's pretty, that it's nice, that it's hospitable, that it's clean, that it's safe."</p>
        <p>The city was playing the constant host. At noon yesterday, Donna Hanover Giuliani threw a luncheon for 400 spouses of world leaders inside the Temple of Dendur at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. The guests sat at 50 tables in the reconstructed Egyptian temple. Waiting on each of their chairs was a gift of a star-shaped crystal ornament from Baccarat.</p>
        <p>As the spouses dined on grilled salmon fillet and roasted breast of chicken, Mrs. Giuliani, Hillary Rodham Clinton and Barbara Walters delivered remarks.The recurring if unofficial theme of celebrating womanhood resounded in a room whose profound imbalance by sex was proof positive that, globally at least, women are hardly on an equal footing with men.</p>
        <p>"I feel duty-bound to point out that there are some male spouses in the room," Mrs. Clinton said. In truth, though, there were fewer than a half dozen men among the guests.</p>
        <p>Making note of the spouses' contributions to the state of world affairs, Mrs. Clinton said, "Thank you for what each of you do every day." And then, in a sort of winking reference to the difficulty of living with powerful men, she said, "Thank you for what each of you puts up with every day."</p>
        <p>There was plenty of unplanned time for the spouses and stores from Tiffany's to F.A.O. Schwarz reported a stream of foreign customers.</p>
        <p>Linda Buckley, the public relations manager for Tiffany's, said, "There are people who are coming in today by appointment or just stopping in." But like spokesmen at other stores, Ms. Buckley refused to reveal the names of customers.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Yeltsin's visit to the Estee Lauder was not a shopping trip but rather a visit to the company's headquarters in the General Motors building, meant to recognize her work in breast cancer awareness and also to highlight the company's operations in Russia, where a second store in Moscow is set to open next week. Mrs. Yeltsin was greeted lavishly by the Lauder family as here motorcade pulled up yesterday morning.</p>
        <p>But whatever hospitality Mrs. Yeltsin and the other guests were feeling, more than a few New Yorkers said they had enough of the traffic tumult caused by the diplomatic invasion, coming just two weeks after the visit of Pope John Paul II.</p>
        <p>Carol Cooper, who lives on the Upper East Side, stopped a police officer on the Fifth Avenue sidewalk yesterday as another motorcade went by. "If they're so security conscious why do they announce where they're going with 18 cars, with horns and sirens and clearing streets?" she asked. "It's crazy."</p>
        <p>The officer, Robert Giannetta, gently told her he really did not know.</p>
        <p>"I think they're all on an ego trip," Mrs. Cooper said.</p>
        <p>"Ma'am," the officer said, "you won't have to worry about it for another fifty years."</p>
        <p>THE U.N. AT 50: AROUND TOWN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
