<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Record Rally Continues in Blue-Chip Stocks</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="813716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STOCK EXCHANGE (NYSE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SLOANE, LEONARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D81E39F935A35751C1A963958260" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Record Rally Continues in Blue-Chip Stocks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEONARD SLOANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SLOANE, LEONARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Blue-chip stocks extended their record-setting rally to a third consecutive session yesterday. But the technology-heavy Nasdaq composite index retreated from the high it set on Monday.</p>
        <p>"We are in the middle of replacing leadership," said Louis Ehrenkrantz, president of Ehrenkrantz King Nussbaum, a securities firm in New York. "This proves there is something called the law of gravity."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Blue-chip stocks extended their record-setting rally to a third consecutive session yesterday. But the technology-heavy Nasdaq composite index retreated from the high it set on Monday.</p>
        <p>"We are in the middle of replacing leadership," said Louis Ehrenkrantz, president of Ehrenkrantz King Nussbaum, a securities firm in New York. "This proves there is something called the law of gravity."</p>
        <p>After soaring 52.39 points on Monday, the Dow Jones industrial average surged 37.93 points, to 5,177.45, marking its 67th record of 1995. For the second consecutive session, this important indicator advanced at one point more  than 50 points, setting off the New York Stock Exchange's collar on computer-programmed trading for the 14th time this year. Such collars are meant  to stabilize the stock market.</p>
        <p>The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index, which increased 6.70 points on Monday, gained 4 points, to a record of 617.68. But the Nasdaq slipped 3.90 points, to 1,065.89.</p>
        <p>Advances far outnumbered declines on the Big Board, 1,410 to 979. Trading rose to 437.4 million shares, from 406.8 million shares Monday and the most recent three-month daily average of 362 million shares.</p>
        <p>The stock market rally has been bolstered in part by expectations that short-term interest rates will soon be lowered by the Federal Reserve. Those expectations held fast yesterday even as the bond market consolidated after a long run. The yield on the 30-year Treasury bond tested the psychologically important level of 6 percent before inching back up to 6.04 percent, from 6.02 percent on Monday. Prices and yields move in opposite directions.</p>
        <p>A standout stock sector was drugs, which have been steadily gaining momentum  in recent sessions. Eli Lilly increased 1, to 100 3/4; Johnson &amp; Johnson rose 1  3/4, to 89 1/2, and SmithKline Beecham advanced 3/4, to 54 5/8.</p>
        <p>Shares of Value Health rose 8.1 percent after the company announced that it would buy Medintell Systems, which sells a pharmacy data system, for $28 million in stock. Value Health rose 2 1/8, to 28 3/8.</p>
        <p>Major oil companies were also strong players in yesterday's rally. Mobil closed at 109 1/2, up 1 1/2, and Exxon closed at 79 3/4, up 1 1/8.</p>
        <p>Once again, Internet-related stocks surprised many analysts by maintaining their sharp ascent. Netscape, which went public on Aug. 9 at 28, spiked 21 1/2,  to 171, and Spyglass added 4 3/4, to 114 1/2.</p>
        <p>But some of the well-known names in the technology group slumped. Microsoft fell 1 7/8, to 86; Intel lost 3/8, to 61 3/8, and Acclaim Entertainment, which restated its earnings on the advice of its accountants, plunged 6 7/8, to 12 5/8.</p>
        <p>Shares of Pixar, which jumped 77 percent on its first day of trading last week, dropped 5 3/4, to 28 1/2, after falling 6 on Monday. The company provided  a three-dimensinal computer animation program for the hit motion picture "Toy Story," but some investors are concerned that its next film will not be released until 1998.</p>
        <p>Bausch &amp; Lomb declined 2 5/8, to 35 3/8. The company projected that its fourth-quarter profits would be below analysts' forecasts.</p>
        <p>On the plus side, International Flavors and Fragrances, perceived as producing big earnings gains next year, rose 1 1/4, to 53 1/2. Hercules, which completed the sale of its electronics and printing division for $130 million, advanced 2, to 58 5/8. And General Motors class H stock, which represents its successful Hughes Electronics unit, increased 1 1/4, to 48 1/2.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
