<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Savoring the World, Cup by Cup</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="739993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COFFEE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOFMANN, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDB1738F93AA15752C0A963958260" item-length="1278" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Savoring the World, Cup by Cup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL HOFMANN;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOFMANN, PAUL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS a native Viennese who in my youth spent too much time in coffeehouses, I have sought out substitutes in my travels around the world ever since.</p>
        <p>I have found some in unlikely places. One was in what is now Kinshasa, Zaire, (then, in 1960, Leopoldville) near the post office; it was actually an ice cream parlor, but it had strong coffee, a sidewalk terrace and, during the sudden tropical sunset, something of a mellow mood. Fink's on Hahistadruth Street in Jerusalem -- also not strictly a coffeehouse but a bar with a small restaurant attached -- somehow combined restfulness with exhilaration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS a native Viennese who in my youth spent too much time in coffeehouses, I have sought out substitutes in my travels around the world ever since.</p>
        <p>I have found some in unlikely places. One was in what is now Kinshasa, Zaire, (then, in 1960, Leopoldville) near the post office; it was actually an ice cream parlor, but it had strong coffee, a sidewalk terrace and, during the sudden tropical sunset, something of a mellow mood. Fink's on Hahistadruth Street in Jerusalem -- also not strictly a coffeehouse but a bar with a small restaurant attached -- somehow combined restfulness with exhilaration.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in my travels outside Europe I found coffee shops, tearooms, brasseries, pizzerias, taverns and places that are touted as international watering holes, which usually turn out to be overdecorated bars in expense-account hotels. A coffeehouse is something else again.</p>
        <p>First, the accent must be on coffee, although alcoholic drinks may be available too. Coziness is another requirement: it's that indefinable gemutlichkeit that may very well be accompanied by, and may even be enhanced by, a degree of shabbiness -- threadbare carpets, slightly greasy banquettes, faded wallpaper.</p>
        <p>The ultimate test of coffeehouse authenticity is relaxation. You mustn't be disturbed after you have ordered your beverage. You may nurse it for hours, ask for a slice of cake with it, pencil the layout of the ideal studio apartment on your table's marble top, chat with friends, flirt, indulge in reveries, write screenplays or read. A coffeehouse in Central Europe supplies the day's newspapers as well as the latest issues of magazines free.</p>
        <p>Plenty of literature was born in coffeehouses. Nikolai Gogol wrote much of "Dead Souls" in the Antico Caffe Greco on Via Condotti in Rome. The establishment, with its early-19th-century decor, black marble tables and frock-coated waiters, still exists; it is a landmark and one of my favorites. The guest book contains autographs from Stendhal, Baudelaire, Wagner and Liszt.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1950's Giuseppe di Lampedusa went every morning to the Caffe Mazzara on the Via Generale Magliocco or the Caffe Caflisch on the Viale della Liberta in Palermo to work on his novel, "The Leopard."</p>
        <p>In Prague, the Arco, opposite the old railroad terminal counted, among its regulars Franz Kafka, his friend Max Brod, the novelist Franz Werfel and other writers and intellectuals. The acerbic essayist Karl Kraus scoffed at them as the "Arconauts."</p>
        <p>Any number of litterateurs have haunted the Left Bank cafes in Paris. Now the haunting at Aux Deux-Magots and the Cafe de Flore on St.-Germain-des-Pres is done mostly by tourists. A journalist friend of mine used to spend an hour every morning over his cafe creme on a glassed-in terrace on Boulevard des Capucines on the Right Bank, and claimed he got a better feeling for the Parisians' mood there than he would later obtain from all the press conferences, interviews, phone calls and news agency items.</p>
        <p>Alfred Polgar, who for many years crafted his scintillating essays and drama reviews at the Cafe Central in Vienna, said that coffeehouses were for "people who want to be alone but need company for it," while for lovers and married couples the coffeehouse was "a refuge from the terrors of undisturbed togetherness."</p>
        <p>Later, in exile in Los Angeles, Polgar pined for the Cafe Central, and eventually emigrated back to Zurich where he settled in at the Cafe Odeon on Limmatquai. James Joyce, Richard Strauss and W. Somerset Maugham were also habitues there. I never pass up the Odeon when I visit Zurich.</p>
        <p>My other favorites include the chatty places around the Rossio in Lisbon's center; the coffee is excellent. In Budapest I prefer the two rooms of the Ruszwurm on Buda Castle Hill to the large Gerbeaud shop on Vorosmarty Square. The 168-year-old Ruszwurm with its neo-classical columns, stucco work and Biedermeier cane chairs oozes atmosphere. The elegant Gerbeaud, which has a popular open-air terrace, is a confectioner's that also serves coffee and tea.</p>
        <p>In Salzburg I am drawn to the Tomaselli on the river embankment where Mozart's father was a regular, and to the Glockenspiel opposite the carillon on Mozartplatz.</p>
        <p>In Venice, the venerable Caffe Florian on the south side of St. Mark's Square with its many tables in the piazza in the warm months and its austere interior on foggy winter days offers the chance for a breather to visitors who are exhausted from walking up and down innumerable canal bridges. In nearby Padua, the 163-year-old Caffe Pedrocchi, watched by stone lions in front of its noble Doric columns, opposite the ancient university, is another glorious landmark. In Trieste, at the Caffe degli Specchi on the airy Piazza Unita d'Italia I always have the feeling of being back in Vienna.</p>
        <p>One of the old coffeehouses in my native city that remains in business is the Pruckl on Stubenring. My friends and I used to hold cram sessions before exams there, played chess, made and received telephone calls, and courted girls (rarely with success). The elderly headwaiter, Ferdinand, suffered from an arthritic shoulder and often muttered to himself, but tirelessly brought us yet another stack of newspapers on bamboo holders, refilled our water glasses and fetched the requisite volume of the encyclopedia that we needed for that tricky Eight Down of a crossword puzzle. In a smoky back room, people who seemed like fossils to us played rummy and bridge endlessly.</p>
        <p>For a laugh, and whenever we could afford it, we descended to a basement theater under the Pruckl where a faux-rustic troupe with phony Tyrolean accents performed parodies of once-popular dramas of chivalry in which armored knights would rescue pigtailed damsels and horribly punish the fiendish and lustful robber baron.</p>
        <p>Astonishingly, there are still similar performances in the Pruckl basement. Card players continue filling the street-level back room, but they no longer look that old to me, and neither does Ferdinand's successor.</p>
        <p>The Pruckl is one of the few survivors of the many coffeehouses that once lined the Ringstrasse, the horseshoe-shaped boulevard hugging the historic city core. Another is the glittering Landtmann, opposite Vienna University, where Sigmund Freud occasionally played tarok, his favorite card game, with academic friends.</p>
        <p>THE Imperial, near the State Opera, which Gustav Mahler favored, is also still going strong. The Cafe Museum, near the Art Academy, where Egon Schiele and Elias Canetti used to hang out, is crowded with students these days and pleasantly seedy.</p>
        <p>Polgar's Cafe Central on Herrengasse was refurbished and reopened some years ago. At a table near the entrance there is now a life-size statue of Peter Altenberg, another celebrated essayist who virtually lived in that coffeehouse and got his mail there. Trotsky played chess at the Central before the Russian Revolution, and Robert Musil, Hermann Broch, Werfel and other writers were among the clientele.</p>
        <p>Today, despite stiff rents, high labor costs and television, which keeps many people at home in the evening, Vienna still boasts 1,500 coffeehouses. And Rome provides the beloved and indispensable stimulant in 6,000 espresso places, many with at least a few tables.</p>
        <p>During my latest sojourn in New York I spent a lot of time sipping cappuccino and letting my mind wander while seated in the coffee bars that have sprouted on Park Avenue South, in SoHo, on the Upper West Side and even in Times Square.</p>
        <p>Caffeinated cheers for that invasion by the Italianate espresso machine with a dash of French cafe flair. Can apple strudel and whipped cream be far behind?  PAUL HOFMANN is a former chief of the Rome bureau of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">PAUL HOFMANN is a former chief of the Rome bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
