<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Civic Groups Rise in Number And Influence</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="740152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: QUEENS UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">QUEENS (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CEDAR GROVE CIVIC HOMEOWNERS ASSN (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ONISHI, NORIMITSU</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DD103DF93AA15752C0A963958260" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Civic Groups Rise in Number And Influence</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ONISHI, NORIMITSU</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cedar Grove Civic Homeowners Association was born last April, the creation of two men who, using their home computers and fax machines, bombarded news organizations and elected officials with grievances. They rallied forces to oppose a group home for the mentally disabled and, more recently, proposed a quixotic plan to wall off the small neighborhood from outsiders in an effort to reduce crime.</p>
        <p>The group home opened last fall, and critics of the newer proposal have accused the association of being divisive and isolationist. But instead of being dismissed for its setbacks, the civic association is gaining attention from elected officials. Last week, its members met with Borough President Claire Shulman for two hours, and then spent an equal amount of time with Mayor Giuliani's criminal-justice coordinator, Katherine N. Lapp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Cedar Grove Civic Homeowners Association was born last April, the creation of two men who, using their home computers and fax machines, bombarded news organizations and elected officials with grievances. They rallied forces to oppose a group home for the mentally disabled and, more recently, proposed a quixotic plan to wall off the small neighborhood from outsiders in an effort to reduce crime.</p>
        <p>The group home opened last fall, and critics of the newer proposal have accused the association of being divisive and isolationist. But instead of being dismissed for its setbacks, the civic association is gaining attention from elected officials. Last week, its members met with Borough President Claire Shulman for two hours, and then spent an equal amount of time with Mayor Giuliani's criminal-justice coordinator, Katherine N. Lapp.</p>
        <p>"We're the vote-casting, tax-paying, middle class of Queens, and we want to be heard," said Brian Cavanaugh, the group's president and one of its founders. The group's membership includes 190 households out of 370 houses in the development.</p>
        <p>Cedar Grove's experience points to the increasingly influential role civic associations are playing in Queens. Because of its high percentage of owner-occupied homes and middle-class residents, the borough, perhaps more than any other, is fertile ground for such groups. Dan Andrews, a spokesman for Mrs. Shulman, keeps a mailing list of more than 400 such associations.</p>
        <p>"This is a politically very well organized borough, with lots of individuals concerned with what's happening on their block," he said.</p>
        <p>In December, at the second annual congress for Queens civic associations, about 400 people from groups from all over the borough gathered at CUNY Law School to share strategies against problems like graffiti, car theft and illegal multiple dwellings. As a testament to the civic associations' clout, Mayor Giuliani made an appearance, joining the usual list of politicians from Queens.</p>
        <p>Bob Harris, president of West Cunningham Park Association and the United Civic Council of Queens, which co-sponsored the congress, said the annual gatherings were organized after years of informal luncheon meetings among the groups' leaders..</p>
        <p>Civic groups have flourished in Queens for years. But some members said that in recent years, political and social circumstances have made them become more active.</p>
        <p>Sean Walsh, a former president of the Douglaston Civic Association and the chairman of the United Civic Council, which includes about 35 groups in central Queens, points to 1989 as a watershed. That year a change in the City Charter eliminated the Board of Estimate, weakening the offices of the borough presidents and centralizing power in City Hall.</p>
        <p>"That was the war cry for the civics," Mr. Walsh said. "There was a feeling that political power was lost in the outer boroughs, and that we wouldn't be heard in City Hall unless we organized."</p>
        <p>Organize they did. As a result, Mr. Walsh sees civics playing a role in Mr. Giuliani's plans to decentralize city government. "At the civic level," he said, "you get to see how decisions, made from afar, affect everything from planting trees to local school issues to traffic flow." Others point out that the associations usually form around a common problem that brings people together spontaneously. In recent years, a single issue -- the growing fear of crime -- has kept many groups active, said Shirley B. Weinstein, president of the Mid-Queens Community Council, a group representing 19 smaller organizations.</p>
        <p>Although statistics show a declining crime rate citywide, they seem to have done little to reduce people's fear. Indeed, many feel the need to organize groups to lobby for more police protection. Most civic leaders are able to rattle off the precise number of patrol cars assigned to their streets, hour by hour.</p>
        <p>She said a typical organization represented several hundred homeowners but depended on two or three committed leaders.</p>
        <p>"Sometimes," Mr. Harris added, "a leader becomes ill, and a civic becomes dormant for many years."</p>
        <p>The Hillcrest Estates Civic Association existed in name only when George Yee revived the organization last year. A rising number of car thefts and other crimes worried Mr. Yee, who has lived in Hillcrest for 12 years. For inspiration, he looked at the Jamaica Estates Civic Association, one of the groups that prevented a Dallas-based company from opening a high-tech shooting range in Queens last year.</p>
        <p>"I had never assumed that a community needed a civic association to get better services," said Mr. Yee, who became the first Chinese-American head of a Queens civic group. "But we noticed that Jamaica Estates Civic, which has been incorporated for 65 years, got respected." NORIMITSU ONISHI Organizing Against a Group Home</p>
        <p>The Cedar Grove Civic Homeowners Association traces its roots to February 1994 when Brian Cavanaugh heard from a neighbor that the State Office of Mental Retardation and Developmental Disabilities planned to open a group home at 63-12 137th Street.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cavanaugh, a textile company manager, passed around fliers to organize a meeting of his neighbors. "It's not that we're against the individuals," he said. "We're just against the concept of having group homes in residential areas."</p>
        <p>After the first meeting, residents began lobbying elected officials in an effort to block the home's opening.</p>
        <p>In April, the civic group was incorporated, with Mr. Cavanaugh as president and Walter Kowsh, a computer consultant, as vice president.</p>
        <p>That same month, the state ruled that the area was not saturated with group homes, and approved the one on 137th Street.</p>
        <p>In June, the civic association filed a lawsuit against the Office of Mental Retardation, but a State Supreme Court judge in August denied its request for a restraining order against the home. The group home, for up to seven residents, opened in mid-October.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cavanaugh says the civic group is appealing the earlier decision. So far, he says, it has spent $15,000 to $17,000 on the campaign against the group home, all of the money raised inside Cedar Grove. N.O.  NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: QUEENS UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
