<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metropolis</title>
    <meta content="22SORELT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="896835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorel, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katchor, Ben</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Julius Knipl: Real Estate Photographer (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3DA143EF931A15751C1A960958260" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metropolis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Sorel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorel, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward Sorel reviews book Julius Knipl, Real Estate Photographer: Stories by Ben Katchor; cartoons (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JULIUS KNIPL, REAL ESTATE PHOTOGRAPHER  Stories.  By Ben Katchor.  Illustrated. 106 pp. Boston:  Little, Brown &amp; Company.  Paper, $12.95.</p>
        <p>It was not love at first sight, although I was instantly attracted. Seven years ago, turning the pages of a neighborhood tabloid, I was startled by the extraordinary drawings in an eight-panel comic strip called ''Julius Knipl, Real Estate Photographer.'' I read every word, but the point of it all eluded me. How could such stunning, accessible pictures be married to such abstruse content? What a pity, I thought.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JULIUS KNIPL, REAL ESTATE PHOTOGRAPHER  Stories.  By Ben Katchor.  Illustrated. 106 pp. Boston:  Little, Brown &amp; Company.  Paper, $12.95.</p>
        <p>It was not love at first sight, although I was instantly attracted. Seven years ago, turning the pages of a neighborhood tabloid, I was startled by the extraordinary drawings in an eight-panel comic strip called ''Julius Knipl, Real Estate Photographer.'' I read every word, but the point of it all eluded me. How could such stunning, accessible pictures be married to such abstruse content? What a pity, I thought.</p>
        <p>I tried again the following week, and the week after that. The drawings were so warm, so passionate and so evocative of the New York City I remembered from my youth that I kept returning to them. In time, I was able to give myself over to the strip's peculiar enchantment and enter into its chiaroscuro metropolis. Now, after years of peregrinating with Knipl in search of vanished places and forgotten dreams, I'm convinced that his creator, Ben Katchor, is the most poetic, deeply layered artist ever to draw a comic strip.</p>
        <p>If my enthusiasm for the way Mr. Katchor draws seems over the top, let me explain that I'm crazy about German Expressionism. My favorite artists are from that period, and Mr. Katchor's work is very much in their style -- sort of Max Beckmann with dialogue balloons. Mr. Katchor's drawing line is uncertain and worried (like the artist -- I met him once), but it is his heavy use of wash that gives his strip its mystery. As every cartoon pro knows, wash cannot survive the coarse halftone used in newsprint, yet somehow Mr. Katchor's does. It's especially pleasing to see his art finally printed with a fine screen and on better stock, as it is here, in the collection ''Julius Knipl, Real Estate Photographer.''</p>
        <p>Now let me introduce you to the eponymous Julius Knipl. Knipl (the word means ''nest egg'' in Yiddish) is short, overweight and about the same age as his creator (mid-40's), although Knipl looks a lot older. He wouldn't dream of going out onto the street without a tie, jacket and fedora. His devotion to conventional dress, his thin mustache and his acceptance of his marginal existence suggest that he actually belongs to a vanished generation. Indeed, Knipl often seems like an anachronism walking through scenes of today's urban squalor. At other times, the city itself looks much like New York in the 1940's.</p>
        <p>Although Knipl is never without his camera, he seldom takes photographs. His function is to observe, reflect and, in the course of his small adventures, catalogue aspects of city life that elicit nostalgia. We find him on a rainy night visiting a hospital to determine how many people have sustained eye injuries from the spokes of open umbrellas, or listening in as a neighbor tearfully laments that everything in his refrigerator -- soy cream cheese, beef bacon, nondairy creamer, vegetarian chicken fat -- is an imitation of some real product. In another strip he encounters men who have the use of only one hand because the other is employed in holding a radio to their ear to catch the latest news bulletins. A passer-by explains to Knipl that ''these men are the bulwarks of all human decency. They act as buffers against the horrific onslaught of daily news. We sit in the sun and consider our moral options while they go through three sets of batteries in a week!''</p>
        <p>In some of Mr. Katchor's stories Knipl is completely absent. In a typically cryptic strip called ''The Radiator Musician,'' one Fetor Maracas plans to perform an evening of ''steam lullabies'' on an apartment radiator. A full house is eagerly waiting to hear the concert when a freak warm spell causes the automatic thermostat to shut off the boiler. No steam. The concert is canceled. Fetor's career is in ruins. Curtain.</p>
        <p>Another character in Mr. Katchor's cast of oddballs is Harold Alms, a professional lecturer so determined not to think about what he is going to say when he steps on stage that he spends the day sitting between two radios he has tuned to different stations. Then there is the parked-car reader, who can intuit the profession and future of the owners of parked cars. Most of the time, however, we walk with Knipl down lonely streets encountering lonely men whose obsessions are all that offer meaning to their lives.</p>
        <p>As should be obvious, the comic territory Mr. Katchor has carved out for himself is not mainstream, certainly not the kind that gets widely syndicated from coast to coast (though his work does appear in newspapers around the country, including The Forward in New York). He will never get royalties from vinyl Knipl figures or be pursued by Disney for movie rights. He will never be able to afford the restaurants frequented by Charles Schulz. Nevertheless, Mr. Katchor should take comfort and a great deal of pride in knowing that he has created perhaps the most original comic strip since George Herriman introduced ''Krazy Kat'' more than 80 years ago.</p>
        <p>Caution: Some of you who will read this idiosyncratic cartoonist for the first time may be more confused than charmed. Be patient. Remember how opaque ''Ulysses'' seemed once? These damned geniuses require work.</p>
        <p>Edward Sorel is a cartoonist and caricaturist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Edward Sorel is a cartoonist and caricaturist.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
