<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Musicians' Musician Still Singing the Blues</title>
    <meta content="MOSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="896919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Marjorie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allison, Mose</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2DF1631F931A15751C1A960958260" item-length="1581" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Musicians' Musician Still Singing the Blues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARJORIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Marjorie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Smithtown, LI, songwriter and pianist Mose Allison notes that he has made over 30 jazz albums and been nominated for Grammy Award; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>QUALITY can be recognized but not described,'' the musician Mose Allison said, quoting from Robert Pirsig's book  ''Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance.'' As a songwriter and master at piano improvisation, Mr. Allison can approximate what he does musically, but he cannot precisely describe it.</p>
        <p>At age 69, Mr. Allison remains a paradox, as enigmatic as a Mona Lisa smile. In his four-decade career he has created a melange of simple downhome blues with sophisticated uptown jazz. His music has inspired more musicians, from the Who to Bonnie Raitt, than it ever sold his own records.His balance between ''novelty and tradition'' never afforded him commercial success, although he was signed by Columbia and Atlantic labels, has recorded more than 30 albums and been nominated for a Grammy Award.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>QUALITY can be recognized but not described,'' the musician Mose Allison said, quoting from Robert Pirsig's book  ''Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance.'' As a songwriter and master at piano improvisation, Mr. Allison can approximate what he does musically, but he cannot precisely describe it.</p>
        <p>At age 69, Mr. Allison remains a paradox, as enigmatic as a Mona Lisa smile. In his four-decade career he has created a melange of simple downhome blues with sophisticated uptown jazz. His music has inspired more musicians, from the Who to Bonnie Raitt, than it ever sold his own records.His balance between ''novelty and tradition'' never afforded him commercial success, although he was signed by Columbia and Atlantic labels, has recorded more than 30 albums and been nominated for a Grammy Award.</p>
        <p>''I'm the man without a category,'' Mr. Allison said during a recent interview at his home, an unpretentious place tucked away on a street in Smithtown.</p>
        <p>In a recording industry whose marketing thrives on placing musicians into genre cubbyholes, Mr. Allison has never neatly fit. Ever since he came to New York in 1957 from rural Tippo, Miss., he has been a ''middle-class white guy singing the blues'' and making it something all  his own. ''The blues is the essential ingredient to my music,'' he said, but not all of it. He did not compromise his musical integrity by being commercially packaged as a colorful Southern rustic.</p>
        <p>Just released last month is a tribute CD, ''Tell Me Something: The Songs of Mose Allison'' (Verve), co-produced by Van Morrison, Georgie Fame and Ben Sidran. The retrospective places Mr. Allison in his rightful position among the legends of contemporary music. Mr. Morrison has been a fan of Mr. Allison's since the 1960's, when his recordings were played in Britain's underground R &amp; B clubs.</p>
        <p>''There are two kinds of musicians,'' Mr. Allison said, ''those who go directly to the audience and become popular, and those who go indirectly from other musicians. I have been able to survive because of other musicians.''</p>
        <p>A biography by Patti Jones, ''One Man's Blues: The Life and Music of Mose Allison'' (Quartet Books), was published in London last year. After hearing a performance, Ms. Jones  based her master's degree in musicology on Mr. Allison and later turned it into the first in depth book on his life.</p>
        <p>People who hear his recordings, and never see him perform, assume he is African-American. ''When I first came to New York jazz clubs, I was somewhat of a freak singing blues,'' he said. ''No one had heard of Muddy Waters. They questioned, was I valid, authentic? Some people still think I'm black. I take it as a compliment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Allison's interest in ethnic music includes ''world blues.'' ''Every country and society has their own brand of blues, a universal lament,'' he said. ''I heard a Chinese opera and the musical intervals were just like the blues, the tenor sounded just like Lightnin' Hopkins.''</p>
        <p>While growing up, Mr. Allison listened to his father's favorites, the music of Louis Armstrong or Fats Waller, on a wind-up phonograph until electricity arrived in Tippo when he was 12. Then he heard the blues on ''race records'' from his father's jukebox at the local gas station. The sound is as much a part of him as his slow drawl.</p>
        <p>His father, a self-taught, semiprofessional stride piano player, took over his grandfather's farm and ran it along with the general store in the town where his mother was a schoolteacher.</p>
        <p>''It takes a village: well, we had that big, stable family background in Tippo,'' he said. He picked his share of cotton, and it was suggested that he continue in the farming tradition, but his parents supported his musical inclinations.</p>
        <p>''I took piano lessons at age 5, but quit when I figured out those songs on my own, hunt-and-peck style,'' he said. Improvisation is his strength. ''Still can't sight-read that well,'' he said. ''Edgar Allan Poe said, 'The human spirit does not want to be instructed, it wants to soar.' ''</p>
        <p>The relaxed phrasing of Nat King Cole and the satiric humor of Louis Jordan's songs echoed in Mr. Allison's early style. High school marching bands, gigs in local honky-tonk clubs and the Army, where he played  in the 179th Army Band, prepared him for life on the road. He later returned to the University of Mississippi in Oxford, where he studied literature and philosophy and played in the Ole Miss Dance Band.</p>
        <p>As a songwriter and pianist Mr. Allison merged the blues with a New Orleans-style jazz, and his own brand of wry lyrics influenced by the prose of the poet Kenneth Patchen and the satiric novels of the French novelist Louis Celine. His songs address the human condition, with the belief that all people share a common experience. An interest in the Hungarian folk songs of Bela Bartok influenced his early album ''Back Country Suite.''</p>
        <p>Irony and ambivalence permeate his music, Ms. Jones wrote in her biography. Mr. Allison adds an intelligent, sardonic twist delivered in a dry conversational style imbued with deadpan humor, she said.</p>
        <p>''Some call it cynical,'' Mr. Allison said, ''but a cynic is negative.'' Music is positive with irony, humor and most of all joy, he said.</p>
        <p>He's a stickler for finding the right word for a lyric. In the song ''Perfect Moment,'' he searched for months, even in the Library of Congress, before selecting ''miocene,'' a geological term, to describe and rhyme with ''valentine.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Allison describes his three basic songwriting categories as slapstick, social comment and personal crisis. ''Your Mind's on Vacation'' is an example of the slapstick category,  written about people ''yakkin' away'' when he was trying to play in the clubs in the early days. ''Now, most people who come to hear me perform, listen,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Everybody Crying Mercy,'' a social comment song, was written during the height of the Vietnam war and situations keep emerging that  make it relevant, he said. ''Bonnie Raitt recorded that before she became famous. If she had waited 15 years to do that song I'd have been a rich man,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Hello Universe'' is a crisis song  he calls his hymn. ''Everyone has to come to some kind of terms with the universe, to find a way to function.'' he said. '' 'Hello Universe' is my individual response, just a comment on being here,''he said.</p>
        <p>Today, the songs he writes are a blend of all three types. A new song, ''What Will It Be?'' (the thing that actually kills you), is a slapstick meditation on death, he said. ''My favorite word is oxymoron. A friend once described my attitude as one of  passive belligerence.''</p>
        <p>''Parchman Farm,'' (1959), his most popularized tune and considered a blues standard, is one he no longer performs. ''Parchman was the name of the town about 30 miles from Tippo. Parchman Farm was what we called the Mississippi State Penitentiary. When I was a kid the posse used to come through with bloodhounds looking for someone who escaped. There was a great fascination with the place, a penal colony. It was an important ingredient to that society at the time.</p>
        <p>The forced labor ''with a 12-gauge shotgun at my back'' is no longer an issue, he said, since the prisoners are paid. It's also come to be a metaphor.  But because of the violence connected to the punch line, ''all I did was shoot my wife,'' he doesn't sing it anymore. ''Nonviolence is the only way we're going to survive ourselves,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Allison continues to practice Tai Chi, the ancient Chinese exercise for balance, which he learned 30 years ago after ear surgery, which also caused him to give up the trumpet.</p>
        <p>In the jazzy tempo of ''Tai Chi Life'' he describes the focus of energy in musical terms: ''Gimme that Tai Chi Life/With the gently flowing motion/ For every move, the same devotion/ Oriental magic potion/ It's that Tai Chi Life/My mind is in position/Place to place in smooth transition/You can even do your own rendition.''</p>
        <p>When he is not on the road performing 125 days of the year from New Orleans to San Francisco to London, he is home in Smithtown, where he and his wife Audre, a recently retired English teacher, raised four children. They have been married since 1951. Their children pursued careers in psychiatry, law and computers. Only one has followed in her father's tradition. Amy Allison, a singer-songwriter, is based in Manhattan. ''You could say Amy is doing in the country idiom what I did in the blues idiom,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Allison has put together some new tunes for his next album. ''I'd like to call it ''Jim Cracks and Gewgaws.'' To define the expression, he pointed to trinkets and knickknacks around his living room.</p>
        <p>From his 1988 song ''Was'':  ''When I become was and we become were/ Will there be any Susans and Ralphs/ Lookin' at old photographs/ And wondering aloud to a friend/ What was it like to be then.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
