<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islanders Fall Just Short Of the Streaking Stars</title>
    <meta content="22ISLE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HOCKEY" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="897187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E7DB1331F931A15751C1A960958260" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islanders Fall Just Short Of the Streaking Stars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I., Dec. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dallas Stars defeat New York Islanders, 3-2, Nassau Coliseum (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Zigmund Palffy was back, but his touch was not. And when he is held without a goal or an assist, the result is pretty much a given.</p>
        <p>Palffy, who missed the Islanders' last game because of a sprained shoulder, did not get his name on the stat sheet tonight. Not coincidentally, the Islanders lost, 3-2, to the streaking Dallas Stars, on Joe Nieuwendyk's goal from the top of the slot with 1 minute 45 seconds to play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Zigmund Palffy was back, but his touch was not. And when he is held without a goal or an assist, the result is pretty much a given.</p>
        <p>Palffy, who missed the Islanders' last game because of a sprained shoulder, did not get his name on the stat sheet tonight. Not coincidentally, the Islanders lost, 3-2, to the streaking Dallas Stars, on Joe Nieuwendyk's goal from the top of the slot with 1 minute 45 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>And now the Islanders, who have lost two straight games for the first time since early November, are 1-10-3 in games in which Palffy has gone pointless.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know that,'' said Mike Milbury, the coach and general manager of the Islanders. ''But it doesn't shock me. He's the go-to guy.''</p>
        <p>Palffy, who wore a shoulder harness for the first time in his career tonight after missing Thursday night's 5-0 shellacking in Philadelphia, admitted that he was bothered by the harness.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't move,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Neither, it seemed, could most of the Islanders.</p>
        <p>Milbury had hoped to get through this grueling three-game span with only one loss, but the Islanders got it right away on Thursday in Philadelphia, absorbed another here tonight at Nassau Coliseum and must still play the Florida Panthers here on Monday night.</p>
        <p>The Islanders had a chance to keep Milbury's goal alive when the unheralded fourth-line center Derek Armstrong drilled home the rebound of a Dan Plante shot with 4 minutes 41 seconds left to tie the game, 2-2.</p>
        <p>But Nieuwendyk skated past Bryan McCabe and then Bryan Berard and then beat Tommy Salo through the five-hole with a slap shot from the top of the slot to give the Stars the victory before a crowd of 11,537 at the Coliseum.</p>
        <p>It was a frustrating finish for Salo, who made 26 saves and even helped set up Marty McInnis's 10th goal of the season when he made a nice save on a three-on-two Dallas break with both teams skating four aside. ''I played really good the whole game,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It isn't going to get easier for the Islanders. This was the second in a seven-game stretch in which the Islanders face six of the top seven teams in the National Hockey League.</p>
        <p>The Islanders played much better than they had in Philadelphia two nights earlier. But the Stars are streaking; they have won their last five games -- four of them on the road -- and are unbeaten in their last seven (5-0-2).</p>
        <p>The Islanders are streaking in a different direction. They have lost 3 of 4 after winning three in a row.</p>
        <p>These next two weeks should tell something about them. They had crept within one game of .500 twice within the last 10 days, only to drop back down the ladder over their last two games to 11-14-8.</p>
        <p>If anything, tonight's game confirmed the importance of Palffy; when he scores, the Islanders are 10-4-5.</p>
        <p>The Stars' defense ranks among the top teams in the league, though, and the Islanders were often listless against it. Defensively, the Islanders were fairly solid -- and also a little blessed -- an apparent first-period goal by Benoit Hogue was disallowed because Hogue was in the crease.</p>
        <p>That helped keep the score even through two periods, but Todd Harvey scored his first goal of the year on a blistering slap shot at 2:28 of the final period, waiting until a sliding Rich Pilon had cleared the left wing circle before he put the puck through Salo's pads. That goal gave the Stars a 2-1 lead that they held for much of the final 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>Armstrong gave the Islanders a flicker of hope, but Nieuwendyk took it away with a marvelous move in open ice.</p>
        <p>Still, Milbury wasn't as unhappy as he has been with some of the Islanders' losses. ''I would have been happier with a point,'' he said. ''If we can consider two games a losing streak, I'm a very lucky man.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOT</p>
        <p>DEREK KING, who has 11 goals, has gone 12 games without scoring one.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
