<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raw Sewage Poses Threat to Kentucky County</title>
    <meta content="22SEWE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="897133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kentucky</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Letcher County (Ky)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E3D71231F931A15751C1A960958260" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raw Sewage Poses Threat to Kentucky County</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WHITESBURG, Ky.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kentucky officials say environmental cleanup is fundamental to bringing Letcher County out of poverty through tourism and new industry; county's fiscal court is enforcing ordinance requiring garbage collection, and citizens group has drafted plan for raw sewage problem (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few sights in eastern Kentucky are more beautiful than the view from Pine Mountain in Letcher County. From the peak, acres of illegal garbage dumps blend with jagged hills, and raw sewage that chokes the rivers appears to be harmless silt.</p>
        <p>The few visitors to the poverty-stricken area, however, quickly discover its dirty secrets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few sights in eastern Kentucky are more beautiful than the view from Pine Mountain in Letcher County. From the peak, acres of illegal garbage dumps blend with jagged hills, and raw sewage that chokes the rivers appears to be harmless silt.</p>
        <p>The few visitors to the poverty-stricken area, however, quickly discover its dirty secrets.</p>
        <p>State officials see an environmental cleanup as fundamental to bringing the area out of poverty through tourism and new industry. James Bickford, the state's top environmental official, said no one would want to visit before a cleanup.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, the county's fiscal court, which governs the area, started enforcing an ordinance requiring garbage collection, and a citizens' group has drafted a plan for the sewage problem. ''We want to see if we can get some other people in some other counties to do the same kind of thing,'' Mr. Bickford said.</p>
        <p>The sewage spills from thousands of houses lacking septic systems or access to treatment plants. Many toilets in the region drain through ''straight pipes'' directly into the nearest creek. In Letcher, officials estimate that 100,000 gallons a day flows into streams, poisoning wells and sickening residents.</p>
        <p>Water officials say they are not sure what treatment systems would work for the rugged terrain and odd housing patterns. Health inspectors have been reluctant to impose fines on residents who cannot afford them.</p>
        <p>The sewage trickles into the Kentucky, Big Sandy and Cumberland Rivers, which have their headwaters in this region. The Kentucky is the source of drinking water for 600,000 households in towns like Whitesburg, Hazard and Lexington.</p>
        <p>The cities' heavy chlorine use leads many residents to avoid drinking tap water.</p>
        <p>Thousand of wells are also contaminated, and a high number of hepatitis infections are reported. Health officials estimate that almost every hand-dug well and at least 20 percent of Letcher's drilled wells are contaminated with fecal coliform bacteria. Other counties have even worse problems, state officials said.</p>
        <p>Forty percent of the 31,000 people in Letcher live in coal camps, built around the turn of the century. None had sewer systems and few properties have enough room for septic systems. But the sewage flow grew too much for the pits, leading to the installation of the pipes.</p>
        <p>The fiscal court has created the first countywide sewer and water district in eastern Kentucky.</p>
        <p>Judge-Executive Carroll Smith, the head of the court, appointed a planning group that said sewer plants could serve at least half the houses with straight pipes. The group suggested a five-stage $62 million plan over 20 years.</p>
        <p>''Most judges who even talk about mandatory sewers haven't been re-elected,'' said Hugh Archer, the executive director of the Kentucky River Authority. ''Carroll Smith has been really brave.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bickford proposed a plan, later endorsed by Gov. Paul Patton, that would direct millions in state aid to clean up a ''model'' community. Although Mr. Bickford has not named the site, people in Letcher feel he had them in mind, because he announced the idea for a model days after his visit there.</p>
        <p>But many continue to refuse to pay their garbage bills, viewing mandatory collection as one more regulation to ignore. Some still dump garbage in their own hollows.</p>
        <p>The chairman of the study group, James McAuley, said he thought most people would be willing to pay a little to clean up the streams. Mr. McAuley, the grocer in Kona, discussed the sewer plan with a customer. ''As long as it's free,'' the customer said as he left, ''go ahead.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
