<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democracy's Uneasy Steps in Islamic World</title>
    <meta content="23BAHR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/23/international/middleeast/23FORCE-BAHR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20011130T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="THE FORCE OF ISLAM: Mosque and State" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1345398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kuwait</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bahrain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bin Laden, Osama</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bahrain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Bahrain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bahrain</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E5D8153AF930A15752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="2126" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democracy's Uneasy Steps in Islamic World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Democracy's Uneasy Steps in Islamic World</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>KUWAIT, Nov. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special report, The Force of Islam, notes that most Muslim countries are ruled by kings, emirs and religious leaders, posing fundamental question: is democracy compatible with Islam? there are ripples of openness in Kuwait and Bahrain, but throughout most of Muslim world, tension between Islam and modernity remains profound; some observers suggest that it is absence of Reformation in history of Islam that helps explain why universities in Arab world that were once most advanced centers of learning have turned inward and backward; some of resonance of Osama bin Laden's appeal to Arab masses lies in fact that masses have little alternative means of political expression; Islam offers code for many aspects of life that is often enforced in legal system; efforts to marry it with democracy face many tests; one is how far rulers accustomed to obedience might be willing to share power, and how far Islamists might challenge rulers by exploiting shared power to impose their own will; chart showing spectrum of governments in Islamic world; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a region coping with Islamist movements, tiny Bahrain has made a strategic shift: from ruthlessness to openness.</p>
        <p>''We never dreamed it could happen so fast,'' said Muhammad al-Jamri, a recently freed political prisoner, his easy manner reflecting the new atmosphere of good will. Under a new emir, the ruling Sunni Muslim family has freed Mr. Jamri and hundreds of others who were jailed in the quashing of a Shiite Muslim uprising several years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a region coping with Islamist movements, tiny Bahrain has made a strategic shift: from ruthlessness to openness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a region coping with Islamist movements, tiny Bahrain has made a strategic shift: from ruthlessness to openness.</p>
        <p>''We never dreamed it could happen so fast,'' said Muhammad al-Jamri, a recently freed political prisoner, his easy manner reflecting the new atmosphere of good will. Under a new emir, the ruling Sunni Muslim family has freed Mr. Jamri and hundreds of others who were jailed in the quashing of a Shiite Muslim uprising several years ago.</p>
        <p>Bahrain's experiment in new freedoms is echoed to some degree in Kuwait and just a few other Arab lands. But with most Muslim countries ruled by kings, emirs and religious leaders, the situation poses a fundamental question: Is democracy compatible with Islam?</p>
        <p>In Kuwait -- a nation that is further along than Bahrain democratically -- many people say that because of Islamic fundamentalism, democratic dreams should be guarded to preserve liberty. ''The democracy has brought Islamists into the Parliament,'' said Ahmad E. Bishara, a liberal who leads Kuwait's National Democratic Union. ''You end up with a Parliament that legislates against public freedom.''</p>
        <p>As in Kuwait and Bahrain, the first ripples of openness have begun to reach other Arab shores. Qatar has promised to establish an elected parliament within two years; Saudi Arabia, a firm opponent of elections, has expanded the authority of an advisory council to the king.</p>
        <p>But throughout most of the Muslim world, the tension between Islam and modernity remains profound. Indeed, some observers have suggested since Sept. 11 that it is the absence of a Reformation in the history of Islam that helps explain why universities in the Arab world that were once the most advanced centers of learning have often turned inward and backward. It appears clear that some of the resonance of Osama bin Laden's appeal to the Arab masses lies in the very fact that those masses have little alternative means of political expression.</p>
        <p>In the Arab world, true democracy is scarcer than in any other part of the globe. The Persian Gulf is ruled by kings, emirs, sheiks and sultans. Elsewhere, leaders may be called president, like Hosni Mubarak of Egypt, but even they are strongmen who run for office unopposed.</p>
        <p>Islam offers a code for many aspects of life that is often enforced in a legal system, and efforts to marry it with democracy face many tests. One is how far rulers like Bahrain's emir, Sheik Hamad bin Isa al-Khalifa, so accustomed to obedience, might prove willing to share power, and similarly, how far Islamists like the freed Mr. Jamri might challenge them by exploiting the shared power to impose their own will.</p>
        <p>Just this year, Bahrain has welcomed home thousands from exile, scrapped emergency laws and promised to revive Parliament, shuttered since 1975, with elections open to all Bahrainis, men and women alike.</p>
        <p>''These leaders want democracy, but they want to take it to certain limits and then stop,'' said Ahmad M. al-Baghdadi, a professor of political science at Kuwait University. ''But the problem with democracy is not just that the people want one and two, but three and four, and five and six, and so on. And they begin to ask: 'Why are you the ruler, not me? Why should it be your son, not mine?' ''</p>
        <p>The Kuwaiti Parliament -- first established in 1961 and still the only fully elected Parliament in the gulf region (Iran's is partly appointed) -- is a raucous, unruly body with the power to pass laws and to challenge the government, which the emir appoints. He has dissolved Parliament three times in its history, usually to silence liberal dissent, only to reinstate it, usually in response to Western pressure.</p>
        <p>The Islamists have emerged as a powerful bloc, in a loose alliance with conservative Bedouin forces, and Parliament has been most visible as an obstacle to Western-style values. It has voted to require the separation of sexes at Kuwait University -- though that has not yet been carried out, both for financial reasons and because of government opposition -- and it has blocked a 1999 decree by the emir, Sheik Jaber al-Ahmad al-Sabah, to open elections to women.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the Kuwaiti Parliament and cabinet are embroiled in a dispute over whether to adopt Shariah as the legal system. Shariah is the religious legal code based on the rulings, called fatwas, of nonelected clerics, rather than the decisions of elected legislators. Walid Tabtabai, an Islamist member of Parliament, wants Kuwait to adopt the system, and said that if it was in effect, ''there would be no terrorism.''</p>
        <p>The Islamists' effort has brought loud protests from people like Mr. Bishara, the liberal, who asked, ''How can you be a democrat and follow a fatwa?''</p>
        <p>The government has blocked the change, but Kuwaiti Islamists are continuing to press for an ''adjustment'' of existing codes to make them consistent with religious laws, including barring banks from charging interest. They say their campaign reflects the will of the people, and would represent a triumph of democracy.</p>
        <p>''People coming from the West want to see Kuwait cut out as another piece of Western society, and that's not possible,'' said Naser J. al-Sane, an Islamist member of Parliament. ''You have to let people choose their way.''</p>
        <p>The Koran advises leaders to follow the practice of consultation, called shura, before making important decisions, but it is silent about how the consultation should take place. Dr. Sane and other Islamists cite democracy as the highest example of shura, saying that because some of the Prophet Muhammad's successors were elected by their peers, Islam places no obstacle to the direct election of leaders.</p>
        <p>But interpretations of the relationship between Islam and democracy are as varied as interpretations of Islam itself.</p>
        <p>Some rulers, like King Fahd of Saudi Arabia, have said flatly that democracy can have no place in Islam; for these rulers, an appointive council is sufficient for consultation.</p>
        <p>The Saudis adhere to strict Islamic law, and the ruling family and its backers say the Koranic injunction to ''obey God, obey the prophet, and obey the ruler'' justifies absolute rule.</p>
        <p>Secularists argue that democracy can succeed only if Islam is separated entirely from political life. Most others advocate coexistence, but their visions become tangled over the central question of which should take precedence, the will of the people or religious teachings.</p>
        <p>''You can have a democratic organization, but it must take its cues from Islam,'' said Khalid al-Essa, 61, a leader of Islam's conservative Salafi movement, who works barefoot in his office in Kuwait so that the floor is kept clean for prayer. Mr. Essa, an American-trained engineer, described Islam as ''a boundary condition'' for democracy.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Sheik Ahmad Fahd al-Sabah, Kuwait's information minister and a member of the ruling family, said the people's will must predominate.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes, when you speak with the people, they say we have to respect God's law,'' he said. ''We say you have to do it through democracy.''</p>
        <p>The basic principle of one person one vote frightens many Arabs, and for a practical reason. At a time when democracy is new and its institutions untested, and with many Arab societies divided among tribes or sects, or between modernists and traditionalists, there are concerns that majorities might become tyrannical.</p>
        <p>Such worries appear to explain why, in Kuwait for instance, open calls for the direct election of leaders have been rare.</p>
        <p>It is understood that ruling families are not eager to cede power, and that those who call for their ouster would be punished. But members of minority factions often welcome the monarchies as buffers that protect existing freedoms.</p>
        <p>''If Kuwait were a true democracy,'' Mr. Bishara said, ''I wouldn't be here talking to you.''</p>
        <p>Of all the Arab ruling families that might have reason to be wary of democracy, the Khalifa of Bahrain stand out.</p>
        <p>Lying just across a 15-mile causeway from Saudi Arabia, Bahrain is in many ways the antithesis of its neighbor. A magnet for both foreigners and Arabs because of its relaxed atmosphere and the ready availability of alcohol, it has served for years as the region's main banking center and as the headquarters of the United States Fifth Fleet.</p>
        <p>Beneath that facade is an imbalance unusual in the Arab world: Though power lies in the hands of the Khalifa family members and their fellow Sunnis, the large majority of the population of some 650,000 are Shiites, aggrieved because of a lack of wealth and privilege.</p>
        <p>Until the recent changes, Bahrain's solution to that imbalance was to silence dissent by exiling thousands of government critics, using emergency laws to arrest hundreds of others, and, in 1975, shutting down a Parliament that had existed for only one year. Under forces headed by a Briton, Ian Henderson, and composed mostly of Pakistani and other foreign troops, Bahrain was transformed into a high-security state by the late 1980's.</p>
        <p>By the mid 1990's, resentment had exploded in bombings, riots and other attacks that claimed 40 lives. When members of some leading Sunni families joined the Shiites by signing petitions urging the government to end its emergency laws and re-establish Parliament, they were fired or suspended from their government jobs. Foreign businesses began to move from Bahrain.</p>
        <p>Not until the death in 1999 of the old emir, Sheik Issa al-Khalifa, and the ascension of his son, Sheik Hamad, now 51, did the picture change in earnest, culminating in the announcement of last February: amnesty for the exiles, including some former Marxists; freedom for the political prisoners; municipal elections in 2002; and parliamentary elections in 2003.</p>
        <p>''The government tried its best to finish the uprising; it couldn't,'' said Mounira Fakhro, a Sunni who was allowed to resume her career as a university professor in February after a break of six years.</p>
        <p>''And the opposition tried its best to the make the government do its part,'' she said. ''That was when we reached this dead end. And thank God, the other emir died, and with the help of the West, I think, the new emir may be willing to give up what we want.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jamri, 42, who spent 10 years in jail, complained, though, that ''everything that has been offered has been offered on the basis of generosity, not on the basis of doing what people want.''</p>
        <p>''This is a Bedouin way of treating others,'' he added.</p>
        <p>''If this situation continues, and there are only gifts, and not rights, this will turn to resentment,'' he said. ''And that might turn into calls for a return to the power of people.''</p>
        <p>Articles in this series are examining growth in the influence of Islam. Later articles will focus on Islam and women, the place of Islam in the secular and democratic state of Turkey, the Taliban, the concept of jihad, or holy war, and the spread of Islam in Europe. Articles in this series and related coverage are available at:</p>
        <p>nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 30, 2001, Friday  A front-page article last Friday  about the prospects for democracy in Islamic countries referred incorrectly to the views of Mounira A. Fakhro, a professor at the University of Bahrain, about the nature of recent changes in her country. She expressed relief over the reform that followed the death of the late emir, Sheik Issa al-Khalifa, in 1999, but not relief over the death itself.</p>
        <p>A chart with the article included one country erroneously among those in which Muslims are a majority of the population. Only about 20 percent of Suriname's population is Muslim.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 30, 2001, Friday</p>
        <p>A front-page article last Friday  about the prospects for democracy in Islamic countries referred incorrectly to the views of Mounira A. Fakhro, a professor at the University of Bahrain, about the nature of recent changes in her country. She expressed relief over the reform that followed the death of the late emir, Sheik Issa al-Khalifa, in 1999, but not relief over the death itself.</p>
        <p>A chart with the article included one country erroneously among those in which Muslims are a majority of the population. Only about 20 percent of Suriname's population is Muslim.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
