<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the 104th Floor in Two Towers, a Boyfriend and a Brother Are Lost</title>
    <meta content="333468SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1345249"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: PORTRAITS OF GRIEF: THE VICTIMS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6D8173BF930A15752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="3053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the 104th Floor in Two Towers, a Boyfriend and a Brother Are Lost</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">These sketches were written by Adam Clymer, Sherri Day, Barnaby J. Feder, Constance L. Hays, Jan Hoffman, Dena Kleiman, Barbara Stewart and Yilu Zhao.</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Portraits of Grief: sketches of some of victims of Sept 11 attack on World Trade Center; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here are glimpses of some of the victims of the Sept. 11 attack on the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>FREDERICK COX  A 'Glutton for Life'</p>
        <p>Climb into that hammock between two trees on an island in Lake Winnepesaukee, N.H. Feel the soft summer stillness. Look up. A tile hanging from one tree reads, ''Do what you love, love what you do.''</p>
        <p>That was Frederick Cox's hammock, his motto, the tile he hung.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here are glimpses of some of the victims of the Sept. 11 attack on the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>FREDERICK COX  A 'Glutton for Life'</p>
        <p>Climb into that hammock between two trees on an island in Lake Winnepesaukee, N.H. Feel the soft summer stillness. Look up. A tile hanging from one tree reads, ''Do what you love, love what you do.''</p>
        <p>That was Frederick Cox's hammock, his motto, the tile he hung.</p>
        <p>Like his motto, Mr. Cox, 27, was a full-throttle enthusiast brushed by navet.</p>
        <p>Even though he sought the serenity of his family's summer home, he lived a Manhattan life of joyous clatter. Buoyantly confident, with his green eyes glowing with mischief, he made friends easily.</p>
        <p>Who could resist that pied-piper promise of adventure, the courtliness of a Georgia-bred gentleman, the charm of a super salesman?</p>
        <p>Not Annelise Peterson, his girlfriend, who described Mr. Cox, an investment banker at Sandler O'Neill, as a ''glutton for life'' -- a painter, writer, golfer, shopper, food lover. He reminded her of her older brother Davin, a trader for Cantor Fitzgerald. Both were tall, loyal, attentive.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Cox's parents divorced when he was 8, he gave his mother a rose every Valentine's Day. His father, the son said, was his best friend.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Cox and Davin Peterson, who dined with Ms. Peterson on Sept. 8, worked on the 104th floor at the World Trade Center -- Mr. Peterson in the north tower, Mr. Cox in the south tower.</p>
        <p>DAVIN PETERSON  A Gentle Giant</p>
        <p>It felt natural to look up to Davin Peterson: he was 6 feet 6 inches tall. But he was also comfortable as a leader and mediator of the four Peterson kids, his mother's stalwart and confidant when the family was cracked by divorce. He was calming, clear-headed, an old soul since childhood, but possessed of an exquisite sensitivity: when one sister was going through a rough time, he wept about it openly at work.</p>
        <p>At 25, he was a trader at Cantor Fitzgerald, although notions of his future were still forming. His travel lust had taken him to Vietnam, China, Scandinavia.</p>
        <p>With a deep interest in human rights, politics and economics, he considered starting a business in an impoverished country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson was also possessed of an antic sense of humor. He cooked anti-Thanksgiving meals -- one year, fajitas, another year, steak.</p>
        <p>He had an elaborate scheme for the secession of his native California, featuring himself as the head of a military coup. And he vowed to leave his life insurance to Rambo, his mother's beloved five-pound Yorkshire terrier.</p>
        <p>Really?</p>
        <p>Ah, got you!</p>
        <p>And whenever he did, Mr. Peterson, enormously pleased with himself, would dance a little jig, a gentle giant with size 16 feet.</p>
        <p>RONALD BUCCA  Rescuer and Counselor</p>
        <p>Ronald Bucca was nicknamed ''the Flying Fireman'' in 1986 after he fell spectacularly from a tenement fire escape, spun around a cable strung through the backyard and lived to tell the tale. And that was just one of his moments.</p>
        <p>His specialty was rescuing mankind from smoke and flames, but he did not mind scorching certain people with his wit.</p>
        <p>His colleagues collected ''Ron-isms.'' An example: ''This one is as sharp as a basketball.''</p>
        <p>He designed hats for other firemen with details that they found hilarious (but unfortunately, that were not printable).</p>
        <p>A firefighter for 23 years, the last nine as a fire marshal, he was also a nurse and a reservist in the United States Army's Special Forces.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bucca trained as an antiterrorist intelligence expert, and when the planes hit the towers on Sept. 11, he called his wife, Eve, and said he was heading to the scene.</p>
        <p>''He knew it was a terrorist attack,'' Mrs. Bucca said. ''He had been expecting something like that for a very long time.''</p>
        <p>Before that day, his final investigation had involved a young woman who set her former boyfriend's letters on fire and left them to burn in a toilet. He counseled her as a father might.</p>
        <p>''No guy is worth getting this upset over; don't be too concerned about this guy,'' he told her, said Keith O'Mara, his partner. ''There are a lot of fish in the sea. And if this should ever happen again, think about buying yourself a paper shredder.''</p>
        <p>KEVIN DONNELLY  Fun Is the Beach</p>
        <p>Fire may have provided Lt. Kevin Donnelly of Ladder Company 3 with his livelihood, but what he loved was water.</p>
        <p>Born under the hot July sun, he got a job as a lifeguard at the town pool in Wantagh, while still a teenager on Long Island, said his mother, Cecilia. As an adult, he found any excuse to head for the water, even when some other task beckoned.</p>
        <p>''He kept a bathing suit, a towel and goggles in his car at all times, just in case,'' said his longtime companion, Mary Coughlin, ''and in the summer, he'd add two beach chairs, a towel and a bathing suit for me.''</p>
        <p>The two of them might be driving along, on their way to Home Depot or some other store to run errands. And Lieutenant Donnelly, 43, would turn to her, and say: ''You know what? We can do this another time. Let's go to the beach.''</p>
        <p>He was not persnickety about his beaches, though he preferred those on the ocean. He was hoping to become a lifeguard again, on some Long Island strand. North Shore, South Shore. ''He wouldn't have cared what beach he ended up on,'' Ms. Coughlin said, ''as long as it was on the sand and near the water.''</p>
        <p>CALIXTO ANAYA JR.  Doing Things Right</p>
        <p>Calixto Anaya Jr.'s wife, Marie, remembers the New York City firefighter everyone knew as Charlie as ''very attentive to the little things that keep love alive,'' whether it was taking days off for activities with their three children or showing up with flowers when she did not expect them.</p>
        <p>''Charlie always wanted to do things the right way,'' Mrs. Anaya said. When they were married in 1990 in a simple civil service, Mr. Anaya insisted that they begin saving for the big church wedding her parents could not afford. Six months later, they marched down the aisle of St. Rita's Roman Catholic Church in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anaya, a former Marine who re-enlisted when the Persian Gulf War broke out in 1991, believed true patriotism meant flying the American flag, not only in front of their home in Suffern, N.Y., but also wherever the family came to rest on camping trips or jaunts to the beach.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anaya, 35, loved the Yankees in baseball and the Giants in football with similar exuberance. He preserved the hole he punched in his basement ceiling while celebrating the Yankees' World Series victory over the Mets last year.</p>
        <p>VIRGINIA M. JABLONSKI  The Early Bird</p>
        <p>Virginia M. Jablonski, an assistant vice president at Marsh &amp; McLennan, liked to get up at 5 a.m. and catch an early bus from her home in Matawan, N.J., to her office on the 94th floor of 1 World Trade Center. In recent months, that often meant slipping out while Barry, her husband of 21 years, was enjoying the extra sleep made possible by his recent retirement from Lucent Technologies.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, Mr. Jablonski is an astronomy buff. Having noted that the International Space Station was scheduled to pass directly overhead shortly before sunrise on Sept. 11, he got up with her that morning. He recalls their standing in their garden, marveling at the stars in the clear sky and sharing the feeling that it would be a good day.</p>
        <p>''She was a bubbly person who was always smiling,'' Mr. Jablonski said. ''Most people wouldn't know if she was angry.''</p>
        <p>No one could miss her passion for cats, though. Mrs. Jablonski, a 49-year-old Brooklyn native, filled their home with cat-themed decorations and doted on her two feline companions, Fred and Bill.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL A. TRINIDAD  Staying Friends</p>
        <p>When Michael A. Trinidad and Monique Ferrer divorced three years ago, they stayed friends. Ms. Ferrer got the custody of their two children, Thea, then 7, and Timothy, then 6, and it was understood that the children were ''theirs'' -- not ''his'' or ''hers.''</p>
        <p>Every other Friday, Mr. Trinidad would come to pick up the children for the weekend. ''He was like a big kid,'' Ms. Ferrer said. ''He would take them to the park, play ball games, call them silly names and just act silly.'' The three also went apple picking in upstate New York and sun-bathing on the Jersey Shore.</p>
        <p>After the first plane hit the trade center on Sept. 11, Mr. Trinidad, 33, who was working in telecommunications accounting for Cantor Fitzgerald, called Ms. Ferrer to say goodbye. '' 'What goodbye?' I asked him. 'Are you going anywhere?' '' Ms. Ferrer recalled asking him, unaware of the disaster.</p>
        <p>'' 'I love you, and I love the kids,' he said. 'I am not going to make it out.' Then he asked to talk to my husband,'' Ms. Ferrer said. ''Michael asked my husband to be his children's father and love them for him.''</p>
        <p>SIEW-NYA ANG  Missing Mommy</p>
        <p>It has been at least eight years since Siew-Nya Ang saw an R-rated movie. Ms. Ang relished family time and since her daughters Jeanee, 8, and Winnee, 4, were too young for movies with grown-up themes, she only watched family-oriented films.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ang, 37, also discouraged her husband, Kui-Liong Lee, from doing yardwork when he could be spending time with the family. ''She would say: 'Wake up early in the morning. You can mow the lawn when we're asleep,' '' Mr. Lee said.</p>
        <p>On weekdays, Ms. Ang left for her job as a technical analyst at Marsh USA while her family was sleeping. But every morning around 8, she called home to make sure her girls were properly equipped to handle a day of school and dance, piano, ice skating or gymnastics lessons.</p>
        <p>Since Sept. 11, the girls say good night to a picture of Ms. Ang, which hangs on the bedroom wall. Some nights, they complain to it, too. ''Sometimes I have to let them know that Mommy is in heaven and other than that I just don't know what to say,'' Mr. Lee said. ''Sometimes if they say 'I want mommy,' I can't do anything.''</p>
        <p>ANTHONY STARITA  Relaxing With a Cigar</p>
        <p>Cigars were a necessary accessory for Anthony Starita. He had one in his mouth when he went to beach, when he puttered around his backyard in Westfield, N.J., and when he relaxed on his deck every night after dinner. ''He liked the flavor,'' said his wife, Diane Starita. ''He didn't always actually smoke them, but he would just have one in his mouth to sort of chew on.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Starita, 35, also chewed on coffee straws, mostly when he got nervous about a deal at his job as a government bond trader at Cantor Fitzgerald. ''When he got a little nervous he put the straws in his mouth and he would start wiping his hands with napkins,'' said Eddie De Castro, Mr. Starita's longtime friend and former trading partner. ''Those were his two things.''</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Starita gave up his full-time golf membership at a country club so that he could spend more time with his wife and two children, Kaila, 6, and Jason, 3.</p>
        <p>After the terrorist attacks, Mrs. Starita told the children that their father had gone to heaven. Kaila wondered why ''does he have to be with God?'' Mrs. Starita said. ''My 3-year-old wanted to know if we could call Daddy in heaven.''</p>
        <p>MARGARET CONNER  Sailing Toward Renewal</p>
        <p>When Margaret Conner wanted to escape the chaos of everyday life, she fled her home in Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, and headed for her daughter's boat on Candlewood Lake in Brookfield, Conn. It did not matter that Mrs. Conner was prone to seasickness and could not swim. Sailing on the lake brought her peace and tranquillity.</p>
        <p>Back home, Mrs. Conner, 57, was the gatekeeper at Cantor Fitzgerald, a receptionist who was the first person people saw when they got off the elevator on the 103rd Floor of 1 World Trade Center. For many young women at the office, she was a relationship therapist.</p>
        <p>''She was just very open and very eager to be there for anyone,'' said her daughter, Corrine Bounty.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Conner and her husband, Frank Conner, were married for 13 years and spent nearly every moment of their free time together, often frequenting Broadway plays and dining out. Every day they recorded and watched Mrs. Conner's favorite soap opera, ''The Young and the Restless.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Conner was also committed to her daily Bible study. On Sept. 11 her study passage was about the healing and renewal of God.</p>
        <p>''I read this passage the next day and was furious with God,'' Mr. Conner said. ''After rereading the passage, I realized that God had fulfilled his message to her. She is now in a place where His ever-renewing life is coursing throughout her body.''</p>
        <p>JANE JOSIAH  Have Friends, Will Travel</p>
        <p>Last year, Jane Josiah began a series of visits to far-flung family and friends that did not end for nearly a year. She did not begin looking for work after being laid off last winter. Instead she flew from Texas, where she had moved seven years earlier, to Seattle to see her brother and sister-in-law.</p>
        <p>Soon after, she went to Washington for a few weeks with Jennifer and Kelly, her daughters. Then she stayed with friends in Philadelphia and Long Island.</p>
        <p>Ms. Josiah, 47, had a gift for making friends, loving them and kicking up her heels with them, said Debra Potash, who knew her 20 years.</p>
        <p>The visiting culminated with Ms. Josiah's 30th high school reunion in Levittown, on Long Island, where old friends persuaded her to come home. After one found her a job at Fiduciary Trust, she drove north to Mrs. Potash's home on Long Island. Her first day was Aug. 27.</p>
        <p>All the traveling had made Ms. Josiah's daughters a bit impatient. ''It was supposed to be a month,'' Jennifer said. ''Then two months. Then four.''</p>
        <p>Now, she said, the months her mother spent with the people she loved seem like an unmatchable gift.</p>
        <p>MARK BAVIS  Scouting Hockey Talent</p>
        <p>Mark Bavis, a hockey scout, was on his way to work on Sept. 11, flying west for the Los Angeles Kings training camp, where he would be checking on the progress of players the team had drafted on his advice. He took United Airlines Flight 175 from Boston.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bavis, 32, had starred for the Boston University Terriers from 1990 to 1993. He was ''a great defensive forward and a real smart playmaker,'' said his coach, Jack Parker.</p>
        <p>The coach used Mark and his twin brother, Mike, as a team to kill penalties. ''The Bavi, we called them,'' Mr. Parker said. ''They were always together.''</p>
        <p>Mike Bavis, an assistant to Mr. Parker, agreed. ''We were very close,'' he said. ''But we were competitive.''</p>
        <p>The scouting job, after a few years in minor league hockey and turns as assistant coach at Brown and Harvard, delighted his brother because of the travel it involved. ''He really enjoyed some of the finer places in our country and loved to have a good time,'' his brother said.</p>
        <p>RALPH GERHARDT  A Dream Fulfilled</p>
        <p>He delighted in bungee jumping and feeding sharks. At 6 feet 2 inches tall, Ralph Gerhardt enjoyed playing the part of daredevil and strong man. He had an impish sense of humor and a reputation for practical jokes.</p>
        <p>Still, he was an affectionate son, who called his parents in Toronto every day.</p>
        <p>He had grown up in Toronto, the son of German immigrants, but New York had always been his dream.</p>
        <p>And so last February -- when Mr. Gerhardt, a 34-year-old bond trader, was transferred by Cantor Fitzgerald to the 105th floor of the World Trade Center -- was one of the happiest times of his life.</p>
        <p>He was eager to show his parents that life -- ''my New York'' as he was so proud to call it.</p>
        <p>His parents came often to visit so he could show them the apartment he was fixing up on Lexington Avenue and 26th Street, the bicycle he liked to ride over to Central Park, the woman from Staten Island he had met at work, the many museums and monuments he prided himself on knowing, as well as the best tour guides.</p>
        <p>''It was the pinnacle,'' said his father, Hans Gerhardt, who last heard from his son at 8:48 a.m., moments after the plane hit. ''He said: 'Something just happened. I am O.K. We are evacuating. I will call you later.' ''</p>
        <p>FLORENCE M. GREGORY  The Stylings of Disco Flo</p>
        <p>Seated in what she thought was too formal a restaurant last winter at Christmas, Florence M. Gregory announced to companions that she was going outside to ask the Salvation Army band on the corner if they knew a certain song. Moments later, the band arrived at the restaurant, took the table next to hers, and played songs for everyone.</p>
        <p>''That was my sister,'' Maureen Petronis said. ''She could break the ice anywhere.''</p>
        <p>Miss Gregory, who was known as ''Disco Flo'' because of her taste in music, loved people. ''She was always smiling and laughing and joking,'' Mrs. Petronis said. ''People were drawn to her.''</p>
        <p>When she was not working at Aon, where she was a specialist in marine insurance, Miss Gregory, 38, could be found golfing, fishing, cooking, traveling and spending time with her two nieces and three nephews. A longtime resident of Breezy Point in Queens, she was one of three children of Florence and John Gregory.</p>
        <p>She was an excellent cook and took particular pleasure in preparing meals for family and friends. Her favorite holiday was St. Patrick's Day, when she would pull out all the stops with corned beef and cabbage.</p>
        <p>''She was a fabulous aunt,'' Mrs. Petronis said.</p>
        <p>The Confirmed Dead</p>
        <p>Following is the name of the person most recently confirmed to have died in the World Trade Center disaster, according to the New York City medical examiner's office, which said the victim's family had been notified.</p>
        <p>GRAY, James Michael</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: PORTRAITS OF GRIEF: THE VICTIMS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
