<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chairman Of ABB Hints At Revamping</title>
    <meta content="23ABB.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/23/business/worldbusiness/23ABB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1345298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abb Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dormann, Jurgen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D7143AF930A15752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chairman Of ABB Hints At Revamping</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chairman of ABB Hints at Revamping Swiss Concern Seeks to Regain Credibility</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Nov. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jurgen Dormann, taking over as ABB chairman, admits company has lost market credibility after series of reorganizations failed to halt slide in share price or restore profitability, interview; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One day after the chairman of ABB, Europe's largest electrical engineering group, resigned unexpectedly, his successor, Jürgen Dormann, acknowledged today that the company had lost ''the credibility of the market'' after a series of reorganizations failed to prevent a drastic slide in its share price or produce profits.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview from Zurich, Mr. Dormann also urged a review of the company's activities to ''focus on a smaller number of businesses and make them grow.'' In the past, said Mr. Dormann, who was already a board member, ''I don't think we have done our homework'' in seeking out businesses that had the potential to expand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One day after the head Europe's largest electrical engineering group resigned, his successor acknowledged that the company had lost "the credibility of the market."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One day after the chairman of ABB, Europe's largest electrical engineering group, resigned unexpectedly, his successor, Jürgen Dormann, acknowledged today that the company had lost ''the credibility of the market'' after a series of reorganizations failed to prevent a drastic slide in its share price or produce profits.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview from Zurich, Mr. Dormann also urged a review of the company's activities to ''focus on a smaller number of businesses and make them grow.'' In the past, said Mr. Dormann, who was already a board member, ''I don't think we have done our homework'' in seeking out businesses that had the potential to expand.</p>
        <p>He did not go into detail, but analysts have suggested that some of the company's activities in oil refining could be cut. Mr. Dormann, 60, took over from Percy Barnevik, 51, who at one time was seen as a corporate icon, a European version of John F. Welch Jr. of General Electric. Mr. Barnevik led the merger of Asea of Sweden and Brown Boveri of Switzerland to form ABB in 1987. The deal and a subsequent string of acquisitions became a business-school model of a huge cross-border merger. Mr. Barnevik had been chairman for five years and had earlier been chief executive for eight.</p>
        <p>An ABB executive called Mr. Barnevik's departure ''the end of an era,'' denoting the declining influence at ABB of Investor, which once controlled the company through a complicated stock structure. Mr. Barnevik is also chairman of Investor, which is based in Stockholm.</p>
        <p>ABB has been roiled in recent years by changes and upsets. Under Goran Lindahl, who became chief executive in 1996, ABB shed major power generation and transport businesses and sought to cast itself as a technology-based business. Late last year, Mr. Lindahl was succeeded by Jörgen Centerman, who went on to announce a decline in profits and 12,000 job cuts at the company, which operates in 100 countries with about 160,000 employees.</p>
        <p>As the company's share price fell to 9 Swiss francs last month from 54 Swiss francs in February 2000, Mr. Barnevik's continued presence as chairman drew criticism from the Swiss investor Martin Ebner, who owns a 10.1 percent stake compared with Investor's 5 percent. Mr. Ebner's BZ Bank in Zurich has welcomed Mr. Dormann's appointment.</p>
        <p>In the phone interview, Mr. Dormann, who is also chairman and chief executive of the French drug maker Aventis, said he had been approached six to eight weeks ago to take over as chairman, and he denied that he represented any block of shareholders. ''I'm a representative of all shareholders,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He forecast that the slowdown in engineering would last 12 to 24 months, but, asked what turnaround measures he would pursue most energetically, he declined to dwell on the job cuts.</p>
        <p>''We lost a little bit of the transparency and credibility of the market, and that's what we are going to change,'' he said, promising ''a sense of urgency'' in reviving the company's fortunes. Shares of ABB rose 1.2 Swiss francs, or 7 percent, to 19 Swiss francs.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
