<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outsize Talent Who Took The A Train To Anonymity</title>
    <meta content="06bell" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/06/arts/television/06bell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1824144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Strayhorn, Billy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4DA133FF935A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outsize Talent Who Took The A Train To Anonymity</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Outsize Talent Who Took the a Train to Anonymity</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In ''Visions of Jazz'' the gifted jazz critic Gary Giddins opens his essay on the composer Billy Strayhorn by noting that Strayhorn, who died on May 31, 1967, at 51, began his rebirth that day. His music has since been paid great tribute. The project of mythologizing Strayhorn has been a continuing affair, culminating in David Hajdu's acclaimed 1996 biography, ''Lush Life.'' It is revisited in a comprehensive if unintentionally undermining documentary by Robert Levi, appearing on PBS this evening, ''Billy Strayhorn: Lush Life.''</p>
        <p>It is virtually impossible to think of another 20th-century artist whose prodigious talents were matched by so overwhelming a sense of modesty and conflicted desire to recede. Strayhorn, who was African-American and gay, did not shun fame as much as he cultivated his own anonymity. For nearly 30 years, beginning in the late 1930s, he worked with Duke Ellington to produce many of the greatest jazz compositions of all time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>PBS’s documentary on the composer Billy Strayhorn and his association with Duke Ellington is comprehensive if unintentionally undermining.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In ''Visions of Jazz'' the gifted jazz critic Gary Giddins opens his essay on the composer Billy Strayhorn by noting that Strayhorn, who died on May 31, 1967, at 51, began his rebirth that day. His music has since been paid great tribute. The project of mythologizing Strayhorn has been a continuing affair, culminating in David Hajdu's acclaimed 1996 biography, ''Lush Life.'' It is revisited in a comprehensive if unintentionally undermining documentary by Robert Levi, appearing on PBS this evening, ''Billy Strayhorn: Lush Life.''</p>
        <p>It is virtually impossible to think of another 20th-century artist whose prodigious talents were matched by so overwhelming a sense of modesty and conflicted desire to recede. Strayhorn, who was African-American and gay, did not shun fame as much as he cultivated his own anonymity. For nearly 30 years, beginning in the late 1930s, he worked with Duke Ellington to produce many of the greatest jazz compositions of all time.</p>
        <p>Their pairing was arguably one of the most fruitful artistic collaborations of the last century. And if Strayhorn did not receive his due during his lifetime, it was in some strong sense, the documentary makes clear, not merely because of Ellington's domineering nature but a function of Strayhorn's complicity in his own effacement as well, easily submitting as he did to his partner's legendarily outsize ego. At one point, Strayhorn even allowed Ellington to be listed as co-writer for ''Something to Live For,'' a piece Strayhorn had written before they had even met.</p>
        <p>Strayhorn, the fourth of 10 children, was a prodigy. He composed the haunting and world-weary ''Lush Life'' as a teenager, a feat the producer Quincy Jones describes here as impressive and ''ridiculous.'' ''Billy Strayhorn: Lush Life'' is implicitly invested in the question of whether Strayhorn was Ellington's artistic superior and furthermore in what would have become of Strayhorn if he had disassociated himself from the partnership.</p>
        <p>The jazz historian Gunther Schuller speculated that Strayhorn might have achieved far greater fame if, for instance, Frank Sinatra had made ''Lush Life'' a hit. But what would it have mattered given Strayhorn's aversion to fame in the first place?</p>
        <p>The fact remains that Strayhorn composed hundreds of songs with Ellington and is connected to far fewer on his own. Only one, ''Lush Life,'' is singularly identified with him, free of any Ellington association. The magic of the Ellington orchestra was in the alchemy. Of all the great musicians who played for him only the tenor saxophonist Ben Webster went on to a career as successful as the one he had with the band.</p>
        <p>Critics have for decades considered Strayhorn among the greatest jazz composers, second only to Ellington. But by fixating on what might have been, Mr. Levi's film ends up inadvertently suggesting that somehow such an achievement is not enough. At one point the film invokes Elvis Costello to perform Strayhorn's rich ''Blood Count,'' composed on his death bed. No serious jazz lover needs Mr. Costello to validate Strayhorn's genius.</p>
        <p>Independent Lens  Billy Strayhorn: Lush Life</p>
        <p>On most PBS stations tonight (check local listings).</p>
        <p>Robert Levi, producer, director and writer; Lois Vossen, series executive producer. Produced by Washington Square Films and Independent Television Service.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
