<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democratic Support Wilts, Endangering Tax Relief Plan</title>
    <meta content="06property" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/06/nyregion/06property.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1824289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Codey, Richard J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Adler, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D7133FF935A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democratic Support Wilts, Endangering Tax Relief Plan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Democratic Support Wilts, Endangering Tax Relief Plan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, Feb. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What was to have been a routine vote for final approval of key property tax relief legislation backed by the governor and the Legislature bogged down in the Senate on Monday after the Democrats' support for the bill weakened.</p>
        <p>Late Monday night, the fate of the measure, which would give 95 percent of New Jersey's homeowners a tax credit of up to 20 percent and provide benefits to about a million renters, was unclear. The Senate recessed at 11 p.m. and planned to reconvene on Tuesday to reconsider the bill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRENTON, Feb. 5  What was to have been a routine vote for final approval of key property tax relief legislation backed by the governor and the Legislature bogged down in the Senate on Monday after the Democrats’ support for the bill weakened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What was to have been a routine vote for final approval of key property tax relief legislation backed by the governor and the Legislature bogged down in the Senate on Monday after the Democrats' support for the bill weakened.</p>
        <p>Late Monday night, the fate of the measure, which would give 95 percent of New Jersey's homeowners a tax credit of up to 20 percent and provide benefits to about a million renters, was unclear. The Senate recessed at 11 p.m. and planned to reconvene on Tuesday to reconsider the bill.</p>
        <p>In all, the measure, which was passed by a wide margin last week in the Assembly, would provide more than $2.2 billion in tax credits in the first year in an effort to ease property tax burdens.</p>
        <p>But the measure would also impose a 4 percent cap on annual increases in local government and school taxes, as a way of controlling future tax increases. That is perhaps the most controversial provision of the bill, with opponents charging that the list of local budget items that are exempt from the caps made the measure too porous to produce any real tax reductions.</p>
        <p>The bill, which Senate President Richard J. Codey has called the heart of the effort to ease property taxes, appeared to be in trouble when two Democratic senators -- John Adler of Cherry Hill and Nia Gill of Montclair -- spoke out against it. Mr. Adler criticized the measure as weak because of the exemptions, and Ms. Gill said it was unconstitutional, because it denied tax relief to those with incomes above $250,000 a year.</p>
        <p>The prospect of two defectors in the 40-member Senate, where Democrats have a one-vote edge, was alarming to Senate leaders and to Gov. Jon S. Corzine. Before recessing on Monday night, legislators looked for ways to extend the relief to the highest earners.</p>
        <p>Some lawmakers dismissed the developments as a simple dispute over language. Others suggested that the bill was kept from passing by behind-the-scenes horse-trading by lawmakers trying to win concessions from the Senate leadership and the governor on bills they considered more crucial to their constituents.</p>
        <p>But as those discussions expanded, others close to the discussions said the real dispute was over efforts by key Democrats to remove language on binding arbitration between local unions and municipalities.</p>
        <p>The language now simply advises state-appointed arbitrators to ''consider as a primary factor'' in their awards the legislation's efforts to cap increases in local property taxes at 4 percent annually.</p>
        <p>Municipal officials had originally sought an absolute mandate that the arbitrators keep their awards within the cap, said William Dressel, executive director of the League of Municipalities, but had accepted compromise language instead.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Dressel and others said, lawmakers were finding even that compromise too threatening to the collective-bargaining process, and were pulling away their support.</p>
        <p>At one point, the Senate president, Richard J. Codey, walked out of the Senate chamber and into the governor's office, where he remained for about 40 minutes. Mr. Codey would not discuss his talks with Mr. Corzine, but when he returned, he recessed the Senate for a few hours and summoned Democrats into a caucus.</p>
        <p>When the Senate resumed its session, it attempted to vote on the measure, only to find that four Democrats were now voting against it, and that more than a dozen Republicans were refraining from entering their votes on the tote board.</p>
        <p>The Republicans watched with some glee as Mr. Codey and his aides struggled in whispered conversations to sway the Democratic holdouts or attract support from Republicans.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
