<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Upheaval in the East;   Shadow of Eastern Europe Looms In Nightmares of Soviet Speakers</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="324146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLER, BILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIDASPOV, BORIS V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROVIKOV, VLADIMIR (AMB)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RYZHKOV, NIKOLAI I (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHEVARDNADZE, EDUARD A (MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD1238F934A35751C0A966958260" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Upheaval in the East;   Shadow of Eastern Europe Looms In Nightmares of Soviet Speakers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KELLER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KELLER, BILL</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Feb. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As the leaders of the Soviet Communist Party labored over their future course today, they confronted the tumult of Eastern Europe as a lesson and a threat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As the leaders of the Soviet Communist Party labored over their future course today, they confronted the tumult of Eastern Europe as a lesson and a threat.</p>
        <p>As the leaders of the Soviet Communist Party labored over their future course today, they confronted the tumult of Eastern Europe as a lesson and a threat.</p>
        <p>Throughout a day of impassioned debate, fears of Eastern Europe surfaced again and again - stark fears that the new shape of Europe, and especially Germany, could menace Soviet security, and more subtle fears that the Soviet Union may not be immune from similar upheaval.</p>
        <p>Vadim A. Medvedev, the party's ideology secretary, said that unless the Communists continue to open democratic channels for the public's discontent, the Soviet Union will go the way of Eastern Europe.</p>
        <p>''During the decades of distortions and stagnation, such a critical mass of explosive material has accumulated that further delay could have resulted in a shock of enormous strength,'' Mr. Medvedev said. ''Today we can see this clearly in the example of the countries of Eastern Europe.''</p>
        <p>The ideologist said that in order to ''prevent a catastrophe'' in the Soviet Union it was necessary ''to transform the impending explosion into a controlled reaction.''</p>
        <p>Justas Paleckis, a guest representing the Lithuanian Communist Party, said the tone of urgency at the party meeting was heightened by the recent memory of collapsing Communist governments from East Germany to Romania, and the nagging worry that the Soviet Union may not escape a similar fate.</p>
        <p>Diverting the Blame</p>
        <p>''Without a doubt, events in Eastern Europe gave a push to the plenum,'' Mr. Paleckis said. Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze insisted fervently that the demise of Communism in Eastern Europe was not Mr. Gorbachev's fault, implicitly acknowledging that some hard-liners in his audience think otherwise.</p>
        <p>''Perestroika should not be blamed for the destruction of the political structure of Europe,'' said the Foreign Minister, one of Mr. Gorbachev's closest confidants in the ruling party Politburo.</p>
        <p>''It has been destroyed by the will of peoples no longer willing to put up with violence,'' he said. ''The undermining of faith in a Socialism based on suppression and violence began in the 1940's, not in 1985,'' when Mr. Gorbachev came to power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shevardnadze said the leadership foresaw the coming changes in Eastern Europe, and fashioned a new policy of non-interference because ''it is easier to change our policies than their people.''</p>
        <p>Fears of 'a New Munich'</p>
        <p>The old guard and new guard of the Soviet leadership were evenly matched today in their horror of German reunification, which Mr. Gorbachev has faced with growing acquiescence.</p>
        <p>Yegor K. Ligachev, the Politburo's pillar of the orthodoxy, said Europe was speeding toward ''a new Munich.''</p>
        <p>''It would be unforgivable shortsightedness and error not to see that a Germany with huge economic and military potential is looming on the world horizon,'' Mr. Ligachev said, in an address guests said was interrupted three times by ovations.</p>
        <p>''I think it is the time to recognize this new danger and loudly proclaim it to the party and the people,'' he added, implying that Mr. Gorbachev had failed to do so.</p>
        <p>''The ghost of revanchism is roaming Europe, hand in hand with the ideas of unity and unification,'' agreed Mr. Shevardnadze, whose world outlook often seems diametrically opposed to Mr. Ligachev's. ''The hunger for justice is diluted by the hunger for political revenge. The new status of the German question has raised dangerous hopes for redrawing of borders.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev has been publicly cautious about reunification, stressing primarily his concern about the sanctity of postwar borders in Europe - including Soviet borders - without dwelling on the more visceral fear of a warlike, united Germany.</p>
        <p>Old Memories Die Hard</p>
        <p>In a meeting last week with Prime Minister Hans Modrow of East Germany, the Soviet leader was described as open to eventual reunification, and Mr. Modrow promptly went home to unveil his own version of a step-by-step German merger.</p>
        <p>But the speeches today, and the answering ovations, were a reminder that the reunification issue touches dark memories in this country, which lost 20 million people to the Nazis.</p>
        <p>The transformation of Europe arose again as speakers touched on the Lithuanian Communist Party's declaration of independence from Moscow, which is on the agenda when the party meeting continues Wednesday.</p>
        <p>In December the Lithuanian Communists, conceding that their Moscow connection was political poison in a republic where separatist sentiment runs high, broke away and adopted a platform just nominally Marxist.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shevardnadze said today he strongly opposed sanctions against the breakaway party, but he urged the Lithuanians to consider whether they wanted to isolate themselves in the growing turmoil of Europe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
