<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Little Pessimism From the Executive Suite</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="819802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="OUTLOOK '96: THE ECONOMY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORPORATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTEREST RATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NINETEEN HUNDRED NINETY-SIX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NINETEEN HUNDRED NINETY-FIVE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOBRZYNSKI, JUDITH H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOTABAERT, RICHARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODE, DAVID R DAVID R GOODE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E7D61539F931A35752C0A960958260" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Little Pessimism From the Executive Suite</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH H. DOBRZYNSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DOBRZYNSKI, JUDITH H;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS everyone knows, you can never satisfy the boss. Business was strong at many of America's big companies in 1995, and it is looking as good or better for 1996. Profits were bountiful, and this year they are again expected to outpace the consensus forecast for economic growth of 2 to 2.5 percent.</p>
        <p>But America's chief executives want more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS everyone knows, you can never satisfy the boss. Business was strong at many of America's big companies in 1995, and it is looking as good or better for 1996. Profits were bountiful, and this year they are again expected to outpace the consensus forecast for economic growth of 2 to 2.5 percent.</p>
        <p>But America's chief executives want more.</p>
        <p>They want lower interest rates. "If they come down 100 to 200 basis points,  this economy will really take off," J. Willard Marriott Jr., chairman and chief  executive of the Marriott Corporation, said several days before the Federal Reserve cut rates 25 basis points -- or hundredths of a percentage point -- last month.</p>
        <p>"The economy could grow 4 percent to 5 percent without reigniting inflation," he added. "This old myth of the minute you have growth of over 3 percent you get inflation doesn't make sense."</p>
        <p>Few executives, however, seem to be counting on the Fed chairman, Alan Greenspan, to bring down rates sharply. For now, they are basing their optimism  on payroll numbers, income statistics, the low inflation rate and what is in their order books.</p>
        <p>"We assume no decreases, but we are confident that 1996 is an election year," noted David R. Goode, chief executive of the Norfolk Southern Corporation, the big railroad. As a rule, the White House does everything in its power to produce a favorable economic climate in the months before the Presidential showdown.</p>
        <p>The election will bolster some businesses directly. Media companies and advertising agencies are bound to benefit. In Chicago, Richard Notabaert, the chief executive of the Ameritech Corporation, is reveling in the prospect of putting in telephone, fax and computer modem lines for politicians, delegates, media people and others attending the Democratic National Convention there this  summer.</p>
        <p>Ameritech -- like other communications companies -- was already doing just fine. "People are making more calls, buying second phone lines, and 12-year-olds today want to get on the Web and communicate," Mr. Notabaert said. "People now see communications as just a given, not an expense, so if the regional economy stays strong, we'll see an upward trajectory in revenue growth."</p>
        <p>Older industries cannot expect to be so buoyant, but they will probably rack  up healthy growth.</p>
        <p>From his office in Norfolk, Va., Mr. Goode gauges the industrial economy by watching rail-car loads. "We've seen some softening in the auto business, a little bit of softening in chemicals -- although that has come back lately -- and building and construction materials are a little weak," he said. "But that's all in comparison to a pretty strong last year and earlier this year."</p>
        <p>"And when we talk to our customers, it looks like we'll get a recovery in 1996," he added. "This is a temporary slowdown in what has been a very robust economic climate."</p>
        <p>"On a scale of 1 to 10, I'd give this economy a 9," said Thomas J. Usher, chief executive of the USX Corporation. "We were running at capacity in 1995, and we will in 1996, too."</p>
        <p>The appetite for steel seems to cut across the industrial spectrum. "It's not concentrated -- the auto business is not as good as it was a year ago, but it's  still good, construction looks pretty good, appliances are still strong and rail cars and barge cars are strong," Mr. Usher said.</p>
        <p>Others offer similar reports. The entertainment economy keeps expanding, securities firms and other financial institutions are faring well and the outlook for health care and pharmaceuticals is healthy.</p>
        <p>In retailing, "1996 will be a rerun of 1995," said David D. Glass, the chief  executive of Wal-Mart Stores. "There's not a lot of real strength, but business  is not bad."</p>
        <p>Mr. Glass faults the merchandise, not the customers, however. "It's not so much that the customer isn't willing to buy or can't buy," he said. "But there's nothing new to buy to drive the business."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, shopping as recreation has lost its allure.</p>
        <p>The new year "will see modest growth, low-single-digit growth in retail sales," Mr. Glass predicted.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Glass is gloomy, however, Mr. Marriott is not. Many of the dollars going unspent in the malls are funneling into hotels, restaurants and other areas of the tourism business. "We just had our best fall since the early 1980's," Mr. Marriott said. "I think 1996 looks real good. I see no reason why there shouldn't be double-digit earnings growth."</p>
        <p>In lodging, where Marriott manages hotels in all price categories, demand has finally caught up with supply. Companies, which cut back travel when the economy soured in the early 1990's, are sending people on the road again. Individuals are traveling more now, too.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marriott believes that after raising prices 6 to 7 percent in 1995, the market can bear another, though lower, price increase in 1996.</p>
        <p>That in itself is remarkable. Many chief executives envy the ability to raise prices once, let alone twice. Cars, industrial materials, consumer goods and food all encountered resistance from consumers when their prices were marked up.</p>
        <p>If the view from these corner offices is correct, the current softness in the economy is temporary, as many companies finish working off inventories that grew too plentiful. Once inventories are back to normal, the economy is expected to resume its climb. The main worry of these captains of industry lies overseas, in the potential problems facing Japan, Europe and other American trading partners.</p>
        <p>Their bottom line: if you liked 1995, you will like 1996. That's not bad, considering America's economic expansion turns five years old -- middle-aged, at best -- in April.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK '96: THE ECONOMY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
