<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cellphones Ringing at Home and at Work</title>
    <meta content="28WCOL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/28/jobs/28wcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1569882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="LIFE'S WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belkin, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Working Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Working Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2DD1030F93BA15750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cellphones Ringing at Home and at Work</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cellphones Ringing at Home and at Work</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lisa Belkin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belkin, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lisa Belkin column observes that when history of turn-of-the-century technology is written, it will show that blurring of line between life and work began with computers but became complete with cellphones; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SITTING at a meeting at a glossy conference table not long ago, I found myself listening to snatches of music. The ''1812'' Overture blared from someone's purse. A calypso tune trilled from someone else's pocket. Here a few bars from Bach; there a few chords from the Beatles. In between there were buzzes, beeps and dings. With each new sound or vibration, someone darted sheepishly from the room, holding a cellphone.</p>
        <p>When the history of turn-of-the-century technology is written, it will show that the blurring of the line between life and work began with computers but became complete with cellphones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The blurring of the line between life and work began with computers but has become complete with cellphones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SITTING at a meeting at a glossy conference table not long ago, I found myself listening to snatches of music. The ''1812'' Overture blared from someone's purse. A calypso tune trilled from someone else's pocket. Here a few bars from Bach; there a few chords from the Beatles. In between there were buzzes, beeps and dings. With each new sound or vibration, someone darted sheepishly from the room, holding a cellphone.</p>
        <p>When the history of turn-of-the-century technology is written, it will show that the blurring of the line between life and work began with computers but became complete with cellphones.</p>
        <p>''This thing that should be serving us has become our master,'' says Terry Phillips, now a television news writer in San Francisco, and one of the writers of ''Wireless Etiquette: A Guide to the Changing World of Instant Communication'' (Omnipoint Books: 1999.) Mr. Phillips says he was inspired to write that book after a meeting that should have been short but that stretched on for hours because everyone kept leaving to answer their phones.</p>
        <p>The book was an attempt to apply some rules of order to the world of cellphones, but it was ''a miserable failure,'' he says. ''I think people are more obsessed with their phones today than before the book came out.''</p>
        <p>There are two types of phone calls that bridge the realms of life and work. The first are business calls that poke their way into life. Marty Kotis is a master of these. The owner of a real estate development company in Greensboro, N.C., Mr. Kotis carries two cellphones at all times (''I can talk on one while checking e-mail or looking at a schedule with the other'') and has a third mobile phone, from a different provider, in his car (''It's useful in case one service isn't working in an area.'')</p>
        <p>''I've done deals while walking around in a Lowe's hardware,'' he says. ''I feel comfortable going through complex deals while pushing a shopping cart through a store.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kotis describes one recent lunch where all four people at the table ''were on the phone at the same time.'' He says that he will talk on his phone only if those he is with are talking on theirs, which, Mr. Phillips says, is a good rule.</p>
        <p>''There was this one couple I watched eating lunch,'' Mr. Phillips remembers. The man spent the better part of the meal on his cellphone, talking shop, and when he finally came up for air, his companion asked to borrow the gadget. ''She dumped it in a glass of water,'' he says. ''That was a great response. Kind of expensive, though.''</p>
        <p>Cellphones do not just bring the office home, however. They very often work the other way around, bringing our outside lives with us to the office.</p>
        <p>By way of full disclosure, I am far too guilty of this. I leave my phone on when I travel for work, and because my preteen children are struggling a bit with the exact meaning of ''very important,'' I have been interrupted during interviews to be asked whether chips and dip are allowed near the computer and whether the dog couldn't maybe wait a few hours to be walked.</p>
        <p>But fear of a real emergency keeps my phone on. It keeps Jodi O'Neill's on, too.</p>
        <p>''I never, never have my cellphone off at work,'' Ms. O'Neill, a senior account executive at Landau Public Relations in Cleveland, explained in an e-mail message. ''You never know when the school nurse is going to call. My cellphone makes my working motherhood possible.''</p>
        <p>Like my sons, however, many of us in the working world seem to have creative definitions of ''very important.'' Yvette Durant, an executive assistant at MJM Creative Services, a production and communications house, tells of shopping in a department store one day when ''the salesperson actually had his phone on and answered it,'' and began blithely chatting.</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Neill describes an intern in her office ''who sat in the conference room on her first day talking to her friends on the phone while she stuffed envelopes.''</p>
        <p>''Needless to say, she didn't last long.''</p>
        <p>Time was when personal calls were not allowed at the office. But what does a rule like that mean when employees bring their own phones along with them?</p>
        <p>Lydia Ramsey, author of ''Manners That Sell,'' (Longfellow Press: 2000) writes a weekly etiquette column for The Savannah Morning News and says the problem is not the high-tech cellphones, but rather, the absence of old-fashioned politeness.</p>
        <p>''People do things with cellphones that they never would have dreamt of doing with 'real phones,''' she says. ''Just because the cellphone rings doesn't mean you have to answer it.''</p>
        <p>LIFE'S WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
