<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="797277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7D71339F930A25753C1A963958260" item-length="582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Producer Prices Up 0.3%; Stocks and Bonds Rally Producer prices rose three-tenths of 1 percent in September, the biggest increase in eight months, but economists dismissed the jump as the result of only temporary factors, not growing inflation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Producer Prices Up 0.3%; Stocks and Bonds Rally Producer prices rose three-tenths of 1 percent in September, the biggest increase in eight months, but economists dismissed the jump as the result of only temporary factors, not growing inflation.</p>
        <p>Economists said that the increase mainly reflected short-term surges in the cost of vegetables and other food as well as the effect of seasonal adjustment,  but many products posted declines. "Inflation fundamentals look as good as they have in 30 years," one economist said. [D2.]</p>
        <p>The report lifted the stock market as the Dow industrials rose 29.63 points, to  4,764.88, and the Nasdaq index climbed 14.06 points, to 1,015.63. On the bond market, the yield on 30-year Treasuries fell to 6.39 percent, its lowest since Feb. 7, 1994. [D8.]</p>
        <p>Paine Webber Earnings Nearly Triple  Paine Webber surprised Wall Street by reporting that third-quarter earnings nearly tripled to $782 million, or 71 cents a share, helped by the surging stock markets, lower interest rates and a flood of money flowing into mutual funds. Its stock hit a new high for the year before closing at $21.375, up $1.75, or 9  percent. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Texas Instruments Profits Jump  Texas Instruments reported that its third-quarter earnings rose 55 percent to $289 million, or $1.48 a share, on soaring demand for computer chips around the  world. [D4.]</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T Names Top Executives  AT&amp;T named one of its top executives to run its core communication company and an outsider to head the equipment business that will be spun off next year. Also, the F.C.C. freed AT&amp;T from the last remnants of rate regulations imposed in 1984. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Coffee Exchange Stays in New York  The Coffee, Sugar and Cocoa Exchange has decided to cancel its plans to move to  Jersey City and will instead build a new trading center in Manhattan. [B1.]</p>
        <p>J. P. Morgan Earnings Up 10%  J. P. Morgan said its third-quarter net income rose 10 percent to $360 million,  or $1.78 a share, its best results since 1993. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Petrie Retail Files for Bankruptcy  Petrie Retail sought protection from its creditors in a bankruptcy filing, and said it has obtained a $115 million credit line from Chemical Bank. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Sybase Net Income Plunges 95%  Sybase's third-quarter earnings fell 95 percent to $1.14 million, or 2 cents a share. Revenue rose 7 percent to $233.1 million. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Xerox Introduces Digital Copiers  Xerox introduced the first of a line of digital copier-printers that are designed to be connected to office computer networks. The two new machines differ from traditional copiers because they can receive documents directly from desktop computers, store them in memory and print them as ordered. [D8.]</p>
        <p>Turner Offers to Take Pay Cut  In a speech, Ted Turner defended the tens of millions of dollars that are to be  paid to Michael R. Milken, an adviser on the proposed $7.4 billion takeover of Turner Broadcasting by Time Warner, and offered to cut his own pay package, which is reportedly more than $100 million. [D5.]</p>
        <p>Britain to Monitor Salomon Unit  British regulators plan to monitor the invest ment business of Salomon Brothers  Interna tional for a year. The firm, an arm of Salomon Inc., lost $126 million last year. [D15.].</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
