<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bond Prices Stage a Broad Retreat</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="556703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOND PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DF173AF935A2575AC0A964958260" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bond Prices Stage a Broad Retreat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bond market, many traders are saying, has had too much of a good thing: bad news on the economy and positive news on inflation. And now, after a vibrant rally, slow economic growth and declining inflation is just not enough to keep the climb going.</p>
        <p>The economic data on retail sales and inflation released yesterday should have been positive for the bond market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The bond market, many traders are saying, has had too much of a good thing: bad news on the economy and positive news on inflation. And now, after a vibrant rally, slow economic growth and declining inflation is just not enough to keep the climb going.</p>
        <p>The economic data on retail sales and inflation released yesterday should have been positive for the bond market.</p>
        <p>Retail sales fell five-tenths of 1 percent in August, and, despite a revised 1 percent growth in July, the totals for the two months were still sluggish.</p>
        <p>On the inflation front, the Consumer Price Index was up three-tenths of 1 percent in August. Prices excluding food and energy are up just 3.5 percent in the last 12 months. In the last three months, these prices are up at an annual rate of just 2.5 percent.</p>
        <p>But the bond market paid no heed yesterday. The 30-year bond gave up all of Monday's gains and more, with its price falling 22/32 in secondary trading to yield 7.30 percent, a jump from 7.25 percent Monday.</p>
        <p>The price fall, however, was across the board and even with another cut in interest rates by the Federal Reserve Reserve still possible, bill rates jumped.</p>
        <p>"We need sensational inflation news and we need seriously weak economic news," said, said Joseph Liro, the chief economist at S. G Warburg &amp; Company in New York. "The market needs bigger and bigger fixes of slow economic data to sustain this."</p>
        <p>Jay Goldinger, a bond trader at Capital Insight in Los Angeles, lamented, "How much better can the news get?"</p>
        <p>Traders attributed yesterday's plunge tothe market's numbness to economic data and a series of other factors, including an overly optimistic reaction to the German interest rate cut Monday and a heavy supply of corporate bonds in the market.</p>
        <p>There were also signs that some investors were considering moving money to Europe, where the promise of a further decline in interest rates means the opportunity for large capital gains.</p>
        <p>The market, according to some traders, also got a bit of indigestion from the issue of $2 billion in five-year global bonds by the Canadian province of Ontario. While one of the two lead underwriters, Merrill Lynch, said it was happy with the big deal, some other traders said they were having trouble selling it.</p>
        <p>"It has been tough sledding," said one trader involved in the deal. "The pricing was right. But with the benefit of hindsight, the size was too big. It is a buyer's market out there and investors can be selective."</p>
        <p>The bonds, with Goldman, Sachs as the other lead underwriter, were priced to yield 48 basis points over the comparable Treasury security. The 5.625 percent five-year Treasury note was priced to yield 5.34 percent in late trading yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Ontario deal was the centerpiece of a day where corporate isses totaled about $3.2 billion, as corporations sought to beneift from some of the lowest interest rates in years.</p>
        <p>But this large supply of corporate notes and bonds is forcing many dealers who buy them to hedge their exposure by selling Treasury securities and this has accounted for some of the downward pressure in the Government market, traders said.</p>
        <p>Among some of the other corporate deals were $300 million in 12-year subordinated debt by Conagra Inc.; $300 million in 10-year notes by the Rockwell Internaitonal Corporation and $250 of 33-year bonds by the Pacific Gas and Electric Company.</p>
        <p>Another factor in the market, traders said, was the selling after some knee-jerk buying, especially in Japan and Europe, after Germany announced its rate cuts on Sunday, but before the actual size of the cut was disclosed Monday.</p>
        <p>While the switch in policy by the German central bank was surprising and very significant, the small half- percentage- point cut in rates disappointed many investors.</p>
        <p>"Its been overestimated in its import, especially in the United States," said Peter Roge, the senior vice president for economics at Swiss Bank in Basel. "A very large difference does remain between the U.S. dollar interest rates and German mark interest rates. So we will continue to suffer from a weak dollar for some time to come." Foreign Bonds</p>
        <p>Bonds fell sharply in Britain, as some of the euphoria over the German rate cuts subsided. Prices were down about a point on the day as the yield on the current 10-year bond, or gild, jumped to 9.27 percent from 9.07 percent in early trading.</p>
        <p>After rallying yesterday, the British pound fell to the bottom of its allowed trading range in the European Monetary System, raising the possibility that the government might have to raise interest rates to defend the pound.</p>
        <p>In France, bond prices were also off, but not as much as in Britain. The yield on the 10-year bond due in November 2002 was up to 8.67 percent from 8.64 percent.</p>
        <p>In Germany, bonds bounced back from early declines to close little changed on the day.  CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
