<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Biaggi Fails in His Bid to Return to Congress</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="556728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: 17TH DISTRICT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BIAGGI, MARIO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ENGEL, ELIOT (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNET, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DC153DF935A2575AC0A964958260" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Biaggi Fails in His Bid to Return to Congress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BENNET, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having tested the limits of political redemption, Mario Biaggi wearily conceded last night that voters' unwillingness to forgive and forget his felonies contributed to his overwhelming defeat in the Democratic primary in the 17th District to the incumbent, Eliot L. Engel.</p>
        <p>"This would have been a classic illustration of society practicing what society preaches," Mr. Biaggi said. "There are millions of people out there who have had traffic with the law."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Having tested the limits of political redemption, Mario Biaggi wearily conceded last night that voters' unwillingness to forgive and forget his felonies contributed to his overwhelming defeat in the Democratic primary in the 17th District to the incumbent, Eliot L. Engel.</p>
        <p>"This would have been a classic illustration of society practicing what society preaches," Mr. Biaggi said. "There are millions of people out there who have had traffic with the law."</p>
        <p>Leaning heavily on his silver crutches as he addressed about 200 diehard, nostalgic supporters who gathered in the Blue Room of Eastwood Manor, a catering service in the Eastchester section of the Bronx, Mr. Biaggi declared that he considered the race a success. 'My Voice Was Not Stilled'</p>
        <p>"Even though I lost this election, I was not defeated," said Mr. Biaggi, his trademark red handkerchief boiling from his breast pocket. "My voice was not stilled and my actions were not stayed, and they never will be."</p>
        <p>While he did not rule out another race in the future, Mr. Biaggi, 74 years old, said he would probably retire from politics to finish a book and perhaps to teach.</p>
        <p>A veteran police officer with a penchant for double-breasted blazers and a passion for old-style, pothole-fixing politics, Mr. Biaggi campaigned vigorously for the Congressional seat he held for 10 terms. But he could not overcome obstacles that included his convictions for bribery, extortion and other crimes, and the redrawing of his old district this year in a way that diluted his traditional base.</p>
        <p>"They definitely cut the heart of this people out," said Joseph Polizzi, 44, whose father served as a police officer with Mr. Biaggi. "Everyone who did vote for him could point to an immediate family member or close friend Mario helped."</p>
        <p>As he campaigned in the Bronx, Mr. Biaggi may have been showered with cries of "Mariooo" by those who remembered old favors, but the 17th District, which slices through southern Westchester County before sweeping down through the northern Bronx, is now two-thirds black and Hispanic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Biaggi was convicted in two trials on charges that he accepted a free vacation and $1.8 million in bribes, among other crimes. In 1989 he was sentenced to eight years in prison. Last year, though, a judge, worried about Mr. Biaggi's weak heart and nerve damage in his legs, freed him after 26 months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Engel hammered away at Mr. Biaggi's criminal record and his miraculous recuperation once he passed beyond the prison walls.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Mr. Biaggi said the criticisms echoed by some voters had hurt.</p>
        <p>"Every once in a while you get cruel, cruel approaches that are needless," Mr. Biaggi said. He once again maintained he was wrongly convicted and accused Mr. Engel of misleading voters about how he got out of prison.</p>
        <p>"When I came home the furthest thing from my mind was running for office or anything else," Mr. Biaggi said. "I was a sick puppy, no question about it."</p>
        <p>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: 17TH DISTRICT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
