<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turning Without Telling</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="314633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="NEW JERSEY OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAMIL, IRVING</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF1F3AF934A35752C0A966958260" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turning Without Telling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Irving Kamil; Irving Kamil lives in Cliffside Park.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAMIL, IRVING</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE major automobile companies can easily reduce the cost of their cars by simply removing all directional signals. No one uses them anyway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE major automobile companies can easily reduce the cost of their cars by simply removing all directional signals. No one uses them anyway.</p>
        <p>THE major automobile companies can easily reduce the cost of their cars by simply removing all directional signals. No one uses them anyway.</p>
        <p>This phenomenon is apparent to anyone driving along the streets or highways of the New York metropolitan area. Cars change lanes without warning. Left turns are made without a moment's hesitation, more often than not from the right lane, leaving the trailing vehicle to test its brakes in extremis, with the distressed car frequently assuming the position of a frightened stallion or of an antelope stretching to chew leaves from the top branches of a tall tree.</p>
        <p>Cars pull onto the shoulder to draw a breath, or to examine an accident in the opposite lane, or to wave to a nodding acquaintance, or merely to keep the car behind on its toes - never, of course, even pausing to consider the possibility of indicating that a move is being anticipated. When I learned to drive, there were no directional signals in automobiles. Instead, I was taught to use my left arm to let the fellow behind me know that there was intelligent life in my vehicle.</p>
        <p>Driving instruction included a veritable arm ballet of assorted positions. Extend your arm if you intend to make a left turn; bend it upward when about to turn right; wave it about if slowing down; splay those fingers before stopping.</p>
        <p>I felt like nothing so much as a one-armed cheerleader, but the hardest part was dealing with my fellow drivers, who seemed incapable of mastering the art at all. I was a batter watching a first base coach with St. Vitus's dance sending signals to the plate.</p>
        <p>Detroit, of course, came to my rescue. My next car had, miracle of miracles, directional signals. No longer would I have to explain to my doctor how I could come down with frostbite only in my left arm. All I needed to do was flick the bar, and the lights on the rear of the car would tell the fellow tailgating me what I had in mind.</p>
        <p>It was a dream come true. The automobile cost a bit more, but think of the savings in doctor's bills.</p>
        <p>Except that the bar didn't turn itself back after I had made my turn. Once lifted, the bar stayed lifted until I remembered to return it to the horizontal position once again. And remembering was quite another problem. I once drove the full length of the Connecticut Turnpike with my right turn signal blinking, all the while wondering why other drivers were waving their fists at me when they passed.</p>
        <p>Once again, Detroit to the rescue. Full service directionals were installed on cars, directionals that not only signaled to the cars behind me, but also remembered to return to the horizontal position after I had completed my turn. The Age of Aquarius. All my needs had been met. I was a truly happy man.</p>
        <p>Naturally, there was a slight additional cost for this convenience, but who said paradise was cheap?</p>
        <p>Now that drivers have given up the use of this wonderful device, I suspect that the gremlins in Auto City are already hard at work on the next generation of directional signals. These will flick themselves on and off automatically, not requiring that an absentminded (or merely ornery?) driver give them that little push. Such signals will read the driver's mind, translate intentions into action, and activate the signal without human help.</p>
        <p>Another miracle in the making, and at a slight additional cost, I need not add.</p>
        <p>I suspect that, after a while, the indefatigable American driver will discover a way to circumvent even this ultimate development in safe driving technology. There is little hope. Man shows every evidence of being a self-destructive animal. And there is no such thing as a driver-proof car. At least, not yet.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
