<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Kidd and Martin Show Takes Over in Overtime</title>
    <meta content="20NETS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/20/sports/basketball/20NETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1353017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Timberwolves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Minnesota Timberwolves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Minnesota Timberwolves</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0DB103EF933A15751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1159" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Kidd and Martin Show Takes Over in Overtime</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kidd and Martin Take Over in Overtime</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Dec. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Nets defeat Minnesota Timberwolves, 117-112; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kenyon Martin raced to find Jason Kidd at midcourt and slammed him for a heartfelt hug shortly after they had decided the Nets' most dramatic victory of the season with a stunning steal and layup and and then a slam-dunk play against the Minnesota Timberwolves.</p>
        <p>Their electricity sizzled back and forth that moment, just as it had all night. ''Jason and Kenyon were just fantastic,'' Nets Coach Byron Scott said. ''They didn't want to lose this basketball game.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kenyon Martin and Jason Kidd clinched the Nets' most dramatic victory of the season on a stunning steal and slam-dunk play in overtime as New Jersey topped Minnesota.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kenyon Martin raced to find Jason Kidd at midcourt and slammed him for a heartfelt hug shortly after they had decided the Nets' most dramatic victory of the season with a stunning steal and layup and and then a slam-dunk play against the Minnesota Timberwolves.</p>
        <p>Their electricity sizzled back and forth that moment, just as it had all night. ''Jason and Kenyon were just fantastic,'' Nets Coach Byron Scott said. ''They didn't want to lose this basketball game.''</p>
        <p>They did not. Kidd scored a season-high 33 points, 25 after halftime, and Martin scored a career-high 31 points, most memorably on rim-rattling dunks. Each scored 6 points in overtime as they lifted the Nets to a 117-112 victory over the Timberwolves in front of a spirited crowd of 12,810 at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>It was a game the Nets nearly lost by squandering a 19-point fourth-quarter lead and by making just 9 of 16 free throws in the final 7 minutes 48 seconds of the game. But Martin's emotion and Kidd's cool saved the Nets and lifted them to another level of legitimacy.</p>
        <p>The Nets won their fourth straight game and improved to 16-7, the best record in the Eastern Conference and they showed resiliency by downing Minnesota (16-8), a heavyweight from the Western Conference.</p>
        <p>When they entered overtime, it looked as if the Timberwolves would steal the Nets' newfound credibility. They had the momentum. But Martin and Kidd had other thoughts. ''I told him, 'We're not losing this game,' '' Martin said. ''And J was like: 'No, we're not. We'll do what we have to do.' ''</p>
        <p>With 1:10 remaining in overtime, Martin dunked and was fouled for a 110-110 tie and set up a possible 3-point play. But he missed the free throw. The Nets would have to rely on defense. With just under a minute to play, Kevin Garnett (who led Minnesota with 29 points and 21 rebounds), was backing into the basket, but Kidd closed in for the double team, pounced on Garnett's dribble and poked the ball away.</p>
        <p>Kidd collected the ball and sprinted downcourt, past three defenders for the layup, giving the Nets a 112-110 lead with 56.1 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>''It was one of those gamble situations,'' Kidd said. ''I got my hand on it at first and he kind of lost control, so I tried to get it and I got lucky and I came up with a steal and I just tried to push it. And I think that helped us win the game.''</p>
        <p>Kidd's next play did seal the victory. With 30.6 seconds remaining, the Nets forced Minnesota's Wally Szczerbiak to throw up a 3-pointer at the top of the arc that bounced off the rim. Kidd was there to grab the rebound. He hurled a pass downcourt for Martin, all alone. Martin punctuated it with a two-handed slam, hanging on the rim and roaring. ''You just have nights like that,'' Martin said. ''He made a shot, I made a shot, it was like taking turns.''</p>
        <p>Beneath the victory, though, was an ugly statistic: the Nets shot 21 for 36, 58.3 percent, from the free-throw line. ''I don't know if guys are just tired or it's lack of concentration or bad free-throw shooters,'' Scott said. ''We'll have a one-hour practice tomorrow and it will be all free-throw shooting.''</p>
        <p>But he was more than mollified by Martin and Kidd, who combined to shoot 23 for 39 from the field.</p>
        <p>''They both knew they had it going, so they kind of fed off each other,'' Scott said. ''I tried to get him and Kenyon playing a two-man game down the stretch as much as possible because both guys were having one of those nights. So you have to go with the flow.''</p>
        <p>Both players knew how to turn on the flow at the right time. Kidd missed his first of two free throws in the final 23.3 seconds of regulation, leaving the Nets with just a 103-101 lead after Todd MacCulloch had already missed two pairs of free throws. Garnett tied the game with an 8-foot turnaround jumper with 10.5 seconds to go.</p>
        <p>Kidd's 3-pointer missed with one second remaining in regulation.</p>
        <p>''We had everything going against us, especially in overtime,'' Scott said. ''To come away with a win the way we did tonight was fantastic.''</p>
        <p>Kidd once again was the steadying and crushing force for the Nets, finishing with eight assists, four steals and six rebounds. When the Timberwolves were trying to win in regulation, Kidd hit two jumpers, the second a 3-pointer with 2:12 to play. In overtime, his driving layup, steal and pass to Martin set up the victory. He also hit three of four free throws.</p>
        <p>''If he's not the best point guard in the league, then you all are crazy,'' Scott said. ''He wants the ball when the game's on the line and so do we.''</p>
        <p>He had it in the third quarter. The Nets were leading by 70-69 when Martin started an 11-0 run with a 3-pointer and Lucious Harris added a layup. Then Kidd took over.</p>
        <p>He hit a 14-foot jumper and then threw a bullet that skimmed two Timberwolves' ears and darted through traffic, finding Harris sprinting in for a layup. Kidd finished the quarter, and a 14-2 Nets run, with a 3-pointer. The shot gave his team an 84-71 lead into the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>The Timberwolves had blown a 22-point lead in the third quarter a night earlier at home and lost to Dallas. Tonight, they tried to make the Nets do the same.</p>
        <p>With the Nets ahead, 95-76, and 7:58 to play in regulation, the Timberwolves launched a 15-0 run while the Nets shot 1 for 7. The Timberwolves put up a zone defense that stymied the Nets, forced them to rush their shots. And Anthony Peeler ripped off 13 points in the fourth quarter, including 3 of 4 3-pointers.</p>
        <p>The Nets were starting to tire. Kerry Kittles, who played 42 minutes despite spraining his left ankle in Sunday's game, was struggling offensively; he finished 1 for 9, with 3 points. And in the fourth quarter, Harris broke his nose in a scuffle.</p>
        <p>Keith Van Horn was no longer hot and MacCulloch had cooled off after scoring 16 points in the first half. It was up to Kidd and Martin to score, and they did.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
