<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SOUTH AFRICAN BLACKS GAIN SHARE OF POWER IN MONTHS BEFORE A MULTIRACIAL VOTE</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="633185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANCTIONS (ECONOMIC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOYCOTTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AFRICA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AFRICAN NATIONAL CONGRESS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">INKATHA FREEDOM PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DE KLERK, F W (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLER, BILL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DC123AF93BA3575AC0A965958260" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SOUTH AFRICAN BLACKS GAIN SHARE OF POWER IN MONTHS BEFORE A MULTIRACIAL VOTE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KELLER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KELLER, BILL</byline>
      <dateline>GEORGE, South Africa, Sept. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The white Government of South Africa tonight agreed to share broad powers with a multiparty transition committee in the months leading up to South Africa's first universal election. The accord would subject the police, the army, the budget and civil service to the oversight of a predominantly black interim council.</p>
        <p>The agreement, completed today at negotiations involving most of the country's political rivals, means that as early as October, South Africa's disenfranchised blacks will have their first formal voice in the running of the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The white Government of South Africa tonight agreed to share broad powers with a multiparty transition committee in the months leading up to South Africa's first universal election. The accord would subject the police, the army, the budget and civil service to the oversight of a predominantly black interim council.</p>
        <p>The agreement, completed today at negotiations involving most of the country's political rivals, means that as early as October, South Africa's disenfranchised blacks will have their first formal voice in the running of the country.</p>
        <p>It also clears the way for the African National Congress to call for the end of the last international economic sanctions against South Africa. A congress leader predicted that call would come by the end of September, after today's pact is enacted into law by Parliament. Composition of Council</p>
        <p>The transition council of about two dozen members, including one representative from every major political party and Government jurisdiction, is to have broad authority to override the Government on virtually anything that could influence the climate for the elections scheduled for next April 27.</p>
        <p>It will require approval of 75 percent of the members to veto a Government action, which could enable President F.W. de Klerk to thwart the council in some cases. In practice, he is expected to exercise such powers only rarely. In their nearly three years of negotiating together, the major parties have acquired a knack for compromise and consensus that gives their decisions great moral authority. Broad Powers Included</p>
        <p>Among the powers laid out for the new council and its seven sub-councils would be: organizing a new peacekeeping force comprising members of the current police and army as well as former anti-apartheid guerrillas, investigating and suspending police officers accused of misdeeds, demanding access to most Government files, monitoring any expenditure of state money, supervising state television and radio, and running all aspects of the elections themselves.</p>
        <p>The Zulu-based Inkatha Freedom Party and the white separatist Conservative Party have been boycotting the talks and insist they will not cooperate in the elections, raising the threat of open resistance to this first stage of multiracial democracy. Leaders of both parties have threatened that the creation of a transition authority could lead to civil war.</p>
        <p>But negotiators still hope that Inkatha, at least, can be lured back by the temptation of a seat on the transitional council. And in any case, by its action tonight, the Government and opposition parties showed they are prepared to go ahead with or without Inkatha and other holdouts.</p>
        <p>Of the 23 participants present tonight at the World Trade Center outside Johannesburg, only two representatives of black homelands voted against it. The militant black Pan Africanist Congress and a right-wing white party, the Afrikaner-Volksunie, abstained.</p>
        <p>Conservatives, black and white, fear domination by the African National Congress, the expected winner of the elections. Militant blacks object to a compromise that will give the white minority a continuing role in a future Government of national unity. One Seat Per Party</p>
        <p>The transition council will in essence be a replica of the multiparty forum where the country's future is being negotiated. Each party technically has equal weight regardless of its public following, with one seat each for the popular African National Congress, the ruling National Party, the tiny Communist Party, one seat for Mr. de Klerk's Government and one each for the rulers of the black homelands created under apartheid.</p>
        <p>In practice the members tend to fall into blocs, and when the two main players, the African National Congress and the Government, find a compromise they usually pull in most of the others. The Government, under fierce attack from conservative whites for ceding power before an election, fought hard to limit the powers of the transition council. At first Mr. de Klerk's negotiators sought to restrict its authority to strictly election-related matters. Then they insisted that an 80 percent majority of the council be required to impose its will on the Government.</p>
        <p>The African National Congress, in turn, battled militants in its ranks who wanted nothing less than joint control of the police force and state budget.</p>
        <p>Under the final agreement, the specialized sub-councils overseeing the police, the army and intelligence would operate by 75 percent majorities. Others, such as those in charge of state finance or local government, would work by a two-thirds majority. If the Government balked, the dispute would be appealed to the full council where a 75 percent vote would be needed to overrule Mr. de Klerk. No Substitute for Government</p>
        <p>Roelf Meyer, the chief Government negotiator, told reporters: "We are satisfied that this bill does not provide for a substitute of the Government in any way whatsoever, or joint control of the security forces."</p>
        <p>Joe Slovo, a Communist Party negotiator and African National Congress stalwart, said the council "has got enormous powers -- the power to poke its nose into everything that has a bearing on a free and fair election. It is not a toothless tiger."</p>
        <p>The Government estimated that the transition council would be operating by the end of October, which would leave the country on schedule for elections in April. Voters are to chose an assembly that will simultaneously write a permanent constitution and serve as the first democratic parliament.</p>
        <p>All parties showing substantial voter support are to be given seats in the first democratic Cabinet. The leader of the winning party -- if polls are accurate, probably Nelson Mandela of the African National Congress -- will become the President.</p>
        <p>The last major task facing the negotiators before the election campaign begins in earnest is to write an interim constitution by which the country will be run until the elected assembly finishes its work.</p>
        <p>The white-controlled Parliament is to convene next Monday to enact tonight's agreement into law, which is regarded as a formality given Mr. de Klerk's support. Then the leaders of all the parties are to meet in a plenary gathering to ratify it, after which the council begins its work.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
