<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>York Journal;God Works in Mysterious Plays, Doesn't She?</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="844900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANGLICAN CHURCHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LYALL, SARAH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anglican Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFD81E39F933A15757C0A960958260" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>York Journal;God Works in Mysterious Plays, Doesn't She?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LYALL, SARAH</byline>
      <dateline>YORK, England</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cast members of the traditional York Mystery Plays were warming up in a freezing rehearsal room here when God, standing in front of Pontius Pilate and the Virgin Mary, began to giggle conspiratorially during the shoulder exercises.</p>
        <p>"I can't do it if you look at me like that!" said God, who was modestly dressed in a pair of baggy corduroy pants and a blue sweater and who is being played by Ruth Ford, a 64-year-old local dealer in antiques.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The cast members of the traditional York Mystery Plays were warming up in a freezing rehearsal room here when God, standing in front of Pontius Pilate and the Virgin Mary, began to giggle conspiratorially during the shoulder exercises.</p>
        <p>"I can't do it if you look at me like that!" said God, who was modestly dressed in a pair of baggy corduroy pants and a blue sweater and who is being played by Ruth Ford, a 64-year-old local dealer in antiques.</p>
        <p>The diminutive Mrs. Ford may seem an unlikely choice to portray the most powerful force in the universe, an understandably pivotal one in a production that depicts biblical stories from Genesis straight through the life of Jesus. "It is by far the biggest role that I've ever had," she said, "and I'm a bit overawed by it."</p>
        <p>She is even more awed by the furor her casting has caused.</p>
        <p>For as long as anyone can remember, a man has played God in the Mystery Plays, which used to be performed by local workers' guilds on the streets of this ancient walled city.</p>
        <p>It is a role that serves as a lightning rod for people's own views about religion and certainly about God, who over the years has been depicted as a stereotypical gray-bearded father figure, as a disembodied voice booming from the heavens and, in one production, as a coal miner from Leeds.</p>
        <p>But the casting of a woman this year has stirred passions across Britain and  fed the continuing debate about the role of women in the conservative, male-dominated Church of England. Since women were first ordained as priests two years ago, the church has remained effectively split between those who favor a larger role for women and all the modernization that the idea suggests, and those who are dead set against it.</p>
        <p>To the dozens of indignant people, clergymen among them, who wrote letters of complaint to John Doyle, the artistic director of the York Theater Royal, the portrayal of God as Woman is the last straw.</p>
        <p>"It's modern political correctness gone mad," said the Venerable George Austin, the staunchly conservative Archdeacon of York, who was vehemently opposed to letting women become priests and who believes that God is male. "The  Bible describes God in male terms, so you should follow scripture -- not modern  feminism."</p>
        <p>But for Mr. Doyle, Mrs. Ford was the best person for the job. When she arrived for the audition, he said, he had a near-thunderbolt of inspiration.</p>
        <p>"It's a very difficult play to cast," he said. "How do you cast the Virgin Mary, Jesus and St. Peter when there are so many preconceptions and religious responsibilities contained within the play? But the first time I set eyes on her," he said, speaking of Mrs. Ford, "I knew I'd found my God."</p>
        <p>What was it about her? "She has strength of character, dignity, charisma, humor and a bit of a twinkle in her eye," he said. "She's just the sort of person that other people would do things for."</p>
        <p>Nor is it fair to say that God is necessarily male, he said, citing the biblical passage in which God says he made both man and woman in His own image.  "But a lot of people don't like new things, and someone wrote to me and said I had no right to have an opinion on what God was. But I believe that it's everybody's right. I'm also not saying that God is a woman, or that Ruth Ford is God. Acting is about what happens on the stage."</p>
        <p>For her part, Mrs. Ford hardly feels particularly God-like, even if fellow dealers in antiques insist on asking whether they should kneel before her when she shows up at antiques fairs.</p>
        <p>"I hope to bring a truth to the role, and a dignity," she said in an interview before the evening's first rehearsal of the scene in which she leads Abraham up the mountain and commands him to kill his son Isaac.</p>
        <p>"If it doesn't sound too pompous, I want to make people think and feel and listen to those beautiful words."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Ford has previously appeared in the Mystery Plays, which are put on every four years or so, in the parts of Mary Magdalene and the wife of Pontius Pilate. This time she heard that Mr. Doyle, who cast a mix of professional actors and amateurs, planned to give some of the traditionally male roles to women, and thought she might be good as the Devil.</p>
        <p>(As it was, Mr. Doyle decided that the part should be shared by a man and a woman, but the woman got a promotion and moved out of town, so this year the Devil remains a man).</p>
        <p>And even Satan says he is delighted to work with Mrs. Ford, who gets no special privileges just because she happens to be playing an all-powerful force. "I believe it was a case of the best man for the job being a woman," said the Devil, Dave Parkinson, a computer consultant.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Ford hopes to understand her character's motivations before the plays are performed in June. "We don't really know what He's like, do we?" she said. But she is also drawing on her own understanding of God, an understanding that has deepened since the sudden death of her husband this year.</p>
        <p>"My sense of Him is that He's a presence, and He's someone I can call on," she said. "I think God is just and that He has a cause for righteous anger at times." She paused. "I shouldn't say 'He.' "</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
