<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Off-Road Philippines</title>
    <meta content="PALA.$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1035949"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Palawan (Philippines)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philippines</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flippen, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2D81F39F931A3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="2383" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Off-Road Philippines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FLIPPEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flippen, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Travel article on trip to island of Palawan in Philippines; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE island of Palawan in the Philippines, far off to the west of the main Philippine group, is something of an isolated backwater. The country's fifth-largest island, it has less than half of one percent of its population. Parts of it remained unexplored well into this century; a Stone Age tribe, the Tau't Batu, was discovered there only in 1978.</p>
        <p>Because of its isolation, Palawan has largely been spared the environmental degradation that has damaged so many other once-pristine spots. On this long, narrow island (about 260 miles long and less than 25 miles wide, essentially a single mountain range thrust from the sea), it is still possible  to find beaches that are empty not only of other humans, but of any sign of human existence as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE island of Palawan in the Philippines, far off to the west of the main Philippine group, is something of an isolated backwater. The country's fifth-largest island, it has less than half of one percent of its population. Parts of it remained unexplored well into this century; a Stone Age tribe, the Tau't Batu, was discovered there only in 1978.</p>
        <p>Because of its isolation, Palawan has largely been spared the environmental degradation that has damaged so many other once-pristine spots. On this long, narrow island (about 260 miles long and less than 25 miles wide, essentially a single mountain range thrust from the sea), it is still possible  to find beaches that are empty not only of other humans, but of any sign of human existence as well.</p>
        <p>When a Filipino-American friend, Joey Juan, invited me to visit his homeland last winter, his relatives in Manila insisted that we visit Palawan before it was ''too late.'' While they depicted it as in imminent danger of being swallowed whole by developers, we found the island to be a place of enviable natural beauty that, so far, is only lightly overlaid by civilization.</p>
        <p>A lot of things are impossible on the island. You cannot travel more than a few miles on a paved road, or find a bank or hospital outside the capital, Puerto Princesa. The city of 130,000 is only now getting its first fast-food restaurant. Public transportation is limited to ''tricycles'' (motorcycles with sidecars, driven by teen-agers, that serve as taxicabs) and ''jeepneys'' (brightly decorated trucks that run on the dirt roads between towns, with passengers who can't find a seat often hanging onto the roof or the rear guardrails).</p>
        <p>But while Palawan requires a certain amount of hardiness, travel here is becoming easier. Puerto Princesa is an immaculate city with plenty of traffic police and crystal-clear air, things sorely lacking in, for example, Manila. And prices are low, with the Philippine peso, battered by Asia's economic turmoil, trading at around 40 to the dollar. It is hard to spend more than $7 for dinner at any of the island's dozens of restaurants, and daylong expeditions to the main sights, complete with air-conditioned van and driver, tour guide and lunch, can be arranged for $25 or less per person.</p>
        <p>Through a travel agent in Manila, Joey and I booked a three-day visit in early March for around $200 apiece, including round-trip air fare from Manila, hotel and tours to the main sights.</p>
        <p>For years, the only part of the island developed for tourism was the El Nido area, at the island's northern tip, where there are several upscale, self-contained beach resorts of a familiar tropical type: cabins arrayed around a central restaurant and bar, with facilities for water sports. Their customers typically arrive on charter flights from Manila rather than suffer through the 12-hour drive on dirt roads from Puerto Princesa.</p>
        <p>In the last couple of years, several attractive hotels have opened in Puerto Princesa itself. Tourists have responded in enough numbers that Philippine Airlines has begun using a wide-body jet on its daily flight from Manila. Travelers who did not make tour arrangements before leaving Manila and want to avoid the crowded, dusty public jeepneys can hire drivers at several travel agencies on Rizal Avenue near the airport.</p>
        <p>Nature is the draw here, and it is at its best at the St. Paul Subterranean River National Park, a five-mile-long water-filled cave that is a few hours' journey by van or jeepney and boat from Puerto Princesa.</p>
        <p>The cave is full of weird, oddly beautiful rock formations; one chamber resembles a huge cathedral, and it is complete with pipe organ, gigantic stone ''candle'' and statues of the Holy Family. But it can be toured only by outrigger canoe, and the park authorities strictly limit the number of boats inside it at any one time. (They also limit the boats to the first mile or so of the cave, with the rest off limits except to scientists.)</p>
        <p>The result is a silence so profound that, except for the occasional comment from a guide or splash of a paddle, the only sounds are the dripping of water from the roof and the twittering of the cave's 40,000 bats. Attentive listeners can even hear the echoes that make the bats' sonar work. The only light comes from a hand-held spotlight on each boat.</p>
        <p>Getting to the cave is a mild adventure in itself, starting with a 50-mile, two- to three-hour van or bus ride, mostly on dirt roads, from Puerto Princesa across the island to the village of Sabang. From there, there are two ways to cover the last two and a half miles: by foot through the jungle on one of two trails or by ''pumpboat'' (a motorized outrigger canoe) through the South China Sea.</p>
        <p>We did what many travelers do: took the pumpboat (crewed by a father and his son, who couldn't have been more than 7 years old) there, then walked halfway back on the Monkey Trail, billed as the less strenuous of two trails linking Sabang and the cave. It was nonetheless strenuous enough, winding up and down across a 300-foot-high ridge, that we were glad to be picked up by the boat at an intermediate beach near the park's central ranger station.</p>
        <p>Though the cave can be visited as a day trip from Puerto Princesa without rushing, Sabang's beaches tempt some travelers to linger; for them, the tiny village offers a few very basic rental cottages and restaurants. Those seeking even more solitude can camp at the ranger station and use its beach, and there is a still emptier beach farther down the Monkey Trail, shaded by butong trees and littered by their dreidel-shaped fruit.</p>
        <p>Another set of caves is also accessible from Puerto Princesa. The Tabon Caves, 95 miles southwest of the capital, are also reached by a combination of bus, van or jeepney (to the village of Quezon) and pumpboat. Of the 200 caves in the complex, only a few are open to the public. In one of them, the oldest human remains in the Philippines were found.</p>
        <p>What is under Palawan's ground is matched or exceeded by what is under the water: coral reefs, especially those in the Sulu Sea, off the island's east shore. Snorkeling is accessible from the public beaches in Puerto Princesa, but the better reefs are found in Honda Bay, about a half-hour drive north of the city.</p>
        <p>The bay is dotted with more than 10 coral-fringed islets, some inhabited, and it is easy to hire a pumpboat here for a half-day or full day of snorkeling or diving. (Those who don't have their own equipment will have to rent it in Puerto Princesa.)</p>
        <p>SNAKE ISLAND, a sandbar barely 20 steps wide but perhaps a quarter-mile long, is among the most popular spots, with fish swarms that the boat operators, who double as guides, enhance by periodic feedings. We arrived shortly after another party and found that they had primed the fish. The effect was like being in a tropical fish tank at feeding time; when the fish realized we had no food to offer, they started nipping at our legs. The fish behaved more naturally, and the coral was more spectacular, at nearby Starfish Island, a wisp of land that has a small canteen and a few shaded picnic tables.</p>
        <p>Compared with these natural splendors, Palawan's manmade attractions take second place. Puerto Princesa, founded in 1872, is a very new town by Filipino standards, and thus almost devoid of historic sites. But an oddity that is worth seeing is the Iwahig Penal Farm, on the city's outskirts. Founded by the American colonial authorities in 1904, it is a prison without walls and, for the most part, guards (though malaria-filled mountains nearby provide a disincentive to would-be escapees). Nearly 5,000 prisoners, convicted of everything from check fraud to murder, raise rice and vegetables and sell handicrafts at a souvenir shop that is next to the prison's tennis court and across the square from an elementary school that serves the prisoners' children.</p>
        <p>Visitors are greeted at an unlocked gate by a prisoner hawking keychains, and can wander and photograph almost at will. (Off limits are the ''medium security'' compound, surrounded by a few strands of barbed wire, and the ''maximum security'' area, which has more barbed wire and a cinder block wall.) Prisoners, identifiable by their orange T-shirts emblazoned with the letter ''P,'' can be chatted up freely.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, the occasional rainy day -- Palawan, west of the typhoon belt, has a somewhat drier climate than most of the Philippines -- can be spent at Puerto Princesa's small museum, in the old city hall, which is notable mainly for its collection of rare, beautiful seashells from the island's waters, including scallops in every color and conchs festooned with spikes. Near the city's Roman Catholic cathedral, in the ruins of the old police station, is a marker noting the place where 143 American prisoners of war were burned to death in a tunnel by Japanese troops near the end of World War II.</p>
        <p>We discovered on checking into our hotel, the Marina de Bay, that locations can be deceiving in Puerto Princesa. The comfortable hotel was indeed ''near City Hall,'' as billed, but Puerto Princesa's city limits encompass a sizable chunk of Palawan, and City Hall is a 20-minute drive from the center of town.</p>
        <p>Still, that trip cost less than $2 by tricycle, and the hotel, at the end of a peninsula with a view across the bay, was quiet and relaxing. Hotels in the center of town, by contrast, can be plagued by the incessant racket of tricycles. In both areas, there is a range of quality and price, from older properties catering mainly to Filipinos and Western backpackers to newer and more upscale hostelries aimed at slightly wealthier tourists (though even in this range, few  charge much more than $40 a night). Most have air-conditioning, but even the relatively upscale hotels may lack hot water -- which is not always a necessity in this climate.</p>
        <p>We spurned the hotel's restaurant in search of more authentic Palawan cuisine and found that Rizal Avenue was lined with inexpensive, atmospheric open-air restaurants. Even more than in the rest of the Philippines, food comes mainly from the sea: the waters around the island teem with giant prawns, rock lobsters, several species of crabs and many kinds of fish. One local specialty is the small dried fish called danggit that Filipinos eat with breakfast. Westerners may find the salty, crunchy danggit to be an acquired taste, but Filipino cuisine, heavily influenced by Spanish traditions, includes many dishes that even unadventurous eaters will like, from garlic prawns and paella to the national dish, a vinegar-based stew called adobo.</p>
        <p>Some 5,000 Vietnamese boat people wound up on Palawan in the 1980's, and though most have been resettled elsewhere, they left their mark on the island's cuisine; nearly a dozen chao long houses offer simple meals of noodle soups with meat for as little as $1, and there are a few full-service Vietnamese restaurants near the airport as well.</p>
        <p>In the end, the best restaurant we tried was also the simplest: Kalui, in a traditional Palawan-style bamboo hut, offers no menu, just a single  meal at a set price. The centerpiece is whatever the fishermen have brought in that day, grilled and served with vegetables and rice. Add a bottle of San Miguel beer, and it's the perfect way to relax after a hard day on or under the sea.</p>
        <p>Fresh seafood, clear seas</p>
        <p>Lodging</p>
        <p>Marina de Bay, Purok Sandiwa, Puerto Princesa; reservations, (63-48) 433-4338 in Puerto Princesa or (63-2) 931-1410 in Manila, fax (63-2) 931-2863 in Manila. Twelve air-conditioned villas with private bath, overlooking Puerto Princesa Bay. Near City Hall, but a 20-minute drive from the center of town; if you don't have a car and driver, you must ask the hotel to call a jeepney to pick you up. Single or double room, $35.</p>
        <p>Restaurants</p>
        <p>Most are on Rizal Avenue, the main street, which stretches from the wharf to the airport. Seafood is the island's specialty; on menus, most fish and shellfish dishes are priced by 100 grams (slightly less than a quarter-pound). San Miguel and other Filipino beers are available everywhere, and most restaurants also have wine (generally low-end labels from California or Australia) and mixed drinks.</p>
        <p>Kamayan, Rizal Avenue near Baltan Street at the eastern edge of downtown, is a large open-air restaurant with an extensive menu of fish and shellfish. Dinners range from about $2 to $7, calculated at 40 Philippine pesos to the dollar.</p>
        <p>Kalui, 369 Rizal Avenue near the airport, is in a traditional bamboo hut. It offers one prix-fixe dinner for $7; the main course depends on the day's catch. Lobster can also be ordered, for about $7 per 100 grams.</p>
        <p>Diversions</p>
        <p>Island Divers, at 371 Rizal Avenue next door to Kalui restaurant, (63-48) 433-2917, rents mask, fins and snorkel for $5 a day. Norman Songco, the owner, also rents scuba equipment, mainly to package tours; if any is left over, individuals can rent it for about $25 a day.</p>
        <p>The Palawan Museum is in the old City Hall building on Mendoza Park in the city center. Open 8 A.M. to noon and 1:30 to 5 P.M. Monday through Saturday, 9 to 11 Sunday. Admission, 25 cents.</p>
        <p>Eidref Tour Agency, 400 Rizal Avenue, (63-48) 433-6496, arranges guided day trips to the Subterranean River ($25 a person, minimum of six), Honda Bay ($20) and other sites; prices include lunch. A car and driver costs about $40 a day in the city.</p>
        <p>ALAN FLIPPEN is an editor on the metropolitan desk of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ALAN FLIPPEN is an editor on the metropolitan desk of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
