<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Good, if Oversold, Trade Deal</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="771806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JAPAN-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CUSTOMS (TARIFF)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROTECTIONISM (TRADE)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Protectionism (Trade)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED71439F93AA15755C0A963958260" item-length="620" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Good, if Oversold, Trade Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although the trade deal struck with Japan yesterday is not the grand breakthrough advertised by the Clinton Administration, it represents a substantial achievement. If details still to be disclosed sustain the outline described by negotiators, the accord should break down protectionist barriers that unnecessarily keep down sales of American autos and auto parts to Japanese manufacturers and repair garages. That would help Japanese consumers and American auto workers.</p>
        <p>What the agreement does not do -- and should not do -- is meet the Administration's desire to impose enforceable, presumably numerical, targets on the Japanese Government that could serve as a basis for later sanctions. The demand for enforceable targets delayed negotiations and led to the Administration's threat to levy sanctions, which would violate United States obligations under international trade rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although the trade deal struck with Japan yesterday is not the grand breakthrough advertised by the Clinton Administration, it represents a substantial achievement. If details still to be disclosed sustain the outline described by negotiators, the accord should break down protectionist barriers that unnecessarily keep down sales of American autos and auto parts to Japanese manufacturers and repair garages. That would help Japanese consumers and American auto workers.</p>
        <p>What the agreement does not do -- and should not do -- is meet the Administration's desire to impose enforceable, presumably numerical, targets on the Japanese Government that could serve as a basis for later sanctions. The demand for enforceable targets delayed negotiations and led to the Administration's threat to levy sanctions, which would violate United States obligations under international trade rules.</p>
        <p>The agreement should improve American sales in several ways. Currently few Japanese dealers sell foreign, let alone American, cars. It commits the Japanese Government to take specific steps to overcome pressure on dealers by Japanese manufacturers to carry only Japanese models. Specifically, Tokyo has agreed to enforce its antitrust laws against collusive agreements that shut out foreign auto makers.</p>
        <p>Mickey Kantor, the American trade representative, said the deal would lead to the opening by next year of 200 dealers that sell American cars, 1,000 showrooms by the year 2000. But these are United States estimates of the impact, not a specific goal set by the Japanese Government.</p>
        <p>The agreement goes further on Japanese repair shops, another source of frustration to American manufacturers. Under current rules, most repairs in Japan must be completed by Government-certified garages that are controlled by Japanese manufacturers. Under the agreement, the Government promises to certify small, independent garages that would be able to buy American parts to complete their repairs.</p>
        <p>This is a bold provision that could pry open Japanese markets to low-cost American parts. Mr. Kantor said as many as 8,000 newly certified garages would be eligible to buy foreign parts, but neither the Japanese Government nor private manufacturers embraced the specific number.</p>
        <p>The agreement makes little headway on Mr. Clinton's demands that Japanese manufacturers operating in Japan purchase more American parts. The manufacturers predict they will buy more foreign parts, but they did not confirm the $6 billion figure offered by Mr. Kantor. The manufacturers volunteered predictions, not enforceable commitments.</p>
        <p>At yesterday's news conferences, President Clinton and Mr. Kantor cited lots of impressive numbers: a half-million new Japanese cars produced in the United States, $12 billion in additional sales of American car parts, 1,000 new Japanese dealerships selling American cars. None of these are written in the agreement. None are enforceable. But the agreement knocks down protectionist barriers and should eventually lead to Japanese consumers' buying as much in American goods as they want. That is all a trade pact should achieve.</p>
        <p>Had the Administration promised no more, the agreement would represent a complete victory. Had it not placed so much emphasis on "results-oriented" commitments, the negotiations might not have dragged on so long, or led to the American sanction threat. The Administration won a good agreement with the threat. A wiser tactic would have been to honor its treaty responsibilities and take the Japanese before a trade tribunal to win the same concessions. It might have taken more time, but there is value in having the world's most important trader live by the rules it negotiated.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
