<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Treasury Prices Rise After Trade Accord Spurs Dollar</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="771796"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TREASURY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HURTADO, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDF1639F93AA15755C0A963958260" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Treasury Prices Rise After Trade Accord Spurs Dollar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HURTADO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HURTADO, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities bounced higher yesterday, erasing early losses after a breakthrough in trade negotiations with the Japanese buoyed the dollar.</p>
        <p>Before that, prices were down as the market geared up for a five-year note auction after a mediocre two-year auction on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities bounced higher yesterday, erasing early losses after a breakthrough in trade negotiations with the Japanese buoyed the dollar.</p>
        <p>Before that, prices were down as the market geared up for a five-year note auction after a mediocre two-year auction on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The market has had many concerns these days, among them the United States-Japanese trade negotiations, which went to the wire. Other concerns have been the supply of new debt issues coming to the market and whether the Federal Reserve will lower interest rates at the meeting of the Federal Open Market Committee less than a week away.</p>
        <p>The 30-year bond rose 17/32 , to a price of 11418/32 for a yield of 6.52 percent, down from 6.54 percent on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>James Hale, a fixed-income analyst with MMS International in San Francisco, said the successful trade negotiation and subsequent surge in the dollar were key factors in the market's about-face. "But even after rebounding on trade-agreement news, trading was still somewhat cautious going into the five-year note," he said.</p>
        <p>The auction of five-year notes turned out to be a well-sold affair, even with retail interest from small investors somewhat subdued. Traders said the $11.5 billion of five-year notes were priced for a high yield of 5.90 percent, the lowest in almost a year and a half, when it was 5.61 percent on Feb. 24, 1994. Last month the yield was 6.25 percent.</p>
        <p>Analysts say yields are moving lower amid expectations that the Fed will lower rates to help bolster the economy.</p>
        <p>Sung Won Sohn, chief economist for the Norwest Corporation in Minneapolis, believes the Fed chairman, Alan Greenspan, will move to cut interest rates next week.</p>
        <p>"Chairman Greenspan desperately wants to achieve a soft landing and prevent the economy from skidding into a recession," Mr. Sohn said. "The Federal funds rate will be cut by half a point. The prime rate and other loan rates should follow."</p>
        <p>Then there is the political factor, Mr. Sohn said. "In a democratic society, Mr. Greenspan cannot ignore political reality," Mr. Sohn said. "The White House wants to lower interest rates; President Clinton doesn't want to go back home to Arkansas in 1997."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sohn said Congress was likely to cut about $50 billion from 1996 spending. "There has always been an unwritten quid pro quo between Congress and the Federal Reserve Board," he said. "Interest rates will be cut if Congress trims spending."</p>
        <p>Even with the market holding its gains and feeling good mainly because of the dollar, Mr. Hale said trading was likely to be cautious heading into a holiday weekend and ahead of the Fed meeting next week, as well as the employment report next Friday.</p>
        <p>"I am 99 percent sure the Fed will go with the rate cut at the meeting and not wait for the employment number," Mr. Hale said. There is no consensus on how much the cut will be, he said, but it could be 25 or 50 basis points. A basis point is one-hundredth of a percentage point.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sohn said there was a risk for stocks and bonds. "If interest rates are not cut either in July or August, both markets will be disappointed," he said. "Interest rates would rise, hurting bonds. Projections for corporate earnings would be scaled back, damaging stocks."</p>
        <p>Analysts said import-export prices for May, released yesterday, put pressure in early trading, as import prices rose 1 percent and exports three-tenths of a percent, both causing inflation flags to flutter.</p>
        <p>Municipal bonds were steady yesterday with some investors reluctant to buy tax-exempt securities after voters in Orange County, Calif., voted down a tax increase to prevent default on its debt.</p>
        <p>Traders said investors were concerned that other municipalities might decide to walk away from their debt through bankruptcy filings. The average yield to maturity for the Bond Buyer's index of 40 municipal issues rose a basis point, to 6.17 percent.</p>
        <p>Some California borrowers paid the price for that concern yesterday. Alameda County, Calif., sold $85 million in one-year notes at prices to yield 6.40 percent, 30 basis points more than same-maturity Philadelphia notes and 25 basis points more than Colorado paper, both rated lower.</p>
        <p>In the corporate debt market, corporations have sold 61 percent more bonds in the second quarter, as the sharp drop in interest rates cheapened the cost of borrowing in the financial markets.</p>
        <p>The Standard &amp; Poor's Ratings Group said companies issued $68.9 billion in bonds in the three-month period, up from the first quarter's $42.8 billion.</p>
        <p>Industrial companies led the surge in new bonds, nearly doubling their sales in the period to $20.4 billion.</p>
        <p>The following are the results of yesterday's Treasury auction of new five-year notes:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures) High Yield . . . 5.905%  Low Yield . . . 5.850%  Median Yield . . . 5.890%  Accepted at low price . . . 51%  Total applied for . . . $32,545 213  Accepted . . . $11,504,684  Noncompetitive . . . $242,000  Interest set at . . . 5.875%  The five-year notes mature on June 30, 2000.</p>
        <p>CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
