<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Monsanto to Acquire 49.9% of Biotechnology Company</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="771942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TOMATOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GENETIC ENGINEERING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CALGENE INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MONSANTO CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GARGIULO LP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, LAWRENCE M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DC103CF93AA15755C0A963958260" item-length="635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Monsanto to Acquire 49.9% of Biotechnology Company</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISHER, LAWRENCE M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Monsanto Company said yesterday that it would acquire a 49.9 percent stake in Calgene Inc., the biotechnology company best known for its development of a genetically engineered tomato, for $30 million. As part of the transaction, Monsanto will turn over to Calgene its 50 percent interest in Gargiulo L.P., the largest packer and shipper of fresh tomatoes in the United States.</p>
        <p>Analysts said the agreement would help all three companies by bolstering Monsanto's position in agricultural biotechnology -- in which it has already spent an estimated $1 billion on research and development -- and by making Calgene and Gargiulo the nation's predominant supplier of fresh tomatoes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Monsanto Company said yesterday that it would acquire a 49.9 percent stake in Calgene Inc., the biotechnology company best known for its development of a genetically engineered tomato, for $30 million. As part of the transaction, Monsanto will turn over to Calgene its 50 percent interest in Gargiulo L.P., the largest packer and shipper of fresh tomatoes in the United States.</p>
        <p>Analysts said the agreement would help all three companies by bolstering Monsanto's position in agricultural biotechnology -- in which it has already spent an estimated $1 billion on research and development -- and by making Calgene and Gargiulo the nation's predominant supplier of fresh tomatoes.</p>
        <p>The deal "makes tremendous strategic sense," said James McCamant, editor of the Agbiotech Stock Letter. "By combining the two organizations you insure that the new entity will be the dominant supplier of fresh market tomatoes for some time."</p>
        <p>In addition to the Flavr Savr, a genetically engineered tomato with an extended shelf life, Calgene has developed seed oils with large potential markets in the food and chemical industries.</p>
        <p>Monsanto, the big chemicals company based in St. Louis, makes bovine growth hormone, which stimulates milk production in cows, and herbicide-resistant soybeans, potatoes and cottonseed.</p>
        <p>Shares of Calgene closed yesterday at $8.25, up 50 cents, after trading as high as $9.9375. The stock was among the most active Nasdaq issues, with almost four million shares traded. The average daily volume of Calgene is 396,600 shares.</p>
        <p>On the New York Stock Exchange, shares of Monsanto rose 50 cents, to $88.625.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the deal, Monsanto will make an equity contribution of $30 million to Calgene, which is based in Davis, Calif. Monsanto will also make long-term credit available to Calgene and Gargiulo.</p>
        <p>After turning over its current 50 percent interest in Gargiulo to Calgene, Monsanto intends to exercise its options to acquire the remaining half of Gargiulo, which is based in Naples, Fla., and then turn it over to Calgene.</p>
        <p>Douglas Groh, an analyst with Merrill Lynch, said sales of bovine growth hormone by Monsanto had exceeded the company's estimates, encouraging it to play a greater role in agricultural biotechnology. "The real benefit to Monsanto," he said, "is gaining access to the plant oil development Calgene has done." He said that Calgene would gain "distribution from Gargiulo, and Monsanto has the deep pockets to fund the research."</p>
        <p>Mr. McCamant of the Agbiotech Stock Letter said Gargiulo had annual revenue of more than $100 million and was profitable.</p>
        <p>Calgene's seed oils under development include a high-laurate oil, which can be used as a substitute for cocoa butter in the production of chocolates and as an ingredient in detergents. The company is also developing a genetically engineered oil that would lower the amount of so-called trans fatty acids in margarine; the acids have been cited in some studies as playing a role in the buildup of cholesterol. The company also has relationships with the Procter &amp; Gamble Company and the British-Dutch group Unilever in developing the oils.</p>
        <p>"The combination of our respective businesses and proprietary technology assets in fresh produce and specialty plant oils will create a leading food and agribusiness enterprise," said Roger H. Salquist, Calgene's president and chief executive.</p>
        <p>Separately, Calgene said it expected to report a loss of between $1 and $1.05 a share on revenue of between $55 million and $58 million for the year ending June 30. In the previous fiscal year, the company had a loss of $1.71 a share on revenue of $39.4 million.</p>
        <p>Calgene also announced that it might raise about $10 million through a private equity placement before the closing of the Monsanto transaction.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
