<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>T.W.A. Cleared for 2d Bankruptcy Filing</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="771811"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKRUPTCIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRANS WORLD AIRLINES (TWA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, ADAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDB1638F93AA15755C0A963958260" item-length="575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>T.W.A. Cleared for 2d Bankruptcy Filing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM BRYANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRYANT, ADAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trans World Airlines celebrated in the fall of 1993 when it emerged from bankruptcy. But the company's executives were cheering again yesterday because T.W.A. is headed for bankruptcy court for its second filing in less than four years.</p>
        <p>The twist stems from winning approval late Tuesday night from its creditors for a restructuring plan to be submitted to bankruptcy court this week. The result, T.W.A. expects, will be to emerge from bankruptcy with a lighter debt burden and a more realistic business plan as early as September -- a quicker and more certain timetable than trying to seek an out-of-court settlement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Trans World Airlines celebrated in the fall of 1993 when it emerged from bankruptcy. But the company's executives were cheering again yesterday because T.W.A. is headed for bankruptcy court for its second filing in less than four years.</p>
        <p>The twist stems from winning approval late Tuesday night from its creditors for a restructuring plan to be submitted to bankruptcy court this week. The result, T.W.A. expects, will be to emerge from bankruptcy with a lighter debt burden and a more realistic business plan as early as September -- a quicker and more certain timetable than trying to seek an out-of-court settlement.</p>
        <p>"This is a major win for T.W.A.," said Robert A. Peiser, chief financial officer of T.W.A., the nation's seventh-largest airline.</p>
        <p>Under the proposed restructuring, T.W.A.'s creditors and noteholders would forgive about $500 million in debt. In return, they would get a variety of securities that would raise their share of the company from about 55 to 70 percent. Employees, who traded wage and productivity concessions for a 45 percent equity stake in the airline, would see their stake reduced to 30 percent from 45 percent. Other creditors whose approval was required included the Pension Benefit Guaranty Corporation, and Carl C. Icahn, T.W.A.'s former chairman, who was owed $190 million.</p>
        <p>Since it emerged from bankruptcy, T.W.A. has defied some industry experts' predictions of its imminent demise. Its tour through bankruptcy court the first time did not help its prospects because, by all accounts, T.W.A. was yoked with a business plan that was all but impossible to meet.</p>
        <p>The plan, for example, called for revenues to rise 70 percent, to $5.7 billion, in 1997, a difficult feat given T.W.A.'s limited route network, which includes only one United States hub, in St. Louis. The latest estimates are for revenues to be about $4 billion in 1997.</p>
        <p>T.W.A. was also hamstrung by rapid shifts in strategy and changes in its top executives in recent years. It added passenger legroom and heavily promoted its new Comfort Class, but later tightened up the seat structure, fearing missed opportunities to earn revenue with more seats. Management inaction was also a problem. It was only last year, for example, that T.W.A. acquired computer software that enables it to better match fares with demand, a technology that other airlines have used for years.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts said T.W.A. would probably emerge into a much healthier market for airlines. Fare wars are more limited and airline stocks have risen sharply, suggesting there might be a market for T.W.A. to raise new equity sometime in the future, said Phillip Brannon, an airline analyst at Mabon Securities in New York.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brannon and T.W.A. executives said they doubted that T.W.A.'s revenues would be hurt by the bankruptcy, since travel agents are generally aware of the reasons behind the move. T.W.A.'s cash cushion was $136 million at the end of March, and dipped below $100 million during the winter months, a dangerously low level for a major airline during the slowest travel period of the year.</p>
        <p>Only a few airlines, including Continental and Braniff, have emerged from bankruptcy court more than once. T.W.A. executives said they had no intention of seeing bankruptcy court a third time.</p>
        <p>"We keep fooling people and we will continue to fool people," Mr. Peiser said. "This company has an attitude of becoming more than just a survivor."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
