<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Journal Faults a Medical Group In a Dispute Over Independence</title>
    <meta content="19journal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/19/business/media/19journal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1726054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plan B (Contraceptive)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ontario Province (Canada)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Canadian Medical Assn Journal</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Canadian Medical Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Canadian Pharmacists Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoey, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austen, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Plan B (Contraceptive)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plan B (Contraceptive)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plan B (Contraceptive)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFDF1730F93AA25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Journal Faults a Medical Group In a Dispute Over Independence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Journal Faults a Medical Group in a Dispute Over Independence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN AUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Austen, Ian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Hoey, editor in chief of Canadian Medical Association Journal, criticizes association for making him change article on experience of 13 women seeking to buy Plan B, morning-after contraceptive pill, without prescription; had to delete portions in which women described how pharmacists asked them for personal information, including sexual history in some cases, as Canadian Pharmacist Association directed them to do; Ontario government notifies pharmacists' group that collecting such information violates privacy laws (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Canadian Medical Association Journal gives readers a mixture of scientific research papers and journalism. Now a dispute about the boundary between the two has led to charges of censorship and the creation of a committee to review the journal's independence.</p>
        <p>This month, the journal's editor in chief, John Hoey, asked two of his reporters to follow up on a recent regulatory decision that made Plan B, a morning-after contraceptive pill, available without a prescription in Canada. They, in turn, sent 13 women to buy the pills at pharmacies in each of Canada's provinces and territories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A medical journal that gives readers a mixture of scientific research papers and journalism is embroiled in a dispute that has led to charges of censorship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Canadian Medical Association Journal gives readers a mixture of scientific research papers and journalism. Now a dispute about the boundary between the two has led to charges of censorship and the creation of a committee to review the journal's independence.</p>
        <p>This month, the journal's editor in chief, John Hoey, asked two of his reporters to follow up on a recent regulatory decision that made Plan B, a morning-after contraceptive pill, available without a prescription in Canada. They, in turn, sent 13 women to buy the pills at pharmacies in each of Canada's provinces and territories.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hoey said he expected that some of the women would find that purchasing the pill was not easy. But he was surprised to learn that all of them were asked for detailed personal information, in some cases including sexual history, which was entered into computers.</p>
        <p>''We thought these privacy issues were important to the story,'' Dr. Hoey said.</p>
        <p>The reporters found that the information was being collected because the Canadian Pharmacists Association had asked pharmacists to do so.</p>
        <p>On Dec. 9, after his reporters interviewed officials at the pharmacists' association, Dr. Hoey received a telephone call from Graham Morris, the Canadian Medical Association's executive in charge of publications. While the association had no advance notice of the journal's contents, Dr. Hoey said it was made clear to him that the pharmacists had complained to the medical association.</p>
        <p>''He said, we're not going to let you publish that story. It's shoddy journalism and what business is it of ours to be criticizing the pharmacists,'' Dr. Hoey recalled, adding that it was the first time in his 10 years as editor that he had been ordered to cancel or change a story.</p>
        <p>The pharmacists contended that because the journal was a scientific publication it should have conducted its informal survey of pharmacies accordingly, using both ethical and peer review committees.</p>
        <p>''We said this was not appropriate for a research journal,'' said Louise Crandall, a spokeswoman for the pharmacists' group. The medical association said that it was unable to make anyone available for comment.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hoey's position, however, is that the informal survey was journalism, not research, and that the pharmacists' argument was ''just a way to force us to pull the story.''</p>
        <p>After initially considering resigning on the grounds of editorial interference, Dr. Hoey said, he took three steps. An article appeared about the information collection but without mentioning the experiences of the 13 women.</p>
        <p>Then on its Web site, the journal published an editorial describing the attempt to cancel the story and criticizing the medical association for interfering with its editorial independence.</p>
        <p>And Dr. Hoey has asked an outside panel, headed by Jerome P. Kassirer, the former editor of The New England Journal of Medicine, to produce guidelines to help define the Canadian journal's future independence.</p>
        <p>But even the truncated article had an effect. After its publication, Ann Cavoukian, the privacy commissioner for the province of Ontario, notified pharmacists' groups and pointed out that the information collection violated privacy laws. A notice went out to pharmacists on Thursday revoking the group's earlier request that they interview buyers of Plan B.</p>
        <p>Since then, Ms. Cavoukian said, she has heard from women who said that they had found the drug store questioning emotionally distressing.</p>
        <p>''It's a shame the C.M.A. choose to censor the content of that article,'' she said. ''Had it been reported, people would have had a sense what women were experiencing.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
