<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marie-Elizabeth Mundheim and Taylor Mali</title>
    <meta content="28vows" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/28/fashion/weddings/28vows.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1764935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Marbletown (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mundheim, Marie-Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mali, Taylor</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mundheim, Marie-Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mali, Taylor</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellin, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DE1E3EF93BA15756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marie-Elizabeth Mundheim and Taylor Mali</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Marie-Elizabeth Mundheim and Taylor Mali</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY ELLIN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marie-Elizabeth Mundheim and Taylor Mali wed in Marbletown, NY; photos (M) (Vows Column)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMETIMES life throws people together a few times before it finally hits them that something significant is going on.</p>
        <p>So it has been with Marie-Elizabeth Mundheim, now 39, and Taylor Mali, 41. The two have been circling each other since 1979, when she was a ninth grader and he was an 11th grader at brother-and-sister prep schools in Manhattan. There was an attraction, nothing more, and soon he was off to Bowdoin College. They lost touch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The couple have been circling each other since 1979. They were married on May 13 in Marbletown, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMETIMES life throws people together a few times before it finally hits them that something significant is going on.</p>
        <p>So it has been with Marie-Elizabeth Mundheim, now 39, and Taylor Mali, 41. The two have been circling each other since 1979, when she was a ninth grader and he was an 11th grader at brother-and-sister prep schools in Manhattan. There was an attraction, nothing more, and soon he was off to Bowdoin College. They lost touch.</p>
        <p>Six years after their first meeting, Ms. Mundheim was in Berkeley, Calif., having recently received a degree from Oberlin College and shed a boyfriend. While wandering in Berkeley, she ran into Mr. Mali.</p>
        <p>The high school friends made a date for the following afternoon, which stretched into a chilly evening lounging on his porch. Mr. Mali brought her one of his sweaters only to discover that she had already put on one of her own. That was when he realized he was in love with her. ''I knew then that I'd be good at anticipating your needs,'' he told her years later. The next morning (yes, the date lasted that long) he drove her to the airport, thinking that a relationship had begun.</p>
        <p>''He's incredibly generous,'' said Elana Bell, a friend. ''He's so excited to share his world.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Mundheim was not ready to involve herself again so soon and rebuffed him. Mr. Mali, a poet who has won the National Poetry slam four times and a voiceover artist for commercials, took the rejection more or less in stride. ''I felt as though I had had a brush with absolute true love,'' he said. ''I considered myself lucky to have been in her presence for such a brief time.''</p>
        <p>In 1993, he married someone else. Two years later he sent Ms. Mundheim a cassette of his poetry, which included ''I Want a Woman'':</p>
        <p>I want a woman in whose presence the room becomes suddenly hot.</p>
        <p>Who, when lost in her beautiful eyes I completely am articulate not!''</p>
        <p>The poem did not bring her closer to Mr. Mali, but playing it became her litmus test for deciding on whether to date other men.</p>
        <p>''She was always a rebel, going against the flow, but she always had a very big heart,'' said Carl Wendt, a childhood friend of Ms. Mundheim's. ''She's gone through so many stages in her life.''</p>
        <p>In 1999, Ms. Mundheim moved back to New York to be with her father, who was terminally ill with cancer. She often bumped into Mr. and Mrs. Mali, who lived in the same neighborhood. Both of Mr. Mali's parents had died of cancer, and he lent a sympathetic ear during their impromptu meetings.</p>
        <p>''He always seemed kind of nervous around me when we'd run into each other,'' recalled Ms. Mundheim, now a life coach, acupuncturist and Chinese herbalist. ''I found out later that it was because he still liked me and was afraid to let that show.''</p>
        <p>Near the end of 2003 , Ms. Mundheim, sick of being single, made a list of the qualities she desired in a partner -- someone who was passionate, creative and generous of spirit. She realized that Mr. Mali came awfully close.</p>
        <p>But when she bumped into him soon after that, she learned that he was living with a girlfriend, having separated from his wife. Nine months later he called her in California, where she was taking a life coach certification course, to tell her that he and the girlfriend had broken up. During a second call, she asked him what his intentions were.</p>
        <p>''I want to marry you,'' he said. ''I've wanted to be with you since I fell in love with you on the porch in Berkeley.''</p>
        <p>Her reply? ''Good, now we can date.''</p>
        <p>But first they waited for a month, what they called the ''trusting time.'' ''We both did a lot of inner work, especially him, getting his life together in order to initiate a new relationship,'' she said. Then in September 2004, intent on proceeding with his divorce, he flew to the coast to be with her. But then news arrived from New York that Mr. Mali's wife had committed suicide.</p>
        <p>"I was an emotional wreck at that time and Marie-Elizabeth was perfect,'' he recalled. "When I would come home and say, 'I just might need to talk for 30 minutes straight,' she would say, 'Absolutely.' And all she would say was, 'And what else?' She was so good for me during that time.''</p>
        <p>She remembers giving him a lot of space. ''I wasn't sure how it was going to go,'' she said. ''But he never rejected me or blamed our relationship for her suicide. That made me feel superhopeful that we would be able to make it through."</p>
        <p>They were married May 13 at Edgewater Farm in Marbletown, N.Y. Menacing clouds hovered overhead, but they parted as the couple said their vows, as if everything was finally right in the world.</p>
        <p>The 150 guests wrote blessings on purple index cards and tossed them into a fire, so that the good wishes could float into the ether.</p>
        <p>Then, as the bride, in a backless Carolina Herrera gown, approached him, the bridegroom mouthed the words ''I love you.''</p>
        <p>Sally Kempton, the Universal Life minister and meditation teacher who married them, said: ''Sometimes when people meet they know they have a destiny, and then the question is -- now or later? Twenty-five years later here they are.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
