<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>That Was an Interesting Film, but It Had Way Too Much Product Placement</title>
    <meta content="20heff" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/20/arts/television/20heff.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1813134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE WEB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Abercrombie &amp; Fitch Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American Eagle</org>
        <org class="online_producer">H&amp;M</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DF1031F933A15751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1309" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>That Was an Interesting Film, but It Had Way Too Much Product Placement</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">That Was an Interesting Film, but It Had Way Too Much Product Placement</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heffernan, Virginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Artist'' must have seemed too big a word for the men and women of Madison Avenue who invent ads for depilatories and frozen foods. But their work struck someone as so creative, apparently, that in the 1960s they became creativity itself -- or, rather, ''creatives,'' with all the V.I.P. access to the imagination that the backformed word would seem to entail.</p>
        <p>Think of them this holiday season, those creatives -- stuck making mere ''spots,'' when their minds are filled with cathedrals, or at least feature films -- while you're trying to make sense of the distracting advertainment that may hold up your last-minute shopping online. Because that's where the advertiser's crossover ambition is most obvious these days: in the odd flashes of programming that have turned up on Web sites run by Abercrombie &amp; Fitch, American Eagle and H&amp;M.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This holiday season, marketing “creatives” are adding cinematic chic and odd flashes of programming to the online shilling of clothes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Artist'' must have seemed too big a word for the men and women of Madison Avenue who invent ads for depilatories and frozen foods. But their work struck someone as so creative, apparently, that in the 1960s they became creativity itself -- or, rather, ''creatives,'' with all the V.I.P. access to the imagination that the backformed word would seem to entail.</p>
        <p>Think of them this holiday season, those creatives -- stuck making mere ''spots,'' when their minds are filled with cathedrals, or at least feature films -- while you're trying to make sense of the distracting advertainment that may hold up your last-minute shopping online. Because that's where the advertiser's crossover ambition is most obvious these days: in the odd flashes of programming that have turned up on Web sites run by Abercrombie &amp; Fitch, American Eagle and H&amp;M.</p>
        <p>At Abercrombie.com, the casual shopper is greeted by a young man for all seasons. He's shirtless, and seemingly greased for a beach, but wearing also an anorak with a fake-fur collar, unzipped and wide open. No product details are given, but the man himself still seems available for Christmas delivery, if you pay expedited shipping.</p>
        <p>The products are the least of what A&amp;F, the onetime outfitter of elite sporting expeditions, seems to be selling. The company gift cards, also promoted on the home page, furnish their bearer with the ''best of the Abercrombie lifestyle,'' and that lifestyle takes the main stage when you click ''A&amp;F New Faces'' and watch the film promoted by a still image of a winsome girl with another Charles Atlas type, aimlessly taking off his black turtleneck. (Again, abs, but no sizes or prices.)</p>
        <p>The film, such as it is, is billed as ''exclusive,'' and it comes up quickly on broadband; watching is no nuisance, though it's an energy-sapping detour from shopping. The film is a black-and-white documentary about the latest models at Abercrombie, with an emphasis on the bronzed glamour boys, their manly camaraderie and the way the women pine for them from the sidelines. The dateline for the warm-weather shoot is given as ''Christmas 2006, Vancouver,'' though such a date does not yet exist in history; these otherworldly creatures look like they might be able to travel through time, if anyone can.</p>
        <p>Still photographs from the catalog shoot are essentially set in motion here, alternated with airhead interviews with the models, including the bare-chested anorak man, Mark Carroll, who elsewhere on the site confesses that he wants Jessica Simpson under his mistletoe. Profiles of the other models -- and easy click from the film -- reveal that the A&amp;F lifestyle includes a Chloe handbag and Christian Louboutin shoes, or at least such deluxe fare make the Christmas wishlist of Charlotte Carter Alan, one of the site's new faces. By contrast Dustin Charapata says he's hoping for ''new clothes from A&amp;F!'' for the holidays. Cheers.</p>
        <p>An edgeless clique of sisterly, slumber-party girls mix it up on ae.com, the site of American Eagle, the cheerful, friendly retailer of mom-approved T-shirts, jeans and hoodies. The company now has underwear too in its Aerie division, which is also the home base of the company's multimedia task force, which partners with television channels, Webcasts music and video and even plays patron to a team it boldly calls ''Aerie artists.''</p>
        <p>When I looked into the artists, someone named Ben Lee turned up, singing ''Since I Met You'' in a bland music video. As he plays guitar, the goofy-looking Mr. Lee extols his endearing flaws -- flat feet, uneven features, bad ears -- while also flaunting them.</p>
        <p>Simultaneously a supercute girl appears to relish his attention via her iPod; she's singing along, playing with a female friend, and occasionally rolling around on her bed, fully dressed. In a hoodie! And T-shirt! I have no doubt that the clothes are by American Eagle, and this struck me as refreshing.</p>
        <p>The Aerie logo appeared at the end of the video, along with ''by American Eagle'' and ''aerie.com,'' and -- as the curtain dropped -- I had the clean, clear feeling of having been advertised to. I did not feel as though I had been shown something kind of like art -- a black-and-white film, say -- that, while not admitting anything, might obscurely have been laced with some kind of consumerist Spanish fly. I felt as if I had seen an ad. How American, like an eagle.</p>
        <p>Billboards in Manhattan showing a melancholy brunette in lingerie have suggested that viewers seeking ''the full story'' turn to hm.com. It's not easy to find on that Web site, but after some false starts and dead ends -- leading to profiles of filmmakers and tours of Paris that seemed to have little to do with the cheap Swedish retailer -- I came across a supremely short film in the spirit of Krzysztof Kieslowski's ''Three Colors'' series. It stars the same sad, smug woman from the billboards. She speaks not a word, but the video is set to Carla Bruni's throaty 2002 Eurohit, ''Le Plus Beau du Quartier.''</p>
        <p>To get the woman's back story, I had a dizzying range of choices, including, no joke, full story: full screen; full story: medium screen; short story: Version 1; short story: Version 2; short story: Version 3. These options also allow an ''extended version.'' I wish Billboard Lady had just decided for me. In the end I watched them all, and they were all almost exactly the same. I think, from this exercise alone, I might have learned something about women.</p>
        <p>Or French women at least. The movie shows the beautiful, sultry model -- ha! it's Emmanuelle Béart, who's now 43! -- as she entertains a spectral visitor who seems to enter with the winter wind. First the ghost sweeps down magically, in a glorious shot through the clock face of the Musée d'Orsay, then out over Paris and into the window of her satiny and golden apartment, through its sexy rooms, and onto her wonderfully overdressed bed. Along the way she half-smiles, come-hithering. The reveal, subtly supplied, seems to be that her eager pursuer is in fact a slate-gray cat, though a little jingle bell seems to hint that it might also be Santa Claus.</p>
        <p>Christmas is not totally forgotten here: the black-and-gold bra set in which she paces her pad is pitched as ''Holiday Underwear.'' It should not be surprising that there are no kitschy vinyl bustiers, or red-and-fluff ho-ho-ho teddies for the French holiday coquette. Instead Ms. Béart, in the sleepy half light of her flat, looks bemused in her gilded deshabillé, and fetching -- though not untouched by time, nor by the cruel-kind technologies of time-fighting.</p>
        <p>Gudrun Schyman, a member of the Swedish parliament and shareholder in Hennes and Mauritz (of H&amp;M), has protested the ''full story'' campaign at H&amp;M as something she calls ''pornification.'' She's probably right -- who can tell? -- but a further complaint might be lodged by whoever is paying Ms. Béart's day rate, as well as shelling out for all this schmancy mise-en-scene. Are the bosses getting their money's worth with this interactive campaign? Though you get multiple opportunities to stop the film and get information about holiday underwear -- the bra is $14.90, the hotpants are $5.90, the collagen is (presumably) priceless -- it seems presumptuous to stop the languid beauty in her tracks and stick a price tag on her. And I'm not sure it's women shopping for bras who are drawn to the video.</p>
        <p>What's more, I had real trouble finding it on the site, and the choice of versions was genuinely stupefying. Finally hm.com does not offer users a chance to order directly from the site, so, were I so inspired, I'd still have to find a bustling H&amp;M store to buy my hotpants. And that would mean getting dressed in actual clothes, and leaving my own apartment: an act not at all compatible with the Emmanuelle Béart holiday lifestyle, from what I've observed.</p>
        <p>THE WEB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
