<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Yorkers &amp; Co.; Keeper of That Statistical Song and Dance</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="141139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BUREAU OF LABOR STATISTICS (BLS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCARDINO, ALBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EHRENHALT, SAMUEL M (COMR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DD113BF931A35756C0A96E948260" item-length="1505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Yorkers &amp; Co.; Keeper of That Statistical Song and Dance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALBERT SCARDINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCARDINO, ALBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Samuel M. Ehrenhalt has an odd passion for statistics. Nothing sets him to dancing like a good strong quarterly report in employment. A steep trend line in new-business formations makes him break into song.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Samuel M. Ehrenhalt has an odd passion for statistics. Nothing sets him to dancing like a good strong quarterly report in employment. A steep trend line in new-business formations makes him break into song.</p>
        <p>Samuel M. Ehrenhalt has an odd passion for statistics. Nothing sets him to dancing like a good strong quarterly report in employment. A steep trend line in new-business formations makes him break into song.</p>
        <p>The regional commissioner of the Bureau of Labor Statistics, Mr. Ehrenhalt, who is in his early 60's, serves as the keeper of the numbers that can redirect public policy in New York City or set off a stampede in the municipal bond market.</p>
        <p>Because he monitors the pulse of the local labor market, his forecasts have been especially in demand since the market crashed last October. If New York's economy does manage to absorb the contraction on Wall Street, Mr. Ehrenhalt will probably be one of the first to deliver the good news. The Poetry of His Numbers</p>
        <p>Last week, he recited the poetry of his numbers: The local economy has expanded moderately in the six months since the market debacle, the declines on Wall Street offset by job growth in construction and other services. At least so far, he said, the rollbacks among financial services companies have taken the employment levels back only to where they were last summer. In fact, there are still nearly 10,000 more people working for financial and business service companies in the New York area than at the beginning of last year.</p>
        <p>All over town, analysts sighed with relief. ''Isn't Sam special?'' the director of a civic business group asked rhetorically.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ehrenhalt often produces strong reactions. More than 200 employees of the Board of Education await his prognostications on job prospects. When Mr. Ehrenhalt says local businesses no longer need workers who know how to reupholster furniture, as he did several years ago, the board converted its vocational schools to teaching building maintenance and construction - an industry hungry for new workers. Wide-Ranging Influence</p>
        <p>He influences compensation levels on Wall Street and rents on Staten Island. He can help the Transit Authority make its trains run on time (by pointing out the shortage in railway maintenance workers) or cause an upheaval in the planning office of the Brooklyn Union Gas Company (by forecasting a move of bank computer operations from Manhattan to the other boroughs).</p>
        <p>Mr. Ehrenhalt manages a staff of 100 people and a budget of $5 million, but only a handful of those people and a small percentage of the money are devoted to statistical research on the economies of New York, New Jersey, Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands, the territory he covers. Most of the resources are spent answering questions about money, trends, budgets and jobs.</p>
        <p>''You can't get a divorce these days without checking in at our office,'' he said last week. ''Unless you have an idea of what the inflation rate is likely to be, you would never know what kind of escalations to ask for in your alimony payments.'' #100,000 Inquiries a Year The New York office of the bureau handles 100,000 inquiries a year. Curious citizens can dial a bank of recorded messages to obtain the latest inflation rate or refresh their perspective on the Long Island economy.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ehrenhalt doesn't stop there in his long-running effort to bring a steady stream of numbers to the public. He organizes seminars in his conference room and delivers speeches on college campuses. He provides running commentary as a guest columnist in newspapers and on television programs.</p>
        <p>He often has to overcome considerable hurdles, even reversing Federal policies, to deliver his material to the public.</p>
        <p>''We moved into new offices last fall, in a converted warehouse where the Federal Protective Service had spent all its effort keeping unauthorized visitors out,'' he said. ''It took several months to convince them that we wanted the security guards to help people find their way up to our offices.''</p>
        <p>The guards now knock on his door from time to time to ask whether he needs help with anything. ''I've become the super for the building,'' he said. Relationship to Politics</p>
        <p>As a civil servant, he does his best to stay out of politics, but his observations about the economy often conflict with the forecasts offered by elected officials. During most of the 1980's, he warned repeatedly that New York City was placing too many of its eggs in one basket by allowing the financial services industry to overwhelm manufacturing as the largest segment of the local economy. The city Government had not done enough, he implied, to preserve balance and diversity.</p>
        <p>''Mayor Koch kept sending me letters that started, 'I can't believe you were quoted correctly,' '' Mr. Ehrenhalt said.</p>
        <p>Yet, when the market crashed in October, Mr. Ehrenhalt rang fewer alarm bells than most of the other economists who monitor the city's pulse. Last week, he offered an audience of 70 New York watchers proof that he had been right.</p>
        <p>''The number of private-sector jobs is up 10,000 since the crash, despite the layoffs at some of the bigger brokerage houses and banks,'' he told the group crowded into his conference room in a Federal office building on Varrick Street. ''The unemployment rate has dropped to the lowest point in 18 years.'' So much for the doomsday scenarios of late October that predicted a decline of 70,000 jobs in the city. Challenge to New York City</p>
        <p>The fall of the dollar has brought hordes of foreign tourists who have spent heavily in department stores and replaced laid-off executives in dining at expensive restaurants. Competitors have picked up much of the talent dismissed from some financial services companies.</p>
        <p>''Oct. 19 did mark the end of the 1980's as far as New York City is concerned,'' he said, ''but only because it ushered in a new era of intense competition, not only among industries but among cities as well.''</p>
        <p>Since 1983, Atlanta, Boston, Los Angeles and Chicago have grown faster than New York as financial service centers, according to Mr. Ehrenhalt. ''That poses a challenge to the city's position as a great center of creative thinking and deal making,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The extraordinary salary increases of the 1980's have stopped, too, he said. Based on the sketchy data available so far, salaries in the financial and business services sector of the economy for the Northeast region as a whole dropped 1.3 percent during the first three months of this year, compared with a 6.2 percent increase during the first quarter of 1987. The bulk of the region's decline took place on Wall Street, he said.</p>
        <p>''We aren't retrenching very much,'' he said, ''but the growth has stopped.'' Native of Poland</p>
        <p>Though he plays no favorites politically in his use of the data his staff compiles, he clearly has a favorite -his hometown. He came to New York with his family from Poland in the 1920's, settling in Brooklyn. He graduated from Brooklyn College, then moved to Manhattan to earn a master's degree in economics from Columbia University.</p>
        <p>He landed a job at the Bureau of Labor Statistics in the mid-1950's and gradually worked his way up the ladder, frequently turning aside opportunities to jump to the headquarters in Washington.</p>
        <p>''About 12 years ago, when my two children were in high school, I decided to accept an offer to move to the banks of the Potomac,'' he said. ''They told me how happy they were for me and how exciting it would be to live in a new place. I could go to Washington, they said, and they would find a family to move in with here.'' Fighting Against Budget Cuts</p>
        <p>He changed his mind and stayed in New York, moving up in 1980 from deputy commissioner to commissioner, the top of the ladder in the regional office. Throughout his tenure he has fought a rear-guard action against budget cuts, reluctantly giving up a different report after each round of slashing.</p>
        <p>Last week, he issued his last quarterly analysis of employment trends among major demographic groups in the city: white, black and Hispanic people; men and women; adult and teen- age workers.</p>
        <p>''When you see such trends as a drop in unemployment among teen-agers from 21.7 percent to 15.4 percent in one year, you want to know what is going on,'' he said. ''But if you don't even compile the report, you can't begin to examine the cause.'' Importance of Immigrants</p>
        <p>Mr. Ehrenhalt dreams of having enough people to study trends in employment among New York's exploding population of immigrants. ''Can you imagine living in a city like this and not knowing what immigrant labor is up to?'' he asked. ''It's crazy.''</p>
        <p>The economists and other researchers who rely on the bureau as the primary source of information about the local market agree with him.</p>
        <p>''I have clients who want to locate new plants anywhere they can find immigrant labor pools,'' said Thomas J. Spitznas, a private industry consultant based in Mount Vernon, N.Y. ''They believe that first-generation immigrants have a very strong work ethic. If they can find where they are, they will build new facilities. That could be important for certain parts of the city where industry has been reluctant to go.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
