<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vacant Lot Was Their Paradise</title>
    <meta content="24bronx" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/24/nyregion/24bronx.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1778285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4D7143FF937A15754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1176" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vacant Lot Was Their Paradise</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vacant Lot Was Their Paradise</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANNY FERNANDEZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Technically, the lot on East 139th Street near Willis Avenue in the South Bronx was vacant, according to city records.</p>
        <p>Yet there was nothing vacant about it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Commercial and residential development has transformed the South Bronx, filling in the empty topography that came to symbolize the decline and abandonment of American cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Technically, the lot on East 139th Street near Willis Avenue in the South Bronx was vacant, according to city records.</p>
        <p>Yet there was nothing vacant about it.</p>
        <p>Over here was the camper where the guys from the neighborhood watched football games on Sundays. Over there was Izzy's 1981 Yamaha motorcycle, an old motorboat, a wheelchair, three Rottweilers and the cages for Mr. Lopez's chickens. Children from across the street used it as a playground. There were parties, domino games, volleyball matches, auto-repair workshops and pig roasts.</p>
        <p>About 12 years ago, Geraldo Justiniano decided to reclaim the abandoned lot for the neighborhood. He put up a chain-link fence, laid down some gravel and mowed the grass. And though he lives in a two-bedroom apartment a few blocks away, he would often sleep in the camper on weekends, soaking up life in the great outdoors of East 139th Street, the morning crows of a rooster his alarm clock.</p>
        <p>When the construction crew arrived this month, no one was really surprised. Mr. Justiniano -- people call him J. J. -- watched one day last week as a giant claw tore a deep hole in the soil. Five three-family homes are going up on the lot, which had become known in this corner of Mott Haven by two names: La Yarda and Paradise.</p>
        <p>''A lot of memories,'' said Mr. Justiniano, 39. His friends and neighbors have been feeling equally nostalgic: On the Fourth of July, they threw him and La Yarda a farewell party.</p>
        <p>The commercial and residential development that has transformed the South Bronx in recent years has done more than added jobs and housing. It has altered the physical landscape, filling in the empty topography that in the 1970's and 80's came to symbolize the decline and abandonment of entire parts of American cities.</p>
        <p>The vacant lots of the area's past -- the eerie urban prairies strewn with garbage and the rubble of dead tenements -- graced the covers of books and the pages of newspapers. They starred in Hollywood movies like ''Fort Apache, the Bronx.'' They drew visits from local politicians, a president, a future president and even a pope.</p>
        <p>Yet for many South Bronx residents, the empty land was something more than an eyesore or an emblem of urban blight. Lots remained abandoned for so long that they took on an unexpected, improvisational life of their own in one of the poorest communities in the country. Now, as new apartment buildings, homes and businesses rise in the area, this small piece of gritty South Bronx history -- the abandoned lot -- is disappearing.</p>
        <p>These lots were unloved for the most part, but not unused. They were dumps, drug bazaars and a breeding ground for illegal activity, but they also became community gardens, outdoor churches and places where streetwise entrepreneurs set up shop. They were home to wooden crosses, discarded couches, oil spills, beat-up cars and people like Jorge Luis Manzo, known as Choco, who years ago lived in a small wooden shack on a burned-out stretch of St. Ann's Avenue, one of many streets devastated at the time by rampant arson.</p>
        <p>Anthony Perez Cassino, a lawyer who is the chairman of Community Board 8 in Riverdale and grew up in the South Bronx in the 1970's, said the abandoned lots cast the entire borough in a negative light, a reputation that continued long after they began to be replaced by much-needed housing. ''It's good to see it go,'' he said of the empty spaces. ''In the bigger picture, it's for the better.''</p>
        <p>According to land-use and geographic data from the Department of City Planning, there were 1,300 vacant parcels in the South Bronx in 2005. Many are now construction sites or are no longer empty, the result of the borough's building boom. Since 2002, $3 billion in private and public money has been invested in residential, commercial and institutional development projects in the Bronx, according to figures from the borough president's office. The number of new Bronx addresses issued in 2005 was 1,352, nearly double the number in 2001.</p>
        <p>The empty lots that remain are narrow slices of pavement or large expanses of urban wilderness. Some are impromptu junkyards. Others have five-foot-tall weeds. Chain-link fences act as billboards advertising mattresses for sale and Carlo's Lite Mover. The fences do not keep people out so much as keep them in. There are dining room chairs set on the grass, crushed beer cans, cigar butts and tables.</p>
        <p>At a lot on Fox Street, there is a touch of gallows humor: a freshly dug mock grave and a cross at the edge of the sidewalk. At a lot at Prospect Avenue and East 156th Street, there is Mama Isabels Place, a food van that has been a neighborhood staple for years. People sit beneath the van's canopy on cafeteria-style chairs, eating $1.25 pastelillos de carne, or meat turnovers.</p>
        <p>And there is La Yarda.</p>
        <p>The 100-by-100-foot space, which is being developed by the Jackson Development Group of Bellerose, N.Y., has been the scene of an unusually friendly property dance, as Mr. Justiniano, the lot's unofficial tenant, moves out and the company, which bought the site six months ago, moves in. The developer even hired Mr. Justiniano to work as a security guard during construction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Justiniano is short and stocky, and he has a tan as deep as any lifeguard's from spending so many hours in the lot. He grew up in the apartment building next door, and his unorthodox view of public and private property began early, when he took over one empty lot on the block at age 9 and another at 19. Now he runs an office-supply delivery company and is the vice president of the Bronx chapter of the Lunatics, a New York City motorcycle club.</p>
        <p>As he sat on a bench that used to be the back seat of someone's van, he talked about the old times in Paradise. He and his friends brought in a projector to show movies on the wall. They had an Easter egg hunt for neighborhood children and once hitched a motorized water scooter to the back of a Jeep during a snowstorm. ''Our own field of dreams,'' said Mr. Justiniano's friend Izzy Fortuna, 45.</p>
        <p>At the goodbye party on the Fourth, neighbors signed a banner spray-painted with the words ''Farewell La Yarda.'' A woman named Sandra wrote: ''We will miss the good times.'' Someone else scrawled: ''Home never has a name.'' José E. Serrano, the Bronx congressman whose district includes Mott Haven and who happened to be in the neighborhood that afternoon, signed the banner and took home a plate of food.</p>
        <p>''This is an example of a spot in the neighborhood that became sort of an oasis,'' Mr. Serrano said. ''I've always seen people using a lot. I've never seen anyone say goodbye to one.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Justiniano is storing the camper, the children's toys and other items at another lot at the corner. It is much smaller than La Yarda. But he thinks it will be perfect for a pig roast.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
