<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Prods College to Cut Its Enrollment After Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="14interboro" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/14/nyregion/14interboro.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1731830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Interboro Institute</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4D8173FF937A25752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Prods College to Cut Its Enrollment After Inquiry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">State Prods College to Cut Its Enrollment After Inquiry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under pressure from the New York State Education Department, Interboro Institute, one of the fastest-growing commercial colleges in New York State, agreed to reduce by about half the number of new students it will enroll for the next several semesters, the school and the state said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Interboro, which has 4,500 students in Manhattan, Yonkers and Flushing, Queens, offers associate degrees in paralegal studies, business administration and other fields. Its enrollment has roughly quadrupled since 1999.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under pressure, Interboro Institute agreed to reduce by about half the number of new students it will enroll for the next several semesters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Under pressure from the New York State Education Department, Interboro Institute, one of the fastest-growing commercial colleges in New York State, agreed to reduce by about half the number of new students it will enroll for the next several semesters, the school and the state said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Interboro, which has 4,500 students in Manhattan, Yonkers and Flushing, Queens, offers associate degrees in paralegal studies, business administration and other fields. Its enrollment has roughly quadrupled since 1999.</p>
        <p>The Education Department reported last month that undercover agents had found instances in which school officials had changed scores on tests used to determine student eligibility for financial aid, as well as other instances of misconduct. An outside panel of educators also reported that it had found problems, including low attendance and inadequate academic support for students. The state demanded that Interboro correct the problems, and reduce its size while it did that.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement negotiated by Interboro and the state, the school will be allowed to enroll no more than 900 new students for the spring and summer semesters; the cap will rise to 1,080 students next fall.</p>
        <p>The Education Department said it would continue to monitor the school closely.</p>
        <p>''This will definitely cut into their revenue,'' said Johanna Duncan-Poitier, deputy commissioner for higher education. ''But it is what the students need. And the school has made a commitment to comply with all of the changes we are asking for, including higher admissions standards and increased support for students.''</p>
        <p>Joseph D. Alperin, general counsel of the school's parent company, EVCI Career Colleges Holding Corporation (EVCI on the Nasdaq stock market ), said yesterday that he and other officials could not comment.</p>
        <p>But in a public statement issued late yesterday, EVCI said that reduced enrollments and other compliance costs would force it to cut expenditures; it said it had identified more than $1.8 million in cost reductions so far. It said that the school faced negative publicity from the state's review, and that complying with the state directives would increase its capital costs by $400,000 and its operating costs by $1 million this year.</p>
        <p>EVCI, whose stock price has plunged, also faces a spate of class-action shareholder lawsuits charging that it had issued false and misleading statements.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
