<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sam Cooke: Cha-Cha-Cha Communicator</title>
    <meta content="06PLAY$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/06/arts/music/06PLAY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1502322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC: PLAYLIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliffe, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Playlist</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E5D7123AF935A35754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sam Cooke: Cha-Cha-Cha Communicator</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sam Cooke: Cha-Cha-Cha Communicator</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliffe briefly notes current recordings of interest; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ERIC ALEXANDER -- It's good to see this tenor saxophonist, part of the bricks-and-mortar of New York's straight ahead jazz mainstream, at work in the clubs. He's absorbed not only the musical syntax of his heroes -- principally Sonny Stitt and John Coltrane -- but the sound: he positions the microphone nearly inside the bell of his horn and gets a deep, rich glow, centering around the low midrange of the horn's notes. His new album is ''Nightlife in Tokyo'' (Milestone), with Harold Mabern on piano, Ron Carter on bass and Joe Farnsworth on drums; it's an extremely able example of post-bop, from ballads (''I'll Be Around'') to fast tunes (''Nemesis'') to minor modes (''Cold Smoke''). But the key is that the band sounds beautiful.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ben Ratliff, a jazz critic for The Times, recommends new releases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ERIC ALEXANDER -- It's good to see this tenor saxophonist, part of the bricks-and-mortar of New York's straight ahead jazz mainstream, at work in the clubs. He's absorbed not only the musical syntax of his heroes -- principally Sonny Stitt and John Coltrane -- but the sound: he positions the microphone nearly inside the bell of his horn and gets a deep, rich glow, centering around the low midrange of the horn's notes. His new album is ''Nightlife in Tokyo'' (Milestone), with Harold Mabern on piano, Ron Carter on bass and Joe Farnsworth on drums; it's an extremely able example of post-bop, from ballads (''I'll Be Around'') to fast tunes (''Nemesis'') to minor modes (''Cold Smoke''). But the key is that the band sounds beautiful.</p>
        <p>BADEN POWELL -- There is a broad soft-to-hard spectrum in bossa nova. At the soft end is some of the cream cheese committed to vinyl after the success of ''The Girl From Ipanema.'' But near the other extreme is the work of the guitarist Baden Powell, who died in 2000. A small, hard-drinking man who only used his reedy, expressive singing voice from time to time, Powell created a link between baroque guitar music and bossa nova: everything he did was virtuosic and rather intense. On ''O Universo Musical de Baden Powell,'' an excellent new two-disc retrospective (Universal France, distributed here on Sunnyside), you can hear his strengths plainly; he had the gift of making serious music very pleasurable -- or sometimes vice versa.</p>
        <p>MARTIRIO -- A thick-voiced Spanish singer in her 40's, who started with rock and moved backward and outward into the traditional music of her country and then elsewhere in the Latin diaspora, Martirio is one of those performers with an almost sadistic control over time. The ratio of intensity and discipline to the number of syllables she utters is high: every one of them counts. On her striking new album ''Mucho Corazon'' (Sunnyside), a smart collection of Cuban, South American and Spanish songs, her band includes percussionists who use their hands and feet, and a harmonica player where you would expect an Argentinian bandoneonist. There's also the exceptional Spanish jazz drummer Guillermo McGill and the jazz trumpeter Jerry González, of New York's Fort Apache Band, who has been living in Madrid for the last three years.</p>
        <p>WYCLIFFE GORDON -- The trombonist, who worked with Wynton Marsalis for a decade and finally left the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra in 2002, is reaching Wyntonian speed as a bandleader: it's more than one record per year now, as well as appearances in quirky bands led by Ted Nash and Randy Sandke. His own albums hold fast to the bright, clean tone of the Marsalis small groups: the sound is nearly diaphanous, and nobody overplays. Yet even through the compression and control, he can outperform nearly anyone playing jazz. He's masterful with mutes, but on the deeper levels of music-making, he has an amazing capacity for playing bravura passages quietly. And on his latest album, ''The Joyride'' (Nagel-Heyer) -- with the pianist Farid Barron, the saxophonist Victor Goines, the bassist Rodney Whitaker and the drummer Herlin Riley -- he creates music so tight and light that it seems to float.</p>
        <p>PAT METHENY -- ''One Quiet Night'' (Warner Brothers) is a home recording made with an unconventionally tuned acoustic baritone guitar. Mr. Metheny, unaccompanied, used a lot of emotion to make it, piling up strumming and filigree on a few chords at a time; the songs are sometimes like tiny cats surrounded by so much fur that they seem gigantic. Or they're performed at such a slow, echoey rubato, with each note superimposed in aural space against the last one, that you can't tell where he's going. It's slightly eerie; its most beautiful sections (especially ''Song for the Boys'') approach actual private thought, in the way that Milton Nascimento's albums used to be able to pull you forcibly into his head.</p>
        <p>SAM COOKE -- During college in the mid-80's, we were all rediscovering Curtis Mayfield, who sang righteous political lyrics in a moving, minimalist falsetto. (And I'm glad we did.) By contrast, Sam Cooke, Mayfield's model and nine years his senior, was obvious: a broad toothy smile, singing inescapable pop songs on oldies stations. So it's possible that many of my generation, like me, never saw footage of Cooke perform. (He died in 1964.) ''Legend'' is Abkco's expanded DVD release of a recent VH1 documentary on Cooke, appearing at the same time as remastered versions of much of Cooke's catalog, including the marvelous ''Live at the Copa.''  ''Legend'' comes with 11 complete, intelligent interviews that were used only briefly in the film, including those with Aretha Franklin, Bobby Womack and several members of Cooke's family. And it demonstrates repeatedly why anyone within 10 feet of a TV variety show that had Cooke on it would have been dumbstruck. A superb rhythmic singer who learned a great deal from Louis Armstrong, he was also a communicator who didn't play coy with the audience: without a lot of shouting, putting a serrated burr on his voice as only one device among many, he was a superman of casual concentration.</p>
        <p>MUSIC: PLAYLIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
