<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sushi and Sashimi in an Upscale Setting</title>
    <meta content="06CTDI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1502571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="DINING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ku (Cos Cob, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1D6163DF935A35754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sushi and Sashimi in an Upscale Setting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks reviews Ku restaurant in Cos Cob, Conn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>KU is a chic new Japanese restaurant in Cos Cob. Its long dining room is enhanced by a window at one end, a mirrored wall at the other, and an open kitchen on one side facing a wall with five narrow niches in which votive candles flicker.</p>
        <p>Upscale is the operative word, which was quickly apparent when our first appetizer arrived.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>KU is a chic new Japanese restaurant in Cos Cob. Its long dining room is enhanced by a window at one end, a mirrored wall at the other, and an open kitchen on one side facing a wall with five narrow niches in which votive candles flicker.</p>
        <p>Upscale is the operative word, which was quickly apparent when our first appetizer arrived.</p>
        <p>Maguro tartar consisted of thinly sliced sushi-raw tuna, seasoned in a soupçon of ''chef Ku's original sauce,'' served in a martini glass. It was incredibly fresh and delicious, though pricey at $12 for a minuscule serving.</p>
        <p>From a menu that is short and light on nonsushi dishes, we found several likeable starters, especially goma tofu (mousse-like) and chilled tofu (though the soy-wasabi sauce was oversalted). Hijiki (cooked dark seaweed) and a seaweed salad with ponzu dressing were acceptable, but the hijiki took forever to make its way to our table. Considering the simplicity of the dish the long delay was surprising.</p>
        <p>For the best and most consistent results, concentrate on the sushi and sashimi plates. Ume zushi - a beautifully presented plate with nine pieces of sushi, including eel, mackerel and a California roll - and take zushi -- 10 pieces, well assorted, with a tuna roll - made wonderfully satisfying choices.</p>
        <p>Chirashi, for those who like their raw fish straight as sashimi, was also first rate, with the various fish pieces served over a bed of sushi rice. If you wish to mix and match your own sushi, there are 26 options, plus 10 or so sushi rolls; each one we tried was perfection, including the anago (eel) and crunchy soft-shell crab roll.</p>
        <p>At lunch I highly recommend syo-kado, a bento box with eight different items, all terrific. These include assorted tempura, five slices of impeccable sashimi, four of sushi, a soupçon of broiled cod and several other first-rate tidbits. All of this for $25. Compared with dinner prices, this is real value. Una-jyu (broiled eel, with teriyaki sauce painted over the top, over rice) was also delectable.</p>
        <p>Among the non-sushi-sashimi main dishes, kajiki teriyaki was the biggest surprise: swordfish fillet with ''chef Ku's teriyaki sauce.'' The fish was moist, juicy and delicious, topped with a mix of diced vegetables (which added to the moistness).</p>
        <p>Rarely have I had such flavorful swordfish. If you desire a cooked entree, I would recommend this dish over all others. Roasted duck is another O.K. option; the duck is marinated, grilled and topped with a pleasing orange sauce. On the other hand, the white tuna was dry, overcooked and characterless.</p>
        <p>Tonkatsu, a sort of Japanese version of wiener schnitzel, but with crisp pork filet instead of veal, can be terrific, but it wasn't at Ku. Served unadorned on a large plate, the pork was dry, slightly limp and devoid of flavor.</p>
        <p>For dessert, try Ku's fruit jelly, a refreshing gelatin in which fresh peaches and strawberries are embedded, served in a soothing coconut custard cream sauce.</p>
        <p>Ku's small wine list is well-chosen and begins at $27. There is also a minuscule beer selection and 13 different sakes, not unusual in an upmarket Japanese restaurant.</p>
        <p>What marred two different evenings (it wasn't a problem at lunch) was the service, the worst I have experienced in years, bar none.</p>
        <p>We were put off both times by the same glib, officious waiter who kept pushing certain dishes. Even more irksome was the slowness. We waited 40 minutes for our appetizers, two of which were cold salads. Two other dishes had been forgotten and never arrived.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, our water glasses remained empty. Then came the really long wait for entrees, almost an hour. When they finally came, there were only two, not four. The hot ones arrived, but the sashimi and sushi plates took another half hour, by which time those of us with the hot dishes had finished our meals.</p>
        <p>How can cold dishes take an hour and a half to prepare? When such service happens twice it isn't just a fluke, but suggests a kitchen in need of serious reorganization.</p>
        <p>This is a shame, as there is much to like about Ku (whose name means ''eat''), especially the sparkling fresh sushi and sashimi and the memorable kajiki teriyaki.</p>
        <p>With better service and less attitude, Ku could be very good indeed. Time will tell.</p>
        <p>Ku  85 East Putnam Avenue, Cos Cob  (203)422-6310</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- COOL, sleek and sophisticated.  NOISE LEVEL -- Extremely high when the restaurant is full.  SERVICE -- At lunch, friendly and helpful. At dinner, confused and slow.  Recommended dishes Maguro tartar, hijiki, soft-shell crab roll, goma tofu, roasted duck, kajiki teriyaki, syo-kado, una-jyu, umi zushi, take zushi, hijiki gohan, Ku's fruit jelly.  PRICE RANGE LUNCH: appetizers $3 to $5.50; entrees $12 to $15, sushi and sashimi $14 to $25. Dinner: appetizers $5 to $12; entrees $11 to $23; sushi and sashimi entrees $22 to $75; desserts $3 to $7.  CREDIT CARDS -- American Express, Visa, Mastercard accepted.  Hours Lunch: noon-2:30 p.m. Monday through Friday; Dinner: 5 p.m.-10 p.m. Sunday through Thursday; 5 p.m.-10:30 p.m. Friday and Saturday.  RESERVATIONS -- Accepted.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Parking lot entrance to restaurant.</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
