<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHAT'S ON TONIGHT</title>
    <meta content="15wart" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1833057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4DF1E31F936A25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHAT'S ON TONIGHT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LORI MOORE
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;7 P.M. (Turner Classic Movies) PRIVATE SCREENINGS: BETTY HUTTON -- A look back at the brassy star of 1940s and 50s Hollywood, who died Sunday at 86. This follows a mini-festival of Ms. Hutton's (Left) films: at noon, ''M.G.M. Parade Show No. 27'' (1955); at 12:30 p.m., ''The Stork Club'' (1945); at 2:15 p.m., ''The Perils of Pauline'' (1947); and at 7 pm., ''The Greatest Show on Earth'' (1952).
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;8 P.M. (ABC) UGLY BETTY -- Betty has the most famous brace face on TV today, so when she has the impulse to ask someone to Charlie's birthday party, it's her orthodontist. In the meantime, Wilhelmina does what she does best and tries to come between Daniel and Alexis.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;9 P.M. (HBO) ADDICTION -- This 90-minute documentary on addiction's causes, effects and treatments is the keystone of an HBO project to show addiction as a treatable brain disease. Notable documentary directors including Albert Maysles and Barbara Kopple made the film's nine separate segments.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;9 P.M. (MTV) TRUE LIFE -- The day-to-day lives of young people who are autistic.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;9 P.M. (Starz) THE CHRONICLES OF NARNIA: THE LION, THE WITCH AND THE WARDROBE -- (2005). In an adaptation of the C.S. Lewis novel, a group of children find themselves transported from World War II England to the mystical land of Narnia, which they must help free from the grip of the evil white witch (Tilda Swinton, right, with Skander Keynes as Edmund).
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;9:30 P.M. (NBC) ANDY BARKER, P.I. -- Accountant Andy Barker had never failed in his life until his business tanked. Rather than fix his current predicament, Andy begins to lead a double life after he's mistaken for a retired private detective who once owned the same office. In the series premiere, Andy must solve a case involving a missing husband and the Russian mafia.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;10 P.M. (NBC) RAINES -- After ''Andy Barker, P.I.,'' NBC unveils another unusual detective show, a drama this time. Jeff Goldblum plays the title character, Michael Raines, a homicide detective who may not talk to ghosts but can imagine what they would say. In the premiere episode, a murdered woman helps him piece together the clues that may lead to her killer.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;10 P.M. (ABC) OCTOBER ROAD -- After Nick Garrett (Bryan Greenbert, left, with Laura Prepon as Hannah, far left) graduated from high school, he only looked back to his small hometown long enough to use his family and friends as fodder for a successful novel. Coming home for the first time in 10 years, he discovers they're not so appreciative.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;10:30 P.M. (Comedy Central) THE SHOWBIZ SHOW WITH DAVID SPADE -- Mr. Spade is back for a third season of satirizing the more ridiculous aspects of Hollywood's inherent ridiculousness.   LORI MOORE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content/>
  </body>
</nitf>
