<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Subway Signs: Less Than Indicative</title>
    <meta content="30SIGN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="947176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Signs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Transit Riders Council</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Transit Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pierre-Pierre, Garry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Signs and Symbols</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DD113AF933A05754C0A961958260" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Subway Signs: Less Than Indicative</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GARRY PIERRE-PIERRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pierre-Pierre, Garry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Transit Riders Council survey finds that misleading, confusing or concealed signs are common problems at many of city's subway stations; Transit Authority says it began $25 million, five-year capital plan two years ago to put up signs where they were missing and replace unclear ones; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you are looking for the M train on a sign at the Canal Street subway station entrances, you will not see it listed with the other trains.</p>
        <p>At the 161st Street station in the Bronx, one of the signs indicates that the Yankee Stadium stop on the C, D and 4 trains is open every day ''from 6:15 A.M. to 12 P.M.,'' which is noon, but the station is open until midnight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you are looking for the M train on a sign at the Canal Street subway station entrances, you will not see it listed with the other trains.</p>
        <p>At the 161st Street station in the Bronx, one of the signs indicates that the Yankee Stadium stop on the C, D and 4 trains is open every day ''from 6:15 A.M. to 12 P.M.,'' which is noon, but the station is open until midnight.</p>
        <p>And the signs for the B, D and Q trains at the Grand Street station  in Manhattan are covered by an advertisement for a Target discount store.</p>
        <p>Misleading, confusing, concealed or unclear signs were common problems at many of the city's subway stations in a three-month survey by the New York City Transit Riders Council, an advocacy group.</p>
        <p>In a report released yesterday, the group said that it had evaluated 100 randomly chosen subway stations and that one out of three had problems with signs that could lead to riders wandering in search of the right subway stations, waiting for trains that are not running and boarding trains bound for the wrong destinations.</p>
        <p>''It's a big and complicated system, and people need direction to find their way,'' said Alan H. Foster, associate director of the riders' council. ''I think that those of us who use the subways every day tend to forget how important the signage is.''</p>
        <p>Officials at the New York City  Transit Authority called the report ''comprehensive'' and said they were well on their way to fixing  problems that were identified in 1987 in a similar report by the council. That reported concluded that signs at the subway stations were ''woefully inadequate.''</p>
        <p>Jared Lebow, a spokesman for the Transit Authority, said that  transit officials had begun a $25 million, five-year capital plan two years ago to put up signs where they were missing and replace unclear ones. So far, he said, some signs at 176 of the 468 stations in the system have been updated, and the program -- it will cover every station -- is expected to be completed by 1999. Even as the report was being released yesterday, transit workers were fixing signs that the report mentioned, including ones at the 86th Street station on the B and C trains that were inconsistent in telling riders which trains stopped there.</p>
        <p>''We're working our way through the system and wherever we have problems with signage we're dealing with it,'' Mr. Lebow said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Foster acknowledged that progress had been made since the 1987 report. He said that 12 workers had surveyed 363 subway entrances, 171 token booth areas, 222 platforms and 262 tracks from February to May this year. He said the most frequent problem was that subway lines were often not listed on the stations' entrance signs. Also, more than one-fifth of the entrances did not have green and red lights to indicate, respectively, whether the entrance and its token booth were open 24 hours or not, the report stated.</p>
        <p>Track signs were a problem at more than one-fourth of the stations surveyed. Most often the signs were not specific enough or gave too little information.</p>
        <p>The report recommended that the Transit Authority install colored lights at entrances that do not have them, maintain signs that are readable and word new signs in a way that can be understood by tourists and others who are unfamiliar with the system.</p>
        <p>Transit officials have said that newly arrived immigrants were largely responsible for a 20 percent increase in subway ridership that occurred in 1996. Still, there are no subway signs in Russian, Chinese or Haitian Creole, the languages of some of the non-English-speaking ethnic groups that officials said had fostered the increase in ridership.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
