<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's My (Virtual) World  and Welcome to It!</title>
    <meta content="03second" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/03/travel/escapes/03second.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1801761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Virtual Reality (Computers)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Second Life (3d Virtual Environment)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Virtual Reality (Computers)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E3D8133FF930A35752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's My (Virtual) World  and Welcome to It!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It’s My (Virtual) World ...</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT GROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Matthew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matt Gross article describes spending weekend in Second Life virtual-reality universe as virtual tourist; Second Life is three-dimensional world of mountains, oceans, forests and cities; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BEN FOLDS was shirtless and mumbling onstage, taking huge swigs from the can of Duff Beer he held in his right hand. Then he fell down drunk. Then he got up and shot laser beams from his eyes.</p>
        <p>Then things turned really nasty: Mr. Folds pulled out a light saber and attacked the audience. To avoid him, I levitated 20 feet, hoping he wouldn't notice. It worked; I survived.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spend a weekend in cyberspace dancing, shopping, chatting and levitating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BEN FOLDS was shirtless and mumbling onstage, taking huge swigs from the can of Duff Beer he held in his right hand. Then he fell down drunk. Then he got up and shot laser beams from his eyes.</p>
        <p>Then things turned really nasty: Mr. Folds pulled out a light saber and attacked the audience. To avoid him, I levitated 20 feet, hoping he wouldn't notice. It worked; I survived.</p>
        <p>As concerts go, this was a fairly normal one -- at least in Second Life, the virtual-reality universe where I recently spent a weekend as a (virtual) tourist. In fact, if the Ben Folds show was unusual in any way, it was that it marked the opening of Second Life's first boutique hotel, an online version of Starwood Hotels' new ''urban loft living'' brand, Aloft. (A bricks-and-mortar Aloft won't open until 2008.)</p>
        <p>And Aloft's arrival -- on a digital tropical island somewhere in a vast virtual ocean -- may itself signal the beginning of Second Life as a casual travel destination. For Second Life is, quite literally, a world unto itself, with three-dimensional mountains, oceans, forests and cities spanning tens of thousands of virtual acres. (It can be entered at www.secondlife.com.)</p>
        <p>A player -- or resident, in Second Life parlance -- navigates this space through an avatar, a digital persona whose features can be adjusted to suit almost any whim (pointy chin, neon-green irises, the thick and full head of hair I remember having for a split-second in 11th grade).</p>
        <p>But unlike other multiplayer online role-playing games, like the insanely popular World of Warcraft (www.worldofwarcraft.com), Second Life is not really a game.</p>
        <p>There are no princesses to save nor orcs to slaughter. Instead, the goal is simply to interact with the million-plus other residents, explore the planet and, in a unique twist, create new parts of it.</p>
        <p>For Second Life lets residents build objects using small, basic shapes called prims. Almost everything you encounter -- from ice-cream cones to modernist houses to cans of Duff -- has been created by a resident, and much of it is for sale.</p>
        <p>It's that commercial aspect that has lured real-life businesses like American Apparel to open in-game boutiques in an attempt not only to build their brands but also to take in a few Linden dollars, the virtual currency named for Second Life's developers, the Linden Lab, and convertible to actual money at a rate of about 250 Linden dollars to $1.Secondlife.com tracks the amount of money spent in-game in the last 24 hours; the record is over $575,000 -- and that's U.S., not Linden!</p>
        <p>Actually, it was American Apparel that took my first stack of digital cash. I -- or rather, Urge Gainsbourg, my avatar -- had arrived in Second Life looking like the tourist that I was, with a generic yellow T-shirt, white button-down shirt and calf-length khaki pants. So I teleported (residents generally walk, fly or teleport around) to American Apparel's store, a glass-walled two-story structure decorated with the same cheerfully sleazy photographs that I'd seen in the company's real-world stores.</p>
        <p>There were no other customers and no model-gorgeous employees; all I had to do was click the racks of brightly colored clothes, and the system would offer to take my money in exchange for a T-shirt. I walked -- that is, teleported -- out of there in a teal T-shirt and blue-and-white hoodie, feeling less like a tourist for having spent 600 Lindens.</p>
        <p>My destination was happy hour at the Elbow Room, which I'd learned about at secondlife.com/events, an hour-by-hour listing of yard sales, book-club meetings and pool parties. The Elbow Room's small, wood-plank dance floor was packed with stylish residents, among them a turquoise-skinned girl in camouflage pants and a gray-and-black-striped cat named Bootes Bellman.</p>
        <p>I wasn't sure how to start grooving, but an automated notification system told me to type ''/dance''; I did, and instantly downloaded a series of animations with names like the Butt Shake Dance. Soon I was shaking around the room to streaming music by KLF, Jane's Addiction, Susannah Hoffs and Weird Al Yankovic.</p>
        <p>Then I was teleporting on to the Bellevue, modeled after a real bar in Hell's Kitchen (''est. 1912,'' it claims) that was giving out free Boingboing.net T-shirts, and then to the SkyClub, a futuristic boîte hovering hundreds of feet overhead. It may have been virtual, but it sure felt like a Friday night.</p>
        <p>Except that I woke up at home, in my own bed. The great thing about weekending in Second Life is that you don't need a place to crash -- you just log off. Neither did I have a hangover -- a surprise since Urge Gainsbourg had fallen off his barstool after drinking too much Duff. (It was Urge who had given Ben Folds the Duff.)</p>
        <p>SATURDAY morning found Urge flying around Svarga, a mountainous island with an ecosystem in which bees flit from flower to flower, pollinating them. ''The seeds blow in the wind,'' Svarga's creator, Laukosargas Svarog, told New World Notes (nwn.blogs.com), one of a handful of Second Life news outlets, ''and if they land on good ground according to different rules for each species, they grow when they receive rain water from the clouds. It's all interdependent.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the programming, Svarga is beautiful, with lush ferns, rushing waterfalls and a grove where violets spring up around your avatar the minute he/she/it sets foot on the grass. In fact, I'm tempted to call it a work of art, my only hesitation being that so much in Second Life is artistically sophisticated, from the snowy wastes of Wengen -- which I tromped across in virtual roller skates -- to the ''zoom blur'' photographs of Bucky Barkley, who showed them at a Second Life gallery on Saturday evening, complete with virtual cheese and crackers.</p>
        <p>Like most events I attended in Second Life -- including Sunday-morning church services -- Barkley's show wound up with everybody dancing. Actually, the only place I went where few people danced (besides the academic discussion of genocide in the freakishly earnest Neufreistadt) was Saturday night's Metajams party, at which eight live musicians performed in a single audio stream. The crowd stood mostly stock still as Ricardo Sprocket, Komuso Tokugawa and others played a medley of folk-slash-indie rock tunes that were easily as good as anything I've heard in New York clubs. Better yet: no cover charge.</p>
        <p>At the same time, I was feeling a bit lonely. I'd had brief chats with a dozen Second Life residents -- the unreality makes it easy to approach them -- but had made no real connection. In a way, it was because I really was a tourist. I had nothing invested in this world, while they were building houses and yachts, organizing rock concerts and fashion shows and creating virtual refugee camps to educate people about Darfur.</p>
        <p>I watched them greeting each other like old friends and cuddling on hilltop picnic blankets, and wished my wife, Jean, who was watching cable in the next room, had a computer of her own, so we could explore Second Life together.</p>
        <p>I considered for a moment going to the strip club I'd accidentally wandered into earlier, but instead I cooked dinner -- a real, not virtual, menu of seared duck breasts, mushrooms sautéed with thyme, and potatoes roasted in duck fat, garlic and rosemary. Then Jean and I opened a bottle of syrah from the Russian River Valley and commenced our feast. It was, we agreed, an especially satisfying meal -- and I knew exactly why: because, as Second Lifers understand all too well, I'd made it myself.</p>
        <p>A CYBERWEEKEND</p>
        <p>Design Yourself a Body; Boogie All Night</p>
        <p>GETTING THERE -- First, download the Second Life software at www.secondlife.com; it's free and available for both Windows XP and Macintosh OSX. A basic subscription costs nothing, but a premium membership, $22.95 for three months, deposits 400 Linden dollars into your account every week.</p>
        <p>Second World is divided into named sections (Svarga, for example) made up of 256-by-256 grids. To reach one, your avatar can walk or fly, which tends to be slow but scenic, or teleport directly, by inputting the area name and coordinates, which make up the addresses.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO STAY -- You don't really need a place to sleep, but there are hotels in Second Life, like the Westport (Sphinx, 32, 104; 200 Linden dollars a week).</p>
        <p>You can't rent a room at Aloft (Aloft Island, 68, 68), but you can see a sample room.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO EAT AND DRINK -- House of Zen (Hinode Shima 198, 31) serves sushi in a traditional Japanese building, free if you order à la carte at the bar, but 150 Linden dollars a person for table service.</p>
        <p>Bellevue (Hawthorne 162, 167) is a rollicking, low-key bar straight out of Hell's Kitchen.</p>
        <p>WHERE TO SHOP -- There are almost as many boutiques and malls as there are residents, so check out Second Style magazine (www.secondstyle.com) for fashion advice. And for the default urban hipster look, there's always American Apparel (Lerappa 152, 64).</p>
        <p>WHAT TO SEE AND DO -- Svarga (Svarga 7, 123) is a constantly evolving world worth exploring.</p>
        <p>Nakama (Nakama 46, 46) is a city designed in various styles of Japanese anime.</p>
        <p>Knock down a few pins at Acropolis Bowl (Walleye 112, 18), then hit the dance floor or listen to live music at Mood Indigo (Olive 217, 227).</p>
        <p>Sundays at noon Pacific time, visit the Church of Elvis (Nampo 231, 228) to learn about the holy trinity: Young Elvis, Fat Elvis and the '68 Comeback Special Elvis.</p>
        <p>The Virtual Hallucinations experiment (Sedig 45, 25) lets you experience the auditory and visual hallucinations that schizophrenics have to deal with every day.</p>
        <p>And if you're feeling lost, Synthravels offers virtual guide services; see www.synthravels.com for details.</p>
        <p>MATT GROSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
