<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Struggle in the Balkins; Cease-Fire in Battered Muslim Town Seals a Key Victory for Serb Forces</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="603232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISLAM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SREBRENICA (BOSNIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA-HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MLADIC, RATKO (GEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF1331F93BA25757C0A965958260" item-length="1664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Struggle in the Balkins; Cease-Fire in Battered Muslim Town Seals a Key Victory for Serb Forces</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>SARAJEVO, Bosnia and Herzegovina, April 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>United Nations officials said tonight that the commander of the Bosnian Government Army had agreed to a cease-fire around the besieged city of Srebrenica and other steps intended to turn the town into a "safe area" to avert a battle to the finish with the town's Serbian attackers.</p>
        <p>Though the accord was reached in response to a demand by the United Nations Security Council on Friday, it involves the disarming of the devastated city's Muslim defenders and allows for an exodus, goals long sought by Serbian nationalist forces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>United Nations officials said tonight that the commander of the Bosnian Government Army had agreed to a cease-fire around the besieged city of Srebrenica and other steps intended to turn the town into a "safe area" to avert a battle to the finish with the town's Serbian attackers.</p>
        <p>Though the accord was reached in response to a demand by the United Nations Security Council on Friday, it involves the disarming of the devastated city's Muslim defenders and allows for an exodus, goals long sought by Serbian nationalist forces.</p>
        <p>The agreement followed four hours of talks at Sarajevo airport between Maj. Sefer Halilovic, the commander of the Bosnian Government Army, and Gen. Ratko Mladic, commander of the Serbian nationalist forces that are battling to dismember Bosnia. It was their first meeting since the war broke out a year ago. 5,000 Killed in Siege</p>
        <p>After a meeting with the opposing commanders in a converted freight building at the airport, the two top United Nations generals in the former Yugoslavia, Lieut. Gen. Lars-Eric Wahlgren of Sweden and Lieut. Gen. Philippe Morillon of France, sent a United Nations official to tell reporters that they had reached an "agreement in principle" to prevent further carnage in Srebrenica and surrounding Muslim villages in eastern Bosnia. Nearly 5,000 people are estimated to have died in the town since the Serbian siege began.</p>
        <p>The United Nations official, Shannon Boyd, said a cease-fire was set for 5 A.M. Sunday, or about 10 P.M. Eastern standard time Saturday. Ms. Boyd said General Mladic, the Serbian military commander, had agreed to allow an infantry company of 150 Canadian soldiers serving with the United Nations peacekeeping force to cross Serbian siege lines and enter Srebrenica at 11 A.M. on Sunday.</p>
        <p>The agreement is also to allow United Nations relief convoys into Srebrenica.</p>
        <p>Ms. Boyd said the Canadian contingent would be involved in carrying out what she called the city's "demilitarization," a task that other United Nations officials said would include gathering under United Nations control all the weapons of the exhausted Bosnian garrison there.</p>
        <p>Ms. Boyd said the commanders also agreed to establish an air corridor through which British and French military helicopters assigned to the United Nations force would evacuate sick and wounded people. Affirming 'Safe Passage'</p>
        <p>The United Nations official said the agreement would also affirm the right of "safe passage" for civilians wishing to move in and out of the city, a step that appeared to open the way for an exodus of thousands who have been desperate to flee.</p>
        <p>The agreement appeared to have averted, at least temporarily, what has threatened to become the largest single catastrophe of the Bosnian war. As the Security Council met to order the establishment of a "safe area" at Srebrenica on Friday night, Serbian forces were reported to be on the outskirts of the old silver-mining city, within hours of overrunning it.</p>
        <p>On similar occasions in the past, in the war in Bosnia and in the conflict in Croatia in 1991, Serbian forces completing their assaults on cities and towns have often engaged in widespread killing of civilians and in wide destruction of property, mainly of Muslim and Croatian homes.</p>
        <p>But what the United Nations military commanders accomplished at the meeting here appeared to fall far short of "saving" Srebrenica, as General Morillon, the United Nations commander in Bosnia, promised when he established a command post in the city in mid-March and vowed to remain with the predominantly Muslim population until their safety was assured. Serbian Gains Seen</p>
        <p>Several United Nations officials said privately that the accord outlined by Ms. Boyd appeared to offer the Serbian commanders a strong prospect of achieving their main goal at Srebrenica, emptying the city and its surrounding villages of an estimated 40,000 to 60,000 Muslim inhabitants, or at least a great majority of them, without having to fight.</p>
        <p>Among the indications that Serbian commanders have not abandoned plans to gain control of the town were a continuing barrage of Srebrenica as the talks opened today in Sarajevo, the Bosnian capital. United Nations officials said the small peacekeeping contingent in Srebrenica had reported "heavy shelling" around lunchtime that resulted in casualties, including the deaths of several civilians struck in areas near the city center.</p>
        <p>One embittered United Nations official said the accord appeared to set the stage for what he called "another chapter of ethnic cleansing," the Serbian nationalist tactic of attacking Muslim and Croatian enclaves and killing or driving out their residents to create exclusive Serbian domains.</p>
        <p>The official, who recently spent several weeks in Srebrenica assisting United Nations relief efforts, predicted that most Muslims there would take the first opportunity to leave aboard United Nations convoys, and would do so all the more speedily once the city's Bosnian Government defenders were disarmed. 150,000 Muslims Lost</p>
        <p>The United Nations generals conducting the airport talks appeared to have had a free hand in interpreting a resolution approved Friday night by the Security Council, the latest in a long series that have sought without success to halt the "ethnic cleansing" offensives by Serbs.</p>
        <p>The Serbian nationalist drive is estimated to have caused the deaths or disappearance of at least 150,000 Muslims. United Nations officials here said the United Nations commanders had received a text of the resolution from New York but no instructions on how it should be put into effect.</p>
        <p>The United Nations resolution was amended before it was unanimously passed to avoid any implication that United Nations forces would assume an active military role in resisting Serbian attacks at Srebrenica, a step favored by some Muslim countries that have seats on the 15-nation Security Council.  Resolution's Instructions</p>
        <p>In its final version, the resolution demanded that all parties in the Bosnian war "treat Srebrenica and its surroundings as a safe area which should be free from any armed attack or any other hostile act." United Nations forces were charged with "monitoring the humanitarian situation in the safe area."</p>
        <p>Ms. Boyd, the United Nations spokeswoman, said important details remained to be worked out by officials who would remain at the airport into the night. Among those details were maps setting out the boundaries of the "safe area," and how much of the area, if any, would include territory under the control of Serbian forces.</p>
        <p>Another matter that remains unresolved, according to United Nations officials, involves the procedures for achieving the "demilitarization" of the area under United Nations monitoring, including arrangements for disarming combatants.</p>
        <p>The details could be crucial. For instance, it was not clear from what Ms. Boyd said whether the airport accord envisaged the disarming of the Bosnian Government forces only, or of Serbian units that have pressed their advance to the perimeter of the city. Pullback Chances Unclear</p>
        <p>It was also not clear whether the pact would include any effective provision for forcing the encircling Serbian units to pull back, as demanded in the United Nations resolution. Without a withdrawal, Muslims in Srebrenica could find themselves surrounded as before by an overwhelming Serbian military force, with only 150 lightly armed United Nations soldiers in the city. They are under standing United Nations orders in Bosnia not to fire unless their own lives are endangered.</p>
        <p>In the 36 hours that preceded the airport meeting, Bosnian commanders in Srebrenica had been negotiating through United Nations officers for a surrender. One interpretation of the airport accord was that it amounted to a face-saving way of ceding the city to the Serbian forces without extensive bloodshed and without the Bosnian Government's having to admit defeat.</p>
        <p>One United Nations official at the meeting said that "Srebrenica is dead," and that efforts should be turned now to finding ways of preventing Serbian forces from proceeding with the "ethnic cleansing" of the last remaining Muslim enclaves in eastern Bosnia, around Zepa and Gorazde. Smiles for the Serbs</p>
        <p>The mood at the meeting of the opposing military commanders reflected the fortunes of the Serbian attackers and of the Muslims who have struggled to hold out against the Serbian barrages for months.</p>
        <p>General Mladic, the Serbian, smiled frequently at its outset. At one point, the 51-year-old general leaned over to one of his subordinates, gestured at the Bosnian officers and whispered something. Both Serbian officers laughed. BALKAN UPDATE</p>
        <p>United Nations officials announced in SARAJEVO yesterday that the top commanders of the armies battling for the besieged city of SREBRENICA had agreed on a cease-fire and other steps intended to turn the city into a United Nations-monitored "safe area," as ordered by the Security Council.</p>
        <p>The commander of the United Nations peacekeeping force in BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA, Lieut. Gen. Lars-Eric Wahlgren of Sweden, negotiated with Serbian and Bosnian military commanders at Sarajevo airport.</p>
        <p>A United Nations convoy of nine trucks carrying food and other humanitarian supplies for the town's inhabitants was forced to return to BELGRADE.</p>
        <p>At the UNITED NATIONS, France and Britain took the lead in pressing for harsh new economic sanctions on Yugoslavia in an effort to influence Belgrade to influence Bosnian Serbs on Srebrenica.</p>
        <p>In PARIS, Foreign Minister Alain Juppe demanded sanctions to cut Serbia off from the world "at the earliest possible moment." In LONDON, a spokesman said the Government favored immediate action against Serbia.</p>
        <p>In BRUSSELS, NATO's military commander in Europe, Gen. John Shalikashvili, said attacks on limited military targets in Bosnia could kill civilians without advancing peace negotiations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
