<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When the Twain of Science and God Meet; Seeking Independently</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="603077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELIGION AND CHURCHES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">APPLEYARD, BRYAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DA113CF93BA25757C0A965958260" item-length="404" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When the Twain of Science and God Meet; Seeking Independently</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Bryan Appleyard has "discovered" in "In Science We Trust" (Op-Ed, April 8) what he believes is a significant change in attitude of scientists toward religion, in that they are now appropriating God.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Bryan Appleyard has "discovered" in "In Science We Trust" (Op-Ed, April 8) what he believes is a significant change in attitude of scientists toward religion, in that they are now appropriating God.</p>
        <p>Apparently, he cannot distinguish between metaphor and belief. There is nothing religious about expressing awe, perhaps couched in metaphorical terms by many of us, in confronting revolutionary observations or insights about the nature of the universe or lesser phenomena.</p>
        <p>Part of Mr. Appleyard's confusion, and that of others, including scientists, is based on the perception that "science" and "religion" are pre-existent, free-standing, self-generated edifices, when in reality they are both human constructs.</p>
        <p>The body of knowledge and experience called science is fluid, subject to constant revision and simply the expression of human beings trying to understand the nature of the universe. The tools and ways of thinking scientists use in the quest are developed as a result of successful experience in getting answers consistent with that body of knowledge, without presupposing their ultimate reality or assuming their innate correctness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Appleyard is concerned that there is "a danger -- that science and religion, after almost four centuries of conflict, had arrived at a modus vivendi." He need not worry. That likelihood is almost nil. Scientists generally accept the probabilistic nature of what they do and learn. The religious insist the absolute nature of what they know is the truth; for them there can be no question of probability regarding the existence of God. The concept of probability will keep the two groups permanently apart.</p>
        <p>Finally, Mr. Appleyard perceives "science's historical role as a purely descriptive exercise." He states, "Religion, however, is about explanation, not description." He again confuses the significant differences. Scientific description is only the first step in trying to explain how things are and came to be. The religious, with their explanation based on authority, have no monopoly in this.</p>
        <p>Mr. Appleyard's misinterpretations, such as this one, only fuel unnecessary confrontations between groups of people trying in their own distinctive ways to shed light on who we are, where we live and whence we came. JEROME GROSS, M.D. Charlestown, Mass., April 8, 1993 The writer is a biologist at Massachusetts General Hospital.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
