<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seoul Urged to Make Amends for 1980 Massacre</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="121715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUPS D'ETAT AND ATTEMPTED COUPS D'ETAT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH KOREA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KWANGJU (SOUTH KOREA)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHUN DOO HWAN (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HABERMAN, CLYDE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD6123CF937A15751C0A96E948260" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seoul Urged to Make Amends for 1980 Massacre</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HABERMAN, CLYDE</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, Feb. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A special Government committee said today that in the name of national harmony, South Korea's new leadership should apologize and pay compensation to survivors of a 1980 massacre in the city of Kwangju.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A special Government committee said today that in the name of national harmony, South Korea's new leadership should apologize and pay compensation to survivors of a 1980 massacre in the city of Kwangju.</p>
        <p>A special Government committee said today that in the name of national harmony, South Korea's new leadership should apologize and pay compensation to survivors of a 1980 massacre in the city of Kwangju.</p>
        <p>The panel, the Committee for the Promotion of Democracy and National Reconciliation, said the Government must act now to ''restore the honor of the citizens of Kwangju,'' a southwestern provincial capital. It also said that the Government should stop describing street protests that led to the killings as a rebellion, and should characterize them instead as part of a pro-democratic movement.</p>
        <p>The committee's recommendation was the first significant measure taken by an official body to heal the wounds left by the Kwangju episode, in which troops gunned downed unarmed civilians protesting a coup led by Gen. Chun Doo Hwan, who is now President. By official count, nearly 200 people died, but Kwangju residents insist that a cover-up has hidden the true death toll, which many of them put at 2,000.</p>
        <p>The massacre was a pivotal event for South Korea. Because of Kwangju, many Koreans - arguably, most -have never accepted the political legitimacy of Mr. Chun, whose term of office expires Wednesday at midnight. He will give way then to Roh Tae Woo, a fellow former general who helped him grab power and who will take office Thursday as South Korea's first freely elected president in 17 years. 'Abide by Its Spirit'</p>
        <p>Mr. Roh, accepting the committee's report, pledged to ''abide by its spirit,'' but he did not say specifically what action he would take, or when.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Roh's inauguration approached, the two main opposition leaders, Kim Young Sam and Kim Dae Jung, met today for the first time since before the presidential election Dec. 16. It was the first sign that the Kims might be able to reunite after a ruinous falling-out last fall, when they both insisted on running for president and thereby split the anti-Government camp, allowing Mr. Roh to win with only 36.6 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>Opposition politicians have expressed concern that unless the Kims can patch up their differences they will face another disaster in National Assembly elections expected to be held in April. It is unclear, though, whether the two men can overcome serious personal and philosophical divisions.</p>
        <p>In an attempt to encourage unity, Kim Young Sam gave up his party's presidency two weeks ago, although he clearly remains its dominant force. Today, he agreed to the other Kim's formula for a pre-election reapportionment of the National Assembly. But thus far Kim Dae Jung has resisted pressure that he similarly step aside, saying he will do so only after the rival opposition parties are merged. Chun Expresses Regrets</p>
        <p>On Kwangju, President Chun has suddenly abandoned years of total silence over the last few weeks, and has used farewell news conferences to express regret that he is stepping down with the matter unresolved. But he has never come close to apologizing for the killings, or to suggesting that his troops may have overreacted, as even the martial-law commander at the time acknowledged recently.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chun's departure after eight years of authoritarian rule is a historic moment for South Korea. Never before has a South Korean leader voluntarily stepped aside, and he presents his action as being, of itself, a critical step in the country's democratic development.</p>
        <p>His successor, Mr. Roh, appointed the 56-member reconciliation committee after his election, and instructed it to suggest ways not only to deal with Kwangju but also to promote democratic change in general.</p>
        <p>Speaking in broad outline, the panel urged the new President, among other measures, to restrict domestic surveillance by intelligence agencies and to guarantee press freedom and an independent judiciary. But its most striking conclusions involved Kwangju.</p>
        <p>Although it called for an official apology, the committee rejected long-standing opposition demands for a new investigation into the incident, calling it fruitless and potentially divisive. Nevertheless, its own inquiry involved days of public hearings, highlighted by often-emotional testimony from people who had been swept up in the 1980 events. Many South Koreans said later that these recollections were in themselves therapeutic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
