<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Battle Over Rights To Bloomingdale's Store</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="351570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKRUPTCIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EVICTIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BLOOMINGDALE'S</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERATED DEPARTMENT STORES INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">B BROS REALTY LIMITED PARTNERSHIP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CAMPEAU CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARMASH, ISADORE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB1031F93BA35756C0A966958260" item-length="594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Battle Over Rights To Bloomingdale's Store</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ISADORE BARMASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARMASH, ISADORE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A bankruptcy court battle has broken out over the rights to the Bloomingdale's flagship store in Manhattan, with the Bloomingdale family, which no longer owns any part of the store but does own the land under it, seeking to evict the store by May 17.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A bankruptcy court battle has broken out over the rights to the Bloomingdale's flagship store in Manhattan, with the Bloomingdale family, which no longer owns any part of the store but does own the land under it, seeking to evict the store by May 17.</p>
        <p>A bankruptcy court battle has broken out over the rights to the Bloomingdale's flagship store in Manhattan, with the Bloomingdale family, which no longer owns any part of the store but does own the land under it, seeking to evict the store by May 17.</p>
        <p>The issue is whether Federated Department Stores Inc., Bloomingdale's parent, which filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy in January, violated terms of the building's lease by transferring the lease from its name to that of Bloomingdale's.</p>
        <p>B. Bros. Realty Limited Partnership, the investment company of the Bloomingdale brothers, insists that the transfer was made without the family's written consent and as part of a pledge of collateral made by Federated to get bankruptcy financing before and after that filing.</p>
        <p>Festering of Resentment</p>
        <p>Underlying the legal battle is an apparent festering of resentment over the Federated bankruptcy between Federated and the descendants of Bloomingdale's founders, Lyman and Joseph Bloomingdale. More than 20 members of the Bloomingdale family own the land and the building of the huge flagship store. About a third of Bloomingdale's $1.3 billion sales in its 17 stores are made in that single building.</p>
        <p>The lease on the building has 16 years to run, and its short duration has been generally deemed a principal reason why the chain failed to attract satisfactory bids when the Campeau Corporation of Toronto, Federated's parent, put it up for sale in September. In its court papers, B. Bros. also charged that Federated had violated the lease terms when it put Bloomingdale's up for sale without first obtaining approval from B. Bros.</p>
        <p>''The interest of B. Bros. in the leases is not adequately protected,'' the court documents say, ''and since B. Bros.' interests are not adequately protected, it is not unreasonable for B. Bros to withhold its consent to any pledge or collateral assignment of the leases.''</p>
        <p>Federated, for its part, flatly denies the transfer of the lease and says that B. Bros. has ''never been able to point to one iota of claimed harm to itself from the alleged transfer.'' The Cincinnati-based retail company, which is owned by Campeau, has filed a motion of its own, asking Bankruptcy Judge J. Vincent Aug to hold a hearing before May 17.</p>
        <p>After first filing its motion on April 17 and then facing an April 20 stay in its motion for eviction, Federated says, B. Bros. said that 30 days after its first motion, it would take steps to terminate the lease on the Bloomingdale's store at 1000 Third Avenue in Manhattan and evict the business.</p>
        <p>Hearing Tomorrow</p>
        <p>A hearing on the Federated motion has been scheduled by Judge Aug on Wednesday in the Cincinnati Federal bankruptcy court.</p>
        <p>The same dispute also involves the Bloomingdale's warehouse at 23-02 49th Avenue in Long Island City, Queens, a 500,000-square-foot structure also owned by B. Bros. and rented by Bloomingdale's.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview yesterday, John L. Ernst, a great-grandson of Lyman Bloomingdale and a general partner in B. Bros., said: ''We want to protect our rights, which we feel were breached. We have asked for information, but what we have gotten is unsatisfactory. We own the land, but the building is owned by Federated. But if the lease is violated, it reverts to us.''</p>
        <p>The flagship building was constructed in 1927, three years before the Bloomingdale family sold the retail business to Federated Department Stores, which promptly added other well-known American retailers like Abraham &amp; Straus in Brooklyn, Filene's in Boston and Lazarus of Cincinnati.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
