<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Shea, Life Diverges for Two Mets</title>
    <meta content="19shea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/19/sports/baseball/19shea.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1783835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Backman, Wally</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dykstra, Lenny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EEDA153EF93AA2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Shea, Life Diverges for Two Mets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Shea, Life Diverges for Two Mets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL S. SCHMIDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmidt, Michael S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty years ago, Lenny Dykstra and Wally Backman were the pesky twins at the top of the Mets' championship lineup. They wreaked havoc on the basepaths, and like many of the other players on that team, partied hard off the field.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, sitting in the back of a black sport utility vehicle at the beginning of a 1986 reunion weekend, the two smoked cigarettes and laughed about their team and their championship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>While Lenny Dykstra has done well with business and stock market activities, Wally Backman has stayed closer to baseball but has dealt with off-field troubles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Twenty years ago, Lenny Dykstra and Wally Backman were the pesky twins at the top of the Mets' championship lineup. They wreaked havoc on the basepaths, and like many of the other players on that team, partied hard off the field.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, sitting in the back of a black sport utility vehicle at the beginning of a 1986 reunion weekend, the two smoked cigarettes and laughed about their team and their championship.</p>
        <p>They had just helped rededicate a room at the Ronald McDonald House of Long Island in New Hyde Park with four of their teammates from the 1986 team -- Keith Hernandez, Ron Darling, Mookie Wilson, and Tim Teufel.</p>
        <p>The weekend was beginning, and players who had kept in touch, and others who had not, would be catching up with one another.</p>
        <p>For Backman and Dykstra, there was plenty to talk about. Since retiring from baseball in 1996, Dykstra, 43, has done well with a car wash business in California, has invested in the stock market and, remarkably, considering his impish image with the Mets, now writes a weekly column about investing on the Web. But he has also been plagued by chronic back problems, and moves slowly these days.</p>
        <p>Backman, in contrast, has tried to keep a closer connection with baseball. He established himself as a standout manager in the minors while displaying some of the firebrand personality he had with the Mets.</p>
        <p>In 2004, he was named manager of the Arizona Diamondbacks. But Backman's tenure as the Diamondbacks manager lasted all of four days.</p>
        <p>His downfall began when an article in The New York Times about his hiring noted that he had difficulties off the field, involving drunken driving, a domestic dispute and a bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>The Diamondbacks, citing the fact that Backman had not been forthcoming about his legal difficulties, dismissed him.</p>
        <p>Since then, Backman, 46, has not coached or managed at any level. He said he spends his days fishing at his home in Oregon, following his son's early career in the minor leagues and planning for the opening of a restaurant in the Oregon town of Prineville.</p>
        <p>Could the Mets be the team that lets Backman back into the game?</p>
        <p>''I talked to the Mets after last year's winter meetings and I talked directly on the phone with Jeff Wilpon,'' Backman said in reference to the team's senior executive vice president.</p>
        <p>''The team didn't think the timing was right to bring me back.''</p>
        <p>Backman says he has paid the price for his off-the-field misjudgments. Mets General Manager Omar Minaya said yesterday that bringing Backman back was not out of the question but that his legal difficulties would have to be taken into consideration just as strongly as his on-the-field credentials.</p>
        <p>''Right now I haven't thought about it, especially being in the middle of the season,'' Minaya said. ''All I have heard is very good things about him as a baseball person.''</p>
        <p>Minaya confirmed that the team spoke with Backman last winter. He said Backman had been asked to interview for the Mets' managing vacancy before Willie Randolph was hired but that Backman had already committed to the Diamondbacks job.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in the back of the sports utility vehicle, Dykstra, laptop in hand, checked his stocks online. He said that his back was so bad he could not even play golf.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to go under the knife again. I had 10 surgeries as a player and many more since,'' Dykstra said, speaking as though he still had his trademark wad of tobacco in his mouth. ''My back is done -- stick a fork in me.''</p>
        <p>It was a lament, half in jest, that some other 1986 Met was likely to make this weekend as the reunion picked up momentum.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
