<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Milestone for the Creator Of the Rosenkranz Double</title>
    <meta content="19card" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/19/crosswords/bridge/19card.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1783743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Bridge"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cards and Card Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Rosenkranz, George</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE5DC153EF93AA2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Milestone for the Creator Of the Rosenkranz Double</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Milestone for the Creator of the Rosenkranz Double</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Phillip Alder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alder, Phillip</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tomorrow is the 90th birthday of Dr. George Rosenkranz, a part-time bridge expert and former full-time executive and chemist. He was born in Hungary, and after gaining a Ph.D. in organic chemistry in Zurich, he left Europe, bound for a teaching position in Ecuador. But those plans were disrupted by the outbreak of World War II, which found him stranded in Havana. After the war he moved to Mexico City, eventually taking control of a fledgling pharmaceutical company called Syntex Corporation. Rosenkranz's team synthesized many important compounds, including the birth control pill and cortisone.</p>
        <p>In his spare time Rosenkranz played bridge, quickly becoming Mexico's top-ranked player. He has nearly 17,000 American Contract Bridge League master points, making him 86th on the lifetime list; holds 12 national team titles; and was elected to the bridge league's Hall of Fame in 2000. He reached the semifinal of the 1983 Bermuda Bowl and is a World Bridge Federation world master.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. George Rosenkranz, a part-time bridge expert and former full-time executive and chemist, turns 90.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tomorrow is the 90th birthday of Dr. George Rosenkranz, a part-time bridge expert and former full-time executive and chemist. He was born in Hungary, and after gaining a Ph.D. in organic chemistry in Zurich, he left Europe, bound for a teaching position in Ecuador. But those plans were disrupted by the outbreak of World War II, which found him stranded in Havana. After the war he moved to Mexico City, eventually taking control of a fledgling pharmaceutical company called Syntex Corporation. Rosenkranz's team synthesized many important compounds, including the birth control pill and cortisone.</p>
        <p>In his spare time Rosenkranz played bridge, quickly becoming Mexico's top-ranked player. He has nearly 17,000 American Contract Bridge League master points, making him 86th on the lifetime list; holds 12 national team titles; and was elected to the bridge league's Hall of Fame in 2000. He reached the semifinal of the 1983 Bermuda Bowl and is a World Bridge Federation world master.</p>
        <p>Rosenkranz has been a prolific writer, contributing many instructive articles to the league's Bridge Bulletin. He is also the author or co-author of more than a dozen bridge books (some written with this columnist).</p>
        <p>A leading theorist, Rosenkranz has always been fascinated by bidding. One of his contributions is the Rosenkranz Double. The original idea has since been switched, giving the Reverse Rosenkranz Double: after an opening bid, an overcall and a response, an immediate raise to two of the overcaller's suit guarantees a top honor -- ace, king or queen -- in that suit, but a double shows support without a top honor.</p>
        <p>Rosenkranz used this device with effect on the diagramed deal, which arose during the J. M. Weston Mixed Pairs at the 1998 world championships in Lille, France. His partner at the table was Edith Rosenkranz, his partner in life since 1945.</p>
        <p>Four spades by North was a common contract, which almost always went down one. Against the Rosenkranzes, though, South did not offer spade support. Knowing from the bidding (George's Reverse Rosenkranz Double as East) that West surely had the heart ace, South preferred to try his luck in three no-trump. But Edith also knew that her partner did not have a high heart. So instead of leading a heart, which would have let declarer run eight tricks, she started with the spade eight, the high card denying an honor in the suit.</p>
        <p>South cashed his seven black-suit winners before leading the diamond king from the board, but George took his ace and shifted to the heart jack, giving the defenders the rest of the tricks. Down two was a near-top.</p>
        <p>Rosenkranz is still very active. He was a member of the consortium involved in the creation of the National Institute for Genomic Medicine, known in Mexico as Imegen. He was later appointed to Imegen's governmental oversight board. An important Imegen project is the study of the variations of the human genome in the diverse Mexican population as they relate to hypertension, heart disease and diabetes.</p>
        <p>Rosenkranz also competes regularly in bridge tournaments. Let's hope that we all play as well as he does when we reach 90.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
