<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prosecutors Call Handyman A Sex Predator</title>
    <meta content="19monmouth" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/19/nyregion/19monmouth.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1783815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings and Downloads (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Peeping Toms</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Monmouth County (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ocean Township (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bilski, Clement Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFDB153EF93AA2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prosecutors Call Handyman A Sex Predator</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Prosecutors Call Handyman a Sex Predator</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS; John Holl contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>FREEHOLD, N.J., Aug. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clement Bilski Jr of Ocean Township, NJ, is charged with sexually abusing at least 11 children in Monmouth County; authorities say Bilski used his job as handyman to gain access to scores of homes, winning over the children and luring them into sexual activities; say he often hid cameras in walls of homes he was working on to surreptitiously obtain images of children and other family members; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A New Jersey man who used his job as a handyman to gain access to scores of homes in the Monmouth County area has been charged with sexually abusing at least 11 children -- ranging in age from 23 months to 8 years old -- actions he captured on hours of taped and digital images, the authorities said on Friday.</p>
        <p>In addition to winning over the children and luring them into sexual activities, the Monmouth County prosecutor said, the suspect, Clement Bilski Jr., 43, of Ocean Township, often hid cameras in walls of the homes he was working on so that he could surreptitiously obtain images of the children and other members of the family when he was not there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New Jersey man had access to scores of homes, and has been charged with sexually abusing at least 11 children  ranging in age from 23 months to 8 years old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A New Jersey man who used his job as a handyman to gain access to scores of homes in the Monmouth County area has been charged with sexually abusing at least 11 children -- ranging in age from 23 months to 8 years old -- actions he captured on hours of taped and digital images, the authorities said on Friday.</p>
        <p>In addition to winning over the children and luring them into sexual activities, the Monmouth County prosecutor said, the suspect, Clement Bilski Jr., 43, of Ocean Township, often hid cameras in walls of the homes he was working on so that he could surreptitiously obtain images of the children and other members of the family when he was not there.</p>
        <p>''The scope and breadth of this indictment reflects the conduct of a deviant sexual predator who targeted the most defenseless and innocent of our communities for his own gratification,'' the prosecutor, Luis A. Valentin, said. ''He exploited the access he got as a handyman to homes in order to exploit the children in those homes. The depravity of this case knows no boundaries.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Valentin said a grand jury indicted Mr. Bilski on Friday on 429 counts, including sexual assault, manufacturing and distributing child pornography from those assaults, and invasion of privacy. Investigators called it one of the worst cases of child sexual abuse they had ever seen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valentin said that the charges announced Friday against Mr. Bilski, whose activities spanned a seven-year-period, might be just the ''tip of the iceberg,'' and that there might be other families whose children had been victimized.</p>
        <p>''Today's indictment is limited to those videotapes in our possession, and we do not know if some others were destroyed or hidden,'' he said. ''So any former clients of Mr. Bilski, particularly those with young children, should contact our investigators.''</p>
        <p>The authorities circulated pictures of Mr. Bilski as well as the two vehicles that he used and the names of the various contracting companies under which he did business -- Bilski Home Improvement, Bilco Home Improvement and J&amp;Z Construction.</p>
        <p>Richard Keil, Mr. Bilski's lawyer, could not be reached for comment on the indictment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bilski, who was first arrested in April on charges of receiving and distributing child pornography, has been in custody in the Monmouth County jail since then in $1 million cash bail.</p>
        <p>Joseph Oxley, the Monmouth County sheriff, said that as a result of this week's indictment Mr. Bilski would be placed in protective custody ''since accused child molesters don't do well in the general population.'' The sheriff added that he would also be placed under 24-hour surveillance to prevent a suicide attempt.</p>
        <p>In some ways, the discovery of the activities described in the indictment was an accident. In April, state police and Monmouth County investigators obtained a warrant to search Mr. Bilski's home after receiving a tip from a Maryland State Police task force that deals with Internet crimes against children. The tip indicated that a computer traced to Mr. Bilski had shared a video showing sexual abuse of a child with other Internet users.</p>
        <p>When investigators searched Mr. Bilski's home, they said, they stumbled on a stash of tapes and DVD's, apparently produced by him, showing him in sexual acts ranging from oral sex to vaginal and anal penetration with nine girls and two boys. Some of the material had been edited and in other instances music soundtracks had been added, said Lt. Col. Frank E. Rodgers, a deputy superintendent of investigations for the state police.</p>
        <p>''The volume of evidence that was waded through would test the sensibilities of the most ardent police investigator,'' Colonel Rodgers said of the months of work by as many as 20 state and local investigators on the case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valentin said that in addition to making it his business to be around homes with young children, Mr. Bilski would learn the daily routines in his clients' homes and would often engage the children to help him with his work.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor called the process ''grooming'' his victims, and said it included giving them candy and toys and instructing them not to tell anyone what had happened.</p>
        <p>Along the quiet dead-end street where Mr. Bilski had lived since February, there was a sense of shock and violation among residents who have watched the investigation unfold since the April raid.</p>
        <p>Bob Strano, who lives across the street from Mr. Bilski's house, wondered how to explain to his grandchildren what the authorities say took place, and then gave up.</p>
        <p>''It's insane,'' Mr. Strano said. ''You just can't comprehend it. I don't know how to explain it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
