<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Pick the School Board?</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="802127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="SCHOOLS: REFERENDUM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCHOOL ADMINISTRATION AND COMMUNITY ROLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MONTCLAIR (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILCHMAN, ALAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODNOUGH, ABBY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">School Administration and Community Role</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DE1E3CF931A15753C1A963958260" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Pick the School Board?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODNOUGH, ABBY</byline>
      <dateline>MONTCLAIR</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Alan Milchman moved his family here two decades ago, he considered the schools to be top-notch. But now, with his youngest child in middle school, Mr. Milchman has had a change of heart. The quality of education has deteriorated, he says, and so many residents have taken their children out of public schools that ethnic diversity -- once a prized feature of the system -- is disappearing.</p>
        <p>In the search for solutions, Mr. Milchman zeroed in on Montclair's Board of Education. Its seven members have always been appointed by the mayor, and as a result, Mr. Milchman and others say, candidates are culled from a select group of civic organizations and tend to represent limited points of view. Since board members are not elected by the public, he says, they are not always sensitive to residents' concerns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Alan Milchman moved his family here two decades ago, he considered the schools to be top-notch. But now, with his youngest child in middle school, Mr. Milchman has had a change of heart. The quality of education has deteriorated, he says, and so many residents have taken their children out of public schools that ethnic diversity -- once a prized feature of the system -- is disappearing.</p>
        <p>In the search for solutions, Mr. Milchman zeroed in on Montclair's Board of Education. Its seven members have always been appointed by the mayor, and as a result, Mr. Milchman and others say, candidates are culled from a select group of civic organizations and tend to represent limited points of view. Since board members are not elected by the public, he says, they are not always sensitive to residents' concerns.</p>
        <p>Last spring, Mr. Milchman and several others formed a group called Elect the Board, which has lobbied to put school board appointments in the voters' hands. As a result of their efforts, residents will decide in a November referendum whether to take on the responsibility of electing board members and voting on school budgets. Such a change would put Montclair in line with the vast majority of districts in New Jersey -- 584 boards are elected, only 23 appointed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milchman and other Elect the Board members say school boards appointed by the mayor have not cured the school system's ills. In particular, they cite concerns over larger classes, falling test scores, discipline problems and annual increases in the property-tax rate to support the budget.</p>
        <p>"Parents have repeatedly gone to school board meetings to make their concerns known, but to a large extent it has fallen on deaf ears," Mr. Milchman said. "We need a board that has a mandate from the public."</p>
        <p>Although Elect the Board collected 3,000 signatures to get a referendum on the ballot, the effort has met with fierce opposition. The Coalition for the Appointed Board, which includes members of Montclair's League of Women Voters, its Civil Rights Commission and its chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, contends that changing to an elected board will mean losing minority representation in a town that is more than 30 percent black. (The current school board has four white members and three black members.)</p>
        <p>"It's very hard for a minority candidate to win the majority vote," said Lucy O'Brien, a coalition member with three children in public schools. "The appointment system assures we have a balanced board representing different races and different skills."</p>
        <p>In a town that has always been proud of its diversity -- many residents say it was their primary reason for moving to Montclair -- the difference of opinion has caused considerable strife. Elect the Board members insist that voters would never allow an all-white school board.</p>
        <p>"Montclair is smarter than that," said Jerry Mosier, who recently put his son in a private elementary school. "This is a town that has elected a number of black mayors and Council members, and there is no reason to believe it would be different with the school board."</p>
        <p>But coalition members point to other racially diverse towns that have changed from appointed to elected boards and lost minority representation. Denise Mayer, a member of the League of Women Voters, notes that West Orange has no black board members and Teaneck has just one, even though both towns have substantial black populations.</p>
        <p>"Show me a community that made the change and fixed the problems and I'll be quiet," she said. "We should spend our energy correcting the things that are flawed instead of expending an entire system for the sake of change."</p>
        <p>Although several dozen school districts have changed from appointed to elected boards over the years hoping to solve problems, Frank Belluscio, a spokesman for the New Jersey School Boards Association, warned that a switch is rarely a cure-all.</p>
        <p>"Generally, changing the manner in which a school board is elected has no influence on things like taxes," Mr. Belluscio said.</p>
        <p>But for residents like Peggy Mangogna, who has grown children and pays about $8,500 in annual property taxes, electing a new school board would at least offer a possibility for change.</p>
        <p>"We've tried everything else and nothing has worked," Mrs. Mangogna said. "At least this will give us the opportunity to vote on the budget."</p>
        <p>Coalition members say voter turnout for school board elections in New Jersey is notoriously low, and people who vote tend to be angry about taxes. With an appointed board voting on the budget, Ms. Mayer said, the district has been able to keep school buildings in good shape, something towns with elected boards often fail to do since voters reject capital improvement plans.</p>
        <p>"There is a sense that just because you elect someone, they'll do your bidding," Ms. Mayer said. "But the reality of what you have to accomplish often goes directly against the will of the people."  SCHOOLS: REFERENDUM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
