<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vice President Leads Republican Chorus Sighing in Relief</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="159282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIONNE, E J JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDA163DF935A35754C0A96E948260" item-length="1089" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vice President Leads Republican Chorus Sighing in Relief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. J. DIONNE, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIONNE, E J JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Attorney General Edwin Meese 3d's announcement today that he would resign in a few weeks came as an enormous relief to Republicans, most notably to Vice President Bush.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Attorney General Edwin Meese 3d's announcement today that he would resign in a few weeks came as an enormous relief to Republicans, most notably to Vice President Bush.</p>
        <p>Attorney General Edwin Meese 3d's announcement today that he would resign in a few weeks came as an enormous relief to Republicans, most notably to Vice President Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meese's impending departure will remove from public life the man who had become the personification of what Democrats have called the ''sleaze factor'' to refer to the alleged ethical lapses in the Reagan Administration.</p>
        <p>The surest sign of Mr. Bush's relief was the brevity of the statement he released shortly after Mr. Meese announced he was quitting. In its entirety, the statement by Mr. Bush, the prospective Republican Presidential nominee, read, ''Ed did the right thing and I wish him well.''</p>
        <p>Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts, who has clinched the Democratic nomination for President, made it clear this afternoon that he would not give up the ''sleaze'' issue. 'Long Overdue'</p>
        <p>''This administration's inability to set high standards for public service will not be solved by the Meese resignation,'' he said. He called the resignation ''long overdue,'' adding that Mr. Meese should not have been appointed in the first place.</p>
        <p>For months, Mr. Dukakis enlivened crowds simply by reciting the words ''Ed Meese'' and won his loudest cheers when he called on the Attorney General to leave or be dismissed.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Meese's departure will make it harder to use the issue. Stuart Eizenstat, a former Carter Administration official and a top Democratic strategist, said Mr. Meese had come to personalize the Democrats' complaints about alleged Administration corruption in much the same way that James Watt, the former Secretary of the Interior, had personalized opposition to Mr. Reagan's environmental policies. Candor From Republicans</p>
        <p>''It was much harder for the environmental groups to get up a head of steam once their favorite demon was removed,'' Mr. Eizenstat said. The same, he said, would be true of the corruption issue and Mr. Meese, who had become for Democrats ''the quintessential demon.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides certainly saw things this way. ''This was one of those items out there chipping away at George Bush,'' said one of them. Asked about the resignation, this aide said: ''Let's face it. This is better for the campaign.''</p>
        <p>Senator Rudy Boschwitz of Minnesota, the chairman of the Republican committee overseeing campaigns for the Senate, was just as candid in expressing his relief.</p>
        <p>''I welcome the resignation announcement of Ed Meese,'' Mr. Boschwitz said. ''When a Cabinet officer becomes a liability to the President and his party, he should resign.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Meese announced his resignation after James C. McKay, the independent counsel looking into Mr. Meese's conduct, filed a report concluding that he lacked the basis for a criminal indictment against him.</p>
        <p>While lawyers familiar with the investigation said the report, which has not yet been released publicly, criticizes the Attorney General, Mr. Meese sought to interpret the prosecutor's decision not to bring charges as full vindication. Anything else in the report, Mr. Meese said, is ''mere commentary and opinion.''</p>
        <p>By quitting now, Mr. Meese could well save himself - and thus the Reagan Administration -from the embarrassment of an administrative review by the Justice Department's ethics unit. Commitment From Meese</p>
        <p>Top Republicans, including some of Mr. Bush's aides, have made it clear for months that they wanted Mr. Meese to leave the Administration. Mr. Bush himself met with the Attorney General in May and said he had won a commitment from him that he would do nothing to hurt the Bush campaign.</p>
        <p>Two months ago, Mr. Bush's top aides were eager to show they wanted Mr. Meese to leave. Now that he has done so, they were at pains to say that the Vice President's office had nothing to do with engineering the departure. ''We were not a part of trying to push the Attorney General out in any way,'' said Craig Fuller, Mr. Bush's chief of staff.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Meese's resignation leaves the Republicans with one less public problem, it still leaves the Democrats with questions surrounding the Speaker of the House, Jim Wright, and the royalties he made from a book published by a campaign contributor.</p>
        <p>Republicans have acknowledged that one reason Representative Newt Gingrich, a Georgia Republican, pressed the accusations against Mr. Wright before the House ethics committee was to give his party an issue to use to counter the charges against Mr. Meese. Views on Wright</p>
        <p>Now, said one top Democrat who asked not to be named, Mr. Meese is gone but the Wright issue is still alive. ''People are going to ask, O.K., how about Wright?'' this Democrat said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dukakis and his campaign aides do not see things that way, in part because they do not see the charges against Mr. Wright as remotely equivalent to those against the Reagan Administration. They point to questions raised not only by Mr. Meese's behavior, but also by the Iran-Contra scandal and the perjury conviction of Michael K. Deaver, Mr. Reagan's former deputy chief of staff.</p>
        <p>''We don't think that the issue of ethics in government goes away just because one more person resigns,'' said Susan Estrich, Mr. Dukakis's campaign manager. ''We've had a roll of dishonor longer than we've ever had before.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dukakis today described the Administration record as ''one scandal after another after another,'' including ''a breaking scandal at the Pentagon which may dwarf any of the others.'' Importance to Dukakis</p>
        <p>The issue of scandal in government is central to Mr. Dukakis's campaign because it allows him to make the case for change on ethical and managerial grounds without getting into arguments about the Administration's conservative philosophy, which remains popular with many voters.</p>
        <p>Morever, Mr. Dukakis can contrast the Democrats' belief in government as faith in public service with the Republicans' dislike of government. ''We need a President who believes in public service, who will set those high ethical standards and make Americans proud once again,'' Mr. Dukakis said today.</p>
        <p>While Democrats said Mr. Meese's resignation in no way diminishes this broad argument for change, Mr. Bush's aides did not try to hide their glee that the man who seemed the best - or worst -symbol of this issue was gone. As an issue, predicted one top Bush aide, who asked not to be named, Mr. Meese would not have much of a shelf life.</p>
        <p>Given how quickly issues move in Presidential campaigns, this aide added, ''It's pretty much out-of-sight, out-of-mind.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
