<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Always Avoid Boredom</title>
    <meta content="12BOSS$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/12/business/yourmoney/12BOSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1455811"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="EXECUTIVE LIFE: THE BOSS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Millenium Pharmaceuticals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rifkin, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levin, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Boss</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Executive Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Millennium Pharmaceuticals Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1DB113EF931A25752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Always Avoid Boredom</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Always Avoid Boredom</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURIEL SIEBERT; Written with Marcin Skomial.</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Millenium Pharmaceuticals Inc chief executive Mark Levin writes in The Boss column about his family and upbringing, varied work history and need to avoid boredom; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN I was 5, Mom and Dad bought a grocery store in Wisconsin and put me to work unpacking boxes of thimbles. After we moved back to St. Louis, where I was born, I worked with my parents in a hearing-aid business, a gas station and a bowling alley. By the time I was 16, they had bought a shoe store. I sold shoes for a long time. In fact, I'm still a fanatic about shoes; I probably own 75 pairs.</p>
        <p>I never saw my parents work for anybody. Dad had the attitude that we could do anything. Mom was the practical one; she understood the numbers and what you needed to make things work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>My greatest influence was my parents. I saw all these crazy things they were doing, and I've always focused on doing things that were interesting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN I was 5, Mom and Dad bought a grocery store in Wisconsin and put me to work unpacking boxes of thimbles. After we moved back to St. Louis, where I was born, I worked with my parents in a hearing-aid business, a gas station and a bowling alley. By the time I was 16, they had bought a shoe store. I sold shoes for a long time. In fact, I'm still a fanatic about shoes; I probably own 75 pairs.</p>
        <p>I never saw my parents work for anybody. Dad had the attitude that we could do anything. Mom was the practical one; she understood the numbers and what you needed to make things work.</p>
        <p>She died when I was 16. Dad was lost without her, and so was I. She was the person who made the family work. Dad grew up one of nine kids in the Depression. He dropped out of school before eighth grade, and parenting was not his greatest strength. I stayed in St. Louis and went to Washington University; that let me help take care of my sisters and my father. I ended up with a master's degree in biochemical engineering.</p>
        <p>When I graduated, I went back to Dad's shoe business. He paid me $2.50 an hour, not a lot of money even in the early 1970's. But I met my future wife, who sold shoes there; we've now been married 25 years.</p>
        <p>After a few months in Dad's store, I landed an engineering job at Eli Lilly, even though I had forgotten to put on socks for my interview. Later, I worked in process engineering for the Miller Brewing Company in Eden, N.C. I put in 13-hour days, but even so, my wife and I bought a doughnut shop. We also owned a monkey and a cockatiel until the local health department condemned our apartment.</p>
        <p>I learned that the doughnut business had to be a 24/7 operation. Often, the baker would quit on the spot and I'd be baking from midnight to 5 a.m. Though we were making doughnuts, I lost a lot of weight. We also lost a lot of money.</p>
        <p>After that, my career swerved across industries and across the country, and I ended up first in the biotechnology field at Genentech in San Francisco, and later as a venture capitalist at Mayfield. We started 10 companies in our offices and I became C.E.O. of five of them, including Millennium Pharmaceuticals.</p>
        <p>I never had a career plan. My greatest influence was my parents. I saw all these crazy things they were doing, and I've always focused on doing things that were interesting. When I got bored, I moved on. I never thought about money, either.</p>
        <p>One of the most important things I've learned is that failure is good for you. People who do great things in life are those who went through lots of adversity. I've made huge mistakes along the way. I watched my parents fail a lot, and I lost my mom at a young age. My wife, Becky, and I have failed along the way, as well.</p>
        <p>Maybe the most important turning point in our lives was having our daughter, who is now 5. To go home and have somebody who is so unencumbered, who sees wonderfulness in everything you do, is an extraordinary experience. For her, it's about chocolate or not chocolate.</p>
        <p>EXECUTIVE LIFE: THE BOSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
