<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Caring for Wood-Floor Finishes</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="510861"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOORS AND FLOORING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WARDE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DA133EF932A35750C0A964958260" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Caring for Wood-Floor Finishes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WARDE, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CARING for modern wood-floor finishes can be tricky, as procedures recommended for some floors can ruin others.</p>
        <p>With all wood floors, frequent cleaning to remove dirt, and particularly grit, which causes scratches, is essential. Go over the floor with a dry untreated dust mop every few days or more often, and vacuum floors with a brush attachment as frequently as you vacuum carpets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CARING for modern wood-floor finishes can be tricky, as procedures recommended for some floors can ruin others.</p>
        <p>With all wood floors, frequent cleaning to remove dirt, and particularly grit, which causes scratches, is essential. Go over the floor with a dry untreated dust mop every few days or more often, and vacuum floors with a brush attachment as frequently as you vacuum carpets.</p>
        <p>Prevent soil from entering the house by placing dirt-trapping mats at all exterior doors. To prevent scratches caused by furniture, equip all items with glides made by gluing thick felt or old carpeting, with the fibers facing down, to the legs or bottom edges, or attach gray-colored, not black, barrel-type nonmarking rubber casters.</p>
        <p>Water can damage all wood-floor finishes. Wipe up food and other spills immediately with a dry cloth or paper towel. Use dampened, never wet, material only if necessary. Then wipe the floor dry with another cloth or paper towel.</p>
        <p>Place absorbent rugs or mats in entryways, near kitchen sinks and beneath plants. But never leave a damp covering on the floor; remove it to dry and wipe up any moisture left behind.</p>
        <p>If flooding occurs -- for example, if an appliance leaks or rain enters -- sponge up as much water as possible. Then open the doors and windows, unless that will admit more water, turn up the furnace to at least 80 degrees, and use fans to increase evaporation and air circulation.</p>
        <p>When cleaning or reviving a dull floor is necessary, knowing the type of finish that has been applied is crucial. If you do not know, ask the builder or have a professional flooring installer or refinisher inspect the floor. If your home has several wood floors, learn the type of finish on each, write down the information and keep it for reference with other household documents.</p>
        <p>To clean waxed floors, which are usually finished with varnish, shellac or lacquer, buff them with a medium- or heavy-weight electric buffer equipped with a fiber-bristle brush. Buffers can be rented, but buying one is a sound investment if the floor receives heavy foot traffic.</p>
        <p>Apply solid or liquid paste wax to small areas that do not respond to buffing, and buff again when the wax dries. When an entire floor needs attention, usually about twice a year, apply a solvent-based liquid product containing cleaner and wax made especially for wood floors. Such products are available from flooring and floor-finishing companies and some janitorial suppliers. Treat the entire floor at one time and then buff.</p>
        <p>Following are some remedies for stains, but only for waxed floors:</p>
        <p>*Alcohol: Rub with No. 000-grade steel wool dipped in silver polish or barely dampened with ammonia. Wax and buff.</p>
        <p>*Burns: If not too deep, rub with No. 000 or 00 steel wool dipped in wax. Buff. To remove deep burns, repair flooring.</p>
        <p>*Chewing gum, crayons or candle wax: Freeze with ice until the deposit is brittle. Dampen the edges with mineral spirits. Then pry up the deposit with a putty knife. Wax and buff.</p>
        <p>*Dark spots: First try rubbing with No. 000 or 00 steel wool dipped in mineral spirits. Next, try wiping the spot with distilled vinegar for three to five minutes. If the spot remains, sand with fine-grit sandpaper, blending at least three inches into the surrounding area. Stain to restore wood color, if necessary, then wax and buff. To remove stubborn stains, repair flooring.</p>
        <p>*Heel and black caster marks: Rub with No. 000 steel wool dipped in wax. Buff.</p>
        <p>*Oil and grease: Wash with a cloth containing soap having a strong lye content, or place a gauze pad saturated with hydrogen peroxide on the stain and cover it with second layer of gauze saturated with ammonia. Let that stand for three minutes. Repeat until the stain disappears. Wax and buff.</p>
        <p>*Water or light spots: Rub spot with No. 000 steel wool, wax and buff.</p>
        <p>To clean floors finished with polyurethane or Swedish finish, wash them by damp-mopping with a product recommended by the finish manufacturer or with a solution of one-quarter cup of distilled vinegar and one quart of warm water. Dry the floor with a towel as you proceed. Dulled floors can generally be restored by electric buffing with a lambs-wool pad.</p>
        <p>Never apply wax to a polyurethane- or Swedish-finish floor. When dull areas cannot be revived by buffing, they should be polished with an abrasive screen mounted on a buffer and then recoated with additional finish.</p>
        <p>That procedure raises little dust and can usually be accomplished in one day. Having a professional floor finisher do the job helps to insure satisfactory results, and recoating floors every three to five years can keep them looking like new indefinitely.</p>
        <p>Recoating is impossible if the floor has been waxed or has been cleaned with products containing oil or detergent. If that is the case, clean and treat the floor as a waxed floor. But if wax or improper cleaning materials have been used infrequently, consult the finish manufacturer or a floor finisher first. Sometimes, a professional application of certain cleaners can undo the effects of such products.</p>
        <p>To clean floors finished with acrylic, which is in most "prefinished" flooring, use only products recommended by the flooring or finish manufacturer. Otherwise, treat the floor as if it were waxed. Buff to restore the luster.</p>
        <p>Refinishing any wood floor is only necessary when it is damaged, when the finish has worn through to bare wood, when a different finish is desired or when polyurethane, Swedish or similar finishes that have dulled have been incorrectly maintained by waxing or improper cleaning.  HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
