<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Will Trim Sale of Reserve Oil by Half</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="419250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESERVES (NATURAL RESOURCES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRATEGIC PETROLEUM RESERVE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKPILING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENERGY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stockpiling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDC123CF932A05752C0A967958260" item-length="933" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Will Trim Sale of Reserve Oil by Half</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Energy Department, facing a very weak market for the high-sulfur crude it had planned to sell from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, said yesterday that it would cut the total sale by nearly 50 percent.</p>
        <p>The department said it would sell only 3 million barrels of the high-sulfur, or "sour," crude instead of the 22.5 million barrels originally planned, because the prices bid were too low. But it said it would increase the sale of "sweet," or low-sulfur, crude to 14.35 million barrels, from 11.25 million barrels. As a result, the sale will comprise a total of 17.35 million barrels, rather than the 33.75 first planned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Energy Department, facing a very weak market for the high-sulfur crude it had planned to sell from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, said yesterday that it would cut the total sale by nearly 50 percent.</p>
        <p>The department said it would sell only 3 million barrels of the high-sulfur, or "sour," crude instead of the 22.5 million barrels originally planned, because the prices bid were too low. But it said it would increase the sale of "sweet," or low-sulfur, crude to 14.35 million barrels, from 11.25 million barrels. As a result, the sale will comprise a total of 17.35 million barrels, rather than the 33.75 first planned.</p>
        <p>The intended sale from the 586-million-barrel reserve was first announced two weeks ago, when the air attack on Iraq began, as a way to avert panic in the oil market. But the price of oil unexpectedly plunged when traders concluded that the attack was a success and that Saudi exports were not threatened. Statement by Watkins</p>
        <p>In a statement yesterday, James D. Watkins, the Energy Secretary, said, "We clearly must remain sensitive to the market by making available the crude oil the industry is saying it really needs, and not allowing bargain hunters to take advantage of the taxpayers."</p>
        <p>He added that the department would also fulfill the commitment it made to the International Energy Agency, the Paris-based organization of 21 oil-importing nations, whose members had collectively agreed to release 2.5 million barrels a day. Half of that was to come from American reserves, although the department had said it would be flexible.</p>
        <p>The largest contract, for 7.52 million barrels, was awarded to Phibro Energy Inc., a trading company and refiner based in Greenwich, Conn. Bids were submitted by 26 companies, 13 of which won contracts.</p>
        <p>The 17.35 million barrels were auctioned at prices ranging from $25.67 to $28.52 a barrel.  Oil Drops 88 Cents</p>
        <p>The news of the amended sale plan, which was first disclosed in The Wall Street Journal yesterday, did not upset the oil market yesterday, with oil for delivery in March closing on the New York Mercantile Exchange at $20.97 a barrel, down 88 cents.</p>
        <p>That oil, however, is sweet crude. The announcement did push up the price of sour crude relative to sweet, according to industry experts. Sour crude is traded among refiners, producers and trading houses, generally at bids expressed in relation to sweet crude rather than at an absolute price. And the announcement prompted the discount for sour crude to shrink, with the price difference per barrel dropping to $3.30 late yesterday from about $3.70 on Tuesday. The reason was that supplies of sour crude will now be smaller than the market had anticipated.</p>
        <p>Market participants said the price of sour crude actually started to close in on the price of sweet crude in trading late Tuesday afternoon. Several participants said they were angry with the Energy Department because it appeared to them that the information had leaked out and that some companies had been able to take advantage of it.  Department Denies Leak</p>
        <p>The department denied there had been a leak. And at least one trader, while saying he had suspicions of such an advantage, said it was possible that an astute trader could have made the same trades based on conclusions drawn from publicly available information.</p>
        <p>Philip K. Verleger Jr., a commodities economist and visiting fellow at the Institute for International Economics in Washington, who follows the oil market closely, said the price move started Tuesday afternoon when Phibro, the company that received the largest contract, "started buying up a lot of sour crude." He said the trading suggested that Phibro had "advance notice" of the change in the oil auction, and that what he believed was an information leak "tarnished what is otherwise the greatest success in energy management in 18 years."</p>
        <p>There is no law against insider trading in commodities, as there is in stocks.</p>
        <p>A Washington lawyer who specializes in energy matters, Peter H. Rodgers, said that trading companies he works with had complained to him yesterday morning, after the change in the auction was made public, that Phibro's purchases, beginning at about 4:30 P.M. on Tuesday, appeared to them to indicate the company had early knowledge.  A 2 P.M. Decision</p>
        <p>Robert F. Baker, a spokesman for Phibro's parent company, Salomon Brothers, would not confirm trading by Phibro, but said any suggestion Phibro had advance information was "utter nonsense."</p>
        <p>At the Energy Department, M. J. Jameson, the chief spokeswoman, said that the decision was made at about 2 P.M. on Tuesday, in consultation with the White House, and that the first time the information was divulged outside the Government was to a Wall Street Journal reporter at 6:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>But a trader at one international oil trading company, who spoke on condition that neither he nor his company be identified, also said Phibro started buying at about 4:30, and he felt there may have been a Government leak. "I trade off information all the time," he said. But, he added that his information usually came from private sources, "and this is a Government body."</p>
        <p>One energy trader at a different international company also said there may have been a leak, although he added that a perceptive reading of publicly available information, including Energy Department data showing that sweet crude was in much higher demand than sour, might have led an astute trader to expect the Government to cut back on its sale of sour crude and to anticipate a rise in its price.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
