<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surprised by the Limelight, A Colonel's Gay Son Shines</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="609513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMOSEXUALITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY PERSONNEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINES, FRANCIS X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PECK, SCOTT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PECK, FRED (COL)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Personnel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DD103AF934A25756C0A965958260" item-length="1390" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surprised by the Limelight, A Colonel's Gay Son Shines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLINES, FRANCIS X</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, May 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two days after he was "outed" before the nation by his own father, Scott Peck finished a strong defense of his homosexuality on the Larry King television program and was rewarded with a kiss from his lover, Bobby Hampson, as the two moved on to the next station and the next interview that would delve into a riveting story of father and son.</p>
        <p>Mr. King told Mr. Peck he was impressive in his cause; Mr. Hampson told him he was wonderful. And Scott Peck, now buoyantly out of the closet, looked eager for the next encounter with mass public relations in a very busy week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two days after he was "outed" before the nation by his own father, Scott Peck finished a strong defense of his homosexuality on the Larry King television program and was rewarded with a kiss from his lover, Bobby Hampson, as the two moved on to the next station and the next interview that would delve into a riveting story of father and son.</p>
        <p>Mr. King told Mr. Peck he was impressive in his cause; Mr. Hampson told him he was wonderful. And Scott Peck, now buoyantly out of the closet, looked eager for the next encounter with mass public relations in a very busy week.</p>
        <p>Blond, handsome, articulate as he leaned back in the television studio limousine, he truly seemed the spokesman son of a spokesman father, Col. Fred Peck, who was the quintessentially masculine voice of the Marine Corps in Somalia.</p>
        <p>"You know, my father can be a sarcastic S. O. B. when he wants, but he really came through for me this time," Scott said with a big smile.</p>
        <p>Colonel Peck startled a Senate hearing and the nation by announcing Tuesday that he had just learned of Scott's homosexuality, and felt obliged to testify even more fervidly that his beloved Marine Corps could provide no safe or tolerant haven for his beloved 24-year-old son or for any other openly gay person.</p>
        <p>Out in California, Lincoln Peck, the 77-year-old progenitor of the two, watched transfixed as the national debate devolved into sound bites in which his own son and grandson maintained antithetical positions on homosexuals in the military. 'I'm Proud of Them Both'</p>
        <p>"Both are doing a hell of a job, showing guts, being true to themselves," said Lincoln Peck, a retired accountant and veteran of the Marines' harrowing Iwo Jima and Saipan campaigns in World War II. "The news set me back a little, but I'm proud of them both."</p>
        <p>Whatever maleness means in the Peck family, a certain courage under pressure can be expected, Grandfather Peck concluded of Frederick and Scott.</p>
        <p>"This is something you really can't do anything about," he said, agreeing with his son that Scott's homosexuality is a fact of nature more than choice, and that, no matter how stunning the discovery, it is no threat to the transcending love of fathers and sons and family.</p>
        <p>Scott Peck and Bobby Hampsonlooked far from threatened as they journeyed back from the television studio in Washington to their apartment here, where Scott, who has been "out" on campus for more than a year as a writer on gay news for the undergraduate newspaper, The Retriever, is about to graduate from the University of Maryland with a bachelor's degree in English.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hampson, a 29-year-old legal assistant who had been hidden from the Peck family for six months, was delighted to find himself finally acknowledged: a message left at the young men's apartment by Colonel Peck on the eve of the Senate hearing was a nod to him and Scott both.</p>
        <p>"Hey, Scott and Bobby, sorry I missed you," the colonel said in typical chipper fashion, Scott related. "I need to speak to either of you."</p>
        <p>For Scott, that acknowledgment and the conversation that followed with his father was the resolution of a struggle with a secret that haunted him from boyhood. A Distant Father</p>
        <p>Because of his parents' early divorce, he never got to know his father until he was 14. Scott thinks his mother, Michaele Harper, might have guessed his secret. But he never discussed it with her and she died of cancer when he was 15. For the next few years, before he went to college, he finally lived with his father.</p>
        <p>"I should have trusted him more," Scott said in an interview in the limousine. "I could have talked to him a lot sooner. Growing up, he was kind of a stranger to me and I missed him tremendously. All I had were photographs."</p>
        <p>He described how he created an image of his father as a strong, terse patriarch, the "archetype" of a marine. "When I met him, of course, he couldn't live up to that," Scott recalled. "But in the years that followed, he really went the extra mile, building a relationship. And now, the gay issue aside, I'm blessed with that relationship."</p>
        <p>Scott said he first sensed his homosexuality in grammar school. Fighting it, he became a staunch born-again Christian but, upon confiding his private temptations, was denounced by a clergyman who thundered, "Let demon sodomy out!"</p>
        <p>Two years ago, still celibate, he sought escape in heterosexuality by dating Kelley Slagle, the editor of The Retriever. "She's six foot tall, flowing red hair, everything a straight guy dreams about," rued Scott. "On top of that I loved her. The only thing missing was that physical component."</p>
        <p>So Ms. Slagle became closest confidante, not lover, as Scott decided to come out gently on campus, writing articles on gay issues. "It was very painful for him not to be able to tell his father, he loved him so," Ms. Slagle recalled.</p>
        <p>In The Retriever, Scott criticized radical groups like Queer Nation, which he said minimized the rich diversity he found among homosexuals. And he wrote that some gay groups presented a simplistic view that frightened the public with images of pedophiles and drag queens, Ms. Slagle said.</p>
        <p>Those articles prompted a response from a campus acquaintance in Queer Nation who threatened to embarrass Colonel Peck by disclosing his son's homosexuality to the news media. That prompted Scott to tell his family and led the colonel to speak of it first, Scott said. "I could not ask him not to appear at the hearing any more than he could ask me not to share my side of this issue," he said of the colonel's determination to step into the limelight.</p>
        <p>In his five months in Somalia, Colonel Peck finally had some of the first-hand, combat-like experience that had long eluded him in 27 years of service, and he decided he was now qualified to testify before the Senate on homosexuals in the military, Scott said. The 44-year-old colonel had spent most of his career in assignments at the Pentagon and even Hollywood, where he advised directors of war movies about the Marine image.</p>
        <p>When Colonel Peck suddenly wrote from Somalia to Scott asking for stateside information about the gay-military debate, the time was becoming overdue to disclose his own homosexuality to his father, the son said. Two months ago, he told his step-mother, Joanna Schilling, a sympathetic Marine Corps major, who broke the news to the colonel five days before the Senate hearing.</p>
        <p>Even before that, however, Scott, searching to come out, had told Major Schilling's mother, Lynn, because he sensed that, as a late-blooming college student and "liberal Democrat," she would be the most tolerant and encouraging member of the family.</p>
        <p>In his dramatic testimony, Colonel Scott said he had not been the best of fathers but he had been blessed with a strong and loving son who, however, would find it "hell" in the service because of his sexual orientation. A Stereotype Vanishes</p>
        <p>"Maybe Dad hurt the gay movement's political agenda but I think he helped individuals a lot, especially parents watching," estimated Scott, who wants no part of military service but plans to write and speak about the newfound blessings of coming out to one's family. "Maybe the sight of this heroic figure, this 110 percent American male, accepting his own son is making other fathers stop and think about their own relations."</p>
        <p>Indeed, with the colonel's testimony a stereotype of the cold, robotic marine vanished, Scott insisted. The benefits to Scott were immediate, beginning with a joint message of congratulations to Scott from his uncles, Charles, Kelly and Michael, soon after the news. There was praise from Grand-stepmother Schilling and pride from the family's original marine, Grandfather Peck.</p>
        <p>"I could watch them both on this issue all day long now that they've been pushed," said Lincoln Peck of son and grandson, "though it does seem it might be better if everyone kept their mouth shut and let this damn issue die. What you don't know won't hurt you."</p>
        <p>In a reprise of their earlier years, father and son have still not met face to face since the colonel's return from Somalia. The colonel went west on leave right after the hearing and has given few interviews.</p>
        <p>"Maybe we'll get together next week on 'Nightline,' " said Scott, checking his increasingly busy agenda as the Peck family's newest spokesman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
