<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mining Generations of Living Experience</title>
    <meta content="SENIOR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="997087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eiseman, Alberta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shuldiner, David P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFDF143FF931A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="1459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mining Generations of Living Experience</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALBERTA EISEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eiseman, Alberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Shuldiner, humanist in residence for Connecticut Social Services Department's elderly services division, develops and implements cultural programs for older adults throughout state; comments on how he plans and funds programs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A DREARY winter day, with snow and sleet competing for attention, would tempt most people to remain indoors, but not the group gathered in the library of the Raymond E. Baldwin Center in Stratford on a recent morning.</p>
        <p>It was the first meeting of a book discussion series entitled ''Good Age, Good Medicine'' -- an exploration of the role of older people as healers in traditional cultures. David Shuldiner, humanist in residence for the elderly services division of the Connecticut State Department of Social Services, had driven down from Hartford to lead the discussion of the day's selection: ''Bless Me, Ultima'' a novel by Rudolfo Anaya set in a New Mexican village. Within minutes of his introduction the participants took over, commenting on the different cultures described in the book; the coexistence of folk beliefs and traditional religion; the acceptance of magic and the power of suggestion in healing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A DREARY winter day, with snow and sleet competing for attention, would tempt most people to remain indoors, but not the group gathered in the library of the Raymond E. Baldwin Center in Stratford on a recent morning.</p>
        <p>It was the first meeting of a book discussion series entitled ''Good Age, Good Medicine'' -- an exploration of the role of older people as healers in traditional cultures. David Shuldiner, humanist in residence for the elderly services division of the Connecticut State Department of Social Services, had driven down from Hartford to lead the discussion of the day's selection: ''Bless Me, Ultima'' a novel by Rudolfo Anaya set in a New Mexican village. Within minutes of his introduction the participants took over, commenting on the different cultures described in the book; the coexistence of folk beliefs and traditional religion; the acceptance of magic and the power of suggestion in healing.</p>
        <p>In selecting the theme, said Mr. Shuldiner, he was guided by his own interest in traditional or alternative medicine. It was soon evident that the small, lively group around the table was well acquainted with the topic and identified strongly with the character of Ultima, the aged healer who understands the relationship between past and present and hands down her insights to the young protagonist.</p>
        <p>The conversation flowed smoothly back and forth, from the book's setting to the participants' own experience with their grandparents, and then with grandchildren of their own.</p>
        <p>''I like to test new programs in Stratford,'' said Mr. Shuldiner after the discussion, ''because this group is one that enjoys challenges. I consider them my best guinea pigs.''</p>
        <p>He ought to know. As humanist in residence he is familiar with the state's senior centers, nursing homes, housing facilities and all locations where older residents gather.  He has held workshops for social workers, therapists, family counselors and nursing home personnel interested in cultural opportunities for  those they serve.</p>
        <p>Born and educated in Southern California, Mr. Shuldiner arrived in Connecticut in 1984 in response to an announcement of a 10-month position with the state's Department on Aging (now the Elderly Services Division of the Department of Social Services), a post newly created and funded by the Connecticut Humanities Council.</p>
        <p>''I had recently completed my doctoral degree in folklore at the University of Southern California,'' said Mr. Shuldiner, a tall, rangy man in his late 40's, ''and I had written my dissertation about a group of elderly Jewish immigrants who had been active in labor and political movements in Europe and the United States.''</p>
        <p>''I grew to appreciate not only the great privilege of sitting at the feet of these repositories of living history,'' he continued, ''but also the importance of providing an opportunity for those with whom I met to share the stories of their lives with me.''</p>
        <p>The new position seemed made to order for someone with his training and outlook, enabling him, he has written, ''to make ample use of the tools of the folklorist's trade,'' like the ability to elicit reminiscences and stimulate dialogue on a wide variety of subjects, including local history, immigration and ethnicity, and traditional arts and music. Such programming, he believes, enables elders to assert their sense of self and community belonging.</p>
        <p>He worked under the supervision of the Director of Community Services and his marching orders, as he calls them, were to develop and implement cultural programs for older adults throughout the state. What programs and how to take them about was up to him, as it still is.  When the 10-month grant was up, the department took over the funding and made the position permanent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shuldiner calls it ''the story of a successful collaboration between two public institutions not usually involved in each other's affairs'' and says he knows of no other position like it in any other state agency in the country. The fact that he has no full-time staff or program budget does not disturb him.</p>
        <p>''I have gotten very creative piggy-backing off other projects,'' he explained. ''Working together, we find the support. So here I am, nestled within the bureaucracy, not bothered with caseloads or paperwork. I can be as creative as I like.''</p>
        <p>Professionals in the aging field welcome his participation.</p>
        <p>''The humanist in residence position is a tremendous resource for us,'' said Marie Guman, the outreach coordinator for Stratford Senior Services, ''and David has the capacity to relate to people from all walks of life, to let them know their input is important. Most of us have so many other responsibilities,'' she continued, ''so many pressing services to deliver. Without him we would not be able to offer these programs that are enriching to the mind and spirit.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shuldiner started, 14 years ago, by visiting sites where innovative programs were already in place, and then traveled throughout the state talking to older residents to get a sense of what interested them, what subjects they wanted to learn more about.</p>
        <p>''I found that many of the people I met shared an avid interest in local history, a pride of place,'' he related.  ''No matter how long or short a time they had lived in the state, they seemed to adopt it.''</p>
        <p>The realization led him to seek out scholars to search for archival material related to the state's history.  This 10-year project resulted in  ''Connecticut Speaks for Itself'' -- an anthology of first-hand accounts Mr. Shuldiner edited in collaboration with Thomas R. Beardsley, published by the Connecticut Humanities Council in 1996.</p>
        <p>He also compiled an inventory of resources -- ''Humanities Programs for Older Adults: A Resource Guide'' -- to be distributed around the state. And he developed, or helped create, a wide variety of model programs, ranging from discussions of books and movies on specific themes to showings of slides and videotapes to explorations of local history, always striving to stimulate the fullest audience participation, to instill in participants a sense of their own worth and promote positive images of aging.</p>
        <p>Often, he is invited to organize intergenerational programs, like a book discussion series held at the high school in Stratford, ''Searching for the American Family.''</p>
        <p>''Both groups were aware of how much attitudes and circumstances had changed,'' he said. ''It was nice for the elders and the young people to recognize their mutual experience.''</p>
        <p>Asked to name projects he considers successful, he described special walking tours and other activities designed around the bicentennial of the town of Bristol and a festive Black History Month program in Stamford featuring two movies on black traditional culture and religion.</p>
        <p>He also cited two plays based on oral history interviews, one performed at various sites in Hartford  and one about Jewish farmers in Colchester. Both -- written and produced by Christine Howard Bailey, who specializes in oral history theater among older adults -- were performed by the elders themselves.</p>
        <p>More recently, he acted as curator for an exhibition entitled ''Portraits of Life'' -- pictures of residents of a nursing home taken by Julia Singer, a documentary photographer, accompanied by excerpts from conversations with the subjects. The exhibition, which had its premiere in Stratford, will travel to Waterford, Stonington and several other venues in the coming months.</p>
        <p>''I meet with a wide variety of elders -- all levels of education and range of interests,'' Mr. Shuldiner said. ''Some had to go right to work, others went through college and had professional careers. We find different ways of presenting literature, of taking great ideas and putting them out in ways that are accessible. Some times we read selections out loud to make sure everyone can be engaged in the subjects raised.</p>
        <p>''One of the aims of the Humanities Council,'' he continued, ''is to bring ideas to the widest possible audience and encourage participants to engage in critical thinking.''</p>
        <p>He favors the term ''elders''.</p>
        <p>''It's a word used by folklorists to symbolize teachers, counselors, leaders, healers,'' he said, ''and it's my desire to reintroduce a term that once denoted respect for an older person.</p>
        <p>''My main objective is to affirm the elders' identity and to enable them to have a voice and express who they are.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
