<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tests Indicate Seized Material Is Nonlethal Form of Anthrax</title>
    <meta content="22NEVA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="997388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anthrax</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Veterinary Medicine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Las Vegas (Nev)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aryan Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siller, Bobby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Larry Wayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leavitt, William Job Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada/Las Vegas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anthrax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Veterinary Medicine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4DE163EF931A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="1239" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tests Indicate Seized Material Is Nonlethal Form of Anthrax</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Feb. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laboratory tests of material seized as potentially deadly anthrax bacteria in Las Vegas, Nev, finds that it is actually harmless veterinary vaccine used to prevent anthrax and cannot spread disease to animals or humans; FBI agent Bobby Siller says Larry Wayne Harris, one of two men who were charged with possession of biological toxins for use as weapon, will remain in custody pending further investigation and hearing; says other suspect, William Job Leavitt Jr has been released; Harris is former member of Aryan Nations white supremacist group (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Laboratory tests of material seized as potentially deadly anthrax bacteria in Las Vegas, Nev., this week found that it was actually a harmless veterinary vaccine used to prevent anthrax and could not spread the disease to animals or humans, the authorities said today.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, F.B.I. agents swooped down on a medical clinic on the outskirts of Las Vegas and arrested two men, one of them a known associate of right-wing hate groups, who they believed were about to test some anthrax bacteria. A local cancer researcher who had been approached about testing the material told investigators that the men said they had ''military-grade anthrax,'' which can be deadly in even microscopic amounts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Laboratory tests of material seized as potentially deadly anthrax bacteria in Las Vegas, Nev., this week found that it was actually a harmless veterinary vaccine used to prevent anthrax and could not spread the disease to animals or humans, the authorities said today.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, F.B.I. agents swooped down on a medical clinic on the outskirts of Las Vegas and arrested two men, one of them a known associate of right-wing hate groups, who they believed were about to test some anthrax bacteria. A local cancer researcher who had been approached about testing the material told investigators that the men said they had ''military-grade anthrax,'' which can be deadly in even microscopic amounts.</p>
        <p>But extensive tests at a military laboratory at Fort Detrick, Md., have determined that the substance in fact contained only harmless traces of anthrax that could not be used to make a biological weapon, Bobby Siller, the special agent in charge of the Las Vegas office of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, said today at a news conference there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Siller said that the anthrax lacked DNA material that would cause it to form spores and so was not toxic, and the F.B.I. said it would be impossible to convert it into a form harmful to humans.</p>
        <p>''There is no reason for anyone to be concerned about contaminants,'' Mr. Siller said.</p>
        <p>Asked if he would have conducted the inquiry any differently, Mr. Siller said: ''Absolutely not. We truly felt and we feel now that we had enough probable cause to believe there was a danger to the community.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Siller said Larry Wayne Harris, one of the two men in Las Vegas who were charged with possession of biological toxins for use as a weapon, would remain in custody at the Clark County Detention Center in Las Vegas pending further investigation and a hearing on Monday.</p>
        <p>The other suspect, William Job Leavitt Jr., was released on his own recognizance at about 6 P.M. today and shared a tearful embrace with his family members.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leavitt declined to answer questions about the case, but he told reporters, ''I understand the position the F.B.I. took based on the information they received.'' He attributed his arrest to ''a misunderstanding, a miscommunication,'' and said, ''I have no hard feelings.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leavitt's lawyer Lamond Mills, a former United States Attorney for Nevada, had earlier reached an agreement with the United States Attorney's office in Las Vegas that his client would refrain from further biological research until the charges are resolved. Mr. Mills said this afternoon that Mr. Leavitt would not have to appear in court on Monday and would appear later, if at all.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harris, a former member of the Aryan Nations white supremacist group, is on probation from a Federal conviction last year on charges of illegally obtaining bubonic plague bacteria from a mail-order laboratory in 1995. One of the conditions of his probation was that he not handle dangerous toxins.</p>
        <p>Mr. Siller said he believed that testing on other material, seized from Mr. Harris's houses in Ohio, had not been completed.</p>
        <p>The initial test results were the latest twist in a case that sent a ripple of fear from Las Vegas to Times Square on Thursday after an early report that the two men might have been planning an attack on the New York City subway system.</p>
        <p>In fact, the Government's official complaint later made clear, Mr. Harris had boasted in the past about how easy such an attack would be, though officials said they had no indication of any plans to use the material.</p>
        <p>Still, investigators took extraordinary precautions after a 12-hour surveillance involving scores of F.B.I. agents and other law-enforcement agencies. They also sealed the suspects' car in plastic and whisked the material off for testing.</p>
        <p>The authorities said the public had never been in danger, but even before the results of the tests were in, investigators said they had been justified in arresting the men and taking such swift steps because of credible information of a severe threat.</p>
        <p>''If this stuff turns out to be Jell-O and I'm faced with this again, we'd have to do exactly the same thing,'' Walter Stowe, the assistant special agent in charge of the F.B.I. office in Las Vegas, said on Friday before the tests were completed. ''The potential threat is just too great.''</p>
        <p>In fact, officials had some reason to be worried. Mr. Harris, a freelance water tester and microbiologist from Lancaster, Ohio, has published a book, ''Bacteriological Warfare: A Major Threat to North America,'' that he describes as a guide for surviving a germ attack, but that also details how such an attack could be carried out.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harris has said he grew anthrax cultures from material taken from a burial ground of cows that died in an outbreak in the 1950's, and law-enforcement officials and experts on right-wing groups say he has traveled the country addressing anti-Government groups on the dangers of germ warfare, and inoculating people against biological agents.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Leavitt, of Logandale, Nev., had no criminal record, and friends described him as a pillar of his local Mormon church who owned a fire safety business and had a passion for alternative medical research in a quest for cures for AIDS and other diseases. His lawyers said he had asked Mr. Harris to help him test an electronic machine that he had been told could kill bacteria.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leavitt had been negotiating with Ronald G. Rockwell, a local researcher who claimed to have developed such a machine, but Mr. Leavitt's lawyers said the two could not agree on a price. This week, when Mr. Harris and Mr. Leavitt told Mr. Rockwell that they had anthrax they wanted tested, Mr. Rockwell had said ''it scared me so bad'' that he called the authorities, who moved in to arrest the suspects as they met Mr. Rockwell at a clinic in Henderson, Nev., on Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>The Government's official complaint, while not identifying Mr. Rockwell as the informant, quotes the informer as saying Mr. Leavitt claimed to have military-grade anthrax. But Mr. Leavitt's lawyers contend that Mr. Rockwell, who was convicted of conspiracy to commit extortion in the early 1980's, was a scam artist who turned on their client when he saw a deal going sour.</p>
        <p>In any event, Mr. Leavitt and Mr. Rockwell made no secret of their testing plans, discussing them on a radio talk show on KNXT-AM in Las Vegas just last week, and saying that Mr. Harris would help them.</p>
        <p>''Larry Harris has been a consultant to our Government for some time, and he will be participating in some very specific tests as far as to the efficacy of the technology, in regard to some of the bacteriologic agents,'' Mr. Leavitt told the radio host, according to a transcript published today in The Las Vegas Review-Journal/Las Vegas Sun.</p>
        <p>In the past, Mr. Harris has claimed that he worked for the Central Intelligence Agency in the 1980's. But a C.I.A. spokesman, Mark Mansfield, said that Mr. Harris had never been employed by the agency.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
