<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Facing the Shortage of Parish Priests</title>
    <meta content="PRIEST$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="997178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Julie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EEDC133FF931A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="1852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Facing the Shortage of Parish Priests</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Catholic leaders in Connecticut weigh changes to deal with worsening shortage of parish priests; weigh organizing churches into groups served by priests living in one rectory and scheduling events, like Mass, for group instead of for each church; are turning more often to lay people for help in running parishes and special ministries; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MEMBERS of the St. Thomas More Roman Catholic Church in North Stonington are making some hard decisions. They are planing for a time when they may not have a full-time priest.</p>
        <p>''It's very difficult for members of the parish to conceive of a time when we won't have our own priest. It's a very emotional topic for a lot of people,'' said Mary Jane Reissner. The Reissners' pastor at St. Thomas More, the Rev. John Nash, baptized their grandson and presided at their youngest son's confirmation. ''People have very personal relationships with Father Jack,'' she added. ''If they have a problem and don't know what to do, they can call Father Jack.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MEMBERS of the St. Thomas More Roman Catholic Church in North Stonington are making some hard decisions. They are planing for a time when they may not have a full-time priest.</p>
        <p>''It's very difficult for members of the parish to conceive of a time when we won't have our own priest. It's a very emotional topic for a lot of people,'' said Mary Jane Reissner. The Reissners' pastor at St. Thomas More, the Rev. John Nash, baptized their grandson and presided at their youngest son's confirmation. ''People have very personal relationships with Father Jack,'' she added. ''If they have a problem and don't know what to do, they can call Father Jack.''</p>
        <p>The days when priests staffed every Catholic parish are rapidly disappearing. Nationally, the number of priests has fallen sharply in recent years. Hundreds of churches without resident priests have hired parish administrators, who are lay people, to handle their daily operations. And when the parish phone rings in the middle of the night, bearing news of a family crisis, the church still answers faithfully, but the bedside prayers and communion may be offered by Sister, not Father, according to R. Scott Appleby, who directs the Cushwa Center for the Study of American Catholicism at the University of Notre Dame in Indiana. In Connecticut, concern among church leaders over the growing shortage of priests is bringing about changes that are certain to have a profound effect on the day-to-day lives of Catholics.</p>
        <p>In 1960 there were 52,689 priests in the United States, and more than 30,000 young men filled the seminaries, Mr. Appleby stated. Since 1960, the Catholic population has risen to 60 million from 40 million. But the number of priests declined in 1997 to 47,223 as a result of resignations, retirements and thinning ranks of new recruits. The number of seminarians dropped in the same year to 4,539, hardly enough to replace the many priests who will soon retire, much less to keep up with the increasing size of the laity.</p>
        <p>Many reasons have been given for the shortage of priests. Included are the broad secularization of society since the 1950's and the fact that there are fewer nuns and priests in the Catholic schools to encourage boys and young men to become priests. The image of the priesthood has been tarnished in recent years by widely publicized lawsuits involving sexual misconduct by priests. Some observers also point to the requirement of celibacy as the decisive factor.</p>
        <p>In any case, the trend is expected to continue for at least the next 20 years, Catholic leaders say. Deaths, retirements and departures among diocesan priests continue to be more numerous than ordinations, according to the Rev. Eugene Hemrick, director of diocesan relations at the Catholic University of America in Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>Half the priests will be 55 or older by the turn of the century, and their workloads are likely to become heavier due to the rising Catholic population. Religious orders reflect a similar situation. The average age of priests in many congregations is 67.</p>
        <p>The trend is not expected to reverse in the near future unless priests are imported from other countries, and a number of dioceses are hesitant to endorse that alternative, Father Hemrick said.</p>
        <p>Church leaders frequently discuss another alternative, a married priesthood, but view it with mixed feelings. And despite discussion about the ordination of women, Father Nash said he thought that that would not occur in his lifetime.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, priests who are responsible for more than one parish are becoming more common. In the Archdiocese of Hartford, which includes Hartford, New Haven and Litchfield counties, approximately 50 of the 335 priests in active ministry are scheduled to retire in the next five years, said the vicar for priests, Msgr. Charles Johnson.</p>
        <p>The number of priests at the altar is nearly the same as it was 25 years ago, but the throngs filling the pews are expanding. As a result, 36 of the 220 churches in the archdiocese are coupled in what is referred to as ''linkings.'' The two churches share the same priest but remain separate in all other respects.</p>
        <p>But this solution is only temporary, Monsignor Johnson said: ''We need 18 fewer priests, but that can't go on forever. We have to think of better ways to provide ministries for our people.''</p>
        <p>One possibility is organizing three or more churches into a group served by priests living in one rectory. Instead of scheduling an event at each church, one event, like a Mass, would be scheduled for the group. This arrangement is already being used in dioceses in Pennsylvania and Illinois, Monsignor Johnson said.</p>
        <p>Then too, bishops are turning more often to lay people for assistance in running parishes and conducting special ministries. Across the country, 6,000 Catholic students are studying to become full-time lay ministers in church-related organizations or on university and college campuses. Twenty thousand men and women work as lay ministers in 19,000 parishes. Since 1986, the number of lay students and ministries has doubled, Father Hemrick said.</p>
        <p>Bishops in Wisconsin issued a pastoral letter explaining the rules for conducting worship without a priest. In Connecticut, priests continue to give communion but often depend on the laity to lead church meetings and adult study groups, conduct prayer services and visit the sick.</p>
        <p>St. Thomas More is one of four parishes, situated near one another in southeastern Connecticut, analyzing their strengths and the ways in which they may want to share resources. All parishes in the Diocese of Norwich, to which the churches belong, will undertake the same study, since 10 of the 78 pastors in the diocese will reach retirement age in the next five years.</p>
        <p>The options being considered by the four churches include merging, sharing priests and hiring a parish administrator. Closing a church is considered a last resort, said the director of planning for the diocese, Sister Mary Alice Kline. ''Rather than waiting until there's a crisis,'' she said, ''when we would make a decision and then tell the troops, we are saying, 'It looks like there will be hard decisions down the road. We'd like you to be part of that decision making.' ''</p>
        <p>Father Nash, the pastor of St. Thomas More, says he fears that if he is called upon to serve more than one church, he will lose contact with the continuity in parish life.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to become a circuit rider or a magic man,'' he said. ''I'm able to be there not just to give first communion but to prepare young people for it, not just to perform a marriage ceremony but to prepare a couple for marriage, not just to come in and bury somebody but to help during the sickness and afterward.''</p>
        <p>He went on: ''I can't just show up and say, 'Here I am,' and then say goodbye. I don't want to become a pop-in priest. I want to be there.' ''</p>
        <p>Not all dioceses are in the same predicament, however. The Bridgeport diocese, the third smallest in the nation in geographic size, is currently able to assign at least one priest to every parish. Most parishes in the diocese, which includes Fairfield County, are large or medium-sized,  in a city or suburb, and staffed with between one and four priests.</p>
        <p>''We have an advantage,'' said the director of communications for the diocese, the Rev. Chris Walsh, ''If we're tight on priests, we can reduce a parish from four to three priests, or from three to two.''</p>
        <p>In addition, the diocese has ordained 21 priests in the past three years, Father Walsh said. Most are from the Northeast, and approximately half are from Fairfield County. The diocese has been able to recruit through the St. John Fisher Seminary Residence, which opened in Stamford in 1989; its mission is to prepare men between the ages of 18 and 39 for advanced study at a major seminary.</p>
        <p>Father Walsh, who is also spiritual director if St. John's, said, ''One of the reasons St. John's gets such priority is that we know we need priests.''</p>
        <p>Priests and lay people are making  adjustments as profound changes take place in parish leadership. The Rev. Joseph DiSciacca, who is 50, became pastor of Sacred Heart Church in Bloomfield two and a half years ago. Father DiSciacca's parish of 1,000 families evolved from a merger with Christ the King Church, a parish of 300 families two miles from Sacred Heart. Father Di Sciacca arrived at Sacred Heart after one of the parish's two pastors had open-heart surgery at the age of 70.</p>
        <p>''I was the person sent to make sure there was good coverage. Before that, the diocese had to scramble a lot to find people who could do funerals and say Mass,'' Father DiSciacca said.</p>
        <p>Father DiSciacca began his pastorate at Sacred Heart shortly before both priests retired. At first, Sacred Heart and Christ the King began collaborating in areas like the music ministry and religious education. Then Christ the King, the smaller of the two parishes, was closed.</p>
        <p>''While there was sadness, people said, 'Let's try to make one parish work.' The beauty of it is that folks from Christ the King have stayed with us,'' Father DiSciacca said. ''Not everybody came along, and some people are still angry. But we've never had a public protest. People have been exceedingly kind and generous.''</p>
        <p>When the doors of Christ the King were closed, members of both parishes joined in a procession from the church to Sacred Heart. A statue taken from Christ the King was carried in the procession by truck and placed in front of its new church home.</p>
        <p>Father DiSciacca, who sometimes visits 6 to 10 hospitalized parishioners a day and ends up with two wakes on Sunday and two funerals on Monday, says he is always training church members to help with the work of the parish.</p>
        <p>''The bishops in the United States are talking more and more about training lay leaders,'' he said. ''There's a strong desire to make sure they are trained well.''</p>
        <p>While the laity are enthusiastic about their deeper involvement in church life, the changes can be difficult for priests, Father DiSciacca added.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes priests can be the ones who change more slowly,'' he said. ''We were the ones who did everything in the past. But I've also seen many people greatly inspired by older priests, who have recognized that this situation is different from the way it was in the seminary.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
