<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not Quite Gone, Far From Forgotten: Newark, Capital of Jazz</title>
    <meta content="22JAZZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="997199"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="R &amp; R"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Performing Arts Center</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Arkestra (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baraka, Amiri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E1D7133FF931A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not Quite Gone, Far From Forgotten: Newark, Capital of Jazz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Performing Arts Center will offer glimpse of early 20th century and its music in The Lost Jazz Shrines of Newark, multi-media program conceived and developed by Amiri Baraka; program will use memorabilia and photos to illustrate musical and vocal performances by 15-piece New Arkestra, made up largely of local jazz performers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the early part of the century, Newark was known as a ''ticklers town.'' The great black jazz piano players had to come and play in the clubs in the section called the Coast on their way to greatness. None other than Duke Ellington said in his memoirs that in the 1920's, one of the best places to hear black music was Newark.</p>
        <p>In clubs with names like Conertons, Bill Buss's Saloon and Randolphs, jazz that was every bit as vibrant and lavishly original as anything heard across the river in New York City was being played here in the narrow strip running from Lincoln Park north to Branford Place Park and west of Broad Street to Washington Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the early part of the century, Newark was known as a ''ticklers town.'' The great black jazz piano players had to come and play in the clubs in the section called the Coast on their way to greatness. None other than Duke Ellington said in his memoirs that in the 1920's, one of the best places to hear black music was Newark.</p>
        <p>In clubs with names like Conertons, Bill Buss's Saloon and Randolphs, jazz that was every bit as vibrant and lavishly original as anything heard across the river in New York City was being played here in the narrow strip running from Lincoln Park north to Branford Place Park and west of Broad Street to Washington Street.</p>
        <p>On Saturday night, the New Jersey Performing Arts Center offers a glimpse of that time and its music in ''The Lost Jazz Shrines of Newark.'' Conceived and developed by the Newark poet and essayist Amiri Baraka, the multi-media program will use memorabilia and photographs from Mr. Baraka's collection and others to illustrate musical and vocal performances by the 15-piece New Arkestra, made up largely of local jazz performers. The program is based on Mr. Baraka's research and rendering in dramatic readings of the life of Willie (the Lion) Smith, an early composer and jazz great whose proficiency in stride piano was considered by many to transcend that of the better-known James P. Johnson and Fats Waller.</p>
        <p>The program in Newark, sponsored by Absolut Vodka and the New Jersey State Council on the Arts, is one of nine around the country intended to highlight the cities, areas, clubs and informal spaces that nurtured jazz and its creators from its beginning. Maurine Knighton, executive director of the Brooklyn arts center 651, who helped develop the idea, said some common strains had emerged from city to city as the organizers looked at the evolution of jazz shrines.</p>
        <p>''There were formal sites like clubs and ballrooms, but there were informal sites as well, like community centers, Masonic halls and churches,'' she said, noting that the venues were as wildly improvised as the music itself. ''People had a proprietary sense about the music, and they held it close and very dear.''</p>
        <p>The other cities planning programs commemorating their jazz shrines are New York, Washington, Philadelphia, Cleveland, Chicago, Indianapolis, Kansas City, Mo., and San Antonio, Tex. In New York, three programs will highlight locations in Brooklyn, Greenwich Village and Harlem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baraka said Willie (the Lion) Smith was a regular on the New York jazz scene from the 1920's until his death in 1974. But his career started in Newark, where he grew up and, as a teen-ager, began playing in the saloons, brothels and ''buffet flats'' -- homes where music was played and food was sold -- of the city's tenderloin district just before and after World War I. It was a time when there was entertainment around the clock, and the first thing a new club or saloon would do when it opened was to have a ceremony built around throwing away the key to the place.</p>
        <p>For the Newark program, Robert Banks, 68, a local pianist and organist who learned his craft from musicians influenced by ''the Lion,'' will play many of the pieces Smith wrote and performed in the old days.</p>
        <p>He describes the style of playing Smith popularized as an up-tempo style that relied on a heavy stride -- left-handed playing that spanned all six and half octaves -- and a lot of countermelody and syncopation. Mr. Banks said one of Smith's signature pieces was ''Fingerbuster,'' a fast-moving piece in which the pianist must demonstrates skill in moving rapidly up and down the entire keyboard.</p>
        <p>Unlike most musicians, Smith's nickname had nothing to do with his playing; it came from his service in World War I as an artilleryman. For 49 days straight, he manned a howitzer alone on the front lines in France, prompting his colonel to call him ''a lion with that gun.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baraka said neighborhoods like the Coast thrived in good economic times but suffered during the Depression, when many clubs and close. But the jazz venues never entirely disappeared, and new places cropped up in the 1930's and 40's as the clubs spread west into the Central Ward and stride gave way to swing. There, clubs with names like Jumping Jive, Lloyds Manor and the Orpheum featured headliners including Newark's own Savoy Sultans, who spiced their performance by dancing while they played and passing their instruments around without missing a beat.</p>
        <p>As recordings replaced live performances as the major vehicle for the spread of jazz or any other music, the clubs disappeared. But even today, Newark maintains three or four jazz venues that still attract top performers.</p>
        <p>In an effort to spread the word about Newark's jazz history, Mr. Baraka and the Performing Arts Center are planning on expanding the program to look at different eras in the city's jazz evolution and staging performances by the New Arkestra of the music of those periods at local clubs.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to take it out into the communities so that people can see what a rich musical history the city has,'' said Stephanie S. Hughley, the center's vice president for programming. ''We hope we can translate some of the enthusiasm of those times.''</p>
        <p>''The Lost Jazz Shrines of Newark,'' Saturday at 7:30 P.M. in the Victoria Theater, New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark. Tickets: $15 and $20. Information: (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>R &amp; R</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
