<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Perot Comes to Town But Then Leaves With It</title>
    <meta content="09PERO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Westlake Journal" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="928660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Westlake Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Movements and Secession</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westlake (Tex)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perot, Ross Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perot, Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDD1439F93AA35756C0A961958260" item-length="1245" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Perot Comes to Town But Then Leaves With It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ross Perot Jr, son of Presidential candidate and multimillionaire in his own right, owned half land in tiny, Westlake, Tex, before he seceded; along with him have gone 2,500 acres on which he plans to build offices, housing and golf courses; most members of Westlake's governing body, Board of Aldermen, have seceded with their land, too, leaving town of 250 residents torn to pieces; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For four years, Ross Perot Jr., son of the two-time Presidential candidate and a multimillionaire in his own right, has owned more than half the land in tiny, once peaceful Westlake, Tex., just north of Dallas and Fort Worth.</p>
        <p>Now he has seceded. Along with him have gone the 2,500 acres on which he plans to build offices, housing and golf courses. And most members of Westlake's governing body, the Board of Aldermen, have seceded with their land, too, leaving the town of 250 residents torn to pieces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For four years, Ross Perot Jr., son of the two-time Presidential candidate and a multimillionaire in his own right, has owned more than half the land in tiny, once peaceful Westlake, Tex., just north of Dallas and Fort Worth.</p>
        <p>Now he has seceded. Along with him have gone the 2,500 acres on which he plans to build offices, housing and golf courses. And most members of Westlake's governing body, the Board of Aldermen, have seceded with their land, too, leaving the town of 250 residents torn to pieces.</p>
        <p>''You've got a town where everyone is at everyone else's throats,'' said Pete Geren, a spokesman for Mr. Perot's development company and a former United States representative from Texas. ''There are irreconcilable differences here.''</p>
        <p>The marriage between Mr. Perot and the town of Westlake seemed promising at the start. When he bought the Circle T Ranch in 1993 from the oilman Nelson Bunker Hunt, who was forced to sell it at the bargain price of $20 million after going bankrupt, residents rejoiced that a man with deep pockets had become the owner of 60 percent of the land within Westlake's borders.</p>
        <p>''We wanted Perot here because he had the money and the forethought and the planning,'' said Don Gardner, a three-year resident.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot owns 25,000 acres throughout the United States, and he heads the industrial cargo park at Fort Worth's Alliance Airport, just a few miles from the edge of the Circle T. Cattle are still being raised on the property, which is also home to a herd of bison.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot, residents figured, would bring investment and, by attracting new residents, additional revenue, too, just as he had done elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''But then,'' Mr. Gardner said, ''we realized he wanted to use our money to build.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot had pledged he would not saddle Westlake with extra taxes. The ranch property, Mr. Perot's representatives pointed out, contained three municipality districts authorized to sell bonds, and thus could finance its own development.</p>
        <p>As outlined by Mr. Perot's representatives, new businesses and residents on the Circle T property could have water, electricity and road improvements financed by bonds sold by the districts. The bonds would be paid off with special taxes assessed on the property owners.</p>
        <p>But longtime residents of Westlake feared they would have to pay taxes, too, if newcomers later took control of the Board of Aldermen and sought to spread the burden.</p>
        <p>The aldermen seemed to share residents' concerns. But after a transaction last December, residents were no longer sure the aldermen were on their side. In that deal, Mr. Perot bought an additional 500 acres from the Hunt family trust, on which an alderman lived. He paid a reported $10 million for the property, to go with the 2,000 acres he already had.</p>
        <p>In a matter of months, four of the five alderman publicly backed Mr. Perot's financing plan, saying that they trusted him to deal in good faith. Many residents noted that the interests of the four aldermen were merging with those of Mr. Perot.</p>
        <p>Were other town leaders, residents asked, hoping to sell their land for a princely sum to Mr. Perot? The Mayor, Scott Bradley, said Mr. Perot had offered to buy his property, which Mr. Perot's spokesman confirmed. The offer was rejected. Suspicions deepened. And the town split.</p>
        <p>One man who had publicly questioned whether Mr. Perot's plans were in the town's best interests was Don Redding, a retired executive with International Business Machines and a member of the Planning and Zoning Board. In February, he declared that he would run for alderman himself. His candidacy did not last long. Four of the five aldermen voted to declare that Mr. Redding's neighborhood of 64 residents, Stagecoach Hills, had never actually fallen within the town's borders, denying him the right to run for office.</p>
        <p>From then on, tensions between pro-Perot and anti-Perot forces worsened. Town meetings were shouting matches, with residents challenging and ridiculing board members. Government was in gridlock. It was a startling turnabout in a place where politics had been so dull that only 21 people showed up to vote in the town election last year.</p>
        <p>Early this month, the board, on a vote of 4 to 1, dismissed Mr. Bradley as Mayor. Mr. Bradley, a former assistant district attorney in Dallas, had been a persistent critic of Mr. Perot's plans. In invoking legal provisions that permitted the Mayor's removal for incompetence, the aldermen cited problems with the board's minutes and with scheduling.</p>
        <p>And there was another problem: Mr. Bradley had opposed the aldermen's move to prohibit Mr. Redding's candidacy.</p>
        <p>''He behaved in a manner unacceptable to anyone else,'' Al Oien, an alderman and Perot supporter, said after the Mayor's ouster.</p>
        <p>Even as Mr. Bradley was being ousted, Mr. Perot requested that the Circle T ranch be excluded from the town's boundaries. Three aldermen, blaming incessant fighting and facing an election in which pro-Perot forces were likely to lose their board majority, requested secession for land they owned, a total of 169 acres, adjacent to the Perot property.</p>
        <p>Eleven other residents, with a total of 95 acres, broke away, too, complaining they were tired of the political fighting and the government's telling them what to do.</p>
        <p>''This is about classic small-town governance issues,'' Mr. Perot said in a recent interview. ''The founders of the city want to be left alone; they want to live their lives in peace.''</p>
        <p>That was the situation when 120 residents gathered in a meeting room adjacent to city hall, atop a day-care center in an office center, to watch most of the 41-year-old town's political leaders and its leading landowner secede, or, in the words of Texas, take part in a ''disannexation.'' It had simply required a public posting of the landowners' intentions 72 hours in advance of the meeting, in addition to a majority vote of the aldermen and that of the Mayor. On the day of the secession vote, the board voted 4 to 1 to appoint a new mayor, Dale White, who is retired. With his support, the secession was a foregone conclusion. Mr. White's 22 acres were among those disannexed.</p>
        <p>Some residents wept.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley, the ousted Mayor, has vowed to fight, with the goal of putting the little town back together. He says he will challenge his dismissal in court.</p>
        <p>For now, with Westlake a third the size it was last month, many residents feel betrayed by Mr. Perot. ''We all went with him because we thought, 'This is Ross Perot, and he's going to do good,' '' Mr. Gardner said. ''But we found out the big boys play hard.''</p>
        <p>The day after the secession, the Fort Worth City Council voted to include Mr. Perot's property in its extraterritorial jurisdiction, which means that the city could make the land part of the city. Becoming part of Fort Worth, said Mr. Perot's spokesman, Mr. Geren, would open several options for financing development.</p>
        <p>Westlake Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
