<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Heeding Health Warnings, Memory Can Be Tricky</title>
    <meta content="27cons" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health&amp;Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/27/health/27cons.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1705254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE CONSUMER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/The Consumer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2D91530F934A1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Heeding Health Warnings, Memory Can Be Tricky</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Heeding Health Warnings, Memory Can Be Tricky</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH FRANKLIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In briefing consumers on health risks, public health campaigns often rely on a catchy strategy: they list the myths about a behavior or product, then follow up those misconceptions with the truth.</p>
        <p>Check any Internet search engine and you will find ''myths and facts'' on health topics like abortion, acne, vaccines and weight loss. But new research suggests that even the sharpest consumer can be tripped up by these warnings because of a flaw in the way we remember what we read or are told.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The catchy strategy of public health campaigns listing the myths and facts of health risks may actually backfire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In briefing consumers on health risks, public health campaigns often rely on a catchy strategy: they list the myths about a behavior or product, then follow up those misconceptions with the truth.</p>
        <p>Check any Internet search engine and you will find ''myths and facts'' on health topics like abortion, acne, vaccines and weight loss. But new research suggests that even the sharpest consumer can be tripped up by these warnings because of a flaw in the way we remember what we read or are told.</p>
        <p>As time passes, the studies show, people remember the health information they were given. But they forget which part was myth, and which was the truth. Experts say consumers and doctors need to be aware of this problem so they can make sure that quirks of memory do not harm anyone's health.</p>
        <p>"Here's what happens,'' said Ian Skurnik, a psychologist and assistant professor of marketing at the University of Toronto, who worked with colleagues from the University of Michigan to study the phenomenon.</p>
        <p>''You notice that your grandmother has been taking useless medical treatments, and you're worried,'' he said. ''You tell her, 'You know, Granny, shark cartilage doesn't help your arthritis.' You tell her three times to make sure she understands, and she seems to.''</p>
        <p>He continued, ''But a few days later you talk to her again and find the warnings have had precisely the opposite effect of what you intended.'' This common problem arises, Dr. Skurnik said, because in laying down a memory trace, the human brain seems to encode the memory of the claim separately from its context -- who said it, when and other particulars, including the important fact that the claim is not true.</p>
        <p>The detailed memory of the experience of learning the information begins to fade almost immediately, and the contextual clues fade faster than the core claim.</p>
        <p>''Long after you've forgotten the context, the claim will still seem vaguely familiar,'' Dr. Skurnik said. That is when a well-documented effect that Dr. Skurnik calls ''the illusion of truth'' kicks in.</p>
        <p>Numerous studies over the last few decades have shown that unless people have some countervailing context or information to grab hold of, they tend to regard information that seems familiar as true.</p>
        <p>To test the power of that effect related to health claims, Dr. Skurnik and colleagues gave 64 volunteers a few dozen bits of unrelated medical information that they were unlikely to have heard before, like ''Corn chips contain twice as much fat as potato chips'' and ''Aspirin destroys tooth enamel.''</p>
        <p>The researchers arbitrarily labeled half the statements false and half as true. Each item was read aloud and simultaneously presented on a computer screen at least once, but half the items appeared three times within the list.</p>
        <p>Half the volunteers were college students ages 18 to 25. The others were healthy adults, ages 71 to 86. Thirty minutes after the volunteers had seen the information, the researchers showed them another list of items that contained all the previous statements, with some new items mixed in.</p>
        <p>They were asked to identify which statements were false, which were true and which were new. The same kind of quiz was repeated three days later.</p>
        <p>The results, published in the March 2005 issue of The Journal of Consumer Research, showed that the older adults were much more likely than the younger ones to misremember the false statements as true, an effect that was exacerbated three days later.</p>
        <p>What's more, having seen a statement three times in the initial list helped the younger people remember it correctly, but made things worse for the older volunteers.</p>
        <p>''Even quite elderly people remain good detectors of information that's new, versus something they have seen before,'' Dr. Skurnik said. ''But in this case, that ability worked against them.'' The repetition of a warning underscored its familiarity.</p>
        <p>The implications of the findings are not limited to older people, Dr. Skurnik said.</p>
        <p>In a follow-up study not yet published, he and his colleagues presented college-age volunteers with a health information pamphlet from the Web site of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, called ''Is It a Flu Shot Fact or Myth?''</p>
        <p>In boldface type, the pamphlet contained eight statements about the flu vaccine -- six labeled false, one true and one ''maybe.'' Each statement was followed by a sentence or two of explanation in smaller type.</p>
        <p>''Immediately after reading the flier, participants made few mistakes in recalling whether a particular statement from the flyer was described as a fact or myth, and there was no difference in the type of mistake,'' the researchers reported. ''However,'' the researchers continued, ''after a half an hour, participants were much more likely to misremember a fact as a myth.''</p>
        <p>''I think the message to physicians from this study and others is that even if you have lots to tell your patient in an office visit, you have to tell them several ways and over time to make sure they understand,'' said Dr. Joanne Schwartzberg, who oversees the health literacy program of the American Medical Association.</p>
        <p>Dr. Schwartzberg advises patients never to worry about saying to a doctor: '''Wait a minute, I need a little more time to see if I've got that right. When I go home, you want me to do this; is that right?'''</p>
        <p>Putting complicated health instructions in your own words and repeating them aloud should help anchor the information accurately in your memory.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Skurnik said, ''Don't trust your memory.''</p>
        <p>Office visits are often time-pressured, anxiety-provoking, and packed with new and technical information -- exactly the conditions most likely to jumble a memory of what was said. Whenever possible, get written information from the doctor, he said, and take a notebook to appointments to jot down instructions. It can also help to take along a friend or family member.</p>
        <p>Patients under the intense stress of a new diagnosis may be those most likely to scan headlines and sift through Web pages in search of information. Print out what you read online, Dr. Skurnik suggested, so that you can go back later and identify the source of the information, as well as the particulars.</p>
        <p>And doctors, he said, would do well to make sure that anything they hand out is written in simple, direct factual language.</p>
        <p>''It's not enough to ensure that people get good information from credible sources,'' Dr. Skurnik said. ''You also have to make sure that they'll be able to recall whether it's true or false later on.''</p>
        <p>THE CONSUMER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
