<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chef and Developers Cancel Columbus Circle Restaurant</title>
    <meta content="27trotter" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/27/nyregion/27trotter.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1705315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Charlie Trotter's</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Trotter, Charlie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Graves, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0D81530F934A1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chef and Developers Cancel Columbus Circle Restaurant</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chef and Developers Cancel Columbus Circle Restaurant</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly two years after it was announced that he would become the final star in the constellation of top chefs at the Time Warner Center, Charlie Trotter and the building's retail developers have decided to cancel plans for him to open a seafood restaurant there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trotter said in a telephone interview yesterday that as his restaurant's budget climbed from $6 million to $9 million to $11.5 million, the Related Companies, the center's co-developer, decided to scale back the concept and design.The $11.5 million cost -- for what would not have been a formal restaurant although it was being designed by the noted architect Michael Graves -- would have been almost as much as that for Per Se, where dinner with wine routinely costs $200 or more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charlie Trotter has decided to cancel his plans for a seafood restaurant at the Time Warner Center, citing an escalating budget.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nearly two years after it was announced that he would become the final star in the constellation of top chefs at the Time Warner Center, Charlie Trotter and the building's retail developers have decided to cancel plans for him to open a seafood restaurant there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trotter said in a telephone interview yesterday that as his restaurant's budget climbed from $6 million to $9 million to $11.5 million, the Related Companies, the center's co-developer, decided to scale back the concept and design.The $11.5 million cost -- for what would not have been a formal restaurant although it was being designed by the noted architect Michael Graves -- would have been almost as much as that for Per Se, where dinner with wine routinely costs $200 or more.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to remove some of the exciting design elements to make it work,'' Mr. Trotter said. ''And then the concept changed to something a little more casual than we originally planned.''</p>
        <p>Kenneth A. Himmel, the president and chief executive of the retail-development division of the Related Companies, said: ''There was a real disconnect between the cost and what this project should come in at. We couldn't get the project to where Charlie and I were both comfortable.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the loss of Mr. Trotter's restaurant, Mr. Himmel said he was looking for a replacement for Jean-Georges Vongerichten's V Steakhouse, on the building's fourth floor. But Phil Suarez, Mr. Vongerichten's partner, said no final decision has been reached on the steakhouse, which is jointly owned by the two men and Related Companies. ''It may happen and it may not,'' Mr. Suarez said.</p>
        <p>From the time the center opened in February 2004, the idea of having five of the nations' most acclaimed chefs cooking in a high-end shopping mall has been controversial. Thomas Keller's Per Se and Masa Takayama's Masa were given four stars by The New York Times's restaurant critic, Frank Bruni. Gray Kunz's Cafe Gray has been well received, and Mr. Himmel said it has been doing better than expected.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Himmel said he has not been happy with the financial performance of the steakhouse, which has gotten a tepid reception since its opening last year. Now, the question of whether what the building's developers have labeled the ''Restaurant Collection'' can succeed as a vertical dining destination in Manhattan is still unclear.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trotter's restaurant in Chicago, Charlie Trotter's, was one of the first to present elaborate, multicourse dinners with small portions of creative food.</p>
        <p>''I was welcoming a chance to do something other than an 18-course tasting menu,'' he said, ''and also to be part of the New York restaurant fabric.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Himmel said he would consider only New York chefs for future restaurants in the center. ''I'm going to have a firm hand in the design and a firm hand in the selection,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
