<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Workers Say They Hit a Job Ceiling</title>
    <meta content="06COMP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/06/nyregion/06COMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1268782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Parks and Recreation Department (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Equal Employment Opportunity Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waldman, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EFDA1E3EF935A35751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Workers Say They Hit a Job Ceiling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY WALDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waldman, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Legal documents are filed with federal Equal Employment Opportunity Commission by 20 parks employees who charged New York City Parks Department in 1999 with discrimination and retaliation against those who complained; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paula Loving went to work for the city's Department of Parks and Recreation in 1987. She rose to become citywide coordinator in the Work Experience Program -- and then saw her rise cut short. Ms. Loving, a black woman, watched, twice, as much-younger white women were promoted to director of work-experience operations, a position she believed entailed more responsibility. To her knowledge, the job was never posted and no interviews were held for it.</p>
        <p>Angelo Colon, 47, went to work for the department in 1988, rising to the position of recreation center manager. He, too, said he then hit a ceiling. A Hispanic man, he applied for a job as Coordinator of Pools in Manhattan, a position with a higher salary, saw it given to a younger, white subordinate whom he had trained, and then watched that man rise -- ultimately to deputy chief of recreation in Manhattan  -- in part on the basis of his experience as pools coordinator. When Mr. Colon applied for the same job again, it was given to a much younger white woman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paula Loving went to work for the city's Department of Parks and Recreation in 1987. She rose to become citywide coordinator in the Work Experience Program -- and then saw her rise cut short. Ms. Loving, a black woman, watched, twice, as much-younger white women were promoted to director of work-experience operations, a position she believed entailed more responsibility. To her knowledge, the job was never posted and no interviews were held for it.</p>
        <p>Angelo Colon, 47, went to work for the department in 1988, rising to the position of recreation center manager. He, too, said he then hit a ceiling. A Hispanic man, he applied for a job as Coordinator of Pools in Manhattan, a position with a higher salary, saw it given to a younger, white subordinate whom he had trained, and then watched that man rise -- ultimately to deputy chief of recreation in Manhattan  -- in part on the basis of his experience as pools coordinator. When Mr. Colon applied for the same job again, it was given to a much younger white woman.</p>
        <p>These are among the instances included in legal documents filed with the federal Equal Employment Opportunity Commission by 20 parks employees who charged the Parks Department in 1999 with discrimination, and retaliation against those who complained.</p>
        <p>Last week, the commission found there was ''reasonable cause'' to believe that the department discriminated on the basis of race and national origin in the assignment and promotion of employees. In the case of Mr. Colon in particular, the commission said he appeared to be as qualified as both the man and woman who were selected over him, and that both had been elevated outside the formal application process. The commission also found that he and at least two others had been retaliated against.</p>
        <p>The parks commissioner, Henry J. Stern, has vigorously disputed the charges, and said he will present more evidence refuting them to the commission. The department's practices also may be fought out in court: 11 of the 20 employees who filed charges with the E.E.O.C. are also planning to file a suit charging that Mr. Stern, the department, and the city violated federal civil rights laws.</p>
        <p>At issue is whether Mr. Stern's stated opposition to the use of quotas masked something more insidious, and whether the department's racial breakdown, in which both the upper echelons and specific geographic assignments are almost exclusively white, is happenstance. The case also pits a largely minority Civil Service staff with long tenures against an elite cadre of young, mostly white employees recruited from top schools and then placed in some of the department's top positions.</p>
        <p>While the commissioner and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that Mr. Stern has increased the number of black managers in the agency, the employees claim no minority has any position of real responsibility. They say they were repeatedly denied promotions and pay raises, and restricted as to what positions they could apply for and in which parts of the city they could work.</p>
        <p>Robert Wright, 46, who came to the department in 1979, said that when he transferred from Queens to Manhattan, he was given the choice to work only in predominantly black or Hispanic neighborhoods. He currently is park recreation manager at Marcus Garvey Park in Harlem. He has supervised only black or Hispanic employees. He, too, said positions for which he would have applied, such as deputy chief of recreation for Manhattan, were never posted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern said yesterday he would provide copies of the department's responses to the commission. He said that he did not want to respond to the charges on a case by case basis because the matter would be entering litigation. He said there were good reasons all of the complaining individuals had not been promoted, but said, ''In fairness to the individuals involved, why should their deficiencies be made public because they've been critical? They're still parkies.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern said there was a black chief of recreation in Brooklyn and that most of the department's recreation center directors were minorities. He conceded that all of the chiefs of operations in the boroughs are white, but said they had been selected through a competitive process.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, Mr. Stern had suggested that what appeared to be a segregation of assignments might simply ''reflect normal patterns of interest and patterns of preference.'' Recreation, he said, ''is traditionally an area blacks have gone into.''</p>
        <p>For workers like Ms. Loving, such explanations may be wanting. After two years with the agency, one of the young women selected over her for the Work Experience job was given a 20 percent raise, to $31,161. That same year, 1997, Ms. Loving was earning $31,930 after 10 years with the department. In December 1999, after 12 years with the Parks Department, she transferred to the city's Department of Health, hoping, she has said, to find opportunities for advancement and professional success that she had not found at Parks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
