<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Islander Bosses Make Torrey an Offer</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="514998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK ISLANDERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TORREY, BILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D61339F93BA25750C0A964958260" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Islander Bosses Make Torrey an Offer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill Torrey, the dominant executive of the Islanders throughout their 20-year history, has been asked by the team's incoming ownership group to remain as general manager in a somewhat diminished role. But his new bosses want to know in the next few days whether he will stay. If he doesn't, they must seek his replacement in time to prepare for the June entry draft and other off-season moves to restructure and re-invigorate the floundering franchise.</p>
        <p>"We're talking to him and we're waiting for it to be resolved," said Stephen Walsh, who will become one of two co-chairmen of the team when and if the partial sale and transfer of the franchise is approved Friday afternoon by the National Hockey League's Board of Governors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bill Torrey, the dominant executive of the Islanders throughout their 20-year history, has been asked by the team's incoming ownership group to remain as general manager in a somewhat diminished role. But his new bosses want to know in the next few days whether he will stay. If he doesn't, they must seek his replacement in time to prepare for the June entry draft and other off-season moves to restructure and re-invigorate the floundering franchise.</p>
        <p>"We're talking to him and we're waiting for it to be resolved," said Stephen Walsh, who will become one of two co-chairmen of the team when and if the partial sale and transfer of the franchise is approved Friday afternoon by the National Hockey League's Board of Governors.</p>
        <p>"We're talking directly to Bill," Walsh said. "I don't want to speculate on anything. He has a phenomenal record and his contribution is enormous to the franchise and what it has been. We have only good things to say about Bill Torrey. We've asked Bill to join us as general manager. We're waiting to hear back from him. That's where we are right now."</p>
        <p>Calls to Torrey's home and office yesterday were not returned. Efforts to reach him through the Islanders' staff were unsuccessful. His current title is chairman of the board and general manager. His only superior on the team directory is John O. Pickett Jr., the current owner, who lives in Florida and delegates almost all responsibility of management to Torrey. Full Operational Control</p>
        <p>That will change significantly if Pickett's fellow owners approve the partial sale when they meet Friday. Although Walsh and his partners are buying less than half ownership of the team at first, they have an option to buy up to 50 percent. In addition, they will have full operational control, both Pickett and the Walsh group said.</p>
        <p>Under the new management structure, at least four executives would outrank Torrey. One would be Walsh, who is a managing partner of Walsh, Greenwood &amp; Company, an investment firm based on Long Island.</p>
        <p>The other co-chairman will be Robert Rosenthal, who is the president and chief executive officer of First Long Island Investors. The new Islander president will be Jerome Grossman, who also will become chief operating officer. Ralph Palleschi will become executive vice president. Walsh is managing partner of Walsh, Greenwood. Grossman is managing director for Walsh, Greenwood. Palleschi is executive vice president and chief financial officer for First Long Island. Other Changes at the Top</p>
        <p>Other changes in the Islanders' hierarchy, some of them significant, are expected shortly. Walsh and Grossman said yesterday that Jack Krumpe, currently the team president, would be asked to stay on in a different capacity. When asked whether Al Arbour would remain as coach, Walsh said that would be the decision of the general manager.</p>
        <p>Torrey joined the Islanders in 1972 as the first hired employee of the expansion franchise. Before that, he worked for the now-defunct California Golden Seals. He frequently represents the team in the inner circle of the sport as its representative to the board of governors. He participates on several influential committees and is highly regarded by his peers.</p>
        <p>Torrey's teams won the Stanley Cup in four consecutive seasons, from 1980 through 1983, but the team has declined steadily in recent seasons. Last season, the Islanders were one of only five teams in the then-21-team league to fail to qualify for the post-season playoffs. This season, they are in fifth place in the six-team Patrick Division, six points behind the fourth-place Pittsburgh Penguins, who hold the fourth and final playoff berth from the division.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
