<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paterno Stays Optimistic Despite a Tarnished Season</title>
    <meta content="11NITT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/11/sports/11NITT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1246366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paterno, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFD71238F932A25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paterno Stays Optimistic Despite a Tarnished Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses one of few losing seasons that Coach Joe Paterno's teams have had in his 35 years as Penn State's football coach; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe Paterno has begun sweeping up a shattered football season, but he sees luster in some of the shards in the dustpan.</p>
        <p>He was asked recently to provide some adjectives for this season, which could go down as the worst in his 35 years as the Penn State football coach. First, Paterno chuckled softly. Then he filibustered for a minute. Finally, he settled on three: disappointing, frustrating and exhilarating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe Paterno has begun sweeping up a shattered football season, but he sees luster in some of the shards in the dustpan.</p>
        <p>He was asked recently to provide some adjectives for this season, which could go down as the worst in his 35 years as the Penn State football coach. First, Paterno chuckled softly. Then he filibustered for a minute. Finally, he settled on three: disappointing, frustrating and exhilarating.</p>
        <p>He is disappointed and frustrated because he thought this team, though young, was capable of so much more and because he could not pull them from a malaise. Instead, the Nittany Lions are 4-6 and will not play in a bowl game for only the fifth time under Paterno. Paterno had a chance to break Bear Bryant's Division I-A record of 323 career victories this year, but the best Paterno can now hope for is a tie.</p>
        <p>Even though this Penn State team has a chance to become his first to lose seven or even eight games, he said he was also exhilarated.</p>
        <p>Defensive back Adam Taliaferro, the freshman who suffered a spinal-cord injury late in the loss to Ohio State, has now made some progress in his rehabilitation.</p>
        <p>Paterno also was exhilarated because quarterback Rashard Casey, a senior, was not indicted on criminal charges of assault in connection with an incident May 14 involving an off-duty police officer in Hoboken, N.J., Casey's hometown. Paterno was criticized for not suspending Casey during the investigation.</p>
        <p>''People kept bugging me about sidestepping the issue,'' Paterno said, ''when I believed he was innocent all along.''</p>
        <p>He said he might have made a mistake by scheduling a 12th game this year against Southern Cal, a season-opening loss that preceded another loss to a stronger-than-expected Toledo team.</p>
        <p>Penn State has two more games to play, at Michigan today and at home against Michigan State next Saturday. Paterno thinks the Nittany Lions can win both. He will not abandon his seniors in these two games to start building for next year.</p>
        <p>''My job,'' he said emphatically, ''is not to make the fans happy.''</p>
        <p>His football program, he said, will be fine. That is not to say that his players were not taking last week's overtime loss to Iowa hard. As defensive tackle Jimmy Kennedy said: ''I think a lot of guys are heartbroken.''</p>
        <p>Fullback Mike Cerimele said his fellow seniors were angry at themselves. A season without a bowl game will be tough enough to take, but losing both their last two games, or even splitting them, would make them the seniors on Paterno's worst team. The 1988 team finished 5-6 and has been, to date, Paterno's only losing team.</p>
        <p>Penn State has struggled this year with slow starts. In their 10 games, the Nittany Lions have led at halftime in only two. The scripted offensive plays, the dozen or so that teams use early in the game to take advantage of defensive tendencies, have not paid off.</p>
        <p>''We could script all the plays we'd want,'' Cerimele said, ''but we still would have to go out and execute them.''</p>
        <p>Paterno has been criticized, most notably this season by tailback Larry Johnson, the son of one of Paterno's assistants, as not having an avant-garde playbook, but Paterno did put in a shotgun offense to take advantage of Casey's mobility. And Casey has played well recently.</p>
        <p>The way Michigan Coach Lloyd Carr sees it, Penn State has been caught rebuilding in the Big Ten, a conference in which teams with experience devour younger teams. Of the 44 players on Penn State's two-deep roster, 22 are in their first or second year of eligibility.</p>
        <p>''Any time you're going to have to play a lot of young guys, you're going to have inconsistency and you're going to have breakdowns,'' Carr said. ''It doesn't have anything to do with effort. Penn State's a very young football team.''</p>
        <p>Kennedy said he thought that next year's team could be a contender for a national championship.</p>
        <p>''Saying 'could have' is a great way to make yourself feel good,'' Paterno said. ''All I know is that I'm excited about going out to Michigan -- and I've been around for about 150 years, it seems like.''</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
