<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anatomy of a $133,000 Ambulance; City Pays Premium, but Its Tough Specs Draw Few Bidders</title>
    <meta content="21AMBU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/21/nyregion/21AMBU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20031023T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1529011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ambulances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Emergency Medical Treatment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Horton Emergency Vehicles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcintire, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Horton Emergency Vehicles</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE3DB1E3EF932A15753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anatomy of a $133,000 Ambulance; City Pays Premium, but Its Tough Specs Draw Few Bidders</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Anatomy of a $133,000 Ambulance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE McINTIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcintire, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City pays $133,000 per ambulance, despite city's strangled budget and fiscal crisis, with high price and elaborate and detailed contract specifications driving off most contractors; only two companies bid on contract, with Horton Emergency Vehicles submitting winning bid; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Los Angeles buys them for $85,000 apiece. Detroit pays $84,000. Closer to home, a major New York hospital system spends less than $80,000.</p>
        <p>But the New York City Fire Department has them all beat, spending more $133,000 each for custom-made ambulances -- all 480 of them. At $65 million, the department's new contract to replace its front-line fleet over five years is the largest and most costly municipal ambulance purchase in United States history, according to industry executives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pricey ambulance purchases raise a question: What is New York getting for its money that other big cities are not?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Los Angeles buys them for $85,000 apiece. Detroit pays $84,000. Closer to home, a major New York hospital system spends less than $80,000.</p>
        <p>But the New York City Fire Department has them all beat, spending more $133,000 each for custom-made ambulances -- all 480 of them. At $65 million, the department's new contract to replace its front-line fleet over five years is the largest and most costly municipal ambulance purchase in United States history, according to industry executives.</p>
        <p>The five-year contract was approved in June and the new ambulances have begun to roll in.</p>
        <p>At a time when budget cuts are closing firehouses, curbing daily ambulance runs and delaying construction of new emergency medical stations, the pricey ambulance purchases raise this question: What is New York getting for its money that other big cities are not?</p>
        <p>Some of the answers are found in a thick set of specifications, drawn up by city fire and purchasing officials. Manufacturers say it is the most detailed and restrictive list of specs out there, dictating everything from the placement of the tailpipe to the vehicle's warranty. Fire Department officials say it ensures that New York gets a high-quality product.</p>
        <p>Critics, however, say some requirements needlessly drive up costs and scare away competition, with bidding limited to those manufacturers willing to take on the risk and cost of retooling assembly lines to accommodate New York's desires for things like specialized interior cabinet doors or reinforced step wells. Some of the requirements are there at the insistence of the municipal labor unions.</p>
        <p>Further limiting the bidding is the ''aggravation factor'' of dealing with New York's procurement bureaucracy, which frequently pays late.</p>
        <p>A result has been that one ambulance manufacturer, Horton Emergency Vehicles of Ohio, has emerged the winning bidder time and again, fueling talk that the city favors that company. That talk has the effect of further tamping down competition.</p>
        <p>''Everybody knows that New York buys Horton ambulances,'' said Battalion Chief Don Frazeur, who oversees the vehicle fleet for the Los Angeles Fire Department. ''All the other companies drool over that contract, but it's so proprietary they feel they don't have a shot to get it.''</p>
        <p>Although more than a half-dozen manufacturers can build the quantity of customized ambulances sought by New York, only two, Horton and American LaFrance of South Carolina, submitted bids this year. Horton's price per vehicle beat American LaFrance, whose bid was about $150,000 each.</p>
        <p>A third company, Wheeled Coach Industries of Florida, the world's largest ambulance manufacturer, took a close look at the specifications and decided not to bid. In a letter to the city, Wheeled Coach's president, Robert L. Collins, said some of New York's terms were ''completely unreasonable and unheard of in this industry.''</p>
        <p>''Overall,'' Mr. Collins wrote, ''it is New York City's taxpayers that will pay the premium. In a time of severe budget constraints, why isn't New York seeking better value rather than greater surety?''</p>
        <p>New York City officials reject suggestions that they are spending too much or favor a specific manufacturer. They say they are seeking the vehicles that can best withstand a brutal working environment, are user-friendly for city employees and can be built quickly.</p>
        <p>''You get what you pay for,'' said Assistant Fire Commissioner James Basile, who oversees the vehicle fleet. ''I can comfortably say that we get 10 years out of these vehicles. There are no other roads like there are in New York City, and the vehicles we buy have to be able to withstand that.''</p>
        <p>Commissioner Basile said that, besides being sturdy, New York's ambulances are designed to make life easier for the mechanics who work on them and the emergency medical technicians who ride in them. He is proud of the demanding specifications, like two green indicator lights on the outside of an ambulance that let you know when its battery has been left on.</p>
        <p>The lights were Commissioner Basile's idea.</p>
        <p>''It's simple things like that, no one else has,'' he said. ''Who knows how much we save each year by not having batteries going dead?''</p>
        <p>Determining why New York's ambulances cost more is difficult, in part because the companies that bid to build them do not break out expenses for individual items. (Several company executives estimated that the cost of adding the green indicator lights, a relatively small item, could add $50,000 to $70,000 to New York's total contract price.)</p>
        <p>Comparing contracts also can be tricky. New York's $133,000 contract price includes a two-way radio system.</p>
        <p>Los Angeles' contract price of $85,000 per vehicle does not include radios, which, when added, bring the total price to about $111,000 -- still below New York's. Detroit's $84,000 contract price includes a partial radio system. San Francisco's $98,000 ambulances come with a complete system.</p>
        <p>The North Shore-Long Island Jewish Health System, which operates one of the largest hospital-based ambulance fleets in the country and responds to emergencies in parts of New York City, pays less than $80,000 for ambulances without radios. When radios and other equipment are added, the cost tops $100,000, said Brian O'Neill, the health system's vice president for emergency services.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neill said the ambulances he buys are built with a van chassis, as opposed to the more expensive pickup truck chassis favored by the Fire Department, which says the cab's extended nose better protects occupants in a crash.</p>
        <p>Other fire departments argue that the van design reduces the likelihood of collisions because its flattened nose allows for greater field of vision and a tighter turning radius.</p>
        <p>That debate is moot in New York City, however. The firefighters' union has made it clear that it favors the truck design, which some company executives say could add as much as $1 million to the city's total contract price.</p>
        <p>''When I buy ambulances, I don't have to deal with the union,'' Mr. O'Neill said. ''If their union makes something a safety issue, then you can't fight it.''</p>
        <p>New York fire officials said that in addition to promoting safety, their specifications had the practical benefit of ensuring that every ambulance is built exactly the same way, making spare parts interchangeable. But they insist they are not wedded to Horton, which has been building ambulances for New York since at least the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>''Over 20 years, we have evolved a spec that works for us,'' said Anthony DeMaio, the assistant deputy director of fleet services. ''Anyone has the opportunity to build it for us -- as long as it is to that spec.''</p>
        <p>When other companies tried to build ambulances for New York City in recent years, they did not get far.</p>
        <p>In 1998, the city postponed plans to buy 400 ambulances after accusations from potential bidders that the specifications favored Horton. For example, one competitor said the Fire Department's vehicle design required rounded corner posts and Y-shaped braces made by Horton but not by other companies.</p>
        <p>After the city revised its specifications and put the contract out to bid again in 1999, another company, McCoy Miller of Indiana, won with a low bid of $110,000 per vehicle. But the department soon complained that McCoy Miller was struggling to meet its production schedule, and that some vehicles were of poor quality. The company tried to mitigate those concerns by offering a $10,000 discount on each vehicle, but the city canceled the contract.</p>
        <p>To pick up the slack left by the cancellation, the Fire Department awarded emergency no-bid contracts for 50 ambulances each to Horton and Wheeled Coach. However, Wheeled Coach backed out after the department found problems with a prototype ambulance it produced and refused to relax what the company considered insignificant yet time-consuming design requirements.</p>
        <p>For instance, the department decided it wanted colored wiring instead of black, and a single exhaust tailpipe instead of two, Wheeled Coach said in a letter to the city. Specifications for double doors on a rear storage compartment were changed to a single door, and detailed requirements were added for the type of threaded fastener to be used to mount the vehicle's warning lights.</p>
        <p>''The specifications do not describe warning light mounting,'' the company said in its letter, and ''this adds additional material and cost.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Wheeled Coach declined to comment on the company's dealings with New York City.</p>
        <p>Horton dismissed the complaints as sour grapes. David Lamon, Horton's vice president for sales and marketing, said New York's specifications did not favor his company, and that any advantage Horton may have comes from its long history of building ambulances for the department.</p>
        <p>''We have more of an understanding of the demands of their system, what their problems are, what their needs are,'' Mr. Lamon said. Still, ''they are a very difficult contract for us to do because it is so different.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DeMaio said Wheeled Coach was a chronic complainer that ''wants to build the vehicles its way, and not our way.'' Other fire departments, including Los Angeles', say they have found Wheeled Coach cooperative and willing to accommodate their specifications.</p>
        <p>''Wheeled Coach is like buying a Chevrolet,'' said Chief Frazeur, the Los Angeles battalion leader. ''There are some more expensive cars out there, while others might not get you back and forth in as much comfort. It's hard to contrast quality and value, but there's a middle ground there somewhere.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 23, 2003, Thursday  An article on Tuesday about the custom-made ambulances purchased by the New York City Fire Department misidentified the union that has a hand in shaping the bid specifications. It is the one representing emergency medical technicians, not firefighters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 23, 2003, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about the custom-made ambulances purchased by the New York City Fire Department misidentified the union that has a hand in shaping the bid specifications. It is the one representing emergency medical technicians, not firefighters.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
