<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="470903"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DD163EF931A3575AC0A967958260" item-length="1147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Soviet Turmoil 4-7</p>
        <p>Insurgent Soviet politicians warned that an emergency Congress aimed at reviving the political system could give reactionaries an opportunity to seek a constitutional coup to depose President Gorbachev. Page 1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Soviet Turmoil 4-7</p>
        <p>Insurgent Soviet politicians warned that an emergency Congress aimed at reviving the political system could give reactionaries an opportunity to seek a constitutional coup to depose President Gorbachev. Page 1</p>
        <p>A debate over the role of the C.I.A. and other intelligence services has begun in the wake of the dissolution of the Soviet Union and purge of the K.G.B. The agencies are again being forced to rethink their roles. 1</p>
        <p>Ambivalence about Boris Yeltsin since the Kremlin coup is growing among Bush Administration officials, who are questioning his actions and intentions and starting to criticize him in private as a demagogue. 7</p>
        <p>President Gorbachev asked for aid from Britain during a talk with Prime Minister John Major, who visited the Soviet Union to formulate recommendations on aid for the Group of Seven nations. 5</p>
        <p>Russians in Lithuania are worried that the good life they have enjoyed for years may be over as the republic races toward independence. They are losing their sense of security as the near-bosses of the region. 6</p>
        <p>A revolutionary school in Leningrad is aimed at restoring pre-revolutionary classical education in the Soviet Union. The city's first "classical gymnasium" once led a gypsy life but now is a monument to a new era.  4</p>
        <p>Baltics' free past: lively era, brutal end 6</p>
        <p>Minorities in Moldavia protest independence moves 6</p>
        <p>Armenians applaud calls for U.N. role in Azerbaijan 6 International 2-3</p>
        <p>A signing of the Yugoslav peace plan, which calls for foreign observers to monitor a cease-fire between Serbs and Croats, was set to take place in Belgrade, even as new clashes reportedly broke out. 3</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister of Singapore, who promised to end authoritarian rule, spoke of changes in the way the nation is governed after his party failed to win by the resounding victory it sought in the election. 3</p>
        <p>Hong Kong Journal: Citified monkeys disturb neighborhood 2  National 8-10</p>
        <p>Intolerance for the homeless is rising as cities around the nation impose harsher restrictions on them to reduce their visibilty or force them out on their own, advocates say. 1</p>
        <p>It is a dark time for organized labor, especially in its relationship with its old ally, the Democratic Party. As a result, it has been unable to drive home its point that living standards dropped under Republican rule.  1</p>
        <p>The future of health care in America may be the system in Minneapolis, where a high 44 percent of the people belong to health maintenance organizations. While there are complaints, most say the system works well. 1</p>
        <p>The drop in infant mortality rates masks the dire state of infant health in America, many health-care experts say. In three other critical areas of infant health, the nation is lagging badly. 9</p>
        <p>The I.R.S. is Willie Nelson's partner on his new album, "Who'll Buy My Memories? (The I.R.S. Tapes)." The singer-songwriter must sell four million copies if he is to erase his $15 million tax bill. 1</p>
        <p>The new Federal wetlands proposal to ease restrictions and hasten the development of marshes and wet for-ests and meadows could have the opposite effect, consultants and state officials say. 8</p>
        <p>The former Governor of Louisisana, Edwin W. Edwards, is campaigning for the job he lost in 1987 and readily admits that, like a slighted Southern gentleman, his sole purpose is to avenge his loss. 8</p>
        <p>Aspen Journal: Near earth's best, plotting to save the rest 8</p>
        <p>Soviet students in the United States can only watch as their country transforms itself. But some say that, paradoxically, they may be in the right place at the right time. 10</p>
        <p>A $150,000 loan to Andrew Young, the former Mayor of Atlanta, was forgiven by the Bank of Credit and Commerce International. Mr. Young said he regarded the gesture as belated payment for consulting fees. 25  Regional 21-24</p>
        <p>The subway crash has forced reviews of a wide range of policies at the Transit Authority, including drug and alcohol testing, standards for hiring train operators and its labor relations, the transit chief said. 1</p>
        <p>Repair work nears end 22</p>
        <p>Race in the City Council elections still looms as an issue, despite the racial gerrymandering that produced New York City's new Council districts. In some district contests there have already been disputes over race. 21</p>
        <p>The parade through Crown Heights, which is a rallying point for the city's West Indian community, is not expected to be marred by racially motivated disturbances, both Hasidic and black residents said. 21</p>
        <p>The new income tax in Connecticut has brought a burst of activity to accountants and to the the state, which is scrambling to hire thousands of tax collectors. But for companies, it is pretty much business as usual. 21</p>
        <p>The abnormal weather this summer has thrown off the season's rhythms. Between the heat, the hurricane and the drought, crops are off schedule, animals are doing odd things and livelihoods are disrupted. 21</p>
        <p>The body of a 12-year-old Bronx boy was retrieved from a 500-foot water shaft that he had fallen into while playing with friends in a maze of empty water pipes on an unguarded construction site near his home. 23</p>
        <p>A policeman mugged an old woman who was walking to her home in Bay Ridge, the police said. The officer, James Carey, 36, was off-duty at the time of the incident. 23</p>
        <p>Business Digest D1 Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>Bossa nova is being revived in Brazil, where for years its gentle rhythms and romantic lyrics were preserved mostly for tourists. Audiences are greeting 30-year-old songs with applause and requests for encores. 11</p>
        <p>TV series filmed on New York streets 11</p>
        <p>Judge rules in Basquiat suit 15</p>
        <p>Music: Thomson's 'Lord Byron 11</p>
        <p>Word and Image: "Far From Home," by Ron Powers 15</p>
        <p>Dance on television 38</p>
        <p>A look at inner-cities 38  Sports 30-37</p>
        <p>Baseball: Phillies edge Braves 36</p>
        <p>Yankees rally past Blue Jays 37</p>
        <p>Mets top Reds 37</p>
        <p>Columns: Anderson on Blair Thomas 31</p>
        <p>Berkow on Michael Jordan 37</p>
        <p>Features: Sidelines 32</p>
        <p>Football: Jets defeat Buccaneers 31</p>
        <p>Cunningham hurt in Eagle opener 31</p>
        <p>Giants-49ers are at it already 31</p>
        <p>Rams fumble game away to Cardinals 33</p>
        <p>Bills outduel Dolphins 34</p>
        <p>Bears beat Vikings 34</p>
        <p>McMillan adjusts to new Jets role 35</p>
        <p>Horse Racing: Meadow Star fourth in Maskette 37</p>
        <p>Black Tie Affair wins Iselin 37</p>
        <p>Tennis: Lendl and Stich struggle ahead 32</p>
        <p>Connors's birthday draws big crowd 32  Obituaries 20</p>
        <p>Jean Vuillequez, ex-metals and mining executive Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials 18</p>
        <p>A defining holiday</p>
        <p>Emergency room emergency</p>
        <p>City libraries, still at risk</p>
        <p>Letters 18</p>
        <p>William Safire: Pour it on 19</p>
        <p>Anthony Lewis: Out of the chaos 19</p>
        <p>Thomas Geoghegan: Labor among the ruins 19</p>
        <p>Lewis Grossberger: Media tips for a revolution 19</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
