<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Only 'Law and Order' Is Filming For TV on New York's Streets</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="470856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAU, ELEANOR</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LAW AND ORDER (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D7163AF931A3575AC0A967958260" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Only 'Law and Order' Is Filming For TV on New York's Streets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR BLAU</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLAU, ELEANOR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The remains of a 9-year-old boy murdered 30 years ago had been found in a brownstone being renovated on West 13th Street. Now the detectives of NBC's "Law and Order" were to take a former resident to the site, hoping she would remember something about her former playmate's demise.</p>
        <p>The detectives, played by Paul Sorvino and Christopher Noth, emerged from their vans for the scene. Mr. Noth butted a soccer ball. Someone hairsprayed Carolyn McCormick, who plays a police psychiatrist. "Stand by," a man called, and then, "Ready . . . action."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The remains of a 9-year-old boy murdered 30 years ago had been found in a brownstone being renovated on West 13th Street. Now the detectives of NBC's "Law and Order" were to take a former resident to the site, hoping she would remember something about her former playmate's demise.</p>
        <p>The detectives, played by Paul Sorvino and Christopher Noth, emerged from their vans for the scene. Mr. Noth butted a soccer ball. Someone hairsprayed Carolyn McCormick, who plays a police psychiatrist. "Stand by," a man called, and then, "Ready . . . action."</p>
        <p>Ms. McCormick will be a recurring figure in the second season of the highly praised series, which opens on Sept. 17 at 10 P.M., the same Tuesday schedule it had last year and during summer reruns.</p>
        <p>Also new is Mr. Sorvino. He will succeed Mr. Noth's partner (George Dzundza), who is killed. The show's producers agreed to do away with the fellow because Mr. Dzundza prefers to live in Los Angeles. Emphatically New York</p>
        <p>That would never do for "Law and Order," which is emphatically New York. It is the only series being filmed continuously on the city streets. (The "Cosby" series emanates mostly from a studio in Astoria, Queens; "The Equalizer" and "Kojak" are history.)</p>
        <p>"Even when we're inside a house, you're seeing New York through a window," said Joseph Stern, co-executive producer of the show, which has sets on a pier at West 23d Street and in a former courthouse on Chambers Street. "You always get a sense of New York bleeding through."</p>
        <p>This is good news for the city, which is only beginning to woo back major-studio movie makers, who stayed away from November to mid-May during a contract dispute with two New York unions. Television wasn't involved in the dispute. Anyway, "Law and Order" was not due to resume shooting until June.</p>
        <p>The series, written by six staff writers and a few freelancers, is determined to be realistic. A lawyer and a police detective make sure the smallest details are correct in both halves of the hourlong show, Mr. Stern said. The first half takes place on the street where a crime is committed and in the police precinct, where it is investigated; the second half traces the course of the case in court.</p>
        <p>"We wanted not just another cop show," recalled Dick Wolf, executive producer and creator of "Law and Order," who was also a producer for "Miami Vice" and script consultant to "Hill Street Blues."</p>
        <p>"Law and Order," he said, aims to "explore the entire realm of the justice system," with stories inspired partly by real news reports. It also considers varying ethical points of view through its characters, who often disagree.  Cops Talk Like Cops</p>
        <p>The characters talk New Yorkese. The cops talk like cops, and some are really officers who get to deliver a few lines. Both Mr. Noth and Michael Moriarty, who plays an assistant district attorney, spent time with their real counterparts to get the feel of their roles; Mr. Sorvino said he didn't need to.</p>
        <p>"I've played a cop so many times, it's home territory," said the actor, who was a Mafia don in the movie "Goodfellas." He's actually a deputy sheriff in Scranton, Pa., ("It's mostly P.R. work," he said) and an auxiliary policeman in Rye, N.Y.</p>
        <p>"I must have some kind of cop mentality," he said. "Their lives are on the line all the time and they're largely spat upon."</p>
        <p>Mr. Noth, who has had mostly stage experience but who was Officer Lipsky in "Hill Street Blues," said he learned a lot from traveling with detectives from the 34th Precinct.  "They're conversational" when talking to suspects, he said. "They're not usually the tough guys. It's subtle manipulation."</p>
        <p>One occasion especially stuck in his mind, when a detective kept playing with a rubber band, stretching it slowly while interrogating a man. "He was screwing the guy to the wall but doing it with a smile on his face," he recalled.</p>
        <p>To portray Detective Logan, Mr. Noth wears an American flag in his lapel because he thinks of his character as conservative in some ways. Yet his views are not predictable; the detective was adamantly pro-abortion rights in one episode, he noted. "The guy really loves doing what he does," he said, "and doesn't take himself too seriously." Art and Reality</p>
        <p>As Detective Cerreta, Mr. Sorvino said, he is playing himself, "the hardest thing I've ever done." His specialty has been character roles with an accent, he said, and he wonders if his own personality resonates, because he doesn't have idiosyncratic speech or the outsize persona of some stars; friends can't mimic him, he said. "Whatever may be interesting about me is likely to be the content; I would doubt it's just because I'm saying it."</p>
        <p>Perhaps a sign of the true-to-life goings-on on West 13th Street was how hard it was to tell real bystanders from the fakes.</p>
        <p>That fellow in tattered jeans, smoking a pipe near the foot of the stairs, for instance; would he be shooed away by one of the young men with walkie-talkies? No, he was an extra. The elderly couple nearby soon showed they were real by approaching Mr. Sorvino as he sat on a metal chair and asking for his autograph.</p>
        <p>The scene that unfolded was one of the less dramatic parts of this episode. The detectives and the psychiatrist escorted the woman (Mary Jo Negro) up the stairs of the brownstone. There was brief dialogue that nobody watching could hear.</p>
        <p>They repeated the ascent a few times to get it just right, as two school girls and a blind man with a Seeing Eye dog repeated their strolls past the building. Before going on to a scene inside the brownstone, where the woman remembers a bloody sweater, everybody broke for lunch.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
