<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Every TV Show Is a Rerun</title>
    <meta content="04GABL$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/04/opinion/04GABL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1275378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gabler, Neal</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">NBC</org>
        <org class="online_producer">NFL</org>
        <org class="online_producer">CBS</org>
        <person class="online_producer">James, Henry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hatch, Richard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DB143BF937A35750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Every TV Show Is a Rerun</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Neal Gabler</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gabler, Neal</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neal Gabler Op-Ed article on spate of 'reality' television programs, which are cheap to produce, satisfy voyeuristic urge and have frisson of authenticity; says they flourish, however, because plots have been exhausted from overuse, and writers cannot possibly keep up with demand from so many media outlets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everyone, it seems, has an explanation for the sudden spate of so-called reality shows like ''Survivor,'' ''Temptation Island'' and even the new XFL football league. They are cheap to produce, they satisfy a voyeuristic urge, they have the frisson of authenticity. But these programs are flourishing for a possibly more significant reason: We are experiencing a deep crisis in narrative.</p>
        <p>You don't normally think of plots as a finite resource like oil or coal that can be exhausted, but that is precisely what is happening to our stories. Over the last 25 years or so they have been depleted, worn out from overuse. As the number of media outlets has increased, the demand for stories has skyrocketed and writers' ingenuity can't possibly keep pace -- not with hundreds of films and programs all urgently needing plots.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everyone, it seems, has an explanation for the sudden spate of so-called reality shows like ''Survivor,'' ''Temptation Island'' and even the new XFL football league. They are cheap to produce, they satisfy a voyeuristic urge, they have the frisson of authenticity. But these programs are flourishing for a possibly more significant reason: We are experiencing a deep crisis in narrative.</p>
        <p>You don't normally think of plots as a finite resource like oil or coal that can be exhausted, but that is precisely what is happening to our stories. Over the last 25 years or so they have been depleted, worn out from overuse. As the number of media outlets has increased, the demand for stories has skyrocketed and writers' ingenuity can't possibly keep pace -- not with hundreds of films and programs all urgently needing plots.</p>
        <p>Primal narratives like ''The Iliad'' or ''Romeo and Juliet'' obviously endure because they are rich and complex and touch each of us differently. But to fill the maw of the mass media, most of the plots, by necessity, are formulaic. Writers and producers find elements that elicit a predictable response in an audience, and they keep recycling them.</p>
        <p>Naturally, the effect tends to diminish. It is not just that the plots become overfamiliar; it is that having seen them so often, the audience begins to see the machinery at work.  When you watch for the umpteenth time the same sort of romantic imbroglio on ''Frasier'' or ''Friends,'' or you watch yet another mad killer being tracked on ''NYPD Blue'' or ''Law and Order,'' you can practically hear the gears grinding.</p>
        <p>Even though narratives are obviously designed to shape audience response, they have increasingly had to contend with this notion that they are a trick, an emotion-mongering hoax, at a time when Americans have become suspicious of any sort of manipulation. Younger audiences, especially, seem to resist the old narrative artifices as deceptions, and so do many of the shows that appeal to them. A program like ''Popular,'' about high school cliques, frequently breaks the pretense of realism by suddenly turning surrealistic -- the better to convince its viewers that it doesn't take narrative seriously.</p>
        <p>Another fairly recent narrative invention, professional wrestling, is even predicated on the idea that it is deliberately and shamelessly plotted. It exposes its plot mechanics so that, in a self-reflexive, post-modernist twist, the manipulation itself becomes the plot. Wrestling fans luxuriate in the falseness of the show and their own savvy in being in on the joke.</p>
        <p>The XFL, cooked up by NBC and Vince McMahon, the wrestling promoter, promised to take the same tack with professional football. Instead it merely foregrounded those elements like violence and sex that the staid National Football League had pushed to the background, emphasizing what it called ''smash-mouth'' football, meaning there was more macho posturing than in the NFL.</p>
        <p>There are no outrageous plots like opposing quarterbacks vying for the heart of a buxom cheerleader, no scripted games with last-second heroics, no coaches having a nervous breakdown in the locker room. There is only a low-rent version of the traditional sports story, winners and losers, which makes the XFL a casualty of, not an antidote to, narrative exhaustion. No wonder its ratings have plummeted.</p>
        <p>If some programs try to meet the narrative crisis by exposing the mechanics of plot, reality programming has taken the opposite tack. It purports to have no preconceived narrative template whatsoever. Within the loose contours of tribal competition on ''Survivor'' or sexual come-ons on ''Temptation Island,'' the contestants are free to do as they please -- in effect, to create the narrative as they go. Reality programming not only provides suspense that conventional narratives have a difficult time matching; it seems to vanquish the threat of manipulation altogether. Henry James called for an aesthetic of ''felt life.'' The premise of reality programming is, why have ''felt life'' when you can have the real thing?</p>
        <p>That is what a program like ''Survivor'' alleges to give and what audiences seem to want: a real plot rather than an imagined one, real people rather than created ones. It is also apparently why NBC chose to counter ''Survivor'' on CBS with outtakes from ''Friends'' that showed  the actors blowing their lines and cutting up. ''Friends'' the series is a conventional program, but the outtakes are reality. Pirandello might have appreciated the fact that the show of outtakes actually posted better ratings than the plotted ''Friends'' episode that week.</p>
        <p>Still, traditional narrative isn't dispatched all that easily. Anyone who has watched ''Survivor II'' has certainly noticed how much it resembles Version One.</p>
        <p>Those first survivors -- villainous Richard Hatch and his crew -- had to create their characters and engineer the plot developments from scratch. Clearly, the second crew was cast to type, but they have readily taken up where the earlier survivors left off -- essentially assuming the roles of the first cast and playing out that cast's narrative. There is a witch, a schemer, a tough guy, a gamine, a salty old timer, et cetera, and there are the very same alliances, ingratiation and backbiting. You can even feel several competitors actively competing to be this season's Mr. Hatch.  In short, ''Survivor'' is rapidly turning into a formula itself.</p>
        <p>Maybe that's just the way it is now. As the quantity of stories proliferates, the formulas kick in faster, which leaves us like oil explorers, searching for the next gusher, only to pump it dry as soon as we find it. Reality programming is today's gusher, helping solve the narrative crisis, but it probably won't be long before it seems as hoary and duplicitous as the conventional narratives it replaced.</p>
        <p>Neal Gabler is the author, most recently, of ''Life the Movie: How Entertainment Conquered Reality.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Neal Gabler is the author, most recently, of ''Life the Movie: How Entertainment Conquered Reality.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
