<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BENEFITS</title>
    <meta content="25BENE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1056811"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEED91E3DF936A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="2768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BENEFITS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cooks and Celebrities</p>
        <p>MONDAY -- Nearly 40 chefs from New York restaurants will cook their signature dishes, assisted by personalities from local television and radio stations, at a dinner to benefit the League for the Hard of Hearing. Among the participants will be Scott Campbell of Avenue, Edward Brown of the Sea Grill and Martin Howard of the Rainbow Room, along with David Diaz of WCBS-TV and Jane Hanson of WNBC-TV. The evening at the Chase Manhattan Bank Dining Rooms, 270 Park Avenue (47th Street), will begin at 6:30. Tickets, $300, from (212) 741-3145, or by teletype machine from (212) 255-1932.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cooks and Celebrities</p>
        <p>MONDAY -- Nearly 40 chefs from New York restaurants will cook their signature dishes, assisted by personalities from local television and radio stations, at a dinner to benefit the League for the Hard of Hearing. Among the participants will be Scott Campbell of Avenue, Edward Brown of the Sea Grill and Martin Howard of the Rainbow Room, along with David Diaz of WCBS-TV and Jane Hanson of WNBC-TV. The evening at the Chase Manhattan Bank Dining Rooms, 270 Park Avenue (47th Street), will begin at 6:30. Tickets, $300, from (212) 741-3145, or by teletype machine from (212) 255-1932.</p>
        <p>Honoring Comden and Green</p>
        <p>MONDAY -- The songwriters Betty Comden and Adolph Green will be honored at a dinner benefiting Primary Stages, an Off Broadway theater company. Leslie Uggams and Cy Coleman will perform during the event, at the 200 Fifth Club, 200 Fifth Avenue (23d Street). Drinks at 6:30. Tickets, $200, from (212) 333-7471.</p>
        <p>The Dinner Circuit</p>
        <p>TUESDAY -- A performance by the Eberli Trio, a reading by the novelist Richard Price and a preview of the musical version of ''Bright Lights, Big City'' will be among the happenings at 10 dinner parties to raise money for Yaddo, the arts colony in Saratoga Springs, N.Y. The dinners, at 10 homes, restaurants or clubs around Manhattan, begin at 7:30. Tickets, $250, from (212) 243-7300.</p>
        <p>Fighting Breast Cancer</p>
        <p>TUESDAY -- The National Breast Cancer Coalition will benefit from a dinner at the Plaza. Dr. Dennis Slamon, the director of the Revlon/ U.C.L.A. Women's Cancer Research Program, will be honored. Drinks at 6:30. Tickets, $500, from (212) 245-6570.</p>
        <p>Opera at the Ballet</p>
        <p>TUESDAY -- The soprano Cecilia Bartoli will accompany a pas de deux and sing other selections at opening night of American Ballet Theater's fall season at City Center. A reception at 5:30 will precede the performance at 7, and a dinner and dance at the Essex House will follow it. Tickets, $1,000, or $200 for the reception and performance only, from (212) 477-3030, ext. 3239.</p>
        <p>An Author Talks</p>
        <p>TUESDAY -- Caleb Carr, the author, will be the first speaker in the annual lecture series at St. Luke's School, 487 Hudson Street (Christopher Street). Other authors scheduled for the series are Arianna Huffington (Dec. 8), Jay McInerney (March 9) and Anna Quindlen (April 27). The lectures, to benefit the school, will begin at 7:30 P.M. Tickets, $20, or $75 for all four talks, from (212) 924-5960.</p>
        <p>Community Service Gala</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- The Community Service Society of New York will honor Marian S. Heiskell, one of the organization's trustees, and Dr. Stephen R. Aiello, the president of Cohn &amp; Wolfe, a public relations firm, at a black-tie dinner at the New York Hilton. The evening, to benefit the society's programs, will begin with cocktails at 6:30. Tickets, $500, from (212) 614-5470.</p>
        <p>A Master of Design</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- The School of Visual Arts will present an award to Paul Davis, the graphic designer, at a dinner and dance at the Carlyle. Proceeds will go to scholarships at the school. Cocktails at 6:30 will be followed by dinner and dancing. Black tie. Tickets, $200, from (212) 260-7607.</p>
        <p>Helping Out Around Town</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- Japanese-American Social Services, which operates charitable programs in the New York metropolitan area, will benefit from a dinner at the New York Hilton. Michie Nakamaru, a soprano from Japan, will perform. The evening will begin with cocktails at 6. Tickets, $150, from (212) 255-1881.</p>
        <p>'On the Town' With Its Writers</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- The New York Shakespeare Festival will benefit from a preview performance of ''On the Town'' at the Gershwin Theater. The 7 P.M. show will be followed by dinner at the Sheraton New York, where Betty Comden and Adolph Green, who wrote the book and lyrics for the show, will be honored. Tickets, $500, from (212) 245-6570.</p>
        <p>Polishing the Apple</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- The Metropolitan Historic Structures Association will honor some of those who have had a hand in the restoration of Times Square, including Robert A. M. Stern and Hugh Hardy, the architects; the Times Square Business Improvement District; the New 42d Street Inc., and the Walt Disney Company.  The reception, to be held at the National Society of Colonial Dames in the State of New York, 215 East 71st Street, begins at 5:30 P.M. Tickets, $50, from (212) 473-6045.</p>
        <p>Political Party</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato, New York State Comptroller H. Carl McCall and Attorney General Dennis C. Vacco will be among the honorees at a dinner aboard the Intrepid, in the Hudson River at 46th Street. The evening will raise money for the Association to Benefit Children. Cocktails at 6 will be followed by dinner at 7:30. Tickets, $750, from (212) 845-3823.</p>
        <p>Spirits in the Park</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- The Central Park Conservancy will hold its annual Halloween Ball under a tent at the Naumburg Bandshell, midpark at 70th Street. Drinks at 7 will be followed by dinner and dancing. Dress is black tie with masks, and the organization is encouraging guests to wear costumes. Tickets, $500, from (212) 888-7003.</p>
        <p>Princess Grace Awards</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- Prince Albert of Monaco will be at the Waldorf-Astoria for the annual presentation of the Princess Grace Awards, which were established as a memorial to his mother. Ashley Judd, the actress, will conduct the ceremonies, during which young American actors, dancers and filmmakers will receive scholarships, apprenticeships and fellowships. The black-tie evening will begin with a cocktail reception at 7, followed by dinner and dancing. Tickets, $500, from (212) 317-1470.</p>
        <p>Downtown Hospital Gala</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- The New York Downtown Hospital will hold its sixth annual dinner and dance at Cipriani Wall Street, 55 Wall Street. Cocktails at 6 P.M. Tickets, $350, from (212) 801-1705.</p>
        <p>Public Education at the Pierre</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- A dinner at the Pierre will benefit the Public Education Association, a New York City organization that encourages parents' involvement in their children's education. David H. Komansky, the chairman of Merrill Lynch &amp; Company and a public school graduate, will be honored. The evening will begin with cocktails at 6:30. Black tie. Tickets, $500, from (212) 675-9474.</p>
        <p>Hulaween With Bette Midler</p>
        <p>FRIDAY -- Bette Midler will perform at the second annual Hawaiian-style Halloween party at the Waldorf-Astoria to benefit the New York Restoration Project, which helps clean and refurbish city parks. Rosie O'Donnell will conduct an auction. Cocktails at 7 will be followed by dinner, dancing and the show. The organization suggests that guests wear costumes. Tickets, $500, from (212) 972-2268.</p>
        <p>Halloween, Hollywood Style</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- A Halloween party at the Space, 425 West 15th Street (Ninth Avenue), will take its theme from classic horror movies. Proceeds will go to the Michael Callen-Audre Lorde Community Health Center in Manhattan, which provides medical care for lesbians and gay men. The event, to begin at 9 P.M., will include drinks, dancing, hors d'oeuvres and Halloween candy. Organizers encourage guests to wear costumes. Tickets, $100, from (212) 271-7263.</p>
        <p>Halloween, Around the World</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- Guests at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum's annual Halloween Ball are encouraged to wear costumes representative of cultures around the world. The party, sponsored by the Guggenheim Circle and the Young Collectors Council, two of the museum's young-professional groups, will run from 10 P.M. to 2 A.M. at the museum and will include an open bar, hors d'oeuvres, dancing and dessert. Tickets, $110, from (212) 423-3534.</p>
        <p>Halloween at the Rihga Royal</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- A costume party at the Rihga Royal Hotel, 151 West 54th Street, will benefit the New York Chapter of the Crohn's and Colitis Foundation. The evening will include an open bar, a buffet and dancing, and will start at 9. Tickets, $75, from (212) 679-1570.</p>
        <p>A Masked Ball</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- Maimonides Medical Center in Brooklyn will benefit from a Venetian-style masked ball at Cipriani Wall Street, 55 Wall Street in Manhattan. Cocktails at 8 will be followed by dinner and dancing. Black or white tie. Tickets, $500, from (718) 283-7046.</p>
        <p>Helping Haiti</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- Representative Maxine Waters, Democrat of California, and Tabou Combo, a Haitian band, will be among the honorees at a black-tie dinner and dance at the Waldorf-Astoria. The evening will benefit the charitable programs of the National Organization for the Advancement of Haitians. Drinks at 6:30. Tickets, $250, from (212) 694-0227.</p>
        <p>Young Professionals</p>
        <p>NOV. 2 -- Students from the Professional Children's School, which provides elementary and high school studies for young actors, singers, dancers and athletes, will perform in a recital at the Union Club, 101 East 69th Street. The benefit for the school's tuition-aid program begins with the concert at 6:15 and will be followed by a reception. Tickets, $175, from (212) 582-3116, ext. 115.</p>
        <p>Jazz at Lincoln Center</p>
        <p>NOV. 2 -- Diana Krall, Bobby Short, Ann Hampton Callaway and the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra conducted by Wynton Marsalis will perform in Jazz at Lincoln Center's third annual benefit concert at Avery Fisher Hall. Benny Carter, the saxophonist, will be among the honorees, and Ed Bradley of ''60 Minutes'' will be the host. Cocktails at 6:15 will be followed by the concert at 7:30 and then a dinner-dance at the New York State Theater. Tickets, $650, from (212) 245-6570; for the concert alone, $40 to $100, from (212) 721-6500.</p>
        <p>Talking About 'Central Park'</p>
        <p>NOV. 2 -- ''Central Park,'' a triptych of one-act operas scheduled to have its premiere in July at Glimmerglass Opera in Cooperstown, N.Y., will be the topic of a discussion benefiting Glimmerglass. The work's composers, Robert Beaser, Deborah Drattell and Michael Torke, will participate, along with Terrence McNally, Wendy Wasserstein and A.R. Gurney, who are writing the three librettos. The evening will begin at 6 with a cocktail reception and the talk at Florence Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street. Dinner will follow at six private homes in Manhattan. Tickets, $300, or $150 for cocktails and the program only, from (607) 547-5704.</p>
        <p>Actors' Fund Gala</p>
        <p>NOV. 2 -- Gerald Schoenfeld, the chairman of the Shubert Organization, and Arthur Sulzberger Jr., publisher of The New York Times and chairman of the Times Company, will be honored at a black-tie dinner and dance at the Sheraton New York. Betty Buckley, Judy Kuhn and Donna McKechnie will sing at the event, to benefit the Actors' Fund of America, which provides financial assistance and counseling to workers in the entertainment industry. Cocktails at 6:30. Tickets, $500, from (212) 245-6570.</p>
        <p>Honoring Architects</p>
        <p>NOV. 4 -- The Dia Center for the Arts, 542 West 22d Street, will honor the architects Philip Johnson and Frank Gehry at its annual fall gala, at the center. Cocktails at 7 P.M. will be followed by dinner and the awards ceremony. Tickets, $500, from (212) 293-5504.</p>
        <p>Conferring Landmark Status</p>
        <p>NOV. 4 -- Bill Blass, Joan Ganz Cooney, Ahmet Ertegun, Kitty Carlisle Hart, Henry R. Luce 3d and Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan will be honored as this year's ''Living New York Landmarks'' at a black-tie dinner and dance at the Plaza. The event will benefit the New York Landmarks Conservancy. Cocktails at 7. Tickets, $500, from (212) 995-5260.</p>
        <p>Circus Gala</p>
        <p>NOV. 6 -- The Big Apple Circus will hold its annual benefit gala under the big tent at Lincoln Center's Damrosch Park. The event begins at 6 P.M. with cocktails, hors d'oeuvres and a boxed dinner, followed by the show at 7. Dessert and dancing will follow in the ring. Michael Bloomberg, president of the news service that bears his name, will be the host of the evening, to benefit the circus and its community outreach programs, including the Clown Care Unit for hospitalized children. Tickets, $100, from (212) 268-2500, ext. 129.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
