<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World: Blueprint; Filling In Peace's Details Is the Painful Part</title>
    <meta content="25BRON$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1056874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bronner, Ethan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE6DF163CF936A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World: Blueprint; Filling In Peace's Details Is the Painful Part</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ETHAN BRONNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bronner, Ethan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many Israelis and Palestinians are wary of celebrating latest accord reached at Wye Plantation; they agreed to make peace five years ago, too, but never did much to alter sense they had of each other; there is feeling that trust and understanding are still missing between two sides; simple words like 'land' and 'peace' are not simple in Middle East; map; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE images were arresting. There they were, Ariel Sharon, who once sent the Israeli military to Beirut for Yasir Arafat's head, and Benjamin Netanyahu, who long avoided shaking the man's hand, sitting together in Maryland agreeing with the Palestinian leader on land and airports and prisoner releases.</p>
        <p>It is often said that the weakness of the 1993 Israeli-Palestinian peace accord worked out in Oslo, Norway, was that it was embraced by only half of Israel, the secular liberals of European origin, and had never been sold to religious Israelis, the poor and those of Middle Eastern origin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE images were arresting. There they were, Ariel Sharon, who once sent the Israeli military to Beirut for Yasir Arafat's head, and Benjamin Netanyahu, who long avoided shaking the man's hand, sitting together in Maryland agreeing with the Palestinian leader on land and airports and prisoner releases.</p>
        <p>It is often said that the weakness of the 1993 Israeli-Palestinian peace accord worked out in Oslo, Norway, was that it was embraced by only half of Israel, the secular liberals of European origin, and had never been sold to religious Israelis, the poor and those of Middle Eastern origin.</p>
        <p>Now, three years after an Orthodox, Yemenite Israeli student sought to end the peace deal by assassinating Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin, here were the representatives of that other Israel coming to terms with the reality that Oslo had created.</p>
        <p>Yes, they were making it hard with their near walkouts and last-minute demands. But that was the way toward real peace: you relinquish holy land with a tear in your eye and an ache in your gut, not with the detachment of the previous Government. Here were negotiators who understood the fears as well as the hopes of their people, who could build an agreement that might survive those fears. Prime Minister Rabin, the messenger of peace, may have died, but his message has survived.</p>
        <p>Perhaps. But the past five years -- since Mr. Rabin and Mr. Arafat shook hands on the White House lawn -- have offered sobering lessons on why optimism has rarely held sway in this process since.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the intimate and personal Oslo negotiations, at the Wye Plantation it took the President of the United States and the King of Jordan days and nights of prodding to produce this next interim step. And its implementation is highly complex. Of course, details and implementation posed formidable barriers to peace from the start. What is different this time is that the Wye agreement comes in the context of difficult experience in making specific peace arrangements work.</p>
        <p>''Until Netanyahu's election more than two years ago, the message from the Government was that we have to begin a new life with the Palestinians; let's be neighbors,'' said Yoel Esteron, managing editor of the Israeli newspaper Haaretz. ''But now there is no spirit of reconciliation. What we have is a deal among technocrats, a deal with no soul or spirit because there is so little good feeling left.''</p>
        <p>Shlomo Gazit, a former director of Israel's military intelligence, put it this way: ''I am very doubtful that this is a new beginning. For the process to go on, there must be trust and understanding between the two sides and a joint will to move ahead to an overall agreement. What happened in recent months does not bring us any nearer to that.''</p>
        <p>One reason is that the Palestinians and Israelis agreed to make peace five years ago but never did much to alter the sense they had of each other. Schools on both sides have virtually no lessons in the other's history. Maps in Palestinian schools still show only the names of Palestinian villages destroyed by Israel, not the new Israeli cities. Israeli maps and textbooks make no reference to the destroyed Palestinian towns or to the life and culture of Palestinians before Zionist immigration in the late 19th century.</p>
        <p>An official 8th-grade textbook from the Palestinian Authority was recently shown to include the sentence, ''The prime examples of racial discrimination are Zionism and Nazism.'' Last August, Palestinian television was showing footage of a summer camp with youngsters training with automatic weapons and chanting, ''I foresee my death and I rush toward it!'' and, ''A hero's death, the death of a suicide warrior!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Esteron of Haaretz said that even the largely liberal, educated Israeli readers of his newspaper seem unmoved by the difficulties that Palestinians suffer as a result of Israeli rules and regulations -- checkpoints, bans on home building, severe restrictions on trade, industry and movement.</p>
        <p>''People look at it as if it were somewhere in the Philippines, not right next door,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Each side has tended to consider the Oslo accord a kind of apology from the other, an acknowledgment that it had done wrong. But each side sees only the other's misdeeds, not its own.</p>
        <p>And the problem that has overwhelmed all others is the enormous imbalance -- military, geopolitical and economic -- between Israel and the Palestinians. For many Palestinians, Israel is simply a neighborhood outpost of the American-dominated global economy.</p>
        <p>Since the new global system has little place in it for land, clan and honor, values upon which Palestinian society has long been built, and can be so unforgiving to those not part of it, Israel is seen as a threat in the most fundamental way to the values of many in the West Bank and Gaza. To many there, Israel stands for sexual permissiveness and godlessness, and so the battle against it goes beyond a fight over land and sovereignty.</p>
        <p>The issue is, of course, still more complicated. A battle over values exists within Israel itself, where a religious-secular divide threatens internal politics. Mr. Rabin's assassin, Yigal Amir, like many Sephardi and religious Israelis, felt that peace was draining the nation of its biblical mission and spirit.</p>
        <p>Now, with Mr. Netanyahu and Mr. Sharon the advocates of peace, the opponents of peace within Israel may feel more and more marginalized. But that does not necessarily mean Israelis will see Palestinians in a more generous light. Israelis feel that what they are giving up is not fully appreciated -- as Mr. Netanyahu has said, 1 percent of the West Bank is the size of Tel Aviv.</p>
        <p>But even if the end of this process includes something that bears the name ''State of Palestine,'' as the Palestinians so fervently hope and the majority of Israelis now accept, many doubt it will end the century-old Jewish-Arab conflict.</p>
        <p>''This deal does not change the basic rules of the game,'' asserted Meron Benvenisti, a former deputy mayor of Jerusalem and advocate of greater Israeli concessions. ''Let's say the Palestinians get even 50 percent of the West Bank.</p>
        <p>''Think about water resources, land development, sewage. Israelis use five times the water of Palestinians. What happens when the Palestinians want more? Where will it come from?</p>
        <p>''The Israelis will say: 'We gave all we could. No more. The rest is ours.' So what the Palestinians will get is exactly what the Israelis can live with, peace without any real price. That's why they don't care if there is a Palestinian state. That's why even Sharon and Netanyahu can accept a state, because of the way they will define it.''</p>
        <p>At the End of the Track</p>
        <p>Ali Jarbawi, a Palestinian political scientist at Bir Zeit University in the West Bank, said he was equally pessimistic. ''I think that for Netanyahu this week's deal is the end of the track altogether,'' he said. ''He won't give up much more land. And what kind of state will we get? There will be cantons with no direct links. It is a gloomy prospect for us.''</p>
        <p>Daniel Ben-Simon, a political analyst for Haaretz, said he believes the new accord will reshape Israeli politics because the issue that has defined left and right for so long -- territorial concession and a Palestinian state -- will no longer be there. In addition, he says that because of the Palestinian question, other Israeli problems, like the religious and ethnic divides, have festered. Now they can be dealt with and that process will produce an entirely new set of parties and coalitions.</p>
        <p>But General Gazit, the former military intelligence chief, is far less hopeful. He believes that Mr. Sharon and Mr. Netanyahu have no long-term vision for the Palestinian question.</p>
        <p>''There is huge writing on the wall,'' he said. ''It shows us that without a comprehensive agreement with our neighbors we are doomed ultimately to war. I think the politicians see it. But they don't have the courage to act on it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
