<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First Boston Seen Settling Kickback Case</title>
    <meta content="12WALL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/12/business/12WALL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1350685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Business"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Investment Banking</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Credit Suisse First Boston</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Investment Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Credit Suisse</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6D9143FF931A25751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First Boston Seen Settling Kickback Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">First Boston Seen Settling Kickback Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Credit Suisse First Boston is expected to pay $100 million to securities regulators to end investigation into whether it received kickbacks from buyers of hot stock offerings in late 1990's; penalty would amount to small fraction of investment banking fees and commissions firm reaped from underwriting technology stocks; regulators accuse firm of demanding that customers pay back some of their profits (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Credit Suisse First Boston may pay $100 million to securities regulators to end an investigation into whether it received kickbacks from buyers of hot stock offerings in the late 1990's, several people close to the matter said yesterday.</p>
        <p>A final settlement may not be reached until early next year, if at all, these people said. But First Boston officials are eager to put to rest this part of the wide-ranging federal investigation into how investment banks handled the sale of new-technology stocks during the boom that collapsed in early 2000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Credit Suisse First Boston may pay $100 million to securities regulators to end an investigation into whether it received kickbacks from buyers of hot stock offerings in the late 1990's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Credit Suisse First Boston may pay $100 million to securities regulators to end an investigation into whether it received kickbacks from buyers of hot stock offerings in the late 1990's, several people close to the matter said yesterday.</p>
        <p>A final settlement may not be reached until early next year, if at all, these people said. But First Boston officials are eager to put to rest this part of the wide-ranging federal investigation into how investment banks handled the sale of new-technology stocks during the boom that collapsed in early 2000.</p>
        <p>They have discussed paying about $100 million in fines to the Securities and Exchange Commission and the National Association of Securities Dealers and are negotiating which violations of securities laws the firm would be charged with, these people said. That penalty would be the fifth largest ever paid by a Wall Street firm, but it would amount to a fraction of the fees and commissions the firm reaped from underwriting technology stocks in the last few years.</p>
        <p>The regulators singled out First Boston, accusing it of demanding that customers pay back some of the profit they made from trading new stocks in the form of inflated commissions on other stock trades. Investigators gathered evidence, including e-mail messages, that indicated that the firm's sale representatives had told some customers to pay the firm at least $1 in commissions for every $3 of new-stock trading profits.</p>
        <p>The proposed settlement was reported in The Wall Street Journal yesterday.</p>
        <p>First Boston officials declined to comment on the proposed settlement yesterday, as did officials of the S.E.C. and the N.A.S.D.</p>
        <p>First Boston, the investment banking arm of the Credit Suisse Group of Switzerland, is in the middle of a reorganization under its new chief executive, John J. Mack. Mr. Mack hopes to clean up the image of the firm, which had run afoul of regulators and prosecutors in the United States and several other countries.</p>
        <p>When the investigations were beginning, more than a year ago, First Boston executives said they had not done anything in selling new stocks that their competitors on Wall Street had not done. But in March, securities regulators informed several First Boston employees that they might be charged. Then in June, the firm fired three brokers that it had suspended in April for violating the firm's policies on the allocation of new stocks.</p>
        <p>''They wanted for a long time to say this is an industry problem, but the rest of the industry was ducking and weaving and saying this is First Boston's problem,'' said John Coffee, a law professor at Columbia University.</p>
        <p>Those other firms will point an accusing finger at First Boston, Mr. Coffee said. ''In this competitive environment, any kind of reputational stigma that you acquire will be used by your rivals, who are not above using any competitive technique to steal your client,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But regulators do not plan to charge First Boston with securities fraud, an indictment that could have permanently tarnished its name and doomed its future as a leading investment bank.</p>
        <p>''If they had accused us of fraud, we were dead,'' said one First Boston executive, who spoke on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>Any such charges, and certainly any conviction, would have provided fodder to the lawyers trying to bring class-action suits against the investment banks.</p>
        <p>Melvyn Weiss, chairman of the executive committee of lawyers who have sued the investment banks over new-stock sales, said the proposed settlement would not weaken the plaintiffs' cases.</p>
        <p>Speaking of First Boston's apparently successful settlement negotiations with regulators, Mr. Weiss said, ''I think they did a great job, but so what?</p>
        <p>''There is no victim fund set up, so it's not going to in any way reduce the amount of money that we're seeking,'' said Mr. Weiss, a senior partner in the law firm Milberg Weiss Bershad Hynes &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>If the $100 million is paid, it would go partly to the S.E.C., which would pass the money on to the Treasury, and partly to NASD Regulation, the regulatory arm of the N.A.S.D., which would use the money for its investigations.</p>
        <p>In any settlement, First Boston would probably not admit or deny its guilt. After settling with the firm, regulators could still discipline the First Boston employees who have been warned, or others.</p>
        <p>It was not clear yesterday whether securities regulators planned to impose any new rules on the allocation of initial public offerings. The urgency of any changes has faded along with demand for new stocks, legal experts said.</p>
        <p>The settlement talks between regulators and lawyers for the firm came after the decision last month by federal prosecutors to drop a criminal investigation into the same matter. The United States attorney in Manhattan had been gathering evidence about accusations that First Boston employees had demanded that buyers of hot stocks share some of their trading profits by paying inflated commissions.</p>
        <p>A settlement with regulators would not solve all of First Boston's problems. Plaintiffs' lawyers have filed more than 1,000 lawsuits against First Boston and about four dozen other securities firms, asserting that they manipulated the prices of new stocks in various ways.</p>
        <p>Those suits contend that sales representatives at First Boston gave relatively big allocations of new stocks to professional investors in exchange for a share of the profits those buyers made by reselling the stocks. They also contend that other investment banks, including Goldman, Sachs and Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, solicited promises from investors that they would buy more shares of a new stock at higher prices after it started trading.</p>
        <p>Such arrangements, expressly prohibited by securities laws, could have driven new stocks to artificially high prices. Spokeswomen for Goldman, Sachs and Morgan Stanley declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Federal regulators are continuing to investigate the second practice, known on Wall Street as ''laddering'' a stock, and they may still bring charges against one or more investment banks. But First Boston is not likely to be among them, several people close to the settlement talks said.</p>
        <p>The investigation into laddering is potentially more important to investors and more damaging to Wall Street and the firms' reputations because the financial harm it could have caused to unwitting investors is more apparent. Most of the alleged kickbacks would have been paid willingly by professional investors, but the most likely victims of artificially inflated stock prices would have been less sophisticated individual investors.</p>
        <p>In most initial public offerings, the underwriters dole out the bulk of the shares to mutual fund companies, hedge funds and other institutional investors. How the underwriters spread them around is generally left to their discretion, with the biggest chunks going to firms that pay the most in commissions to brokerage firms.</p>
        <p>Individual investors scrap for as little as 20 percent of all the shares distributed before trading begins. Those left out must buy shares in the market when the original buyers start reselling them. During the technology stock boom, individual investors helped fuel the rapid rise of new stocks by jumping to buy at market prices on the first day of trading.</p>
        <p>''If you can show that there has been this kind of laddering, that's a clear violation, and I think that still could produce much more serious charges and settlements,'' Mr. Coffee said. ''That does hurt a clear victim: the poor fool who doesn't get the allocation and is buying in the secondary market.''</p>
        <p>Business</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
