<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Get a Job</title>
    <meta content="17FRIE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1002862"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3DD1339F934A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Get a Job</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <dateline>HENG DAO, China</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column says not only is China's move toward free market irreversible, but that it is now being driven as much from villages as from Beijing; says ideologically, Chinese Communist Party is dead (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While monitoring village elections in northeastern China with a U.S. observer team, I wandered through the hamlet of Heng Dao, dropping in on a farmer-turned-mechanic who had geese and pigs in the front yard but a stereo and color television inside his brick hut. Our interpreter asked him what had happened to the loudspeaker that the Communist Party had in his ''brigade,'' as small villages were known in Mao's day. The loudspeakers were used to blare out instructions and propaganda from the party. ''We took it down last year,'' the villager said. ''No one wanted to listen to it anymore. We have stereo and TV now.''</p>
        <p>There are many things you learn observing village elections in China, but the overriding impression is this: Not only is China's move toward a free market irreversible, it is now being driven as much from the villages up as from Beijing down. When people say that in China today the Government's only ideology -- and basis of legitimacy -- is its ability to keep incomes rising, they are so right. Ideologically, the Chinese Communist Party is dead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While monitoring village elections in northeastern China with a U.S. observer team, I wandered through the hamlet of Heng Dao, dropping in on a farmer-turned-mechanic who had geese and pigs in the front yard but a stereo and color television inside his brick hut. Our interpreter asked him what had happened to the loudspeaker that the Communist Party had in his ''brigade,'' as small villages were known in Mao's day. The loudspeakers were used to blare out instructions and propaganda from the party. ''We took it down last year,'' the villager said. ''No one wanted to listen to it anymore. We have stereo and TV now.''</p>
        <p>There are many things you learn observing village elections in China, but the overriding impression is this: Not only is China's move toward a free market irreversible, it is now being driven as much from the villages up as from Beijing down. When people say that in China today the Government's only ideology -- and basis of legitimacy -- is its ability to keep incomes rising, they are so right. Ideologically, the Chinese Communist Party is dead.</p>
        <p>In the village campaign speeches we heard, the Communist Party was mentioned in only the most perfunctory references. Instead every candidate dwelled on his commitment to be ''practical'' or ''pragmatic'' in finding ways to raise village incomes. Sure, the party is still in control, but without any message. None. That's why they've taken down the loudspeaker. There's only one message from the party to the masses now: GET A JOB.</p>
        <p>Indeed, what is so striking out here on the Nebraska-like plains of Manchuria is that the same pressures on advanced economies -- to downsize and streamline government, to seek out foreign investors, to plug into global markets and to become more competitive and more diversified -- are squeezing Chinese villages as well. Almost no one is beyond the frontiers of globalization anymore, even Heng Dao village. As China becomes integrated into the global market, the Chinese regime is being forced to reduce subsidies to state industries, reduce social benefits and pressure the whole society to become more competitive. That leads to pressure on the provinces and then the counties, and ultimately it trickles down to Heng Dao, where water buffalo share the roads with motor scooters. Listen to the campaign speeches for village chief here and tell me they don't sound as if they're running for mayor of Toledo, Ohio.</p>
        <p>The incumbent, Jiang Ying: ''I have tried to be very pragmatic in leading the village on the road to wealth. Our annual income is now 2,300 yuan per year. The budget is much smaller and during my tenure we've gotten many cadres off the village payroll. If elected, we need to introduce more science and technology into agriculture, get more enterprises here and speed up procedures for generating wealth . . . [because] the whole world is turning into one big market for merchandise.''</p>
        <p>I asked him where he got such ideas. The village has only one phone. He answered: ''I read newspapers. I listen to radio. We have a window-frame factory here. Right now we only sell locally, but we were told that if we improved the quality, we can sell abroad, make more money.''</p>
        <p>His challenger, Chen Guoshuang, vowed: ''I will bring happiness to the village. I will use more technology, which is the key to bringing wealth. First, we must diversify our economy. Families in Brigade 8 planted strawberries in hothouses and made much profit. We are near the paved road. We should be in the shipping business. One of our villagers did that last year and earned 10,000 yuan. Really! We can walk with many legs. We will operate our window-frame factory according to market demands. We must learn all about the market for aluminum and improve our factory. With profitable village enterprises, we can reduce taxes and our children can go to school without us having to pay fees.''</p>
        <p>So there you have it: Tip O'Neill was wrong. All politics isn't local. All politics is global. Almost everyone now is feeling the same pressures, constraints and opportunities, almost every government, no matter how big or small, is having to put on the same Golden Straitjacket -- which increases economic growth, but shrinks political choices.</p>
        <p>Just ask Chen Guoshuang, Jiang Ying and the Mayor of Toledo, Ohio.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
