<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China Tries Again to Curb Independent Press in South</title>
    <meta content="15PRES$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/15/international/asia/15pres.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1574265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Southern Metropolitan Daily (China)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom of The Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EEDD143BF936A25757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China Tries Again to Curb Independent Press in South</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">China Tries Again to Curb Independent Press in South</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>GUANGZHOU, China, April 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chinese authorities sharply step up their tactics in campaign to rein in country's most widely respected news organization, Southern media group; provincial courts have recently handed down harsh prison sentences for senior executives of group's Southern Metropolitan Daily, alleging corruption, and have initiated charges against newspaper's top editor; reporters throughout country and international advocates of press freedom see case as major test of new Chinese leaders' pledges to transform country into law-based society that tolerates greater freedom of expression; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After two years of state-imposed firings and staff reassignments and the suspension of one of its publications, the Chinese authorities have sharply stepped up their tactics in a campaign to rein in this country's most widely respected news organization.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, alleging managerial corruption, provincial courts here have handed down harsh prison sentences for senior executives of the Southern media group's Southern Metropolitan Daily and have initiated charges against the newspaper's top editor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chinese authorities have sharply stepped up their tactics in a campaign to rein in China's most widely respected news organization.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After two years of state-imposed firings and staff reassignments and the suspension of one of its publications, the Chinese authorities have sharply stepped up their tactics in a campaign to rein in this country's most widely respected news organization.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, alleging managerial corruption, provincial courts here have handed down harsh prison sentences for senior executives of the Southern media group's Southern Metropolitan Daily and have initiated charges against the newspaper's top editor.</p>
        <p>The provincial authorities in Guangzhou, China's third-largest city and a longstanding incubator of innovative journalism, have accused the newspaper's leaders of embezzlement. But reporters throughout the country and international advocates of press freedom see the case as a major test of China's new, reform-minded leaders' pledges to transform the country into a law-based society that tolerates greater freedom of expression.</p>
        <p>Chinese journalists say that more than any other publications, Southern Metropolitan Daily and its sister magazine, Southern Weekend, the country's most popular weekly, have been responsible for reinventing the Chinese press, by creating a journalism that even within the constraints of state ownership and censorship pushes for the truth.</p>
        <p>In the past several years, the publications have broken news about deaths in police custody and environmental damage related to the huge Three Gorges dam project and have celebrated repeated scoops over the outbreak, cover-up and then recurrence of the SARS virus.</p>
        <p>If the newspaper's leaders lose their judicial appeals, journalists from the Southern media group, Chinese intellectuals and colleagues from other publications say, the embattled newspaper will have also exposed the limits of free expression and political reform in their country.</p>
        <p>In an unusually bold petition, dozens of prominent journalists and academics have decried the prosecutions as the ''illegal use of all kinds of measures, including juridical methods, to limit press freedoms and crack down on the media and limit its space.''</p>
        <p>If the persecution of the newspaper does not end, the signers warned that ''the authority and credibility of the party and the government bodies and the legislature will be questioned, and news media whose responsibility is to push the society forward will find it difficult to survive.''</p>
        <p>Although the official charge was embezzlement of company bonuses, most observers say the most immediate apparent cause for Southern Metropolitan Daily's legal troubles was its reporting in December of a suspected re-emergence of the SARS virus, which caused a deadly epidemic a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Yu Huafeng, the newspaper's general manager, was recently sentenced to 12 years in prison. Li Minying, a former editor in chief, was sentenced to 11 years. Cheng Yizhong, the paper's top editor, is under arrest and has been charged with embezzlement.</p>
        <p>''The convictions and trials are a severe blow to the country's media reforms,'' said Xiao Qiang, director of the China Internet project at the University of California-Berkeley. ''It shows the leadership fears the country's press might be getting out of control and has decided to strike back.''</p>
        <p>The Southern media group has curious origins for a muckraking paper that regularly irritates the authorities. It was founded in 1997 by the provincial Communist Party, just as the region's economic growth kicked into high gear.</p>
        <p>Guangzhou had already been a breeding ground for the country's liberalizing economic reforms. The city has long been a relatively freewheeling place, far from Beijing and near Hong Kong, whose intensely competitive news media make censorship here almost pointless.</p>
        <p>For weeks, reporters and editors at the newspaper and at Southern Weekend have been unwilling to speak publicly about their situation for fear of inviting further trouble for their publications or being made targets themselves. Privately, though, several employees spoke of an atmosphere of fear, but also of intense pride at what their journalism had accomplished.</p>
        <p>''There is an end-of-an-era feeling about this building, filled with all kinds of feelings: depression, sadness and anger,'' said one veteran of the newsroom. But even though the news staff realizes that it has to be cautious for now, the reporter said, it will be difficult to arrest the push for freer expression.</p>
        <p>''I don't think you can say we are all afraid,'' he said, speaking on condition of anonymity. ''If it closes it closes, but that would create a very strong feeling among people, both readers and within the industry.''</p>
        <p>Contemplating the same kind of penalty, another staff member from the group reached another conclusion, one echoed by many journalists.</p>
        <p>''If they close the Southern Daily it wouldn't matter,'' he said. ''The newspaper's example has already been absorbed by journalists all over China, and their goal is not just to copy it, but to do even better.''</p>
        <p>That kind of spirit is not driven by journalistic idealism alone, but also by intense commercial competition among Chinese newspapers, the vast majority of which, though officially state-owned, no longer receive subsidies.</p>
        <p>An editor from Southern Metropolitan Daily who met with a foreigner in a cafe after work said his staff was under immense stress because of the trials. He still managed to be philosophical about the Chinese press, whose continued growth and improvement he called unstoppable.</p>
        <p>''All Chinese media have three functions: mouthpiece for the government and party, to support themselves by making money and, thirdly, to give journalists a means to influence society,'' he said. ''The three goals are irreconcilable, and if you go too far in any one direction, the result is trouble. We are all learning there is a bottom line somewhere, and although nobody wants to be punished, no one knows where it lies exactly.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
