<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUILDING ON THE ARTS: A special report.; Cities Are Fostering the Arts As a Way to Save Downtown</title>
    <meta content="18DOWN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="973998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Palm Beach (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cleveland (Ohio)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Escondido (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Americans for the Arts</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio/Cleveland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Palm Beach</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E4DB1E38F93BA25752C1A961958260" item-length="3324" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUILDING ON THE ARTS: A special report.; Cities Are Fostering the Arts As a Way to Save Downtown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <dateline>SAN JOSE, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special report, Building on the Arts, finds cities that have long followed modish urban development trends are shifting to development of downtown arts centers as recipe for revilatization; are trying to attract tourists, burnish regional reputations and stimulate blighted neighborhoods by creating arts districts, financing arts festivals and promoting regularly sheduled cultural events; most dramatic municipal ventures involve buildings, particularly rash of ambitious theater/exhibition/performance complexes constructed nationwide in last decade as local governments follow lead of private foundations; Americans for the Arts reports local government support to arts groups in nation's 50 largest cities has increased average of 4.7 percent annually since 1991; arts projects in West Palm Beach, Cleveland and Escondido (Calif) described; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this city in the heart of Silicon Valley, where the rise in property values (and taxes) over the last decade has fueled a mammoth redevelopment effort, the city government has built from scratch, among other things, a children's museum, a new wing for the art museum, and, opening next month, a 525-seat theater that will be the new home of the San Jose Repertory Theater. All in a downtown that was, a dozen years ago, in the words of one city official, ''a wasteland, chaos everywhere you looked.''</p>
        <p>Under construction in the same general neighborhood is a technology museum, a community paean to the industry that has spurred the city's resurgence. The building is scheduled to open next fall, and the cost, $43 million, is being covered by the city. Another city-financed project, the $9.1 million Mexican Cultural Heritage Gardens, with performance space for local dance and drama troupes, is to open in 1999 in another rundown district.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In this city in the heart of Silicon Valley, where the rise in property values (and taxes) over the last decade has fueled a mammoth redevelopment effort, the city government has built from scratch, among other things, a children's museum, a new wing for the art museum, and, opening next month, a 525-seat theater that will be the new home of the San Jose Repertory Theater. All in a downtown that was, a dozen years ago, in the words of one city official, ''a wasteland, chaos everywhere you looked.''</p>
        <p>Under construction in the same general neighborhood is a technology museum, a community paean to the industry that has spurred the city's resurgence. The building is scheduled to open next fall, and the cost, $43 million, is being covered by the city. Another city-financed project, the $9.1 million Mexican Cultural Heritage Gardens, with performance space for local dance and drama troupes, is to open in 1999 in another rundown district.</p>
        <p>''We want our downtown to have the support of future generations,'' said Frank Taylor, since 1979 the executive director of the redevelopment agency. ''We lost an entire generation of children, who grew up ashamed of their downtown. There is no better way to get children acquainted with a city than through cultural facilities, through art, through music, those experiences they can share. So that's been our approach.''</p>
        <p>In a report titled ''American Canvas,'' the National Endowment of the Arts recently described the arts in  the United States as being vastly undersupported, and the Federal Government continues to debate withdrawing from its already modest role as bolsterer of the nation's creative artists. But it is one measure of the complexity of the role of the arts in this country that San Jose is voting another way, aggressively using the arts to fuel its growth.</p>
        <p>And though this city's investment in the arts is extraordinary, it is hardly unique. From Anchorage to Fort Lauderdale, Fla., cities have recently built or are in the midst of building arts palaces.</p>
        <p>One of the most visible examples of big arts dollars being pressed into the service of local uplift is Newark, where the new $180 million New Jersey Center for the Performing Arts opened on Oct. 18 to considerable fanfare and great hope that it will turn the fortunes of a downtown area stagnant since the 1960's; more than $100 million of the cost came from the state. In September, just an hour's drive north of here, the historic War Memorial Opera House in San Francisco reopened after a refurbishment costing nearly $90 million,  more than half of which was financed by a city bond issue. The same month, Kansas City opened the first American museum devoted entirely to jazz, paid for by the city. And earlier this year, Chicago announced its $18.8 million contribution to a new building for the Goodman Theater, a prominent nonprofit venue.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia is in the midst of a $330 million project, the Avenue of the Arts. And Miami awaits ground-breaking on a mammoth performance center that would provide a home for its symphony and its opera.</p>
        <p>''You could easily say there has been $4 billion to $5 billion in arts capital building in the last decade alone,'' said Steve Wolff, the president of AMS Planning and Research, a consulting concern in Fairfield, Conn., that specializes in capital building projects in the arts. ''I can add up the first $3 billion in 30 seconds without even thinking.''</p>
        <p>Beyond the big-ticket building projects are myriad other efforts in which cities have imposed designated taxes on hotel rooms and amusements, offered incentives to developers and aggressively leveraged property tax revenue to raise money. They have created arts districts, financed arts festivals and promoted regularly scheduled cultural events. Often they have invested large  amounts of public money in museums, concert halls and theaters to create tourist destinations, burnish regional reputations and stimulate blighted neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>White Elephants? Hard Lessons From the Past</p>
        <p>Cities have long been known for following the modish urban redevelopment concept of the day, only to find their tomorrows beset by the flaws in those ideas. Urban renewal left vast empty tracts. New highways wound up speeding the flow out of cities rather than traffic into them. Downtown office development bred design sterility and nighttime ghost towns. Whether reliance on the arts will have a similar legacy in many locales is an open question.</p>
        <p>Many fear that without solid indigenous programming, an interested audience to build on, and links between the projects and the fabric of the city, the grandest of the arts projects can turn into white elephants. Indeed, since Lincoln Center opened in New York City in 1962, more than one city intent on replicating its success has built an arts complex that remains underused and cut off from the city.</p>
        <p>''We have a tendency in America, if we have a success in one place, we want to replicate it,'' said James W. Hughes, dean of the Edward Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy at Rutgers University. ''But there is no panacea. Arts centers are not necessarily sufficient in and of themselves to cause revitalization.''</p>
        <p>Such projects can also raise political issues that can be dangerously volatile. Is it right to spend taxpayer money on a risky capital venture that many citizens may see as elitist when hospitals, schools and roads also cry out for attention?</p>
        <p>Supporters of the new initiatives maintain that they apply lessons learned from both the successes and failures of the past.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if it's that people are becoming more sophisticated,'' Mr. Wolff said. But in many cities, he said, arts groups have led the effort to weave a new center into the fabric of the city. It was the arts people, he noted, for example, who initiated an elaborate sign system to help visitors find their way through downtown Newark.</p>
        <p>In any case, the presumption that art is good for everybody seems to be carrying the day.</p>
        <p>A Solution Local Governments Into the Breach</p>
        <p>Congress has cut Federal financing for the National Endowment for the Arts from $176 million in 1992 to just under $100 million today, raising questions about the survival of many theater, dance and performance troupes. Still, a survey of the involvement of municipalities presents an optimistic picture of support for the  arts.</p>
        <p>According to figures compiled by Americans for the Arts, which serves as a kind of trade association for community arts groups, local government support to groups in the nation's 50 largest cities has increased an average of 4.7 percent annually since 1991. That does not take into account much of the spending of local governments on things like independent festivals and new buildings.</p>
        <p>Providence, R.I., pushed a law through the state legislature that gives artists who move to a designated downtown district an exemption from state income tax sales of their work; landlords in the district who convert commercial space to living space get breaks on property taxes.</p>
        <p>In Tucson, Ariz., a partnership of  the city, artists and building owners has created a ''phantom gallery,'' placing artworks in unoccupied storefronts downtown while the owners seek tenants. Rock Island, Ill., has made a modest $600,000 arts center and a riverboat gambling casino on the Mississippi the twin cornerstones of an arts and entertainment district that has witnessed an influx of restaurants, nightclubs, design firms and galleries.</p>
        <p>''Almost every community in this country is using the arts in some way as a part of revitalization,'' said Hilary Frost-Kumpf, who is writing a book about municipal cultural districts for the Americans for the Arts coalition. There are 55 to 60 officially designated cultural districts in cities across the country, and in many of them, ''people are coming downtown again,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The most dramatic municipal ventures involve buildings, particularly the rash of ambitious theater/exhibition/performance complexes that  have been constructed all over in the last decade as local governments  followed the lead of private foundations in places like Cleveland.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, three downtown theaters in Cleveland were refurbished into Playhouse Square, a performing arts center that brought about a renaissance just when the city was financially desperate. In Pittsburgh, during similarly lean times, the old Stanley Theater was expanded into the Benedum Center, home to the opera and the ballet: since opening in 1987, it has become the building block of an expanding arts district.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, cities as small as West Palm Beach, Fla., and Escondido, Calif., a San Diego suburb, have invested millions in arts centers. Charleston, W. Va., with less than 100,000 people, has an $80 million project, a combination concert hall, arts museum, interactive science museum and planetarium, scheduled to begin construction in the spring; the state has contributed $22 million, and the city has pledged $5.5 million, with corporations, grants and private donors also contributing.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia's ongoing $330 million Avenue of the Arts project, which would line Broad Street with cultural sites anchored by a $200 million performing arts center that is still a twinkle in Mayor Ed Rendell's eye, includes $100 million in support from the state and the city.</p>
        <p>Miami is certainly going through hard times now, the World Series notwithstanding. Its coffers are low  and its municipal government has been buffeted by a massive corruption scandal. But that has not extinguished hope for the future, based in large part on the arts. Optimism endures even though a plan to build two performance halls totaling 4,700 seats on a seedy tract just north of downtown is now well over budget and the city is seeking $48 million in private money to start the project.</p>
        <p>''We have aspirations to be one of the great cities of the 21st century,'' said Michael Spring, director of the Metro-Dade Cultural Affairs Council. ''Our civic leaders believe that great cities have great buildings. This will be the jewel in our crown.''</p>
        <p>Chicago considered and rejected the construction of a new arts center. But it has the Goodman, and it is working with a variety of entertainment giants -- Disney, Livent of Toronto and Fox Theatricals -- to refurbish other theaters in a part of the city that is now dark and dangerous at night. By the year 2000, there could be 15,000 seats to fill for performances in a radius of just a few blocks -- an American theater district second only to Broadway.</p>
        <p>''The downtown already had most of the museums,'' said Lois Weisberg, the city's cultural affairs commissioner. ''It had most of the interesting architecture that people come here to see. I would say Chicago is pinning its hopes on cultural institutions to redevelop downtown.''</p>
        <p>The historical model for these efforts is Lincoln Center, which broke ground in 1959 in what was then a benighted neighborhood and is now the anchor of Manhattan's thriving Upper West Side. But the transformation took decades, a luxury of waiting that many cities may not be able to afford.</p>
        <p>''We always felt that in a city like Miami, which is already made out of many pieces, it was very risky to bet on the success of a facility in an isolated area,'' said Jean-Francois Lejeune, a professor at the University of Miami's school of architecture. ''In the case of Lincoln Center, it took a long time, maybe 20 years. We are afraid it may be the same for Miami.''</p>
        <p>The other, and in some ways larger, question is whether such an entity  is suited to the local arts marketplace. An arts center in a small city, like a Wal-Mart on the outskirts of town, can siphon attention and audiences from the arts groups already operating. And to sustain a major arts venue in a place where none existed before, the habit of attendance has to be nurtured in the potential audience. Lincoln Center, after all, not only had New York, with its built-in demand for the arts, it had world-class performing organizations -- the Metropolitan Opera and the New York Philharmonic -- as original tenants.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't an economic development project, it was an artistic project with development overtones,'' said Nathan Leventhal, the president of Lincoln Center. Although this might be disputed by the urban planners who once derided the project as gussied-up slum clearance that uprooted a viable neighborhood, its artistic potential wouldn't be disputed by anyone. The problem faced by many of these new centers elsewhere, Mr. Leventhal said, is ''what they call product.''</p>
        <p>''What do they actually put in these buildings?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>A Textbook Case From Arts Showplace To Bar Mitzvah Venue</p>
        <p>Perhaps nowhere have these issues been more evident than in Escondido, a city of 125,000, which spent $81 million in public money to build the California Center for the Arts. The center -- which includes a 1,500-seat concert hall, a 400-seat theater, a contemporary art museum and a conference center on a 12-acre greensward across the street from a struggling mall -- is a beautiful campus, but it does seem a bit overwhelming in what is fundamentally a bedroom community with empty storefronts downtown.</p>
        <p>It opened in 1994 with a hugely ambitious program that was meant to lure audiences and performers north from San Diego (though the larger hall is too small for sizable Broadway productions and big-draw concert performers). It was also hoped that, in combination with the nearby San Diego Wild Animal Park, the arts center would help establish Escondido as a destination all of its own, even though there is not a single hotel downtown.</p>
        <p>The operating budget was $3.5 million, but the center spent more than $8 million its first year. Corporate and private donations declined after the hoopla of the grand opening. All of this forced the city to triple its annual support, from $500,000 to $1.5 million, and bring in a new director, Robert A. Freedman, who cut staff and all department budgets by 20 percent. The city's Mayor faced an unexpectedly close re-election campaign, as a result, many felt, of his big project.</p>
        <p>Since then Mr. Freedman has had to cut back on the center's ambitions by allotting more events to independent promoters, essentially renting the place out, and to find other revenue-producing uses for the buildings. The campus is a frequent site of photo shoots and, increasingly, television and film sets, and the conference center is booking bar mitzvahs and weddings.</p>
        <p>The center's programming is sprinkled with the kinds of pop performers not ordinarily thought to be regulars on the arts circuit. Country and New Age music increasingly joust with classical performers for room on the marquee.</p>
        <p>''In a community like this there's always a balancing act,'' Mr. Freedman said. ''We have a lot of trailer parks here. Do you bring in Yo-Yo Ma for the people who write the checks? Or do you bring in Johnny Cash for the people who might want to see something else? Yo-Yo Ma sold out. Johnny Cash sold out. John Tesh sold out.''</p>
        <p>After losses totaling $1.5 million two years ago, the center had a deficit of just $76,000 last year and is expected to break even for the 1997-98 season. ''We may not be drawing for every show, '' Mr. Freedman said. ''But we're finding out who our audience is. And it feels good.''</p>
        <p>Success Story How a City Was Reborn</p>
        <p>Escondido seems to have discovered what San Jose foresaw -- that, in the words of David Resnicow, a museum consultant in New York who has worked with many city planners around the country, ''the big issue is whether a city government makes arts building a part of a broader strategy, woven into the city's infrastructure, or whether it's supposed to be a quick fix.''</p>
        <p>San Jose, with a population of 850,000, was once the small, thriving capital of the agricultural region below San Francisco. But it began losing its center in the 1950's, when City Hall and the newspaper, The San Jose Mercury News, moved from downtown and a new mall drained away shoppers. Over the next three decades, downtown went to seed as the population grew on the outskirts.</p>
        <p>''The city we're replacing was a city of 50,000 to 75,000,'' said Mr. Taylor, the redevelopment director, ''a city that existed from 1900-1950. It was just a nice place. You went downtown, the doctor was there, the dentist was there. You bought a hat; you got a key made; you went home.''</p>
        <p>It was in 1976 that San Jose built its performing arts center downtown as a home for the San Jose Symphony. Though the center thrived on its own, it never catalyzed the kind of  renaissance that places like Newark and Escondido are hoping for.</p>
        <p>''When people used that one lonely cultural facility, they came into town and left right afterwards,'' said Carol Beddo, an assistant to Mr. Taylor who grew up in San Jose.</p>
        <p>But today, a half-dozen major arts sites are within walking distance of one another downtown, all built with the 2 percent of the budget that goes to public art. An arts district on South First Street (nicknamed SoFa) is beginning to bloom, with coffeehouses, music clubs, galleries and movie houses.</p>
        <p>Members of the arts community are delighted by the city's rebirth. But more notable is their sense of being included -- ''We're all trying to make this a barn-raising mentality,'' said Peter B. Giles, the president of the new technology museum.</p>
        <p>It is a place where the glass indisputably seems half full. ''The city gave us the land, and they gave us $20 million,'' said Timothy Near, the artistic director of the San Jose Repertory Theater, which is about to move into its first permanent home since its inception in 1980. ''They said, we want this, but you are the professionals, so we had a lot of input into making this building. For a city to put this much support behind a theater company, it's an extraordinary expression of its desire to have a cultural heart.''</p>
        <p>Granted, San Jose's resurgence has required a windfall; the bustle of Silicon Valley has provided property-tax income that the city has leveraged in the bond market to the tune of more than $1 billion over the last dozen years. The money financed a  strategy of knitting arts building to other civic concerns like creating parks, building a light-rail system, a convention center and an arena  (which brought a professional hockey franchise, the San Jose Sharks, to town) and luring corporations like Adobe Systems, which established its headquarters downtown last year.</p>
        <p>''You can redevelop without cultural institutions,'' Mr. Taylor said, ''but it's not going to be a happy city, a city you'll feel proud about.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
