<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EMPLOYEE LAYOFFS IN NEW YORK AREA DISRUPT ECONOMIES</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="509941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAYOFFS (LABOR)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL MOTORS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN TELEPHONE &amp; TELEGRAPH CO INC (AT&amp;T)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS MACHINES CORP (IBM)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARTLETT, SARAH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DE133BF935A15751C0A964958260" item-length="1864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EMPLOYEE LAYOFFS IN NEW YORK AREA DISRUPT ECONOMIES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH BARTLETT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARTLETT, SARAH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With companies from General Motors to United Technologies announcing plans to shrink their work forces, the New York City region faces the prospect of at least 40,000 employees losing their jobs during the next few years, primarily in manufacturing, transportation and government. And those are just the layoffs that have been publicly announced.</p>
        <p>Coming on the heels of the more than 500,000 jobs lost in the region since employment peaked in February 1989, this latest round of announcements is certainly not good news. Even before this, the total exceeded the 350,000 jobs lost in the region from late 1973 through 1976, when the area was suffering its worst recession since the 1930's. Heightened Concern</p>
        <p>But there is a new and, in many ways, more disruptive element to the latest round of layoff announcements. Companies are revealing that thousands of people will be laid off but are providing scant details as to when, where or who will be affected. That is creating heightened uncertainty, and causing even those whose jobs are not threatened to cut back their spending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With companies from General Motors to United Technologies announcing plans to shrink their work forces, the New York City region faces the prospect of at least 40,000 employees losing their jobs during the next few years, primarily in manufacturing, transportation and government. And those are just the layoffs that have been publicly announced.</p>
        <p>Coming on the heels of the more than 500,000 jobs lost in the region since employment peaked in February 1989, this latest round of announcements is certainly not good news. Even before this, the total exceeded the 350,000 jobs lost in the region from late 1973 through 1976, when the area was suffering its worst recession since the 1930's. Heightened Concern</p>
        <p>But there is a new and, in many ways, more disruptive element to the latest round of layoff announcements. Companies are revealing that thousands of people will be laid off but are providing scant details as to when, where or who will be affected. That is creating heightened uncertainty, and causing even those whose jobs are not threatened to cut back their spending.</p>
        <p>"If anything, announcements without specified targets and time frames could affect even more people's behavior than normal layoffs," said Nancy R. Lazar, an economist with International Strategy and Investment Group in New York.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to say exactly how many jobs have been earmarked for termination. In general, only large companies laying off at least 500 employees or smaller companies laying off at least 33 percent of their work forces are required to report their plans to state departments of labor. And some companies announce layoff plans and then change their minds.  More Losses Expected</p>
        <p>Still, the announcements already made bring the tally to 35,000, and at least 5,000 more can be expected from companies that have said they will shrink their global work force but have not released details about the New York region.</p>
        <p>Of course, when compared with the half-million jobs that have already been lost, that may sound like a pittance and leave the impression that job losses may be slowing. But the half million are actual job losses, whereas the 40,000 are just announced layoffs that are known to date. Economists say it is too early to conclude that the rate of job losses is finally slowing.</p>
        <p>Connecticut is likely to be hardest hit. From last May through November, Edward J. Deak, an economics professor at Fairfield University, counted 13,307 jobs that had either been lost or were expected to be lost in coming months in his state. That was the highest number since he began monitoring job reductions four years ago. And it was before the state announced it would lay off 2,700 employees, before Electric Boat's announcement of as many as 4,000 layoffs and before United Technologies' decision to lay off 6,400 in the next four years.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, the tally kept by the Department of Labor suggests that more than 5,500 jobs will be lost during the next year or so. That does not include unspecified numbers of New Jersey workers who could lose their jobs as General Motors sheds 74,000 positions nationwide, or as A.T.&amp;T. reduces its national work force by 14,000.</p>
        <p>In New York City, announcements by banks, local and state governments and large companies suggest that 10,000 to 15,000 jobs are already likely to be lost this year.</p>
        <p>On Long Island, layoffs are expected to exceed 9,000 because of reductions by Nassau County, school boards and some unspecified cuts by the Grumman Corporation, a large military contractor.</p>
        <p>Even Wstchester County, which has been relatively immune from layoffs, will suffer. Monday's announcement that G.M. intends to close its plant in North Tarrytown, resulting in 3,500 layoffs by 1995, comes on top of I.B.M.'s planned reduction of 20,000 worldwide. At least some of those reductions are likely in Westchester, where 12,000 work for the company. However, since I.B.M. is offering early retirements rather than laying people off, the effects are likely to be gentler.</p>
        <p>Although 40,000 layoffs may sound like a lot, in the context of a regional work force of eight million, it is not quite so daunting. Also, economists caution that job losses should not be considered in isolation: jobs are created as new companies are formed and those in existence expand.</p>
        <p>Matthew P. Drennan, a professor of economics at Cornell University, is one who is not especially alarmed by the latest announcements. He sees nothing to cause him to revise his semiannual forecast, issued in January, of a net decline of 48,000 jobs in the region this year, compared with 258,000 lost in 1991. Tracking Fallout From the Shock</p>
        <p>However, other economists worry that the recent announcements will intensify economic distress. Many say the layoffs will trigger job losses at other companies that supply those reducing in size. And the next round of layoffs will occur when it is already increasingly difficult for those out of work to find jobs.</p>
        <p>Moreover, to the extent that these job losses are not spread evenly but are concentrated in pockets like Hartford or Groton, Conn., the psychological and economic fallout can be tremendous.</p>
        <p>The layoff announcements did, for instance, cause Mr. Deak to change his forecast. Until recently, he thought there was a 50 percent chance that the state's job slide would end in the third quarter. He has since revised that to a less than 50 percent chance that it will end this year.</p>
        <p>Economic forecasting has never been an exact science. But what makes this recession particularly difficult to fathom is the way that layoffs are taking place. In the "good old days," a company would announce layoffs and within days or weeks, the employees involved would be notified and then removed from their positions.</p>
        <p>In today's age of reorganizations and downsizings, companies are just as likely to announce that they intend to shed 10 to 20 percent of their work force, but provide almost no details about when or where the cuts will take place.</p>
        <p>"There's a sense of paralysis that it leaves with people, even those not directly affected," said Stephen Ristau, senior vice president of Family Services Association in Southern New London County, which works with employees at companies undergoing reorganizations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ristau said that the trauma of not knowing whether an employee is next in line to lose his or her job has increased job stress, drug and alcohol abuse and family violence. He said it has also created a sharp reduction in spending, which is likely to worsen the economic impact of the job losses.  "Even those with relatively stable incomes are becoming more conservative in their spending habits," he said.  How Insecurity Hurts Economies</p>
        <p>Consider the reaction of Bob Goldberg, a 28-year-old systems programmer who works for Aetna Life and Casualty Company in Middletown, Conn. In the fall of 1990 the company announced that it would reduce its work force by 2,600, a target it has more or less achieved. Mr. Goldberg is still employed and has no reason to think that his job is in immediate jeopardy. But he is still driving his '85 Chevrolet, even though it has 115,000 miles on it and he would like a new car. This year he drove instead of flew to Florida for his annual vacation and stayed with friends instead of in a hotel.</p>
        <p>"There's just no security any more, working for somebody else," he said.</p>
        <p>Cheryl Garber, a probation officer for Nassau County, is also anxiously trying to conserve her savings. Last year she moved in with her parents in Jericho to save money for a down payment on a house. But when the county recently laid off 98 people in her department, she gave up hope of buying a house and is now just concentrating on saving money. Since the county's layoffs are based on seniority, eliminating those whose employment began after January 1984, and since Ms. Garber was hired in October 1983, she is convinced that she will not survive another round of cuts.</p>
        <p>"I live in a state of constant anxiety," she said. "I don't sleep much and I certainly don't spend any more money than I have to." She said she no longer eats lunch with friends or drives to visit friends and relatives on weekends.</p>
        <p>As people like Mr. Goldberg and Ms. Garber pull back, it is likely to depress local economies. The repercussions are already evident in southern Connecticut. When asked about the impact of the announcements, Robert Jones, the owner of a recreational vehicle dealership in East Lyme, Conn., said, "See for yourself," and waved his hand at a showroom empty of people. "I called one woman today who was supposed to be buying an R.V. and she said she wants to wait and see if her husband has a job," he said.</p>
        <p>It is not an easy time to be a real-estate broker in Connecticut either. Nick Palmerone, a partner in the Hedden Real Estate Agency in Groton, said that business had finally started to improve after the first of the year, after mortgage rates fell to levels not seen for 20 years. "Things started to look up," he said. "Then, the day after the Seawolf announcement, I kept picking up the phone to see if it was working." Seawolf is the submarine program that the Bush Administration said it would eliminate.</p>
        <p>City and state officials are also trying to brace themselves against the impact of these rolling layoffs. After United Technologies announced its intention to lay off workers, fears grew in Stratford that a number of those layoffs might be at the company's Sikorsky subsidiary, which makes helicopters. The town receives almost 12 percent of its property taxes from the company and its employees, as well as financial support for community activities and job training.</p>
        <p>"The saying in town is, 'If Sikorsky sneezes the entire town catches pneumonia,' " said Joseph Stavola, the town's director of community and economic development, who has since retired.  The Worst Fear: The Best May Leave</p>
        <p>The worst fear of many local officials is that people will feel compelled to move out of the area. In the last two years, Connecticut has seen its population level off at 3.3 million, after growing by 20,000 a year from 1985 to 1989. Mr. Deak said he thought that 26,000 state residents would leave in each of the next two years. The danger is that those who leave will be those with job skills and the most promising employment opportunities, while those left behind will contribute the least to the tax base.</p>
        <p>Another alternative, one that would be better for the region, would be if adversity were to unleash a burst of entrepreneurship. Mr. Goldberg, for instance, was inspired by the job insecurity he sensed at his company to try to set up a recruiting business on the side with a friend, Duane Dubuque, who works at the troubled Ames Department Stores and also feels his employment future is uncertain.</p>
        <p>If enough people respond as Mr. Goldberg and Mr. Dubuque have, that could provide some vitality to the region. "There's a tradition of entrepreneurialism in this area," said Mr. Deak, the Fairfield University economist. "The question is whether enough people do it, and if enough of those people are successful."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
