<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HIGH COURT DEFINES NEW LIMIT ON FORCE BY A PRISON GUARD</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="509946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRISONS AND PRISONERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSTITUTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EIGHTH AMENDMENT (US CONSTITUTION)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSAULTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRUTALITY AND HARASSMENT CHARGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GUARDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOUISIANA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUDSON, KEITH J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCALIA, ANTONIN (ASSOC JUSTICE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, SANDRA DAY (ASSOC JUSTICE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, CLARENCE (ASSOC JUSTICE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutional Amendments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DB103BF935A15751C0A964958260" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HIGH COURT DEFINES NEW LIMIT ON FORCE BY A PRISON GUARD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an important decision on prisoners' rights, the Supreme Court ruled today that a beating or other use of excessive force by a prison guard may violate the Constitution even if it does not result in a serious injury to the prisoner.</p>
        <p>The vote was 7 to 2, with a majority opinion by Justice Sandra Day O'Connor and a dissenting opinion by Justice Clarence Thomas, who said that the Eighth Amendment's prohibition against cruel and unusual punishment "is not, and should not be turned into, a national code of prison regulation." Justice Antonin Scalia signed Justice Thomas's dissent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an important decision on prisoners' rights, the Supreme Court ruled today that a beating or other use of excessive force by a prison guard may violate the Constitution even if it does not result in a serious injury to the prisoner.</p>
        <p>The vote was 7 to 2, with a majority opinion by Justice Sandra Day O'Connor and a dissenting opinion by Justice Clarence Thomas, who said that the Eighth Amendment's prohibition against cruel and unusual punishment "is not, and should not be turned into, a national code of prison regulation." Justice Antonin Scalia signed Justice Thomas's dissent.</p>
        <p>The decision overturned a ruling by a Federal appeals court that the use of force against a prison inmate violates the Eighth Amendment only if it results in "significant injury."  Administration's Position</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration joined prisoners' rights groups in urging the Justices to overturn the 1990 ruling. It was appealed to the Supreme Court without legal assistance by a Louisiana prison inmate who had been beaten and punched by two prison guards while he was handcuffed and shackled. Because the inmate's injuries, which included bruises, swelling and loosened teeth, did not require medical attention, the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit, in New Orleans, overturned a decision by a Federal magistrate awarding him $800 in damages.</p>
        <p>In rejecting the Fifth Circuit's "significant injury" requirement, Justice O'Connor said: "When prison officials maliciously and sadistically use force to cause harm, contemporary standards of decency always are violated. This is true whether or not significant injury is evident." Malice Issue in Dispute</p>
        <p>Justice O'Connor's opinion was joined by Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and by Justices Byron R. White, Anthony M. Kennedy and David H. Souter. Justices John Paul Stevens and Harry A. Blackmun concurred in separate opinions.</p>
        <p>While the latter two Justices endorsed Justice O'Connor's treatment of the "significant injury" question, they objected to another portion of her opinion, which held that the use of excessive force against prison inmates violates the Eighth Amendment only when prison officials have acted "maliciously and sadistically for the very purpose of causing harm."</p>
        <p>The Court had previously applied this standard only to evaluate the force used to put down a prison riot, a circumstance in which the Court has given prison officials a high degree of deference. Requiring evidence that officials acted "maliciously and sadistically" even in less extreme conditions places a heavy legal burden on inmates. But Justice O'Connor found that the inmate in this case, Keith J. Hudson, had met this rigorous standard.</p>
        <p>Justice Thomas's dissenting opinion provided the clearest road map so far to the new Justice's approach to constitutional interpretation. He placed heavy emphasis on the history of the Eighth Amendment, which until modern times was interpreted as applying only to the nature of sentences and other official "punishments," and not to conditions within a prison.</p>
        <p>In 1976, in a case involving medical care in a Texas prison, the Supreme Court first applied the Eighth Amendment to prison conditions beyond the actual sentence. Referring to that decision and to several decisions that flowed from it as having "cut the Eighth Amendment loose from its historical moorings," Justice Thomas strongly implied, without saying so directly, that these precedents should be overruled.</p>
        <p>"Today's expansion of the cruel and unusual punishment clause beyond all bounds of history and precedent is, I suspect, yet another manifestation of the pervasive view that the Federal Constitution must address all ills in our society," Justice Thomas said. He added that while abuse by prison guards is "deplorable" or perhaps "criminal," it does not violate the Eighth Amendment unless it causes "significant harm."</p>
        <p>In her majority opinion, Hudson v. McMillian, No. 90-6531, Justice O'Connor responded at length to Justice Thomas's dissent, which she said "ignores the body of our Eighth Amendment jurisprudence." She seemed to accuse Justice Thomas of being insensitive, a charge he sought at length to dispel in the weeklong confirmation hearings last year before the Senate Judiciary Committee. In particular, she objected to Justice Thomas's assertion that prisoners presenting claims of excessive force should have to clear the high legal hurdles that the Court has required of prisoners bringing Eighth Amendment challenges to general conditions of confinement.</p>
        <p>"To deny, as the dissent does, the difference between punching a prisoner in the face and serving him unappetizing food is to ignore the concepts of dignity, civilized standards, humanity, and decency that animate the Eighth Amendment," Justice O'Connor said.</p>
        <p>During the confirmation hearing, Justice Thomas sought to reassure his Democratic critics of his compassion when Senator Herb Kohl of Wisconsin asked him why he wanted to serve on the Court. The nominee, then a Federal appeals court judge, replied that he believed he could "bring something different to the Court," an understanding of how the Court's decisions affect the underprivileged.</p>
        <p>Almost every day, he told the Senators, he looked out the window of his appeals court office to watch the busloads of prisoners being driven away. "I say to myself almost every day, 'But for the grace of God, there go I,' " he said. "You feel you have the same fate, or could have, as those individuals. So I can walk in their shoes and I could bring something different to the Court."</p>
        <p>The dissenting opinion today also highlights the close alliance that has developed between Justice Thomas and Justice Scalia. One of Justice Thomas's first acts was to hire a young lawyer who had had been a clerk for Justice Scalia in the Court's last term. His dissenting opinion today reflected views on constitutional interpretation, in general, and the Eighth Amendment, in particular, that Justice Scalia has expressed in the past.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
