<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Historical Society Reshaping Itself for Survival</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="202700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCGILL, DOUGLAS C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEBS, BARBARA KNOWLES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D71531F933A05752C1A96E948260" item-length="1421" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Historical Society Reshaping Itself for Survival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS C. McGILL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCGILL, DOUGLAS C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A revitalized board of trustees of the New-York Historical Society has begun taking steps in recent weeks to bring back the troubled institution from the brink of bankruptcy and to insure its future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A revitalized board of trustees of the New-York Historical Society has begun taking steps in recent weeks to bring back the troubled institution from the brink of bankruptcy and to insure its future.</p>
        <p>A revitalized board of trustees of the New-York Historical Society has begun taking steps in recent weeks to bring back the troubled institution from the brink of bankruptcy and to insure its future.</p>
        <p>''It's a major overhaul for a major institution,'' said Barbara K. Debs, the interim director of the 184-year-old society on Central Park West, which operates the state's oldest museum. ''It has a major collection that has important things to say to our collective history. It needs to take its rightful place in the city, the state and the country.''</p>
        <p>Thus far, the trustees have raised $1 million among themselves, to help erase the society's projected deficit of $2 million this year. They intend to raise the remaining money by the end of their fiscal year in June. They have also raised an additional $30,000 to reopen the museum on Sundays, which they hope to do in January.</p>
        <p>The museum's leaky roof, a major problem and danger to its collection of rare manuscripts and works of art, is also within sight of repair after $400,000 was donated at a successful fund-raiser on Halloween night to honor the former Federal Reserve Board chairman Paul A. Volcker. It was a rare evening for an organization that in the past had admitted running itself like a private club and that eschewed such public methods of raising funds to meet its needs. New Master Plan for Growth</p>
        <p>Perhaps most significantly, the society's officials report that trustees, administration and staff are working together to create a new master plan for the growth and operation of the museum.</p>
        <p>The society's financial woes are far from over. Its yearly operating costs are around $4 million and no predictable streams of revenue have yet been devised to cover those costs. Moreover, $1.2 million of this year's deficit remains to be covered. Yet staff members, many of whom were despairing a few months ago, now see signs of hope.</p>
        <p>''All these years can't be turned around in a few months,'' said Holly Hotchner, the director of the society's painting conservation department. ''But every correct step that can be taken, at this point, is being taken. Every hard question is being asked, to address every hard problem of this museum.''</p>
        <p>The society's present troubles, which have been growing for years, erupted this summer into a crisis that brought a mass dismissal of employees, a closing of some gallery space, and revelations of substandard storage conditions for a significant portion of its art collection. Potential Bankruptcy</p>
        <p>Last January, after many years of using money from the society's endowment to pay for yearly operating deficits, the trustees determined that the endowment had dwindled to the point where the institution would be bankrupt in 18 months.</p>
        <p>In June, the trustees moved to cut expenses by ending Sunday visiting hours, closing two of the museum's four floors of galleries and dismissing nearly a fourth of its 106-member staff.</p>
        <p>In July, after disclosures in The New York Times that hundreds of paintings and other works of art in the society's collection had seriously deteriorated in storage, the society's former director, James B. Bell, resigned, and his deputy was dismissed. The New York State Attorney General, Robert Abrams, began an investigation of the society's financial and curatorial management that is continuing.</p>
        <p>Pamela Mann, an assistant Attorney General in charge of the investigation, said that the society's financial records had been scrutinized, and that testimony had been taken from some trustees and former employees of the society. The investigation will probably be completed ''in the early part of next year,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In August, the trustees assembled a 12-member advisory committee of prominent businessmen, educators and museum administrators led by John D. Macomber, the former chairman of the Celanese Corporation.</p>
        <p>The committee has advised the trustees to shelve their planned sale of a building and plot of land the society owns on the Upper West Side and to focus instead on two more fundamental tasks - clarifying the society's mission and quickly raising the money needed to wipe out this year's deficit. 'Trustees Responded Very Well'</p>
        <p>''There would be no credibility for this institution if the trustees didn't raise the $2 million, which we think is a lead-pipe cinch,'' Mr. Macomber said in an interview. ''No question about it, the trustees have responded very well.''</p>
        <p>An earlier plan of the trustees to raise $15 million to $20 million by selling paintings from the society's collection was discarded in July after strong protests from many art museum professionals.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Macomber and other members of the advisory committee say that once the society's mission is seriously analyzed and redefined, some sale of works deemed outside that mission might be justified. Among the questions being asked is whether the society should regard works of art and artifacts from outside New York State as within its domain.</p>
        <p>Subcommittees of the advisory group are working on a detailed mission statement, a long-term financial plan for the institution, and ''blocking and tackling'' suggestions to increase the financial heft of the board of trustees and to improve their functioning, Mr. Macomber said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Debs, who was president of Manhattanville College from 1975 to 1985, is credited by staff members and trustees with having providing a much needed jolt of energy to the flagging institution. What Has Happened</p>
        <p>Shortly after assuming her post in early September, Ms. Debs initiated weekly talks with the society's staff, hired a chief financial officer to set strict budgets for each department, hired a specialist in arts fund raising, and began making contact with city and state arts agencies and corporate philanthropists.</p>
        <p>Next month, Ms. Debs said, after the advisory committee has submitted its revised statement of mission to the trustees, she plans to begin to reshape the society's administrative structure to reflect that new mission.</p>
        <p>Changes in administrative, curatorial and financial operations, she said, as well as architectural and real estate plans, are likely to be made in the next few months.</p>
        <p>Last month, Ms. Debs disentangled the society from a lawsuit begun during Mr. Bell's tenure by the photographer Robert Mapplethorpe, who had sought the return of a silver collection that had been lent to the society by Samuel Wagstaff Jr. in 1986. The society returned the silver and Mr. Mapplethorpe, the executor of Mr. Wagstaff's estate, dropped his lawsuit.</p>
        <p>''The society, particularly at this juncture in its history, does not wish to pursue this costly, lengthy and distracting litigation,'' a statement issued by the society said.</p>
        <p>The society is also working with the New York Public Library to determine how to repair several dozen paintings that the library lent to the society in 1944 and that suffered severe deterioration while in storage. The damaged paintings were part of a collection of 244 works, mostly 18th- and 19th-century American and European paintings, which were lent to the society that year. Efforts to Repair Paintings</p>
        <p>Don Anderle, the library's associate director of special collections, said members of the library's staff had visited the storeroom where the paintings were being kept by the society. On the basis of that visit and talks with the society's staff, Mr. Anderle said, the library officials believe that the society is now taking what steps it can, given its resources, to repair the damaged works. Under the loan agreement, the library remains the owner of the paintings, but responsibility for their conservation lies with the society.</p>
        <p>Despite these and other remaining problems, though, the society's administrators and curators point to evidence that its long year of crisis is ending and a new era lies ahead.</p>
        <p>A new group of supporters of the society's painting conservation department has been formed, for instance. And a $300,000 grant from the National Endowment for the Arts to build a new storeroom for paintings, which was returned by Mr. Bell when no matching funds could be found, has been resubmitted to the agency, with some matching funds already raised.</p>
        <p>''It's the difference between night and day,'' Karen Buck, the society's assistant director of development, said of staff morale under the old and new administration. ''I think the jury's still out, whether the society's going to make it. But we now have the best shot that we could possibly have.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
