<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Collapse of Inner-City Families Creates America's New Orphans</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="517482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">URBAN AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACQUIRED IMMUNE DEFICIENCY SYNDROME (AIDS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GROSS, JANE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DB153CF93AA15750C0A964958260" item-length="1753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Collapse of Inner-City Families Creates America's New Orphans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GROSS, JANE</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., March 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marianne Nolte avoids saying "mom" or "dad" in her ninth-grade math class, referring instead to "family" in deference to the many shamefaced children who have been abandoned to other relatives, foster homes or institutions.</p>
        <p>Sylvia Parker knows she will dial multiple wrong numbers when she tries to call a student's home, spending hours if not days retracing the zigzag path these children travel from parent to grandparent to foster home and sometimes back again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marianne Nolte avoids saying "mom" or "dad" in her ninth-grade math class, referring instead to "family" in deference to the many shamefaced children who have been abandoned to other relatives, foster homes or institutions.</p>
        <p>Sylvia Parker knows she will dial multiple wrong numbers when she tries to call a student's home, spending hours if not days retracing the zigzag path these children travel from parent to grandparent to foster home and sometimes back again.</p>
        <p>And Carolyn Ayana has written a song called "Gimme Back My Mama" for her seventh-grade music class, hoping it will open discussion among students who avert their eyes and whisper that everything is fine at home long after their parents are lost to crack or locked in jail, and they are living with grandma, auntie or a stranger.</p>
        <p>These teachers and their students are struggling with a profound social problem, the disintegration of the inner city family, which has taken a terrible toll at Frick Junior High School here. The principal and a school social worker estimate that more than half the 750 youngsters at Frick live with neither a mother nor a father.</p>
        <p>Frick is rare among schools in trying to count how many of its children are without either parent. But experts say high concentrations of these children, America's new orphans, are common in schools in the inner city, where fathers have long been absent and mothers have more recently disappeared into the nether world of crack. In Every City</p>
        <p>"You could use expressions like, 'It's mushrooming' or 'growing exponentially,' but these words aren't strong enough," said Lois G. Forer, a retired judge in Philadelphia and the author of a provocative 1988 article in The Washington Monthly calling for the return of orphanages to help with the problem.  "It's everywhere -- New York, Los Angeles, Chicago, Detroit, you name it."</p>
        <p>The phenomenon of children with no parents is prompting educators to rethink how to run schools that were meant to serve nuclear families. Even more tellingly, it is creating growing support for the idea of bringing back the orphanages of the 19th and early 20th centuries.</p>
        <p>"This is still a high voltage subject," said Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, the New York Democrat, who in 1989 wrote a paper forecasting the explosion of zero-parent families. "You get an awful shock if you go near it, so people avoid it. But custodial institutions are clearly on their way."</p>
        <p>Senator Moynihan added that crack is creating not only orphans but a need for orphanages, in the same way that epidemics of diphtheria, influenza and tuberculosis once did.</p>
        <p>There is some dispute about how best to count these children, who overwhelmingly live in neighborhoods where drugs, AIDS and guns are rampantand the zero-parent family is replacing the single-parent family as the emblem of social distress. Their situations vary, but in all categories the numbers of these new orphans are increasing.</p>
        <p>Some are true zero-parent children, living permanently with relatives, in foster homes or in institutions because their parents are dead, incarcerated or have disappeared. Many more are youngsters who are shuttled from pillar to post, farmed out to a shifting cast of relatives while a drug-abusing or vagabond parent is unable or unwilling to care for them.</p>
        <p>According to the Federal Bureau of the Census, 2.8 million children, or 4.5 percent, of America's 63.8 million children were true zero-parent children in 1980, up from 3.5 percent 10 years before. And the numbers are far worse among black children: In 1980, 10.6 percent of them lived in parentless households, up from 9.4 percent in 1970. The 1990 census data on these children is not yet available. Measuring the Problem</p>
        <p>But some demographers are looking for a more inclusive description for the messy way that families fall apart, a better statistical measure for this new social problem.</p>
        <p>According to the Kids Count Data Book, an annual profile of American children by the Annie E. Casey Foundation and the Center for the Study of Social Policy, nearly 1 of every 10 American children lived in a household headed by someone other than a parent in 1990, up from 6.7 percent in 1970.</p>
        <p>A mother is sometimes present in these homes, but she is often a drug addict or a teen-ager who comes and goes while someone else cares for her children. At a recent conference at the American Enterprise Institute these households were described as "family radicals," using the scientific jargon for unbalanced atoms.</p>
        <p>At Frick Junior High and similar schools in inner-city neighborhoods, the statistics are even more extreme. At least two-thirds of the school's 750 pupils are new orphans.</p>
        <p>Forty percent live in county foster homes. At least half that many are living with grandmothers or aunts. Many more live with a drug-abusing mother one week and a weary relative the next. The principal, Murphy Taylor, said virtually all these children are black. The Hispanic families, he said, almost always remain intact.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor, a first-year principal who is black and a longtime foster parent, decided to learn where his students were living after he found that many of them were routinely out of control: fighting with classmates and shoving or cursing teachers. This behavior, he knew, matched what child development experts see in abandoned youngsters.</p>
        <p>Scarred by years of abuse and neglect, many of these children are angry and disruptive, even after they settle in loving foster homes or with doting grandmothers. They are distrustful of adults, greedy for attention and convinced that they must be worthless or their parents would not have left them. They are unresponsive to threats that their misbehavior will land them in trouble, because things already seem as bad as they can get.</p>
        <p>"People look at these kids and think they're crazy," said Nanette Sanders, the mother of a ninth grader and president of the Parent Teachers Association at Frick, where an average meeting draws a half-dozen parents. "Well, society hasn't dealt them a fair hand. The person who's supposed to have taken care of them didn't. So they develop an attitude. They get hard."</p>
        <p>The teachers at Frick are scornful of foster homes and say that most of them are economic arrangements that do not nurture children. The children with relatives are loved, the teachers say, but often poorly supervised because the grandmothers and aunts are exhausted, afraid to come out at night to attend school events and unwilling to hear bad news about the youngsters. The children who move from house to house have no stability and bear the wounds of repeated rejection.</p>
        <p>The new orphans, particulary those in foster homes, are ashamed and secretive, never volunteering information about who they live with, refusing rides home and not inviting friends to visit.</p>
        <p>"They have a keen awareness of what a family should be like," said Cheryl Vawter, a history teacher. "And they desperately want that."</p>
        <p>Teachers usually have no idea who students live with because the children do not tell, different last names are the norm, and such information is not routinely available or changes so often that school records cannot be kept up to date.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ayana, the music teacher, said she learned that one of her favorite students was living in a foster home only after the girl arrived at school with black-and-blue marks suffered from a beating. The police were then summoned. Mrs. Vawter said she had a similar surprise after a student disappeared from the school. The girl, despite frequent references to her mother and father, had been living in a group foster home and had run away.</p>
        <p>Disciplining these children is tricky. Miss Ayana showed why by citing a typical exchange.</p>
        <p>TEACHER: "All right, Charles, I'm going to call your mother."</p>
        <p>STUDENT: "Go on ahead. I don't have no mother no way."</p>
        <p>When the children are moving from relative to relative, or their telephone has been disconnected, they act up with impunity. "They know you can't get in touch," said Bob Kenney, a social studies teacher. The 'Concentration Effect'</p>
        <p>Schools like Frick have disproportionate numbers of orphans, just as certain neighborhoods wind up overwhelmed by the most disadvantaged people after the others flee. And the results are much the same, said William Julius Wilson, a professor of sociology at the University of Chicago, who coined the phrase "concentration effect" to describe the corrosion of a community when only the most impoverished people remain.</p>
        <p>At Frick, many of the more organized families have fled the chaos by enrolling their children in magnet or parochial schools. "This futher isolates and stigmatizes these youngsters," said Toni Cook, a member of the Oakland Board of Education. "They don't get to mix and mingle with other youngsters for whom the ball has bounced right. They don't get to see how the grass can be greener."</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor, the principal at Frick, is trying to lure the stable families back. He took the 20 most disruptive children from all three grades and moved them to a satellite classroom in a nearby church. The children seem to be doing better with one teacher responsible for them all day. And the main school building is a less threatening place with these disruptive students gone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor has also encouraged more appealing activities for families, including weeky math nights in the computer laboratory so that the adults can learn along with the children. He also hopes to open the gymnasium on nights and weekends so that children from other schools will play alongside Frick's youngsters.</p>
        <p>Across the country, inner city schools are tentatively making changes because of the proliferation of new orphans.</p>
        <p>In some districts health services have relocated to school buildings so that needy children will not have to depend on absent or inattentive parents to take them to a clinic. In many junior high schools, including Frick, students are moving from subject to subject in intact classes to create a sense of family.</p>
        <p>In New York City, the Parents Association handbook is being revised to explain that the term "parent" includes "guardians and persons in parental relationships to children." And in the District of Columbia, the school board is considering residential schools.</p>
        <p>"These kids can't fit into the boxes we've created," Mr. Taylor said. "And it's not their fault. Very dysfunctional children need something significantly different, and it's up to us to figure out what that is."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
