<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Answering The Mail</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="387636"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D7163CF933A0575AC0A966958260" item-length="266" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Answering The Mail</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD GLADSTONE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Q. We have several hardwood floors that are badly scratched in several places. There are black marks where a heavy piece of furniture was moved. Is there any way I can restore the finish in these areas?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Q. We have several hardwood floors that are badly scratched in several places. There are black marks where a heavy piece of furniture was moved. Is there any way I can restore the finish in these areas?</p>
        <p>Q. We have several hardwood floors that are badly scratched in several places. There are black marks where a heavy piece of furniture was moved. Is there any way I can restore the finish in these areas?</p>
        <p>A. Try removing the black marks by wiping with paint thinner, then sanding the scratched areas with N120 sandpaper. If the black comes off, sand again with N220 and then touch up with several coats of the same finish that was originally applied to the floors. If sanding will not remove the black marks, even if you sand down to the wood, chances are the floors will have to be stripped and then refinished. Bleaching may also be required (after stripping and sanding) to remove marks that are in the wood itself.</p>
        <p>Q. The slate roof on my house has been leaking for several years. Several roofers could not find the problem, and so I called one who was supposed to be an expert on slate roofs. He claims the slate itself is porous and must be replaced, that slate has an average life of 30 or 40 years and, since mine is 50 years old, has outlived its life. What do you think?</p>
        <p>A. I do not think that porosity of the slate (even if true) could be the problem. The shingles on any roof, including slate, are not what keeps the water out; it is the heavy black felt paper (tar paper) under the shingles that sheds the water. Your problem could be with the black felt paper under the slate shingles. Most often, such leaks are due to problems with the flashing or with one or more of the valleys. Or it could be one of the seams, such as where the roof meets the chimney or a house wall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
