<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campus Life: Colorado;   After Coors Gift, Arena Renaming Angers Students</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="387873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">COORS BREWING CO</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DF1E31F933A0575AC0A966958260" item-length="406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campus Life: Colorado;   After Coors Gift, Arena Renaming Angers Students</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>BOULDER, Colo.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Student groups that receive money from the student government at the University of Colorado will no longer be allowed to accept support for fund-raisers and other activities from the Coors Brewing Company, student legislators decided last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Student groups that receive money from the student government at the University of Colorado will no longer be allowed to accept support for fund-raisers and other activities from the Coors Brewing Company, student legislators decided last week.</p>
        <p>Student groups that receive money from the student government at the University of Colorado will no longer be allowed to accept support for fund-raisers and other activities from the Coors Brewing Company, student legislators decided last week.</p>
        <p>The action was taken on Thursday in response to a decision made a week earlier by the Board of Regents to change the name of the university's indoor sports arena to the Coors Events Conference Center. The regents acted after the Colorado Foundation, which solicits money from alumni and private companies, received a $5 million donation from the Adolph Coors Foundation, a charitable organization separate from the brewing company.</p>
        <p>Some students are critical of what they see as the Coors company's poor environmental record and the Coors family's support for conservative political causes.</p>
        <p>The student government, in its 17-to-2 vote, demanded that the regents reconsider their decision on the conference center and allow students to speak to the regents on the issue.</p>
        <p>Circulating Petition</p>
        <p>Student leaders were particularly angry because the arena proposal had not been listed in advance on the agenda for the regents meeting.</p>
        <p>A petition is circulating on campus that would put the question of changing the name of the event center to a vote of the student body. But such a referendum would not be binding on the regents.</p>
        <p>Some students see accepting the donation from Coors as a compromise of the student government's environmental stance. ''Coors has one of the worst records in Colorado when it comes to polluting our environment,'' said Eric Kessler, a sophomore from New York City and a member of the the university's Environmental Board, which researches environmental issues for the student government and promotes environmental awareness on campus.</p>
        <p>Students in favor of the name change say corporate financial support is important to the university and should not be denied on the basis of political beliefs.</p>
        <p>''As generous as this contribution is, I don't think we should shove it back in their face,'' said Carl Algermissen, a junior who is president of College Republicans.</p>
        <p>Under the proposal adopted by the student government last week, students will be asked in a referendum in November whether they support banning the sale of Coors beer in the student center and continuing the boycott of Coors sponsorship of student events, such as fund-raisers or concerts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
