<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Blueprint For U.S. Forces</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Op-Ed at 20 Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Is the cold war over? An occasional series" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="387707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON AND MOSCOW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPECIAL SECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMAN, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D91F3CF933A0575AC0A966958260" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Blueprint For U.S. Forces</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Lehman; John Lehman was Secretary of the Navy from 1981 to 1987.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMAN, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The new Defense Secretary, Dick Cheney, has hardly settled in his seat and already the civilian and uniformed sachems of the military tribe are leaping about him with their hair on fire, urging immediate decisions. He should refuse - until he has made his most important choice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The new Defense Secretary, Dick Cheney, has hardly settled in his seat and already the civilian and uniformed sachems of the military tribe are leaping about him with their hair on fire, urging immediate decisions. He should refuse - until he has made his most important choice.</p>
        <p>The new Defense Secretary, Dick Cheney, has hardly settled in his seat and already the civilian and uniformed sachems of the military tribe are leaping about him with their hair on fire, urging immediate decisions. He should refuse - until he has made his most important choice.</p>
        <p>That choice is this: Should we accept a military of roughly the same proportions as today's, but drastically compromised in effectiveness by cuts in operations, maintenance, training and modernization? Or, should we create a fundamentally different military establishment that has fewer but more effective active forces and greatly expanded reserves, which could be quickly mobilized?</p>
        <p>The second alternative won't appear in the bureaucrats' option papers, but it's the only logical choice.</p>
        <p>Two facts argue for a new approach. First, the immediate Soviet threat is much diminished. Mikhail Gorbachev's realism, Soviet economic decline, ethnic strife and the very success of the Reagan military buildup have turned the Soviets away from an unwinnable arms race.</p>
        <p>Is it tactical retreat or strategic change? We don't yet know. For the foreseeable future, however, the Soviets will invade neither the oil producers of the Persian Gulf nor the allies of NATO.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reality, Wetern perception of the Soviet threat, especially in Europe, has dissipated. That leads to the second reality, which is the certainty of deep cuts below current Pentagon plans.</p>
        <p>If the Administration chooses to continue down the road of orthodoxy - the only road the bureaucracy will present as a choice -then we will repeat the peacetime collapse of our military in the 70's, or even the 30's. In the defense industries, competition will disappear, economies of scale will be lost and unit costs will explode. Morale in the armed forces will collapse. A few big-ticket weapons will be canceled, but herds of cripples will be continued. Moreover, since land troops outnumber seamen by 4 to 1, the sea services will suffer disproportionately.</p>
        <p>The alternative, which will horrify the 90,000 defense bureaucrats, is to shift perhaps a third of our force structure from full-time regulars to the ready reserve. This plan would cut overall defense costs by 10 to 15 percent, or $30 billion to $45 billion. The only loss of military capability would be the need for additional weeks or even months to mobilize fully for all-out war.</p>
        <p>To fill the expanded reserves, we must pay reservists more, especially at the lower ranks. Even if we doubled current pay, the average cost of a reserve soldier would still be about one-eighth that of a regular.</p>
        <p>Since the costs of active manpower now eat up about half of the defense budget, the cuts that are almost certainly coming could easily be absorbed without reducing our forces or falling behind in military technology - if this path is chosen.</p>
        <p>We would not have to withdraw forces from Europe or South Korea, and the Navy could still keep its battle groups forward.</p>
        <p>The tradition of this country is the citizen soldier and sailor, not the large, professional standing force. American privateers captured nearly 100 times more British ships in the War of Independence than did the Continental Navy, and the ratio of reservists to regulars in World War II was about 70 to 1. Let us make a virtue of budget necessity and global relaxation, and shift back toward that tradition. (March 26, 1989)  WASHINGTON AND MOSCOW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
