<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind Iraqi's Oratory, Cautious Game Is Seen</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="387913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES FOREIGN SERVICE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SADDAM (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DC1430F933A0575AC0A966958260" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind Iraqi's Oratory, Cautious Game Is Seen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq, Sept. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the city's hotels, officials of President Saddam Hussein's Information Ministry have set out, in several foreign languages, an imposing array of speeches and statements that Mr. Hussein has made since Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the city's hotels, officials of President Saddam Hussein's Information Ministry have set out, in several foreign languages, an imposing array of speeches and statements that Mr. Hussein has made since Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2.</p>
        <p>In the city's hotels, officials of President Saddam Hussein's Information Ministry have set out, in several foreign languages, an imposing array of speeches and statements that Mr. Hussein has made since Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2.</p>
        <p>The themes running through many of them are that Kuwait's annexation is ''eternal and irreversible'' and that Iraq is ready to fight and prevail in a war against the United States.</p>
        <p>Prompted by those statements, and a variety of indications from Kuwait that Mr. Hussein is consolidating his hold, the Bush Administration has tightened military, economic and political pressures on Baghdad and hinted that the crisis may ultimately have to be resolved by war. At the United States Embassy here, diplomats make little secret of their conviction that nothing will budge Mr. Hussein from Kuwait but his military defeat, unless Mr. Hussein unexpectedly loses his position of absolute power.</p>
        <p>Steps to Limit Risks</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in Baghdad, there are people who are not yet convinced that Mr. Hussein is as implacably committed to his course as he has sounded in his diatribes.</p>
        <p>Some oblique hints from senior Iraqi officials have suggested to Western diplomats that Mr. Hussein may have realized that neither Iraq nor his leadership have much chance of winning a war against the United States. Further, the diplomats say, there are signs that Mr. Hussein is taking steps to limit the risks of sliding into a war by accident or by a provocation that would give Washington a reason to strike.</p>
        <p>Those who take this view suffer from the same disadvantage as those who believe that Mr. Hussein cannot be dissuaded from a course that will plunge the region into conflict: None of them have talked with the Iraqi leader directly, at least not since Aug. 2, and they thus rely on their reading of Mr. Hussein's character and record. The Iraqi leader operates in tight secrecy and nobody in the capital in recent days has been able to say whether the President is even in Baghdad, much less to avow that they are privy to his thinking. Decision Not Yet Made?  Still, the view among the diplomats, who include several Western ambassadors, is that Mr. Hussein has probably not yet made a final decision on what to do about Kuwait, and that much depends on matters that may take weeks or months to become clear.</p>
        <p>Among the factors are the impact of the United Nations embargo on Iraq's military effectiveness. The sanctions have cut off badly needed spare military parts. Along with this, there is the possibility of popular discontent over mounting food shortages. Perhaps most important, there is the question of whether the common front mounted against Iraq by the United States and the Soviet Union, along with Western Europe and several important Arab allies, can be maintained.</p>
        <p>Attempting to drive wedges into this alliance is likely to be a major preoccupation of Mr. Hussein in the weeks ahead, the diplomats said.</p>
        <p>When the diplomats speak of moves by Mr. Hussein that suggest a concern not to provoke a war, they cite several things. One was the Foreign Ministry's rapid backing away from a diplomatic note delivered to Western embassies last weekend in which the ministry appeared to be threatening diplomats with execution by hanging if they persisted in giving sanctuary to Western men who have been declared hostages by Mr. Hussein. About 200 men are staying at the American, British and other missions or in diplomatic homes.</p>
        <p>Note Withdrawn After Calls</p>
        <p>After calls to the Foreign Ministry by Joseph C. Wilson 4th, the American charge d'affaires here, asking whether the ministry intended to hang him, the diplomatic note was withdrawn.</p>
        <p>Other recent incidents tend to support a belief that Mr. Hussein might be playing a cautious game behind his oratory. First, there was Baghdad's instruction to the captains of Iraqi ships to comply with orders to submit to inspection by United States naval vessels in the Persian Gulf. The order was given before the United Nations gave its backing to such actions, and was designed, diplomats say, to avoid the risk of a confrontation.</p>
        <p>This week, the Information Ministry took steps to ease tensions created when Mr. Hussein implied last Sunday that Iraq might strike first if its population of 18 million people is ''strangled'' by the embargo. Officials drew reporters' attention to an official Iraqi translation of the statement by the ruling Revolutionary Command Council in which the key paragraph in the speech included a phrase not present in Western translations.</p>
        <p>First-Strike Phrase Omitted</p>
        <p>As translated from Arabic by The Associated Press, whose version was widely used by Western newspapers, the statement did not include the qualifying phrase that appeared to make an Iraqi strike contingent on there being ''some who are directing a bloody strike at the Iraqis'' first. The official Iraqi version read: ''If we feel that the people of Iraq are being strangled and that there are some who are directing a bloody strike at the Iraqis, we will strangle all those who are the cause of such a state of affairs.''</p>
        <p>The diplomats cautioned that they were far from persuaded by such moves that Mr. Hussein was preparing to relent over Kuwait, only that he was intent for now on avoiding war.</p>
        <p>''Saddam is his own worst enemy,'' an envoy said. ''He heads one of the least pleasant regimes in the world, he's offended every single Western sensibility, and he compounds it all by issuing statements that talk about Iraq being ready for war.''</p>
        <p>But the diplomat added, ''Nonetheless, I've come around to thinking that the leadership here is fully conscious of what might take place if war were to occur, and what this would mean personally for Saddam.''  CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
