<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outsider? Insider? A Lawyer Wins as Both</title>
    <meta content="12PROF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1168026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Law</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Ted Wells</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton &amp; Garrison</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Jan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wells, Ted</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFDE173AF931A25752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outsider? Insider? A Lawyer Wins as Both</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Jan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column profiles career of lawyer Ted Wells following his becoming newest partner at Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton &amp; Garrison; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH the nonchalant elegance of Astaire, the lawyer Ted Wells tap dances at the edge of the abyss for his clients -- C.E.O.'s and politicians, mostly. On behalf of a national cabinet secretary he addressed a jury for three days, without notes; on behalf of another, Mr. Wells, after having had his way with the 70 witnesses the federal government had put on the stand, didn't bother putting on any of his own.</p>
        <p>Both times he won acquittals, of course. White-collar litigators, not typically generous with praise unless they're looking in the mirror, invariably speak of Mr. Wells's record -- recently, seven for seven -- as ''staggering,'' his courtroom performances ''magnificent,'' and his standing as one of the ''premier trial lawyers in America.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH the nonchalant elegance of Astaire, the lawyer Ted Wells tap dances at the edge of the abyss for his clients -- C.E.O.'s and politicians, mostly. On behalf of a national cabinet secretary he addressed a jury for three days, without notes; on behalf of another, Mr. Wells, after having had his way with the 70 witnesses the federal government had put on the stand, didn't bother putting on any of his own.</p>
        <p>Both times he won acquittals, of course. White-collar litigators, not typically generous with praise unless they're looking in the mirror, invariably speak of Mr. Wells's record -- recently, seven for seven -- as ''staggering,'' his courtroom performances ''magnificent,'' and his standing as one of the ''premier trial lawyers in America.''</p>
        <p>So why, in conversation the other day, was he being so cautious?</p>
        <p>For just when a topic would take flight, he would bring it back to earth -- deftly, with a toothy smile -- and order it off the record, or retool it with tamped-down language. You could almost see him weighing every remark against the reaction of all the constituencies who may be taking notice, because of his new job.</p>
        <p>''I'm a little nervous,'' said Mr. Wells, on his sixth day at Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton &amp; Garrison, where he is the first outsider in 30 years to be brought in as a partner. He was not only named co-chairman of its 150-lawyer litigation department, but is also expected to revive the luster that dimmed with the passing of its superstar, Arthur L. Liman, in 1997.</p>
        <p>A tale from his activist days in the black students' movement is followed by: ''I don't want people to think there's some rabble-rouser at Paul, Weiss. Don't do that to me!''</p>
        <p>Charming grin, apology, explanation of sorts: ''I try to play at a lot of different levels. I want to do the Microsofts. And my guy is running for president.'' Mr. Wells is campaign treasurer for a friend of more than 20 years, Bill Bradley.</p>
        <p>That layered look is what makes Mr. Wells, 49, so intriguing, this moment such a mix of accolades and agita. In moving from Lowenstein Sandler, his New Jersey firm for 22 years, to Paul, Weiss, an international powerhouse, he can compete for the biggest cases in the country, billing $575 an hour.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Wells, a behind-the-scenes force in New Jersey politics, notably for Representative Donald M. Payne of Newark, has moved to a national stage. He has helped raise nearly $28 million for Mr. Bradley, by wheedling and holding fund-raisers at the Livingston, N.J., home he calls ''my expensive steal,'' where he lives with Nina, his wife of 28 years, who is also a lawyer. Their two children are on leave from college to toil for Mr. Bradley.</p>
        <p>HIS professional ambition and political activism are shaped by his self-awareness as a role model. He is Paul, Weiss's only black partner.</p>
        <p>''My age group is very sensitive to its responsibilities in terms of giving back to the African-American community,'' Mr. Wells said. ''As opposed to black people under 35 who say, 'I'm doing this on my own and I don't want to hear about being black.' ''</p>
        <p>''My litigation practice has ranged from Michael Milken to Floyd Flake to Exxon to the N.A.A.C.P.,'' he continued. ''Mike Espy and Ray Donovan'' -- the former cabinet secretaries -- ''came to me when they were in trouble. Great trial lawyers are not limited to a select group of white males. There's a social value in having African-American lawyers thought of in that ilk, and it's important to break the mold.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wells, who attended Holy Cross on a football scholarship and has a master's in business and a law degree from Harvard, was raised in Washington, on a shoestring by his mother, who worked in a Navy mail room. Ma Wells, as she is known, attends all his Washington cases.</p>
        <p>''She owns the federal courthouse!'' he said. ''She exudes love. My mother just embarrasses mean people into being nice.''</p>
        <p>Something of that compassionate demeanor translates into her son's courtroom style, described as approachable and appealing rather than dazzling and theatrical. To get juries to trust him, he will concede that his clients have made mistakes, and then argue why they still deserve to be acquited.</p>
        <p>''I've said I love juries, and I believe in unconditional love,'' said Mr. Wells, who is 6 foot 3 with an athlete's energy and grace. ''And I'll say, 'I can't just love you when you vote my way -- I have to love you however you vote.' ''</p>
        <p>In other words, making jurors feel guilt-ridden if they find his clients guilty. ''I haven't just won,'' he said. ''I've won and had jurors embrace the client. That's the real goal.''</p>
        <p>Even for trials close to home, Mr. Wells moves into a hotel, getting pumped in a high-end bunker with legal briefs, room service and daily workouts. Next will be the Rihga Royal to prep for the Jan. 24 criminal trial of Dr. Niels Lauersen, a Park Avenue specialist accused of insurance fraud over billing for infertility treatments, which are not covered, as standard gynecological care. ''It's a very difficult case,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I don't turn down cases because the facts are bad,'' said Mr. Wells, who rejected opportunities to be a federal judge or United States attorney -- too staid. He would love to square off against David Boies, who prosecuted the Microsoft case.</p>
        <p>''You bet! We're all just big kids,'' Mr. Wells said with his bright grin. ''Bottom line? 'Hey, let's draw!' ''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
