<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Make Friends and Pick Stocks</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Your Money Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="590077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, ANDREE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDD103CF930A25751C0A965958260" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Make Friends and Pick Stocks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREE BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, ANDREE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Armed with specialized reports and chatting enthusiastically about the performance of Amgen, a pharmaceutical company, and Gtech, makers of computerized gaming systems, 14 women gathered around a table at the Westport Women's Club one recent noontime for a session of their Venture Investment Club.</p>
        <p>Gtech had been enthusiastically endorsed by the majority for purchase -- "think of all those casinos being opened on the Indian reservations," said one member -- but another reminded the group that Gtech was a gambling stock and thus not quite suitable for a gathering of grandmothers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Armed with specialized reports and chatting enthusiastically about the performance of Amgen, a pharmaceutical company, and Gtech, makers of computerized gaming systems, 14 women gathered around a table at the Westport Women's Club one recent noontime for a session of their Venture Investment Club.</p>
        <p>Gtech had been enthusiastically endorsed by the majority for purchase -- "think of all those casinos being opened on the Indian reservations," said one member -- but another reminded the group that Gtech was a gambling stock and thus not quite suitable for a gathering of grandmothers.</p>
        <p>"Well, what do you think the stock market is?" demanded Elsie Ball, 80, a member for over 10 years and one of the club's most respected amateur analysts. Gtech stayed on the "to buy" list.</p>
        <p>Scenes like these are taking place all across the country as the number of investor clubs grows. The National Association of Investors Corporation in Royal Oak, Mich., which represents the bulk of investment clubs, now lists 9,200 nationwide, the most ever.</p>
        <p>In the last six months, newly formed clubs have been affiliating at an explosive rate of 75 a week, compared with 40 a week in the 80's. Barry Murphy, the association's director of marketing, attributes the surging growth to the lackluster performance of investment alternatives to stocks, like C.D.'s and real estate, and to the increasing number of Americans with self-directed retirement funds. These changes, he said, require ordinary people to become more financially savvy.</p>
        <p>"I didn't want someone else telling me what to do for the rest of my life," said Trudy Seagraves, 60, a medical writer in Norwalk, Conn., and a newcomer to the Venture group.</p>
        <p>She said she had grown weary of leaving her modest nest egg in the hands of professionals who seemed to her to be more motivated by commissions and fees than her well-being. And she considers a club the best way to learn the ropes.</p>
        <p>The Venture Club's portfolio has been achieving average annual gains of 12 percent over the 13 years since it was founded; last year the portfolio had a gain of 11 percent. Those rates of gain are typical for member clubs across the country, according to the investors' association.</p>
        <p>Taken as a group, the clubs in the association did well over the last three years, with more than 60 percent of them equaling or bettering the performance of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index. The clubs had much spottier records from 1984 to 1989, however.</p>
        <p>Besides growth of capital, which is a prime goal of most members, the clubs also offer companionship. Virtually all the clubs are gatherings of friends or of people who know one another as neighbors, golfing partners, church or synagogue members or colleagues at work. The word is spread privately and informally, and members are accepted by recommendation. Anyone eager to join will need to network aggressively.</p>
        <p>Before joining a club, prospective members are advised to inquire into its portfolio strategy to make sure it is compatible with their goals. Those looking primarily for long-term capital growth might not be happy in a club whose members are seeking big dividends.</p>
        <p>It is also a good idea to look at the club's partnership agreement, to ask about administrative fees and attend at least one meeting as an observer.</p>
        <p>An alternative is to start a new club as Dr. David Wendel, a 30-year-old chiropractor in Woodbridge, N.J., recently did with five of his friends. "There were enough of us to start our own club," he said. "And the only other club in town was filled."</p>
        <p>Typically, a club operates most efficiently with around 15 to 20 members. The method favored by the investors' association is for each member to buy units in the club -- say $20 per unit with perhaps a minimum number required. Members normally add around $30 more on a monthly basis. "It behaves like a personalized mutual fund," Mr. Murphy said.</p>
        <p>The cash is deposited in a club account with a broker chosen by the members, usually a discount broker because members prefer to do their own research. Members discuss and research the tips they bring to each meeting, typically held in a member's living room.</p>
        <p>"I like the idea of bouncing ideas off 5 to 10 different people," said Phil Crocker, an assistant store manager in Colonia, N.J. "You can only read so much yourself."</p>
        <p>Members then vote on what to buy or sell. The majority rules. Executive positions are normally rotated. Nobody gets paid, and if a member wants to buy stocks the others reject, he or she must set up an account outside the club.</p>
        <p>Surveys by the national association show that most members have private portfolios twice as large as the money they invest with the club. Those club investments range widely -- from as little as $500 to as much as $300,000.</p>
        <p>The club contract may require a 30-to-90-day notice for withdrawals. Joe Smith, 54, an international marketing manager in Paramus, N.J., said that his club also had a 3 percent redemption fee, "because we like to stay fully invested," he said. "And this means we have to sell something every time a member wants his money, which costs money," he added.</p>
        <p>Normally, one or two members are assigned to follow a particular stock in the club's portfolio, in addition to seeking out new opportunities. But relying only on volunteers, Mr. Smith warned, could mean that a handful could end up doing all the work. So it's best to rotate tasks.</p>
        <p>The national association, which can be reached at (313) 543-0615, can provide new clubs with a free start-up kit as well as manuals and software. It also has a direct stock purchase program that permits member clubs to buy shares in about 100 major corporations without paying a broker's fee. The association's annual dues for clubs are $30 plus $10 for each member.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
