<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mideast Talks Stall, and U.S. Mediator Says He's Going Home</title>
    <meta content="28ISRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="886252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hebron (West Bank)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ross, Dennis B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmemann, Serge</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1D61739F93BA15753C1A960958260" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mideast Talks Stall, and U.S. Mediator Says He's Going Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmemann, Serge</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Monday, Oct. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special US Middle East negotiator Dennis Ross will leave for US without accord between Israel and Palestinians over withdrawal of Israeli forces from Hebron and other issues; decision to return home is based on assumption that no agreement is possible for next few days, because of departure of Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat for visits to Finland and Spain (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After shuttling on Sunday between Haifa and Gaza in a last minute attempt to bridge remaining gaps in a Hebron agreement, Dennis Ross, the American mediator, announced early today that he was leaving for Washington without an accord.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross's decision was evidently based on the assumption that no agreement was possible during the next few days, since the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, left today for visits to Finland and Spain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After shuttling on Sunday between Haifa and Gaza in a last minute attempt to bridge remaining gaps in a Hebron agreement, Dennis Ross, the American mediator, announced early today that he was leaving for Washington without an accord.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross's decision was evidently based on the assumption that no agreement was possible during the next few days, since the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, left today for visits to Finland and Spain.</p>
        <p>Up till the last minute, Israeli officials had insisted that a deal was imminent. But after three weeks of intensive efforts by Mr. Ross and often round-the-clock negotiations, it was evident that the differences remained acute.</p>
        <p>In an effort to prod both sides, President Clinton had telephoned Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and Mr. Arafat on Sunday. The White House spokesman, Michael D. McCurry, said Mr. Clinton had made the calls because the negotiations were ''down to some difficult issues.''</p>
        <p>Chief among the remaining obstacles is reported to be disagreement over Israel's demand for the right to chase Palestinian attackers into Palestinian-controlled portions of Hebron.</p>
        <p>Israel wants the right of ''hot pursuit'' as part of the complex security arrangements for the 500 Jewish settlers living in enclaves in the heart of the West Bank city.</p>
        <p>Another unresolved issue reportedly centers on where armed settlers have the right to move in the city.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross, who canceled his announced departure last Monday after an 11th-hour breakthrough in one part of the talks seemed to clear the way for a quick conclusion, said on Sunday that he would leave today if no agreement was reached before Mr. Arafat's planned journey.</p>
        <p>''It's clear that we have further narrowed the differences that exist, but we have not overcome those differences,'' Mr. Ross said after meeting with Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu in Haifa. ''Clearly the pace of negotiations is affected when the leaders aren't here because part of my mission is very clearly to go back and forth between the leaders.''</p>
        <p>Accordingly, Mr. Ross was to have gone from Haifa to Gaza to see Mr. Arafat, but the death of a close relative of the Palestinian leader delayed the meeting until late evening.</p>
        <p>The tense and secretive negotiations, which have shifted repeatedly between Tel Aviv, Jerusalem and the southern resort of Eilat, have been accompanied by growing bitterness.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials have repeatedly insisted that they are prepared to settle immediately and that it is the Palestinians who are holding out. One senior official said Mr. Arafat was laboring under an ''enormously exaggerated sense of international support,'' especially after a visit to the Palestinian city of Ramallah by President Jacques Chirac of France, and was hoping that this support would translate into gains at the negotiating table.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials also suggested that Mr. Arafat was holding out until the American elections were over, in the hope that a re-elected President Clinton would be free to put greater pressure on Mr. Netanyahu.</p>
        <p>Evidently to increase the pressure on Mr. Arafat, Mr. Netanyahu introduced new demands over the weekend, insisting that the Palestinian leader explain comments he made in Bethlehem last week calling for a jihad, or sacred struggle, and that the Palestinians must declare their intentions about a National Covenant that they said six months ago they would rewrite.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat often uses the term jihad in his speeches, but he argues that it does not necessarily mean violent struggle.</p>
        <p>As for the covenant, most Palestinians have considered the matter closed since the Palestine National Council voted in April to excise those portions calling for Israel's destruction and the changes were accepted by the Israeli Government and the United States.</p>
        <p>For their part, the Palestinians have continued to maintain in public that they are not prepared to alter the agreement concluded a year ago on the Hebron withdrawal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat's more basic objection is reportedly his deep distrust of Mr. Netanyahu's intentions. Mr. Arafat is said to fear that once the Israelis redeploy their forces in Hebron, a step considered virtually inevitable, Mr. Netanyahu will take no further actions required under the agreement, which include extensive further Israeli withdrawals in the West Bank.</p>
        <p>''The negotiations are one of our means of struggle,'' Mr. Rahman said. ''We have a long breath.''</p>
        <p>The tension at the talks was accompanied by growing tension on the ground. In Hebron, a heated meeting between Jewish settlers and Israeli security officials on Sunday was interrupted when shooting broke out. Israeli television said the incident had begun when settlers complained about the presence of Palestinian journalists at the meeting. The argument led to rocks being thrown from the Palestinian side, to which settlers responded with gunshots. No one was wounded.</p>
        <p>In another development bound to raise tempers, the Israeli Government was reported to have approved the sale of 3,000 housing units in various West Bank settlements to Jewish settlers. The apartments were built the last time the Likud Party was in power, but their use was frozen by the Labor Government that was in power from 1993 until Mr. Netanyahu's victory in May.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
