<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cable TV News Competition Spills Onto the Web</title>
    <meta content="28SITE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Taking In the Sites" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="886257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="Taking In the Sites"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Msnbc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cable News Network (Cnn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allen, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EED61739F93BA15753C1A960958260" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cable TV News Competition Spills Onto the Web</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE ALLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Allen, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cable news war has spawned companion Web sites crammed with scripts, wire stories and market tables; Web site for MSNBC, venture of NBC and Microsoft Corp, is programmed in Redmond, Wash; users can request daily E-mail delivery of customized news page, or sign up for News Alert service that flashes icon when stories break; on CNN Interactive, a 'pager' lets users scroll through news, market, weather and Hollywood headlines; chart listing news sites on Web (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MSNBC recently posted a spreadsheet on the Internet for calculating your monthly savings from cutting back on coffee, bagels and movies.</p>
        <p>CNN's World Wide Web site, CNN Interactive, offers the Shockwave Pager, which sits in the corner of your screen, reloading its headlines every 30 minutes and beeping when news breaks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MSNBC recently posted a spreadsheet on the Internet for calculating your monthly savings from cutting back on coffee, bagels and movies.</p>
        <p>CNN's World Wide Web site, CNN Interactive, offers the Shockwave Pager, which sits in the corner of your screen, reloading its headlines every 30 minutes and beeping when news breaks.</p>
        <p>The Fox News site created a cheeky ''Tale of the Tape'' for the presidential candidates. Under the year of graduation from high school, the ''Most Popular TV Show'' category for President Clinton listed ''Bonanza'' and for Bob Dole said, ''Television not invented yet.''</p>
        <p>The cable news war has spawned companion Web sites crammed with scripts, wire stories and market tables. The MSNBC site and the site by CNN, which is owned by the Turner Broadcasting System, have large staffs of their own; the site by Fox, a unit of the News Corporation, is spare by comparison.</p>
        <p>The Web site for MSNBC, the venture of NBC, a unit of the General Electric Company, and the Microsoft Corporation, is programmed in Redmond, Wash. Users can request a daily E-mail delivery of a customized news page, or sign up for a News Alert service that flashes an icon when stories break.</p>
        <p>The bagel table was part of a series on simplifying your life that included a questionnaire for rethinking work habits and a spreadsheet for figuring how long you have to work to pay for child care or dry cleaning.</p>
        <p>''We try to add personalization to everything we do -- more chat, more feedback, more polling,'' Merrill Brown, the editor in chief of MSNBC on the Internet, said.</p>
        <p>MSNBC's site includes an Investor Toolkit, with market indexes, a mortgage-payment calculator and an archive of corporate earnings and dividend reports.</p>
        <p>For those whose tastes run to the more sensational, MSNBC has local news pages maintained by 30 NBC-owned and affiliated stations. One recent morning's fare included ''Football player dies after warm-ups,'' from New York; ''Officer killed in freeway crash,'' from Los Angeles; ''Families mourn murder victims,'' from Chicago, and ''Arson fire,'' from Washington.</p>
        <p>On CNN Interactive, which has a staff of 100 in Atlanta, the ''pager'' looks like an actual pager and lets users scroll through news, market, weather and Hollywood headlines.</p>
        <p>The CNN site includes a section called Fringe has a weird story each day (''Angry gorilla halts jet''). Other categories include Sci-Tech, Style, Showbiz, Health and Earth. In the Web's irreverent style, a page called Big Brother offers a shot of the newsroom, updated every two minutes.</p>
        <p>Today on CNN updates its schedule of guests throughout the day; Video Vault houses news clips, and What's on TV carries programming grids for 65 networks and lets users set up personalized program guides.</p>
        <p>A companion site for business news is CNNFN, which shares an assignment desk with the CNNFN cable channel in Manhattan. ''We tend to be within 30 seconds of each other,'' Rich Zahradnik, the executive producer of CNNFN Interactive, said.</p>
        <p>Market averages are posted every three minutes and new graphs go up every 15 minutes. Digital Jam, with its Tech Lab and Bits and Bytes, is stuffed with technology news and reviews. Other CNNFN features include Biz Buzz, Grapevine, and Deals. Click Briefing to see stories posted during the day.</p>
        <p>A shot of the CNNFN cable screen reloads every few seconds, and FN to Go launches a small browser window that updates headlines and market indexes as the user travels elsewhere on the Web.</p>
        <p>The Fox site has a handy keyword searcher that pops up on each screen. The site offers an audio feed of the channel, and divides copy into News, Business, Health, Sports, Technology and Wires.</p>
        <p>Last week the site began posting a daily column. Mike Schneider, a Fox anchorman, writes ''Behind the Desk'' each Tuesday. Other weekly columns cover business, technology, media, sports and foreign affairs.</p>
        <p>Fox plans to wire the green rooms of its studios so guests can take questions on the Web site right after appearing on television.</p>
        <p>Much of the business copy on the news channels' sites comes from the news agency Reuters, which sells news reports to 35 major Web sites. To promote its Web products, the Reuters corporate site has a News Room section with up-to-the-minute photographs and breaking business, sports and political stories.</p>
        <p>Bloomberg Business News, owned by Bloomberg L.P., charges $1,640 a month for its full-blown terminal. But many of the fruits of Bloomberg are free at the company's Web site.</p>
        <p>Click on Who/What/Where/When for a lottery scoreboard; horoscopes (''brought to you by Standard &amp; Poor's''); a help-wanted section devoted to jobs paying more than $100,000, and real estate listings divided by continent and promoting must-see features like ''spacious three bedroom house with detached pool house and large garden overlooking bird sanctuary.''</p>
        <p>Taking In the Sites</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
