<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="11FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1558024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFDF123AF932A25751C0A9629C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Bomb at Iraq Police Post Kills 54, Many Job Seekers  A car bomb exploded outside the police station in a town 30 miles south of Baghdad, killing at least 54 people and wounding at least 60 others, police and hospital officials said. Most of the casualties were Iraqis applying for jobs with the police.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>France Votes to Ban Scarves  The National Assembly voted 494-to-36 to ban Muslim head scarves and other religious symbols from public schools, a move that underscored the broad public support for the French secular ideal but was certain to deepen resentment among France's large Muslim population.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Bomb at Iraq Police Post Kills 54, Many Job Seekers  A car bomb exploded outside the police station in a town 30 miles south of Baghdad, killing at least 54 people and wounding at least 60 others, police and hospital officials said. Most of the casualties were Iraqis applying for jobs with the police.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>France Votes to Ban Scarves  The National Assembly voted 494-to-36 to ban Muslim head scarves and other religious symbols from public schools, a move that underscored the broad public support for the French secular ideal but was certain to deepen resentment among France's large Muslim population.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Russian Candidate Reappears  A Russian presidential candidate, Ivan P. Rybkin, 57, reappeared at Sheremetyevo Airport, outside Moscow, alive and well if confused about the fuss he had caused. He disappeared under mysterious circumstances on Thursday evening.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Young Detainee Returns Home  Mohammad Ismail Agha, 15, one of three young Afghans released 10 days ago from imprisonment at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, has returned home, no worse for wear but bitter at what he has been through.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Haiti Moves to Curb Violence  Haiti said it had regained control over three of the towns convulsed by an armed uprising, while the Bush administration suggested that it might support President Jean-Bertrand Aristide stepping down.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Romania Gains in AIDS War  Romania has finally declared itself the winner of a long war against AIDS. The country is now being cited as a model of how governments, drug companies and international agencies can bring AIDS under control. However, public health experts fear a second wave will hit soon.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-26</p>
        <p>Kerry Wins Big Victories In Virginia and Tennessee  Senator John Kerry won commanding victories in the Tennessee and Virginia primaries, dealing a serious blow to his rivals for the Democratic presidential nomination.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Gen. Wesley K. Clark abandoned his race after third-place finishes.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Bush Releases Records  The White House released 18 months of President Bush's National Guard payroll records showing what officials asserted was proof that he had fully completed his service in the Guard during the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Compromise in Gay Marriage  Massachusetts state lawmakers fashioned a proposed amendment to the state constitution that would define marriage as a heterosexual institution but allow same-sex couples to join in civil unions.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Rights Panel Backs D.C. Voting  An international human rights commission has ruled that the United States is violating international law by refusing to give residents of Washington a vote in Congress.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Protester Subpoenas Dropped  Federal prosecutors dropped subpoenas they had issued ordering antiwar protesters to appear before a grand jury and ordering a university to turn over information about them.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>'Smoking Guns' Not Found  The chairman of the commission on the Sept. 11 attacks said that there were ''no smoking guns'' in classified Oval Office intelligence reports.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Fulbright Applicants Reviewed  A compromise was reached that will allow 30 students to compete for Fulbright scholarships even though their applications were delayed.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>Phone Customers Bilked In a New Mafia Venture  New York organized crime figures bilked millions of unsuspecting customers out of more than $200 million over five years by piggybacking bogus charges on their telephone bills, federal authorities said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Outrage at Release of Records  New York City officials released Dr. Robert Atkins's confidential medical report, revealing that he had a history of heart attack. The release outraged Atkins followers and annoyed the mayor.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Woman Dies Retrieving Phone  A woman, 19, whose cellphone dropped onto the tracks in a Queens subway station was killed when she climbed down to retrieve it and was crushed by an oncoming train.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B10-11</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>H.I.V. Outbreak in Colleges  A new H.I.V. test has led health workers in North Carolina to identify what they and federal officials say is the first outbreak of the infection among college students.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18</p>
        <p>OPEC Cuts Oil Production  OPEC announced cuts in production, aggressively displaying its desire to maintain oil prices at their highest sustained level in two decades. Oil prices jumped in response.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Claim of Stewart Cover-Up  Martha Stewart's assistant testified that Ms. Stewart deleted part of a record of a phone message from her stockbroker after a telephone conversation with her lawyer.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Bidders for AT&amp;T Wireless  Cingular and Vodafone are the only companies expected to make bids for AT&amp;T Wireless when the company is put up for auction on Friday, according to people close to the auction.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A28-29</p>
        <p>Editorials: The president's Guard service; an environmental deficit; Haiti erupts; this is your proselytizer speaking.</p>
        <p>Columns: Nicholas D. Kristof, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
