<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tax-Free Shopping Week in New York Thins the Mall Crowds Across the Hudson</title>
    <meta content="19SALE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="988908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales Tax</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3D71238F93AA25752C0A96E958260" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tax-Free Shopping Week in New York Thins the Mall Crowds Across the Hudson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <dateline>JERSEY CITY, Jan. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tax-free week of shopping in New York hurts stores in New Jersey; many shoppers in midtown Manhattan say that they usually shop in New Jersey to escape 8.25 percent sales tax in city; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yes, Carlos Sosa did some shopping in his home state of New Jersey today. But only on his way to New York City, where he planned to take full advantage of the tax-free shopping week that started on Saturday.</p>
        <p>After making a single purchase at the Newport Centre Mall here, Mr. Sosa hustled to Manhattan, where he planned to put hundreds of dollars worth of clothing on layaway at stores like Old Navy and Filene's Basement. New Jersey has those same stores and never charges a tax on clothing. So what was going on?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yes, Carlos Sosa did some shopping in his home state of New Jersey today. But only on his way to New York City, where he planned to take full advantage of the tax-free shopping week that started on Saturday.</p>
        <p>After making a single purchase at the Newport Centre Mall here, Mr. Sosa hustled to Manhattan, where he planned to put hundreds of dollars worth of clothing on layaway at stores like Old Navy and Filene's Basement. New Jersey has those same stores and never charges a tax on clothing. So what was going on?</p>
        <p>''There's always more selection in New York,'' said Mr. Sosa, a parking garage attendant from Jersey City. ''I'm kind of sick of the malls, anyway. It's more interesting to shop over there.''</p>
        <p>Others apparently thought so, too. Sales clerks at Newport Centre said that despite sales on many items, their stores were surprisingly empty today. While the bad weather and long holiday weekend could have been factors, they speculated that the brief repeal of New York's sales tax was mostly to blame. In Manhattan, shops of all sizes reported unusually strong sales of everything from silk underwear to hiking boots.</p>
        <p>The tax-free shopping week is the third in New York City since last January, when many retailers said sales more than doubled while the repeal was in effect. The occasional tax breaks are meant to appease not only shoppers but also retailers, who have long complained that they lose business to New Jersey because they have to charge 8.25 percent in sales taxes.</p>
        <p>But while a spokeswoman for Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said today that the city loses $700 million a year in retail sales to New Jersey, she added that the Mayor was not trying to snatch business away from suburban shopping malls.</p>
        <p>''What the Mayor is hoping for is increased retail activity,'' the spokeswoman, Colleen Roche, said. ''It doesn't matter to him what the source is.''</p>
        <p>Nor did it matter to shopkeepers, who gleefully rang up sales to New Yorkers, New Jerseyans and others.</p>
        <p>The manager at Wild Pair, a shoe store in the Manhattan Mall on 33d Street and Broadway, said she sold 40 pairs of shoes today, twice as many as usual for a Sunday. Wild Pair was giving people an 8 percent discount on top of the sales tax break, which applies to all purchases of clothing and shoes less than $500.</p>
        <p>At Macy's, Andrea Gould of the Bronx said she bought a pair of 9 West shoes and some Donna Karan underwear ''because those are the most expensive, and you don't have to pay tax.''</p>
        <p>''I usually go to New Jersey,'' said Ms. Gould, a part-time model. ''As long as there's no tax, I'll buy it.''</p>
        <p>Residents of both states are choosing to shop in New York this week even though many stores in New Jersey are offering special discounts to counter the damage, said Walter Loeb, publisher of the Loeb Retail Letter.</p>
        <p>Back at Newport Centre Mall, even sales people who get generous employee discounts were wishing they could flee to New York with their credit cards.</p>
        <p>Ronnie Rajkumar, a manager at Aeropostale, said he planned to spend his day off shopping in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Rosemary Castillo, a manager at Filene's Basement, said she preferred shopping in New York because she did not have to drive there. ''To get to Macy's out here, you have to take Route Whatever to Route Whatever, with all the traffic,'' said Ms. Castillo, who lives in Jersey City. ''To get to Macy's in New York, I jump on the PATH train.''</p>
        <p>The New York State Legislature voted last year to repeal permanently the sales tax on clothing purchases under $100 in December 1999. But Mayor Giuliani has been pushing for the repeal to apply to purchases of up to $500.</p>
        <p>Ms. Roche, his spokeswoman, said sales were strong enough in the first two days of this tax-free shopping week to justify a $500 limit. ''The ultimate goal is to get the Legislature to drop the tax completely,'' she said. ''Ultimately, the result of that will be more jobs.''</p>
        <p>Could another result be an exodus of shoppers from New Jersey to New York?</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Gov. Christine Todd Whitman said he could not envision such a scenario. The spokesman, Pete McDonough, said people from both states would continue to shop in New Jersey because malls are more comfortable than city streets.</p>
        <p>While New Jersey does charge a sales tax on some merchandise, it is generally cheaper than New York's tax, he said.</p>
        <p>''It's not an immediate concern,'' Mr. McDonough said. ''The whole shopping atmosphere in New Jersey is better than in New York. It's just a much more pleasant experience here in New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>Although New Yorkers were scarce in Newport Centre today, Ms. Castillo and other sales clerks said they usually shop here in droves, eager to avoid New York's sales tax.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Long, a singer from Manhattan who had come to return a shirt to Sears, said he liked not just escaping New York's sales tax, but also escaping New York.</p>
        <p>''We have all the chain stores in New York now that used to only be in the suburbs, but out here, you get the tax savings,'' Mr. Long said as he rested on a bench. ''And it's nice to get a taste of suburbia.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
