<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giving Up a Death Wish To Guide a Brother's Life</title>
    <meta content="25NEED" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1171272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE NEEDIEST CASES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jewish Child Care Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E1DB163CF936A15752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giving Up a Death Wish To Guide a Brother's Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Times Neediest Cases Fund; teenager Crystal J discusses how Jewish Child Care Assn has helped stabilize her life (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, Crystal J. felt that the ambulances always came too early and the police too late.</p>
        <p>Before she turned 17, Crystal recalls, she had been raped twice and had attempted suicide three times. Each time she tried to soothe her suffering with toxic tonics concocted from medicine and liquor cabinets, but she was thwarted by doctors intent on prolonging her painful life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, Crystal J. felt that the ambulances always came too early and the police too late.</p>
        <p>Before she turned 17, Crystal recalls, she had been raped twice and had attempted suicide three times. Each time she tried to soothe her suffering with toxic tonics concocted from medicine and liquor cabinets, but she was thwarted by doctors intent on prolonging her painful life.</p>
        <p>''I'd be semiconscious in a whitish haze,'' she recalls. ''Then I'd always see these flashing red lights, and men coming in waking me up. I even tried locking them out once, thinking, 'Just a couple more minutes and all my problems will be over.' ''</p>
        <p>But her problems continued. Her teenage years were a series of traumas, family deaths and fights with her parents and a dozen short stays in psychiatric hospitals.</p>
        <p>But lately, Crystal, now 19, has begun to stabilize her life with help from the Jewish Child Care Association, a beneficiary of the UJA-Federation of New York, one of seven charities receiving support from The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>Even after her mother's death a year ago, Crystal has continued going to college and taking care of her brother, Noel, 13, in their home in East New York, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''Now I want to live,'' she said. ''Even if I didn't owe it to myself, at least I owe it to Noel.''</p>
        <p>The child care association's intensive case management program provides a social worker who spends several hours a day with Crystal making sure she attends daily counseling sessions and gets the services she needs to take care of herself and Noel. The agency also helps to pay for a variety of expenses, including food, furniture and a part-time homemaker.</p>
        <p>As a child living with her mother in East New York, Crystal became an honors student in junior high school, earning a scholarship to Cathedral High School, on East 56th Street in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>But just before Crystal started there, in 1994, her close friend and her grandfather died.</p>
        <p>Then, she said, a former boyfriend forced her to have sex with him after a party. Crystal told nobody. But one afternoon, she raided the medicine and liquor cabinets and swallowed cups filled with pills and liquor. Her mother came home early and found her on the living room floor.</p>
        <p>''I just wanted to go to sleep and wake up dead,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Instead, Crystal survived and spent four weeks in Holliswood Hospital, a psychiatric care center in Queens.</p>
        <p>During her freshman year at Cathedral, Crystal moved in with her father. One night, after an argument with him, she gulped down some pills and a bottle of peroxide upstairs in her room, while the family watched television in the living room.</p>
        <p>After another hospital stay, she returned to live with her mother, but they often argued. At 16, Crystal said, she moved in with a friend, whose mother was a drug addict and was rarely home. Crystal began spending her nights out smoking marijuana and drinking.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes, I'd get home just in time to put on my uniform and get to  school,'' she said. It was during this period, Crystal said, that she was raped a second time, once again by someone she knew.</p>
        <p>After the attack, Crystal was taken to Brookdale University Hospital and Medical Center for a week of psychiatric treatment.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't believe this could happen to me twice,'' she recalled. ''I just wanted to end it. Every night I wanted to go to sleep and never wake up.''</p>
        <p>Soon, she again tried to commit suicide and spent three months in Holliswood. A hospital social worker referred Crystal to the Jewish Child Care Association, where a counselor kept her attending weekly psychiatric sessions and rape counseling.</p>
        <p>Now a freshman at the DeVry Institute of Technology in Queens, Crystal is studying computer programming. She recently got an A on her essay titled ''The Ambulance Came Too Soon,'' written for an English class.</p>
        <p>Actually, Crystal says she becomes more grateful each day that the ambulances did arrive in time.</p>
        <p>''I've realized that your life is not all your own,'' she said. ''It also belongs to the people around you. It sounds weird, but I wouldn't change my life one bit. It's made me a stronger person, and now I'm taking control of it.''</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to P.O. Box 5193, General Post Office, New York, N.Y. 10087, or any of these  organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE  285 Schermerhorn Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK  1011 First Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS  191 Joralemon Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES  281 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK  Church Street Station, P.O. Box 4100, New York, N.Y. 10261-4100</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Donations may be made with a credit card online, courtesy of the Qpass digital commerce service, at www.nytimes.com/neediest. Online donors receive a free trial subscription to the crossword puzzle of The New York Times on the Web.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on Federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
        <p>Previously recorded $5,054,995.10  Recorded Monday $27,112.24</p>
        <p>Total $5,082,107.34</p>
        <p>THE NEEDIEST CASES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
