<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Co-ops That Require 'Flip Taxes'</title>
    <meta content="27QA.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/27/realestate/27QA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1507440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Q. &amp; A."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2DF153FF934A15754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Co-ops That Require 'Flip Taxes'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Co-ops That Require `Flip Taxes'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Housing Q&amp;A on paying co-op 'flip tax,' on buying one's own refrigerator when landlord does not supply working one</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. My co-op has a policy that requires the seller of shares to pay the co-op a ''flip tax'' of $15 per share sold. There is no mention of this requirement in the occupancy agreement, the bylaws or the certificate of incorporation. None of those documents have been amended by vote of the shareholders since the co-op came into existence in 1959. Can the board impose this fee without amending the occupancy agreement or the bylaws? The amount involved is approximately $4,500. If I refuse to pay this flip tax, can the board hold up the sale of the shares? . . . Ken Baron, Manhattan</p>
        <p>A. Dennis H. Greenstein, a Manhattan co-op lawyer and former state assistant attorney general in the real estate finance section, said that for a flip tax to be enforceable it must be authorized by the proprietary lease (in this case, the occupancy agreement), by the co-op's bylaws or by a properly approved amendment to one of those documents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q My co-op has a policy that requires the seller of shares to pay the co-op a</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. My co-op has a policy that requires the seller of shares to pay the co-op a ''flip tax'' of $15 per share sold. There is no mention of this requirement in the occupancy agreement, the bylaws or the certificate of incorporation. None of those documents have been amended by vote of the shareholders since the co-op came into existence in 1959. Can the board impose this fee without amending the occupancy agreement or the bylaws? The amount involved is approximately $4,500. If I refuse to pay this flip tax, can the board hold up the sale of the shares? . . . Ken Baron, Manhattan</p>
        <p>A. Dennis H. Greenstein, a Manhattan co-op lawyer and former state assistant attorney general in the real estate finance section, said that for a flip tax to be enforceable it must be authorized by the proprietary lease (in this case, the occupancy agreement), by the co-op's bylaws or by a properly approved amendment to one of those documents.</p>
        <p>So, he said, if the letterwriter is correct in stating that the fee is not authorized by either the occupancy agreement or the bylaws and it has not been authorized by an approved amendment to either document, the flip tax would not be valid. He pointed out, however, that some bylaws permit amendment by the board without the consent of the shareholders. ''If the letter writer's bylaws allow for such director amendments, then the board may claim that its policy of implementing the flip tax amounted to an amendment to the bylaws,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He added that if the flip-tax policy does not constitute a proper amendment to the bylaws and the co-op refuses to close without payment of the fee, the letter writer should make the payment ''under protest and without prejudice'' and after the closing begin a lawsuit to recover the amount paid.</p>
        <p>A Renter's Right To a Refrigerator</p>
        <p>Q. A very good friend of mine, now 84, has been living in the same rent-stabilized apartment on the Upper East Side for about 40 years. The building went co-op some years ago, and, needless to say, the owner of the apartment would be happy to have her out. After all these years, the original refrigerator does not work well anymore. When she inquired a couple of years ago whether she could get a new one, even buying it herself, she was told, ''Absolutely not.'' If we, a few of her friends, buy her a refrigerator as a gift, is this not allowed either? I have a hard time believing that the law would be so cruel. . . . Margot R. Calles, Upper Black Eddy, Pa.</p>
        <p>A. ''The law is not so cruel,'' said Thomas P. Higgins, a Manhattan landlord-tenant lawyer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Higgins said that unless there is a specific provision in the lease to the contrary, the rent laws do not prohibit a tenant from replacing an existing refrigerator with a new one purchased by the tenant or in this case by concerned friends.</p>
        <p>''The problem is, what do you do with the old one?'' Mr. Higgins said, explaining that since the existing refrigerator is the property of the owner of the apartment, the tenant must be prepared to ensure the original refrigerator is returned to the apartment when she ultimately vacates.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Higgins said, the rent laws do require a landlord to keep supplied appliances in good working order.</p>
        <p>''That doesn't mean he has to give her a new one,'' he said, ''but it sure sounds like the one she has isn't working very well.'' If that is the case, Mr. Higgins said, the tenant should ask the landlord for a working refrigerator. If the landlord does not provide one, he said, the tenant can withhold her rent and use the landlord's failure to provide a functioning refrigerator as a defense in any action he may bring against her.</p>
        <p>Mr. Higgins added that if the tenant asks the landlord for a new refrigerator and he provides one, the landlord would be entitled to a permanent increase in rent equal to one-fortieth of the cost of the new refrigerator if the tenant and the landlord agree to the increase in writing.</p>
        <p>Q. &amp; A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
