<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="07TRAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="993570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0D9103DF934A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  BOSTON RED SOX--Agreed to terms with OF Troy O'Leary on a four-year contract.  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Named Felix Fermin manager for their Dominican summer league team.  YANKEES--Acquired 2B Chuck Knoblauch from the Minnesota Twins for LHP Eric Milton, RHP Danny Mota, OF Brian Buchanan, SS Cristian Guzman and $3 million.  TEXAS RANGERS--Agreed to terms with LHP Darren Oliver, RHP Aaron Sele and LHP Matt Perisho on one-year contracts.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Agreed to terms with OF Shawn Green on a two-year contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League  BOSTON RED SOX--Agreed to terms with OF Troy O'Leary on a four-year contract.  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Named Felix Fermin manager for their Dominican summer league team.  YANKEES--Acquired 2B Chuck Knoblauch from the Minnesota Twins for LHP Eric Milton, RHP Danny Mota, OF Brian Buchanan, SS Cristian Guzman and $3 million.  TEXAS RANGERS--Agreed to terms with LHP Darren Oliver, RHP Aaron Sele and LHP Matt Perisho on one-year contracts.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Agreed to terms with OF Shawn Green on a two-year contract.</p>
        <p>National League  ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS--Agreed to terms with RHP Hector Carrasco on a one-year contract.  ATLANTA BRAVES--Agreed to terms with OF George Lombard and OF Curtis Pride on one-year contracts.  COLORADO ROCKIES--Agreed to terms with RHP Mike Dejean and OF Curtis Goodwin on one-year contracts.  METS--Acquired LHP Al Leiter and INF Ralph Milliard from the Florida Marlins for LHP Jesus Sanchez, RHP A.J. Burnett and OF Robert Stratton. Agreed to terms with RHP Turk Wendell, RHP Derek Wallace and RHP Jason Isringhausen on one-year contracts. Named Roger LaFrancois roving minor-league catching instructor and manager of Pittsfield of the New York-Penn League.  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Agreed to terms with INF Andy Sheets, C Mandy Romero, RHP Marc Kroon, RHP Jim Sak and RHP Donne Wall on one-year contracts.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>FORT WAYNE FURY--Added G Damon Bailey to its roster.  YAKIMA SUN KINGS--Waived F Nate Green.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  JACKSONVILLE JAGUARS--Agreed to terms with LB Jeff Kopp, DT Jose White, OG-OT Todd Fordham and CB Ricky Parker.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  NHL--Suspended Tampa Bay Lightning D Bryan Marchment indefinitely for kneeing Kevin Dineen of the Carolina Hurricanes in a game Feb. 4.  TORONTO MAPLE LEAFS--Assigned C Jamie Baker to Chicago of the IHL.  VANCOUVER CANUCKS--Traded RW Trevor Linden to the New York Islanders for D Bryan McCabe, C Todd Bertuzzi and a 1998 third-round draft pick.  WASHINGTON CAPITALS--Assigned LW Jaroslav Svejkovsky to Portland of the AHL on a conditioning loan.</p>
        <p>American Hockey League  PORTLAND PIRATES--Recalled RW Rob Bonneau from loan to Hampton Roads of the ECHL.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  LOS ANGELES GALAXY--Signed F Mehran Molkara and MF-D Vrez Shakbandaryan.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>EASTERN ILLINOIS--Named Roy Wittke assistant head football coach and Bob Krieger defensive coordinator.  LAMAR--Announced the resignation of David McKey, women's basketball coach, effective at the end of the season.  SAN JOSE STATE--Named Chuck Ball athletic director.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
