<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For One Fortuneteller, Unforeseen Steel Bracelets</title>
    <meta content="01PSYC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/01/nyregion/01PSYC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1453136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Psychics and Psychic Phenomena</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fortune Telling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liu, Ying</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chung Chen Ling</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Psychics and Psychic Phenomena</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Occult Sciences</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E4D6123FF932A35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For One Fortuneteller, Unforeseen Steel Bracelets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Psychic Faces Charges of Charging for Nothing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Queens fortuneteller Ying Liu is scheduled to appear in court on charges of larceny; she promised Chung Chen Ling that for $8,000 she would grant him same psychic powers she has (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Latest fortune for Ying Liu, a Queens fortuneteller: You will be arrested, hauled into court and accused of making expensive predictions that did not come true.</p>
        <p>The Buddha's eye sees many things, according to Ms. Liu, 45, who has been peddling her psychic powers to Chinese immigrants from a storefront in Flushing for several years. She has predicted marriages, career advancements and births, and she has also made hypertension, cancer and other illnesses disappear, according to her advertisements. Among her grander forecasts is that New York City will be the host of the 2012 Summer Olympics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seems unlikely that Queens fortuneteller Ying Liu saw handcuffs in her future when she agreed to help a man who paid $8,000 and waited almost a year for fortunes that never came true.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Latest fortune for Ying Liu, a Queens fortuneteller: You will be arrested, hauled into court and accused of making expensive predictions that did not come true.</p>
        <p>The Buddha's eye sees many things, according to Ms. Liu, 45, who has been peddling her psychic powers to Chinese immigrants from a storefront in Flushing for several years. She has predicted marriages, career advancements and births, and she has also made hypertension, cancer and other illnesses disappear, according to her advertisements. Among her grander forecasts is that New York City will be the host of the 2012 Summer Olympics.</p>
        <p>But it seems unlikely that Ms. Liu saw handcuffs in her future when she agreed to help Chung Chen Ling, 30, who sought her supernatural services in June 2001, according to court papers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Liu told Mr. Chung that for a fee of $8,000 she would grant him the same psychic powers that she herself had found so useful, according to investigators, who said Ms. Liu's case was among the more unusual ones to show up in the Queens courts.</p>
        <p>Fortune-telling is illegal, according to the New York State penal code. Under the law, a fortuneteller is defined as anyone who ''claims or pretends to tell fortunes, or holds himself out as being able, by claimed or pretended use of occult powers, to answer questions or give advice on personal matters or to exorcise, influence or affect evil spirits or curses.'' The law does not apply to people who tell fortunes ''as part of a show or exhibition solely for the purposes of entertainment or amusement.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chung paid the $8,000 fee and waited almost a year, according to prosecutors, who said they were looking into whether Ms. Liu left other victims with fortunes that were paid for but never came true.</p>
        <p>The district attorney's office says that even in a city where soothsayers abound, particularly in many immigrant neighborhoods, fortunetellers are seldom arrested. ''Prosecutions for the crime of fortunetelling are not unheard of, but they are still exceedingly rare,'' said Patrick Clark, a spokesman for the Queens district attorney, Richard A. Brown.</p>
        <p>It may well be that most of those who find themselves swindled out of promised rose gardens are reluctant to come forward. But Mr. Chung, who lives on Long Island and visited Ms. Liu at her Flushing office, said that when he finally realized he had been had, he had to do something.</p>
        <p>After more than 11 months, there was still nothing psychic about him, he said; no special powers, no ability to predict the future, no Buddha's eye. So he went to the authorities, first to the state attorney general, who referred the case to the Economic Crimes Bureau of the district attorney's office.</p>
        <p>After an investigation into Mr. Chung's lack of psychic powers, detectives arrested Ms. Liu on Dec. 20 and she was charged with grand larceny in the third degree -- in effect, stealing money from Mr. Chung by not delivering the promised goods, the psychic powers -- and fortunetelling. She was arraigned on Dec. 21 and is due back in court on Monday.</p>
        <p>If convicted, Ms. Liu could be sentenced to up to seven years in prison on the grand larceny charge and up to 90 days in jail on the fortunetelling charge.</p>
        <p>Ms. Liu, who also runs a beauty salon in Flushing, refused to discuss the case yesterday. She referred calls to her lawyer, who was out of town and could not be reached.</p>
        <p>Last week, Ms. Liu told The World Journal, the Chinese-language daily newspaper, that she was innocent of the charges, and she has told reporters that she would hold a news conference to explain it all.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
