<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Estate Lives On, Thanks to Apples</title>
    <meta content="01APPL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/01/garden/01APPL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1338842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="House Proud"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apples</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Talavera (Claverack, NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Claverack (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Philips, Leila (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Dinitia</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Family Place, A (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/House Proud</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Berkshires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Catskills (NY)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Berkshires (Mass)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EFD71230F932A35752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Estate Lives On, Thanks to Apples</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Estate Lives On, Thanks to Apples</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DINITIA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Dinitia</byline>
      <dateline>CLAVERACK, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philips family maintains Talavera, estate in Claverack, NY, that has been in family for nearly 200 years, by becoming modern apple growers; Leila Philip, professor of English at Colgate University, tells its story in A Family Place: A Hudson Valley Farm, Three Generations, Five Wars, One Family; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM Route 9H, you can just glimpse Talavera, a yellow, Greek revival mansion with white trim and fluted columns. The house, serenely overlooking the Catskills and the Berkshires, seems deliberately hidden as you wind your way up a long driveway. Only as you reach the foot of the spacious lawn does Talavera reveal itself in all its faded elegance, subject to the inroads of time but occupied in unbroken succession by the Van Ness and Philip families for nearly 200 years.</p>
        <p>Every fall, some 2,000 city dwellers and suburbanites make their way to the orchards around back, where descendants of the original owners are making ends meet by running a pick-your-own-apple business. Apples cost $14 to $16 a bushel, depending on the variety, which includes McIntoshes, Northern Spy, Mutsu and Jonagolds. The family also sells heritage tomatoes and pears -- among them Anjou, rare on the East Coast, and Harrow Sweet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every fall, some 2,000 city dwellers and suburbanites make their way to the orchards behind the Talavera mansion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM Route 9H, you can just glimpse Talavera, a yellow, Greek revival mansion with white trim and fluted columns. The house, serenely overlooking the Catskills and the Berkshires, seems deliberately hidden as you wind your way up a long driveway. Only as you reach the foot of the spacious lawn does Talavera reveal itself in all its faded elegance, subject to the inroads of time but occupied in unbroken succession by the Van Ness and Philip families for nearly 200 years.</p>
        <p>Every fall, some 2,000 city dwellers and suburbanites make their way to the orchards around back, where descendants of the original owners are making ends meet by running a pick-your-own-apple business. Apples cost $14 to $16 a bushel, depending on the variety, which includes McIntoshes, Northern Spy, Mutsu and Jonagolds. The family also sells heritage tomatoes and pears -- among them Anjou, rare on the East Coast, and Harrow Sweet.</p>
        <p>''My great-great-aunts would have died to see me in pants and down there taking money,'' said Leila Philip, 40, an English professor at Colgate University in Hamilton, N.Y. ''But it's an important job that needs to be done. I enjoy the people, and I feel it connects me to a long history.''</p>
        <p>The Philip family's once extensive land holdings in Columbia County -- 294 acres in 1732 -- have diminished to 125 acres. In 1992, when Ms. Philip's father, John Van Ness Philip Jr., died, it looked as though the family might lose the place forever. The cost of labor, machinery and materials had risen drastically in recent years, and apples could be raised more cheaply outside the United States.</p>
        <p>But the family -- five adult siblings and their mother, Julia Willis Philip, 76 -- decided to save Talavera.</p>
        <p>''People said, 'You're crazy,' '' Ms. Philip said. '' 'You should sell it!' '' Instead, the siblings agreed to maintain Talavera for agricultural use. They also created a trust fund for the property, a fund to be dipped into in case of calamity. The agreement will last until three years after their mother dies.</p>
        <p>To remain competitive, the Philip family had to become modern apple growers. They are replacing the larger trees with smaller ones that will yield more fruit to the acre, a task their father began.</p>
        <p>They recognize that just one bad harvest could tip the balance. In 1970, there were 89 apple farms in Columbia County. Today, according to the State Agriculture and Markets Department, there are fewer than half that number. An orchard across Route 9H from Talavera, owned by the Hotaling family, recently went out of business. Today, Philip Orchards is one of the last commercial orchards in town.</p>
        <p>Ms. Philip's mother lives at Talavera and manages the farm. The siblings help out on weekends and vacations. At apple picking time, which is just ending, the whole family takes cash from customers. Leila Philip is married to the artist Garth Evans and has a son, Rhys, 4. She comes down from Hamilton regularly to assist with the ''bug checks'' (looking for pests) and with pruning. Every year, she and her mother attend ''fruit school,'' run by the Cornell Cooperative Extension, where they learn about new apple breeds and pest control regulations.</p>
        <p>John Philip, a lawyer and actor in New York, cares for the formal gardens and the heritage tomatoes. In the summer, William Philip, a linguistics professor in the Netherlands, arrives to help out. Thomas Philip, a construction project manager in New York, oversees building projects. Another sibling, Katherine Chansky, a librarian in Saratoga Springs, cares for the main house.</p>
        <p>The family has struggled to repair the house and to make the orchards profitable. ''Without that kind of involvement, it would be impossible,'' Leila Philip said.</p>
        <p>Her involvement has also included delving into the family's attic -- the diaries, trunks and boxes -- and local records, a  search that turned up renegade aunts, ne'er-do-wells, Civil War heroes and a secret love child, the result of a relationship between her grandfather and a maid at Talavera. Ms. Philip, who previously wrote ''The Road Through Miyama,'' about her apprenticeship to a master Korean potter in Japan,  then sat down to write ''A Family Place: A Hudson Valley Farm, Three Generations, Five Wars, One Family,'' published by Viking Press. A review in Publishers' Weekly  called it ''an exquisite rendering of a Hudson Valley family farm, as detailed and colored as a Persian miniature.''</p>
        <p>The book begins with a scene that evokes the powerful hold of the house upon the family: ''Before me stood Talavera, but all around was darkness,'' Ms. Philip writes. ''Light was spewing out from so many of the tall windows that the house could have been a ship sailing the night sea.''</p>
        <p>Elsewhere she calls the house ''that grand vessel of the past.'' Ms. Philip's family arrived in America in 1669, when a Dutch admiral, Adrian Van Ness, settled near Albany. His descendant Willem founded the family farm in Claverack, with a Dutch-style farmhouse.</p>
        <p>Over the years, the Van Nesses married into Hudson Valley aristocracy, the Livingstons, the Philipses of Philmont, the Stottses of Stottville. In 1807, Willem's grandson, William W. Van Ness, a judge in the New York State Supreme Court, built Talavera, named after the Battle of Talavera de la Reina in Spain, Napoleon's famous land defeat by the British.</p>
        <p>Talavera was built in the neoclassical style favored by the English, instead of the reigning Dutch style in Claverack. Its formal gardens were laid out like an English estate, with a gradual flowing of park land into farmland. Trees were planted deliberately to create areas of light and dark. A lilac walkway and a cedar walk were added.</p>
        <p>Today, the estate has been reduced to less than half its former size. And despite the Philip family's effort to support Talavera through selling apples (and selling off a  Gilbert Stuart portrait of Ms. Philip's ancestor Gen. John P. Van Ness), the 15-room house is something of a grand ruin. The wallpaper is peeling, the upholstery on the furniture is torn, the rugs are threadbare. Some parts of the house, including the dining room, still have no electricity.</p>
        <p>Ms. Philip rationalizes that doing work on the house could risk destroying Talavera's historical integrity. ''Sometimes the worst thing you can do to an old house is repair it,'' she said. ''Everything needs to be done by people who have a historical background. There are not that many carpenters who even know how to put a base on the big columns on the front.''</p>
        <p>The house's very authenticity led the New York company of Brunschwig &amp; Fils in the 1980's to copy the 1812 French wallpaper in the dining room. In exchange for the copyright on a design the company called Talavera, it gave the Philip family enough wallpaper to do the dining room. (Beige Talavera wallpaper is still available from Brunschwig for $47 a roll.) Much more remains to be done for Talavera, including rewiring, replastering and new plumbing.</p>
        <p>Friends have pitched in to help. In May of last year, at the family's annual apple blossom picnic, one friend presented the family with a copy of the Gilbert Stuart portrait, to hang in the dining room, right where the original once hung.</p>
        <p>The family is struggling to decide what to do when Mrs. Philip is unable to run the farm anymore. In the event of her death,  ''then, we are at a critical juncture,'' Ms. Philip said. The agreement among the siblings could be broken, the land could be sold.</p>
        <p>Still, this year there was a good apple harvest, she said. ''The economics are definitely year by year. But we've learned we can get through a really hard time,'' she said, ''and we're still here.''</p>
        <p>House Proud</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
