<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seidman Asks Stiffer Bank Curbs</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="436815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL DEPOSIT INSURANCE CORP (FDIC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEIDMAN, L WILLIAM (CHMN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LABATON, STEPHEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DE133DF931A25757C0A967958260" item-length="1163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seidman Asks Stiffer Bank Curbs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LABATON, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>L. William Seidman, the nation's senior banking regulator, asked Congress today to reverse sharply the deregulatory trend of the last two decades and adopt a law that would make it harder for banks to issue loans for construction and purchases of raw land and other real estate.</p>
        <p>Whether or not Congress acts, the pronouncements alone by Mr. Seidman, chairman of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, are expected to reduce credit further in already tight markets for certain real estate loans. Analysts expect that his recommendation will translate into a tougher stance toward such loans by Government examiners, who have the authority to impose restrictions on the institutions they supervise to insure their safety and soundness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>L. William Seidman, the nation's senior banking regulator, asked Congress today to reverse sharply the deregulatory trend of the last two decades and adopt a law that would make it harder for banks to issue loans for construction and purchases of raw land and other real estate.</p>
        <p>Whether or not Congress acts, the pronouncements alone by Mr. Seidman, chairman of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, are expected to reduce credit further in already tight markets for certain real estate loans. Analysts expect that his recommendation will translate into a tougher stance toward such loans by Government examiners, who have the authority to impose restrictions on the institutions they supervise to insure their safety and soundness.</p>
        <p>Appearing today before the House Banking Committee, Mr. Seidman attributed much of the blame for the current banking crisis to a loosening of the banking laws in 1974 and 1982, as well as a laxness among regulators, that enabled banks to make real estate loans that have since turned into monumental losses in several regions of the country, notably the Southwest and the Northeast. Before 1974, banks had been restricted in making such loans.</p>
        <p>"It is time for insured institutions to return to old-fashioned standards of safe and sound banking," Mr. Seidman said. "The restrictions lifted by Congress in 1974 and 1982 should be reinstated."  Treasury Officials Disagree</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Mr. Seidman has delivered several speeches before bank and savings and loan organizations stressing the need for caution in real estate lending. That position has put him at odds with Treasury officials, who declined to include his proposal in their plan to overhaul the banking system that was presented last month.</p>
        <p>The Treasury officials said in their presentation to Congress that statutory prohibitions on certain types of bank loans would only aggravate problems that have arisen from already stingy lending for commercial real estate.</p>
        <p>The Treasury Department has responded to criticism from bankers and other businesses about the tight lending by seeking to ease accounting standards to coax banks to extend more credit. Both the General Accounting Office and some lawmakers have attacked this approach.</p>
        <p>It is too early to tell how receptive Congress will be toward Mr. Seidman's proposal to restrict lending.</p>
        <p>In a sign that he was leaning toward endorsing such a move, the House Banking Committee chairman, Henry B. Gonzalez, Democrat of Texas, said at today's hearing that he had voted against the legislation in 1982 that had eased restrictions on lending practices and was troubled by the enormous amount of real estate lending by the banks.</p>
        <p>Senator Donald W. Riegle Jr., the Michigan Democrat who is chairman of the Senate Banking Committee, is said to be considering throwing his support behind restricting certain kinds of real estate loans.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, real estate and banking lobbyists are expected to wage a hard campaign to keep the law from changing.</p>
        <p>"Our initial reaction is that this does nothing to address today's paramount crisis, which is the credit crunch," said Steven A. Wechsler, president of the National Realty Committee, a trade organization in Washington representing developers and other business executives involved in real estate. "These suggestions address what could be tomorrow's problem if history repeats itself. Today's problem is the credit crisis."</p>
        <p>"I do find it interesting that in 1982, when these statutory restrictions were lifted, they were done to provide the regulators with flexible and realistic standards," he added. "Given the fact that the flexibility has been available, it's not clear what legislation would do."  'Paying the Consequences'</p>
        <p>In his testimony today, Mr. Seidman said the F.D.I.C. "has been paying the consequences" ever since Congress and the White House decided in 1974 and 1982 to ease restrictions on real estate lending. The rising number of bank failures has left the fund that protects deposits at its lowest ratio to deposits since its creation in 1934. Mr. Seidman today reiterated his prediction that the fund would probably not be insolvent this year unless the economy failed to recover in the next few months. Many economists and officials have forecast an upturn.</p>
        <p>"There may be a time when the taxpayer has to pick up the bill," Mr. Seidman said of the federally guaranteed fund. "I do not believe we have arrived at that point now, and I hope we never arrive at that point."</p>
        <p>Mr. Seidman said that whether any new borrowing to keep the bank insurance fund afloat would come from the Treasury or the Federal Reserve was "of secondary significance." The Administration has sought to have $25 billion of the $70 billion in new borrowing authority that the White House has requested be available from the Fed. But some senior Fed officials say that using the central bank for a possible taxpayer bailout sets a bad precedent. The General Accounting Office has also come out against tapping the Fed.</p>
        <p>In recent months, Mr. Seidman, who has enjoyed a strong reputation in Congress, has come under increasing political pressure as the bank insurance fund's problems have grown. Many members of Congress continue to praise him. But some lawmakers have begun to draw comparisons between him and M. Danny Wall, the former head of the Federal Home Loan Bank Board, who has been accused of failing to adequately warn Congress of the growing problems of the savings and loan industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seidman, who will be 70 years old at the end of the month, has deflected the comparisons with good humor. Introducing his wife to the committee today, he remarked, "I think she came to watch the slaughter."</p>
        <p>He has also declined to pin down his plans, other than to say he expects to leave before his term expires. His term is scheduled to end in October, but the F.D.I.C. has obtained a legal opinion that an ambiguity in the law may allow him to continue serving through February 1993.  Three Changes Criticized</p>
        <p>In his testimony, Mr. Seidman cited three changes in the banking laws that he said contributed significantly to the current banking crisis. The changes, many of which came under the Garn-St Germain Act of 1982, permitted nationally chartered banks to make loans on raw land; allowed loans on construction projects even when the builder contributed less than 25 percent equity, and eliminated restrictions on a bank's total real estate loan portfolio.</p>
        <p>"In the three years following the passage of the Garn-St Germain Act, construction and land development loans by Texas commercial banks doubled as a percentage of assets and nearly tripled in dollar terms," Mr. Seidman said.</p>
        <p>Congressional aides noted today that the savings and loan bailout legislation adopted in 1989 had restricted some forms of real estate lending and that Congress was likely to be similarly inclined to impose some restrictions on banks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
