<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Arsenal</title>
    <meta content="30food-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1779374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santopietro, Jill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E1DD153FF933A05754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Arsenal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jill Santopietro</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santopietro, Jill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recipes for Asian version of chicken wings and sweet-and-spicy baked one</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The key to cooking chicken wings is to get the meat tender and the skin crisp. Eating them poses an altogether different challenge. It requires a certain comfort level with stickiness -- plus a heap of wet wipes and some dexterity with your teeth. An aficionado in Indianapolis invented ''the Smash,'' a technique for removing the two bones of the flat with one easy swipe, leaving just the meat and skin for dipping. You can find instructions at www.cluckbucket.com/techniques/smash.htm. (It works, but wait until they cool slightly before trying it.) Smashing isn't for everyone: to many, the messy payoff is worth all the nibbling, especially with these two recipes, an Asian version and a sweet-and-spicy baked one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The key to cooking chicken wings is to get the meat tender and the skin crisp. Eating them poses an altogether different challenge. It requires a certain comfort level with stickiness -- plus a heap of wet wipes and some dexterity with your teeth. An aficionado in Indianapolis invented ''the Smash,'' a technique for removing the two bones of the flat with one easy swipe, leaving just the meat and skin for dipping. You can find instructions at www.cluckbucket.com/techniques/smash.htm. (It works, but wait until they cool slightly before trying it.) Smashing isn't for everyone: to many, the messy payoff is worth all the nibbling, especially with these two recipes, an Asian version and a sweet-and-spicy baked one.</p>
        <p>Fried Sambal Wings With Cucumber Cream</p>
        <p>1/2 cup yuzu juice</p>
        <p>1/2 cup kosher salt, plus more as needed</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons sugar</p>
        <p>18 chicken wings, about 3 * pounds, wing tips removed, each wing cut in half</p>
        <p>6 1/2 tablespoons unsalted butter</p>
        <p>1/4 cup sambal</p>
        <p>1/4 cup sriracha hot sauce</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon rice-wine vinegar</p>
        <p>1/2 English cucumber, quartered lengthwise and seeded</p>
        <p>1 4-inch piece ginger</p>
        <p>1 cup sour cream</p>
        <p>1 quart vegetable oil.</p>
        <p>1. Make the brine by combining the yuzu juice, 1/2 cup salt, sugar and 2 quarts water in a container large enough to hold the wings. Stir until the salt and sugar dissolve. Add the wings and refrigerate overnight. Rinse well and pat dry.</p>
        <p>2. In a small saucepan over low heat, combine the butter, sambal, hot sauce and vinegar. Simmer for a few minutes, stirring occasionally. Transfer to a blender and purée until smooth.</p>
        <p>3. Cut the cucumber crosswise into -inch-thick pieces. Sprinkle them lightly with salt and let them sit for 10 minutes. Pat dry with a towel. Grate the ginger over a towel or cheesecloth and squeeze out 2 tablespoons juice into a bowl. Add 1/2 teaspoon salt to the juice, then combine with the sour cream and cucumber. Season to taste.</p>
        <p>4. Pour 2 inches of oil in a 10*-by-4-inch pot and place over high heat. When the oil reaches 375 degrees, fry the chicken wings in batches. Cook for about 15 minutes, or until nicely browned. Transfer wings to a bowl. Toss with hot sauce. Serve with cucumber cream. Serves 6 as an appetizer. Adapted from Taku restaurant in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>NOTE: If yuzu juice is unavailable, use 6 tablespoons fresh lemon juice and 2 tablespoons fresh lime juice, plus the zest from 1 lemon and 1 lime.</p>
        <p>Malaysian Chicken Wings</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons cumin</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons fennel seed</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon plus 1 teaspoon coriander seed</p>
        <p>4 1/2 dried Thai bird chilies</p>
        <p>1 cup kecap manis (sweet Indonesian soy sauce), preferably ABC brand</p>
        <p>1/2 cup fish sauce</p>
        <p>1/2 cup light soy sauce</p>
        <p>1/2 cup sugar</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon red food coloring, optional</p>
        <p>1 1 1/2 -inch piece ginger, peeled and thinly sliced</p>
        <p>3 cloves garlic, thinly sliced</p>
        <p>12 whole chicken wings, about 2 1/2 pounds.</p>
        <p>1. In a small sauté pan over low heat, toast the cumin, fennel seed, coriander seed and chilies, then grind them in a spice (or coffee) grinder.</p>
        <p>2. In a large bowl, combine the kecap manis, fish sauce, soy sauce, sugar and food coloring, if using. Add the ground spices, ginger and garlic. Stir until the sugar has dissolved. Put the chicken wings in a container large enough to hold the wings and sauce. Pour the sauce over the wings and toss to coat. Place a piece of parchment paper over the wings, then top with a plate to keep them submerged. Refrigerate for 24 to 48 hours, stirring occasionally.</p>
        <p>3. Preheat the oven to 375 degrees. Place a wire rack on a parchment-lined baking sheet. Lay the wings, skin side down, on the rack. Cook for 20 to 25 minutes.</p>
        <p>4. Bring the marinade to a boil in a heavy-bottomed saucepan. Lower the heat and simmer until it reduces by about half into a thick glaze. Strain through a fine sieve into a large bowl. Add half of the aromatics in the sieve back into the glaze and stir. Toss the cooked wings in the glaze. Serves 4 as an appetizer. Adapted from Fatty Crab in New York.</p>
        <p>For a recipe for classic Buffalo wings, go to nytimes.com/magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
