<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Move Over, New Jersey. New Trend Puts the Con in Connecticut.</title>
    <meta content="30TOWN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/30/nyregion/30TOWN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1539481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Our Towns"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Richard Lezin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EED8133AF933A05752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Move Over, New Jersey. New Trend Puts the Con in Connecticut.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Move Over, New Jersey. New Trend Puts the Con in Connecticut.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD LEZIN JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Richard Lezin</byline>
      <dateline>BRIDGEPORT, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Lezin Jones Our Towns column contends that wave of scandals plaguing Connecticut politics could put state ahead of New Jersey, which has long history of government corruption (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT may have been just wishful thinking, but from his humble perch along a worn-down stretch of Main Street here -- where the burglar bars in abandoned storefronts protect empty showrooms -- Emanuel Cannon swore that his beloved, bedraggled city was on the verge of something resembling a renaissance.</p>
        <p>''Yeah,'' said Mr. Cannon, 56, a manager at the One Stop News and Deli. ''Things were going all right, the mayor was doing good. Then you started hearing all this stuff about bribes and racketeering.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Refined Connecticut is challenging the Garden State for an unwanted mark of distinction in the region: the state with the most dysfunctional politicians.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT may have been just wishful thinking, but from his humble perch along a worn-down stretch of Main Street here -- where the burglar bars in abandoned storefronts protect empty showrooms -- Emanuel Cannon swore that his beloved, bedraggled city was on the verge of something resembling a renaissance.</p>
        <p>''Yeah,'' said Mr. Cannon, 56, a manager at the One Stop News and Deli. ''Things were going all right, the mayor was doing good. Then you started hearing all this stuff about bribes and racketeering.''</p>
        <p>In Connecticut? Who knew? It turned out that Bridgeport's former mayor, Joseph P. Ganim, was shaking down contractors who wanted to do business with the city, raking in home renovations, expensive wines and a half-million dollars in cash.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ganim, convicted in March on 16 counts of corruption, is now serving a nine-year prison term. Mr. Cannon's dreams of a rebirth for Bridgeport, however fanciful, were delayed. And the city's woes -- a high unemployment rate, soaring taxes, dismal schools -- continued.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ganim's transgressions may be helping to give otherwise refined Connecticut an unexpected and unwanted mark of distinction in the region: the state with the most dysfunctional politicians.</p>
        <p>For years, New Jersey's dominance in government corruption -- as is the case with its cranberry production and proliferation of jug-handle turns on the highway -- has been widely accepted. There was a period over the past few years when prosecutors averaged an indictment a month. But to hear political scientists and other observers tell it, a series of high-profile corruption cases in Connecticut may be challenging the Garden State's supremacy in ignominy.</p>
        <p>''It may not be the classic, New Jersey style of corruption, with the mobsters, the bold suits and guys with gold chains driving big cars,'' said Christopher Barnes, the associate director of the University of Connecticut's Center for Survey Research and Analysis. ''But what's happening here is something all its own.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barnes was referring to an earlier model of malfeasance -- with apologies to Tony Soprano, the mob's influence on government corruption is thought to have waned considerably -- and noted that today's scandals are driven largely by ''pay to play'' schemes, in which officials dangle lucrative contracts and other public work for bribes.</p>
        <p>Just consider some cases that have unfolded in recent months. There's Paul J. Silvester, the former state treasurer, who 10 days ago was sentenced to 51 months in prison for accepting bribes. Waterbury's former mayor, Philip A. Giordano, was sentenced in June to 37 years in jail after wiretappers learned that he was having sex with two girls, ages 8 and 10. Lawrence E. Alibozek, a former aide to Gov. John G. Rowland, admitted to accepting bribes for helping to put the fix in for state contracts.</p>
        <p>In response to cases like those, Connecticut's chief state's attorney, Christopher L. Morano, last week announced the creation of a toll-free number -- (888) 742-2726, reachable only in Connecticut -- that allows callers to report corruption anonymously.</p>
        <p>Despite appearances, Mr. Barnes said that the recent cases were not necessarily a sign of an increase in corruption, but may simply be the most recent crest of waves of official misconduct that have ebbed and flowed here for decades.</p>
        <p>ALTHOUGH he noted that most corruption still centers on cash bribes or expensive gifts, Mr. Barnes said that Mr. Giordano's transgressions belonged to a different realm. ''There's been the disgusting category with Giordano, that's a whole other level of corruption,'' Mr. Barnes said. The former mayor was first singled out over suspicions about the cost of projects like sewage treatment plants and animal shelters.</p>
        <p>''They made more money per square foot on this dog pound,'' he said. ''It's like if Imelda Marcos had a dog pound.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barnes said that he wasn't sure how effective the toll-free number might be. But he said that it might yet yield a few surprise scandals in a state where he noted that misconduct is unexpected for other reasons besides Connecticut's modishness and manners. Said Mr. Barnes: ''People joke that the state's just too boring to have this kind of corruption.''</p>
        <p>Our Towns</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
