<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reynolds and St. John's Overcome Distractions</title>
    <meta content="30STOR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/30/sports/ncaabasketball/30STOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1539517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St John's University (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">State University of New York at Stony Brook</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dicker, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">St John's University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">State University of New York at Stony Brook</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reynolds, Grady</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3D6133AF933A05752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reynolds and St. John's Overcome Distractions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reynolds and St. Johns Overcome Distractions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON DICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dicker, Ron</byline>
      <dateline>STONY BROOK, N.Y., Nov. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>St John's University defeats Stony Brook University, 72-61; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Grady Reynolds, a senior forward for St. John's, knows about performing when off-court matters take precedence. He played all of last season while facing an assault charge before the matter was resolved over the summer.</p>
        <p>So on Saturday night, with St. John's playing its first game without the senior guard Willie Shaw, who was suspended for the second time after his arrest on a marijuana possession charge, Reynolds helped the Red Storm turn what could have been a morale killer into a mere distraction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Grady Reynolds scored a career-high 26 points on 13-of-17 shooting and St. Johns avoided its first 0-3 start since 1917 by beating Stony Brook.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Grady Reynolds, a senior forward for St. John's, knows about performing when off-court matters take precedence. He played all of last season while facing an assault charge before the matter was resolved over the summer.</p>
        <p>So on Saturday night, with St. John's playing its first game without the senior guard Willie Shaw, who was suspended for the second time after his arrest on a marijuana possession charge, Reynolds helped the Red Storm turn what could have been a morale killer into a mere distraction.</p>
        <p>Reynolds scored a career-high 26 points on 13-of-17 shooting and St. John's avoided its first 0-3 start since 1917 by beating Stony Brook, 72-61, before a crowd of 3,765 at the Indoor Sports Complex.</p>
        <p>After two sloppy defeats, St. John's (1-2) could not take any game for granted, even if the Red Storm had beaten the Seawolves (1-3) by an average of more than 25 points in their previous four encounters. Shaw's arrest with the former St. John's star Marcus Hatten in Queens on Tuesday would only make things tougher. Or would it?</p>
        <p>''Basically it's been the same,'' Reynolds said. ''We've focused on practice and on going to class.''</p>
        <p>The verbal support came from the senior guard Andre Stanley, who emphasized ending the losing streak, not erasing Shaw from their minds.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to get the monkey off our back,'' Stanley said. ''Just win and let everything take care of itself.''</p>
        <p>Stanley benefited the most from Shaw's absence, scoring 13 points from his teammate's wing position.</p>
        <p>Shaw's status has not changed, Coach Mike Jarvis said. He is off the team indefinitely after Queens detectives said they found a marijuana cigarette and a bag of marijuana in a car he and Hatten were driving on Tuesday. Jarvis said he suspended Shaw for reasons other than the arrest, though they were related. He did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>Calling Shaw one of his children, Jarvis said he pledged his support until the day Shaw graduates, ''whether or not he plays another minute for St. John's.''</p>
        <p>''We are more concerned about Willie right now as a person than a basketball game,'' Jarvis said. ''We hope that Willie will learn and grow like the rest of us.''</p>
        <p>The Red Storm learned quickly Saturday that it was taller and faster than Stony Brook but required nearly the whole game to put the Seawolves away. Despite shooting 61.5 percent in the first half, St. John's led by only 35-33. Ahead by 63-59 with 2 minutes 23 seconds to go, St. John's outscored Stony Brook by 7-2 the rest of the way. The sophomore guard Elijah Ingram (15 points) dribbled the final nine seconds away.</p>
        <p>D. J. Munir had 15 points for Stony Brook, but Reynolds was able to stifle the Seawolves' upset bid with athletic play rarely seen in this gym.</p>
        <p>In the summer, Reynolds settled charges that he had struck a female student by taking anger-management classes. Now he might be the Red Storm's best hope of making a star-free team respectable.</p>
        <p>Shaw, from Kennedy High School in the Bronx, averaged 13.8 points as a freshman, but he averaged 4.5 points in his two games this season.</p>
        <p>Asked how the team responded to adversity this week, the often-philosophical Jarvis said, ''I like to hope that once again every day carries its own life, its own identity.''</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
