<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can Goat Meat Be The Next Cash Crop?</title>
    <meta content="30NJGOAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1539450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="NEW JERSEY &amp; COMPANY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Goats</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldblatt, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE3D8133AF933A05752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1430" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can Goat Meat Be The Next Cash Crop?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER GOLDBLATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldblatt, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>AUGUSTA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on nascent goat meat market in New Jersey; New Jersey State Meat Goat Assn, with help of $31,320 grant from US Agriculture Department, hopes to develop education program for farmers, quality standards and marketing venues for goat meat; state reportedly has largest concentration of annual goat slaughters in country; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TUCKED in the hilly northwest corner of Sussex County, where rusty silos share the land with freshly minted custom homes, Sean Gebauer sees New Jersey's next farming opportunity.</p>
        <p>Seventeen female goats huddle around a hayrack in front of him, jostling for access. Some of them lodge their entire heads into the hay for the maximum serving size.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TUCKED in the hilly northwest corner of Sussex County, where rusty silos share the land with freshly minted custom homes, Sean Gebauer sees New Jersey's next farming opportunity.</p>
        <p>Seventeen female goats huddle around a hayrack in front of him, jostling for access. Some of them lodge their entire heads into the hay for the maximum serving size.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people aren't aware that the goat market is there,'' Mr. Gebauer said on a recent visit. ''We're just not meeting it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gebauer belongs to a group of local farmers who are trying to make the goat New Jersey's next piece of agricultural pride and joy. They want to serve more of the 47 million pounds of goat meat consumed in the United States and develop standards for raising the animals that will merit the livestock equivalent of the name brand, Jersey Fresh.</p>
        <p>''If we can raise goats on farms in New Jersey and direct market them to consumers, we can get a higher return to farmers and keep open space and farmland preserved,'' said Dan Wunderlich, an agricultural consultant who helped form the New Jersey State Meat Goat Association last year. With the help of a $31,320 grant from the United States Department of Agriculture, they hope to develop an education program for farmers, quality standards and marketing venues for goat meat.</p>
        <p>Proponents say New Jersey could be the ideal breeding ground for such a venture. After all, New Jersey has the largest concentration of annual goat slaughters in the country, according to the Agriculture Department. And the state is surrounded by the most prevalent goat consumers: the estimated 750,000 Muslims who live in New York and northern New Jersey, along with sizable immigrant populations from Latin American and Caribbean countries.</p>
        <p>Until now, that demand has been met by Australia and New Zealand, which supply about 35 percent of the goat consumed in the United States, according to the American Meat Goat Association, based in Sonora, Tex. Texas dominates domestic goat meat production, and New Jersey ranks a paltry 27th in goat meat sales, Agriculture Department figures show.</p>
        <p>But as local immigrant populations swell, many say that could quickly change.</p>
        <p>''New Jersey people don't realize that they're sitting on a tremendous gold mine,'' said Dr. Robert Herr, a consultant and goat broker in Narvon, Pa. ''All these goats are coming in from different places and the local farms could be filling the demand themselves. In our economic times, goats are one of the bright spots.''</p>
        <p>For New Jersey's farmers, goats are appealing for two main reasons: they provide a new market with low barriers to entry, and for livestock they lead a relatively low-maintenance lifestyle.</p>
        <p>Goats only need a fraction of the acreage of larger animals. About five of them could occupy the two acres it would take to accommodate one cow and require just a few daily feedings, Mr. Wunderlich of the meat goat association explained. He said a farmer could start a herd of the popular Boer goats with a male and a female that each cost about $600.</p>
        <p>Moreover, goats are not particularly picky eaters, and help rid farmland of nuisance vegetation. While sheep and cows graze down grassy pastures, goats are known as browsers. They have no qualms about browsing through a poison ivy patch for a feast or scarfing down briar-covered multiflora rose bushes.</p>
        <p>And for many farming families, goats are both pets and meat. They come when you call them, and they like to be petted.</p>
        <p>Florence, one of the 13 goats owned by Paula Schafer, who lives just across the Delaware River in Dingmans Ferry, Pa., breeds or shows at the New Jersey State Fair, likes to ride around town in the front seat of her daughter's Ford pickup. ''They've got great personalities,'' Ms. Schafer said. ''They like to be with you.''</p>
        <p>Culinary experts say that there is a potentially hefty appetite for a New Jersey-bred goat.</p>
        <p>Because the meat is as high in protein as beef and chicken but lower in fat, according to the Agriculture Department's research service, it would be an easy sell to the well-heeled eating public that is infatuated with precocious cuisine as well as the low-carbohydrate, protein-intensive Atkins diet.</p>
        <p>The meat, which is sometimes sold as Chevon (a name rooted in ''chevre,'' the French term for goat), has an approachable flavor and texture that chefs place somewhere between beef and lamb.</p>
        <p>''It's doesn't taste barn-yardy in any way,'' said Tina Ujlaki, executive food editor of Food and Wine magazine, who speculated that goat could easily make its way into the mainstream just as buffalo meat has in the last decade. ''Do I think it could become the next buffalo? Absolutely.''</p>
        <p>Goat is already a staple in many Muslim homes. The animal is commonly sacrificed and served during Eid al-Adha, the festival that marks Abraham's willingness to sacrifice his son in response to a command from God, as it is written in the Koran. The meat is often roasted in a curry sauce and served with rice.</p>
        <p>In Jamaican cuisine, curried goat kid is standard fare. In Latin American venues, Seco de Chivo, an Ecuadorian braised goat stew, is often served. And capretto, a slow-roasted baby goat, has become the signature dish at L'Impero, an Italian restaurant in Manhattan. When Scott Conant, the chef, opened last year, he said he was buying about three goats a week, each of which could make about 24 portions. Now, his weekly goat buy is 14.</p>
        <p>''It's really taken on a life of its own,'' said Mr. Conant, who gets his goat from a cooperative in Vermont. ''For that to happen, without going out and pushing it, just putting it on the menu, kind of says it.''</p>
        <p>James Laird, chef and owner of Restaurant Serenade in Chatham, said he would like to add goat to his market menu, which now includes soup made from Vineland asparagus and organic pork from Pittstown.</p>
        <p>''Everyone knows that something that comes from your backyard is going to be fresher,'' said Mr. Laird, who noted that goat could also help keep his cuisine on the cutting edge.</p>
        <p>''That's the whole thing for marketing a restaurant,'' he said, ''bringing new and creative ideas to the customers without being gimmicky.''</p>
        <p>But a chef's inventions can go only so far. ''You can't create a new animal,'' Mr. Laird said. ''God only created so many.''</p>
        <p>For the state, the goat meat drive fits into a continuing endeavor to diversify the Jersey Fresh brand, which includes blueberries, honey and nearly 80 other products. The state's Department of Agriculture recently developed the Jersey Bred label, the livestock version of Jersey Fresh, under which thoroughbred horses and goat could be sold. It also recently obtained a $79,070 grant from the United States Department of Agriculture to study the market for produce used by various ethnic groups.</p>
        <p>State officials hope these efforts will help protect New Jersey farmland.</p>
        <p>''Our producers have a hard time in some areas of the commodity marketplace because of the high cost of doing business in a densely populated market like ours,'' Agriculture Secretary Charles Kuperus said. ''We need to be innovating and seeking out new markets in order to sustain their agricultural operations.''</p>
        <p>For now, the demand is certainly there. The American Meat Goat Association says domestic goat consumption has quadrupled since 1997.</p>
        <p>But some say that local suppliers will have a hard time profiting from goats, given the higher cost of land, feed and taxes compared with other states. Goat development programs have already sprung up in Alabama, Maine, Ohio and South Carolina. Other countries may also boost goat meat exports, said Marvin Shurley, president of the association.</p>
        <p>''If and when it happens,'' Mr. Shurley said, ''it's going to have an effect on the prices our producers see.''</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY &amp; COMPANY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
