<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Cruise Web Sites Are So 20th Century</title>
    <meta content="20prac" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/20/travel/20prac.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20051127T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1718890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER: THE INTERNET"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reservations (Airlines, Hotels, Etc)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel Agencies and Agents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trucco, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reservations (Airlines, Hotels, Etc)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Agencies and Agents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFDE103EF933A15752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1299" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Cruise Web Sites Are So 20th Century</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Why Cruise Web Sites Are So 20th Century</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY TRUCCO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Trucco, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Terry Trucco Practical Traveler column on problems with cruise line Web sites; complaints include online customer service, difficulty in researching shipboard activities and limited online booking; cruise lines, more than almost any segment of travel industry, still depend upon travel agents; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHY are cruise Web sites so lousy? Despite the boom in the Internet, particularly when it comes to travel, most cruise lines have yet to embrace the online world. While many lines use their Web sites to publish last-minute deals, only a handful offer passengers online booking, and researching a cruise -- whether it's trying to find an itinerary or the layout of staterooms -- can be an exercise in frustration.</p>
        <p>Judi Brownell, a professor at the Cornell Hotel School who follows the cruise industry and has taken six cruises since January, said she often ends up making calls to book cruises, when she would rather complete the transaction on her computer. ''If I wanted to call an 800 number or speak to a travel agent, I wouldn't be online,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because booking a cruise is more complicated than booking a flight, cruise lines have long depended on travel agents. Now some cruise lines are starting to embrace the Web.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHY are cruise Web sites so lousy? Despite the boom in the Internet, particularly when it comes to travel, most cruise lines have yet to embrace the online world. While many lines use their Web sites to publish last-minute deals, only a handful offer passengers online booking, and researching a cruise -- whether it's trying to find an itinerary or the layout of staterooms -- can be an exercise in frustration.</p>
        <p>Judi Brownell, a professor at the Cornell Hotel School who follows the cruise industry and has taken six cruises since January, said she often ends up making calls to book cruises, when she would rather complete the transaction on her computer. ''If I wanted to call an 800 number or speak to a travel agent, I wouldn't be online,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Professor Brownell isn't alone. Just 37 percent of 2,000 participants in a recent interactive test of travel industry Web sites found cruise line sites to be satisfactory, according to Keynote Systems, a company that analyzes e-businesses.</p>
        <p>''The sheer number of people who experienced frustration on the cruise line sites was high, especially when compared to lodging and airline sites,'' said Bonny Brown, director of research at Keynote, in San Mateo, Calif. Complaints include online customer service, difficulty in researching shipboard activities and, at the top of the list, limited online booking.</p>
        <p>Some cruise lines, however, are trying to change. Many, notably Royal Caribbean and Celebrity, provide full or partial check-in online. Crystal was among the first to offer online reservations for shipboard classes, specialty restaurants, and spa appointments; Silversea recently introduced a similar feature. Princess, which had already offered excursion booking, has unveiled a feature allowing viewers to compare up to three cruises at a time, based on such criteria as itinerary and price. Next year, Radisson Seven Seas will introduce a tool for booking cruises.</p>
        <p>Still, for travelers accustomed to buying flights and hotels online, it seems downright puzzling that Internet booking is not offered by more cruise lines, especially since online agencies like Expedia and Travelocity book cruises. But more than almost any segment of the travel industry, cruise lines still depend upon travel agents.</p>
        <p>The sites are designed primarily to be like instant brochures, said Terry L. Dale, president of the Cruise Line Industry Association. Because a cruise is a more complex product than a flight or a hotel room, ''the cruise industry will always encourage consumers to work with an agent,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That dependency on agents means cruise lines have been slow to produce top-notch sites. ''Having a great site wasn't a strategic issue since the cruise lines have used agents to sell their product,'' said Scott Barry, a cruise line analyst with Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
        <p>Nor have cruise lines been eager to alienate the sales force they have relied upon for decades by encouraging online sales, he said. Airlines and hotels, of course, once depended heavily upon travel agents. ''Particulars aside, the cruise industry typically tends to lag behind hotels and airlines,'' Mr. Barry said.</p>
        <p>The close relationship between cruise lines and travel agents is rooted in cruising's multifaceted nature. It requires choices of ship, itinerary, stateroom, dining options and often flight and lodging connections, and so lends itself to sit-down sessions with a agent.</p>
        <p>For first-time cruisers in particular, industry experts say, it is important to have an agent explain how things work. A good agent will match you with the right ship, a key decision since ships and cruise lines have distinctive personalities.</p>
        <p>''The most frequent complaint I hear is that the ship did not meet expectations, and that's because people didn't understand what they were purchasing,'' said Linda Coffman, editor of Cruisediva.com, a Web site that posts reader reviews of ships.</p>
        <p>Cruise lines, meanwhile, like having travel agents act as buffers between themselves and passengers. According to Brian Major, a spokesman for the Cruise Line Industry Association, the average number of calls made by each cruiser is in the double digits. Agents provide a vital service for the lines, which, he said, ''are not equipped to process the number of questions people have before taking a cruise.''</p>
        <p>Passengers who work with agents often receive incentives, as they often do when booking a hotel room. Free shore excursions and stateroom upgrades are among the possible perks, said Carolyn Spencer Brown, editor of cruisecritic.com.</p>
        <p>Cruise lines, meanwhile, offer agents powerful incentives. While a 10 percent commission is widely accepted as the base, they can exceed 17 percent, experts say.</p>
        <p>In contrast, most major airlines did away with commissions to agents in 2002, though some quietly pay negotiated commissions to online agencies or to specific travel agents, according to a spokesman for the Airline Reporting Corporation.</p>
        <p>But aspects of this delicate ecosystem could change as passengers demand online booking. Travel agents, including online agents like Orbitz and Cruisedirect, now book 90 percent of all cruises, according to the industry association. But Mr. Barry predicts that by 2008, direct sales will rise, shrinking agent reservations to 75 percent.</p>
        <p>''The growth in short cruises from drive-to ports lends itself to direct distribution,'' he said. ''And once people cruise, they have a propensity to book direct the next time.''</p>
        <p>Sophisticated Web sites with direct booking are of particular importance if cruise lines want to attract younger passengers. Ms. Brown of Keynote points out that the people most comfortable using the Web are under 40. ''Cruise lines risk being left behind if they don't improve their sites,'' she said.</p>
        <p>This past summer, aasyCruise, a new budget line based in London, relied upon online bookings to lure cruisers in their 20's, 30's and 40's on its ship in the Mediterranean. Online sales help the company trim costs and raise or lower prices in synch with demand, according to James Rothnie, director of corporate affairs for easyGroup.</p>
        <p>''The younger audience we targeted lives on the Internet,'' he said. The company had occupancy rates of 80 percent and above and is considering a second ship, Mr. Rothnie said.</p>
        <p>Still, a cruise is a cruise: Mr. Rothnie admitted the company planned to work with travel agents while its ship is in the Caribbean this winter. ''Getting to the Caribbean is a big deal, especially from the U.K., so this is an instance when you might want a travel agent to coordinate flights, transfers and hotels, ''Mr. Rothnie said.</p>
        <p>Among established lines, Royal Caribbean's Web site leads the pack, according to Keynote's research. Bonny Brown cited the site's clean look, easy online booking, clear pricing and smart use of images. Celebrity scored high for customer support, and Carnival for activity research.</p>
        <p>Available since 1999 on the Royal Caribbean site, online purchases account for ''less than 10 percent'' of sales, said Barbara Shrut, a Royal Caribbean vice president who until recently was in charge of e-marketing. But Mr. Barry said he believed the cruise industry is quietly gearing up for online purchases, particularly the mass market lines. ''It's like a duck on the water,'' he said. ''You don't see much, but there's a lot going on under the surface.''</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER: THE INTERNET</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 27, 2005, Sunday  Because of an editing error, the Practical Traveler column last Sunday, about cruise line Web sites, misspelled the name of a London-based line offering bookings on its site and omitted the site's address. It is easyCruise, and its Web site is www.easycruise.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 27, 2005, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, the Practical Traveler column last Sunday, about cruise line Web sites, misspelled the name of a London-based line offering bookings on its site and omitted the site's address. It is easyCruise, and its Web site is www.easycruise.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
