<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets Dig Out From Under and Win in Overtime</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="574410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN ANTONIO SPURS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY NETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, MIKE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D71E38F936A35751C1A964958260" item-length="716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets Dig Out From Under and Win in Overtime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREEMAN, MIKE</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Dec. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>People actually began leaving the arena as the Nets were trailing the San Antonio Spurs late in the game tonight. It was a mistake, because what they missed was an all-star performance by Kenny Anderson, an acrobatic shot by Drazen Petrovic that sent the contest into overtime and a huge 108-103 victory in which the Nets displayed an inordinate amount of heart. And all of it happened with their star forward, Derrick Coleman, who was out of the game because of a knee injury.</p>
        <p>The Nets, on an emotional high, left immediately after the game on a flight to Miami, where they will play the Heat tonight. But their bodies are sure to be sore. Four starters, including Anderson, had more than 40 minutes of playing time. At one point, New Jersey was down by 18 points but as forward Rick Mahorn said: "We didn't want to roll over. We were having too much fun being ourselves."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>People actually began leaving the arena as the Nets were trailing the San Antonio Spurs late in the game tonight. It was a mistake, because what they missed was an all-star performance by Kenny Anderson, an acrobatic shot by Drazen Petrovic that sent the contest into overtime and a huge 108-103 victory in which the Nets displayed an inordinate amount of heart. And all of it happened with their star forward, Derrick Coleman, who was out of the game because of a knee injury.</p>
        <p>The Nets, on an emotional high, left immediately after the game on a flight to Miami, where they will play the Heat tonight. But their bodies are sure to be sore. Four starters, including Anderson, had more than 40 minutes of playing time. At one point, New Jersey was down by 18 points but as forward Rick Mahorn said: "We didn't want to roll over. We were having too much fun being ourselves."</p>
        <p>Anderson had a career-high 17 assists. He also had a career-high 31 points and was basically Superman, playing 50 of the possible 53 minutes. By far, this was his best game as a pro. Petrovic made a slashing, falling layup right in front of giant center David Robinson that tied the score at 96 with one-tenth of a second left in regulation.</p>
        <p>Petrovic had 34 points. Forward Chris Morris had 32 points, and all he did was hit key jumper after key jumper. San Antonio's Lloyd Daniels, in a homecoming of sorts, scored 21 points. 5 Victories in a Row</p>
        <p>The result was New Jersey's fifth consecutive victory and a 9-7 record, just a half-game behind the second-place Knicks.</p>
        <p>"This shows a lot of character on our part," said Morris. "We could have laid down."</p>
        <p>What made the victory incredible was that it was accomplished without Coleman. The Nets cringed when Coleman left with 1 minute 16 seconds left in the first half with a strained ligament in his right knee. He hurt it while going for a loose ball and getting tangled with the Spurs' Antoine Carr. For several seconds, he just lay on the court, and the crowd of 15,068 at Byrne Meadowlands Arena held its breath.</p>
        <p>Team officials said Coleman would not travel to Miami and would undergo further tests. They are listing him as day to day.</p>
        <p>In the final 37.8 seconds of regulation, the Nets overcame a 94-89 deficit. Two Anderson free throws and a Petrovic 3-pointer tied it at 94. Carr was then fouled by Morris and made his two free throws. That's when Petrovic, who made five 3-pointers in the game, made his shot.</p>
        <p>"It was a real tough shot," he said. "I didn't have a lot of options. I went in and saw David Robinson in my face and just threw it up."</p>
        <p>In overtime, the teams exchanged leads until an Anderson jumper with just over two minutes remaining gave New Jersey a 104-101 lead. A Morris dunk made it 106-101 and the Nets never let go from there.</p>
        <p>Anderson said that from the beginning he kept telling his team to stay together. It was a good thing he did, because the Nets struggled for much of the game.</p>
        <p>Any time a team goes up against Admiral Robinson, there is a chance of being run out of the neighborhood. Early on, he dominated the inside lanes, blocking three shots alone in the first period. Once, when Petrovic drove the lane, Robinson swatted the ball so hard it bounced off the backboard and landed near half-court.</p>
        <p>But as scary as Robinson was (he finished with 23 points, 13 rebounds and 6 blocked shots), the biggest damage to the Nets early was accomplished by their own bench, which had trouble scoring when the starters took a breather.</p>
        <p>Yet, just when it looked as if the Nets were going to be blown away, they came back strong behind Petrovic. At one point, a Daniels short jumper made the score 67-49 in favor of the Spurs. But the Nets went on a run of their own and eventually cut the deficit to 71-64 with a Petrovic three-pointer.</p>
        <p>Petrovic then hit another 3-pointer and was fouled in the process. That made it 71-68. And in the final minutes, the Nets rallied once more.</p>
        <p>Mysteriously, Spurs Coach Jerry Tarkanian didn't make Robinson the focal point of the offense early on. By the end of the third quarter, he had just 10 points. Then, as if remembering what Robinson can do, the Spurs went to him. Almost a dozen times in the final nine minutes of regulation. But even Robinson wasn't enough to deny the Nets.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
