<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rural Flouting of One-Child Policy Undercuts China's Census</title>
    <meta content="Y14POP$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1191804"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Census</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Census</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6DC1E3EF937A25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rural Flouting of One-Child Policy Undercuts China's Census</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>LUFENG, China</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>China's excruciatingly tough one-child policy is flouted in rural areas, and large young families are scattered throughout countryside; size of rural population boom is unclear because many 'illegal' children are never officially registered; and so, as China prepares this year to conduct its once-a-decade census, true size of world's most populous country remains in doubt (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Next to an imposing government office building, at a roadside stand selling soda and toys, Lin waddles over to dust off her children, two boys ages 5 and 2, and a 3-year-old girl. She is 26, a farmer's wife, and eight months' pregnant.</p>
        <p>''Oh yes, family planning is very strict here,'' the woman, who was wary of giving her full name, said without a touch of irony. ''But fine me? There's no way. I'm a peasant and I don't really have any income. What can they do?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Next to an imposing government office building, at a roadside stand selling soda and toys, Lin waddles over to dust off her children, two boys ages 5 and 2, and a 3-year-old girl. She is 26, a farmer's wife, and eight months' pregnant.</p>
        <p>''Oh yes, family planning is very strict here,'' the woman, who was wary of giving her full name, said without a touch of irony. ''But fine me? There's no way. I'm a peasant and I don't really have any income. What can they do?''</p>
        <p>In a country best known for its excruciatingly tough one-child policy, large young families today are scattered throughout the countryside. Although, technically, rural families can have only up to two children -- and then only if the first child is a girl -- families with three, four, five or more children are now the norm in many areas, including this southern coastal region of Guangdong.</p>
        <p>The size of the rural population boom is unclear because many ''illegal'' children are born in secret, their births never officially registered. And so, as China prepares this year to conduct its once-a-decade census, the true size of the world's most populous country remains in doubt.</p>
        <p>''Underreporting in population and family planning statistics has become widespread,'' wrote Qi Lili and Li Haidong, two demographers, in a book published late last year. ''Gathering accurate data, especially data on births, has become more difficult with each passing year.''</p>
        <p>The number of illegal births has surged in some areas, experts say, in part because the family planning system has largely put an end to the coercive techniques of the past, like mandatory sterilizations or bulldozing the homes of women who disobeyed. It now relies on education and a system of ''family planning fees'' for women who have unapproved children.</p>
        <p>The relative opening of Chinese society has also diminished the system's effect: as more women move around the country to work, it is increasingly hard to monitor pregnancies. Village heads, now often elected, are less inclined to enforce an unpopular policy. And, in a country where people have more freedom -- and more money -- fees are not that strong a disincentive.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately if a couple really wants to have additional children, there's not really much you can do to stop them,'' said Chen Shengli, a department head at the State Family Planning Commission, although he added: ''People who want more children are in the minority.''</p>
        <p>Overall, Mr. Chen and a number of other demographers believe that the high birthrates in some rural areas are balanced by the low birthrates in cities, and that at census time the official population estimate of 1.26 billion will be confirmed.</p>
        <p>But others say that the census may not yield an answer because children born outside the system can be hard to count. Ms. Lin, for example, said she plans to have her fourth child at home, as she did her last son. Her youngest three will not be officially registered -- which does not bother her because she does not know if she wants them in school anyhow.</p>
        <p>The census office already adjusts its raw figures somewhat to account for such children, but unannounced spot checks by the State Statistics Bureau have discovered undercounts of up to 40 percent in some villages, Chinese demographers say.</p>
        <p>''My sense is that nobody knows the actual population of the People's Republic of China,'' said Susan Greenhalgh, a professor at the University of California at Irvine, who is writing a book about the family planning system. ''And that makes it impossible to engage in the economic and social planning that China needs to do.''</p>
        <p>With the census approaching, top government officials and the state news media are all clearly anxious about a simmering rural population problem.</p>
        <p>Last month, President Jiang Zemin called on cadres to ''strengthen population and family planning work,'' to achieve a stable, low-level birthrate. ''They must establish an attitude of protracted war,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the Central Party Discipline Inspection Committee of Guangdong issued a warning that ''certain local leaders'' had ''not grasped family planning work, or muddled through it, or even fiddled with and faked numbers to win merit.''</p>
        <p>To prove its point, it highlighted Guangdong's Tanba township for failing to report more than 2,000 births. In Tanba's Xin village, nearly 80 percent of women had three or more children, including 21 of the 25 married members of the local Communist Party cell. ''The population is seriously out of control,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>China's family planning system, which carries out the country's 20-year-old one-child policy, has been generally effective at controlling population, dropping the average number of children per woman to 1.8 today from 5.8 in 1970, according to official statistics. The population is growing by about 10 million a year.</p>
        <p>On paper, the system allows urban residents one child, and rural residents a second if the first was a girl. Members of China's minorities also may have two, and three in some western regions.</p>
        <p>In China's large cities, the policy is strictly enforced, but in the countryside there is tremendous variation.</p>
        <p>In Beijing, just one-tenth of 1 percent of newborns were third or later children in 1997, according to the commission's estimates. But in provinces where large families are preferred, the percentages are much higher. In Guangdong, the number of babies who were born third or later was 6.4 percent, in Hainan Province it was 15.5 percent and in Ningxia Province it was 10.2 percent.</p>
        <p>Almost all of those births are illegal. And most demographers assume that these and other official statistics drastically understate the population problem because family planning regulations give Chinese a powerful incentive to conceal excess births.</p>
        <p>At an international conference in Beijing in 1997, many academics assumed that the average number of children per women was 2.1 and some as high as 2.6, virtually ignoring the official 1.8 figure.</p>
        <p>In rural China, every large family makes its separate peace with the local family planning system. Those who are too poor ignore the fees, those who have money often pay them. In many places, officials are lackadaisical and fees are applied unevenly, deeply discounted or forgiven as a political favor.</p>
        <p>In Guangdong's Fu village, for example, Fu Nancheng and his wife help look after their 17 grandchildren, all under 8, in their simple brick house -- the offspring of five sons who work in factories. Their two daughters, who live elsewhere, have nine children between them. The couple is certain there are more grandchildren to come.</p>
        <p>''It used to be much harder,'' said Mr. Fu, speaking in a sitting room crawling with children. ''When the family planning cadres came you used to have to hide them.''</p>
        <p>''Now it's much easier, though we still hide some,'' he added. ''The family planning workers don't care too  much about three or four -- as long as you pay a fine.''</p>
        <p>Likewise, Li Yanchang of Kui Tan Township, has five children, from newborn to 8 years old. The first two are legal. He paid only about $40 to register and get residency permits for the other children -- far lower than the officially mandated fees of over $600. But he said that new local leadership had recently closed that back door. ''You can't buy a permit that cheap anymore,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Li said the higher fees now in place will stop him from having more children because he wants his offspring to be officially registered so that they can go to school.</p>
        <p>''There are two types of people for whom fees are ineffective: the richest, who just pay them and don't care, and the poorest, who can't pay them and don't care,'' said Mr. Chen of the Family Planning Commission.</p>
        <p>Officials and academics are debating how, and if, the coming census can count the unregistered children from unapproved pregnancies, collectively known as the ''black population.''</p>
        <p>Meng Qingpu, a senior statistician at the National Statistics Bureau, which conducts the census, estimated there were five million such children in China, although he added, ''I think that's a little on the low side.''</p>
        <p>But he dismissed the notion that the number could be much higher, as well as doubts about the census' ability to arrive at accurate population figures. He said that raw data is adjusted upward by the bureau to compensate for any undercounting. ''It's very hard to do a census in China and getting harder, but we've thought long and hard about how to figure out exactly how many people we have,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Starting on Nov. 1, more than five million census workers will go door-to-door in homes and hotels, taking tallies. To encourage honest answers, respondents will be told that their answers on family size are confidential and will not be used to penalize them, Mr. Meng said.</p>
        <p>But even some officials are skeptical that the people will be forthcoming, noting that census takers are hired by the local government, and -- after the last census, in 1990 -- confidentiality was commonly violated.</p>
        <p>''The fact that some regions suffered bitterly because of the Fourth Census has educated a great many people,'' wrote Chen Youhua, a family planning official, in the most recent issue of Population and Economics. ''Whether these people will truthfully deal with the Fifth Census is a cause of great anxiety.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, after 20 years of family planning, hiding extra children is second nature in parts of China, and the state-controlled media has been filled with examples.</p>
        <p>When reporters from the Economic Information Daily traveled incognito through several counties in Henan -- a solid mainstream province -- they were appalled by what they saw. ''The extent of excess births is shocking and the black hole in family planning is unfathomably deep,'' the reporters wrote.</p>
        <p>In two counties they found families with 10 children. In a primary school in Kaifeng County, more than half of the pupils had four or more siblings. Places that had been declared ''model family planning counties,'' reporting negative population growth, were teeming with children.</p>
        <p>In that region, officials happily overlooked extra children so long as the villagers coughed up heavy fines -- about $1,200 for a second child and about $2,400 for a third. Family planning fees are often split between the county, the township and the village, providing a valuable income stream.</p>
        <p>The State Family Planning Commission admits that such places exist, but believes they are quite rare. ''In the countryside most families -- 90 percent -- have two children,'' said Mr. Chen. ''There's a small minority that has three, four or five and that's principally because they want a son.''</p>
        <p>Still, the commission is starting to experiment with new methods to further encourage small families in rural regions, like low-interest business loans and discounted fertilizer for households with two children or less. ''In the next decade,'' Mr. Chen said, ''our focus will be impoverished areas, but this is a process that takes time.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
