<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Salary Arbitration a Key Factor As Baseball Talks Are Stalled</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="328277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAJOR LEAGUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOCKOUTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD133CF933A15751C0A966958260" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Salary Arbitration a Key Factor As Baseball Talks Are Stalled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Salary arbitration, the system that has resulted in an aggregate 98 percent raise for about one-quarter of all major league players, continued to keep baseball's club owners and players sufficiently apart yesterday to jeopardize the start of the exhibition schedule.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Salary arbitration, the system that has resulted in an aggregate 98 percent raise for about one-quarter of all major league players, continued to keep baseball's club owners and players sufficiently apart yesterday to jeopardize the start of the exhibition schedule.</p>
        <p>Salary arbitration, the system that has resulted in an aggregate 98 percent raise for about one-quarter of all major league players, continued to keep baseball's club owners and players sufficiently apart yesterday to jeopardize the start of the exhibition schedule.</p>
        <p>The chief negotiators for both sides reported after a two-hour session that they were still mired in a deadlock over arbitration. The talks had resumed, after a two-day recess, on the fifth day of the owners' spring training lockout.</p>
        <p>The talks were held at the commissioner's office in Manhattan. Negotiators will meet again today.</p>
        <p>''It's going to take a lot of flexibility on both sides,'' Charles O'Connor, the owners' labor spokesman, said after the fruitless meeting, discussing the arbitration issue.</p>
        <p>Acknowledging the problem, Donald Fehr, his counterpart for the players, said: ''If we are not at the point where we are implicating the first regularly scheduled spring training games, we are very close to that. It takes more than just a day or two or three of tossing on the side for a pitcher to throw in any kind of a game situation. The first games are clearly in jeopardy.''</p>
        <p>The exhibition schedule is supposed to begin March 1, and Fehr said both sides would have to reach a settlement this week for the initial games to be played.</p>
        <p>No settlement, however, is in sight. Other issues remain to be resolved, particularly the owners' contribution to the players' pension and benefit plans, but for the moment, salary arbitration is the seemingly insurmountable roadblock to a settlement.</p>
        <p>The players want to reduce from three years to two the amount of major league service needed for arbitration eligibility. The owners want some way of controlling salaries gained in arbitration.</p>
        <p>The owners, in Commissioner Fay Vincent's plan, proposed a 75 percent cap on salary increases in salary arbitration. But O'Connor said yesterday that proposal was more off the bargaining table than on.</p>
        <p>''We've heard the union loud and clear,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The owners have made it clear that they do not like salary arbitration. The results from this year's salary arbitration proceedings make it clear why the owners don't like it.</p>
        <p>With only a handful of cases remaining, the players who filed for arbitration and have negotiated salaries or had them decided by arbitrators have had their salaries increase by an aggregate 98 percent from last year. That is up from a 71 percent increase the arbitration group had last year.</p>
        <p>Players who have lost their cases and those who were eligible for arbitration for the first time have fared especially well.</p>
        <p>The 10 players who have lost in arbitration have increased their salaries by 110 percent. A year ago, the losers in arbitration gained an aggregate 16 percent increase in salaries. The 51 first-timers have had raises amounting to 162 percent, compared with 137 percent for last year's first-time eligibles.</p>
        <p>While the figures explain why the owners would like to eliminate arbitration or at least alter it significantly, they also show why the players are adamant about keeping it intact and want to expand it to more players.</p>
        <p>The players want to return the eligibility level to two years, the standard that was in effect until the last negotiations in 1985. The owners' revenue-sharing plan would have eliminated arbitration altogether. Having abandoned that proposal, the owners, through Vincent, went to the idea of a cap on arbitration awards.</p>
        <p>''Nothing's going to happen as long as there are caps on the table,'' Paul Molitor, the American League player representative, said before the negotiators resumed talks today. ''There won't be an agreement. There's no number that would be acceptable.''</p>
        <p>Of the 20 players whose salaries have been decided by arbitrators, five winning players and five losers have had their salaries rise by more than 75 percent. Numerous other players who have negotiated contracts have had such increases. The players feel that if there were a 75 percent cap on awards, clubs would have little incentive for negotiating such contracts.</p>
        <p>As for the players' desire to reduce the eligibility level, Molitor said: ''We made a concession in 1985 based on their revenue projections. They said they had economic problems. Now that that's no longer true, we asked that we get back the year we gave then. Two years is the right way to go.''</p>
        <p>''They have to do something,'' said Molitor, whose salary rose 72 percent in average annual contract value this year after he filed for arbitration. ''They haven't come in our direction. We'll just have to wait and listen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
