<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Search for Miss Polaroid</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="601486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">VOLLMANN, WILLIAM T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEARSON, T R</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CRY ME A RIVER (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DE153FF932A25757C0A965958260" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Search for Miss Polaroid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William T. Vollmann;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VOLLMANN, WILLIAM T</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CRY ME A RIVER</p>
        <p>By T. R. Pearson. 258 pp. New York: Henry Holt. $22.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CRY ME A RIVER</p>
        <p>By T. R. Pearson. 258 pp. New York: Henry Holt. $22.</p>
        <p>HERE we have a weird crime story, the weirdness being in the story, not particularly in the crime. The narrator is a cop and loser whose fellow cop and loser he finds missing essential pieces of cranium. Inside the dead man's wallet is a pornographic Polaroid print of a lady not his widow (the widow being referred to by the narrator simply as "Dale's little sister"; we never find out much about who Dale is). The narrator has a very reasonable hunch that this other woman might have something to do with the murder. T. R. Pearson's new novel, "Cry Me a River," is the tale of his search for her and what happens after he finds her (in a Wal-Mart, entirely by accident).</p>
        <p>The weirdness begins with the fact that our slinky suspect -- like the crime itself -- is less the focus of Mr. Pearson's attentions than an excuse to introduce us by degrees to an ordinary, everyday menagerie of flatulent dogs and human beings of equal caliber with whom the narrator has been thrown into accidental or contingent relations: the lady who calls the police to investigate prowlers almost every night, it seems (each prowler a double of the latest one she's met in her drugstore romance novels), the two sisters who are not whores but who are known for the generosity with which they sexually gratify strange motorists, the hyperactive homosexual guy upstairs who makes the ceiling quake to the beat of his Dancercise.</p>
        <p>The author's intelligence and subtlety bring these and many other characters entirely alive. Beneath its whodunit disguise, "Cry Me a River" is a minor "Middle march" in its vivid delineation of a large gallery of complex, driven figures. Although Mr. Pearson has bowed so far as to give us a perfunctory, obligatory denouement, you'll find no suspense, no burning gunpowder narrative trail to get you there. I would say that this novel is about two-thirds digressions by weight, and the digressions are delicious. They can best be compared to chocolates, and 200 or 300 pages more of them would gladly have been consumed with no loss of appetite.</p>
        <p>I read this novel with a pleasure uncorrupted by its publicity, which -- I suppose because the story is set in a Southern town and there are lots of long sentences -- quotes someone comparing it to Faulkner. T. R. Pearson does not write like Faulkner at all. His language is rarely sensuously elliptical -- the opposite, in fact: it is conceptually precise, and beautifully so. A couple of examples: Members of a party that had "quaffed among them adequate to come to be sluggish and slow weren't in short the ideal crowd to let on and imply at." An undertaker "liked to think of himself as a general purpose liaison between his clients and the everlasting, was fond of proclaiming that he did for the dead everything they'd probably do for themselves if they weren't too dead already to do it." These extracts are representative of the novel's tone of gentle and understated sarcasm. Mr. Pearson (or at least his narrator) does not have a high opinion of people. There is not a single admirable entity in his cosmos, in "my sorry holdings, my table and my chair, my secondhand TV with the aerial wrenched from it, my former wife across town, my job down at the station where me and Lonnie did whatever Dewey wouldn't do."</p>
        <p>AS one might expect from such descriptions, the narrator is a mordant</p>
        <p>flaneur</p>
        <p>alienated from everybody and everything. His closest intimate is a drunk who explains over and over the mechanics of copulating with a duchess in the w.c. of a Canadian train. This gallant becomes the narrator's unofficial deputy in his search for Miss Polaroid, on balance doing more harm than good. Then there is the narrator's projective, obsessive relationship with the Polaroid print itself, which he loves to admire in the comfort of his own Naugahyde chair. He is not interested in the girl in her own right, although she'd willingly squeeze him in. After it's all over, he's still in his "sorry holdings," admiring the snapshot. With everyone else in the story, he functions in his various narrow grooves of neighbor, cop or colleague, thinking his own thoughts in a cold and ugly world.</p>
        <p>This is much less depressing than it sounds, because of the sarcasm -- which is both a strength and a weakness. Line for line, "Cry Me a River" is wonderful. But when sad and gruesome things happen, it is difficult to be moved by them. This may be exactly the author's intention, but, for me at least, the absence of feeling occasionally undercuts scenes that ought to be more convincingly tragic: a suicide, for instance, or a guilty nightmare. However, the book gains far more than it loses; such is the pleasure of its fine sentences.</p>
        <p>William T. Vollmann is the author of a forthcoming novel, "Butterfly Stories," his fifth, and a forthcoming collection of stories, "Thirteen Stories and Thirteen Epitaphs."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William T. Vollmann is the author of a forthcoming novel, "Butterfly Stories," his fifth, and a forthcoming collection of stories, "Thirteen Stories and Thirteen Epitaphs."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
