<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Dinosaurs Why Must This One Thrive?</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="601598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORMAN, JAMES</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BARNEY &amp; FRIENDS (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D91131F932A25757C0A965958260" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Dinosaurs Why Must This One Thrive?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Gorman;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GORMAN, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Help! he's fat, he's purple, he's goofier than Gomer Pyle, and he's eating our children! Well, he's gnawing away at their imaginations, anyway. Who is he? For those who are not parents of toddlers, he is Barney, a stuffed animal (ostensibly a dinosaur) who comes to life, delighting his little chums and threatening the sanity of adults.</p>
        <p>"Barney and Friends," broadcast daily on most PBS stations, is a half-hour show that deals with issues like rain, sun, friendship and going to the beach. Barney, about six feet tall, with thunder thighs, chipmunk cheeks and overbright eyes, is all sweetness and fun. He leaps around the stage and leads a group of multicultural suburban children in song and dance -- well, in song and movement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Help! he's fat, he's purple, he's goofier than Gomer Pyle, and he's eating our children! Well, he's gnawing away at their imaginations, anyway. Who is he? For those who are not parents of toddlers, he is Barney, a stuffed animal (ostensibly a dinosaur) who comes to life, delighting his little chums and threatening the sanity of adults.</p>
        <p>"Barney and Friends," broadcast daily on most PBS stations, is a half-hour show that deals with issues like rain, sun, friendship and going to the beach. Barney, about six feet tall, with thunder thighs, chipmunk cheeks and overbright eyes, is all sweetness and fun. He leaps around the stage and leads a group of multicultural suburban children in song and dance -- well, in song and movement.</p>
        <p>The production has a distinctly low-budget, amateur feel to it. But since it joined the PBS lineup about a year ago "Barney and Friends" has become a great success for its creators, a group of video neophytes known as the Lyons Group, with headquarters in Allen, Tex., outside Dallas. Connecticut Public Television helps produce the show and gets a small share of the profits. (Yes, Virginia, Barney is a for-profit dinosaur.) One indication of the show's popularity is that sales of Barney spinoff toys are expected to reach $200 million or more this year. Among the best-selling videos listed in Variety, Barney is always well represented.</p>
        <p>There are, however, naysayers. Many parents were angered to learn that PBS stations were scheduling pledge-drive appeals during the show, prompting children to beg their parents to send money on Barney's behalf.  There are also those who just plain hate Barney. That is the way it is always phrased: "I hate Barney." Barney does not inspire mere dislike or annoyance. As an anti-Barney parent myself, I can testify that he is capable of producing the sort of rage that surfaced in Michael Douglas in "Falling Down."</p>
        <p>Fortunately, the Barneyphobes, by and large, do not own artillery. And of course, the genuine dinosaurs are long gone, so they're safe. But I do fear for the future of vertebrate paleontology, the discipline that brought us the real creatures whose thunder Barney has stolen. What if the public concludes that since Barney is what we get for studying dinosaurs, we should stick to quasars? By the way, it has been scientifically proved, time and again, that none of the real dinosaurs were half as dumb as Barney (and they were better dancers, too).</p>
        <p>Actually, I'm not that upset about Barney as an insult to dinosaurs. It would be small-minded to complain about his resemblance to a talking eggplant. Barney is to dinosaurs as Mickey is to mice; anatomy is not the issue here. The issue is that, as they used to say, the child is father to the man; and as they say now, the television is parent to the person. In short, Barney is molding the future of our nation, and he's a bad influence.</p>
        <p>Take, for example, his voice. He giggles and guffaws incessantly, beyond reason, beyond belief. His laugh alone is enough to make you want to harm him or yourself. I can't imagine the effect on the developing mind of long-term exposure to Barney's laugh. But one clear implication of Barney's persona is that friendliness and idiocy go together. A lesson for our times: Smart is bad. Dumb is good.</p>
        <p>Barney's second problem is the crowd he hangs out with. They are soooo nice. They are world-class nice. Next to Barney and his friends, Sandy Duncan is a flesh-eating succubus. It's not that I want my children watching "Bram Stoker's 'Dracula.' " But there are age-appropriate villains who add a little spice to toddlers' entertainment. My 2-year-old son is comfortable with Oscar the Grouch from "Sesame Street," and with Oscar's colleague Bert, who is not all sweetness and light. My son is also fascinated by the wolf in the story of the three little pigs. He feels, if I may translate his comments, that the wolf adds an element of suspense and reflects the unarguable presence of danger in the world.</p>
        <p>I don't blame the child actors who portray Barney's friends. I know that in real life they eat junk food and are sometimes impolite.  But what can you do with dialogue like "I wish we had some sunscreen lotion to protect our skin." Right. And why didn't we get any homework over summer vacation?</p>
        <p>It's as if the National Association for the Promotion of Blandness had created its dream show. One doesn't often find people who admit to being members of N.A.P.B., but evidence of their work is everywhere: the story of Hansel and Gretel has disappeared from the canon, Smurfs are a national menace, and the wolf doesn't even get to eat the first two lazy, no-account shoats in some versions of the three little pigs.</p>
        <p>Even though they disguise themselves, I have some suspicions about who the culprits are. They are the people who believe you have to talk in a high, silly voice to young children. They are the folks who, when the pet fish dies, say it went to fishy heaven. They are people who have been justifiably offended by the speedy, cocaine-freak, stimulus overload of most television shows and movies. The problem is that the right antidote to amphetamines is not barbiturates. The right antidote to mayhem, slaughter and jump cuts is not unimaginative treacle.</p>
        <p>To be fair, Barney by himself does not represent the downfall of civilization. And the show could be pretty easily fixed. There's no need to design a new, anatomically correct Barney. That would scare kids. I suggest the creators rename him Harvey, make him invisible and silent, and bring in George Carlin as his visible friend and translator. Failing that, just kill the laugh.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION VIEW James Gorman is the author of "The Man With No Endorphins," a collection of essays about science.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Gorman is the author of "The Man With No Endorphins," a collection of essays about science.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
