<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Principles of Creating Arches</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="601542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WARDE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED9113EF932A25757C0A965958260" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Principles of Creating Arches</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WARDE, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CREATING an arch by opening a nonload-bearing wall or converting a wide doorway can add a striking design feature to a home. The job should not be too difficult for an amateur with moderate carpentry and drywall experience.</p>
        <p>Before starting, be sure to understand the principles in case alterations are required. Also be sure that quarter-inch-thick drywall and plastic archway corner bead are obtainable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CREATING an arch by opening a nonload-bearing wall or converting a wide doorway can add a striking design feature to a home. The job should not be too difficult for an amateur with moderate carpentry and drywall experience.</p>
        <p>Before starting, be sure to understand the principles in case alterations are required. Also be sure that quarter-inch-thick drywall and plastic archway corner bead are obtainable.</p>
        <p>Building supply stores have in stock or can order quarter-inch drywall. Plastic archway bead, available with a square or bullnose (rounded) edge, can be ordered from Trim-Tex Inc., 3700 West Pratt Avenue, Lincolnwood, Ill. 60645 (800-874-2333). It costs 12 cents a foot.</p>
        <p>If you plan to open a wall for the arch, determine that it is nonload-bearing, meaning that it does not support building materials above it. If unsure, have the wall inspected by a skilled professional carpenter, an independent building inspector or a building engineer.</p>
        <p>A doorway need not be examined, unless you plan to widen it. Besides being a comfortable width, the sole requirement is that the height be enough to allow reducing it at least two inches, the thickness of the archway materials, without sacrificing too much headroom.</p>
        <p>With a wall, start by removing the existing wallboard or plaster to expose the studs. If the wall is plaster, leave a strip along the top, or plate, where the wall meets the ceiling to avoid unnecessary patching later.</p>
        <p>Remove studs from the wall to create the desired opening. The easiest way to remove studs is to saw them in half and then twist each piece free from the plate and the bottom of the wall frame, called the sole.</p>
        <p>Decide the height of the arch. Then cut two pieces of 2 x 4 lumber for trimmers. Stand each on the sole, against the studs forming the opening, so that the trimmers face each other across the span. Nail the trimmers to the sole and longer studs.</p>
        <p>Cut two pieces of 2 x 6 lumber for headers to bridge the opening and rest on the ends of the trimmers. After placing them on the edge across the opening so that their sides are flush with edges of the studs and trimmers, attach the 2 X 6's by nailing into their ends through the studs against them.</p>
        <p>Cut small lengths of 2 x 4 lumber, called cripples, to fit vertically between the tops of the headers and the plate. Position them at the same intervals as the original studs and fasten them with nails.</p>
        <p>With a handsaw, cut through the section of the sole spanning the opening. Pry it from the floor if necessary and discard it.</p>
        <p>Draw the arch on a piece of 1 x 6 or wider solid lumber or on a strip of five-eighths-inch-thick plywood wide enough to accommodate the entire curve. At its height, the distance of the curve from the board or strip's top edge has to be at least one and one half inches to hide spacer and anchor blocks.</p>
        <p>Cut along the curved line with a saber saw. Use the piece as a pattern to cut a second piece identical to it. The length of both pieces has to equal the width of the opening, namely the distance between the trimmers.</p>
        <p>To assemble the arch, subtract the combined thickness of the pieces from the width of the trimmers or other studs. Then cut blocks from 2 x 4 lumber to that length and sandwich them at six- or eight-inch intervals between the pieces, specifically along their curved edges.</p>
        <p>Position the blocks so that their undersides are flush with the bottoms of the pieces, and nail or install screws through the pieces into the ends of the blocks.</p>
        <p>Attach blocks to the tops of the trimmers, centering them so that the sides of the arches can rest against the blocks and be flush with the edges of the studs.</p>
        <p>Usually, it is easier to make the blocks by narrowing 2 x 4 lumber to the required dimension rather than crosscutting it. Also, blocks made this way are less likely to split when fasteners are installed.</p>
        <p>Cut and attach blocks similar to those above at one-foot intervals along the underside of the paired headers. If necessary, alter the intervals so that the blocks do not interfere with those sandwiched between the sides of the arch.</p>
        <p>Lift the arch into place and install nails or screws through the sides and into the blocks attached to the trimmers and headers. Attach drywall of any desired thickness to the sides of the wall and arch. Half-inch-thick drywall is standard.</p>
        <p>To cover the underside, use two thicknesses of quarter-inch drywall. Bending the material is tricky. If you have not done it before, expect to break a few pieces before getting it right.</p>
        <p>Start by dampening a strip on one side by sponging or misting and then waiting about 10 minutes for the strip to become pliable. Next, screw the strip, its wetter side up, to the blocks spanning the arch sides, starting in the middle and working toward the ends.</p>
        <p>If necessary, have someone support the strip while you fasten it. Repeat the procedure to fasten a second strip against the first.</p>
        <p>Cover the drywall seams and fasteners with ordinary drywall tape and joint compound, but attach flexible plastic corner bead to the curved edges where the sides of the arch meet the underside.</p>
        <p>Use blued lath nails with wide flat heads to attach the bead, not screws or drywall nails, which can distort it. Then cover the bead with joint compound, just as with ordinary metal corner bead.</p>
        <p>Finish the arch by applying primer. Then paint or wallpaper.</p>
        <p>To convert a doorway to an arch, remove the door and frame to expose the trimmers and header surrounding it. By working carefully, you may not have to remove much drywall or plaster from the wall.</p>
        <p>Assemble and install an arch as described above, and attach it to blocks fastened to the existing trimmers and header.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
