<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All the World, Through Its Beads</title>
    <meta content="12CRITIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/12/fashion/shows/12CRITIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1796521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Critical Shopper"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicrafts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6DD1030F931A25753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All the World, Through Its Beads</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">All the World, Through Its Beads</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex Kuczynski</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kuczynski, Alex</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you are my brother-in-law who lives in Buffalo and writes erotic poetry, stop reading right now. Same applies to your wife.</p>
        <p>It's not that I'm going to write anything bad about you. I like your poetry. Really, I do. We had to hide it from the kids this summer, but I was happily surprised to find them reading it out loud to one other, giggling. I would rather they learn about sex from poetry than from pornography.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The store Beads of Paradise is not just a beads store.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you are my brother-in-law who lives in Buffalo and writes erotic poetry, stop reading right now. Same applies to your wife.</p>
        <p>It's not that I'm going to write anything bad about you. I like your poetry. Really, I do. We had to hide it from the kids this summer, but I was happily surprised to find them reading it out loud to one other, giggling. I would rather they learn about sex from poetry than from pornography.</p>
        <p>But here's the thing: I get very nervous about holiday shopping. My deadline -- gifts wrapped, cards written, address labels smacked on -- is usually Thanksgiving. But I have a particularly hectic autumn schedule and have set this year's gift-purchasing deadline at Halloween. Last week, in one fell swoop at Beads of Paradise, one of those hole-in-the-wall places that open up into glorious emporia of treasure, I covered half my list -- including the brother-in-law of the erotic poetry. He has a wonderful wife who doesn't seem to mind that he writes all these intimate details about well, never mind. She is, and I quote, the sand rolling in his waves, etc.</p>
        <p>By name alone, Beads of Paradise certainly suggests the store sells beads, which it does. Unfortunately, some visitors think it's just a bead store, a place to buy all the gewgaws and glues and chunks of cheap turquoise that a run-of-the-mill bead store would sell. The name is not quite the right fit. There are beads, yes. There are Tiger's Eye beads ($3 apiece) along with gold beads, Venetian millefiori beads, glass beads and seed pearls. But there are also Venetian chevron beads ($65 each) that were worn by, the sign says, 17th- and 18th-century Cameroon kings.</p>
        <p>Most of the store, really, is given over to scarves, sculpture, artwork, rugs, jewelry and furniture collected from countries like Ghana, India, Mexico, Myanmar, Nigeria, Pakistan, Thailand and Vietnam. It is a paradisiacal hodgepodge of silk curtains from India and Nepal, antique coins, fisherman's pants from Bali and silk quilted jackets and comforters from Vietnam. The front of the shop is devoted to jewelry, most handmade, and some made by students of the store's bead-making seminars. Prices for hoop earrings in gold with seed pearls or garnets can run up to $150. An antique silver necklace consisting of hammered hoops is $300.</p>
        <p>Curios abound. I was sorely tempted to buy a commemorative medal featuring the Ethiopian emperor Haile Selassie, mostly because my sister went to college with his grandson and I had a huge crush on him. But the medals were $185, and I couldn't think of anyone on my gift list who needed a Haile Selassie medal. And if I bought it for myself, I'd have to explain to my husband about my sudden fascination with Haile Selassie-ana.</p>
        <p>Vintage glass Buddhas from the 1960's ($60) are stacked next to Djenne religious figures from Mali from the 9th through 12th centuries (up to $625). Most works of art in sub-Saharan Africa during that period were made of perishable materials like fiber or wood, but terra cotta and metal sculptures have survived. (Sotheby's has sold Djenne figures from similar periods for prices in the hundreds of thousands of dollars, so ask for a certificate of provenance if you're interested in buying one.)</p>
        <p>AS sick as I am of the campy plastic Buddha as an object of interior decoration, Beads of Paradise sells a mosaic-glass Buddha-head lamp from Bali ($185) that is so self-referentially amusing -- and not in the smarmy, all-knowing, wink-wink, city-chic way -- that I almost bought it. I'm also totally sick to death of naïf art and all the trustafarians who hang rusty signs from old Cuban restaurants in their $3 million lofts and talk about how authentic that sign is, and how you can practically taste the coffee they must have served at that authentic Cuban place and so on until you find the person who brought you to the stupid party in the first place and get out.</p>
        <p>But Beads of Paradise manages to stock interesting pieces that don't look too kitschy, like a 12-foot-long painted advertisement on canvas of ''Sabado Haircuts,'' depicting Caribbean men with different haircuts (like ''Fade'' and ''Cocaine''), and a sign from Ghana for a doctor's office in which patients apparently receive high colonics.</p>
        <p>At the jewelry counters, I was transfixed by a display of enamel amulets from India, featuring Hindu gods like Hanuman, the monkey-face guy who stands for courage, and Ganesh, the remover of obstacles and promoter of wealth. Just below them sat rows of cylindrical objects with rounded ends, some made of wood, others of stone, and each marked with its own clefts, curves and -- well, it was a shelf of lingams.</p>
        <p>A lingam, if you don't know or haven't read the Kama Sutra, is the phallic symbol used in the worship of Siva, the Hindu god of destruction and reproduction. Right in the middle of all the little lingams was a 13-inch-long antique mango wood lingam. In American culture, we shy away from overtly celebrating the penis, but in Asia, it's the thing. Guys in Thailand wear lingams around their belts to show how studly they are. (I guess here, it's watches.)</p>
        <p>Long story short, I bought the mango wood lingam ($98) for the poet and his wife. When December comes, he can feel like Siva, and she can feel like Parvati, his female consort, and may their winter flow with cosmic energy.</p>
        <p>Merry Christmas!</p>
        <p>Beads of Paradise  16 East 17th Street; (212) 620-0642</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Slightly dusty cabinet of curiosities.  SERVICE -- Can be really good up front, and occasionally snippy if you're a neophyte stepping into the bead room for the first time.  PRICES -- From $4 for a pewter dowry ring to $1,800 for an Ethiopian painting on leather in the classic Coptic style, and beyond.</p>
        <p>Critical Shopper</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
