<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Allies Till Fertile Soil, Among Baptists, for Votes</title>
    <meta content="18BAPT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/18/politics/campaign/18baptists.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1590346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: STRATEGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baptist Churches</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Southern Baptist Convention</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirkpatrick, David D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baptist Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Southern Baptist Convention</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DA1739F93BA25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Allies Till Fertile Soil, Among Baptists, for Votes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Allies Till Fertile Soil, Among Baptists, for Votes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush's re-election campaign takes its effort to enlist churches in turning out conservative voters to annual meeting of Southern Baptist Convention, Indianapolis, urging pastors to do everything short of risking their churches tax-exempt status to support Bush's re-election; Bush's courtship of Southern Baptists begins when he addresses them in live telecast from White House and thanks them for their prayers; Ralph Reed, former head of Christian Coalition who is now an official of Bush camapign, arrives to ask pastors more explicitly for their help in winning votes; photo of Bush and Dr Jack Graham, president of Southern Baptist Convention (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's re-election campaign took its effort to enlist churches in turning out conservative voters to the annual meeting of the Southern Baptist Convention this week, urging pastors to do everything short of risking their churches' tax-exempt status to support the president's re-election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's courtship of Southern Baptists, the largest Protestant denomination, began Tuesday when he addressed them in a live telecast from the White House and thanked them for their prayers. The campaign's appeals picked up in earnest the next day, when Ralph Reed, the former head of the Christian Coalition, who is now an official of the Bush campaign, arrived to ask pastors more explicitly for their help in winning votes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's campaign urged Southern Baptist pastors to do everything short of risking their churches' tax-exempt status to support the president's re-election.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's re-election campaign took its effort to enlist churches in turning out conservative voters to the annual meeting of the Southern Baptist Convention this week, urging pastors to do everything short of risking their churches' tax-exempt status to support the president's re-election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's courtship of Southern Baptists, the largest Protestant denomination, began Tuesday when he addressed them in a live telecast from the White House and thanked them for their prayers. The campaign's appeals picked up in earnest the next day, when Ralph Reed, the former head of the Christian Coalition, who is now an official of the Bush campaign, arrived to ask pastors more explicitly for their help in winning votes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reed delivered his remarks at a Bush-Cheney ''pastors reception,'' paid for by the Bush campaign. The hosts were the departing president of the Southern Baptists and three other prominent leaders, and the reception was in a conference room of a hotel adjacent to the convention. As the pastors came in, a campaign aide collected about 100 signatures and addresses from ministers pledging to endorse Mr. Bush's re-election publicly, to ''host a citizenship Sunday for voter registration,'' to ''identify someone who will help in voter registration and outreach'' and to organize a '''party for the president' with other pastors'' on specific dates closer to the election.</p>
        <p>As the pastors mingled around fountains of soft drinks and trays of cubed cheese, Mr. Reed urged, ''Without advocating on behalf of any candidate or political party, you can make sure that everyone in your circle of influence is registered to vote.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's political advisers often repeat their belief, Mr. Reed reminded the pastors, that about four million conservative Christian voters did not vote in the last presidential election. The campaign is determined not to let that happen again.</p>
        <p>And the leaders of the 16 million Southern Baptists have already organized what they say is the first major voter registration drive in their history, beginning at the annual meeting.</p>
        <p>But as the Bush campaign escalates its appeals to conservative Christian churches, experts in election law say, it is inviting pastors toward potentially treacherous terrain where letting personal endorsements spill over into the business of their churches can jeopardize their tax-exempt status.</p>
        <p>''It is pushing the line,'' said Larry Noble, executive director of the Center for Responsive Politics and the former general counsel to the Federal Election Commission. ''It goes to the question of, 'How often can you switch hats?'''</p>
        <p>The dividing line in the tax laws gets even blurrier, Mr. Noble said, when the same pastors are also engaging in their clerical capacity in churchwide voter-registration drives that are officially nonpartisan. And the line can become blurrier still, he added, if the church officials are specifically directing their messages to partisan voters -- if, for example, Southern Baptist leaders believe that most of their members are likely to vote Republican.</p>
        <p>''Then, when you start combining endorsements with church activity that is supposed to be nonpartisan,'' Mr. Noble said, ''it gets murkier.''</p>
        <p>Some Baptists have objected on religious grounds to the support of the denomination's leaders for conservative politicians. Daniel Vestal, a pastor and former candidate for president of the Southern Baptists who is now coordinator of the dissident Cooperative Baptist Fellowship, which represents 450,000 parishioners, said the denomination had traditionally accommodated a host of political views among its pastors and officials, until fundamentalists within the denomination began taking over its leadership 25 years ago.</p>
        <p>''The Southern Baptist Convention has become aligned with the secular political agenda of one particular part of one party, and that is tragic,'' Mr. Vestal said. But Dr. Jack Graham, the departing president of the denomination, whom Mr. Reed contacted to be the host of the Bush-Cheney reception, said there was a clear distinction between his roles at the convention and at the reception. ''This is Jack Graham the person, not Jack Graham the president of the Southern Baptists,'' he said in an interview at the event.</p>
        <p>What is more, he said, he believed the Bible called on Christians to support godly politicians.</p>
        <p>Asked about the potential benefits to the Bush campaign from his personal endorsement as an individual and from the Southern Baptists' voter registration efforts, Mr. Graham said: ''You can connect the dots. I don't mind if you connect the dots. You can't separate what you believe from the political process. ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reed, for his part, appeared to relish any criticism of the campaign for cultivating churches, since it served to reinforce the campaign's connection to the faith. In his speech at the reception, he brought up recent criticism of the campaign over an e-mail message from Pennsylvania suggesting that supporters distribute campaign information inside the places of worship of ''friendly congregations,'' something specialists in election law say might jeopardize their tax status.</p>
        <p>''I, for one, believe people of faith have the same rights to participate in the political process as any other citizens,'' he said. ''Christians should not be treated as second-class citizens.''</p>
        <p>Still, in an interview, Mr. Reed acknowledged that the reference in the Pennsylvania e-mail message to distributing campaign information ''in a place accessible to the congregation'' -- presumably in the place of worship -- might have gone too far. ''That I would not recommend,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Richard Land, the president of the Ethics and Liberty Commission of the Southern Baptist Convention and the denomination's principal advocate in Washington, did not attend the Bush-Cheney event. He spent much of the convention presiding over the official kickoff of the denomination's ''I Vote Values'' voter registration campaign.</p>
        <p>In addition to a Web site, it centers on a bus: on the outside of the bus is a picture of Dr. Land speaking about the importance of voting, and on the inside are interactive video monitors. The Baptists plan to send it around the country distributing booklets instructing pastors and parishioners on how to comply with tax laws while registering people to vote.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Dr. Land said the registration efforts would undoubtedly sign up some Democrats, since 20 percent of Southern Baptists voted Democratic in the last election and the ''I Vote Values'' campaign is carefully nonpartisan.</p>
        <p>And several people at the convention did express some reservations about the president. Al Oxford, a retired coal miner and Democrat from southern Illinois, criticized the Bush tax cuts. ''My daughter is a single mother,'' she said. ''She didn't get any of that.''</p>
        <p>THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: STRATEGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
