<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Courts Plan to Waste Less of Jurors' Time</title>
    <meta content="18JURY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/18/nyregion/18jury.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1590340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramirez, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaye, Judith S (Chief Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Tyco International Limited</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE7DA1739F93BA25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Courts Plan to Waste Less of Jurors' Time</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Courts Plan to Waste Less of Jurors' Time</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramirez, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special commission on jury reform in New York recommends to Chief Judge Judith Kaye series of proposals intended to make jury service more palatable; first phase of reform eliminated automatic exemptions for service; details of proposals noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since 1995, when automatic exemptions for jury duty were lifted, the reverse Darwinism of picking juries in New York has been slowly ending.</p>
        <p>The hapless or the unemployed are no longer the ones dragooned onto juries, but everyone is summoned and may be called -- rich and poor, doctors and journalists, even the occasional state legislator.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since 1995, when automatic exemptions for jury duty were lifted, the reverse Darwinism of picking juries in New York has been slowly ending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since 1995, when automatic exemptions for jury duty were lifted, the reverse Darwinism of picking juries in New York has been slowly ending.</p>
        <p>The hapless or the unemployed are no longer the ones dragooned onto juries, but everyone is summoned and may be called -- rich and poor, doctors and journalists, even the occasional state legislator.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the other shoe of jury reform dropped. A special commission recommended changes that addressed a single issue: now that everyone serves, how can the state stop wasting jurors' time?</p>
        <p>The commission -- which reports to Chief Judge Judith S. Kaye, who has been pressing for jury reform -- recommended several proposals, including one that would provide subway and bus passes for jurors or parking near the courthouse that was free or discounted.</p>
        <p>Another proposal would offer free Internet access for jurors stuck in a hot, airless courthouse. Still another would let jurors awaiting a trial leave the courthouse if they are not needed, as long as they agreed to be available by cellphone or pager and could return within two hours.</p>
        <p>Under another proposal, lawyers could be penalized for ''multiple unexcused latenesses,'' a common juror complaint. A suggestion that is expected to draw some criticism would require a settlement conference in all trials before jury selection could begin.</p>
        <p>''The commission heard testimony that some parties, particularly those represented by insurance carriers,'' the report said, ''do not engage in serious settlement discussions until they see the whites of the jurors' eyes.''</p>
        <p>Mark C. Zauderer, chairman of the Commission on the Jury, a 29-member group, told reporters, ''We don't believe citizens should be pawns in the process.''</p>
        <p>The report is available online at www.nycourts.gov/press.</p>
        <p>Unlike the first phase of jury reform, most of the proposals can be put in place by the courts without legislative approval, the chief administrative judge, Jonathan Lippman, told reporters yesterday.</p>
        <p>One proposal needing legislative approval has already been passed, he said, and is being considered by Gov. George E. Pataki. The bill increases the time between jury summonses to six years from four years and as long as eight years for jurors who served in long trials.</p>
        <p>One significant earlier proposal, all but banning the sequestration of juries, was opposed by the court officers union because it hurt members' overtime. The proposal passed when other overtime opportunities were found.</p>
        <p>This time, Dennis W. Quirk, president of the New York State Court Officers Union, described all of the commission's proposals as excellent, except one.</p>
        <p>''When it comes to parking,'' he said, ''my members come first.'' Mr. Quirk noted that two-thirds of the system's 4,500 officers -- the police of the courthouse -- work in New York City.</p>
        <p>''They need to work on the court employees' parking problems,'' he said, ''before they need to work on the jurors' parking problems.''</p>
        <p>While much of the commission's plan does not require legislative attention, it may get it anyway. State Senator John A. DeFrancisco, a Syracuse Republican and chairman of the Judiciary Committee, said he did not like the requirement of a settlement conference before jury selection.</p>
        <p>''It's just another useless meeting,'' Mr. DeFrancisco, a trial lawyer, said.</p>
        <p>The commission did not offer proposals to solve one of the biggest objections to jury duty. More than 600,000 potential jurors show up every year, yet more than 80 percent are never chosen.</p>
        <p>The principal reason, the commission found, is prosecutors and defense lawyers need as many as 90 in the pool to select 12 jurors and a few alternates. Both sides in a trial, including civil cases, typically prefer having large jury pools, the commission found. New York State allows some of the highest number of challenges to jurors of any system in the country, as many as 20 for the prosecution and for each defendant in the most serious felonies.</p>
        <p>The commission found no solution to this issue. ''A certain amount of discretion'' has to be left to lawyers, Mr. Zauderer, the commission chairman, said.</p>
        <p>One of the biggest deterrents to jury duty may be insoluble.</p>
        <p>''The building conditions of courthouses are horrendous,'' Mr. Quirk said. ''They're dirty, they're decrepit and the air-conditioning doesn't work properly. The court is not a pleasant place to be.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
