<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even Calm Voices Are Unsettling for Relatives</title>
    <meta content="18TAPE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/18/politics/18tapes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1590305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE REACTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Traffic Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEEDC1739F93BA25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even Calm Voices Are Unsettling for Relatives</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Even Calm Voices Are Unsettling for Relatives</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stolberg, Sheryl Gay</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Relatives of those who died in Sept 11 terrorist attacks, stoic throughout investigation commission's hearings, weep as they hear recordings of hijackers' voices on doomed aircraft and seeming calm of air traffic controllers as they struggled to understand what was happening; photo of relatives at commission's final public hearing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the relatives of the victims, who have attended the hearings of the 9/11 commission this past year with an extraordinary blend of stoicism and resolve, Thursday's session may have been the hardest.</p>
        <p>Elaine Hughes came prepared, as she always has, with a notebook tucked in her bag and a big round button pinned to her lapel, the smiling face of her dark-haired, handsome son, Kris. But she was not ready for what she would hear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>WASHINGTON, June 17 - For the relatives of the victims, who have attended the hearings of the 9/11 commission this past year with an extraordinary blend of stoicism and resolve, Thursday's session may have been the hardest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the relatives of the victims, who have attended the hearings of the 9/11 commission this past year with an extraordinary blend of stoicism and resolve, Thursday's session may have been the hardest.</p>
        <p>Elaine Hughes came prepared, as she always has, with a notebook tucked in her bag and a big round button pinned to her lapel, the smiling face of her dark-haired, handsome son, Kris. But she was not ready for what she would hear.</p>
        <p>''Nobody move,'' came a voice over the loudspeaker, in distinctly accented English. ''Everything will be O.K. If you try to make any moves, you'll endanger yourself and the airplane. Just stay quiet.''</p>
        <p>The voice, replayed along with other audio transmissions, belonged to one of the hijackers of American Airlines Flight 11, which crashed into the north tower of the World Trade Center. For Ms. Hughes, whose final conversation with her son came as he watched the devastation from the south tower, the recording brought forth a flood of emotion. Tears streamed down her cheeks as she listened.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't expecting to hear what I heard,'' Ms. Hughes, of Smithtown, N.Y., said afterward. ''I wasn't expecting to hear the hijackers' voices.''</p>
        <p>Through precise timelines and audio excerpts, the session on Thursday told a story of mistakes on that fateful blue-skied day in September 2001. The relatives had long ago come to terms with the idea that at least some of the victims could have been saved were it not for bungled communications between the Federal Aviation Administration and the military.</p>
        <p>But to see it laid out so precisely, to hear the voices of the attackers and the officials, was almost too much to bear.</p>
        <p>''We speculated, based on timelines, that there was enough time for intercepts,'' said Beverly Eckert, of Stamford, Conn., whose husband died in the attacks. ''But to hear it, the admission today, to confirm that. '' Her voice trailed off as she searched for words. ''It resolved something, but it is also enormously devastating to hear.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Eckert is among a small coterie of victims' relatives who, through sheer grit and political savvy, prodded Congress and the White House to establish the commission. They have done considerable research on their own and have bird-dogged the panel's every move.</p>
        <p>By exerting political pressure on elected officials -- including President Bush -- the relatives have made it politically untenable for government agencies to brush aside the panel's requests. ''We have gotten information that people thought it would be impossible for us to get, and that is largely because of the work of the families,'' Jamie Gorelick, one of the commissioners, said.</p>
        <p>But the effort has taken its toll. ''It's very emotionally draining,'' said Mary Fetchet, of New Canaan, Conn., whose son Brad was killed on Sept. 11. Along with Ms. Eckert, Ms. Fetchet founded a support group, Voices of September 11. She said she was struck, on Thursday, by the sound of the civilian and military authorities as they struggled to respond. Their calm troubled her.</p>
        <p>''There was no sense of chaos in their voices,'' she said. ''Did it seem like we were under attack? I didn't get a sense of urgency.''</p>
        <p>For Ms. Fetchet and the others, Thursday's retelling evoked not only painful memories, but awful questions. ''This is the last minutes of my son's life,'' she said. ''What was happening in the plane? What was happening in the building? How did they die? So many of us don't know.''</p>
        <p>Though the hearings are over -- several family members expressed relief at that -- this will not be the last the commission, or the public, hears from the Sept. 11 relatives. Ms. Eckert said she was planning to arrange a meeting with the commission to talk about its report, expected to be released next month. Once the report is issued, the relatives plan to go back to Congress, to begin the long task of lobbying for its recommendations to be put into place.</p>
        <p>''To me,'' said Mrs. Hughes, ''this is just phase one. The report will come out, the recommendations will come out. I'll be banging on all the senators' doors.''</p>
        <p>THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE REACTION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
