<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush and Cheney Talk Strongly Of Qaeda Links With Hussein</title>
    <meta content="18DEBA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1590318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE QAEDA CONNECTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sudan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toner, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sudan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sudan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E3DB1739F93BA25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1274" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush and Cheney Talk Strongly Of Qaeda Links With Hussein</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER and ROBIN TONERl; David E. Sanger reported from New York for this article, and Robin Toner from Detroit.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E; Toner, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush and Vice Pres Cheney say they remain convinced that Saddam Hussein's government in Iraq had long history of ties to Al Qaeda, despite Sept 11 commission report that classified intelligence shows no evidence of 'collaborative relationship'; photo; Bush says his administration never said Sept 11 attacks were orchestrated with Hussein, but does say there were 'numerous contacts,' as when 'Iraqi intelligence officers met with bin Laden' in Sudan; repeats that Hussein was 'sworn enemy' of US; Cheney calls The New York Times coverage of commission findings 'outrageous'; charges press confuses issue of Iraqi role in Sept 11 with other ties to Al Qaeda, for which he says there is 'overwhelming' evidence; Democratic candidate John Kerry demands Bush explain why he rushed to war; says Bush and Cheney, not press, are muddling distinctions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush and Vice President Cheney said yesterday that they remain convinced that Saddam Hussein's government had a long history of ties to Al Qaeda, a day after the commission investigating the Sept. 11 attacks reported that its review of classified intelligence found no evidence of a ''collaborative relationship'' that linked Iraq to the terrorist organization.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, responding to a reporter's question about the report after a White House cabinet meeting yesterday morning, said: ''The reason I keep insisting that there was a relationship between Iraq and Saddam and Al Qaeda'' is ''because there was a relationship between Iraq and Al Qaeda.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush and Vice President Cheney said yesterday that they remain convinced that Saddam Hussein's government had a long history of ties to Al Qaeda, a day after the commission investigating the Sept. 11 attacks reported that its review of classified intelligence found no evidence of a ''collaborative relationship'' that linked Iraq to the terrorist organization.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, responding to a reporter's question about the report after a White House cabinet meeting yesterday morning, said: ''The reason I keep insisting that there was a relationship between Iraq and Saddam and Al Qaeda'' is ''because there was a relationship between Iraq and Al Qaeda.''</p>
        <p>He said: ''This administration never said that the 9/11 attacks were orchestrated between Saddam and Al Qaeda. We did say there were numerous contacts between Saddam Hussein and Al Qaeda. For example, Iraqi intelligence officers met with bin Laden, the head of Al Qaeda, in the Sudan. There's numerous contacts between the two.''</p>
        <p>He repeated that Mr. Hussein was ''a threat'' and ''a sworn enemy to the United States of America.''</p>
        <p>Last night Mr. Cheney, who was the administration's most forceful advocate of the Qaeda-Hussein links, was more pointed, repeating in detail his case for those ties and saying that The New York Times's coverage yesterday of the commission's findings ''was outrageous.''</p>
        <p>''They do a lot of outrageous things,'' Mr. Cheney, appearing on ''Capital Report'' on CNBC, said of The Times, referring specifically to a four-column front page headline that read ''Panel Finds No Qaeda-Iraq Tie.'' Mr. Cheney added, ''The press wants to run out and say there's a fundamental split here now between what the president said and what the commission said.''</p>
        <p>He said that newspapers, including The Times, had confused the question of whether there was evidence of Iraqi participation in Sept. 11 with the issue of whether a relationship existed between Al Qaeda and Mr. Hussein's government.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the commission, he said, ''They did not address the broader question of a relationship between Iraq and Al Qaeda in other areas, in other ways.'' He said ''the evidence is overwhelming.'' He described the ties and cited numerous links back to the 1990's, including contacts between Osama bin Laden and Iraqi intelligence officials.</p>
        <p>Senator John Kerry, the presumptive Democratic nominee for president, also jumped into the debate yesterday, saying: ''It is clear that President Bush owes the American people a fundamental explanation about why he rushed to war for a purpose that it now turns out is not supported by the facts. That is the finding of this commission. The war against Al Qaeda is not the war in Iraq, when it began.''</p>
        <p>Staff Report 15, released by the commission Wednesday, detailed how a senior Iraqi intelligence officer ''reportedly made three visits to Sudan'' and met with Mr. bin Laden in 1994. At that meeting, the report concluded, Mr. bin Laden sought permission to establish training camps in Iraq and help in obtaining weapons, ''but Iraq apparently never responded.''</p>
        <p>''There have been reports that contacts between Iraq and Al Qaeda also occurred after bin Laden had returned to Afghanistan, but they do not appear to have resulted in a collaborative relationship,'' the report continued. ''Two senior bin Laden associates have adamantly denied that any ties existed between Al Qaeda and Iraq. We have no credible evidence that Iraq and Al Qaeda cooperated on attacks against the United States.''</p>
        <p>The Times quoted that section of the report at length on Thursday, along with quotations from Mr. Bush's and Mr. Cheney's statements before and after the Iraq invasion on the questions of links and of evidence of Iraqi involvement in the Sept. 11 attacks. Those included Mr. Bush's Sept. 17, 2003, statement: ''No, we've had no evidence that Saddam Hussein was involved with Sept. 11.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney expressed a slightly different view last night, saying, ''We have never been able to prove that there was a connection there on 9/11.'' He went on to cite a Czech intelligence service report that Mohamed Atta, one of the lead hijackers, met a senior Iraqi intelligence official in April 2001. ''That's never been proven,'' he said. ''It's never been refuted.''</p>
        <p>The commission report released on Wednesday concluded: ''We do not believe that such a meeting occurred,'' citing phone records and other evidence that Mr. Atta was in Florida at that time, not Prague.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney returned to the subject of The Times's coverage later in his appearance on CNBC when an anchor, Gloria Borger, began saying, ''But the press is making a distinction between 9/11 and -- -- ''</p>
        <p>''No, they're not,'' Mr. Cheney said. ''The New York Times does not. 'The Panel Finds No Qaeda-Iraq Ties,''' he said, quoting the headline. ''That's what it says. That's the vaunted New York Times. Numerous -- I've watched a lot of the coverage on it and the fact of the matter is they don't make a distinction. They fuzz it up. Sometimes it's through ignorance. Sometimes its malicious. But you'll take a statement that's geared specifically to say there's no connection in relations to the 9/11 attack and then say, 'Well, obviously there's no case here.' And then jump over to challenge the president's credibility or my credibility.''</p>
        <p>The article in The Times yesterday noted that the White House said Wednesday that it did not see the commission's report as a contradiction of past statements by Mr. Bush and Mr. Cheney, and the article reported that the White House said the administration had always been careful not to suggest that it had proof of a tie between Mr. Hussein and Sept. 11. Dan Bartlett, the White House communications director, was quoted in the article reinforcing those points.</p>
        <p>The Times's coverage of the Iraq-Al Qaeda issue was consistent with that of other large newspapers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and Mr. Cheney were not alone in responding yesterday to the commission's findings. Speaker J. Dennis Hastert, Republican of Illinois, also charged that the media had distorted the findings of the commission about links between Mr. bin Laden and Mr. Hussein. He sad the report showed the two men were ''developing a relationship.''</p>
        <p>''That relationship could have led to dire consequences for the United States,'' Mr. Hastert said, adding that the two men ''are cut from the same cloth.''</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Bush and Mr. Kerry had expected to focus on the economy yesterday, but the dispute over the 9/11 commission's report overshadowed that effort.</p>
        <p>Speaking to reporters in Detroit, Mr. Kerry said that it was Mr. Bush and Mr. Cheney who were muddying distinctions. ''The president and the vice president on a number of occasions have asserted very directly to the American people that the war against Al Qaeda is the war in Iraq. And on any number of occasions, the president has made it clear that the front line of the war against Al Qaeda is in Iraq.''</p>
        <p>Later yesterday he told officials in the Michigan A.F.L.-C.I.O: ''Now we learn in the latest reports of the commission that Al Qaeda had nothing to do with what was happening in Iraq, and we're spending $200 billion of your tax money over there.''</p>
        <p>THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE QAEDA CONNECTION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
