<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ignited by Their Absence, Two Hearts Grow Fonder</title>
    <meta content="18WIND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/18/movies/18WIND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1590237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ozpetek, Ferzan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mezzogiorno, Giovanna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bova, Raoul</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Facing Windows (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Ozpetek, Ferzan</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Facing Windows (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7D81639F93BA25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ignited by Their Absence, Two Hearts Grow Fonder</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ignited by Their Absence, Two Hearts Grow Fonder</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews movie Facing Windows, directed by Ferzan Ozpetek and starring Giovanna Mezzogiorno and Raoul Bova; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Facing Windows,'' a lush, surreally flavored immersion in voyeurism and romantic dreams, muses on many of the same themes as Alfred Hitchcock's ''Rear Window'' and ''Vertigo,'' but from a more conventional emotional perspective. This seductive Italian film uses the image of beautiful strangers secretly and obsessively studying each other through opposite windows to reflect on two related romantic quandaries: the ''grass is always greener'' and ''absence makes the heart grow fonder.''</p>
        <p>Last year, ''Facing Windows'' swept the David di Donatello awards (Italy's Oscars) and helped establish Ferzan Ozpetek, who directed the gay-oriented cult films ''His Secret Love'' and ''Steam,'' as an international voice to be reckoned with.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This lush, surreally flavored immersion in voyeurism and romantic dreams muses on many of the same themes as Alfred Hitchcock's "Rear Window" and "Vertigo."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Facing Windows,'' a lush, surreally flavored immersion in voyeurism and romantic dreams, muses on many of the same themes as Alfred Hitchcock's ''Rear Window'' and ''Vertigo,'' but from a more conventional emotional perspective. This seductive Italian film uses the image of beautiful strangers secretly and obsessively studying each other through opposite windows to reflect on two related romantic quandaries: the ''grass is always greener'' and ''absence makes the heart grow fonder.''</p>
        <p>Last year, ''Facing Windows'' swept the David di Donatello awards (Italy's Oscars) and helped establish Ferzan Ozpetek, who directed the gay-oriented cult films ''His Secret Love'' and ''Steam,'' as an international voice to be reckoned with.</p>
        <p>Despite its surreal touches and an improbable story that piles on the metaphors, the movie, which has a rich, honey-dripping score by Andrea Guerra, maintains a tone of refined heart-tugging realism. Its bittersweet emotional mood recalls Vittorio De Sica's 1970 masterpiece, ''The Garden of the Finzi-Continis,'' whose Holocaust theme is echoed here more softly and from a much greater distance.</p>
        <p>In the close-ups of Giovanna Mezzogiorno, who plays Giovanna, an unhappily married 29-year-old mother of two, and Raoul Bova as Lorenzo, the bachelor bank manager across the way, the camera swoons over two faces of luminous beauty and sensitivity. (The director has put spectacles on Mr. Bova, the Italian heartthrob familiar to American audiences from ''Under the Tuscan Sun,'' to give him an enigmatic Clark Kentish aura.) Despite yourself, you're lured into their mutual fantasy of a fairy-tale escape and a sensual happily-ever-after.</p>
        <p>Instead of encasing the characters in a Hitchcockian murder mystery, the movie, written by Mr. Ozpetek with Gianni Romoli, compares the possible lovers' fantasies to an older romantic story that slowly comes into focus from clues dropped by a mysterious octogenerian (Massimo Girotti), who calls himself Simone but has otherwise lost his memory.</p>
        <p>Slowly, the drama of Simone's youthful love affair, consisting mostly of stolen glances and impassioned notes tucked in the crevices of a statue, begins to cohere. The movie suggests that his memory of that doomed passion remains the defining, possibly life-sustaining experience of his now geriatric existence. Even in retrospect, passion thrives on mystery, distance and obstacles. And Mr. Girotti's quaking, volatile performance suggests that emotions don't evaporate in old age; they only settle into a deeper recess of the heart.</p>
        <p>The man calling himself Simone enters Giovanna's life when her husband, Filippo (Filippo Nigro), a sometime auto mechanic reduced to working night shifts pumping gas, takes pity on him and brings him into their home after he is found wandering the streets looking for help. Filippo's impulsive charity becomes the latest bone of contention in the couple's frayed nine-year marriage. Giovanna, who dreams of being a pastry chef, loathes her work as an accountant in a poultry factory and angrily harangues Filippo for not being able to hold a job for long.</p>
        <p>An introductory flashback, set in 1943 and fleshed out only at the end, shows the youthful Simone (Massimo Poggio) working in a dingy bakery. Unexpectedly assaulted by his boss, Simone grabs a knife, stabs his assailant and flees panic-stricken into the streets.</p>
        <p>Six decades later, the handsome boy has deteriorated into an addled, muttering old man subject to fits of paranoia and weeping. As he dodders along the streets of Rome, his mind plays tricks, and the scene ricochets between the 1940's and today. Once his true identity is determined (it would be giving away too much to say any more), he emerges as the movie's resident sage, a flawed hero who, after regaining some of his memory, lectures Giovanna. ''Don't be content to survive!'' he advises in a tone of trembling agitation. ''You must demand to live in a better world, not just dream about it!''</p>
        <p>When Giovanna first meets Lorenzo, the spark between them is palpable. But they remain circumspect as together they piece together clues -- a concentration camp number tattooed on Simone's arm, a pocket full of gems and an impassioned letter found on his clothing -- as to his true identity. Gradually, the two unfinished love stories, one six decades old, the other just taking shape, begin to merge.</p>
        <p>''Facing Windows,'' which opens today in New York and Los Angeles, is full of small, incisive touches, including the hardheaded comments of Eminè (Serra Yilmaz), Giovanna's busybody neighbor and co-worker at the chicken factory. The vicious fights between Giovanna and Filippo unleash the pent-up frustration of two people impulsively blaming each other for everything that's wrong in their lives.</p>
        <p>The movie's most haunting moment lasts only a few seconds. Breaking away from the besotted Lorenzo, who is almost sobbing with joy now that his dream lover has materialized in his apartment, Giovanna goes to the window through which he's been studying her, and gazes across the way. What she discovers in a hallucinatory revelation is the image of herself gazing back.</p>
        <p>''Facing Windows'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for sexual situations.</p>
        <p>FACING WINDOWS</p>
        <p>Directed by Ferzan Ozpetek; written (in Italian, with English subtitles) by Gianni Romoli and Mr. Ozpetek; director of photography, Gianfilippo Corticelli; edited by Patrizio Marone; music by Andrea Guerra; art direction, Andrea Crisanti; produced by Tilde Corsi and Mr. Romoli; released by Sony Pictures Classics. Running time: 106 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Giovanna Mezzogiorno (Giovanna), Massimo Giroti (Simone), Raoul Bova (Lorenzo), Filippo Nigro (Filippo), Serra Yilmaz (Eminè), Maria Grazia Bon (Sara) and Massimo Poggio (young Simone).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
