<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newsday Says Its Circulation Was Inflated, As Was Hoy's</title>
    <meta content="18PAPE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/18/business/media/18paper.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1590276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tribune Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Newsday</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hoy (Spanish-Language Newspaper)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Audit Bureau of Circulations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Jacques</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Tribune Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Newsday</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Audit Bureau of Circulations</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DD1739F93BA25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newsday Says Its Circulation Was Inflated, As Was Hoy's</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Newsday Says Its Circulation Was Inflated, as Was Hoy's</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinberg, Jacques</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Newsday and Spanish-language daily Hoy, owned by Tribune Co, inflated circulation figures by as much as 10 percent for year ended September 2003; Newsday says it is reducing by about 40,000 copies average daily circulation of 579,729 it had reported to Audit Bureau of Circulations; says average Sunday figure it had reported, 671,819, is being reduced by about 60,000; Hoy's average weekday and Sunday circulation figures--92,604 and 33,198--are being reduced by about 15,000 and 4,000 copies respectively (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two newspapers owned by the Tribune Company, Newsday and the Spanish-language daily Hoy, inflated circulation figures by as much as 19 percent for the year ended last September, Newsday announced yesterday. The paper placed its vice president for circulation on administrative leave.</p>
        <p>Newsday, based in Melville, N.Y., said it was reducing by about 40,000 copies the average daily circulation of 579,729 it had reported to the Audit Bureau of Circulations. It said that the average Sunday figure it had reported, 671,819, was being reduced by about 60,000 copies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Newsday and the Spanish-language daily Hoy inflated circulation figures by as much as 19 percent for the year ended last September.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two newspapers owned by the Tribune Company, Newsday and the Spanish-language daily Hoy, inflated circulation figures by as much as 19 percent for the year ended last September, Newsday announced yesterday. The paper placed its vice president for circulation on administrative leave.</p>
        <p>Newsday, based in Melville, N.Y., said it was reducing by about 40,000 copies the average daily circulation of 579,729 it had reported to the Audit Bureau of Circulations. It said that the average Sunday figure it had reported, 671,819, was being reduced by about 60,000 copies.</p>
        <p>The newspaper said that Hoy's average weekday and Sunday circulation figures -- 92,604 and 33,198 -- were being reduced by about 15,000 and 4,000 copies respectively. Hoy publishes in New York, Chicago and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The discrepancies emerged on Tuesday, as part of a continuing internal audit by Tribune of the newspapers' circulation. Tribune said it began that inquiry in February, after three advertisers filed suit in federal court against Newsday, accusing it of encouraging distributors to destroy unsold copies of the paper so that they would appear to have been sold. The advertisers suggested such practices allowed the paper to raise its circulation base and advertising rates.</p>
        <p>Newsday, which has denied the charges, filed a motion in May seeking a dismissal of the suit, which contends circulation improprieties occurred from 1995 to 1999. That motion is still pending.</p>
        <p>''It would appear that our allegations have substance,'' said Joseph O. Giaimo, the lawyer representing the advertisers in the suit.</p>
        <p>A Tribune spokesman, Gary Weitman, said that the company ''continues to believe the allegations contained in the lawsuit are without merit,'' and that the company's investigation, which is proceeding, ''hasn't uncovered anything to demonstrate otherwise.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, in its statement, Newsday said that the Tribune Company's audit had determined that during parts of 2002 and 2003, ''some copies of Newsday that were distributed for free as part of a home delivery promotional campaign were improperly recorded as paid copies.''</p>
        <p>''In addition,'' the newspaper said, ''some single-copy sales could not be verified because of inadequate record-keeping by one of Newsday's outside distributors.''</p>
        <p>Neither the newspapers nor the Tribune Company offered any explanations yesterday for Hoy's inflated circulation figures. But until February 2003, when it became a unit of Tribune, Hoy was a subsidiary of Newsday. Then, as now, the two newspapers shared some distribution outlets.</p>
        <p>A Newsday spokesman, Stu Vincent, said the circulation executive who was put on leave, Robert Brennan, had worked for the newspaper for more than a decade, mostly in the circulation department. Along with Newsday and Tribune, Mr. Brennan is among the defendants named in the suit.</p>
        <p>A telephone message left last night for Mr. Brennan at his office was not immediately returned.</p>
        <p>As a result of the lawsuit, Newsday's circulation practices are also being investigated by the Audit Bureau of Circulations -- which routinely collects circulation data, but is now looking more deeply at Newsday's numbers -- as well as by the Securities and Exchange Commission. Newsday said yesterday that it expected it would amend the six-month circulation figures it had reported to the audit bureau for the six months ended in March.</p>
        <p>The Newsday announcement comes less than two weeks after Tribune said it was cutting expenses at many of its 14 daily newspapers -- but particularly The Los Angeles Times -- because of advertising losses that were centered in Los Angeles. Newsday reported last week that its publisher, Raymond Jansen, was seeking to lay off more than four dozen pressroom employees to meet Tribune's budget mandates, but was being rebuffed by the union that represents them.</p>
        <p>Newsday's disclosures also come just two days after Hollinger International reported that one of its daily papers, The Chicago Sun-Times, had been overstating its circulation figures. While the company said the size of the overstatement was unclear, it said such practices had apparently occurred over several years.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
