<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With No Other 'Dollys,' Cloning Report Draws Critics</title>
    <meta content="Y30CLO$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cloning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sheep</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Science (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Nicholas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zinder, Norton D (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sgaramella, Vittorio (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cloning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E3DE153AF933A05752C0A96E958260" item-length="1555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With No Other 'Dollys,' Cloning Report Draws Critics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Nicholas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Credibility of experiment reporting cloning of Dolly, Scottish sheep, from cell of adult ewe is being challenged by Dr Norton D Zinder, leading biologist, and other eminent scientists agree that experiment needs to be repeated before it can be accepted; challenge is in form of letter, published in Jan 30 issue of journal Science, by Zinder and Dr Vittorio Sgaramella of University of Calabria in Italy; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The credibility of the experiment reporting the cloning of Dolly the sheep from the cell of an adult ewe is being sharply challenged by a leading biologist, and other eminent scientists agree that the experiment needs to be repeated before it can be accepted.</p>
        <p>The skepticism is erupting almost a year after the original report. The critics note that no other scientist has succeeded in cloning a mammal from an adult cell, although the birth of at least one calf cloned this way is said to be imminent. The cloned calves born earlier this month were generated from fetal cells, not those of an adult cow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The credibility of the experiment reporting the cloning of Dolly the sheep from the cell of an adult ewe is being sharply challenged by a leading biologist, and other eminent scientists agree that the experiment needs to be repeated before it can be accepted.</p>
        <p>The skepticism is erupting almost a year after the original report. The critics note that no other scientist has succeeded in cloning a mammal from an adult cell, although the birth of at least one calf cloned this way is said to be imminent. The cloned calves born earlier this month were generated from fetal cells, not those of an adult cow.</p>
        <p>The challenge is in the form of a letter, being published today in the journal Science, by Dr. Norton D. Zinder, a microbiologist at Rockefeller University and a member of the National Academy of Sciences, and Dr. Vittorio Sgaramella of the University of Calabria in Italy.</p>
        <p>In a response, the chief author of the cloning experiment, Dr. Ian Wilmut of the Roslin Institute in Scotland, dismissed the possibility of error but said that some extra tests suggested were under way and would be reported when completed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zinder's position is not that the cloning of Dolly never occurred, merely that so far there is not enough evidence to prove it.</p>
        <p>In their letter, Dr. Zinder and Dr. Sgaramella note that Dr. Wilmut's cloning of an adult sheep was successful only one out of some 400 times and that in science, one success in 400 ''is an anecdote, not a result.''</p>
        <p>They also criticize Dr. Wilmut's original report for failing to mention that the adult sheep from which Dolly was cloned had died several years earlier. Its absence prevented any direct comparison between Dolly and her donor, in particular the decisive test of a skin graft from one to the other. If true clones, each would have accepted the other's skin graft; if not, any graft would have been rejected.</p>
        <p>Dolly was cloned from a vial of sheep breast cells that had been frozen away in Dr. Wilmut's freezer as part of another project. The critics say it is hard to know what other kinds of sheep cell may have been around in the vial but, since the sheep in question was pregnant at the time, the vial could have contained some of the fetal cells that circulate in the mother's body. If it was a fetal cell that generated the Dolly clone, the outcome would not be startling because Dr. Wilmut had already demonstrated that fetal cells could be cloned.</p>
        <p>''The most heinous crime was not saving the parent,'' Dr. Zinder said.</p>
        <p>''I just don't understand that. There could be nothing more exciting than seeing the two twins standing there,'' he said, referring to the fact that the cloned animals would be like identical twins although of different ages.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilmut said in a phone interview yesterday that he had not intended to clone an adult cell when he started the experiment, which originally dealt with fetal cells. Midway through that experiment, he said, he decided to try cloning an adult cell.  Instead of working with a live animal, he said he used a cell line that was already available.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zinder's criticisms have resonated among other biologists, in part because of a seminar Dr. Wilmut gave recently at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. The seminar was attended by many of Boston's leading biologists, several of whom were surprised to hear him say he did not intend to repeat the experiment.</p>
        <p>It is an article of faith among scientists that an experiment should be replicated in one's own laboratory in case of an error the first time around, as often happens. Also, it is usual to follow up an important result with more experiments.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilmut confirmed that he did not intend to replicate his experiment.</p>
        <p>''I don't perceive a need,'' he said yesterday. ''The principle is established. Repeating experiments is boring and unimaginative.''</p>
        <p>He said he expected his results to be repeated by many other laboratories in the next few months.</p>
        <p>So far three laboratories have tried and failed to repeat Dr. Wilmut's experiment, but others are still trying and are confident of ultimate success, according to an article in Science.</p>
        <p>Other scientists disagree with Dr. Wilmut's view that one need not replicate one's own results.</p>
        <p>''If I have one success in 215 tries and I don't try to duplicate it, then I'm concerned it's not science,'' said Dr. Philip Sharp, a Nobel Prize-winning biologist at M.I.T. who attended the seminar.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sharp described Dr. Wilmut as a ''reputable scientist who has worked long and hard in the field.'' But, he added, ''if you have only one success in an experiment which is so widely recognized from a public and now political perspective, then I am really leery.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruce Alberts, president of the National Academy of Sciences, said he could not comment on Dr. Zinder's letter. ''However,'' Dr. Alberts added, ''it is fair to point out that scientists generally require that a new result be repeated in at least one independent laboratory before they are ready to accept it unambiguously.''</p>
        <p>The issue of human cloning has received considerable public attention since Dr. Wilmut's announcement last February. Politicians from President Clinton, in his State of the Union Message this week, to President Jacques Chirac of France have called for a ban on cloning people.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zinder said he wrote to Science because of his feeling that if there was going to be such an intense public debate over cloning, it would be useful to make sure the underlying facts were true.</p>
        <p>''The whole ambiance of this story was that nobody ever questioned whether or not this was true, and that included the 100-odd page report of the President's Commission on Bioethics,'' Dr. Zinder said. ''Wilmut sat before Congress with Varmus sitting next to him and nobody ever said, 'Is this possibly not true?' '' Dr. Harold Varmus is director of the National Institutes of Health.</p>
        <p>For biologists, the cloning of animals from adult cells has been a longstanding barrier, but one founded more on practical than theoretical obstacles. A full-fledged carrot can be cloned from any cell of an adult carrot, whether a root cell or a leaf cell. So it would not in principle be surprising if the same were true of animals.</p>
        <p>But the most serious effort to clone animals, an elaborate series of experiments on frogs in the 1960's, showed that cells from tadpoles could be cloned but that viable offspring could almost never be obtained from the cells of adult frogs.</p>
        <p>The inference was that as an animal progresses from egg to embryo to adult, its cells become increasingly committed to specific fates. A skin cell, say, somehow switches off all its genes except those needed to operate a skin cell. The off-switches can be reset in a tadpole's cells to generate a whole frog, but not in a grown frog's cells.</p>
        <p>Efforts to clone even fetal cells in mammals failed for many years, and some biologists began to doubt that cloning would ever be possible from specialized adult cells, also known as differentiated cells.</p>
        <p>''The cloning of Elvis Presley from fully differentiated cells is not something we should count on,'' declares a recent textbook on developmental biology. But biologists had been edging ever closer to that goal, or at least its general vicinity, as their techniques improved. By 1986 lambs had been cloned from very early embryos, and Dr. Wilmut in 1996 showed how lambs could be cloned from a later embryo's cells.</p>
        <p>His report last February that he had made the leap to cloning adult cells was more credible because of his previous work in the field. To prove that Dolly's and her donor's DNA were identical, however, Dr. Wilmut used only a single test, the same DNA typing technique that is now accepted in courts. Dr. Zinder said this test was strong but not conclusive, because domestic animals are often highly inbred, meaning that the DNA from two different sheep could quite possibly be identical. Dr. Wilmut said the assertion that sheep are highly inbred was a ''silly exaggeration.''</p>
        <p>The doyen of animal cloning, Dr. John B. Gurdon of Cambridge University in England, who performed the frog cloning experiments of the 1960's, said he believed that Dr. Wilmut's experiment showed an animal could be cloned from an adult, but whether the cell was differentiated was ''a point that has not been shown by Dolly the sheep.'' The frog evidence was more compelling, Dr. Gurdon said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilmut has no doubt that other laboratories will be able to repeat his success.</p>
        <p>''Dolly is real,'' he said. ''In the next few months you'll see positive results coming in from other labs and people will accept it for what it is.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
