<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gotti's Son Is Said to Have Talked in Jail of Killing Co-defendant</title>
    <meta content="30GOTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991539"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gotti, John Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2D7143AF933A05752C0A96E958260" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gotti's Son Is Said to Have Talked in Jail of Killing Co-defendant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, Jan. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal prosecutors say that jail house informant overheard John Gotti Jr say in his Weschester County cell that he wants to kill one of co-defendants in racketeering and extortion case against him (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal prosecutors said today that a jail house informant overheard John Gotti Jr. say in his Westchester County cell that he wanted to kill one of the co-defendants in the racketeering and extortion case against him.</p>
        <p>The accused mob leader -- and son of the convicted Gambino crime family boss, John Gotti -- ''was overheard speaking in jail, discussing his desire to kill a co-defendant,'' said Vincent Heintz, the assistant United States attorney prosecuting the case. He described the source as someone ''with a track record for truth.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal prosecutors said today that a jail house informant overheard John Gotti Jr. say in his Westchester County cell that he wanted to kill one of the co-defendants in the racketeering and extortion case against him.</p>
        <p>The accused mob leader -- and son of the convicted Gambino crime family boss, John Gotti -- ''was overheard speaking in jail, discussing his desire to kill a co-defendant,'' said Vincent Heintz, the assistant United States attorney prosecuting the case. He described the source as someone ''with a track record for truth.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gotti appeared in Federal District Court here for a bail hearing; Magistrate Judge Mark Fox said he would rule on Monday on Mr. Gotti's request to be released from jail. Last week, Mr. Gotti and 39 other defendants were indicted on charges of racketeering and extortion, based on 7,000 Government tapes of their conversations at various places, and on documents and other items seized during raids.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gotti's new lawyer, Gerald Shargel, said the jail house conversation described by prosecutors would prove to be grossly insubstantial evidence. Speaking at a news conference, he said: ''Since the beginning of time, in jail houses across America, people have come to authorities to better themselves. It's not surprising, and I don't take it too seriously.''</p>
        <p>In the hearing, prosecutors argued that Mr. Gotti should not be freed because he has supervising power over the Gambino crime family and was a danger to the community. Mr. Shargel, who in the past has represented Mr. Gotti's father, contended that his client presented no danger, saying he would be willing to accept a large bond and home detention.</p>
        <p>The case against the younger Mr. Gotti is built largely on the tapes, dating back to 1994, which the Government recorded using listening devices planted in key Gotti gathering spots and places of business. Federal officials also have evidence taken from Scores, a nightspot in Manhattan that the Gambino crime family is accused of taking over, and from a social club in Queens.</p>
        <p>At the Queens social club, investigators also found three guns -- a .32-caliber handgun with a silencer, an AR-15 assault rifle and a two-shot derringer. Mr. Shargel said that only the derringer belonged to Mr. Gotti, and that it was an antique that had belonged to his grandfather.</p>
        <p>During the hearing, the judge seemed skeptical of the allegation about Mr. Gotti's jail house threat, or at least of whether it should affect a decision on bail. He offered the prosecution a chance to tell him more about the threat in chambers.</p>
        <p>Another defense lawyer, Richard Rehbock, said: ''You can tell when the Government is losing a case when they come up with some little cockroach in jail who says he heard something. John didn't threaten anybody.''</p>
        <p>To bolster its case that Mr. Gotti should be denied bail, the Government played tapes of some conversations in an effort to show that Mr. Gotti had power in the Gambino crime family after his father was imprisoned for life for racketeering.</p>
        <p>On one tape, Mr. Gotti is heard speaking about Greg DePalma, now a co-defendant: ''Tell him John says: We're all chipping in for Christmas and we're buying him a radio station.'' Mr. Heintz said that followed the disclosure of some leaks and that Mr. Gotti was warning Mr. DePalma that ''he had a big mouth.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Shargel said that in the conversation, Mr. Gotti was simply ''kidding a friend about something.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
