<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wary Gore Confronts A Dilemma</title>
    <meta content="Y30GOR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE PRESIDENT UNDER FIRE: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DD153AF933A05752C0A96E958260" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wary Gore Confronts A Dilemma</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore, despite his limited public role in dealing with sex scandal that has engulfed Pres Clinton, has been active behind scenes; he has told friends and advisers that while he does not known many details about Clinton's involvement with former White House intern Monica S Lewinsky, he believes President is telling truth; aides say Gore has been advising Clinton on how to handle scandal politically; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore stood before television cameras on Wednesday and forcefully defended President Clinton. ''He is the President of the country; he is also my friend,'' Mr. Gore said in introducing the President at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. ''And I want to ask you now, every single one of you, to join me in supporting him and standing by his side.''</p>
        <p>But today, in an event at the Genentech protein laboratory in South San Francisco, the Vice President stuck to the usual script and made no special effort to speak out -- or up -- for the beleaguered Commander in Chief.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore stood before television cameras on Wednesday and forcefully defended President Clinton. ''He is the President of the country; he is also my friend,'' Mr. Gore said in introducing the President at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. ''And I want to ask you now, every single one of you, to join me in supporting him and standing by his side.''</p>
        <p>But today, in an event at the Genentech protein laboratory in South San Francisco, the Vice President stuck to the usual script and made no special effort to speak out -- or up -- for the beleaguered Commander in Chief.</p>
        <p>Unquestionably, Mr. Gore and Mr. Clinton are devoted friends who look out for each other personally and politically.</p>
        <p>Yet the contrast between the two days underscores the dilemma that confronts Mr. Gore. He cannot afford to appear anything but 100 percent loyal. But Mr. Gore's advisers acknowledge that they have made several calculations to make sure that the scandal does not spill onto the Vice President: They have instructed aides to keep out of speeches the Vice President's frequent laugh line about how, because of a glitch during Mr. Clinton's swearing-in ceremony last January, there was actually a ''Gore administration'' for five minutes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's advisers said they delayed the official start of a political action committee -- a vehicle to win support for his Presidential hopes by helping other Democrats this year -- in part out of fear that it might leave an impression that the Vice President was moving too quickly.</p>
        <p>''He was ready to crank out the PAC,'' said a leading Democrat who speaks with Mr. Gore regularly. ''It's been put on hold. Everybody just stopped.''</p>
        <p>A White House official said, ''They're slow-walking it.''</p>
        <p>And Gore aides, not wanting the Vice President to be too prominent in Tuesday night's television coverage of the scandal and the President's State of the Union address, decided not to put him before the cameras after Mr. Clinton's speech. ''There was just so much going on,'' one official said, adding that the decision was that ''it wasn't worth it.''</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Gore's introductions of the President in Champaign, Ill., and La Crosse, Wis., on Wednesday were carefully calibrated. While Mr. Gore vigorously asked the audiences to stand by the President, he did not mention the scandal directly. By that approach he sought to appear loyal without being drawn into the crisis.</p>
        <p>The Vice President has not added any new events to speak out on behalf of Mr. Clinton. But Mr. Gore has used previously scheduled stops -- like his appearances with the President on Wednesday in the Midwest -- to lend his energetic support. But today it was back to his planned schedule, with no special mentions of Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Robert Squier, Mr. Gore's longtime media consultant, said, ''What he is trying to do under these tough circumstances is to keep his eyes straight ahead, doing the job the President assigned him and helping him through this any way he can.''</p>
        <p>Asked why the Vice President did not appear on network television programs on Sunday to defend the President, as did White House aides, Mr. Squier said it was inappropriate for Mr. Gore to discuss details of the accusations.</p>
        <p>''It just didn't seem appropriate that he's the best guy to do that,'' Mr. Squier said. ''You don't have the Vice President going out and basically doing Sunday shows on a story like that.''</p>
        <p>Despite his limited public role in dealing with the scandal, Mr. Gore has been active behind the scenes. He has told friends and advisers that while he does not know many details about Mr. Clinton's involvement with a former White House intern, Monica S. Lewinsky, he believes the President is telling the truth. And in an already-scheduled private meeting with moderate House Democrats on Monday, Mr. Gore offered a feisty defense of the President.</p>
        <p>Aides said Mr. Gore has also been advising Mr. Clinton on how to handle the scandal politically. They said that at their regular lunch last Thursday, both men spoke at length about the unfolding scandal. And late Tuesday night, at a post-State of the Union reception at the White House, the President and Mr. Gore were seen at length talking privately.</p>
        <p>But the aides said the Vice President has kept his advice to Mr. Clinton private, so they do not know specifically what he has told him.</p>
        <p>On Jan. 21, the day the scandal broke, Mr. Gore was traveling in Tennessee but was on the phone frequently with Mr. Clinton. Douglas Sosnik, a senior Clinton adviser, said the President met with top aides in the Cabinet room last week to brief him before he was being interviewed on the scandal. Mr. Sosnik recalled that the President said: ''I just had a conversation with the Vice President. He really gave me good advice. I'm really glad I talk to Al.''</p>
        <p>But publicly, Mr. Gore maintained a game face -- as he did with the lawmaker who traveled with him to Tennessee on Jan. 21. Representative Harold E. Ford Jr., the Tennessee Democrat who accompanied Mr. Gore, said the Vice President did not once mention the scandal, either in their conversations or in public appearances.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's advisers said they were confident their approach is working, because opinion surveys have found that the Vice President's popularity is rising even in the face of Mr. Clinton's troubles.</p>
        <p>One adviser even remarked that the scandal would help the Vice President politically because it has overshadowed Mr. Gore's own campaign finance problems. ''It put a giant period after the end of that particular sentence,'' the adviser said.</p>
        <p>Andrew M. Cuomo, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development who is close to Mr. Gore, insisted that Mr. Clinton and the Vice President were so close that political calculations were not driving Mr. Gore's response to the scandal.</p>
        <p>''This is an issue that is less about political strategy and more about character quality,'' Mr. Cuomo said. ''It's a very simple issue for Al Gore -- it's all about loyalty.''</p>
        <p>THE PRESIDENT UNDER FIRE: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
