<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zambia Gazes at the Power Elite's Dirty Laundry</title>
    <meta content="Y30ZAMB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zambia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcneil, Donald G Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaunda, Kenneth D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zambia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zambia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EED8143AF933A05752C0A96E958260" item-length="1501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zambia Gazes at the Power Elite's Dirty Laundry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONALD G. McNEIL Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcneil, Donald G Jr</byline>
      <dateline>LUSAKA, Zambia, Jan. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Zambian Pres Kenneth D Kaunda is under house arrest while police try to build case that he was behind three-hour coup attempt on Oct 28; his lawyers are fighting to have him released, since prosecutors have presented no evidence, other than unsubstantiated statement that he agreed to give coup leaders money and jobs; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When former President Kenneth D. Kaunda arrives at court each morning, up to 100 soldiers surround him and not only shove photographers back with rifle butts, but also jump like basketball forwards trying to block his face.</p>
        <p>Inside, when a political ally of his asks for a glass of water, a lawyer for Mr. Kaunda makes the court clerk taste it first.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When former President Kenneth D. Kaunda arrives at court each morning, up to 100 soldiers surround him and not only shove photographers back with rifle butts, but also jump like basketball forwards trying to block his face.</p>
        <p>Inside, when a political ally of his asks for a glass of water, a lawyer for Mr. Kaunda makes the court clerk taste it first.</p>
        <p>Suspicion runs deep in Zambian politics these days.</p>
        <p>In the last two years, Zambia has had a bomb blast outside the President's house, a roundup of opposition leaders, a flawed election, the shooting of two opposition candidates, a lawsuit asserting that the President is secretly a foreigner, threats of invasion, riots in the capital, a coup attempt, a roundup of 90 coup suspects, torture allegations and, on Christmas Day, the arrest of Mr. Kaunda.</p>
        <p>And yet, life goes rather normally.  The country, some say, would probably be much the same if none of this had happened. This nation of nine million people on the divide between relatively stable southern Africa and chaotic central Africa is stumbling along: Once relatively wealthy, now poor; once staunchly socialist, now aggressively free-market; never wholly democratic nor wholly despotic, Zambia is still giving the donor nations that support it a combination of hope and the heebie-jeebies.</p>
        <p>A state of emergency is in effect.  But there is no curfew, airports are open and rush-hour traffic jams the business district. As a police sergeant in the northern city of Kitwe said, ''The state of emergency is only for the political elite in Lusaka.''</p>
        <p>Under the emergency's broad detention laws, Mr. Kaunda is under house arrest while the police try to build a case that he was behind the three-hour coup attempt on Oct. 28.</p>
        <p>His lawyers are fighting to have him released, since the prosecutors have presented no evidence, other than an unsubstantiated statement that he agreed to give the coup leaders money and jobs. But Zambia's courts are so slow that a habeas corpus hearing, normally urgent, has dragged on for a month. The Government says Mr. Kaunda exploits the hearings to make speeches, and the court has barred all press contact with him.</p>
        <p>Many Zambians and outside experts believe that the coup attempt had nothing to do with Mr. Kaunda, but was a foray by a few captains and majors who had been drinking and were bitter about their low pay and their generals' handsome lifestyles.</p>
        <p>One of the two accused coup leaders, Capt. Jackson Chiti, testified on  Jan. 15 that the police had tortured him, demanding that he implicate Mr. Kaunda. But he denied that the former President was involved and tearfully apologized to him in court.</p>
        <p>But there are other theories too:  one put about by some American officials and South African military experts is that Zambia overreacted to a feeble coup attempt because it is terrified that Angola is plotting against it.</p>
        <p>Supply flights to the Unita rebels in eastern Angola have originated in western Zambia, prompting threats of invasion by the Angolan Government. Since Angolan troops helped overthrow Presidents Mobutu Sese Seko in the former Zaire and Pascal Lissouba in the Congo Republic last year because Unita had bases in those countries, Zambia is nervous.</p>
        <p>But Eric Silwamba, the President's chief of staff and a special envoy to Angola, said Zambia closed the airstrips and expelled the South African company running the supply flights, Meteor-Ex. Its relations with Angola are cordial again, he said.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, a South African military expert said western Zambia's airspace is still largely unwatched by radar and the Zambian Army is spread thin in border areas west of the Zambezi River.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silwamba denied that the demoted Defense Minister and other party insiders had enriched themselves by helping Unita, which still controls diamond areas.</p>
        <p>The most common outlook on the repeated crises of the last two years is that they all spring from a deep hatred between two very touchy men: Mr. Kaunda, a schoolteacher who led Zambia to independence from Britain in 1964 and ruled it for 27 years, and President Frederick J. T. Chiluba, a trade unionist who formed the coalition that ousted Mr. Kaunda in a democratic election in 1991 and then fractured in squabbles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chiluba ''tried to destroy Dr. Kaunda's reputation, calling him a dictator who ruined the country,'' said the Rev. Nevers Mumba, a clergyman building his own political party. ''That touched Dr. Kaunda's ego and pride. That's what made him come back into politics.''</p>
        <p>The two could hardly be more different. Mr. Kaunda is tall and solid, wears Nehru suits and affects a large white handkerchief into which he alternately storms and weeps; as a liberation leader he combed his hair like Don King's, but now, at 73,  he has a gray beard and lives on raw vegetables.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chiluba, 54, is tiny and efficient, a fundamentalist Christian who wears natty suits and does without a scurrying entourage. In his rapid-delivery speeches, he quickly lapses into tart scorn, doing imitations while telling folksy stories deriding Mr. Kaunda, African and Western leaders and other critics.</p>
        <p>''I think he's driven by a fear of appearing weak,'' said Jim Polhemus, an American consultant studying democracy here. ''The people around him are telling him not to let Mandela or Mugabe or the donor nations push him around.''</p>
        <p>Asked about the series of crises,  Mr. Kaunda's party says Mr. Chiluba changed the Constitution to bar him from running again in 1996, planted small bombs as an excuse to claim the existence of a ''Black Mamba gang'' and jail his party leadership until the 1996 race was over, rigged the election, secretly ordered the police to fire into Mr. Kaunda's car during a 1997 party meeting, grazing him and seriously wounding an ally, framed him on the coup charges and hopes for another chance to kill him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chiluba's aides say Mr. Kaunda ignored the people's will by running again, produced false witnesses saying Mr. Chiluba is Zairian, faked his own shooting, provoked the 1997 riot in which the downtown  market was burned and arranged the coup attempt.</p>
        <p>Almost every one of these charges has led to court; almost all have petered out inconclusively. The Black Mamba bombing charges were dropped for lack of evidence.  The Supreme Court ruled that Mr.  Chiluba did not have to take a DNA test to prove his identity. It still has not ruled on the 1996 election. The wounding of Mr. Kaunda has yet to be officially investigated.</p>
        <p>Acknowledging that it looked as if the Government trumped up the  Black Mamba case, Mr. Silwamba says the police botched it by being hasty. They do not want to repeat that mistake over the coup, he said.  He denied that the Government was persecuting Mr. Kaunda.</p>
        <p>Many Zambians view these fights as confined to the political elite.</p>
        <p>''The average Zambian is marginalized completely, and the playing ground is being left to the politicians,'' said Ngande Mwanajiti, who ran the Clean Campaign Committee in 1996. As a defender of civil liberties, though, he feels threatened.  ''The police can come and take me away at any time.''</p>
        <p>Most Zambians, however, are just trying to get by. The standard of living today is about half what it was in 1964, when copper prices were high. Mr. Kaunda's socialism unraveled the economy, and Mr. Chiluba's bold privatization efforts have forced thousands of layoffs.</p>
        <p>The foreign investment he hopes to attract is slow in arriving, and the budget is propped up with foreign aid. Mr. Silwamba calls that ''the pity of being a poor country -- they give the money, so they want you to play the tune.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chiluba's Government resents the fuss foreigners are suddenly making over Mr. Kaunda. They recall that Mr. Kaunda muzzled the press, jailed hundreds of political opponents and made children leave school to line the roads and wave whenever his motorcade went by.  Many Zambians remember waiting all night for cooking oil or sugar, which inevitably ran out, leaving soldiers to whip angry shoppers away.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' a museum guard said, ''it is the opposite. There is food on the shelves -- but no money to buy it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
