<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the New Mayor, a City's Advice on Challenges That Must Be Faced; Untangling Transportation</title>
    <meta content="MB024742" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1342447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DA1338F931A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the New Mayor, a City's Advice on Challenges That Must Be Faced; Untangling Transportation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City's mayor-elect, Michael R Bloomberg, will be called on to fix growing traffic problems; unusually broad coalition of civic leaders, business groups and transportation experts agree on need to place tolls on East River bridges (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Memo to: Michael R. Bloomberg.</p>
        <p>Re: Advice from experts, academics, union leaders, politicians and ordinary New Yorkers on coping with business, transportation, housing, education, race relations and municipal labor unions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Memo to: Michael R. Bloomberg.</p>
        <p>Re: Advice from experts, academics, union leaders, politicians and ordinary New Yorkers on coping with business, transportation, housing, education, race relations and municipal labor unions.</p>
        <p>Effective: Jan. 1, 2002.</p>
        <p>Institute tax-free days on some retail goods. Begin charging tolls on East River bridges. Build housing on industrial sites. End political fighting over schools and think of the one million pupils as your children. Make your administration racially and ethnically diverse and its spending policies fair. Keep a lid on city labor costs, but don't lose teachers or police officers to the suburbs. Hold down the deficits, but preserve those city services.</p>
        <p>These are just a few ideas to get you started. Good luck!</p>
        <p>The issue probably could not be summed up more accurately or succinctly than it was in Mayor-elect Bloomberg's campaign position paper on transportation:</p>
        <p>''Traffic is a mess!'' the paper's first sentence read.</p>
        <p>It was already a mess before Sept. 11 -- and not just for drivers. Underground, the huge increase in subway ridership in the past five years has brought the morning commute to dangerously crowded levels.</p>
        <p>Since the attacks, the mess has grown  worse and much harder to untangle. And as Mr. Bloomberg begins to assign priorities, an unusually broad coalition of civic leaders, business groups and transportation experts seems to be reaching a consensus on one way for him to deal with the problems.</p>
        <p>The idea, long considered untouchable in New York City politics, is to place tolls on East River bridges -- in essence, ending free passage by automobile into Manhattan on all the major crossings. The change could then be coupled with raised tolls on the crossings during the morning rush and lowered ones during off-peak times.</p>
        <p>It's not a new concept: long-distance telephone companies and airlines have long charged customers more for periods of high demand. The basis of the idea for New York City is to treat roads in the city's business center as a much more precious resource than they are now. Drivers who want to commute into Manhattan by car could still do so, but they would have to pay.</p>
        <p>''It's been something that no politician has really ever wanted to talk about,'' said John Kaehny, executive director of Transportation Alternatives, a pedestrian advocacy group. ''But for the first time, usually skittish elected officials are giving this a serious look.''</p>
        <p>Effects could be wide-ranging. Tolls could serve to reduce traffic not only in Manhattan but throughout the city, easing congestion for commercial vehicles and for emergency traffic, a much greater priority in the city since Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>More importantly, the tolls could generate more than $700 million a year, which could be used exclusively for maintaining roads and bridges and also, toll proponents have stressed, for mass transit.</p>
        <p>Improving and expanding the subways -- buying more trains and buses and even building new lines for the first time in decades -- is something transit officials and riders said must happen if more people are going to be persuaded to leave their cars.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Bloomberg's notable promises was that he will urge more people to take mass transit by taking it often himself. Advocates for better transportation policies said they hoped that he not only stuck to that promise but also followed through on other proposals for transportation that he campaigned on -- like regaining more city control over subways and buses, reducing wait times for subways, and creating dedicated rapid bus lanes in the city.</p>
        <p>''Bloomberg's transportation platform for the campaign was a good one,'' said Elliot G. Sander, director of the Rudin Center for Transportation Policy and Management at New York University. ''He should not let the events of Sept. 11 take him off course.''</p>
        <p>RANDY KENNEDY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
