<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kenyans Sip Democracy But Find It Bitter, So Far</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="579738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KENYA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOI, DANIEL ARAP (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOBLE, KENNETH B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D61631F93AA15751C1A964958260" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kenyans Sip Democracy But Find It Bitter, So Far</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH B. NOBLE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NOBLE, KENNETH B</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, Dec. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The campaign for Kenya's first multiparty elections in 26 years ended tonight with charges that brutality and fraud were being used to win votes.</p>
        <p>On the eve of the voting Tuesday, President Daniel arap Moi urged supporters not to drink any alcohol, warning that the opposition was plotting to dilute them with hallucinogens to make voters so drowsy that they would oversleep and miss the balloting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The campaign for Kenya's first multiparty elections in 26 years ended tonight with charges that brutality and fraud were being used to win votes.</p>
        <p>On the eve of the voting Tuesday, President Daniel arap Moi urged supporters not to drink any alcohol, warning that the opposition was plotting to dilute them with hallucinogens to make voters so drowsy that they would oversleep and miss the balloting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moi, who has ruled for 14 years, also announced an overnight ban on the use of trucks and other large vehicles. He said this was to prevent opposing parties from busing supporters to voting districts where they were weak.</p>
        <p>And two of the main opposition contenders, Oginga Odinga and Mwai Kibaki, charged that serious electoral irregularities had already occurred. They insisted that the President would finish no higher than third in a fair election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moi, who succeeded Jomo Kenyatta as President in 1978, may have surpassed him in concentrating Kenyan political power in the presidency. After a coup attempt 10 years ago, he intensified efforts to put down dissent.</p>
        <p>A year ago, Mr. Moi grudgingly agreed under foreign pressure to end a ban on opposition parties and promised fair elections. Some thought Kenya, long a one-party state, was moving toward political pluralism.</p>
        <p>But increasingly in recent weeks, the political climate has again turned rough and sometimes ugly, with little focus on issues. Candidates and their supporters have often campaigned with invective and have sometimes returned to violence.</p>
        <p>An editorial today in The Nation, an independent paper, reflected the anger and anxiety many Kenyans feel.</p>
        <p>"It impossible to pretend," it said, "that the electoral process has been totally fair. Kenyans should make no mistake: as a country we are at a crossroads. Kenya's once-booming economy is under severe pressure" and can no longer bear "the effects of accumulated corruption and inefficiency that is pulling it down.". Once Seen as a Model</p>
        <p>Such pessimism is striking in light of Kenya's previous reputation as an economically stable and politically mature African country. In the 1970's and 80's, in part because of its pro-Western outlook and position on the Indian Ocean, Kenya received large amounts of Western aid.</p>
        <p>In recent months, though, much aid has been suspended because donors including the United States regard the Moi Government as increasingly corrupt and authoritarian.</p>
        <p>The conventional wisdom in Kenyan political circles had at first been that virtually any of the seven candidates challenging Mr. Moi would win handily in a fair contest. So incompetent and unpopular was the incumbent, it was said, that he would be lucky to win a majority even among his own small tribe, the Kalenjin.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Moi is a relentless campaigner and his party, the long-ruling Kenya African National Union, remains a vote-generating machine.</p>
        <p>The President's pitch has not wavered: Stability, he says, can be guaranteed only if he and his party win. The other parties, he insists, represent tribalism, the curse of Africa.</p>
        <p>"The opposition badly underestimated Moi," said an African diplomat with long experience in Kenya. "Here is a man who has been a professional politician for 37 years; you don't last that long at the top unless you're smart and savvy. Moi has outwitted them all."  Second Round Possible</p>
        <p>Still, predictions about the outcome are uncertain. The main question is whether Mr. Moi can win the 25 percent in five of the eight provinces that is required for outright victory. If he fails, most impartial observers believe, he will face a tougher run-off against the strongest challenger.</p>
        <p>The prospects for a first-round opposition victory, however, are hardly promising. The opposition is deeply split along regional and tribal lines. Mr. Odinga, a Luo from western Kenya and a former Vice President, leads one faction. Kenneth Matiba, a Kikuyu and former Cabinet minister, who was detained by Mr. Moi for almost a year in 1990 and 1991 for urging an end to one-party rule, leads another. Still another faction, the Democratic Party, is led by a former Vice President and Finance Minister, Mwai Kibaki, who is also from the Kikuyu tribe, the largest and formerly the most powerful in Kenya.</p>
        <p>Perceptions of electoral integrity, or the lack of it, are expected to determine whether Kenya stands at the dawn of progress under a new democracy or the brink of political disarray. Only the Government and the ruling-party apparatus can tamper with the vote effectively. If Mr. Moi wins, the cheating issue will loom large.</p>
        <p>Whether the election is perceived as being fair will determine in large part whether donor nations will continue to reduce or withhold aid.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
