<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Freshman Is Lead Again In 'A Star Is Born' Sequel</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="599779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="WOMEN'S DIVISION I"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, KATIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BONDY, FILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DD1231F930A35757C0A965958260" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Freshman Is Lead Again In 'A Star Is Born' Sequel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FILIP BONDY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BONDY, FILIP</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Katie Smith is busy being discovered, again, this weekend in Atlanta at the N.C.A.A. women's Final Four.</p>
        <p>The freshman forward thought these revelations were finished when she was playing high school basketball in Logan, Ohio (population 6,725). Scouts came regularly to the Chieftains' cozy gym then, watched Smith average 29.2 points a game and dubbed her the Larry Bird of women's basketball. By the time she was a senior, Smith was so popular, the school built a 2,200-seat gym, where the scouts and fans could be more comfortable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Katie Smith is busy being discovered, again, this weekend in Atlanta at the N.C.A.A. women's Final Four.</p>
        <p>The freshman forward thought these revelations were finished when she was playing high school basketball in Logan, Ohio (population 6,725). Scouts came regularly to the Chieftains' cozy gym then, watched Smith average 29.2 points a game and dubbed her the Larry Bird of women's basketball. By the time she was a senior, Smith was so popular, the school built a 2,200-seat gym, where the scouts and fans could be more comfortable.</p>
        <p>Smith, the valedictorian of her class last June, chose to attend Ohio State, ahead of offers from Virginia, Stanford and Kent State. But it wasn't a hometown decision.</p>
        <p>"It wasn't like I was always a Buckeye at heart," Smith said yesterday. "Logan was closer to the Ohio University campus, and my dad played football there. I was an O.U. Bobcat fan, and we owned season tickets to all the basketball games." A Title on Her Shoulders?</p>
        <p>After Texas Tech meets Vanderbilt in the first semifinal game on Saturday, Smith and Ohio State will face the tough Iowa man-to-man defense and the clawing arms of Tia Jackson. And Smith is again the source of curiosity. Experts wonder whether a 5-foot-11-inch forward, even one who averaged 18.0 points, 5.7 rebounds and 3.2 assists a game this season, can really carry her team to a championship.</p>
        <p>Smith, who will swing back to guard at times against the Hawkeyes, is remarkably versatile. She has a steady outside shot, hitting 35 of 77 3-pointers and 56.7 percent from the floor over all during the regular season. She can post up, using her solid, 167-pound frame to body up against defenders. She has a quick first step and natural basketball instincts off the ball.</p>
        <p>There is another Bird-like trait: Smith is not a great leaper, which is never a fatal affliction in the women's better-grounded game.</p>
        <p>"I do a little of everything," Smith said. "I take great pride in creating for other teammates. Sometimes, I'm a decoy. I don't dribble between my legs. When I do dribble, I'm going somewhere." Support System</p>
        <p>Ohio State Coach Nancy Darsch was a bit apprehensive about the pressure and attention that Smith would face here in Atlanta this weekend. But Ohio State also starts three seniors and a junior, and they have been extremely supportive of their freshman star.</p>
        <p>"They all sort of took Katie and explained to her that we were all in this together," Darsch said. "She's not here by herself."</p>
        <p>Ohio State, ranked No. 3 in the Associated Press poll, barely survived its regional final against Virginia, holding on to a 75-73 victory. Now the Buckeyes face the erratic, emotional Iowa team, which split two games with Ohio State during the season. Thinking of Dental School</p>
        <p>"When they came to Columbus, it was a sellout, and Iowa was so pumped they were just jumping out of our gym," Smith said. "But we contained them, and that's how it's got to be again this time. Whoever jumps out first, plays the toughest defense, is going to win."</p>
        <p>Smith might be a gifted ballhandler and a product of smalltown Midwestern basketball, but the comparisons with Bird end with her post-graduate plans. Because there are no professional opportunities available in the United States for female basketball players, Smith has other career notions.</p>
        <p>"I'd like to go to dental school," Smith said. "But I'll take something out of the basketball. I'll know about leadership, and taking charge, and accepting criticism." Focus on Swoopes</p>
        <p>Smith is not the only leader at the Omni. In the first game on Saturday, Texas Tech's Sheryl Swoopes, the N.C.A.A. player of the year, will be the focus of attention and the chief threat to No. 1-ranked Vanderbilt.</p>
        <p>The 6-foot Swoopes scored 53 points against Texas three weeks ago, but will face a different sort of challenge in Heidi Gillingham, the Commodores' 6-10 center.</p>
        <p>"She's going to be a little intimidating," Swoopes said of the tallest player at the Final Four. "When someone is that tall, it makes you think twice about taking a shot in the paint. But I'll still attack her."</p>
        <p>Gillingham said she was ready for the aptly named Swoopes and her dashes for the basket.</p>
        <p>"I'll be inside as a barrier to her drives," Gillingham said. "She's a great player, but I'll be there."</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Coaches and officials are trying to ignore the irksome notion that the local CBS affiliate in Atlanta has decided to pick up the first semifinal game on Saturday in progress, after its early afternoon news program. . . . VIVIAN STRINGER, coach at Iowa, is angrier about something else: The Ohio State public address announcer will be courtside, acting in that capacity for the Buckeye-Hawkeye semifinal.</p>
        <p>"Any slight hint of a comfort zone should be taken away," Stringer said. "It bothers me a great deal, because this game doesn't have anything to do with their school."  WOMEN'S DIVISION I</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
