<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Trade Ties to Hanoi, Japanese Jump the Gun</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="568409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JAPAN-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-VIETNAM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIETNAM WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRISONERS OF WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSING IN ACTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EMBARGOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VIETNAM</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANGER, DAVID E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MIYAZAWA, KIICHI (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Vietnam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Vietnam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D9123DF935A35752C1A964958260" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Trade Ties to Hanoi, Japanese Jump the Gun</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SANGER, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Friday, Nov. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jumping ahead of American policy in Asia, the Japanese Government announced today that it was resuming broad economic ties with Vietnam, including the offer of a major loan package, senior Japanese officials said.</p>
        <p>The move comes in response to heavy pressure from Japanese business groups, which have urged the governing Liberal Democratic Party to pave the way for a variety of long-planned investments in Vietnam by Japanese companies. Tokyo is expected to announce a $375 million package on Friday, and that may be followed by loans from its Export-Import Bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jumping ahead of American policy in Asia, the Japanese Government announced today that it was resuming broad economic ties with Vietnam, including the offer of a major loan package, senior Japanese officials said.</p>
        <p>The move comes in response to heavy pressure from Japanese business groups, which have urged the governing Liberal Democratic Party to pave the way for a variety of long-planned investments in Vietnam by Japanese companies. Tokyo is expected to announce a $375 million package on Friday, and that may be followed by loans from its Export-Import Bank.</p>
        <p>Some government officials and business executives familiar with the internal debate over the issue said the Government of Prime Minister Kiichi Miyazawa had postponed its announcement until after the American elections. It feared that acting earlier would open Japan to criticism during the Presidential campaign that it was catering to the Japanese business interests while questions remain unresolved about the fate of American soldiers missing since the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>With the recent announcement by Hanoi that it would open its records on American P.O.W.'s and M.I.A.'s, Washington is expected to move fairly quickly to lift the American embargo on trade with Vietnam and to begin to normalize relations.</p>
        <p>Japanese officials said they had informed the United States of their actions, but they declined to characterize the American response. They also said Japan had urged the Vietnamese to provide more information about the missing Americans.</p>
        <p>Unlike the United States, Japan never broke relations with Hanoi after the American pullout from Vietnam. But in 1979, after Vietnamese troops invaded Cambodia, it halted virtually all aid to the Communist Government. Vietnam, in return, refused to pay back Japanese loans amounting to nearly $200 million, and since then economic relations have been stalled.</p>
        <p>A senior Japanese official involved in the decision over Vietnam said recently that "we are looking at this as a symbol," and that Japan has told the United States that "we want U.S. relations with Vietnam normalized."</p>
        <p>American officials have said little publicly about Japan's impending action, though the Bush Administration was apparently informed of it several months ago. Last week Lawrence S. Eagleburger, the acting Secretary of State, said during a visit to Tokyo that "whatever the Japanese Government decides to do, we have our own view of how to proceed."</p>
        <p>"We will not be affected by what the Japanese Government decides," he added.</p>
        <p>For Japan, the decision appears to edge away from foreign policy positions that were largely defined by the United States. In recent months Japan has been stepping up its warming of relations with China, capped by a tour of the country last month by Emperor Akihito. Tokyo has also kept up a dialogue with the repressive Government of Myanmar, formerly Burma, where Japanese diplomats insist that quiet persuasion -- and continued relief aid -- has begun to soften the regime.</p>
        <p>For the Vietnamese, courting Japan has been a major priority. Not only is Tokyo the largest contributor of aid, it is also the likeliest source of capital to rebuild the country's decrepit infrastructure. Some here say the expanded relationship with Japan may place subtle pressure on the United States to restore diplomatic relations and end its trade embargo, though Japanese officials deny that this is their goal.</p>
        <p>Among Japanese companies, Vietnam is considered one of Asia's last frontiers: a cheap and well-educated work force, in a country with enough population density to become a prime market, over time, for the lowest-tech Japanese goods.</p>
        <p>Already Ho Chi Minh City's hotels are brimming over with Japanese businessmen, looking for everything from oil contracts to good sites for low-technology factories. Japanese-made products, especially electronics, are already widely sold. Executives say they want to lay the groundwork for the day when Thailand and Malaysia, two other countries that have received enormous Japanese capital investment in recent years, become too expensive for further expansion. Business Dealings Grow</p>
        <p>Over the last two years, several of Japan's giant trading houses have opened small offices for representatives in Vietnam. Recently five Japanese companies joined to open a shipping and distribution company that could send manufacturing plants and equipment to Vietnam. Mitsubishi Oil Company recently signed a contract for rights to conduct test borings for oil off Vietnam's southern coast.</p>
        <p>Before they expanded further, however, the Japanese companies wanted to see Japanese aid pouring into the country, partly as insurance that their bills would be paid. "We knew that we had to get past the burden of the unpaid old loans," said an official of Mitsui, one of the trading houses with a growing presence in Vietnam. "But they have oil and cheap labor, and because the infrastructure is so limited, we can expect some business to build it."</p>
        <p>Japanese officials, in announcing the package this morning, said that they had received "support" from the United States for the resumption of aid. Under the package announced today, the $375 million loan must be repaid within 30 years, but Japan will charge no interest for the first 10 years and only 1 percent interest thereafter.</p>
        <p>Vietnam will pay off its outstanding loans with cash received under the new program. That is expected to leave more than $200 million for projects to rebuild the country's shattered roads, and to build new factories and housing.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>U.S. Re-examining Policy</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, Nov. 5 (Special to The New York Times) -- Buoyed by a Vietnamese decision to turn over archival material on missing Americans, the Bush Administration is re-examining its policy on recognition of Vietnam and the lifting of a trade and aid embargo, officials say.</p>
        <p>American companies have been pressing President Bush to allow trade and investment in Vietnam, where, in addition to the Japanese, businesses from Taiwan, South Korea, Singapore, Hong Kong and Thailand have been very active.</p>
        <p>Under a road map to recognition given to the Vietnamese a year ago, "substantial" progress on explaining the fate of missing Americans could lead to the lifting of the embargo and the opening of an American liaison office in Hanoi and a Vietnamese office in Washington.</p>
        <p>Full diplomatic recognition, according to the Bush Administration's plan, would await a democratic election in Cambodia, tentatively scheduled for next spring. President-elect Bill Clinton has given no indication that this timetable would change.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
