<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For This Mother of 9, Faith Equals Teaching by Example</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="One Catholic Family: A Glimpse of the Pope" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="794871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THE POPE'S VISIT: THE REIDYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ST JOSEPH'S SEMINARY (YONKERS, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REIDY, MARCIA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REIDY, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REIDY, NIALL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">POPE (JOHN PAUL II)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D6103FF934A35753C1A963958260" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For This Mother of 9, Faith Equals Teaching by Example</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marcia Reidy awoke at 6 A.M. and the day started as usual for the mother of nine. She fed the children, she acted as chauffeur for her 16-year-old daughter, she took the three youngest to the park. And then, at a little after 2 P.M., she went off to see Pope John Paul II in Yonkers.</p>
        <p>"It was terrific," she said afterward, in her matter-of-fact way. There was a moment yesterday, though, when her blue eyes misted. It was when the Pope slowly turned the corner in the Popemobile and seemed to look straight at her family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marcia Reidy awoke at 6 A.M. and the day started as usual for the mother of nine. She fed the children, she acted as chauffeur for her 16-year-old daughter, she took the three youngest to the park. And then, at a little after 2 P.M., she went off to see Pope John Paul II in Yonkers.</p>
        <p>"It was terrific," she said afterward, in her matter-of-fact way. There was a moment yesterday, though, when her blue eyes misted. It was when the Pope slowly turned the corner in the Popemobile and seemed to look straight at her family.</p>
        <p>"He seemed so close," she said, asking her 10-year-old son, Niall, "Did you see him wave at you?"</p>
        <p>It was the culmination of a week of planning and a lifetime of faith. Getting to St. Joseph's Seminary in Yonkers was no simple matter. Her husband, William, uses crutches, and Niall is in a wheelchair because of two strokes he had after heart surgery five years ago.</p>
        <p>Would they get close enough to see after Niall and Mr. Reidy were put in the wheelchairs? Would the crowd be too big?</p>
        <p>It turned out that the three were in the front row of the small crowd of handicapped people behind a fence in front of the seminary. During the two-hour wait for the Pope, Mrs. Reidy fed chocolate chip cookies to Niall, who cannot feed himself. She watched to see that her husband was not getting too tired leaning on his crutches. She kept an eye on a little boy in a wheelchair next to them, warning his mother when he was in danger of poking himself in the eye with the stick of a papal flag.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Reidy spends much of her time worrying about others. At 48, the big-boned blond daughter of an investment banker, who was reared in comfort on Manhattan's Upper East Side, presides over a brood ranging in age from 20 to 3.</p>
        <p>She is a quiet woman but it is clear that she is always in charge. She knows where everyone is at all times. She never has to raise her voice or repeat herself to be heard.</p>
        <p>For years, her husband ran Reidy's, the East Side restaurant he inherited. Because of his disability from a childhood bout with polio, many of the tasks of running the household fall on her shoulders.</p>
        <p>"People say, 'Does your mother have a job?' " Anne, 17, said. "It's hard to say she's at home. You can't define what my mother does. She's on the parents committee at school; she manages Niall; it's so much."</p>
        <p>In her big home in the Riverdale section of the Bronx, Mrs. Reidy has a desk in the kitchen that is obscured by a blizzard of papers and a white telephone with several lines. On a wall in front of her are the school schedules and calendars of the seven children who live at home. Five schools in all.</p>
        <p>She is on the mother's board of Ursuline School, which Marcia, the 16-year-old, attends; she is part of parish school planning at St. Gabriel's, attended by three of her sons; and she helps the board of Regis School, attended by Owen, 14.</p>
        <p>She does not have much time to think about what it means to be Catholic. The best example she can think of dates back to the first six weeks of Niall's life, which he spent in a hospital. Her parish jumped in to help.</p>
        <p>"The parents of St. Gabriel coordinated themselves so that there was dinner on the table every night," she said. "I'll never forget that as long as I live."</p>
        <p>"I think you treat others as you want to be treated," she said. "You do the most good where you are in life, as a homemaker or priest or whatever."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Reidy says she tries to teach by example. She does not talk about the need for volunteer service, but rather goes to visit elderly and sick people in the neighborhood. As she left for St. Joseph's yesterday, she reminded Conor, 6, that his overnight guest "came first."</p>
        <p>On the short drive to St. Joseph's Mrs. Reidy seemed a bit nervous. She asked Mr. Reidy if he had the tickets to get in.</p>
        <p>Then the Pope drove by, his ruddy face bright. Marcia Reidy seemed happy, in a moment that belonged to her alone.</p>
        <p>TOMORROW: With the Reidy daughters at the papal Mass in Central Park.</p>
        <p>THE POPE'S VISIT: THE REIDYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
