<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After a Turnabout in the Beginning, Kasparov and Anand Coast to a Draw</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="794735"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHESS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL CHESS FEDERATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BYRNE, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KASPAROV, GARY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANAND, VISWANATHAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4DB1239F934A35753C1A963958260" item-length="429" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After a Turnabout in the Beginning, Kasparov and Anand Coast to a Draw</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT BYRNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BYRNE, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whether he wanted it or not, Viswanathan Anand agreed yesterday to a draw in  Game 16 of his world championship chess match with Gary Kasparov. It was correctly played, but there were no stirring moments, no inspiring what-if moves that could have enlivened a slow, maneuvering game. So it looks as though the 25-year-old Indian grandmaster has reconciled himself to bowing out with respectable draws.</p>
        <p>Sometimes in chess, it takes magic to create the kind of unbalanced melee from which a bright victory might emerge. But it is very often difficult to budge an opponent going all out to be careful. And Kasparov has obviously no interest in running up the score with some speculative adventure. It is hard to  imagine him taking any kind of bait, supposing that Anand could find something to put on his hook.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whether he wanted it or not, Viswanathan Anand agreed yesterday to a draw in  Game 16 of his world championship chess match with Gary Kasparov. It was correctly played, but there were no stirring moments, no inspiring what-if moves that could have enlivened a slow, maneuvering game. So it looks as though the 25-year-old Indian grandmaster has reconciled himself to bowing out with respectable draws.</p>
        <p>Sometimes in chess, it takes magic to create the kind of unbalanced melee from which a bright victory might emerge. But it is very often difficult to budge an opponent going all out to be careful. And Kasparov has obviously no interest in running up the score with some speculative adventure. It is hard to  imagine him taking any kind of bait, supposing that Anand could find something to put on his hook.</p>
        <p>The score is now 9 1/2-6 1/2 with four games left. Another draw will give Kasparov at least a tie match and thus enable him to retain his title.</p>
        <p>During a press briefing after the game, Anand politely refused to sum up the  match. "I am not pretending that I am going to win," he said, "but there are two more games to be played."</p>
        <p>Actually, that was a revealing slip because there would be four games, if by  some miracle he could start winning and keep it up. He is too sensible to have high hopes.</p>
        <p>Turnabout is fair play. Anand had not played a Sicilian Defense in this match, and very sparingly in the last few years, but yesterday he selected Kasparov's favorite Najdorf Variation of the Sicilian. Of course, when Anand used to play the Sicilian, he often made it a Najdorf, so he was hardly a stranger to it. To keep the turnabout going, Kasparov selected the quiet, positional 6 Be2 that Anand has been confronting him with in this series.</p>
        <p>The game copied Game 7, with colors reversed, up to 15 . . . Qb8, when 16 e5  was the move, but now Kasparov chose the noncommittal 16 Bd4. This foreshadowed  what was to happen. The champion simply held his ground as White and Anand could not find a way to heat up a fight. When Kasparov offered a draw, the challenger  accepted it.</p>
        <p>The players took an hour and a quarter for the 20 moves. Game 17 is scheduled for Monday at 3 P.M.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
