<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When the News Is Bad, Analysts Feel the Heat</title>
    <meta content="12OOPS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Agco Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Snyder, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gladestone, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DA1731F931A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1299" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When the News Is Bad, Analysts Feel the Heat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK GLADSTONE</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on rare downgrade of Agco Corp stock to 'market performance,' considered euphemism for 'sell,' by securities analyst David Snyder; other analysts comment on such actions and their consequences; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL STREET securities analysts occasionally deliver bad news on a stock. But it's unusual when they unequivocally call their past advice to buy it a blunder.</p>
        <p>That is what David Snyder, an analyst at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, did with regard to the shares of the Agco Corporation, a leading maker of farm equipment, whose stock has fallen by a third since March and is languishing in the $19 to $20 range. Mr. Snyder removed Agco from the firm's ''recommended list'' on May 30, saying the company had often fallen short of earnings expectations since 1996, when it began an enormous expansion overseas. Given that history, he wrote in a summary of Donaldson, Lufkin's stock picks, ''investors are not likely to be very patient with any disappointments.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALL STREET securities analysts occasionally deliver bad news on a stock. But it's unusual when they unequivocally call their past advice to buy it a blunder.</p>
        <p>That is what David Snyder, an analyst at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, did with regard to the shares of the Agco Corporation, a leading maker of farm equipment, whose stock has fallen by a third since March and is languishing in the $19 to $20 range. Mr. Snyder removed Agco from the firm's ''recommended list'' on May 30, saying the company had often fallen short of earnings expectations since 1996, when it began an enormous expansion overseas. Given that history, he wrote in a summary of Donaldson, Lufkin's stock picks, ''investors are not likely to be very patient with any disappointments.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Snyder went further. He wrote that Agco's stock valuation would likely remain depressed, and that ''we have been terribly wrong on Agco's stock over the past two years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Snyder subsequently left Donaldson, Lufkin, co-manager of the underwriting of Agco securities in 1996 and 1997, for Dawson Samberg Capital Management, a money management firm. Leslie Thompson, a spokeswoman for Donaldson, Lufkin, called Mr. Snyder's departure and the Agco downgrade coincidental. ''A good analyst is an honest analyst,'' she said. ''Mr. Snyder is a very well respected person. We have the highest regard for him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Snyder did not return several telephone calls for comment.</p>
        <p>Judith Czelusniak, vice president of corporate relations at Agco, said the company, based in Duluth, Ga., had only recently learned that Mr. Snyder had moved on, but she declined to comment on his departure.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Snyder's downgrade of Agco to ''market performance'' -- considered a euphemism for ''sell'' -- was conspicuous because of its blunt, self-critical assessment of a perceived mistake. Against the backdrop of the voracious appetite for stocks in a seven-year-old bull market, a sell signal like that tends to stand out.</p>
        <p>''He committed the unforgivable,'' said Marvin Roffman, a securities analyst at Roffman Miller Associates in Philadelphia. In the ''sell side'' world of stocks, Mr. Roffman said, ''even using the word 'sell' is anathema.''</p>
        <p>MR. SNYDER was not the first to lower his opinion of Agco. Eric Hunter, an analyst at S.&amp; P. Equity Group, said he downgraded the stock from ''accumulate'' to ''hold'' in January, largely because the company was trying to maintain prices in Latin America, one of its most promising markets, while rivals were cutting theirs. ''How long can you maintain that strategy until you lose customers?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Others say the stock remains attractive. John Mackin, who follows Agco for Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, said the decline in the share price reflected economic pressures in developing countries that have affected all companies trying to sell costly machinery abroad. His rating on the stock has been a ''strong buy'' for two years.</p>
        <p>Downgrades of stocks have become unusual in the last several years, in part because of a marked change in the role analysts play in a stock's prospects.</p>
        <p>These researchers once worked in relative obscurity to help determine which stocks clients should buy and sell. Now, firms compete more aggressively for the lucrative investment banking business of publicly traded companies, so it is in their interest to promote the stocks of those companies.</p>
        <p>As a result, critics say, many stock analysts who work for Wall Street firms have grown too cozy with the companies they cover and have lost credibility -- effectively becoming cheerleaders instead.</p>
        <p>That may help explain why recommendations to buy stocks vastly outnumber recommendations to hold or sell. The First Call Corporation, a Boston research firm that tracks analysts' opinions on 6,000 stocks, says more than a third are rated ''strong buys,'' slightly less than a third are ''buys,'' and most of the rest are ''holds.'' Only 1 percent are ''sells.''</p>
        <p>Chuck Hill, research director for First Call and a former securities analyst himself, said there was more fear now among analysts that they would offend their firm's investment banking departments or the companies they cover.</p>
        <p>''There is some reluctance to put a sell on a stock,'' Mr. Hill said. ''It's tougher now to be independent.''</p>
        <p>Others are far more indignant about what they regard as a high level of excessively optimistic analysis, which they say hurts investors' ability to gauge a stock's prospects.</p>
        <p>''Unequivocally, what you'll see is that today, analysts are like the front guys,'' said Mr. Roffman, a former analyst at Janney Montgomery Scott, a Philadelphia investment firm. ''They can't tell it like it really is.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roffman speaks from experience: He was dismissed by Janney Montgomery in 1990 after he refused to retract a negative report about the financial stability of Donald J. Trump's Taj Mahal casino after Mr. Trump had complained and pushed for Mr. Roffman's dismissal. Mr. Roffman then started his own research firm, unfettered by possible conflicts that might arise if he were also trying to generate investment banking fees. Mr. Roffman also sued Mr. Trump, contending defamation, settled the case for an undisclosed sum and was awarded $750,000 from Janney Montgomery in a New York Stock Exchange arbitration claim.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roffman's case was well known in the industry, but there have been other, less publicized examples. Wall Street firms sometimes lose a client company's investment banking business because of a downgrade, and analysts have been ostracized by a company in retaliation for a downgrade. Sometimes, a company sharply curtails analyst access to management if it deems that a rating on its stock is too low.</p>
        <p>In April, Michael L. Mayo, a banking analyst at Credit Suisse First Boston, was excluded from a Mellon Bank analysts meeting. When he asked why, he said Mellon executives told him it was ''because of your rating on the stock.'' Mr. Mayo rates Mellon as a ''hold.'' Mellon declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Even analysts who do not work for Wall Street firms can find it difficult to appraise a company's stock critically. Like others, they try to maintain cordial relations with a company's management to gain access to information that will help them evaluate growth potential.</p>
        <p>''We have a lot more leeway than these guys on the Street. There's not much a company can do if we downgrade its stock,'' said Mr. Hunter of S.&amp; P. Equity Group. Still, he said, issuing a downgrade ''is never a comfortable situation.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, however, a sell signal can make an analyst a hero. Andrew Shore, an analyst at Paine Webber, downgraded the shares of the Sunbeam Corporation in early April before the appliance company -- formerly a Wall Street darling -- began a plunge from the mid-$40's to the $10 level last month. Mr. Shore was also the first analyst to publicly question the capability of Albert J. Dunlap, Sunbeam's chief executive, who was dismissed on June 13 amid growing questions about the company's accounting practices.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I had made a major sell call like this in my whole life,'' Mr. Shore recalled.</p>
        <p>Immediately after he downgraded the stock, Mr. Shore said, he received some ''extremely nasty phone messages.'' Weeks later, he said, some of those same callers phoned to apologize and to thank him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shore said that he felt vindicated but that any analyst who issued a sell recommendation had better be right.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot more pressure when you say sell,'' he said. ''Everyone who owns it at least listens when you say sell.''  INVESTING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
