<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Camp Helps Lower-Income Kids Get Ahead</title>
    <meta content="12FRIE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">On Your Marks Summerbridge (Camp)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saslow, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFDA1E3EF931A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Camp Helps Lower-Income Kids Get Ahead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SASLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saslow, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>LOCUST VALLEY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes activities at On Your Marks Summerbridge, six-week tuition-free camp for lower-income Long Island students which focuses on math, science, reading, languages and study skills; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HUDDLED around a bowl filled with milk, the three campers watched intently as a chocolate-chip cookie began to sink and disappear.</p>
        <p>''The Chips Ahoy took 14 seconds,'' reported 10-year-old Robert Abney, as he looked at his watch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HUDDLED around a bowl filled with milk, the three campers watched intently as a chocolate-chip cookie began to sink and disappear.</p>
        <p>''The Chips Ahoy took 14 seconds,'' reported 10-year-old Robert Abney, as he looked at his watch.</p>
        <p>Sitting next to him on top of a picnic table, Toni Leachin, 12, recorded the result in her notebook.</p>
        <p>''It took 28 seconds for the Keebler,'' said the third member of the group, Anelie Thelemaque, 10. ''If the cookies sink faster, that's better, because it means they have more chips. But if they're slow, then they have more air.''</p>
        <p>While giggling and munching on milk-soaked cookies, Robert, Toni and Anelie were conducting a science experiment on density. Unlike those summer campers who spend their mornings on the ball fields, the 80 campers at On Your Marks Summerbridge work on math, science, reading, languages and study skills, with two hours of homework every night.</p>
        <p>On Your Marks Summerbridge is a six-week tuition-free program for students entering sixth and seventh grades in Nassau County public schools. Campers attend the program for two consecutive summers, with Saturday classes during the school year.</p>
        <p>The program uses space on the campus of Friends Academy in Locust Valley, but operates autonomously. Campers come from Hempstead, Westbury, Glen Cove, Roosevelt, Oyster Bay and Roslyn, and, according to the camp's director, Jacques Pierre, they are children who do not have the resources or opportunities to have a productive summer. At Summerbridge they learn many of the subjects they will face in the following year's grade. The program, Mr. Pierre said, emphasizes academic excellence, leadership, creativity and diversity.</p>
        <p>''It's like summer school and camp at the same time,'' Robert said.</p>
        <p>''If I wasn't here, I'd be doing nothing,'' Anelie said. ''It's pretty cool because the teachers let us call them by their first names.''</p>
        <p>The 25 Summerbridge teachers are high school and college students, ages 15 to 21, who receive two weeks' training. Many are interested in careers in education, Mr. Pierre said. High school students receive a $500 stipend and college students receive $750.</p>
        <p>Valerie Desrouleaux, a Summerbridge instructor from Westbury, is 15 and a student at Friends Academy. ''The campers like it that we're close in age to them,'' she said. ''We can relate to them, and it makes learning more fun.''</p>
        <p>Now in its fourth year at Friends Academy, On Your Marks Summerbridge was brought to the campus by the headmaster, Marcus Hurlbut. Mr. Hurlbut said he started a Summerbridge program in New Hampshire, where he worked previously, and saw the need for such a program on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Summerbridge is a national program whose goal is to prepare primarily low-income middle-school students to enter and succeed in strong academic high school programs. It also strives to encourage and prepare high school and college students to enter the field of education. There are 39 Summerbridge programs at individual schools, but each operates independently.</p>
        <p>Admission to On Your Marks Summerbridge is based on merit and desire, said Mr. Hurlbut. He added that it was designed as a two-year program in order to provide continuity, to inspire a love for learning, help campers develop self-confidence and, ultimately, to help them in the next step of their academic lives.</p>
        <p>''The program is not remedial but enrichment,'' Mr. Hurlbut said. ''These kids are motivated and talented, but many come from personal situations that would challenge their success. We're hoping to give them a little jump start.''</p>
        <p>The program is aimed at the middle-school age range -- 10 to 12 -- because this is the group that is greatest at risk, Mr. Hurlbut said.</p>
        <p>''They're old enough to take care of themselves, but too young to get a job,'' he said, ''and many don't come from families where camp or a summer vacation is an option. So it's hangout time. Our goal is to send them back into their public schools more academically and emotionally developed.''</p>
        <p>Mornings at Summerbridge concentrate on academic and study skills, while the afternoons offer more electives, ranging from foreign languages (including Japanese and Chinese this year) to computer programs, basketball, theater, fencing, Latin ballroom dancing and African drumming.</p>
        <p>On the first morning of this year's  camp season, a class of eight second-year veterans going into seventh grade were brushing up on their Spanish skills. Their teachers, Caron Pinkus of Port Washington, a student at Northwestern University, and Saul Mercado of Babylon, a Cornell University student, led them in ''get acquainted'' role-playing scenes.</p>
        <p>Two at a time, they stood in front of the class, laughing as they shook hands and greeted each other in Spanish, then practiced their dialogue.</p>
        <p>During a break, a camper, Jon Claude Alexander of Roosevelt, said, ''I'm really happy to be here at Summerbridge, and I think it will help me get into college.''</p>
        <p>In a nearby classroom, younger first-time campers were going around the room to introduce themselves.</p>
        <p>''My name is Lillian,'' said one camper, ''and I'm kind of shy.''</p>
        <p>''I'm Marcia,'' said the girl next to her. ''I like to read and I'm kind of shy, but I'm also kind of bold.''</p>
        <p>On the first day, new campers are apprehensive, Mr. Pierre said, adding, ''but within a few days, they're at home here.''</p>
        <p>The ratio of one teacher for every four to seven students helps to make campers feel more comfortable, he said.</p>
        <p>By the program's third day, Summerbridge campers appeared as if they had known one another for months.</p>
        <p>''We didn't know each other before,'' Toni said during the chocolate-chip cookie experiment, ''but now we're already friends.''</p>
        <p>The annual operating budget for On Your Marks Summerbridge is about $153,000, which includes a $26,000 grant from Americorps, the national service program created by the White House in 1993.</p>
        <p>Financing depends primarily on donations from individuals and corporations, said the program's assistant director, Ingrid Wong.</p>
        <p>''That's one of our biggest problems,'' she said. ''Once we get our feet into the door, Summerbridge is an easy sell, but it's very difficult to raise money on Long Island.''</p>
        <p>On Your Marks Summerbridge is a true collaborative effort, said Mr. Hurlbut, between parents, teachers, students, the public schools and community organizations.</p>
        <p>''The success depends on everybody working together,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For Bradley Scott, who is going into seventh grade in the Westbury public schools, this is the second summer at On Your Marks Summerbridge.</p>
        <p>''It was my father's idea,'' he said. ''and I didn't know what it was going to be like. But it's really fun, and if I wasn't here, I'd be home watching Jerry Springer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
