<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fitting Final for Century's Last World Cup Will Bring a Familiar or a New Champion</title>
    <meta content="12CUPP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031393"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="WORLD CUP '98"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E5D91531F931A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fitting Final for Century's Last World Cup Will Bring a Familiar or a New Champion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, July 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for Brazil-France world cup championship soccer match; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With all due respect to the protocol-conscious people across the English Channel who essentially invented soccer, Sunday's final between France and Brazil is an appropriate finish to the last World Cup of the 20th century.</p>
        <p>It will be the nation that launched the globe's most popular sporting event against the nation that has been the most successful in it. It will be South America against Europe; Ronaldo and the world's most technically sound attacking players against Marcel Desailly and the world's most tactically sound defense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With all due respect to the protocol-conscious people across the English Channel who essentially invented soccer, Sunday's final between France and Brazil is an appropriate finish to the last World Cup of the 20th century.</p>
        <p>It will be the nation that launched the globe's most popular sporting event against the nation that has been the most successful in it. It will be South America against Europe; Ronaldo and the world's most technically sound attacking players against Marcel Desailly and the world's most tactically sound defense.</p>
        <p>It will be Brazil's Cafu against Bixente Lizarazu on one wing; Brazil's Roberto Carlos against Lilian Thuram on the other. It will be every man against his own nerves and his own limitations, and when the last whistle of an exhausting, emotional month is blown Sunday sometime between 10:45 P.M. and midnight, there will either be a familiar champion and dancing in the streets of Rio de Janeiro or a first-time champion and the biggest party the Champs-Elysees has seen since Liberation.</p>
        <p>''When you're a child and you play soccer, you always dream about being in a World Cup final,'' Thuram said. ''I remember playing games with my friends: France against Brazil, but I was always on the Brazilian team.''</p>
        <p>It is often that way on the playgrounds of the world. Brazil is a symbol, a soccer state of mind. But this time, France will have the home-team advantage, if there is one.</p>
        <p>This will be the first time that a host nation and a defending champion will meet in a World Cup final. One reason France is host to this event at all is because a Brazilian, FIFA's outgoing president, Joao Havelange, put his weight behind its bid. Havelange will be rooting against the French on Sunday as he sits near the French President, Jacques Chirac. This is not the first time their nations meet with much at stake.</p>
        <p>In 1958 in Stockholm, the Brazilians defeated the French, 5-2, in the World Cup semifinals. Pele, then 17, scored three of the Brazilian goals, but the match might have been less lopsided if the French captain, Robert Jonquet, had not injured his knee in the 35th minute. This was in the stiff-lipped era before substitutions were authorized, so Jonquet limped and soldiered on.</p>
        <p>The French would get a measure of revenge in the 1986 quarterfinals in Guadalajara, Mexico. After 90 minutes of regulation and 30 minutes of overtime, the score was tied, 1-1, but the French prevailed on penalty kicks, 4-3. The team was widely considered the finest in French history, but for all their flair and experience, the French would prove unable to solve the riddle posed by a fresher West German side in the next round.</p>
        <p>Twelve years later, French soccer has a new high-water mark, and Coach Aime Jacquet's team has reached this level for some of the same reasons Brazil ended its 24-year championship drought at the last World Cup. The French, like the Brazilians, have put new emphasis on defensive rigor at the expense of attacking brilliance. The French players, like the Brazilians, have fled their underfinanced, underexposed domestic league and signed big contracts with clubs in the leagues in Italy, Spain, Germany and England.</p>
        <p>''By changing teams we changed mentality,'' said the French midfielder Emmanuel Petit, who plays for Arsenal in England. ''Before, everybody knew that the French had some great qualities and wonderful players, but we never quite had the mental strength that this sort of competition demands. By going abroad and playing for the best clubs and under great pressure, I think we have learned what it takes to win.''</p>
        <p>Of the 32 teams who played in these expanded World Cup finals, France and Brazil were the only ones that did not have to qualify. While Italy flew nervously north to Russia, and Argentina landed high in the Andes to face Bolivia, the France and Brazil played friendly after essentially meaningless friendly. And now after a month of intense competition, France and Brazil are one victory away from another automatic berth for the next World Cup in 2002.</p>
        <p>This is the fourth consecutive final in which a European team will face a South American team. In the first three meetings, the team playing closest to home has always prevailed. To keep that streak alive, the French know they will have to keep Ronaldo from having time to turn with the ball. They know they must mark the Brazilians tightly to keep them from making fast-twitch transitions from defense to attack: either up the wings with outside fullbacks Cafu and Roberto Carlos or up the middle with Rivaldo. They also must avoid leaving too much space between their lines: space that their more potentially dangerous opponents are well-equipped to exploit.</p>
        <p>''This Brazilian team has been in some awkward situations in this cup, but they have players with so much talent that they can resolve problems all by themselves,'' said the French midfielder and captain Didier Deschamps.</p>
        <p>What the French can potentially exploit is Brazil's central defense, which proved vulnerable to well-timed crosses against the Dutch in the semifinals, and a certain lack of consistency. Can it be a coincidence that in four of its six matches, Brazil has taken a lead and then allowed its opponent to equalize? Another question is whether France and its Brazilian-style playmaker Zinedine Zidane can turn these relative weaknesses into goals. Zidane has yet to score, and since the second round began, all three French goals have been scored by defenders</p>
        <p>Perhaps that is why Brazilian Coach Mario Zagallo has had little trouble laughing in the face of precedent this week. ''We have won all of our World Cups outside the country,'' Zagallo said. ''I respect very much the French team, but I am not afraid of it. We are too used to big finals and big matches to approach them with apprehension. If any players should have goose bumps before the kickoff, it should be the French, not the Brazilians.''</p>
        <p>The only World Cup final Brazil has lost was at home in 1950, when a crowd of 200,000 at the Maracana Stadium in Rio de Janeiro had to watch Uruguay's team celebrate. Zagallo, then in the midst of his military service, was one of the mourners in Maracana that July.</p>
        <p>But since moving from the stands to the field, he has become a talisman for his nation. He was a fine player on the team that won in 1958 and 1962, the coach in 1970 and an assistant coach in 1994.  WORLD CUP '98</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
