<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Group Show and Solo Make Up Swan Song</title>
    <meta content="12ART.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sound Shore Gallery (Cross River, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sundgaard, Erik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raynor, Vivien</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD7113EF931A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Group Show and Solo Make Up Swan Song</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIEN RAYNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raynor, Vivien</byline>
      <dateline>CROSS RIVER</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vivien Raynor reviews last show before closing of Sound Shore Gallery in Cross River, NY, featuring anthology by seven artists and solo show by newcomer Erik Sundgaard; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NARDIN Galleries in Somers departed for Manhattan last year; Elizabeth Galasso of Ossining and John Froats of Cold Spring have long since closed their doors. Now, Mary Udell, the proprietor of Sound Shore here, announced that the show she has just pened is her last -- an ironic situation for the 16-year-old gallery, which was born and raised in Port Chester and recently returned to the county after a spell in Stamford.</p>
        <p>Those who understand it insist that the economy is all better, but they do not explain why it still seems bent on doing away with the amenities -- esthetic and practical -- that make life better.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NARDIN Galleries in Somers departed for Manhattan last year; Elizabeth Galasso of Ossining and John Froats of Cold Spring have long since closed their doors. Now, Mary Udell, the proprietor of Sound Shore here, announced that the show she has just pened is her last -- an ironic situation for the 16-year-old gallery, which was born and raised in Port Chester and recently returned to the county after a spell in Stamford.</p>
        <p>Those who understand it insist that the economy is all better, but they do not explain why it still seems bent on doing away with the amenities -- esthetic and practical -- that make life better.</p>
        <p>The same goes for a dealer told me that collectors these days tend to be more interested in acquiring objects with a predictable resale value -- Oriental rugs, for example -- than in taking a chance on contemporary paintings and sculpture, but he offered no reason for the change. Then, from the museum world comes news of the difficulty in obtaining Government support for shows that do not toe the party line -- all nine yards of it, including family values. Perhaps things will get better when La Nina takes over from El Nino.</p>
        <p>Be that as it may, Mrs. Udell ignores the grimness of the times, delivering a sprightly swan song. It comes in two parts, one an anthology by seven artists, a few of whom have been with her for years, the other a solo by a newcomer, Erik Sundgaard.</p>
        <p>The group show opens on the stairs with works by George Hofmann, notably three acrylic abstractions on paper. In those, Mr. Hofmann is the compleat automatist, dashing two or three flamboyant strokes of, say, black, green or raw siena onto a yellow ground.</p>
        <p>But in his new abstractions on canvas the artist turns cool and impressionistic, applying whites and high-keyed hues gently, almost tentatively, and though the titles invoke Tiepolo, the images recall the windswept interiors of Turner.</p>
        <p>An Abstract Expressionist more concerned with color relationships, Frank Wimberley presents three works, the best an untitled canvas centering on a black oblong tinged with crimson and suspended over a gray field, which is horizontally divided by a thin yellow stripe. Ken Marchione all but fills a large canvas with a wall of impastoed ''bricks'' in brownish reds, blues, white and black. Impressive though it is, the image lacks the presence of its smaller companion in which the wall has metamorphosed into a kind of house, similarly constructed but rougher in texture. Both canvases are edged with what looks like the color key used by printers.</p>
        <p>Lou Hicks contributes small but effective seascapes, which double as abstractions composed of generally low-keyed colors laid on in horizontal bands. Stripes of purple and cobalt, grayish blue and slate combine to make ''Dawn'' his most successful effort.</p>
        <p>J. Pindyck Miller is represented by three welded steel constructions and three sculptural paintings -- abstractions cut into sections, which are is applied to wood blocks of different sizes. To judge from ''Brazil for Jobim'' of 1998, Mr. Miller has abandoned angular simplicity for biomorphic complexity, but when it comes to balance, precision and an immaculate finish he is his usual self.</p>
        <p>''Abstraction to Date'' may be Sound Shore's best production but that does not prevent Robert Goodnough from stealing it with three images, each suggesting a flock of birds in space. In reality, the birds are the painter's characteristic geometric shapes, except that they are stenciled small and dabbed with color. Mr Goodnough has devised a language in which anything can be expressed, even a self-portrait.</p>
        <p>Spilling over into the adjoining gallery, the show also includes the welded geometry of Robert Cronin -- arcs and circles cut out of steel and painted in pastel colors. The way they stand, these shapely constructions could be metaphors for plants and as such contrast sharply with Mr. Sundgaard's landscapes and still lifes. Contrary to his experience as an illustrator, this artist works on a relatively large scale, drawing inspiration from Cubism, Surrealism and, possibly, Marc Chagall, as well as Americans like Hopper.</p>
        <p>''A Woman and Her Pig'' is an aerial view of houses, which rarely have right angles but lie on neat plots, their chimneys belching smoke in an orderly fashion as woman and pig walk a path single file. Giant sunflowers preside over a table loaded with grapefruit and peaches and accompanied by a black and white cat dozing in the background. Elsewhere, sailboats cut through solid-looking blue seas and pears as big as basketballs fight for space. The eccentricity seems a bit calculated at times, but it is always sharp in focus and rendered in pleasing high-keyed colors.</p>
        <p>The show closes July 31, but the gallery will long remain in the memory of its patrons. The information number is 763-6870.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
