<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Television's 'Lottery Guy' Strives to Stay in Senate</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="554278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGISLATURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOTTERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, JERRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAROSSA, DICK (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D71738F937A3575AC0A964958260" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Television's 'Lottery Guy' Strives to Stay in Senate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GRAY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRAY, JERRY</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, Sept. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>According to a tale making the rounds of the State House, the first time Donald T. DiFrancesco, the Senate President, saw Dick LaRossa striding through the corridors he exclaimed, "Hey, there goes the lottery guy."</p>
        <p>Mr. DiFrancesco was told, so the story goes, that Mr. LaRossa was not only a Senator but also a fellow Republican.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>According to a tale making the rounds of the State House, the first time Donald T. DiFrancesco, the Senate President, saw Dick LaRossa striding through the corridors he exclaimed, "Hey, there goes the lottery guy."</p>
        <p>Mr. DiFrancesco was told, so the story goes, that Mr. LaRossa was not only a Senator but also a fellow Republican.</p>
        <p>With no political experience but arguably one of the most recognizable faces in the state, Mr. LaRossa left a part-time job as the television host of the New Jersey State Lottery Commission's weekend drawings and made his first bid for office last year.</p>
        <p>Running as a Republican, he defeated a five-term Democratic legislator, Gerald R. Stockman, in a Trenton-based district that had not elected a Republican to the Senate since 1946, the year Mr. LaRossa was born. 14-Hour Days</p>
        <p>Since taking office in January, Mr. LaRossa has worked 14-hour days in an attempt to solidify his grasp on a district that even his party thought he had no chance of winning and still thinks he has little chance of keeping.</p>
        <p>That has meant abandoning, at least for the moment, daily oversight of his 10-year-old consulting company, Computer Services Group of Trenton.</p>
        <p>On weekends, Mr. LaRossa moonlights as the featured vocalist and master of ceremonies for an 18-piece swing band called the Lamplighters. He jokingly bills himself these days as "the singing Senator."</p>
        <p>With the coiffured look of a television anchor and a flair for theatrics -- he is an active member of both the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists and Actors' Equity -- Richard J. LaRossa has what is easily the highest profile among freshmen in the 205th Legislature.</p>
        <p>As chairman of a joint legislative committee that has begun looking into the state's loss of nearly half a billion dollars in Medicaid money, for which the Republicans blame Governor Florio, Mr. LaRossa will get more television time. And the Republicans have in him a committee chairman tailor-made for what is expected to be a media event. A Gadfly and a Wild Card</p>
        <p>Mr. LaRossa has gained a reputation as a hard worker and one of the most publicity-hungry legislators in Trenton. He has become a gadfly to the Democratic administration and something of a wild card to Republican leaders.</p>
        <p>He disputes none of those characterizations, saying, "None of us were elected to keep our mouths shut."</p>
        <p>Mr. LaRossa is one of 10 freshmen in the 40-member Senate -- there are 23 in the 80-member Assembly -- and they have been especially aggressive, sometimes becoming worrisome to veteran Republican leaders fighting to retain control over their two-thirds majorities in both houses.</p>
        <p>The real power in the Legislature still rests with veterans, but in the Republican drive to undo Gov. Jim Florio's programs, freshmen have frequently been the sponsors of major bills.</p>
        <p>That exposure has helped bolster the confidence of junior lawmakers, but it has also created what one senior Republican in the Assembly described as "Frankenstein monsters," frank-talking, shoot-from-the-hip freshmen who do not always toe the party line.</p>
        <p>Traditionally, legislative leaders have kept mavericks in the fold by appealing to party loyalty and, if that failed, by threatening to withhold campaign dollars or stall legislation that would benefit the members' districts.</p>
        <p>On the surface, Mr. LaRossa seems impervious to such disciplinary methods. He registered as a Republican for the first time last year when he filed as a Senate candidate five days before the deadline. Then he ran a grassroots campaign that drew scant attention from the party that had written the district off as unwinnable.</p>
        <p>Mr. LaRossa has voted with the party on such major legislation as the rollback of the sales tax from 7 to 6 percent and the override of Mr. Florio's veto of the Republican budget. But he has balked at supporting legislation that he felt would hurt state workers, thousands of whom are his constituents. "I will work with the team," he said, "but when the team is wrong, I'm not going to be part of the play." Skips the Convention</p>
        <p>Indeed last month, while many Republicans were in Houston attending their national convention, Mr. La Rossa was marching outside the State House with members of the Communications Workers of America, the state's largest public-employees union, who were protesting the administration's layoff plan.</p>
        <p>The Republicans have 58 members in the Assembly, 4 more than they need to override a Florio veto. But in the Senate, the party has only the 27 votes it needs to thwart the Governor. That conceivably gives each Republican, including the freshmen, a personal veto and a powerful bargaining chip.</p>
        <p>Wielding that power, Mr. LaRossa was able to get party leaders lined up behind two Senate bills that amended the Republicans' budget to protect certain classifications of state workers from layoffs.</p>
        <p>One senior Republican said the party's leaders in the Legislature intend to support a LaRossa effort to prevent N.J. Transit from building a rail yard in Morrisville, Pa. Mr. La Rossa wants the yard and the jobs it generates in Trenton.</p>
        <p>Mr. LaRossa is still ribbed about his days as the lottery host, when, in a rich baritone, he called out numbers inscribed on Ping-Pong balls. During budget negotiations, fellow committee members offered to scribble figures on Ping-Pong balls to aid him.</p>
        <p>Asked to review his own performance as a legislator, Mr. LaRossa likens himself to Don Quixote, a character he once portrayed on stage. But, he adds, "I don't think even Don Quixote ever fought a windmill like state government." PROFILE</p>
        <p>Richard Joseph LaRossa Born: July 1, 1946; Trenton.  Hometown: Trenton.  Education: Notre Dame High School, Trenton; B.A., major in speech, minor in English, Trenton State College; graduate study in psychology, Fairleigh Dickinson University, East Rutherford.  Career Highlights: Marketing specialist for electronics and audiovisual companies, 1974-81; host for televised New Jersey Lottery drawings, 1980-91; founder and president, Computer Services Group, 1982-present; member, American Federation of Television and Radio Artists, 1988-present; member, Actors' Equity, 1990-present.  Family: Married to Sharon A. Marcello, 1972; no children.  Hobbies: Golf, racquetball, singing and community theater.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
