<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kremlin Softens Its Threat to Armenia</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="375063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARMENIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOHLEN, CELESTINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TER-PETROSYAN, LEVAN (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RYZHKOV, NIKOLAI I (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Armenia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Armenia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED71230F933A2575BC0A966958260" item-length="588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kremlin Softens Its Threat to Armenia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOHLEN, CELESTINE</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Soviet Government has agreed not to send troops into the republic of Armenia to disarm militant groups that have refused to surrender their weapons, the newly elected nationalist President of the republic said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Soviet Government has agreed not to send troops into the republic of Armenia to disarm militant groups that have refused to surrender their weapons, the newly elected nationalist President of the republic said today.</p>
        <p>The Soviet Government has agreed not to send troops into the republic of Armenia to disarm militant groups that have refused to surrender their weapons, the newly elected nationalist President of the republic said today.</p>
        <p>The agreement, reached after talks in Moscow between the Armenian President, Levan Ter-Petrosyan, and Prime Minister Nikolai I. Ryzhkov of the Soviet Union, removes a potential flashpoint in the Caucasus region, where political violence has often erupted in recent years.</p>
        <p>At a news conference, Mr. Ter-Petrosyan said Moscow had extended the deadline of a presidential decree ordering the surrender of illegal arms, and had given sole responsiblity for their collection to the local authorities. ''We have an agreement that we will be able to carry out the decree freely without intervention from outside,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a decree issued July 25, President Mikhail S. Gorbachev set today as the deadline for armed groups to hand over their weapons, or else face their forcible seizure by Soviet troops. The measure was directed at politically sensitive regions, principally Armenia, where open warfare has broken out between rival gangs using weapons stolen from police and army depots. #1,600 Weapons Turned In The Soviet Ministry of Internal Affairs reported today that across the country, a total of 1,600 weapons had been handed in since the decree was issued, and that more were still coming in. On Wednesday, the Minister of Internal Affairs, Vadim V. Bakatin, appealed to Mr. Gorbachev to extend the deadline indefinitely, citing a new, ''responsible'' approach on the part of the newly installed authorities in Armenia.</p>
        <p>Disarming criminal gangs and militant groups will be a difficult and delicate task for the republic's police forces, a spokesman for a leading Armenian nationalist group said today. But Amburtsum Galtsyan of the Karabakh Committee added: ''The most important thing is that people support us. If Gorbachev sent in troops, there would have been a violent reaction.''</p>
        <p>The agreement between Mr. Ter-Petrosyan and Mr. Ryzhkov signals a new stage in Moscow's willingness to relinquish control to new political forces emerging at the republic level. It also softens the impact of the presidential decree, which with its threat of intervention by federal troops, had been viewed in some republics as a challenge to local sovereignty. The Armenian Parliament voted to suspend the decree.</p>
        <p>A turning point in the crisis in Armenia was the election last week of Mr. Ter-Petrosyan, a leader of the nationalist movement, a linguistic scholar and a former political prisoner who spent the first six months of last year in jail under investigation for his political activities. Mr. Ter-Petrosyan, who is 45 years old, was arrested during Mr. Gorbahcev's visit to Armenia after the December 1988 earthquake.</p>
        <p>Phone Call From Gorbachev</p>
        <p>Two days ago, Mr. Gorbachev, who is on vacation in the Crimea, called Mr. Ter-Petrosyan to congratulate him on his election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ter-Petrosyan also said he was ready to establish better relations with Azerbaijan, the republic that borders Armenia and with which it has been fighting over control of the mountainous territory of Nagorno-Karabakh.</p>
        <p>The first order of business for the new government is to restore stability to a republic that has been badly shaken by lawlessness, he said.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, the Armenian capital, Yerevan, has been depicted by the Soviet press as a gunfighters' corral, where shootouts are almost an evening sport.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
