<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Tracking Stocks' Luster Masks Risk and Conflicts of Interest</title>
    <meta content="Y12PLA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/12/business/12PLAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1254604"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgenson, Gretchen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DE123FF931A25751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Tracking Stocks' Luster Masks Risk and Conflicts of Interest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN MORGENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenson, Gretchen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Market Place column on growing popularity of tracking stock, which mirrors performance of specific part of company's business but does not give its shareholders any ownership in assets of that business; tracking stocks are popular with both companies and investors because they seem to increase shareholder value by letting market judge worth of fast-growing part of company independent of its slower-growing lines of business; companies can raise capital more cheaply and have pricier stock with which to buy other companies; but pitfalls are emerging; University of Iowa academics find that tracking stocks do not perform as well as shares of other companies in same industry; other problems have emerged; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American infatuation with the new is well known and mined on Wall Street. Fertile minds at the nation's brokerage firms have for years made a lucrative trade of creating newfangled securities in the hope that they will appeal to investors looking for fresh and exciting places to put their funds.</p>
        <p>Few of these inventions, however, have grown as popular in recent years as the tracking stock, which mirrors the performance of a specific part of a company's business but does not give its shareholders any ownership in the assets of that business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American infatuation with the new is well known and mined on Wall Street. Fertile minds at the nation's brokerage firms have for years made a lucrative trade of creating newfangled securities in the hope that they will appeal to investors looking for fresh and exciting places to put their funds.</p>
        <p>Few of these inventions, however, have grown as popular in recent years as the tracking stock, which mirrors the performance of a specific part of a company's business but does not give its shareholders any ownership in the assets of that business.</p>
        <p>Tracking stocks have been issued by companies as big as AT&amp;T and General Motors and for smaller concerns like Ziff-Davis and Alcatel Optronics. So far this year, new tracking stocks have accounted for 12.5 percent of the $79.5 billion raised in initial public offerings. In all of 1999, only 0.7 percent of the $69 billion raised in I.P.O.'s consisted of tracking shares.</p>
        <p>Tracking stocks are popular with both companies and investors because they seem to increase shareholder value by letting the market judge the worth of a fast-growing part of a company independent of its slower-growing lines of business. With investors willing to pay more for this growth, companies can raise capital more cheaply and have a pricier stock with which to buy other companies.</p>
        <p>As with many inventions or creations, the pitfalls emerge only gradually. University of Iowa academics found that tracking stocks do not perform as well as shares of other companies in the same industry. And tracking stocks can pose other risks for investors and for the parent companies, as shareholders in the biotechnology company Genzyme are discovering this week.</p>
        <p>Genzyme shareholders are mulling over the creation of a new tracking stock that would result from an acquisition proposed by management. Two of the Genzyme Corporation's units covered by tracking stocks would buy the company, Biomatrix, using money borrowed by the parent Genzyme. While the purchase could increase the market prices of the tracking stocks, which are to be combined, the liability for the loan would ultimately fall on the parent company, leaving it to shoulder most of the risk yet receive little of the benefit.</p>
        <p>B. Kenneth West, senior consultant for corporate governance at TIAA/ CREF and a director at Motorola, questions whether investors holding tracking stocks really understand what they own. ''I'll bet the shareholders in these things don't know if they're on foot or horseback,'' he said. ''But the main drawback in tracking stocks is that they create significant potential conflicts of interest among stockholders, the board of directors and management.''</p>
        <p>The risks to shareholders have risen as tracking stocks have grown in popularity. Since 1984, according to Spinoff Advisors of Chicago, companies have issued 33 tracking stocks, 15 of those in the last two years. This year, three issuers have raised almost $12 billion.</p>
        <p>Five companies, including The New York Times Company, had tracking stocks in registration this year, hoping to raise a combined $1.375 billion. Many of those stocks were Internet-related and all were withdrawn as the market fell in late summer.</p>
        <p>USX was one of the early issuers of tracking stocks when, in 1991, it used one to separate its oil business from its steel operations. Now, the company is having second thoughts. At a meeting with securities analysts on Nov. 30, Thomas J. Usher, the chairman of USX, said he was beginning to believe that the tracking shares were hurting its overall performance in the stock market and that the company was considering ending the dual stock structure.</p>
        <p>Beyond the questionable arguments made by Wall Street firms selling the concept of tracking stocks to their corporate clients, there are some benefits to be had.</p>
        <p>One is that losses incurred by the business covered by a tracking stock, unlike those of a spinoff, can be applied to reduce the taxes owed by the parent company. And unlike companies spun off to full independence, businesses covered by tracking stocks find it easier to raise money from investors because they are still technically owned by a larger company with a possibly stronger financial position. Full spinoffs typically pay more for their capital because they are generally small and on their own.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, these benefits are not nearly as evident to shareholders of tracking stocks as are the increasingly apparent disadvantages. For starters, these shares have lagged behind the performance of their peers and of the market over all in recent years.</p>
        <p>In a study published in March, Matthew T. Billett and Anand M. Vijh of the University of Iowa's Henry B. Tippie College of Business analyzed the returns of 28 tracking stocks issued before 1999. They found that on average, tracking stocks earned 11.7 percent a year in the first three years after their issuance, while the return of an index of their peers was far higher: 18.1 percent a year. The overall market trounced them all, rising 21 percent a year, on average.</p>
        <p>The two academics pointed out that even the 11.7 percent returns of the tracking stocks were probably overstated because they included an outsized performance from Sprint PCS, a tracking stock that increased more than 500 percent in value in its first three years. If this stock were excluded, the 27 other tracking stocks earned a paltry 5.7 percent a year, the University of Iowa academics said.</p>
        <p>One reason the performance of tracking stocks tends to lag behind others may be that these shares cannot be acquired if another company buys the operations they reflect. Therefore, holders of tracking stocks never receive the big premiums to the market price that holders of common stock often do in a takeover.</p>
        <p>Even more worrisome, to shareholder activist groups, is the conflict of interest that tracking stocks present to company directors and shareholders, a conflict that is playing out right now in Genzyme's boardroom in Cambridge, Mass.</p>
        <p>Genzyme consists of four tracking stocks: Genzyme General covers the company's therapeutic products; another reflects its molecular oncology operations; a third mirrors its tissue-repair business; and a fourth tracks its surgical products division.</p>
        <p>At issue for shareholders is Genzyme's proposed $245 million acquisition of Biomatrix, which makes products used in medical and skin-care applications.</p>
        <p>The deal, announced in March and to be voted on by the shareholders on Friday, calls for the Genzyme Corporation to borrow $200 million of the purchase price for Biomatrix. After the deal is completed, Genzyme's surgical-products and tissue-repair tracking stocks would be combined with Biomatrix into one new tracking stock called Genzyme Biosurgery.</p>
        <p>In the filing describing the terms of the deal, Genzyme said its board believed that the Biomatrix acquisition ''has the potential to benefit all Genzyme shareholders,'' but is careful to add that ''Genzyme stockholders should recognize that the acquisition of Biomatrix will disparately impact Genzyme's tracking stocks.''</p>
        <p>It goes on to say that if the financial liabilities allocated to the new tracking stock ever exceed the assets of that division, the assets of Genzyme General may be used to cover those liabilities.</p>
        <p>Such a situation is not out of the question. According to company documents, if the Biomatrix acquisition goes through as planned, the new tracking stock would have a tangible net worth of a negative $175.5 million while Genzyme General's net worth would be more than $1 billion.</p>
        <p>Executives at both Biomatrix and Genzyme say the risk of potential liabilities resulting from the deal is slight.</p>
        <p>Elliott Hillback, senior vice president for corporate affairs at Genzyme said: ''What we're doing is strengthening an organization through an acquisition. We've created the thousand-pound gorilla here, and that's got a lot of value. Why is a hypothetical risk more important than this value?''</p>
        <p>Rory Riggs, president of Biomatrix, said, ''We expect these companies by 2001 to be operating at break-even.''</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch, which is advising Genzyme on the acquisition, has supplied an opinion on the fairness of the deal to shareholders, as is required in such a transaction. Although Merrill said the amount paid by Genzyme for Biomatrix is fair from a financial point of view, it pointedly added, ''We express no opinion as to the fairness of the reorganization to the holders of Genzyme common stock.''</p>
        <p>Late last week, Genzyme issued a press release stating that Institutional Shareholder Services, a proxy-voting advisory firm, had recommended that Genzyme shareholders approve the acquisition. The company did not note that on Dec. 5, Proxy Monitor, another voting adviser to institutional shareholders, advised stockholders of Genzyme General to vote against the merger proposal.</p>
        <p>''This transaction presents a classic case study in the inherent conflicts involved when tracking stocks are created and how a board decision may disparately impact different series of shareholders,'' said Desmonde Printz, a senior analyst at Proxy Monitor. ''Genzyme General is acting as a bank in the transaction because without that balance sheet,  there's no way the smaller division could borrow this money. Genzyme General is the group of shareholders I think the transaction is least fair to.''</p>
        <p>In a few days, it will become evident whether a majority of Genzyme General shareholders have voted in favor of the Biomatrix acquisition. But shareholder activists think this will not be the last situation in which tracking stocks place shareholders of the same company at odds.</p>
        <p>Still, Wall Street continues to peddle tracking stocks to its corporate clients. No surprise there. After all, as Mr. West of TIAA-CREF pointed out, investment bankers are on a constant lookout for new ideas to generate lucrative transactions. So what if these deals are not lucrative to their shareholders?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
