<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>India Faces India</title>
    <meta content="21ROSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="On My Mind" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="917146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="On My Mind"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenthal, A M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7DA173BF932A15750C0A961958260" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>India Faces India</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A.M. ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenthal, A M</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A M Rosenthal Op-Ed column contends that India is undergoing national self-examination to determine why for half century elected officials failed to provide majority of Indians with decencies of life (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Close now to 50 years of independence under political democracy, Indians are deep in national self-examination -- sparing nothing, from  corroding corruption to quota by casteism to bureaucratic strangulation.</p>
        <p>In range and bite, no other society, democratic or totalitarian, approaches the long look in the mirror that Indians are taking at themselves and those they entrusted to govern them. The pain is already bringing political and economic changes to India, whose history affected the world for centuries and still does.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Close now to 50 years of independence under political democracy, Indians are deep in national self-examination -- sparing nothing, from  corroding corruption to quota by casteism to bureaucratic strangulation.</p>
        <p>In range and bite, no other society, democratic or totalitarian, approaches the long look in the mirror that Indians are taking at themselves and those they entrusted to govern them. The pain is already bringing political and economic changes to India, whose history affected the world for centuries and still does.</p>
        <p>But despite some excellent Indian and foreign journalism, this pivotal event in democracy gets less attention from Western capitals than twitches in Beijing's Communist rhetoric do.</p>
        <p>For 40 years, ever since my four reporting years in this country, I have been seized by India. The glory of the variety of Indian ways, history, religions, art and friendships -- the colors of life -- made me rush forward to meet the gift of the day.</p>
        <p>For all those years, Indians and friends like myself said that India was of huge importance to the world because it was the only newly independent country to choose and stick with political democracy.</p>
        <p>Now they say that is still true, but democracy defeats democracy when it is used to explain away or apologize for the nasty blotches.</p>
        <p>The mirror asks why for half a century elected Indian governments have failed to provide the great majority of Indians with the decencies of life -- clean water, toilets, sufficient food and medicine, enough roads so villagers do not have to walk hours to the nearest one. Why does India lag behind so many other comparable societies in basic education, birth control, life expectancy, health care, income, foreign investment?</p>
        <p>It is not the major politicians and parties that are trying to answer those questions. They have been sidelined by the disgust of Indians using ballots as an archer his arrows. In last year's election voters virtually wiped out the Congress Party, which led India to independence under Mohandas Gandhi and Jawaharlal Nehru and then marched purposefully into corruption, disdain and slovenly government.</p>
        <p>Indian voters, investigative courts and a vivid press show their conviction that it was not democracy that failed India but the politicians who failed both. Every day brings exposure of official corruption. One former cabinet minister was sentenced for sheltering a leader of bandits who terrorize great swatches of India -- 10 years' hard labor. The last Prime Minister, P. V. Narasimha Rao, is fighting to stay out of prison for bribery.</p>
        <p>India's political leaders were a choke collar on economic progress. For cash and caste, they helped cronies, kept the economy in government hands and restricted foreign investment far beyond the steps necessary to protect farmers and small businesses that do need help, as they once did in the West.</p>
        <p>No party won a majority. A coalition of 13 parties, most regional-based, was pasted together to block the Hindu nationalist party from taking control. A provincial leader from Karnataka, H. D. Deve Gowda, won the lottery for prime ministership, to his astonishment.</p>
        <p>Even if it does not last, his Government already has put forward a budget that is India's most friendly to foreign investors and Indian business. Foreigners should remember that he also has valid commitments to the vast, scrabbling rural constituency that needs help.</p>
        <p>The election already has produced a shift of some political power and economic say-so from New Delhi to the 25 states. The mishmash of free enterprise and Socialist regulation is held in growing contempt.</p>
        <p>Communism and Fascism taught us that tyranny can prosper under capitalism. India teaches us that in a democracy the corruption, hypocrisy, arrogance and fossilization of elected leaders can perpetuate destitution.</p>
        <p>Now I am going out for a walk in this city, where Indian freedom was proclaimed on Aug. 15, 1947. When I get back, I will be like the country -- hot, sweaty and impatient, but eager again to meet the gift of a day in India.  On My Mind</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
