<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Delays Paralyze Newark's Efforts to House Poor</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="505316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMELESS PERSONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATE AND LOCAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEWARK (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEWARK HOUSING AUTHORITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIEVES, EVELYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D81E3AF930A35751C0A964958260" item-length="1977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Delays Paralyze Newark's Efforts to House Poor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NIEVES, EVELYN</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, Feb. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a ramshackle area of wood-frame houses in the Central Ward here, officials held a ground breaking last April that they hailed as the start of a new era for Newark's poorest residents.</p>
        <p>But there was more to it: The 100 town houses were to be a new start for the Newark Housing Authority, which had become notorious for failing to build or maintain housing even when it had money to do both. The ceremony would begin a $110 million construction program -- as ambitious as any in public housing -- that would replace 11 deteriorated high-rise buildings with scattered two- and three-story houses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a ramshackle area of wood-frame houses in the Central Ward here, officials held a ground breaking last April that they hailed as the start of a new era for Newark's poorest residents.</p>
        <p>But there was more to it: The 100 town houses were to be a new start for the Newark Housing Authority, which had become notorious for failing to build or maintain housing even when it had money to do both. The ceremony would begin a $110 million construction program -- as ambitious as any in public housing -- that would replace 11 deteriorated high-rise buildings with scattered two- and three-story houses.</p>
        <p>Today the lot where officials gathered with shovels and promises remains empty. The developer chosen for the project never secured financing, and construction schedules are still changing. Instead of a new beginning, the groundbreaking has become a vivid reminder -- along with two town houses under construction that blew down in a windstorm -- that the authority is unable to shelter the poor. Indeed, since the authority demolished four 13-story buildings in 1987, vowing to start construction of new town houses within 90 days, it has built one house. A Last Resort Deteriorates</p>
        <p>To some degree, the failure of Newark's public housing is the story of the failure of public housing all over the country. Where projects became the housing of last resort, buildings were allowed to deteriorate. Peter Marcuse, a professor of urban planning at Columbia University who is writing a book on public housing, calls the pattern "a clear recipe for disaster."</p>
        <p>"Wherever public housing has become the housing for the poorest," he said, "buildings have been similarly abandoned, torched."</p>
        <p>But while replacing the failures of the past with better, more humane housing has not been an easy task anywhere, it has been especially tortuous in Newark. The Housing Authority's management has been hapless -- inept and riddled with unbridled patronage, some argue -- and its housing is far more unwieldy than most.</p>
        <p>To many here, the situation is the shame of Newark. New market-rate housing and $6 billion worth of construction seem to have begun a revival in Newark's downtown, a state arts center is planned and there is even talk of building a convention center. But decent low-income housing is a crucial need in this city where the median income is $12,000, unemployment exceeds 12 percent and one-third of its 275,000 residents receive welfare.</p>
        <p>In the Central Ward, filled with rundown houses, boarded-up buildings and homeless men warming themselves around trash-can fires, the need is obvious. The 10 buildings of the Hayes Homes, a Housing Authority complex, loom above bald dirt, shriveled trees and broken playground equipment. Shards of glass litter the central courtyard. Five of the buildings are vacant except for drug-addicted squatters. 'Reservations For the Poor'</p>
        <p>There is a consensus that both Newark's public housing and the authority are in desperate condition. Mayor Sharpe James, the city's most indefatigable booster, calls the public housing high-rises "shameful reservations for the poor."</p>
        <p>No one disputes him, though many argue that even wretched public housing is better than nothing, especially when there are an estimated 5,000 to 10,000 homeless people, not including those who live doubled up or in substandard conditions. Hundreds of families stay in expensive welfare hotels, and community leaders say their numbers are growing.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, 22 housing authority high-rises stand empty and several others are only half full. Walls in empty apartments have been punched so full of holes that it is often hard to tell where the doorway was. Pipes have been pulled out, light fixtures and wiring removed and floor tiles ripped up, and the staircases are full of garbage and reek of urine. Dried blood is a common sight.</p>
        <p>Residents keep their occupied apartments as tidy as anyone's. But 11 vacated buildings, including all 8 of those in Columbus Homes, have been declared too ravaged to fix and are destined for the wrecking ball. But that could be years away. As part of a 1989 settlement with a coalition of tenant and community groups that blocked plans to level 39 of the authority's 46 high-rises, the authority must begin to build replacements before it tears down any more units.</p>
        <p>The alliance of community groups, the Newark Coalition for Low-Income Housing, charges that mismanagement and incompetence are behind the construction delays. Last month, the coalition asked the Federal Department of Housing and Urban Development, which oversees public housing, to appoint a receiver to take over the construction program.</p>
        <p>"It's the same story over and over," said J. Harris David, a lawyer for the coalition. Small projects have taken an average of 10 years to complete, Mr. David said, adding: "H.U.D. bears a special responsibility here. There is more than $110 million and 1,777 units of housing at stake."</p>
        <p>Victor DeLuca, the coalition's chairman, says the demolition plan proves that the housing authority, with H.U.D.'s acquiescence, has abandoned its mission. "No one wants to build housing for the poor," he said. "Some of the land is becoming too valuable for poor people."  Red Tape And Recession</p>
        <p>Authority officials call such charges ridiculous and counter that construction has stalled because of the recession, which has made banks uneasy about backing projects that cost, on average, more than $10 million. And they cite bureaucracy that has hindered obtaining titles to land or site approvals.</p>
        <p>"Each step along the way, not only do we get some problem, perhaps," said Robert Graham, the authority's interim assistant director, "we also get the entity using all the available time to give us their approval. And oftentimes it's not done concurrently, but consecutively." Burton Bloomberg, acting manager of the H.U.D. office in Newark, said, "It's a complex situation with a lot involved."</p>
        <p>But stalled construction is not the authority's only problem. Its leadership is in disarray. In August, its board dismissed its executive director, Dr. Daniel W. Blue Jr., who has since joined the Chicago Housing Authority. In December, four top officials resigned. Mayor James, who opposes a Federal receiver for the authority, contends that new management is needed.</p>
        <p>"For too long, the Newark Housing Authority has been a political pork barrel for patronage-giving contracts," he said in an interview at City Hall recently. "I'm looking forward to an independent board with a new N.H.A. director who puts shovels in the ground and builds housing." The Mayor won a court fight in 1990 for the right to appoint six of seven commissioners, five without City Council approval, where the Council previously appointed five and the Mayor one. The Governor appoints the seventh.</p>
        <p>Most of the top administrative jobs at the authority, which has 1,000 employees, have changed hands at least once since 1988, said Frank Armour, an authority lawyer. And there was excitement in 1989 at the appointment of Dr. Blue, who had been Mayor Kenneth Gibson's chief of staff, and fanfare over a new board back in 1987. Both appointments were hailed as the beginning of a turnaround.</p>
        <p>The Newark authority currently houses about 7,900 households. It has 10,700 units, not including those scheduled for demolition, a waiting list that hovers around 6,500 families, and one of the highest vacancy rates in the country for a public housing authority. In several projects, money is desperately needed for basic maintenance, though the authority receives subsidies for vacant apartments and though its operating reserves, the money used to spend on repairs as needed, are at 90 percent.</p>
        <p>Michael B. Janis, deputy assistant secretary at H.U.D.'s Bureau of Public and Indian Housing, said the "very, very high" operating reserve was one reason the authority, the nation's eighth largest, was considered among the nation's most troubled. "If there are units in the housing agency that need some maintenance," he asked, "why isn't that money being utilized to improve the housing?"</p>
        <p>But Ben Quattlebaum, the authority's former chief of staff and one of the four officials who recently resigned, said more than 1,600 apartments had been renovated over the last two years to comply with the settlement agreement. He added that the agency had increased its spending on maintenance and modernization and earmarked some reserves for capital improvement.</p>
        <p>Some critics trace the authority's problems back to a source of many of the city's other enduring woes, the 1967 riots, which left 26 people dead and leveled entire neighborhoods, destroying more than 1,000 businesses. Residents who could afford to flee did so. Between 1970 and 1990, according to Census Bureau statistics, Newark lost 27 percent of its population. What remained were the projects.</p>
        <p>Housing Authority officials say a plan embraced in the 1980's by public housing authorities all over the country sheds some light on their vacancies and maintenance problems. Authorities came to see demolition as the only way to put ravaged, crime-ridden high-rises out of their misery, a concept the N.H.A. wholeheartedly endorsed. It devised a plan that would have seen the most sweeping removal of public housing by any city in the country. More than 5,000 of its 13,133 units would have been eliminated, and thousands were warehoused in preparation for the demolition. No money was spent to either repair or maintain them.</p>
        <p>But the authority's plans came to a halt in 1987, when Congress outlawed the demolition of public housing without a one-for-one replacement of the units destroyed. The Newark Coalition sued, and the authority was forced to reverse its course.</p>
        <p>Now, said Mr. Graham, the authority is in a Catch-22. "We can't demolish the buildings and they were not maintained, so the cost of trying to fix them is too high," he said.  Tenants Clean Up: 'This Is Our Home'</p>
        <p>But Pearl Cole, who has lived in Building No. 1 at Hayes Homes since it opened 37 years ago, cannot believe that it would cost $100 million to restore the project's former pride. Ms. Cole, co-chairwoman of the Hayes Homes Tenants Committee, said the tenants started a clean-up campaign in December that had made a world of difference. "We wanted to look good for Christmas," she said. "We bought some cleaner to get rid of the smell and the housing authority gave us the paint to do the walls."</p>
        <p>Building No. 1 is now a clean, well-lighted place. The front door has no lock and the linoleum is worn, but there are no graffiti on the walls and no trash in the stairwells. Residents have been moved down to the lower 6 of its 12 floors, but there are no squatters in vacant apartments. "We chased them out," she said. "This is our home."</p>
        <p>The tenants at Hayes Homes want the housing authority to unbolt sealed floors and buildings and make the project livable. That is unlikely. The housing authority plans to close two buildings and consolidate the tenants in the remaining three.</p>
        <p>Stephen Finn, the director of the Newark Coalition's home project, which monitors the 1989 settlement, said that efforts to consolidate Hayes Homes tenants would be challenged in court. "We would hope the Mayor would become more involved," he said. "Instead of going around like Gorbachev trying to sell everybody on how great Newark is, he could be helping the residents of the city."</p>
        <p>The Mayor bristles at the criticism. "My commissioners fired the executive director," he said, adding that "the James era" will start with the new executive director. Mr. James also added that his administration was the first of any city to build its own low-income housing, Victory Gardens. But others point out that Victory Gardens does not serve the most needy since its 100 units are for sale, not rent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
