<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Many Feasts In the Religion Of Parking</title>
    <meta content="14NYC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="965047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D81F3CF937A25753C1A961958260" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Many Feasts In the Religion Of Parking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clyde Haberman NYC column discusses joyous reaction of New Yorkers to lifting of alternate side parking rules in New York City in observation of national and religious holidays (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the tale goes, a reporter looking for a local angle on the annual Rosh ha-Shanah story once began his account something like this: Jews in New York City ushered in the New Year today in traditional style, filling synagogues with prayer and parking on both sides of the street.</p>
        <p>O.K., it was mildly irreverent. But you have to admit that it went to the heart of what certain holidays, be they religious or civic, really mean to many New Yorkers. Either way, car owners know them as times when they can rest easier because alternate-side parking rules are suspended.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the tale goes, a reporter looking for a local angle on the annual Rosh ha-Shanah story once began his account something like this: Jews in New York City ushered in the New Year today in traditional style, filling synagogues with prayer and parking on both sides of the street.</p>
        <p>O.K., it was mildly irreverent. But you have to admit that it went to the heart of what certain holidays, be they religious or civic, really mean to many New Yorkers. Either way, car owners know them as times when they can rest easier because alternate-side parking rules are suspended.</p>
        <p>''It's great,'' Carl Rivers said yesterday morning after pulling into a space on West 87th Street that would have been verboten at that hour had Christopher Columbus not stumbled upon the Bahamas on Oct. 12, 1492.</p>
        <p>October is rich with days when the normal rules do not apply: eight in all, thanks largely to a succession of Jewish holy days. Through the year, there are 30 parking-sensitive holidays, covering a total of 39 days. For some time now, it has not required a transportation specialist to sort them all out. It's taken a theologian.</p>
        <p>AND only a New York theologian knows instinctively what the Assumption of the Blessed Virgin, Id al-Fitr and Shemini Atzereth have in common, other than God, of course. You've got it. Christian, Muslim or Jewish, they are all days when alternate-side regulations, officially called Street Cleaning Rules, go by the boards.</p>
        <p>There was a time when major Jewish festivals were the main beneficiaries of special treatment. That is because Jews traditionally are not supposed to drive on those days, and the Talmud provides no known exception for New Yorkers who have to move the car before the tow truck shows up.</p>
        <p>But we now live in an age of diversity, which has created new cultural and political pressures, not to mention rampant me-tooism. If one religion receives a municipal dispensation from the rules, others feel they must get theirs, too, even though there are no proscriptions against Roman Catholics' driving on Holy Thursday or Muslims' on the feast known as Id al-Adha.</p>
        <p>''The up side is that we're a melting pot, and this is another way that reflects it,'' said Bob Leonard, a spokesman for the city's Department of Transportation, which sets the parking rules. Besides, he said, even if someone's religion does not forbid him to drive, ''Do you want him to have to leave in the middle of prayer because he realizes: 'Oh my God, it's 11 o'clock. I have to move the car'?''</p>
        <p>Fair enough. But think of the possible demands as new immigrants change the face of the city.</p>
        <p>Why shouldn't Buddhists, Hindus, Sikhs, Jainists, Confucians and Zoroastrians all get their own days? What about various ethnic minorities who might want the same parking recognition accorded the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'s Birthday? Why not the right to leave the car where it is on Simon Bolivar's birthday, or Sun Yat-sen's?</p>
        <p>''If it continues this way, it could get a little nuts,'' one official acknowledged.</p>
        <p>AS far as the Rev. Canon John C. Powers is concerned, the number of parking-privilege days should, if anything, be rolled back. Remember, Canon Powers says, a car-free Chelsea resident and executive vice president of the Association of Episcopal Colleges, this boon for auto owners means dirty streets.</p>
        <p>At certain times, like this week, the exempt days add up, especially since streets are already not swept on Wednesdays, Saturdays and Sundays. In Manhattan, for example, the north side of streets will not have seen a city broom between last Friday and next Monday because of Columbus Day yesterday and Succoth on Thursday and Friday. Today is the only day that the south side will have been swept in the 12 days from last Thursday to next Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''The greater public good on sanitation and beautification of the city should take precedence over holidays when, frankly, the suspension of alternate side is not always needed,'' Canon Powers said. Concern for the common weal, he added, lies ''at the heart of most religious traditions.''</p>
        <p>Amen, responded Lucian Chalfen, a Sanitation Department spokesman. But he asserted that lost street-sweeping days can always be recovered, as they are after snowstorms. Besides, ''Not every holiday affects every neighborhood,'' Mr. Chalfen said, ''because that neighborhood might not have been swept that day anyway.''</p>
        <p>Left unmentioned in this debate was that streets might be cleaned more effectively even on normal days -- and traffic flow certainly improved -- if New Yorkers simply did not own quite so many cars and used mass transit instead.</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
