<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>33 in Turkey Sentenced to Die For Killing 37 Secular Figures</title>
    <meta content="T03TURK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D8173DF930A35751C1A961958260" item-length="463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>33 in Turkey Sentenced to Die For Killing 37 Secular Figures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER</byline>
      <dateline>ISTANBUL, Turkey, Dec. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In one of the most sweeping verdicts issued by a Turkish court in recent years, 33 people have been sentenced to death for their roles in a mob attack in 1993 in which 37 secular intellectuals were killed.</p>
        <p>The attack, whose victims included poets, writers and folk singers, sent shock waves through Turkey and the Islamic world. Secularists describe it as one of the most horrific episodes in modern Turkish history, but some ardent Muslims say it was justified revenge against atheists who sought to humiliate Islam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In one of the most sweeping verdicts issued by a Turkish court in recent years, 33 people have been sentenced to death for their roles in a mob attack in 1993 in which 37 secular intellectuals were killed.</p>
        <p>The attack, whose victims included poets, writers and folk singers, sent shock waves through Turkey and the Islamic world. Secularists describe it as one of the most horrific episodes in modern Turkish history, but some ardent Muslims say it was justified revenge against atheists who sought to humiliate Islam.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said at least some of the condemned men were members of underground Islamic cells.</p>
        <p>Turkish law permits the death sentence for criminals convicted of seeking to overthrow the constitutional order by force. But there have been no executions here for more than a decade, and commentators predicted that the death sentences would probably be commuted to long prison terms.</p>
        <p>In the 1993 attack, a mob surrounded a hotel in the Anatolian city of Sivas, where intellectuals had gathered to discuss ways of promoting secularism.</p>
        <p>The most prominent among them was the satirist Aziz Nesin, who in his writing often ridiculed what he described as religious fanaticism. He also translated parts of Salman Rushdie's novel ''The Satanic Verses,'' which some Muslims consider blasphemous and which prompted Iranian calls for Mr. Rushdie's death.</p>
        <p>Sivas is known as a stronghold of religious conservatism, and some residents found the specter of such a meeting repugnant. Reportedly spurred on by some religious figures and pro-Islamic politicians, a mob surrounded the hotel and set it afire. Mr. Nesin barely escaped, but 37 participants in the conference were burned to death.</p>
        <p>Organizers said later that some of them had frantically telephoned police and military units seeking help, and that the units had been conspicuously slow in arriving.</p>
        <p>Several prominent figures in the religious-oriented Welfare Party expressed sympathy with the attackers, saying they had been intentionally provoked. One of the attackers' lawyers, Sevket Kazan, later became Justice Minister in the Welfare-led Government of Necmettin Erbakan, which held power for 12 months in 1996-97.</p>
        <p>The death sentences were handed down on Friday by the State Security Court in Ankara. They may be appealed to a higher court. Not all of the condemned are in custody, and reports in the Turkish press say 14 of them have disappeared.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nesin died of a heart attack in 1995. Relatives of several of those killed said they had not sought the death penalty but were relieved that the court evidently shared their view of the seriousness of the attack.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
