<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; A U.S. fund manager in Prague has found privatization corrupt.</title>
    <meta content="Y03PLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D6173DF930A35751C1A961958260" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; A U.S. fund manager in Prague has found privatization corrupt.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane Perlez</byline>
      <dateline>PRAGUE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM a distance, says Howard I. Golden, the president of a mutual fund that invests in Central Europe, the Czech Republic looked like a great place to do business: an educated work force, English-speaking colleagues, and according to the World Bank, an undervalued currency.</p>
        <p>But when he started to invest here two years ago, the close-up view was different.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM a distance, says Howard I. Golden, the president of a mutual fund that invests in Central Europe, the Czech Republic looked like a great place to do business: an educated work force, English-speaking colleagues, and according to the World Bank, an undervalued currency.</p>
        <p>But when he started to invest here two years ago, the close-up view was different.</p>
        <p>''Like most post-Communist countries, there was an ingrained system: never tell the truth and always help your buddies,'' said Mr. Golden, whose closed-end Central European Privatization Fund has invested $35 million here.</p>
        <p>That the Czech Cabinet of Prime Minister Vaclav Klaus collapsed this past weekend over a financial scandal involving political contributions came as little surprise to Mr. Golden or many other foreign investors in the Czech Republic.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the Czech Stock Market index rose 4.80 points, or just over 1 percent, to 463.30 after digesting a 4.3 percent drop on Monday, the first day of trading after Mr. Klaus's resignation.</p>
        <p>Investors like Mr. Golden, as well as some Czech economists, had been complaining for more than a year that the sweeping privatization of Czech companies Mr. Klaus carried out in the early 1990's was a good idea that went wrong.</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister's belief in the invisible hand of the marketplace, combined with his opposition to basic financial regulations, led to widespread corruption, they said. The most common form of corruption was stock manipulation that included bidding up share prices and insider trading.</p>
        <p>Under the privatization plan, shares or vouchers in nearly 2,000 companies were virtually given away to Czech citizens, allowing many to feel that they were part of the new capitalism.</p>
        <p>But then Czech investment funds, often controlled by Government-influenced banks, bought up the citizens' shares and got control of Communist-era, inefficient industries they had little intention of revamping.</p>
        <p>In many cases, Mr. Golden and other investors said, the investment funds stripped the companies of assets, leaving minority shareholders -- ordinary Czechs -- with nothing.</p>
        <p>This year, as inflation started to rise and growth slowed, people became resentful that a few were getting rich through illicit means while most were just making ends meet.</p>
        <p>''Klaus wanted a buildup of Czech capital without caring who it harmed,'' said Mr. Golden, a New Yorker who visits Prague for a week each month and has been writing opinion pieces in the Prague Business Journal, a weekly publication here. ''His answer to me was: Jay Gould and Vanderbilt were robber barons, but one generation later they were respected people.''</p>
        <p>In the last few months, experts in the Czech Finance Ministry backed Mr. Golden's view, releasing a document titled ''Current Aspects of the Czech Capital Market.''</p>
        <p>Written as the basis for introducing regulatory reform, the document listed 15 techniques that the investment funds and their managers were using to enrich themselves at the expense of the companies and the capital markets. The document said that because minority shareholders had no protection under the law, corporate raiders had discovered ''a risk-free method of removing money from companies.''</p>
        <p>Despite what he called ''massive theft,'' Mr. Golden's fund, which has bought into some of the 500 or so Czech investment funds, has not done badly here. He said the Central European Privatization Fund had gained 18 percent in value in two years. And he asserted that if managers of Czech funds ''had not stolen, we would have doubled'' the 18 percent gain.</p>
        <p>James Woolf, a British businessman who has invested in the Czech Republic since 1990, said that Mr. Klaus's departure as Prime Minister would set the stage for more disclosures about improprieties in the markets and about connections between privatization deals and campaign contributions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woolf said he had successfully built a portfolio of investments that included buildings in Prague and a new chain of cosmetics stores, Body Basics. But he said that his effort to buy a big manufacturer of glassware and lead crystal, Crystalex, in conjunction with a Czech bank had been turned down in the spring by the Finance Ministry, even though his $27 million offer was nearly three times the $10 million deal of a Czech company that was accepted.</p>
        <p>The crystal company was bought by Porcela Plus, which according to Mr. Woolf had contributed through its holding company to Mr. Klaus's Civic Democratic Party. The scandal that brought down Mr. Klaus ''is just the tip of the iceberg,'' Mr. Woolf said.</p>
        <p>The head of the United States Export-Import Bank in the early years of the Clinton Administration, Kenneth D. Brody, who bought a Czech company that makes compact disks last month as his first investment in the Czech Republic, said he believed that belated moves by the Klaus Cabinet to introduce capital market regulations would check the ''unacceptable behavior.''</p>
        <p>''People were stealing from companies -- as simple as that,'' asserted Mr. Brody who is a former managing partner of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company. But despite these failings, Mr. Brody said in a telephone interview from Washington that he still believed Mr. Klaus had been the best of the post-Communist Prime Ministers in Eastern Europe.</p>
        <p>''Klaus got the country going in the right direction,'' he said. The shortcomings, though dramatic, were ''correctable.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
