<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Line, Big Test For Giants</title>
    <meta content="30GIAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="FOOTBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="953877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Eagles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fassel, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Philadelphia Eagles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E7DE1131F933A0575BC0A961958260" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Line, Big Test For Giants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Aug. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Focus of New York Giants' first game of season, against Phliadelphia Eagles, will be on new offense installed by new coach Jim Fassel, as operated by 'new and improved' Dave Brown (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A good offensive line has been likened to a clenched fist. Tightly packed, it can strike. It is also good for protection. But one weakened joint and the unit fails.</p>
        <p>Since the Giants opened training camp, the offensive line's makeup has been a source of concern. The line has been anything but tight, more like a unit in flux. Its best part, the veteran center Brian Williams, was sidelined with an eye injury. Parts were shifted, parts were added and parts were discarded as the unit was remade and remade again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A good offensive line has been likened to a clenched fist. Tightly packed, it can strike. It is also good for protection. But one weakened joint and the unit fails.</p>
        <p>Since the Giants opened training camp, the offensive line's makeup has been a source of concern. The line has been anything but tight, more like a unit in flux. Its best part, the veteran center Brian Williams, was sidelined with an eye injury. Parts were shifted, parts were added and parts were discarded as the unit was remade and remade again.</p>
        <p>When the Giants open their season against the Philadelphia Eagles on Sunday, the focus will be on the new offense installed by the new coach, Jim Fassel, as operated by the new and improved Dave Brown. In the middle will be the retooled offensive line -- the clenched fist at the crux of every play.</p>
        <p>The question is whether the line of the rookie center Derek Engler, guards Greg Bishop and Ron Stone and tackles Scott Gragg and Roman Oben can act cohesively to protect the quarterback and lead the way for the running backs.</p>
        <p>''We don't have any more time to find that out,'' John Matsko, the Giants' offensive line coach, said today. ''Time's up on Sunday. I think we are better and will continue to get better. But we need to go 5 for 5. Five guys, no breakdowns.''</p>
        <p>That is a big assignment even for a veteran line, especially when the opponent is the aggressive Eagles defense. The Giants' line has an undrafted free agent rookie at center in Engler, a first-year starter at left tackle in Oben and a left guard who has not played consecutive seasons at one position in Bishop.</p>
        <p>The strength of the line is its right side, where Stone has emerged as a punishing run blocker and a stalwart in pass protection. Gragg, who is 6 feet 8 inches and 325 pounds, plays right tackle and has looked more comfortable in the starting role he earned for the first time last season.</p>
        <p>On the left side, things have been highly unpredictable. Oben is 6-4 and 300 pounds, small for a tackle, but the Giants have chosen to develop Oben, who was in for only four plays as a rookie last year, because he could be quicker and more athletic than some tackles. Sometimes, he has looked capable; other times, overmatched.</p>
        <p>''Roman is going to draw a rough, tough guy to block every week,'' said Fassel, well aware that most teams put their strongest pass rusher against the left tackle because he protects the quarterback's blind side. ''He's got to become a tough, ornery guy himself.''</p>
        <p>Bishop was the starting guard two seasons ago. Last year, he was switched to left tackle when the team brought in left guard Lance Smith. Fassel's staff did not want Bishop at left tackle, and Smith was expected to start at left guard.</p>
        <p>But the team had worries about the durability of Smith, who is 34. Bishop is 26 and has never missed a pro start in his four seasons. Bishop played well against the Green Bay Packers in the final exhibition game, and suddenly the Giants gave Bishop his old job back and cut Smith.</p>
        <p>The biggest surprise is Engler, the rookie out of the University of Wisconsin who took every snap from center in the preseason. He gets to start because he is the only center Brown has worked with extensively.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, the parts must draw together as one. Without them, the Giants will almost certainly lack punch.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>JIM FASSEL officially named five rookies -- wide receiver IKE HILLIARD, running back TIKI BARBER, safety SAM GARNES, center DEREK ENGLER and punter BRAD MAYNARD -- as starters. According to the Elias Sports Bureau, the Giants are the youngest team in the National Football League with an average age of 25 years 246 days. The oldest team is San Francisco with an average age of 28 years 361 days.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
