<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Criticizes Croatia, but Only Halfheartedly, for Attack on Serbs</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="780269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CONFLICT IN THE BALKANS: THE ALLIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">US-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-YUGOSLAVIA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CROATIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D6173FF936A3575BC0A963958260" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Criticizes Croatia, but Only Halfheartedly, for Attack on Serbs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States and the major European powers urged Croatia today to halt its offensive to recapture Serb-held lands, but Washington's criticisms were muted.</p>
        <p>White House and Pentagon officials said they understood Croatia's motive for the attack. But the Administration said Croatia should seek to regain the land through negotiation, not fighting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States and the major European powers urged Croatia today to halt its offensive to recapture Serb-held lands, but Washington's criticisms were muted.</p>
        <p>White House and Pentagon officials said they understood Croatia's motive for the attack. But the Administration said Croatia should seek to regain the land through negotiation, not fighting.</p>
        <p>The West has been ambivalent about the Croatian offensive.</p>
        <p>On the one hand there is fear that the attacks will cause more loss of life and a dangerous widening in fighting in the Balkans. On the other hand, the West recognizes Croatia's right to regain control of its land and expects that the drive will divert Serbian forces from their attack on Bihac, a United Nations-protected enclave across the border in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>"We have asked them to exercise real restraint because we are very concerned about a wider war," President Clinton said today. But he stopped short of condemning the Croatian action, saying it was "animated by the Serbian attack" on Bihac.</p>
        <p>NATO warned Croatia today that Croatian troops might be bombed if they harmed United Nations peacekeepers in the Serb-held area, known as Krajina. But there was no immediate allied response after Croatian shells killed a Danish peacekeeper and wounded two Poles.</p>
        <p>In remarks that some Europeans complained were far too easy on the Croats, Defense Secretary William J. Perry expressed some support for the offensive because it could take pressure off Bihac.</p>
        <p>Appearing on Reuters Television, he said, "The Croatian Government has an obvious frustration with the move of the Bosnian Serbs and the Krajina Serbs into Bihac, and their actions are intended among other things to stop that. We hope that that's successful, and the Serbs will stop their offensive in Bihac."</p>
        <p>He urged the Croatian Government not to extend its attacks beyond that objective. "The danger, of course, is that the war could accelerate, and could become a long and protracted war in Croatia, and has the danger of drawing Serbia into the war," he told reporters.</p>
        <p>A British Foreign Office statement was far harsher, saying, "The British Government strongly condemns Croatia's offensive on the Krajina region. It is clear that the possibility of further negotiations had not been exhausted."</p>
        <p>Some European and Russian diplomats complained that the Clinton Administration gave a green light to Croatia by signaling it would not criticize attacks against Serb forces in Bihac.</p>
        <p>In a statement today, the Russian Foreign Ministry said unnamed Western governments, "despite feeble protests, actually showed solidarity with the military action of the Croatian side." The Ministry accused Croatia of provoking the conflict.</p>
        <p>American diplomats vigorously denied that they had urged the Croats to attack Krajina: They said they took a nuanced approach that gave a green light for an attack on the Serbs in Bihac, while giving a red light to a broader offensive in Krajina for fear it would widen the war.</p>
        <p>Like the Clinton Administration, Germany urged President Franjo Tudjman of Croatia to stop the offensive, but was not unduly harsh. "We can't forget that the years of Serb aggression, especially the recent attack by Croat Serbs against Bihac, have sorely tried Croatia's patience," Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel said.</p>
        <p>With tens of thousands of Croatian troops massing near Krajina in recent days, the United States Ambassador to Croatia, Peter W. Galbraith, had sought to negotiate a peaceful resolution.</p>
        <p>David T. Johnson, a State Department spokesman, said, "We regret very much that Croatia chose not to pursue this, and we urge the parties to return as soon as possible to the bargaining table."</p>
        <p>Early today, President Clinton approved release of $17 million in Pentagon funds to support the European rapid-reaction force that is to support United Nations peacekeepers in Bosnia. The aid, which will include weapons, ammunition and communications equipment, is part of $60 million that Mr. Clinton has said he will take from the Pentagon budget for the force.</p>
        <p>The conflicting attitudes that the Americans and Europeans took toward the Croatian attack pointed once again to the sharp differences over how to end the four-year-old war in the Balkans.</p>
        <p>The United States and Germany, which said they understood Croatia's frustrations, are among that country's closest allies. Russia, however, is a traditional ally of the Serbs. And France and Britain, with the largest number of peacekeepers on the ground, are anxious to avert a surge in fighting.</p>
        <p>Carl Bildt, the European Union mediator for the former Yugoslavia, said the killing of Serbian civilians in the Croats' shelling of Knin, the Serbian headquarters in Krajina, would cast "a dark shadow over Croatia for a long time to come."</p>
        <p>The United Nations Secretary General, Boutros Boutros-Ghali, harshly condemned the Croatian offensive. In a statement today he said, "The deliberate reopening of large-scale conflict flouts the cease-fire that has provided the opportunity to search for a peaceful settlement. More lives will now be needlessly lost as a result of the course of action that President Tudjman and his Government have adopted."  CONFLICT IN THE BALKANS: THE ALLIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
