<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Move Intended to Quiet Questions on Clinton's Land Deal Seems to Backfire</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="672840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHITEWATER CASE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISKE, ROBERT B JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whitewater Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0DD1E3AF935A35750C0A962958260" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Move Intended to Quiet Questions on Clinton's Land Deal Seems to Backfire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN ENGELBERG,</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were many in the White House, including President Clinton, who hoped that the appointment in January of Robert B. Fiske Jr. as a special counsel would ease political pressure stemming from Mr. Clinton's Arkansas business dealings.</p>
        <p>For a few weeks, it looked like a savvy move. Stories about an investment by Mr. Clinton and his wife, Hillary, in real estate in the Ozark Mountains largely disappeared from front pages and television programs as Mr. Fiske hired a staff and set up shop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There were many in the White House, including President Clinton, who hoped that the appointment in January of Robert B. Fiske Jr. as a special counsel would ease political pressure stemming from Mr. Clinton's Arkansas business dealings.</p>
        <p>For a few weeks, it looked like a savvy move. Stories about an investment by Mr. Clinton and his wife, Hillary, in real estate in the Ozark Mountains largely disappeared from front pages and television programs as Mr. Fiske hired a staff and set up shop.</p>
        <p>But the subpoenas served Friday on 10 Administration officials suggest that the relief was illusory and that Mr. Clinton's White House may well be hostage to the workings of a grand jury for months or even years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fiske's subpoenas -- served on Treasury officials and White House aides involved in three meetings focusing on a failed Arkansas savings and loan with ties to the Clintons -- also illustrates how quickly the inquiry has reached inside the Clinton White House. Until now, much of the focus has been on the murky details of business deals that unfolded long before Mr. Clinton was elected President. Common Practice</p>
        <p>Samuel Dash, the Georgetown University law professor who was chief counsel to the Senate Watergate Committee, said Mr. Fiske's subpoenas were a straightforward use of the grand jury, a move copied by hundreds of prosecutors every day.</p>
        <p>Professor Dash said: "You hear an allegation. You order people to come forward. You order them to bring records. And you order them not to destroy anything. That's what any good prosecutor does."</p>
        <p>But Professor Dash acknowledged that grand jury proceedings, however routine, produce "smoke," suggestions that behind closed doors prosecutors are questioning someone who has done something wrong. In fact, he noted, being called as a witness could suggest the opposite, since prosecutors typically avoid calling witnesses who might become targets.</p>
        <p>He acknowledged, however, that neither the public nor Mr. Clinton's political opponents were likely to appreciate such distinctions.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, subpoenas of White House officials are unusual. In the Watergate case, President Richard M. Nixon made broad claims of executive privilege, and subpoenas were never issued for top Nixon aides, Professor Dash said.</p>
        <p>Lawrence E. Walsh, who investigated the Iran-contra affair, chose to secure the cooperation of most officials in the Reagan Administration, believing that he could get more material more quickly without subpoenas.</p>
        <p>In his first news conference on Jan. 21, Mr. Fiske said he had worked out his charter with Attorney General Janet Reno "so that I can do anything I feel I have to do to do this job right." His mandate, as he described it that day, included a close look at Madison Guaranty Savings and Loan, the Arkansas institution owned by James B. McDougal, the Clintons' partner in the land venture, and the circumstances surrounding the suicide last July of Vincent W. Foster Jr., the deputy White House counsel.</p>
        <p>Mr. McDougal was a partner with the Clintons in the venture, the Whitewater Development Company. Even before Mr. Fiske's appointment, investigators at the Federal agency overseeing the bailout of the savings and loan industry, the Resolution Trust Corporation, had found evidence indicating that Mr. McDougal diverted money from Madison to Mr. Clinton's campaign for governor.</p>
        <p>Resolution Trust first asked Federal prosecutors to take a closer look at Madison in the fall of 1992, when Mr. Clinton was the Democratic Presidential nominee. The agency can bring only civil cases; investigation of criminal wrongdoing falls to the Federal Bureau of Investigation. Leery of Inquiry</p>
        <p>Bush Administration officials, leery of what could be seen as a politically tainted inquiry, did not push ahead. In March, after the Clinton Administration took office, the Justice Department told the banking agency that it would not pursue the case.</p>
        <p>By the fall, however, the agency had produced a second Madison-related request, called a "criminal referral." It named the Clintons as possible subjects of an inquiry, but did not accuse them of any wrongdoing. It was at this stage, before the referral was formally sent to the Justice Department, that Mr. Nussbaum met with Jean Hanson, general counsel of the Treasury Department, which oversees the agency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nussbaum and other White House officials attended a second meeting in October with Treasury Department officials in which the Resolution Trust inquiry was discussed. Ultimately, the agency did send its criminal referral to Federal prosecutors, and the case was briefly investigated by a team of lawyers from the Justice Department before becoming a central part of Mr. Fiske's inquiry. A third meeting was held last month.</p>
        <p>What was said, and by whom, at the meetings between White House aides and the Treasury Department officials is clearly a line of inquiry for Mr. Fiske. It would be improper, and possibly illegal, for anyone at the White House to impede an investigation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
