<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fans Dashing Off to 100-Meter Trials</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="628766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRACK AND FIELD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FINLAND</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PLAATJES, MARK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESSAYAH, SARI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LITSKY, FRANK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D9173BF936A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fans Dashing Off to 100-Meter Trials</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LITSKY, FRANK</byline>
      <dateline>STUTTGART, Germany, Aug. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On opening day of the world outdoor track and field championships, the only finals were the men's marathon, won by Mark Plaatjes, a 32-year-old American, and the women's 10-kilometer walk, won by Sari Essayah, a 26-year-old Finn.</p>
        <p>But for many spectators at Gottfried-Daimler Stadium today, especially those who relish the psychological as well as the physical combat of the sport, nothing was more exciting than the first two rounds of the men's 100-meter dash.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On opening day of the world outdoor track and field championships, the only finals were the men's marathon, won by Mark Plaatjes, a 32-year-old American, and the women's 10-kilometer walk, won by Sari Essayah, a 26-year-old Finn.</p>
        <p>But for many spectators at Gottfried-Daimler Stadium today, especially those who relish the psychological as well as the physical combat of the sport, nothing was more exciting than the first two rounds of the men's 100-meter dash.</p>
        <p>With the semifinals and final set for Sunday, the winner will probably be the Americans Andre Cason, Carl Lewis or Dennis Mitchell or Linford Christie of Britain. If that seems indecisive, you should have seen their races in this morning's heats and this evening's quarterfinals. Take That!</p>
        <p>The four quarterfinals were a succession of in-your-face races, each faster than the previous one, each sending a message that the winner was ready to win more and win faster.</p>
        <p>Lewis won the first quarterfinal in 10.11 seconds and looked good. Mitchell won the next in 10.07, clapped his hands, punched an uppercut and never turned off his hypnotic stare.</p>
        <p>Christie won the next quarterfinal in 10.00. Then Cason, a solid block of 5 feet 7 inches, won the last quarterfinal in 9.96, his fastest ever. That time should have registered on the others.</p>
        <p>"I have no idea if it did," Cason said. "It actually doesn't matter. Tomorrow is another day."</p>
        <p>Yes, Andre, but in the 100, in which one sprinter tries to play with the next man's head, psychology sometimes conquers physiology. And Cason turned on the psychological switch. Aiming for Perfection</p>
        <p>"That wasn't the most perfect race I've ever run," he said. "I've never run a perfect race. Maybe tomorrow. I feel very good about myself."</p>
        <p>Christie, the 100-meter champion at the Barcelona Games, would not talk about the day's races. But he has made it clear that running fast is fine, but not his main goal.</p>
        <p>"Winning medals is far more important than running fast," he said. "I get a buzz out of hearing 'God Save the Queen.' You don't hear that as much as the American national anthem."</p>
        <p>The men's 100 and the men's 400 are two prospective highlights of the nine-day championships. In the first of four rounds of the 400, the fastest runner was Butch Reynolds, the American who holds the world record. He ran relaxed, almost lazily, in a time of 45.34 seconds in the first round.</p>
        <p>"I'm really looking forward to trying to bring out the man in me," he said.</p>
        <p>In the day's one women's final, Essayah won the 10K walk in 42 minutes 59 seconds. She was one of the few to escape the race unscathed as mixups sent some competitors to the first-aid room and one to the hospital. Many women complained that the water they received at water stations along the course was carbonated, leaving them with stomach aches.</p>
        <p>Kerry Junna-Saxby of Australia, who has set 30 world records, said she would have settled for an upset stomach. The official results listed her as disqualified. Actually, she said from a hospital bed, she felt dizzy late in the race, stopped, then started walking again, although somewhat shaky. She said the next thing she remembered was waking up in the hospital, an intravenous tube in her arm and her sinuses badly clogged.</p>
        <p>In the 800 meters, Johnny Gray, America's best in the event for a decade, advanced easily through the first round, the third-fastest qualifier in 1:46.28. Jose Luiz Barbosa of Brazil was the fastest in 1:46.12.</p>
        <p>Mark Everett, an American medal candidate, bumped another runner approaching the last turn and won the last qualifying place in his heat by an inch in 1:48.89. Joetta Clark, a perennial American 800-meter champion among the women, got caught up in a slow race, finished in 2:02.15 and missed advancing by 37-hundredths of a second.</p>
        <p>Bob Kennedy, America's best bet in the men's 5,000 meters, suffered a similar fate. His time of 13:42.17 was the 16th fastest, and 15 advanced to the final.</p>
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
