<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Find Two Potential 20-Game Winners Better Than One</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="628767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLE, DICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Colorado Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D7173BF936A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="1479" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Find Two Potential 20-Game Winners Better Than One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Talk about cautious conservatism.</p>
        <p>Dick Pole, the San Francisco Giants' pitching coach, supervises the two most successful pitchers in the National League, but he won't acknowledge, publicly at least, that they are on the verge of gaining a distinction rare in the National League in recent years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Talk about cautious conservatism.</p>
        <p>Dick Pole, the San Francisco Giants' pitching coach, supervises the two most successful pitchers in the National League, but he won't acknowledge, publicly at least, that they are on the verge of gaining a distinction rare in the National League in recent years.</p>
        <p>John Burkett and Bill Swift can become only the second pair of teammates in nearly a quarter century to become 20-game winners. Burkett has an 18-4 record, Swift a 17-5 mark. No one else in the league has more than 13 victories.</p>
        <p>But old spoilsport Pole said: "They haven't done it yet. I had an experience in 1988 with a kid who was 15-1 at the All-Star break, and he wound up 18-7 or something like that."</p>
        <p>Greg Maddux actually had a 15-3 record at the All-Star break that season and finished 18-8, but Pole made his point. Nothing is guaranteed, especially with something as fragile as pitching arms. Short of suffering disabling injuries, though, Burkett and Swift seem certain to gain the victories they need for 20.</p>
        <p>They would then be the first 20-game winning teammates in the National League since Joaquin Andujar and John Tudor of St. Louis in 1985 and only the second since 1969. The last time the Giants had two 20-game winners was in 1966, when Juan Marichal and Gaylord Perry reached that plateau.</p>
        <p>"They complement each other," Pole said of his prized pupils. "We have a good defense. These guys throw strikes; they make guys put the ball in play. The defense knows the ball can be hit in their direction at any time. And with our offense, if they keep the game close, we can win at any time."</p>
        <p>The Giants have won 38 of the 49 times Burkett and Swift have started. The Giants -- and the pitchers -- have compiled a 14-2 record since Swift last lost, to the Mets of all people, July 3. Swift has won seven times in seven starts since then. Burkett has won his last five starts.</p>
        <p>"They make adjustments, they're open to suggestions, they follow signs, they're coachable, they're bright, they're what you want in pitchers," Pole said. "Both have a good feel for pitching. It's something you can bring out in a guy, but you can't pound into a guy. They have good arms, know how to change speeds and don't panic when they get into a predicament."</p>
        <p>Swift found himself in a predicament last season. Strictly a relief pitcher the year before with Seattle, Swift became a starter -- indeed, he was the opening-day starter -- for the Giants. But the pitching load might have been too much too soon, and he developed problems in his right shoulder, twice going on the disabled list and finishing the season in relief.</p>
        <p>He also finished the season with a league-low 2.08 earned run average.</p>
        <p>Swift, the club decided, would start, but Manager Dusty Baker and Pole would closely watch the number of pitches he threw and innings he worked. Swift Was Monitored</p>
        <p>"We wanted to monitor him early in the season, try to keep him below 100 pitches," Pole said. "He's very conservative with his pitches. He was getting through seven or eight innings with 90 pitches."</p>
        <p>Swift hasn't pitched a complete game in his 24 starts.</p>
        <p>"If you have opportunities to take him out of the game when he doesn't have to complete it, you take him out," Pole said. "We don't have many complete games, only three. These guys could each have five or six complete games, but we thought it was better to let someone else complete the game. We've got six guys in our bullpen, and it's a very capable bullpen."</p>
        <p>Swift, 31 years old, is a complete game, or nine innings, away from matching his busiest season -- 174 2/3 innings.</p>
        <p>Burkett, who in winning a total of 39 times the previous three seasons indicated he was blossoming into a top-flight pitcher, was buoyed by the Giants' signing of Barry Bonds during the offseason.</p>
        <p>"When we acquired Bonds, he really started to bear down and accelerated his off-season program," Quinn said. "It was time to step it up a notch."</p>
        <p>As potent as the Bonds-bombarding offense has been, Burkett and Swift have not won just because of the runs scored for them. Besides a career-high victory total, the 28-year-old Burkett has a 3.09 earned run average, nearly a full run below his career 3.92 mark. Swift is even more stingy at 2.61.</p>
        <p>Before the season, no one mentioned the Giants' pitching staff in the same conversation that included the Atlanta Braves' contingent, but the Giants now are a close second to the Braves. The Tiger Barrage</p>
        <p>In scoring 47 runs in three successive games against Baltimore last week, the Detroit Tigers surpassed their 45-run assault against Minnesota in April. Only one other American League team has scored as many as 30 runs in three consecutive games against the same team. The Yankees amassed 32 runs against Oakland last month. The National League high is 39, Philadelphia battering Colorado.</p>
        <p>The Tigers have scored 10 or more runs 15 times, erupting for 20 twice in April four days apart. The most bizarre aspect of their scoring splurges: In the seven games in which they have scored 15 or more runs, Cecil Fielder, who is in position to lead the major leagues in runs batted in for an unprecedented fourth straight season, drove in only four runs of the 120 scored. He hit no home runs in those seven games. He drove in only one run in each of the three-game explosions against the Twins and the Orioles. The Mysterious Rockies</p>
        <p>Someday maybe someone will be able to explain why these things happen. Colorado loses 13 games in a row, then reels off six consecutive victories. Sunk by a pitching staff that allows nearly six earned runs a game, the team gets such sizzling performances from their starters that they allow only 11 earned runs in 45 innings for a 2.20 e.r.a. In the six games, the Rockies give up 12 runs.</p>
        <p>In each of the first five victories, the starter pitch at least seven innings.</p>
        <p>"So I didn't have to go to the bullpen," Manager Don Baylor said. "Normally, our downfall is the starter gets knocked out in the second or third and I have to use everybody. I've told those guys if you give me seven, we'll win the game."</p>
        <p>Baylor, who this season will be watched by more fans than any manager in baseball history, also tells his pitchers to speed up their work habits.</p>
        <p>"When you take all day to pitch, the defense is on their heels," he said. "We went through a bad streak where they couldn't catch the ball. When you go to three balls on every hitter, everybody is sitting back. If you're decisive about what you want to do on the mound, it keeps everybody in the game. I told Kent Bottenfield if I'm going to watch 'Sports Center,' you better pick it up. It helped him the next game."</p>
        <p>That game was a seven-hitter in one of the Rockies' four victories over the stunned Los Angeles Dodgers. '93 Season, '94 Guarantee</p>
        <p>Pitchers sometimes have contracts in which the following season's salary becomes guaranteed if they reach a certain number of games or innings pitched. But Jeff Russell has a unique economic agreement with the Boston Red Sox under which his 1994 salary became guaranteed with his appearance against Toronto Friday night.</p>
        <p>The option in the reliever's contract became vested when he earned enough bonuses to push this season's pay to his magic number of $1.7 million. Added so far to his base salary of $500,000 have been bonuses worth $400,000 for games pitched, $375,000 for games finished and $500,000 for number of days on the Red Sox roster. His pay stands at $1,775,000 and, without much difficulty but with good health, could go to $2,775,000.</p>
        <p>His 1994 salary will be $2 million or whatever he earns this year. Owners' Woes</p>
        <p>The second day of the owners' economic summit meeting in Kohler, Wis., began with owners of five wealthy clubs, including George Steinbrenner of the Yankees and Peter O'Malley of the Dodgers, walking through a side door of the building where the meeting was being held. A minute later, the owners walked sheepishly back through the door to the street. That entrance did not lead to the meeting room.</p>
        <p>The day ended, about 15 hours later, with all of the owners escaping from Kohler under dark of night in half a dozen vans. The owners had not made their reservations at the American Club through Thursday night, and they had to go elsewhere to sleep or get their private planes.</p>
        <p>Town residents, attracted by the television lights, stood on Highland Drive and Orchard Road watching the spectacle. The owners and their aides did not look happy.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, Richard Ravitch, the engineer of the revenue-sharing effort, was talking with reporters. He looked tired as he began to tell a joke, then paused.</p>
        <p>"I have to think about it before I start," he said. "I'd look foolish if I started it and couldn't finish it."</p>
        <p>That also was the problem he was trying desperately to avoid with his revenue-sharing effort.</p>
        <p>NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
