<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Transactions</title>
    <meta content="31TRANS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1035729"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E2D61338F932A05754C0A96E958260" item-length="547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Transactions</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League</p>
        <p>ANAHEIM ANGELS--Purchased contract of INF Troy Glaus from Vancouver of the PCL. Optioned LHP Jarrod Washburn to Vancouver. Transferred RHP Mike James and 1B Todd Greene to 60-day disabled list.  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Traded C Charlie O'Brien to the Anaheim Angels for LHP Jason Stockstill and RHP Brian Tokarse. Purchased the contract of RHP Chad Bradford from Calgary of the PCL.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Activated 2B Scott Spiezio from the 15-day disabled list. Sent OF Jack Voigt to Edmonton of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Traded 1B-DH Mike Stanley to the Boston Red Sox for RHP Peter Munro and RHP Jay Yennaco.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League</p>
        <p>ANAHEIM ANGELS--Purchased contract of INF Troy Glaus from Vancouver of the PCL. Optioned LHP Jarrod Washburn to Vancouver. Transferred RHP Mike James and 1B Todd Greene to 60-day disabled list.  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Traded C Charlie O'Brien to the Anaheim Angels for LHP Jason Stockstill and RHP Brian Tokarse. Purchased the contract of RHP Chad Bradford from Calgary of the PCL.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Activated 2B Scott Spiezio from the 15-day disabled list. Sent OF Jack Voigt to Edmonton of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Traded 1B-DH Mike Stanley to the Boston Red Sox for RHP Peter Munro and RHP Jay Yennaco.</p>
        <p>National League</p>
        <p>ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS--Activated RHP Felix Rodriguez from 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Bob Wolcott to Tucson of the PCL.  ATLANTA BRAVES--Traded RHP David Cortes and LHP Mike Porzio to the Colorado Rockies for 1B Greg Colbrunn.  CHICAGO CUBS--Optioned RHP Rodney Myers to Iowa of the PCL. Transferred RHP Jeremi Gonzalez to the 60-day disabled list.  CINCINNATI REDS--Placed OF Mike Frank on the 15-day disabled list, retroactive to July 27.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  National Football League</p>
        <p>BALTIMORE RAVENS--Signed DB-KR Tyrone Hughes.  MIAMI DOLPHINS--Waived WR Terry Guess.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY  National Hockey League</p>
        <p>BUFFALO SABRES--Signed C Domenic Pittis and C Craig Fisher.  DALLAS STARS--Signed LW David Roberts to a one-year contract.  EDMONTON OILERS--Announced the retirement of D Kevin Lowe and named him assistant coach.  SAN JOSE SHARKS--Announced the retirement of G Kelly Hrudey.  TAMPA BAY LIGHTNING--Signed C Jesse Belanger. Re-signed RW Corey Spring.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>BROCKPORT STATE--Named John Dumaw softball coach. Promoted Nanette Fox to field hockey coach.  CENTRAL FLORIDA--Named Miriam Ochoa volleyball coach.  DARTMOUTH--Named Erica Walsh women's assistant soccer coach and Jane Taylor assistant strength and conditioning coach.  DICKINSON--Named Kris Carroll interim field hockey and women's lacrosse coach.  HARVARD--Named Tim Murphy men's swimming and diving coach.  EAST CAROLINA--Named Tom Morris men's and women's tennis coach.  KINGS POINT--Named Jim Anson men's assistant soccer and lacrosse coach.  NEW ORLEANS--Named Gary Gallup, director of athletic marketing and promotions, and Nikita Johnson, men's assistant basketball coach.  TEXAS-PAN AMERICAN--Named Kevin Brown administrative assistant for men's basketball.  WESTMINSTER--Named Girish Thakar men's soccer coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
