<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>George Balanchine's "The Nutcracker"; An Intimate 'Nutcracker' With a Culkin Star Turn</title>
    <meta content="118893SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="651952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Review</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">George Balancine's The Nutcracker (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6DD1E3AF937A15752C1A965958260" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>George Balanchine's "The Nutcracker"; An Intimate 'Nutcracker' With a Culkin Star Turn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You don't have to believe in Santa Claus to be swept up in the magic of Christmas. By the same token, some of the fairy-tale magic of "George Balanchine's 'The Nutcracker' " has been lost in its translation from a staged ballet into a film, but it doesn't hurt; it is only a fraction. If Rouben Ter-Arutunian's depiction of the Sugarplum Fairy's Palace of Pleasures is obviously a painted stage set, its elegant swirl of domes and pedestals is still gorgeous.</p>
        <p>And what is sacrificed in realism is gained in intimacy. In close-up, Karinska's original costumes are even more awesome in their beauty and richness of detail than when seen from afar. And children who watch Emile Ardolino's handsome film version of the New York City Ballet's classic production can be vicarious participants in its Christmas Eve games, folk dances and roughhouse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You don't have to believe in Santa Claus to be swept up in the magic of Christmas. By the same token, some of the fairy-tale magic of "George Balanchine's 'The Nutcracker' " has been lost in its translation from a staged ballet into a film, but it doesn't hurt; it is only a fraction. If Rouben Ter-Arutunian's depiction of the Sugarplum Fairy's Palace of Pleasures is obviously a painted stage set, its elegant swirl of domes and pedestals is still gorgeous.</p>
        <p>And what is sacrificed in realism is gained in intimacy. In close-up, Karinska's original costumes are even more awesome in their beauty and richness of detail than when seen from afar. And children who watch Emile Ardolino's handsome film version of the New York City Ballet's classic production can be vicarious participants in its Christmas Eve games, folk dances and roughhouse.</p>
        <p>The film places you directly under the production's spectacular Christmas tree, which magically grows to be 40 feet tall. And once the tree has reached its full height, the camera mischievously peers down from the top. The intimate perspective also provides a throne's-eye view of the ballet's waltzing snowflakes and whirling candy canes and of its comic giantess, Mother Ginger. And when at the end, the Nutcracker Prince (Macaulay Culkin) and his sweetheart Marie (Jessica Lynn Cohen) soar off in a sleigh, you're there to bid them goodbye.</p>
        <p>The movie, which opened today, doesn't spend too much time gazing into people's faces. It is very scrupulous in the way it establishes a mood of participatory excitement, then draws back far enough so that the classic ballet sequences choreographed by Balanchine and staged by Peter Martins can be seen in their full glory. In these sequences, the camera enhances the fluency of the dancing and of the sweeping Tchaikovsky score by slowly, almost imperceptibly floating forward and upward.</p>
        <p>Much of the dancing is breathtaking. Darci Kistler's Sugarplum Fairy whirls and leaps with an otherworldly lightness and speed. And Damian Woetzel as her Cavalier moves with a slashing grace. Wendy Whelan's Coffee projects an enigmatic sensuality. And Gen Horiuchi's Tea is a spectacularly acrobatic jack-in-the-box.</p>
        <p>The film's inclusion of a narration by Kevin Kline pays off. Key changes of scene are unobtrusively introduced by the actor in two or three sentences that clear up any confusion and keep the story moving. Mr. Ardolino (who died on Saturday) has also added several short transitional sequences that were not choreographed by Balanchine. But they are close enough in style to the original ballet so as not to seem intrusive.</p>
        <p>One reason the film is so captivating is that this 1816 fairy tale by E. T. A. Hoffmann is almost as well acted as it is danced. As Herr Drosselmeier, the white-haired old magician who dispenses the magic, Bart Robinson Cook inserts enough of a hint of the sinister into a benignly twinkling portrait to give the character a mystical stature. Miss Cohen's Marie is at once dignified and heartfelt. And the ensemble's depictions of parents, guests and children sharing a 19th-century Christmas have all the right storybook inflections.</p>
        <p>The film's only serious flaw is Mr. Culkin's Nutcracker Prince. The entrance of the 11-year-old child star into this traditional setting is a little like having a baby Mick Jagger leap onto the stage as Jumping Jack Flash.</p>
        <p>Heavy-lidded and pouting and wearing too much lipstick, Mr. Culkin radiates a narcissistic star buzz. And his uncomfortably heavy presence in the nonspeaking role suggests that much of this young actor's appeal comes from his cutely spunky line readings. Mr. Culkin also walks through the Nutcracker Prince's big number, in which the character recapitulates the story in pantomime; he simply goes through the motions looking superior and detached.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Culkin's presence throws the film slightly off balance at moments, the role is finally too small for the performance to undermine the film significantly. The Nutcracker Prince is merely an observer of magic that is conjured in one glorious scene after another by dancers who are virtuosos in the art of bringing dreams to life.</p>
        <p>George Balanchine's 'The Nutcracker'  Directed by Emile Ardolino; choreographed by George Balanchine; adapted from the stage production by Peter Martins; music by Tchaikovsky; narration by Kevin Kline; costumes by Karinska; scenery by Rouben Ter-Arutunian; director of photography, Ralf Bode; edited by Girish Bhargava; produced by Robert A. Krasnow and Robert Hurwitz; released by Warner Brothers. Running time: 93 minutes. This film is rated G.</p>
        <p>Marie . . . . . Jessica Lynn Cohen  The Nutcracker . . . . . Macaulay Culkin  Herr Drosselmeier . . . . . Bart Robinson Cook  The Sugarplum Fairy . . . . . Darci Kistler  Her Cavalier . . . . . Damian Woetzel  Dewdrop . . . . . Kyra Nichols  Coffee . . . . . Wendy Whelan  Tea . . . . . Gen Horiuchi</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
