<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why the Pay Gap Persists for Women</title>
    <meta content="l31gender" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1815593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DD1630F932A05751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why the Pay Gap Persists for Women</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Scant Progress on Closing Gap in Women's Pay'' (front page, Dec. 24):</p>
        <p>Why do women earn so much less than men? Because employers pay women so much less. Why? Because they can.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Scant Progress on Closing Gap in Women's Pay'' (front page, Dec. 24):</p>
        <p>Why do women earn so much less than men? Because employers pay women so much less. Why? Because they can.</p>
        <p>You don't mention the key problems: the undervaluing of women's work, thanks to the legacy of discrimination (why do accountants earn so much more than social workers?); the mommy gap, penalizing mothers 5 percent per kid (only Alaska and Washington, D.C., outlaw discrimination based on family duties); the lack of bargaining power (women may ask for less, but most aren't allowed to negotiate, and many are penalized if they discuss pay with co-workers); and inflexible workplaces that measure success by face time instead of quality of work.</p>
        <p>It's time to close the pay gap by fixing these problems not as a favor to women but as a better way to get things done.</p>
        <p>Ellen Bravo  Milwaukee, Dec. 24, 2006</p>
        <p>The writer, a former director of 9to5, National Association of Working Women, teaches women's studies at the University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In the interesting article about the gender pay gap, you correctly point out that much of it results from different average trade-offs made by men and women between financial and nonfinancial work rewards -- a source of the gap that does not truly result in gender differences in the total level of work rewards.</p>
        <p>But there is a source, besides outright sex discrimination, that does result in unequal reward levels. That is the tendency for couples in dual-career marriages to give priority to his career over hers.</p>
        <p>In most, though not all, higher-level jobs, a willingness to relocate is requisite to maximizing work rewards, and it is unlikely that many couples can both maximize their rewards in the same location.</p>
        <p>Thus the market tends to discriminate against the spouse whose career is not given priority.</p>
        <p>Norval D. Glenn  Round Rock, Tex., Dec. 26, 2006</p>
        <p>The writer is a sociology professor at the University of Texas, Austin.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It should be noted that measuring the gender wage gap among all graduates of four-year colleges can be misleading.</p>
        <p>In an earlier New York Times article, ''At Colleges, Women Are Leaving Men in the Dust'' (front page, July 9), you wrote that more women are college students than men, and that women have been the majority on campuses for the last 25 years. But the graduation rates of the most competitive colleges will be about equal parts male and female, while less competitive schools are graduating vastly more women than men.</p>
        <p>As more women graduate from less competitive colleges, they dilute the average earning power of female college graduates. While discrimination is certainly a factor, the dilution may explain the stagnating wage gap among educated workers.</p>
        <p>Nathaniel L. Schwalb  Glen Ridge, N.J., Dec. 24, 2006</p>
        <p>The writer is a high school junior at Newark Academy.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Men dominate the highest-paid specialties in medicine, like orthopedic surgery, where annual salaries exceed $400,000. That is because their salaries are dependent on insurance reimbursement, which favors procedures over prevention and coordination of care.</p>
        <p>Here's a solution: Increase reimbursement for the ''nurturing'' specialties, like family practice, internal medicine and pediatrics. Decrease reimbursement for knee replacements and spine fusions, so that all the specialties earn about the same amount.</p>
        <p>The bonus: less elective surgery, more primary care for all.</p>
        <p>Helen Feit, M.D.  Villanova, Pa., Dec. 24, 2006</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
