<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Everybody's Wendy'' WENDY WASSERSTEIN b. 1950</title>
    <meta content="31wasserstein.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/31/magazine/31wasserstein.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1815391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE LIVES THEY LIVED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Frank Rich</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0DA1E31F932A05751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Everybody's Wendy'' WENDY WASSERSTEIN b. 1950</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Everybody’s Wendy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rich, Frank</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Along with their own grief, what those who knew and loved Wendy Wasserstein close up couldn't get over was how so many strangers knew and loved her from afar. There was no big-time playwright, perhaps no celebrity, more approachable than Wendy. She was incapable of turning away from the fan who stopped her on the street. She would show up for any obligatory cause, cultural event or party, if only someone asked. She was everybody's Wendy. Everybody who met her, everyone who was touched by her writing, thought they knew her intimately. This is not something that would be said about David Mamet or Edward Albee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What those who knew and loved Wendy Wasserstein close up couldn’t get over was how so many strangers knew and loved her from afar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Along with their own grief, what those who knew and loved Wendy Wasserstein close up couldn't get over was how so many strangers knew and loved her from afar. There was no big-time playwright, perhaps no celebrity, more approachable than Wendy. She was incapable of turning away from the fan who stopped her on the street. She would show up for any obligatory cause, cultural event or party, if only someone asked. She was everybody's Wendy. Everybody who met her, everyone who was touched by her writing, thought they knew her intimately. This is not something that would be said about David Mamet or Edward Albee.</p>
        <p>As news spread of her death, the strangers who had felt so proprietary about Wendy buttonholed her friends and family in person and by phone, letter and e-mail with their own outpourings of loss and vivid memories of chance encounters. André Bishop, the producer whose career and life had intertwined with Wendy's since their early days in the theater, was almost overwhelmed by the size of the crowd that turned up for the memorial he staged in March at Lincoln Center's Vivian Beaumont Theater. (The overflow had to settle for a satellite broadcast at Juilliard.) The program included some of Wendy's favorite actors performing scenes from her plays and some of her closest friends and artistic collaborators recalling her infectious humor and countless acts of generosity. Among Wendy's many selfless works was the creation of a mentoring program that opened up New York's theaters to public-high-school students who would otherwise be shut out.</p>
        <p>Yet what lingers most from the memorial these months later is the montage of home movies and photos at its end: Wendy hamming it up for the camera during her ostensibly cheerful middle-class childhood. Wendy, an uncommon woman among the Playwrights Horizons gang of men, preparing to conquer the New York theater from way West 42nd Street. Wendy, middle-aged, successful, a fixture of the establishment, yet still with that wide-open smile and ragamuffin's wardrobe. And finally, Wendy in late-in-life parenthood, the single mother of Lucy Jane. The dramatic arc of the Wendy chronicles was a shapely three acts plus an epilogue, marred only by the abrupt fall of that tragic final curtain.</p>
        <p>And yet what haunts all these months later is this: There was something missing in those pictures, something that had fallen through the cracks. As Wendy knew better than anyone, the most revealing, and heartbreaking, drama can often be found in what is not said.</p>
        <p>The Wendy Wasserstein who was always there for everybody (including me) at every crisis and celebration, the Wendy with that uproarious (yet musical) laugh and funny (yet never bitchy) dialogue for every fraught situation, the Wendy the whole world knew and adored was also an intensely private person who left many mysteries behind. Though she had countless circles of friends, the circles didn't always overlap: her life was more compartmentalized than she let on. Though she had written a memorable memoir for The New Yorker about her personal and physiological journey to childbirth, the subject of her child's paternity was strictly off-limits. Though it was apparent that she was ill for several years before her death, she hid the specifics and terminal gravity of her illness (lymphoma) until the endgame gave her away. By then she was out of reach of intimates who might have wanted to have a cognizant goodbye.</p>
        <p>After her death, her closest friends were left to compare notes and clues about what had gone unsaid. But we had no answers. Roy Harris, the devoted stage manager for many of Wendy's plays, including her last, ''Third,'' spoke for many of us when he published a tender reminiscence that also acknowledged his anger ''that she hadn't allowed any of her friends to be a part of her final months.''</p>
        <p>As Roy wrote, dying was entirely Wendy's ''own business.'' She was entitled to her decisions and her secrets. But the fact that she so successfully took so many of those secrets to the grave was a major revelation in itself. How could the most public artist in New York keep so much locked up? I don't think I was the only friend who felt I had somehow failed to see Wendy whole. And who wondered if I had let her down in some profound way. I grieve as much for the Wendy I didn't know as the Wendy I did.</p>
        <p>That Wendy I miss badly enough. We met just as her career as a playwright and mine as a drama critic were starting in earnest. Because of that journalistic conflict, I excused myself from reviewing her plays. But she was my loyal companion to other writers' plays as I made my reviewing rounds in the 1980s. She'd say yes to all my invitations, no matter how suspect the title of that night's production (''Moose Murders'' included). She was not without her own closeted talent for unsparing drama criticism. At one long-forgotten fiasco, we returned from intermission to discover a ''real'' swimming pool displayed on stage, with an invalid perched in a wheelchair at its edge. Wendy turned to me with a conspiratorial grin. ''Honey,'' she said in that husky tone that signaled a punch line was on the way, ''by the end of this play that woman in the wheelchair will be in that pool.'' (We were not to be disappointed.)</p>
        <p>If I had reviewed Wendy's plays, I imagine I would have said what her many critical admirers did: She was a voice for the boomer generation whose wit could not disguise the seriousness of her often frankly political passions. Even the plays that didn't succeed had their indelible scenes of sharp, articulate outrage as her heroines took stock of a world that promised women many more choices, in love as well as in life, than it actually delivered.</p>
        <p>In retrospect, Wendy's public image, that of a cuddly, always-merry Wendy doll, undersold just how tough her writing was and just how tough she was. She wasn't from a family overstuffed with high-achieving business executives for nothing. A woman of her generation didn't have her career in the theater, especially the commercial theater, without fighting for it.</p>
        <p>The plays may well look different with the passing of time and without the author herself on hand to mediate between them and the audience. Like so many who loved her, whether up close or from a seat in the balcony, I keep replaying the monologue she wrote for her iconic heroine, the star art historian Heidi Holland. On the verge of becoming a single parent, Heidi is contemplating the unfulfilled ideal of sisterhood among women of her generation. ''It's just that I feel stranded,'' she says. ''And I thought the whole point was that we wouldn't feel stranded. I thought the point was we were all in this together.''</p>
        <p>But of course that was never the point, and Wendy understood that before many of us did. Everybody's Wendy, that garrulous character adored by so many, was an act of artifice. ''The Heidi Chronicles'' was the truth. Perhaps only now that Wendy is gone can we begin to appreciate the full force of what she worked so hard to say.</p>
        <p>THE LIVES THEY LIVED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
