<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Midmajor Teams Take Fewer Lumps In Padding Résumé</title>
    <meta content="05midmajor" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/05/sports/ncaabasketball/05midmajor.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1809688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Collegiate Athletic Assn</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DF1631F936A35751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Midmajor Teams Take Fewer Lumps In Padding Résumé</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Midmajors, Victories Now Could Mean More in March</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wichita State's 64-61 victory at Syracuse on Saturday was more than just an intriguing early-season upset involving two previously undefeated teams from different conferences.</p>
        <p>The victory by the Shockers (6-0) over the Orange (7-1) showed how the status-seekers in men's college basketball juggle exposure, money and road-court disadvantage in an intricate calculation of risk and reward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The status-seekers in men’s college basketball juggle national exposure, money and the disadvantage of playing top-ranked opponents on the road.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wichita State's 64-61 victory at Syracuse on Saturday was more than just an intriguing early-season upset involving two previously undefeated teams from different conferences.</p>
        <p>The victory by the Shockers (6-0) over the Orange (7-1) showed how the status-seekers in men's college basketball juggle exposure, money and road-court disadvantage in an intricate calculation of risk and reward.</p>
        <p>Syracuse, which was ranked 15th, was the favorite. The Shockers were No. 17. The Orange was in its big home arena, the Carrier Dome, before 23,857 fans, and it plays in a more prestigious conference, the Big East.</p>
        <p>The Shockers are from the Missouri Valley Conference, a league whose profile has soared in recent years but is still considered by many to be merely midmajor. So, when Wichita State won, it received more than a bigger number in its win column.</p>
        <p>In addition to the guaranteed appearance fee of $80,000 paid by Syracuse, the Shockers banked a credit that may pay a dividend in March, when the N.C.A.A. chooses its 65-team tournament field.</p>
        <p>''You want to have those marquee games on your résumé,'' said Jim Schaus, the athletic director at Wichita State, which is now ranked 10th.</p>
        <p>Schaus said that when 34 at-large bids are debated by the N.C.A.A. selection committee, ''a committee member from a major conference wants more sizzle'' than he may see from victories against only Missouri Valley opponents.</p>
        <p>Along with the growing number of tournaments that teams are playing in the early part of the season, ''guarantee games'' like Wichita State-Syracuse demonstrate that, for midmajor teams like the Shockers, the competition is intense early. Prominent teams from major conferences can work out their kinks and experiment with different lineups during the nonconference season, but this time of year can be do or die for midmajor teams that are hoping to build their N.C.A.A. tournament résumés.</p>
        <p>''If you don't play a tough enough schedule, you don't position yourself for success,'' Schaus said.</p>
        <p>Last season, the Shockers compiled a 26-9 record and reached the Round of 16 in the N.C.A.A. tournament before losing to George Mason of the Colonial Athletic Association.</p>
        <p>The rise of the midmajors came into focus last spring, when George Mason reached the Final Four. This season, Wichita State has already won at George Mason and at Louisiana State, which also played in the Final Four last season. Generally, the major conferences are regarded as those that participate in the Bowl Championship Series in football and also have long-standing basketball traditions.</p>
        <p>They include the Atlantic Coast Conference, the Big East, the Big Ten, the Pac-10, the Southeastern Conference and the Big 12. The midmajors are six to eight leagues with less television exposure and revenue and, in general, a lesser profile in football.</p>
        <p>Other teams from midmajor conferences that have already improved their status this season are Oral Roberts (3-3), from the Mid-Continent Conference, which won at Kansas; Butler (9-0), from the Horizon League; and another M.V.C. team, Missouri State, which defeated Wisconsin when it was ranked No. 7.</p>
        <p>Butler won last month's N.I.T. Season Tip-Off tournament at Madison Square Garden with victories over Tennessee and Gonzaga. Earlier, Butler defeated Indiana and Notre Dame. ''Marquee wins,'' Schaus called them.</p>
        <p>Oral Roberts, coached by Scott Sutton, reached the N.C.A.A. tournament last season for the first time in 22 years but, seeded 16th, lost to top-seeded Memphis. Now, the Golden Eagles are more ambitious.</p>
        <p>Of his team's 78-71 victory over the Jayhawks on Nov. 15, Sutton said, ''That win alone will carry a lot of weight'' when tournament bids and seedings are decided. He added, ''It could mean two or three spots in the seeding -- 13th or 14th instead of 16th.''</p>
        <p>Sutton, who is more involved than some coaches in scheduling, has two more games on his road schedule -- at Georgetown on Dec. 9 and at Arkansas on Dec. 22 -- that are considered guarantee games, meaning Oral Roberts will be paid by the host team.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't do this with a young team,'' said Sutton, whose team starts two seniors and three juniors.</p>
        <p>He said a young team might be discouraged by losses on the road to more prestigious teams. But not this Eagles team, Sutton said. ''I like playing in big-time environments,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One negative aspect of playing guarantee games, Sutton and others said, is that teams from major conferences will not reciprocate by playing on the campuses of teams from midmajor conferences.</p>
        <p>Doug Elgin, commissioner of the M.V.C., said, ''Many of our coaches have staunchly refused to go on the road'' to play teams that will not return a home game.</p>
        <p>''The risk can be job security, or it's going to cost you ticket sales'' if you lose too many of them, he said.</p>
        <p>Elgin said he urged his teams to save a road date for a late addition to the schedule as leverage with a top program that needs to fill an open home date. Such teams may agree to a home-and-home arrangement out of desperation, he said.</p>
        <p>Another way around guarantee games on an opponent's floor is to play tournaments at neutral sites, as Butler did in New York. Schaus said Wichita State would play next season in the Virgin Islands in an early-season tournament that will include Georgia Tech and Notre Dame, well-known programs that might not otherwise play the Shockers.</p>
        <p>Jon LeCrone, commissioner of the Horizon League, said that his conference had success with such tournaments this season and that creative scheduling in the early season was ''probably more of an art than it is a science.''</p>
        <p>Referring to guarantee games, LeCrone said host teams paid ''opponents to come in, so opponents take the money, come play the game and generally are saddled with a loss.''</p>
        <p>But, LeCrone added, ''If you can put 40, 50 or 60 thousand dollars into your athletics budget for one game, you're probably going to get beat, but that's a tradeout, and some schools look at it that way.''</p>
        <p>Elgin said, ''The playing surface is anything but level from the get-go,'' because some teams played most of their nonconference games at home while others were forced to play most of their nonconference games on the road.</p>
        <p>Elgin said he did not mind the midmajor label; he uses it himself to describe his conference. But Schaus of Wichita State objected to it. ''I don't like that term,'' he said. ''Our program is 17th in the country. We're good. We're strong.''</p>
        <p>That is one of the reasons Syracuse booked them. Rob Edson, senior associate athletic director for Syracuse, said his program had arranged nine guarantee games at home this season because it sold 17,000 season tickets and knew weekend home games against ascendant programs like Wichita State would draw customers.</p>
        <p>''The revenue is obviously significant, so it behooves us, purely from a financial perspective,'' Edson said. He said that prices of guarantee games had increased significantly in recent years and that some teams included clauses in coaching contracts that paid the coaches a percentage of bonus money from guarantee games.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
