<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Something Different At Rutgers: Success</title>
    <meta content="22knights" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/22/sports/ncaafootball/22knights.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1711431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rutgers University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4DA133FF931A15753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Something Different At Rutgers: Success</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Something Different at Rutgers: Success</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <dateline>PISCATAWAY, N.J., Oct. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ryan Neill is having a hard time getting tickets for his friends and family for Saturday's game at Connecticut. It is the first time Neill, a fifth-year Rutgers senior and a starter at defensive end, has had this problem.</p>
        <p>It seems that Rutgers (4-2), which may be headed to its first bowl appearance since 1978, has something it has not had in a long time: a bandwagon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seems that Rutgers, which may be headed to its first bowl appearance since 1978, has something it has not had in a long time: a bandwagon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ryan Neill is having a hard time getting tickets for his friends and family for Saturday's game at Connecticut. It is the first time Neill, a fifth-year Rutgers senior and a starter at defensive end, has had this problem.</p>
        <p>It seems that Rutgers (4-2), which may be headed to its first bowl appearance since 1978, has something it has not had in a long time: a bandwagon.</p>
        <p>''There's a different atmosphere here this year,'' Neill said. ''The fan base is changing. I can't get any tickets for UConn and usually it's easy to get tickets for a road game. It's getting to be a lot of fun here.''</p>
        <p>Has Rutgers finally turned that elusive corner? Considering that the 2004 team was also 4-2 before losing its last five games and that Rutgers has not had a winning season since 1992, there is plenty of room for skepticism.</p>
        <p>But this team, 2-1 in the Big East, seems different from its struggling predecessors, which were often beaten down at this point of the season. The Scarlet Knights are coming off one of their best performances in years, dominating Syracuse, 31-9. Rutgers had lost 21 of its 22 previous Big East road games.</p>
        <p>''I feel like this is a different team,'' Coach Greg Schiano said. ''There is a workmanlike attitude about this team that I enjoy. They are businesslike and they work hard. They know what is at stake. You don't have to tell them about it.''</p>
        <p>Much of the success has been the result of strong defensive play. Since losing, 33-30, in overtime in its season opener at Illinois, Rutgers has given up an average of 12.2 points a game.</p>
        <p>Against Syracuse, the freshman quarterback Mike Teel made his first start, replacing Ryan Hart, the Scarlet Knights' career leader in passing yards. Teel, who has not lost a game in which he was a starting quarterback since his Pop Warner days, has a stronger arm than Hart and is more of an improviser.</p>
        <p>Teel could start the rest of the season, leading Rutgers through a fairly soft schedule. They need to win only two more games to become eligible for a bowl game, an accomplishment that may be within their reach. For a team that has not appeared in a bowl game in 27 years, playing in one would mean achieving a major goal.</p>
        <p>''I just want this to be a successful season and I want us to win a bowl game,'' said John Glass, a senior offensive guard. ''That's definitely a goal of this team. This is my last year here, and I want to go out a success and have something positive to look back on.''</p>
        <p>Rutgers ended last season with a 41-35 loss to Connecticut, but that was against a Huskies team quarterbacked by Don Orlovsky, now with the Detroit Lions. Orlovsky's replacement, Matt Bonislawski, broke his collarbone two weeks ago. He was replaced by D.J. Hernandez, who broke a wrist in his nonthrowing hand last week. Dennis Brown, a freshman who has never taken a snap for UConn, will start Saturday.</p>
        <p>Connecticut (4-2) is a beaten-up team. Over its last two games, the Huskies have lost eight starters to injuries, and at least four starters on defense will miss Saturday's game. Connecticut lost, 28-17, last week at Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>Rutgers is 0-3 versus Connecticut since the Huskies switched to Division I-A in 2000. The inability to beat a team that recently made the jump from Division I-AA is a part of the losing legacy at Rutgers, something that may finally be changing.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
