<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="806470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA &amp; HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1D61639F937A35752C1A963958260" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 3-8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 3-8</p>
        <p>A GREAT DIVIDE IN BOSNIA Despite their alliance, Bosnia's Croats and Muslims are two peoples moving apart. Each side has diametrically different views of what the country should be. 1 HUMAN RIGHTS STRESSED AT TALKS During three days of peace talks on Bosnia, human rights violations have been pushed high on the agenda, with the Bosnian Government demanding that the Serbs  do more to punish those responsible. 6</p>
        <p>DOLLAR HAVOC IN RUSSIA Russians covet, hoard and trade $100 bills more than people in any country other than the United States. So the newly designed note was expected to make a splash here. But nobody was prepared for what has already happened. 1</p>
        <p>UNEASE IN OKINAWA To listen to Okinawans, the American military presence here is not a source of comfort or protection, but an annoyance and a threat. 3</p>
        <p>TYPHOON BLASTS PHILIPPINES A typhoon raged through the main Philippine island of Luzon, leaving dozens of people dead and millions of dollars worth of crops and property destroyed. 8</p>
        <p>NO MORE QUEBEC POLLS SOON The Parti Quebecois looks unlikely to call soon for a new referendum on sovereignty after its frustrating loss in the latest referendum. 8</p>
        <p>Orienburg Journal: Budget cuts affect exhibits at Holocaust site. 4</p>
        <p>National 9-14</p>
        <p>SHIFT IN MEDICAL COSTS SEEN Economists and Washington business lobbyists contend that millions of working people and companies may have to pay more for health care and that many employees of small businesses could lose their insurance. They expect projected  Government cuts in health care spending to result in shifting costs to the private sector. 1</p>
        <p>AMENDMENT STEALS THE SPOTLIGHT Representative Ernest J. Istook Jr. has caused quite a stir with the Istook Amendment, which would restrict Government lobbying by certain nonprofit groups  that receive Federal grants.  1</p>
        <p>THE CAUTIOUS GENERAL For Gen. Colin L. Powell, making a decision on a run for the Presidency means talking to a small army of people.  1 TESTING SOUTHERN WATERS The race for governor of Mississippi will provide a clue as to what kind of coalition, if any, can get a progressive Democrat elected in the Deep South these days.  1</p>
        <p>In Kentucky, the gubernatorial contest lacks passion.  12</p>
        <p>REUNION WITH THE DEPARTED In a San Antonio cemetery, families celebrated an ancient holiday: the Day of the Dead.  9</p>
        <p>CHANGING RULES FOR JURIES Some recent verdicts and the public reaction to them have states and courts changing the rules of the jury system.  9</p>
        <p>JUDAISM AND CULTURAL ISSUES In seminars that are sometimes low key and sometimes lively, Judaism is debating its role in American cultural wars.  14</p>
        <p>Metro Digest 25 PROPOSAL ON REGENTS EXAMS The State Education Commissioner, with strong support from the Board of Regents, proposed requiring all students in New York to pass the state's rigorous Regents exams to earn a high school diploma. 1</p>
        <p>Business Digest 37</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment 15-21, 52</p>
        <p>Music: Pavarotti takes a chance.  15</p>
        <p>Alicia de Larrocha.  15</p>
        <p>Urge Overkill.  21</p>
        <p>Dance: San Francisco Ballet.  20</p>
        <p>Glej Theater and Betontanc.  20</p>
        <p>Television: Critic's Notebook 15 Gay equality series.  52</p>
        <p>Fashion 30</p>
        <p>Calvin Klein, Donna Karan and Isaac Mizrahi struggle with image.</p>
        <p>Mondrian.</p>
        <p>Sports 31-35</p>
        <p>Baseball: Steinbrenner makes overture to Mattingly. 31</p>
        <p>Basketball: Knicks beat Pistons. 31</p>
        <p>Raptors beat Nets in N.B.A. debut. 31</p>
        <p>Riley and the Heat trade for Mourning. 35</p>
        <p>Boxing: Odds favor Bowe. 31</p>
        <p>King says accountant made decisions. 33</p>
        <p>Columns: Rhoden on South African basketball team. 31</p>
        <p>Hockey: Penalty costly to Devils. 35</p>
        <p>Islanders lose to Lightning. 35</p>
        <p>Obituaries 54</p>
        <p>J. Bradbury Thompson, graphic-arts designer.</p>
        <p>Florence Greenberg, pop-record producer.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed 22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>New York's new housing plan.</p>
        <p>Outlawing an abortion method. Scandals in South Korea.</p>
        <p>Long Island's quiet election.</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>Frank Rich: Get Powell.</p>
        <p>Russell Baker: And a year yet to go.</p>
        <p>Kenneth W. Jenkins: N.A.A.C.P is lost in Yonkers.</p>
        <p>Neil J. Sullivan: Big league welfare.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Netanyahu: Act now against the terror network.</p>
        <p>Chronicle 24</p>
        <p>Bridge 21</p>
        <p>Crossword 20</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
