<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>T.W.A. Crash Prompts a Recommendation for Safer Fuel Tanks</title>
    <meta content="21PLAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="931424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoke Detectors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fire Extinguishers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Transportation Safety Board</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trans World Airlines (TWA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoke Detectors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E1D6163BF932A15756C0A961958260" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>T.W.A. Crash Prompts a Recommendation for Safer Fuel Tanks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Transporation Safety Board, updating list of 'most wanted safety improvements' in wake of 1996 Trans World Airlines crash, recommends change to insure that atmosphere in half-empty fuel tanks will not sustain fire or explosion; calls for installing smoke detectors and fire extinguishers in cargo holds of passenger planes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Updating its list of ''most wanted safety improvements,'' the National Transportation Safety Board today added a recommendation that grew out of the crash of T.W.A. Flight 800, a change meant to insure that the atmosphere in half-empty fuel tanks will not sustain a fire or explosion.</p>
        <p>The safety agency also made a priority of having smoke detectors and fire extinguishers installed in the cargo holds of passenger planes. That recommendation was first made after the Valujet Airlines crash in the Florida last May.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Updating its list of ''most wanted safety improvements,'' the National Transportation Safety Board today added a recommendation that grew out of the crash of T.W.A. Flight 800, a change meant to insure that the atmosphere in half-empty fuel tanks will not sustain a fire or explosion.</p>
        <p>The safety agency also made a priority of having smoke detectors and fire extinguishers installed in the cargo holds of passenger planes. That recommendation was first made after the Valujet Airlines crash in the Florida last May.</p>
        <p>The agency also said it was studying the feasibility of ''black boxes'' for automobiles somewhat like the ones used on planes to record data about crashes.</p>
        <p>Five safety recommendations were added by the safety board, an independent agency that makes recommendations to the Federal Aviation Administration and state and local transportation officials, among others.</p>
        <p>James E. Hall, the board chairman, noted that some recommendations had been on the list since it was first put together in 1990.</p>
        <p>''All the items on this list came about as a result of unfortunate, tragic events,'' Mr. Hall said.</p>
        <p>One of the new recommendations was for automatic recording devices on ships, trucks and rapid transit trains. Hundreds of thousands of trucks already have such recorders, which are used to determine if the driver has been speeding, but they are not required by law.</p>
        <p>Vernon Ellingstad, the director of the office of research and engineering, said the board was looking into crash recorders in automobiles, which could record, among other factors, crash pulses through the vehicle. These would be helpful in evaluating the performance of air bags and other safety features, he said.</p>
        <p>The board reissued its call for changes in airplane fuel tanks to insure that partly empty tanks cannot sustain a fire or an explosion. As for the installation of smoke detectors and fire extinguishers in cargo holds, the airlines have agreed but have said it will take years.</p>
        <p>The board also called for research and development in ice detectors and de-icing systems for airplanes, and improvements in pipeline safety.</p>
        <p>Board members voiced frustration over the fate of some recommendations already on the list. For example, the board wants better flight data recorders on Boeing 737's, after two crashes that investigators have spent years looking into because the recorders on those planes were rudimentary. The F.A.A. has instead proposed, but not issued, a rule for upgrading the recorders on all old planes, which the safety board believes slowed the process.</p>
        <p>''If the proposed final rule were issued now, the first retrofits wouldn't have to begin until 1999,'' Mr. Hall said. ''They wouldn't have to be finished until May 2001. If you add it up, that's more than six years since we issued our recommendations.''</p>
        <p>The board has also called for airlines to share pilot records, and noted that Congress had acted on the subject last year. The board said the new law did not solve the problem.</p>
        <p>The recommendation has been issued four times in nine years, most recently after a December 1994 crash of an American Eagle plane, caused by the error of a pilot who had recently been hired there, after quitting another airline just before it would have dismissed him for poor performance. The new law allows records to be shared, but it does not require disclosure of work history like that of the American Eagle pilot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
