<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nations Sign Pact to Stop Desert Growth</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="718529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAND USE POLICIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AFRICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3DB123CF935A25753C1A962958260" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nations Sign Pact to Stop Desert Growth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A plan drawn up two years ago at the Earth Summit to prevent agricultural land from turning into desert has been translated into an international agreement signed this week by some 100 countries here.</p>
        <p>The Convention on Desertification focuses on the world's arid and semi-arid lands, which are steadily yielding less because of overgrazing, excessive planting, poor irrigation and deforestation linked to population pressures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A plan drawn up two years ago at the Earth Summit to prevent agricultural land from turning into desert has been translated into an international agreement signed this week by some 100 countries here.</p>
        <p>The Convention on Desertification focuses on the world's arid and semi-arid lands, which are steadily yielding less because of overgrazing, excessive planting, poor irrigation and deforestation linked to population pressures.</p>
        <p>The erosion and exhaustion of the soil is considered most serious in Africa, where close to 75 percent of the arid land is already considered degraded. Overall, arid and semi-arid lands make up a quarter of the earth's land mass and sustain some 900 million people.</p>
        <p>The convention, which will become legally binding for the signers in two years, establishes a "Global Mechanism" to coordinate projects to protect and rehabilitate lands and to find money for that purpose. It urges governments to channel such money through the Global Environmental Facility, a fund that was created to finance projects dealing with worldwide environmental concerns like changes in the climate and the loss of species.</p>
        <p>Desertification was an important topic at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro, with African nations pressing for a commitment on the issue from rich countries in exchange for votes on issues more important to the industrialized world. With the convention, poor nations hope to revive interest in the issue and attract money for development aid.</p>
        <p>At the signing ceremonies here on Friday, rich nations pledged little new money but committed funds for further exploratory studies. The United Nations estimates that $10 billion to $22 billion will be needed annually over the next 20 years to finance the rehabilitation of land and stem the decline in fertility.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the convention generally agree that action is urgently needed to prevent mass migration from exhausted lands, which would create a need for emergency aid.</p>
        <p>The United States is expected to pledge $500 million initially, and other Western donors are expected to contribute as well. The donors refused to set up a new global trust fund requested by poor countries, saying that existing development funds could be applied more effectively. The Global Mechanism will be used to locate and channel such financing.</p>
        <p>Word that only modest new funds would be forthcoming angered many representatives from the developing world. Some said the rich were only interested in financing imminent problems of war and peace.</p>
        <p>"We have to realize that environmental degradation is as much of a threat to the planet and civil society as war," said Shri Kamal Nath, the Environment Minister of India. "And we have to combat it with as much vigor."</p>
        <p>One part of the convention commits governments to a "bottom-up" approach involving local communities and non-governmental organizations in designing and carrying out projects. Donors have said that this would insure use of traditional knowledge and local practice and improve the chances for honest use of the money.</p>
        <p>Some delegates from African governments objected privately to the close involvement of grass-roots groups. Members of non-governmental organizations at the conference here said that in a number of African countries, authoritarian governments see the groups as a threat to their power.</p>
        <p>The agreement also calls for the transfer of technology and the exchange of information to monitor the extent of land degradation.</p>
        <p>Scientists disagree, for example, on the precise causes of the expansion of deserts at the hand of man. Some say there is evidence that deserts have expanded and contracted over the millenia as climates changed. Even today, some argue, it is a lack of rain, not human activity, that is the main influence on crops and ecosystems in the dry lands.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
