<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Diary: October 9-14</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="718377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS DIARY (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0D6143CF935A25753C1A962958260" item-length="1428" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Diary: October 9-14</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Hubert B. Herring</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COMAPNIES Today's Artists Unite, and Hollywood May Never Be the Same  In 1919, Charlie Chaplin, Mary Pickford, Douglas Fairbanks and D. W. Griffith had a Hollywood-shaking idea -- get together some people who know movies and let them run the show. United Artists was born. Since those glory days, though, corporations and committees and accountants have taken over -- and their movies, alas, often look the part. But last week a grand cycle came round again as three men who indisputably know movies now -- Steven Spielberg, Jeffrey Katzenberg and David Geffen -- joined forces to create a studio. The rest of Hollywood may soon look as if a "Jurassic Park" dinosaur had tromped through. Mr. Spielberg will stop making films for Universal, Mr. Katzenberg will probably raid the animation talent at Disney, his former home, Mr. Geffen will bring his production unit. And all that talent will flow to the new studio. A Novel Cash-Flow Problem  Every company should have such problems. Chrysler -- yes, the one that almost went under -- has been making so much money it's running out of mattresses to stuff it in. With buyers clamoring for its cars and Cherokees, its earnings reports are getting boring -- another quarter, another record. And again last week: $11.66 billion in revenues, $651 million in profits, both records. So, what to do with it? The company even has all it needs in its pension funds -- the first time since 1957. It could raise the dividend, it could buy back some stock. But it also hasn't forgotten how wet the rainy days can be.  The Car-Buying Minuet  What is it about new cars? When you buy anything else, you shop around, you find the best price, you pay it. Simple. (Or you don't shop around, you pay too much, you kick yourself.) With cars, though, a bizarre world has evolved -- meaningless price tags, complex formulas for figuring what the price should be and the dealer's profit. (But do you know the deli's profit on that bagel and coffee?) And then "no haggle" pricing, to make it all nice and simple. But nothing, of course, is simple -- last week it turned out that the Justice Department is investigating the whole idea of no-haggle pricing. What are they looking for? Price-fixing possibly. Or maybe, like the rest of us, they're just trying to figure out what's going on.  Lutece Super-Value Meals?  The bistros come and go, the temples of Tuesday's cuisine vanish by Wednesday. And then there's Lutece, as indestructible as the Brooklyn Bridge. But the bridge shook a bit last week: Andre Soltner sold Lutece. So is it any cause for alarm that the buyer, Ark Restaurants, owns less-illustrious establishments like Albuquerque Eats and B. Smith's? No, insists Ark's president; this pillar of French cuisine will remain intact. But -- a "but" always seems to sneak in about now -- "there may be room for enhancement," he said, like a "Lutece Brasserie somewhere." Stay off the Brooklyn Bridge. Toys Don't Kill? Think Again  Kids love toy guns; parents hate them. So guess who usually wins out: Toy guns were a $246 million business in this country last year. But parents' vague unease has turned to tangible fear lately, as one New York boy, then another, was shot by a police officer who mistook a toy gun for the real thing. Toys 'R' Us heard those shots loud and clear, and last week it said it would stop selling "realistic" toy guns; others, like Kay-Bee Toys, quickly followed suit. Toys 'R' Us had banished toy guns before, but later started selling guns in bright colors -- to mark them as fake. But kids started painting them to look real, so the issue exploded again.  Microsoft, On Top Again  Microsoft clearly intends to be master of everything it touches, and if it can't build what it needs, it won't hesitate to buy it. Its own personal-finance software has managed only 4 percent of the market. But Bill Gates probably can't even see numbers that small, so last week, he had Microsoft issue $1.5 billion in stock -- in the largest software acquisition ever -- to buy Intuit, whose Quicken software owns the market. So if more people take to writing checks and paying bills electronically, Microsoft could just tiptoe in with a tiny transaction fee, then gather those golden crumbs into quite a rich cake indeed. ECONOMY Making Economics a Game  There's a concept in economics called "perfect competition" -- the idea that businesses and nations exist in a vast state of nature, and the fittest will prevail by brute, faceless mathematical force. Some economists, though, think it's a bit murkier -- that something called "game theory" must be factored in. That theory takes into account the bluff and swagger, the backing and filling, of real-life competition -- a world, in short, in which rivals play a lot of "games," possibly devious ones. Last week this economic school got a powerful blessing when the Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Science was awarded to three game-theory pioneers.  Lilco as Politics? Don't Be Silly  There's been talk of a state takeover of the Long Island Lighting Company for years, especially during the Shoreham mess. But it's naturally just a coincidence that Governor Cuomo proposed a takeover just last week -- a few weeks before his charmed political life could skid to a halt. Certainly it's not politics -- though the takeover would, by the by, lower rates for Lilco customers, among the nation's highest, by about 10 percent. George Pataki -- possibly munching some sour grapes as he witnessed, in living color, the joys of incumbency -- called it "the height of political opportunism." But Mr. Cuomo insisted it was "for the public." Follow the Bouncing Subsidy  One way to get cheap magazine subscriptions is to accept a cut-rate offer, not renew, then take another introductory offer. Companies could probably play that game, too, hopping from New York to Connecticut and back, following the tax break du jour. Last week, angry that Swiss Bank had been lured to Stamford, Mayor Giuliani started talking tough, saying that a 1991 tristate peace treaty had been broken and he'd start trying to entice companies away from Connecticut. New York, in fact, has just offered Viacom $15 million in tax breaks to stick around. Of course, as a Connecticut official pointed out, the whole region gets hurt by this tax-draining game.  No Inflation for Retirees  Don't mention inflation to people getting Social Security; there's none of it in their paychecks. When the consumer price numbers came in on Friday, the yearly increase added up to just 2.8 percent -- and that instantly became the magic number for 1995 Social Security increases. But for all that talk about lurking inflation, that's the third-smallest increase since the payments were pegged to price rises two decades ago. And the consumer-price data came on top of a surprising decline in producer prices reported the day before -- so, yet again, that feared price pressure isn't showing up on any radar. INTERNATIONAL A Weak Link: The Ruble  Russia's on a tightrope. It has to get its economy moving, but if it tries to do so by overdoing subsidies to business, the resulting inflation will be as destructive as anything else. Last week it took quite a jolt on that tightrope, as currency markets suddenly had big doubts and sent the ruble plummeting by 25 percent against the dollar -- its biggest single drop ever. Russia had made big strides in taming inflation, but this could well send it back to the drawing board. Boris Yeltsin started talking about conspiracies, and heads rolled -- Mr. Yeltsin fired the acting Finance Minister. But it was really just the market, and speculators, at work. The central bank managed to get the ruble to bounce back the next day, but that by no means meant the crisis was over. That was clear on Friday when the head of the central bank resigned. What Now for Mexican Labor?  So now that Nafta has been around a while, what's in store for workers at American-owned plants in Mexico? An answer may be taking shape. With Mexican factory workers lucky to get $16 a day -- about what Americans get an hour -- American unions have been trying to address that disparity. But there have been charges that companies like Honeywell and General Electric have fired union sympathizers, so the unions turned to Labor Secretary Robert Reich to ride to the rescue. But last week Mr. Reich refused to pursue the complaints. And union organizers and companies alike were watching it all very closely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COMAPNIES Today's Artists Unite, and Hollywood May Never Be the Same  In 1919, Charlie Chaplin, Mary Pickford, Douglas Fairbanks and D. W. Griffith had a Hollywood-shaking idea -- get together some people who know movies and let them run the show. United Artists was born. Since those glory days, though, corporations and committees and accountants have taken over -- and their movies, alas, often look the part. But last week a grand cycle came round again as three men who indisputably know movies now -- Steven Spielberg, Jeffrey Katzenberg and David Geffen -- joined forces to create a studio. The rest of Hollywood may soon look as if a "Jurassic Park" dinosaur had tromped through. Mr. Spielberg will stop making films for Universal, Mr. Katzenberg will probably raid the animation talent at Disney, his former home, Mr. Geffen will bring his production unit. And all that talent will flow to the new studio. A Novel Cash-Flow Problem  Every company should have such problems. Chrysler -- yes, the one that almost went under -- has been making so much money it's running out of mattresses to stuff it in. With buyers clamoring for its cars and Cherokees, its earnings reports are getting boring -- another quarter, another record. And again last week: $11.66 billion in revenues, $651 million in profits, both records. So, what to do with it? The company even has all it needs in its pension funds -- the first time since 1957. It could raise the dividend, it could buy back some stock. But it also hasn't forgotten how wet the rainy days can be.  The Car-Buying Minuet  What is it about new cars? When you buy anything else, you shop around, you find the best price, you pay it. Simple. (Or you don't shop around, you pay too much, you kick yourself.) With cars, though, a bizarre world has evolved -- meaningless price tags, complex formulas for figuring what the price should be and the dealer's profit. (But do you know the deli's profit on that bagel and coffee?) And then "no haggle" pricing, to make it all nice and simple. But nothing, of course, is simple -- last week it turned out that the Justice Department is investigating the whole idea of no-haggle pricing. What are they looking for? Price-fixing possibly. Or maybe, like the rest of us, they're just trying to figure out what's going on.  Lutece Super-Value Meals?  The bistros come and go, the temples of Tuesday's cuisine vanish by Wednesday. And then there's Lutece, as indestructible as the Brooklyn Bridge. But the bridge shook a bit last week: Andre Soltner sold Lutece. So is it any cause for alarm that the buyer, Ark Restaurants, owns less-illustrious establishments like Albuquerque Eats and B. Smith's? No, insists Ark's president; this pillar of French cuisine will remain intact. But -- a "but" always seems to sneak in about now -- "there may be room for enhancement," he said, like a "Lutece Brasserie somewhere." Stay off the Brooklyn Bridge. Toys Don't Kill? Think Again  Kids love toy guns; parents hate them. So guess who usually wins out: Toy guns were a $246 million business in this country last year. But parents' vague unease has turned to tangible fear lately, as one New York boy, then another, was shot by a police officer who mistook a toy gun for the real thing. Toys 'R' Us heard those shots loud and clear, and last week it said it would stop selling "realistic" toy guns; others, like Kay-Bee Toys, quickly followed suit. Toys 'R' Us had banished toy guns before, but later started selling guns in bright colors -- to mark them as fake. But kids started painting them to look real, so the issue exploded again.  Microsoft, On Top Again  Microsoft clearly intends to be master of everything it touches, and if it can't build what it needs, it won't hesitate to buy it. Its own personal-finance software has managed only 4 percent of the market. But Bill Gates probably can't even see numbers that small, so last week, he had Microsoft issue $1.5 billion in stock -- in the largest software acquisition ever -- to buy Intuit, whose Quicken software owns the market. So if more people take to writing checks and paying bills electronically, Microsoft could just tiptoe in with a tiny transaction fee, then gather those golden crumbs into quite a rich cake indeed. ECONOMY Making Economics a Game  There's a concept in economics called "perfect competition" -- the idea that businesses and nations exist in a vast state of nature, and the fittest will prevail by brute, faceless mathematical force. Some economists, though, think it's a bit murkier -- that something called "game theory" must be factored in. That theory takes into account the bluff and swagger, the backing and filling, of real-life competition -- a world, in short, in which rivals play a lot of "games," possibly devious ones. Last week this economic school got a powerful blessing when the Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Science was awarded to three game-theory pioneers.  Lilco as Politics? Don't Be Silly  There's been talk of a state takeover of the Long Island Lighting Company for years, especially during the Shoreham mess. But it's naturally just a coincidence that Governor Cuomo proposed a takeover just last week -- a few weeks before his charmed political life could skid to a halt. Certainly it's not politics -- though the takeover would, by the by, lower rates for Lilco customers, among the nation's highest, by about 10 percent. George Pataki -- possibly munching some sour grapes as he witnessed, in living color, the joys of incumbency -- called it "the height of political opportunism." But Mr. Cuomo insisted it was "for the public." Follow the Bouncing Subsidy  One way to get cheap magazine subscriptions is to accept a cut-rate offer, not renew, then take another introductory offer. Companies could probably play that game, too, hopping from New York to Connecticut and back, following the tax break du jour. Last week, angry that Swiss Bank had been lured to Stamford, Mayor Giuliani started talking tough, saying that a 1991 tristate peace treaty had been broken and he'd start trying to entice companies away from Connecticut. New York, in fact, has just offered Viacom $15 million in tax breaks to stick around. Of course, as a Connecticut official pointed out, the whole region gets hurt by this tax-draining game.  No Inflation for Retirees  Don't mention inflation to people getting Social Security; there's none of it in their paychecks. When the consumer price numbers came in on Friday, the yearly increase added up to just 2.8 percent -- and that instantly became the magic number for 1995 Social Security increases. But for all that talk about lurking inflation, that's the third-smallest increase since the payments were pegged to price rises two decades ago. And the consumer-price data came on top of a surprising decline in producer prices reported the day before -- so, yet again, that feared price pressure isn't showing up on any radar. INTERNATIONAL A Weak Link: The Ruble  Russia's on a tightrope. It has to get its economy moving, but if it tries to do so by overdoing subsidies to business, the resulting inflation will be as destructive as anything else. Last week it took quite a jolt on that tightrope, as currency markets suddenly had big doubts and sent the ruble plummeting by 25 percent against the dollar -- its biggest single drop ever. Russia had made big strides in taming inflation, but this could well send it back to the drawing board. Boris Yeltsin started talking about conspiracies, and heads rolled -- Mr. Yeltsin fired the acting Finance Minister. But it was really just the market, and speculators, at work. The central bank managed to get the ruble to bounce back the next day, but that by no means meant the crisis was over. That was clear on Friday when the head of the central bank resigned. What Now for Mexican Labor?  So now that Nafta has been around a while, what's in store for workers at American-owned plants in Mexico? An answer may be taking shape. With Mexican factory workers lucky to get $16 a day -- about what Americans get an hour -- American unions have been trying to address that disparity. But there have been charges that companies like Honeywell and General Electric have fired union sympathizers, so the unions turned to Labor Secretary Robert Reich to ride to the rescue. But last week Mr. Reich refused to pursue the complaints. And union organizers and companies alike were watching it all very closely.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
