<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL REPORT</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="718543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E5D9123CF935A25753C1A962958260" item-length="1308" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL REPORT</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long Island  TROJANS STOPPED AT 49: The last time GARDEN CITY lost a regular season game was 49 games ago against LEVITTOWN DIVISION, on Oct. 1, 1988. Yesterday, the Trojans did not lose to Division, but their 49-game regular-season winning streak came to end, when they tied Division, 7-7. Both of the teams' scores came as a result of long drives. Patrick Rock capped a 18-play, 75-yard drive, with a 2-yard burst to account for Division's (2-1-1) score. Garden City (3-0-1) scored on a 3-yard run by Patrick Murphy, who put an exclamation mark on the Trojans' 13-play, 67-yard drive with 8 minutes and 46 seconds remaining in the game.  SANTORO WHIPS TIGERS: Tom Santoro rushed for three touchdowns and 140 yards on 9 carries as MASSAPEQUA (4-0) cruised past HEMPSTEAD (2-2), 26-0. Cornerback Mike Sheridan (1 interception), linebacker Sal Alosi (12 tackles, 1 sack), and tackle Mike Shelly (10 tackles) were all instrumental in blanking the Hempstead Tigers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Long Island  TROJANS STOPPED AT 49: The last time GARDEN CITY lost a regular season game was 49 games ago against LEVITTOWN DIVISION, on Oct. 1, 1988. Yesterday, the Trojans did not lose to Division, but their 49-game regular-season winning streak came to end, when they tied Division, 7-7. Both of the teams' scores came as a result of long drives. Patrick Rock capped a 18-play, 75-yard drive, with a 2-yard burst to account for Division's (2-1-1) score. Garden City (3-0-1) scored on a 3-yard run by Patrick Murphy, who put an exclamation mark on the Trojans' 13-play, 67-yard drive with 8 minutes and 46 seconds remaining in the game.  SANTORO WHIPS TIGERS: Tom Santoro rushed for three touchdowns and 140 yards on 9 carries as MASSAPEQUA (4-0) cruised past HEMPSTEAD (2-2), 26-0. Cornerback Mike Sheridan (1 interception), linebacker Sal Alosi (12 tackles, 1 sack), and tackle Mike Shelly (10 tackles) were all instrumental in blanking the Hempstead Tigers.</p>
        <p>WINNING COMBO: Quarterback Jason Barnett threw two scoring strikes and Dewayne Whittingham (19 carries for 107 yards) rushed for two scores as BALDWIN (2-1-1) rocked LONG BEACH (1-3), 30-0. . . . . HERRICKS (4-0) cruised past Elmont (3-1), 34-20, behind the strong throwing of Rich Vetter (7 of 10 for 146 yards, 3 touchdowns) and elusive running of Rich Renny (18 carries for 165 yards, 2 touchdowns). Vetter hooked up with Matt Bresso (2 receptions for 67 yards, 2 touchdowns) and Matt Watts (4 receptions for 69 yards, 1 touchdown) all afternoon. As a linebacker, Renny had a big day, too, recording 14 tackles and recovering a fumble. Herricks held Elmont to 23 total yards in the first half and led at one point, 34-0, before bringing in the second team. . . . . Fred Espro (2 touchdowns) and Angelo Amato (1 touchdown) rushed for a combined 150 yards as WEST HEMPSTEAD (1-3) defeated GREAT NECK NORTH (0-4), 19-7, in its homecoming game.  HIGH SCORER: Nick Mucciacciaro ran the ball four times for 127 yards and three touchdowns, clinching a 27-12 LYNBROOK (3-1) victory over PLAINEDGE (2-2). Mucciacciaro broke loose for touchdowns on 24 and 35-yard carries, and grabbed another score on a 1-yard pass play from John C. McInerney, who also connected on one other scoring play.  100-YARD CLUB: Tim Bellisari racked up a combined 100 yards (14 rushes for 91 yards, 2 receptions for 9 yards and a touchdown) to carry LOCUST VALLEY (4-0) to a 22-7 victory over MANHASSET (2-1-1). Dennis McKeesery added to the scoreboard, completing 5 passes for 51 yards and two touchdowns. Nick Matrone led the defense with 15 tackles.</p>
        <p>FALCONS SOAR AGAIN: In a rematch of last year's Division III championship game, DEER PARK (2-2) defeated SAYVILLE (1-2) again, this by the score of 19-7. Last season, the Falcons beat Sayville, 14-0. Shane Tinling helped lead the way, as he rushed 12 times for 97 yards, including a 71-yard scoring scamper. Cornerback Dan McCaw returned an interception 33 yards and Matt Whelan kicked two field goals (25 and 38 yards) to help the Falcons to their second consecutive victory. DALERS GO THE LONG ROUTE: John Curtis (37 and 80-yard scampers), Rob Mulligan (60-yard fumble return) and Antonio Smikle (46-yard run) all scored on long sprints as FARMINGDALE (2-0-2) defeated EAST MEADOW (1-3), 37-28.  ONE-MAN GANG: Lloyd Harrison blocked an extra-point attempt to lift SEWANHAKA (3-1) over SEAFORD (2-2), 4-13. Harrison also scored both touchdowns for the Indians, on 10 and 3-yard runs.</p>
        <p>DELROSSO GETS HAT TRICK: Matt DelRosso (15 carries for 92 yards) rushed for two touchdowns and returned a fumble 44 yards in COMSEWOGUE'S (4-0) 45-22 victory over EAST HAMPTON (3-1). Mike Romaszka was the Warriors' leading rusher, carrying 12 times for 128 yards and one touchdown.  SCORING MACHINE: Boyd O'Kelley rushed for four touchdowns, on 23, 28, 65, and 34-yard runs, igniting AMITYVILLE'S (4-0) 42-14 whipping of HARBOR FIELDS (2-1-1). O'Kelley amassed over 220 total yards, and scored a pair of 2-point conversions. FRIDAY NIGHT MASSACRE: Matt Botz (7 rushes for 116 yards) and Jason Mirabella each scored two touchdowns as WEST ISLIP (4-0) destroyed CENTRAL ISLIP (0-4), 68-6.  CHARGE!: John Roden exploded into the end zone on 76-and 1-yard carries, as BETHPAGE (4-0) blanked NEW HYDE PARK (3-1), 36-0. Scott Renneisen contributed to the scoring effort with a 48-yard touchdown run, and Troy Gorman blasted a 59-yard touchdown pass to Mike Miale. CRUISIN': Bart Orr ran the ball 14 yards for a touchdown and Chris Grote kicked in a 23-yard field goal in HUNTINGTON'S (3-1) 15-0 victory over RIVERHEAD (2-1-1). Huntington held the Blue Waves to under 100 yards in rushing and capitalized on a key 65-yard punt return by Ricky Raganela.  New Jersey STILL NO. 1: Jim Finn rushed for 141 yards on 15 carries and three touchdowns to lead the state's No. 1 rated team, BERGEN CATHOLIC (4-0), to a 45-0 victory over PATERSON KENNEDY (1-3). Kicker Buck Elsey booted a 31-yard field goal and kicked all six extra points. The Crusaders amassed 392 total yards and held Paterson Kennedy to 62 yards.  RUNNING AND CATCHING: Rotating from the tailback to wide receiver positions, Tony Gselle rushed 8 times for 93 yards and caught 2 passes for 51 yards and two touchdowns as IMMACULATA (3-1) whipped ROSELLE (2-2), 41-0.  WAKELY RAMBLES OVER CRUSADERS: John Wakely rushed 19 times for 120 yards and one touchdown to catapult CALDWELL (4-0) to a 20-14 victory over MORRIS CATHOLIC (1-2-1).  DEADLOCKED AT 9: Scott Reddy kicked a 39-yard field with 2 minutes and 32 seconds remaining in the third quarter to help GOVERNOR LIVINGSTON (1-2-1) tie DAYTON (1-2-1), 9-9. Quarterback Paul Petraccoro scored on a 3-yard burst to account for Governor Livington's only touchdown. Chris Reno drew first blood, when he was credited with a safety to get Dayton on the scoreboard. Mike Keller hit Joe Coffi with a 9-yard scoring pass for Dayton's touchdown. D-DAY: The DELBARTON defense held WEST MILFORD to 123 offensive yards (67 rushing, 56 passing) and grabbed a fumble recovery and an interception, as the Green Waves triumphed in a 14-0 shutout. Lou Basenese and Ryan Crane, paced Delbarton's offense, scoring on 3 and 1-yard dashes, respectively.  Connecticut  KARPIUK SCORES THREE: Sean Karpiuk (18 rushes for 74 yards) scored three touchdowns as SEYMOUR (4-1) scored 27 points in the final quarter to beat WILBY (0-5), 33-6.  A ROUT IN ANSONIA: Luke Richmond tossed three touchdowns as ANSONIA routed HOLY CROSS, 56-0, on Friday night. Ron Tate and Steve Cauklin each scored twice for the home team. Preps STRONG-ARMED: Fueled by the rifle arm of Michael Taylor, HACKLEY (4-1) blazed to a 14-6 victory over RIVERDALE (2-1-2). Taylor (5 of 12 for 89 yards) hit Justin Vargas with a 43-yard bullet for the first score, and snapped a 14-yard pass to Shawn Lyons in the end zone to cushion the win.  THREE'S A CHARM: Willie Edwards scored three touchdowns as KENT (4-0) rolled past GUNNERY (0-4), 31-6. Edwards rushed 22, 19, and 10 yards for the scores, and Mas Sunami added a 9-yard scoring scamper.  TWO AT A TIME: Peter Hall and Marc Maccarini rushed for two touchdowns each while Peter Rogosa passed for two others in DEERFIELD'S 36-14 victory over LOOMIS. Randall Williams scored the winning team's other touchdown to help Deerfield (3-1) to its third consecutive victory. . . . . David Bruc and Cord Stahl each rushed for a pair of touchdowns as WESTMINSTER (4-0) beat SALISBURY (2-2), 27-6. . . . . Daryl McElvenn (23 carries for 186 yards) scored two touchdowns and defensive tackle Omar Pickerins had eight tackles to help RYE (3-2) shut out DWIGHT-ENGLEWOOD (1-4), 28-0. CLOSE CALL: Daryl Simmons cashed in on a 15-yard run in the third quarter as MORRISTOWN BEARD (5-0) edged MONTCLAIR KIMBERLY (2-2), 21-20.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
