<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="17DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1473079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DA1631F934A25750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Microsoft Said to Abandon Goal of Overtaking AOL  IDC, the big technology research firm, said in a report that Microsoft had abandoned its goal of trying to overtake America Online as the largest online service.</p>
        <p>''MSN,'' the report states, ''has adopted a new strategy -- to ultimately become a portal or software company, with customers obtaining their own Internet access from any source.'' [Page C5.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Microsoft Said to Abandon Goal of Overtaking AOL  IDC, the big technology research firm, said in a report that Microsoft had abandoned its goal of trying to overtake America Online as the largest online service.</p>
        <p>''MSN,'' the report states, ''has adopted a new strategy -- to ultimately become a portal or software company, with customers obtaining their own Internet access from any source.'' [Page C5.]</p>
        <p>After spending more than a year trying to determine what sort of video programming Internet users will pay for, Yahoo will introduce its first subscription video service today. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Lil' Kim Surprises Her Critics  The outrageous rapper Lil' Kim surprised her critics last week when her new album, ''La Bella Mafia,'' became the fifth top-selling CD. Lil' Kim, a disciple of the late gangsta rapper Biggie Smalls, is making a comeback after three years of making an art of self-promotion through outlandish entrances at red-carpet events, taking on acting roles and becoming a spokeswoman for cosmetic lines. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Barnes &amp; Noble Alters Agreement  Barnes &amp; Noble has restructured its partnership with Book to cut costs and more closely integrate the magazine with the chain. Starting with the May/June issue, the magazine will be called Barnes &amp; Noble Presents Book. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Report Sees More Telecom Woes  Probe Research issued its latest dose of hopelessness about the telecommunications industry in its report ''Debt, Demographics and Telecom,'' which outlines the possibility of an even bigger crisis than the industry has had the last couple of years. [C8.]</p>
        <p>There is a long way to climb back from the peak of the bubble years, executives gathered at the CeBIT technology convention in Germany pointed out. [C2]</p>
        <p>Consumers Downloading Coupons  Coupon clicking may be an idea whose time has finally come. Consumers downloaded about 242 million coupons last year, 111 percent more than in 2001, according to CMS Incorporated, a coupon management company. Of those, 7.6 million were redeemed, which is an increase of more than fourfold from 2001.  Bob Tedeschi: E-Commerce Report. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Ephedra Marketers Take Cover  Since the death of a Baltimore Orioles pitcher who had been taking ephedra, an over-the-counter dietary supplement advertised for weight loss and muscle gain, critics are saying the supplement poses unreasonable health risks, putting its marketers increasingly on the defensive. Advertising. [C9.]</p>
        <p>More Repetition on Radio Stations  Top 40 radio stations sound a lot like hip-hop and rhythm and blues stations (''mainstream urban'' and ''rhythmic,'' to use the industry categories) because of extensive overlap of play lists, according to Mediabase 24/7, a tracking service. Ja Rule's ''Mesmerize,'' for example, was played heavily on Top 40, rhythmic and mainstream urban stations in the week ended March 11. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Fund Dominates US Airways' Board  Under terms of US Airways' restructuring, the Retirement Systems of Alabama has received eight seats on the board, plus 70 percent voting control of the airline. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Patent Donations Are Criticized  Gregory Aharonian is intent on exposing what he says may turn out to be the next big tax accounting scandal: patent donations. Mr. Aharonian's e-mail newsletter, Internet Patent News, says there is an alarming trend of companies ''donating bogus patents to universities and claiming big tax deductions on their federal taxes.'' Patents. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
