<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Joint News Conference: 'Tomorrow Is a Moment of Truth'</title>
    <meta content="Y17DTE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/17/international/17DTEX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1473120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THREATS AND RESPONSES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Portugal</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barroso, Jose Manuel Durao (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aznar, Jose Maria (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Portugal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Portugal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E5DD1731F934A25750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="3283" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Joint News Conference: 'Tomorrow Is a Moment of Truth'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Excerpts From Joint News Conference</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>LAJES, Azores, March 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from news conference by Pres Bush, Prime Min Jose Manuel Durdo Barroso of Portugal, Prime Min Jose Maria Aznar of Spain and Prime Min Tony Blair of Britain on need to act on Iraq; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a news conference today by President Bush, Prime Minister José Manuel Durão Barroso of Portugal, Prime Minister José María Aznar of Spain and Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain after a summit meeting here, as recorded by Federal News Service Inc. Comments by Mr. Barroso and Mr. Aznar were translated from the Portuguese and the Spanish by interpreters. A complete transcript is online at nytimes.com/international.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Barroso</p>
        <p>. . . This meeting in the Azores . . . shows the importance of trans-Atlantic relations, and also shows the solidarity among our countries. Actually this agreement has approved two statements -- one statement on trans-Atlantic relations, and a declarative statement on Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEJAS, Azores, March 16  Following are excerpts from a news conference today by President Bush, Prime Minister José Manuel Durão Barroso of Portugal, Prime Minister José María Aznar of Spain and Prime Minister TonyBlair of Britain after a summit meeting here, as recorded by Federal News Service Inc. Comments by Mr. Barroso and Mr. Aznar were translated from the Portuguese and the Spanish by interpreters. A complete transcript is online at nytimes.com/international.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a news conference today by President Bush, Prime Minister José Manuel Durão Barroso of Portugal, Prime Minister José María Aznar of Spain and Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain after a summit meeting here, as recorded by Federal News Service Inc. Comments by Mr. Barroso and Mr. Aznar were translated from the Portuguese and the Spanish by interpreters. A complete transcript is online at nytimes.com/international.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Barroso</p>
        <p>. . . This meeting in the Azores . . . shows the importance of trans-Atlantic relations, and also shows the solidarity among our countries. Actually this agreement has approved two statements -- one statement on trans-Atlantic relations, and a declarative statement on Iraq.</p>
        <p>We have joined this initiative, and we organized it here in the Azores, because we thought this was the last opportunity for a political solution. And this is how we see it. This is the last possibility for a political solution to the problem. Maybe it's a small chance, a small possibility. But even if it's one in one million, it's always worthwhile fighting for a political solution. And I think this is the message that we can get from this Atlantic summit. . . .</p>
        <p>President Bush</p>
        <p>. . . I'm standing here with you and our friends as we work toward a great cause, and that is peace and security in this world. We had a really good discussion. We've been doing a lot of phone talking, and it was good to get together and to visit and to talk. We concluded that tomorrow is a moment of truth for the world. Many nations have voiced a commitment to peace and security, and now they must demonstrate that commitment to peace and security in the only effective way: by supporting the immediate and unconditional disarmament of Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>The dictator of Iraq and his weapons of mass destruction are a threat to the security of free nations. He is a danger to his neighbors. He is a sponsor of terrorism. He is an obstacle to progress in the Middle East. For decades he has been the cruel, cruel oppressor of the Iraq people.</p>
        <p>On this very day 15 years ago, Saddam Hussein launched a chemical weapons attack on the Iraqi village of Halabja. With a single order, the Iraqi regime killed thousands of men and women and children without mercy or without shame. Saddam Hussein has proven he is capable of any crime. We must not permit his crimes to reach across the world. Saddam Hussein has a history of mass murder. He possesses the weapons of mass murder. He agrees -- he agreed to disarm Iraq of these weapons as a condition for ending the Gulf War over a decade ago. The United Nations Security Council in Resolution 1441 has declared Iraq in material breach of its longstanding obligations; demanded once again Iraq's full and immediate disarmament; and promised serious consequences if the regime refused to comply. That resolution was passed unanimously, and its logic is inescapable. The Iraqi regime will disarm itself or the Iraqi regime will be disarmed by force. And the regime has not disarmed itself.</p>
        <p>Action to remove the threat from Iraq would also allow the Iraqi people to build a better future for their society. And Iraq's liberation would be the beginning, not the end, of our commitment to its people. We will supply humanitarian relief, bring the economic sanctions to a swift close, work for the long-term recovery of Iraq's economy. We will make sure that Iraq's natural resources are used for the benefit of their owners, the Iraqi people.</p>
        <p>Iraq has the potential to be a great nation. Iraq's people are skilled and educated. We'll push as quickly as possible for Iraqi interim authority to draw upon the talents of Iraq's people to rebuild their nation. We are committed to the goal of a unified Iraq, with democratic institutions of which members of all ethnic and religious groups are treated with dignity and respect.</p>
        <p>To achieve this vision, we will work closely with the international community, including the United Nations and our coalition partners. If military force is required, we will quickly seek new Security Council resolutions to encourage broad participation in the process of helping the Iraqi people to build a free Iraq. Crucial days lie ahead for the world.</p>
        <p>I want to thank the leaders here today, and many others, for stepping forward and taking leadership and showing their resolve in the cause of peace and the cause of security. José María.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Aznar</p>
        <p>. . . I would first like to refer to our document on Atlantic solidarity. We have renewed our Atlantic commitment on our common values and principles in favor of democracy, freedom and the rule of law. . . .</p>
        <p>In view of the situation created by Iraq, with their continued noncompliance of international law, I would like to remind you that we all said before we came here that we were not coming to the Azores to make a declaration of war; that we were coming after having made every possible effort -- after having made this effort, continuing to make this effort to working to achieve the greatest possible agreement and for international law to be respected, and for U.N. resolutions to be respected. . . .</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Blair</p>
        <p>. . . For four and a half months now we've worked hard to get Saddam to cooperate fully, unconditionally, as that resolution demanded. Even some days ago we were prepared to set out clear tests that allowed us to conclude whether he was cooperating fully or not, with a clear ultimatum to him if he refused to do so. And the reason we approached it in that way is that that's what we agreed in Resolution 1441. This was his final opportunity. He had to disarm unconditionally -- serious consequences would follow if he failed to do so. And this is really the impasse that we have, because some say there should be no ultimatum, no authorization of force in any new U.N. resolution -- instead, more discussion in the event of noncompliance.</p>
        <p>But the truth is that without a credible ultimatum authorizing force in the event of noncompliance, then more discussion is just more delay, with Saddam remaining armed with weapons of mass destruction and continuing a brutal murderous regime in Iraq.</p>
        <p>And this game that he is playing is frankly a game that he has played over the last 12 years. Disarmament never happens, but instead the international community is drawn into some perpetual negotiation, gestures to divide the international community, but never real and concrete cooperation leading to disarmament. And there's not a single person on the Security Council that doubts the fact he is not fully cooperating today. Nobody, even those who disagree with the situation we have outlined, is prepared to say there is full cooperation as 1441 demanded. Not a single interview has taken place outside of Iraq, even though 1441 provided for it. Still no proper production or evidence of the destruction of, for example, just to take one example, the 10,000 liters of anthrax that the inspectors just a week ago said was unaccounted for. And that is why it is so important that the international community at this time gives a strong and unified message. And I have to say that I really believe that hadn't we given that strong message some time ago, Saddam might have realized that the gains had to stop.</p>
        <p>So now we have reached the point of decision, and we make a final appeal for there to be that strong unified message on behalf of the international community that lays down a clear ultimatum to Saddam that authorizes force if he continues to defy the will of the whole of the international community set out in 1441.</p>
        <p>We will do all we can in the short time that remains to make a final round of contacts, to see whether there is a way through this impasse. But we are in the final stages, because after 12 years of failing to disarm him, now is the time when we have to decide.</p>
        <p>Two other points briefly on the documents that we've put before you. The first, as President Aznar was just saying to you a moment ago on the trans-Atlantic alliance, is I think very important. Some of you will have heard me say this before, but let me just repeat it. I believe that Europe and America should stand together on the big issues of the day. I think it is a tragedy when we don't. And that trans-Atlantic alliance is strong, and we need to strengthen it still further.</p>
        <p>And, secondly, we have set out for you that should it come to conflict we make a pledge to the people of Iraq. And as President Bush was just saying to you a moment or two ago, it is the people of Iraq who are the primary victims of Saddam: the thousands of children that die needlessly every year; the people locked up in his prisons or executed simply for showing disagreement with the regime; a country that is potentially prosperous, reduced to poverty; 60 percent of the population reliant on food aid. And what we say is that we will protect Iraq's territorial integrity. . . .</p>
        <p>On the Middle East peace process, I welcome very much the statement President Bush made the other day. I think it's important now. He said he wanted a partner on the Palestinian side. I think the coming appointment of Abu Mazen is so important there. It allows us to take this process forward. The road map gives us the way forward. The appointment of Abu Mazen gives us the right partner to take this forward. And I believe that that will demonstrate -- and it's important to demonstrate in particular at this time that our approach to people in the Middle East, in that troubled region, is indeed even-handed, and all of us will work to make sure that that vision of the Middle East -- two states, Israel confident of its security, a Palestinian state that is viable, comes about and is made reality. Thank you.</p>
        <p>Questions and Answers</p>
        <p>Q. Mr. President, before I ask my question, I just want to nail down one thing so there is no confusion. When you talk about tomorrow being the moment of truth, are you saying that is the . . .</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH -- Is this the question? Are you trying to work in two questions?</p>
        <p>Q. When you say tomorrow is the moment of truth, does that mean tomorrow is the last day that the resolution can be voted up or down, and at the end of the day tomorrow, one way or another, a diplomatic window has closed?</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH -- That's what I'm saying.</p>
        <p>Q. -- Thank you, sir. And now for the question. . . . That being the case, regardless . . .</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH -- That was my answer.</p>
        <p>Q. Regardless of whether the solution goes up or down or gets withdrawn, it seems to me you are going to be facing a moment of truth. Given that, you have already said you don't think there's very much chance Saddam Hussein is going to disarm. And given that you say you don't think there's very much chance he's going to go into exile. Aren't we going to war here?</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH -- Tomorrow is the day that we will determine whether or not diplomacy can work. And we sat and visited about this issue, about how best to spend our time between now and tomorrow. And as Prime Minister Blair said, we will be working the phones, talking to our partners and talking to those who may not clearly understand the objectives. And we'll see how it goes tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Saddam Hussein can leave the country, if he's interested in -- you see, the decision is his to make, and it's been his to make all along on whether or not there's the use of military. He got to decide whether he's going to disarm -- and he didn't. He can decide whether he wants to leave the country. These are his decisions to make, and thus far he has made bad decisions.</p>
        <p>Q. I understand that if tomorrow is the day for taking the final decision, that means that you consider that there's no possible way out through the United Nations, because a majority does not support a war action. I would like to know, Mr. Blair, Mr. Bush, whether in that military offensive you count on many countries, or whether it's going to be the U.K. and the U.S. carrying out the military offensive. I understand from what Mr. Blair has said that you are counting on the U.N. for the reconstruction. Are you going to look for other countries through the United Nations?</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH -- Resolution 1441, which was unanimously approved, that said Saddam Hussein would unconditionally disarm, and if he didn't there would be serious consequences. The United Nations Security Council looked at the issue four and a half months ago and voted unanimously to say: disarm immediately and unconditionally, and if you don't there are going to be serious consequences. The world has spoken, and it did in a unified voice.</p>
        <p>MR. BLAIR -- The issue is very simply this: that we cannot have a situation where what happened through the United Nations having agreed to 1441, having said there would be serious consequences if he doesn't cooperate fully and unconditionally, what we cannot have is a situation where we simply go back to endless discussion.</p>
        <p>Now, we have provided the right diplomatic way through this, which is to lay down a clear ultimatum to Saddam, cooperate or face disarmament by force. That's entirely within the logic, the letter, the spirit of 1441. And that is why all the way through we have tried to provide a diplomatic solution -- after four and a half months since we passed Resolution 1441 -- we're now three months on from the declaration that Saddam made on the 8th of December that not a single person in the international community -- not one believes was an honest declaration of what he has. And yet 1441 says the first step of cooperation was to make an honest declaration.</p>
        <p>So people say, Have we exhausted all the diplomatic avenues? We tried exhausting. But understand from our perspective and from the perspective of the security of the world we cannot simply go back to the Security Council for this discussion to be superseded by that discussion, to be superseded by another discussion. That's what happened for 12 years. That's why he has still got the weapons of mass destruction. We have to come to the point of decision, and that really is what the next period of time is going to be about.</p>
        <p>Q. Can I ask first of all Prime Minister Blair -- you said that you want a second resolution to be put down and voted on. It would be clear. Is that what's going to happen tomorrow under all circumstances? And, either way, also if I may for President Bush, if you don't get that second resolution, what is the future for the United Nations? You talked about Saddam Hussein dividing the world community. Surely he's succeeded.</p>
        <p>MR. BLAIR -- On your last point, I think this is one of the things that is tragic about this situation, that Saddam plays these games, and we carry on allowing him to play them. Now, we will do in the next period of time, in respect to the resolution, what we believe to be in the interests of the U.N.</p>
        <p>But I want to say why I think it is so important that even now at this late stage we try to get the United Nations to be the root of resolving this, because the threat is there, and everyone accepts it. The threat of weapons of mass destruction, the threat of weapons of mass destruction in the hands of terrorists who will cause maximum damage to our people. Everybody accepts the disarmament of Saddam has to happen. Everybody accepts that he was supposed to cooperate fully with the inspectors. Everybody accepts that he is not doing so. So whatever the tactics within the U.N. -- and that's something we can decide -- whatever those tactics, the key point of principle is this: that when we came together last November and laid down Resolution 1441, now is the moment when we decide whether we meant it and it was his final opportunity to disarm or face serious consequences; or whether, alternatively, we are simply going to drag out the diplomatic process forever. And that's why I say it's a point for decision.</p>
        <p>Q. Voted or not?</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH -- I was the guy that said they ought to vote. And one country voted -- showed their cards, I believe -- it's an old Texas expression -- show your cards, when you're playing poker? France showed their cards. After I said what they said, they said they are going to veto anything that held Saddam to account. So cards have been played. And we just have to take an assessment after tomorrow to determine what that card meant.</p>
        <p>Let me say something about the U.N. It's a very important organization. That's why I went there on Sept. 12, 2002, to give the speech, the speech that called the U.N. into account -- that said if you are going to pass resolutions, let's make sure your words mean something, as I understand the wars of the 21th century are going to require incredible international cooperation. We are going to cooperate to cut off the money of the terrorists and the ability for nations' dictators who have weapons of mass destruction to provide training and perhaps weapons to terrorist organizations. We need to cooperate -- and we are. Our countries up here are cooperating incredibly well, and the U.N. must mean something.</p>
        <p>Remember Rwanda or Kosovo -- the U.N. didn't do its job. And we hope tomorrow the U.N. will do its job. If not, all of us need to step back and try to figure out how to make the U.N. work better as we head into the 21st century. Perhaps one way will be if we use military force in the post-Saddam Iraq the U.N. will definitely need to have a role. And that way it can get -- begin to get its legs -- legs of responsibility back. But it's important for the U.N. to be able to function well if we are going to keep the peace. And I will work hard to see to it that at least from our perspective that the U.N. is able to be a responsible body, and when it says something it means it for the sake of peace and for the sake of the security -- for the capacity to win the war, the first war of the 21st century, which is the war against terrorism and weapons of mass destruction in the hands of dictators.</p>
        <p>THREATS AND RESPONSES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
