<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In America; The Hate Virus</title>
    <meta content="10HERB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1038110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Harlem (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muhammad, Khalid Abdul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbert, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bob Herbert</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4DC1F3BF933A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In America; The Hate Virus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB HERBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herbert, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Herbert Op-Ed column, commenting onMillion Youth March in Harlem planned for September 5, notes it is led by Khalid Abdul Muhammad, avowed anti-Semite; urges prominent African-American leaders to be more vocal in condemning Muhammad's rhetoric, making clear that his type of leadership is virus that is potentially as debilitating to black community as AIDS (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The purpose of the march, according to its organizers, is to bring black and Latino youngsters from all over the city and all around the country to Harlem to loudly protest such pervasive evils as police brutality, job discrimination and substandard educational opportunities.</p>
        <p>A worthy goal. But to pull this off safely and successfully, it would help if you had leaders as conscientious and disciplined as, say, Martin Luther King, Roy Wilkins, Whitney Young, John Lewis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The purpose of the march, according to its organizers, is to bring black and Latino youngsters from all over the city and all around the country to Harlem to loudly protest such pervasive evils as police brutality, job discrimination and substandard educational opportunities.</p>
        <p>A worthy goal. But to pull this off safely and successfully, it would help if you had leaders as conscientious and disciplined as, say, Martin Luther King, Roy Wilkins, Whitney Young, John Lewis.</p>
        <p>But those are names from a brave and glorious past. Times have changed. Once there was jazz and blues. Now there is gangsta rap. And the so-called Million Youth March scheduled for Sept. 5 is being led by one Khalid Abdul Muhammad.</p>
        <p>''The so-called Jew claims that there were six million in Nazi Germany. I am here today to tell you that there is absolutely no evidence, no proof. There is absolutely no evidence to substantiate, to prove that six million so-called Jews lost their lives in Nazi Germany.''</p>
        <p>That was Mr. Muhammad speaking at San Francisco State University on May 21, 1997.</p>
        <p>Same speech: ''Don't let no hooked-nose, bagel-eating, lox-eating, perpetrating-a-fraud so-called Jew who just crawled out of the ghettoes of Europe just a few days ago . . . ''</p>
        <p>Same speech: ''Who's pimping the world? The hairy hands of the Zionist in the world.''</p>
        <p>Different speech, this one on the weekend before the Million Man March in Washington in October 1995: ''Look at it, so-called Jew. Look at it, imposter Jew. Somebody must call you what you are. Somebody must look you in your cold lying blue eyes and pull the cover off of you today. I don't give a damn about you and I will give you hell from the cradle to the grave.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Muhammad, a former Nation of Islam official, has also made sickening comments about rabbis and circumcision and was disciplined by Louis Farrakhan after making a speech in which he referred to Jews as ''bloodsuckers.''</p>
        <p>There is a big controversy now over Mr. Muhammad's desire to hold his march, which would move through the heart of Harlem, along the 37 blocks of Malcolm X Boulevard between 147th Street and Central Park North. Nearly everyone agrees that no matter how repellent his views, Mr. Muhammad has a First Amendment right to march, but the exact time and place are subject to reasonable regulation by the city.</p>
        <p>At the moment, the city is being led by one Rudolph Giuliani. For him, this is an easy call. We are headed for a showdown.</p>
        <p>''From my point of view,'' said the Mayor, ''this is a hate march.''</p>
        <p>The city has refused to grant Mr. Muhammad and his fellow organizers a permit for a march on Malcolm X Boulevard. Officials have offered instead to authorize a gathering at a different site, perhaps Van Cortlandt Park in the Bronx or Randalls Island.</p>
        <p>The response from a colleague of Mr. Muhammad was as follows: ''The Constitution does not say that Mayor Adolph Giuliani can determine the time and place of the execution of our free speech and assembly.''</p>
        <p>The organizers insist the march will go on as planned.</p>
        <p>So what happens next?</p>
        <p>It would be helpful if some prominent African-American leaders, faced with the grotesque reality of a virulent anti-Semite playing Pied Piper to the nation's black children, would stand up and say enough is enough. This is wrong. This is not what our community stands for, and it is not a message that we will allow to be fed to our young.</p>
        <p>Representative Charles Rangel, no ally of Mayor Giuliani, has denounced Mr. Muhammad, saying, ''We don't need anybody preaching hatred in Harlem.'' A few other black officials have issued more or less muffled statements about not condoning Mr. Muhammad's rhetoric.</p>
        <p>More voices need to be heard, and they need to be louder and more forceful. It needs to be made clear that Mr. Muhammad's type of leadership is a virus that is potentially as debilitating to the black community as H.I.V.</p>
        <p>It would also be helpful if public officials more skilled at negotiating than Mr. Giuliani were allowed to play significant roles in resolving the problem of when and where Mr. Muhammad is allowed to have his say.</p>
        <p>William Safire is on vacation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William Safire is on vacation.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
