<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knoblauch Loves It, Weird Year and All</title>
    <meta content="Y10CURR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1038127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knoblauch, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7DA1F3BF933A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knoblauch Loves It, Weird Year and All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch says playing for New York Yankees is 'most positive experience' he has had in baseball; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch was doing high-step running exercises in front of the first-base dugout with the rest of the Yankees two hours before yesterday's game. All the Yankees needed were tires strewn across the grass to make the drill look even more animated. Legs churned, arms pumped, faces contorted.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, Knoblauch abandoned the routine and zigged and zagged between and around his teammates like a miniature Jerry Rice. It was a trivial display, but it looked natural for Knoblauch to behave expressively, and it made his teammates chuckle. That meant it was a successful venture for Knoblauch. He looked comfortable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch was doing high-step running exercises in front of the first-base dugout with the rest of the Yankees two hours before yesterday's game. All the Yankees needed were tires strewn across the grass to make the drill look even more animated. Legs churned, arms pumped, faces contorted.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, Knoblauch abandoned the routine and zigged and zagged between and around his teammates like a miniature Jerry Rice. It was a trivial display, but it looked natural for Knoblauch to behave expressively, and it made his teammates chuckle. That meant it was a successful venture for Knoblauch. He looked comfortable.</p>
        <p>''I've said it before, and I'll say it again, this is the most positive experience I've had in baseball and in my baseball life,'' Knoblauch said. ''Off the field, everything.''</p>
        <p>Considering that Knoblauch won a World Series championship with the Twins as a rookie in 1991 and that his .254 average this season is a whopping 50 points lower than the career average he entered the season with, it was an intriguing comment. The Yankees have not had one post-season game yet and Knoblauch has already called it the most positive experience of his eight-year career. It sounds like a person who adores New York, or one who really wants everyone to believe he does.</p>
        <p>The always intense Knoblauch loosened up considerably as he recounted walking through Manhattan recently and being jolted when a truck driver abruptly stopped a few feet away from him. The trucker shouted, ''Hey, Chuckie,'' waved his fist, told the second baseman the Yankees ruled, and rumbled away.</p>
        <p>''New York is just different from any other city,'' Knoblauch said. ''The people, the city, everything is great.''</p>
        <p>While it has been thrilling for Knoblauch to be the leadoff man for a team that is barreling toward the major league record for regular-season victories, perplexing moments have collided with positive moments. From the inexplicable throwing troubles he has endured to the subpar batting average to the dwindling on-base percentage to the remarkable splurge of homers that exceeds what Mark McGwire has done since the All-Star Game break, this season has also been a soap opera of sorts for Knoblauch.</p>
        <p>Even though Knoblauch has socked 11 homers since July 10, two more than McGwire in the same period, it has puzzled Manager Joe Torre. Torre is not sure how to feel about Knoblauch's swinging at the high pitches he is being fed.</p>
        <p>''He's hit more than McGwire since the All-Star break, hasn't he? It's weird,'' Torre said. ''They have the cameras in the wrong place. Again, I'm not sure if it's good or bad, because he's a get-on-base guy. Turns out he's helped us win games in other ways, with the home runs.''</p>
        <p>Knoblauch helped yesterday by reaching base in three of four at-bats, including a single in the sixth inning to begin a three-run rally as the Yankees edged the Royals, 5-4. Still, the numbers that matter most are 84-29. That is the Yankees' record, and why Knoblauch said: ''I want to play here. I haven't thought any differently since I was traded. I can't say how much I enjoy being a Yankee.''</p>
        <p>General Manager Brian Cashman should clip Knoblauch's words out of the paper and save them as potential bargaining tools. Because Knoblauch was traded in the middle of a five-year, $30 million contract, he can demand a trade within 15 days after the conclusion of the World Series. Knoblauch, who will have three years and $18 million remaining on the deal after the season, does not seem likely to do that. But Alan and Randy Hendricks, his agents, would surely like a contract extension.</p>
        <p>When those discussions happen, Cashman should politely remind the agents that Knoblauch had a good, not a great, year. Cashman should also tell them that Knoblauch's $6 million salary would be more than anyone on the roster who has a guaranteed contract for 1999 except for Paul O'Neill. The general manager should say $6 million is enough. For now, forget an extension.</p>
        <p>''The only discussion we had was early and how he doesn't want to go anywhere and we don't want him to go anywhere, so let's not worry about it,'' Cashman said. ''I'm not worried about it.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees traded pitcher Eric Milton and three minor leaguers for Knoblauch, and that is another reason they do not want to lose the  30-year-old.</p>
        <p>''It's a good relationship,'' Knoblauch said. ''Hopefully, there won't be a problem. I don't foresee any as long as they want me to play here.''</p>
        <p>But Knoblauch halted his ''I Love New York'' campaign when asked what he would do if the Yankees sought to honor his current contract and did not offer him a dollar over $18 million, which is quite plausible and quite fair.</p>
        <p>''It's something I haven't even thought about,'' Knoblauch said. ''It's hard for me to answer.''</p>
        <p>It should not be hard. Not for someone who loves New York so much.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
