<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federal Judge on Trial in a Racketeering Case</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="323856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COURTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JUDGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BISHOP, KATHERINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AGUILAR, ROBERT P (JUDGE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THAM, MICHAEL RUDY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHAPMAN, ABE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DE1F3EF935A35751C0A966958260" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federal Judge on Trial in a Racketeering Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE BISHOP, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BISHOP, KATHERINE</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Feb. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Jury selection began here today in the trial of the first Federal judge charged with violating the Federal racketeering statute through his involvement with two convicted felons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Jury selection began here today in the trial of the first Federal judge charged with violating the Federal racketeering statute through his involvement with two convicted felons.</p>
        <p>Jury selection began here today in the trial of the first Federal judge charged with violating the Federal racketeering statute through his involvement with two convicted felons.</p>
        <p>In an eight-count indictment handed down last June, the judge, Robert P. Aguilar, who presides over the Federal District Court in San Jose, was charged with conducting the affairs of his office through a pattern of racketeering activity by giving illegal assistance to Michael Rudy Tham, a former official of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, and Abe Chapman, a convicted narcotics trafficker. Both Mr. Tham and Mr. Chapman are also charged in the case.</p>
        <p>All three defendants are charged with conspiracy and obstruction of justice. The indictment said Judge Aguilar improperly interceded with another Federal judge on behalf of Mr. Tham, who was seeking to overturn an embezzlement conviction, and for informing Mr. Chapman of Government wiretaps on his telephone and surveillance of his activities.</p>
        <p>Judge Aguilar is also charged with unlawful disclosure of the wiretaps and with lying to agents of the Federal Bureau of Investigation about his activities on behalf of the two men.</p>
        <p>Defense Motion Denied</p>
        <p>Today, before jury selection began, Judge Louis C. Bechtle of the Eastern District of Pennsylvania, who is specially assigned to the case, denied without comment a main defense motion seeking to exclude evidence from 1,500 tapes gathered in wiretaps on the office and home telephones of Judge Aguilar and his co-defendants.</p>
        <p>Judge Aguilar, 58 years old, was appointed to the bench by President Jimmy Carter in 1980. He is the fourth sitting Federal judge to be indicted in the last 10 years. The others are Harry Claiborne of Nevada, Alcee Hastings of Florida and Walter Nixon of Mississippi. All three were impeached and removed from office by Congress, although Judge Hastings was acquitted of the criminal charge against him.</p>
        <p>Judge Aguilar is the first Federal judge to be charged under the Racketeer Influenced Corrupt Organizations Act, which is aimed at fighting organized crime. If convicted, he could receive up to 55 years in prison and $2 million in fines. He could also face impeachment and removal from office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tham and Mr. Chapman, who are named in only two of the indictment's eight counts, face possible sentences of 10 years in prison and $500,000 in fines each if convicted.</p>
        <p>Two-Month Trial Likely</p>
        <p>All three defendants have pleaded not guilty to the charges. The case is being prosecuted by the Justice Department's public integrity section, with William A. Keefer and Ralph Drury Martin as lead counsel. The trial is expected to last two months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tham, 66, is serving a five-year prison sentence for violating probation. He was convicted in 1980 of embezzling teamster funds to entertain Aladena T. Frantianno, a self-described Mafia killer who later turned Government informer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chapman, 83, who is related by marriage to Judge Aguilar, lives in Pittsburg, Calif., 35 miles east of here.</p>
        <p>In addition to the charges involving his co-defendants, Judge Aguilar is charged with racketeering in helping Vera L. Hoff, his former legal secretary who was a Federal fugitive, to remain in hiding in Mexico. He is also charged with trying to influence another judge on behalf of a former Nevada casino owner indicted on charges of fraud.</p>
        <p>In papers filed with the court last week summarizing their case, Government prosecutors said Judge Aguilar maintained clandestine contact with Mrs. Hoff after she and her husband fled to Mexico when she was convicted of tax evasion.</p>
        <p>Testimony From Ex-Fugitive</p>
        <p>The court papers said the judge visited Mrs. Hoff and her husband in Acapulco, Mexico, in 1982. Mrs. Hoff, who was arrested last year, is known to have testified before the grand jury in Judge Aguilar's case.</p>
        <p>The papers also said Judge Aguilar tried to intercede improperly with the trial judge on behalf of a former client, Ronald V. Cloud, in Mr. Cloud's trial in 1987. Mr. Cloud, a multimillionaire plumbing contractor who lost his license to operate the Cal-Neva Lodge after the authorities said the casino's slot machines were rigged, was subsequently convicted of bank fraud in the sale of the casino.</p>
        <p>The case grew out of an investigation of Angelo T. Commito, who was identified in a 1981 Government report as a known associate of organized crime leaders. Wiretaps of Mr. Commito's telephone disclosed information that was used to obtain applications for taps in 1987 and 1988 on the phones of Mr. Tham, Mr. Chapman and eventually Judge Aguilar. But, because another judge ruled that the wiretap in Mr. Commito's case was improperly obtained, defense lawyers argued that the wiretaps in Judge Aguilar's case were tainted. Judge Bechtle's ruling today allows the use of those wiretaps.</p>
        <p>While lawyers now decline to comment, citing Judge Bechtle's order not to discuss the case, lawyers representing Judge Aguilar have previously argued that before the investigation Judge Aguilar did not know that Mr. Chapman was a convicted felon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chapman, who is represented by Stephen Krimel, a lawyer from San Diego, served a total of 33 years in Federal prison on four convictions for violations of Federal narcotics laws, including heroin trafficking, dating from 1930. He pleaded guilty to attempted bribery of a public official in 1975 and received a six-month suspended sentence. In 1984 he pleaded guilty to attempted fraud of a local culinary union's pension and welfare fund. The plea was withdrawn, and he was acquitted in Federal District Court here last February.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
