<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One, by One, by One, Manhattan Marches On</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="732813"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MANHATTAN COLLEGE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRASCHILLA, FRAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIS, GEORGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2D81138F931A15751C1A962958260" item-length="530" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One, by One, by One, Manhattan Marches On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE WILLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILLIS, GEORGE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coach Fran Fraschilla of Manhattan has a motto his players are sold on. "We want to start a one-game winning streak with every game," he said. "That's all we ever care about."</p>
        <p>That motto has significance these days, a method of keeping the Jaspers focused during a seven-game winning streak that is building optimism and confidence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Coach Fran Fraschilla of Manhattan has a motto his players are sold on. "We want to start a one-game winning streak with every game," he said. "That's all we ever care about."</p>
        <p>That motto has significance these days, a method of keeping the Jaspers focused during a seven-game winning streak that is building optimism and confidence.</p>
        <p>With a victory over Wright State at 7:30 tonight at Draddy Gymnasium, Manhattan can match its best start since the 1982-83 team opened 8-0. It would also mark the school's 1,000th victory over all.</p>
        <p>"As players, we talk about the winning streak a little bit," said Jamal Marshall, the only contributing senior on a team stocked with eight sophomores and freshmen. "But we try to keep our focus and do what Coach Frasch wants us to do and that's to approach each game on its own."</p>
        <p>That task could be more difficult than usual tonight. Looming on Tuesday is a showdown with St. John's in the first round of the Chemical Bank ECAC Holiday Festival at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Publicists for the tournament already are calling it the battle for New York. Even though that may be a bit extreme, the Jaspers would certainly like to make a statement at the Red Storm's expense.</p>
        <p>"It's the type of game you want to play in if you're a player or coach," Fraschilla said. "To play in Madison Square Garden in front of a great crowd against St. John's is what a college basketball player should live for."</p>
        <p>The Jaspers' impressive start is the product of several factors: the perimeter shooting of the junior guard Ted Ellis, who has made 14 of 32 from the 3-point stripe and averaged 13 points a game; the rapid maturation of the freshman forward Heshimu Evans of the Bronx, who leads the team in scoring at 14.6 points a game, and a contributing bench that goes nine players deep.</p>
        <p>But Manhattan's best asset is its athleticism, especially on defense where the Jaspers have limited opponents to 35.1 percent shooting from the field.</p>
        <p>"We've got more quickness and athletic guys that can get in your face," said Marshall, who is averaging 9.7 points and 6.3 rebounds a game. "Our defense has been solid."</p>
        <p>Fraschilla, who guided the Jaspers to the National Collegiate Athletic Association Tournament in 1993 and the National Invitation Tournament last season, once thought his team's youthfulness would be a drawback, but now he welcomes his players' unspoiled exuberance.</p>
        <p>"I don't think they realize how good they can be," he said. "These young guys have bought into playing hard all the time and they do a good job of it."</p>
        <p>St. John's (5-0) will also be in action tonight when it entertains Fordham (1-5) at 8 P.M. at Alumni Hall. It will be the Red Storm's first game since an exhibition outing against Marathon Oil on Dec. 10.</p>
        <p>The Red Storm will be without the senior guard Derek Brown and the junior forward Fred Lyson for the remainder of the season. The two have not played this season and will sit out the year as medical red shirts.</p>
        <p>Brown is recovering from a torn hamstring and Lyson remains sidelined by a torn abdominal muscle. St. John's will be seeking its 1,500th victory tonight, joining North Carolina, Kentucky and Kansas.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
