<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coffee Prices Stage a Rally On Plan by Some Producers</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="732729"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="FUTURES MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUTURES TRADING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COFFEE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DC1138F931A15751C1A962958260" item-length="335" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coffee Prices Stage a Rally On Plan by Some Producers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Financial turmoil in Mexico and a round of speculative dollar buying against European currencies lifted the dollar higher yesterday.</p>
        <p>The dollar's gains were seen by analysts as temporary, coming in thin, pre-holiday trading.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Financial turmoil in Mexico and a round of speculative dollar buying against European currencies lifted the dollar higher yesterday.</p>
        <p>The dollar's gains were seen by analysts as temporary, coming in thin, pre-holiday trading.</p>
        <p>A day after the peso was devalued, Mexico's stock market fell sharply, with the Bolsa index down 3.1 percent after trading as low as 11.7 percent off. The peso was devalued by about 15 percent against the dollar on Tuesday in a move to calm markets shaken by renewed unrest in Chiapas state.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the peso fell modestly. In late New York trading, the dollar bought 3.9870 pesos, compared with 3.9750 pesos on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The decline in Mexican stocks prompted some United States money managers to pull out of investments in Latin American markets, some analysts said. That heightened currency-market expectations of a rally in United States securities if those funds are invested in United States equities, raising demand for dollars needed to buy them.</p>
        <p>But many currency dealers were skeptical about whether Mexico's financial turmoil would have much long-term effect on United States markets and the dollar.</p>
        <p>"There is going to be buying of U.S. assets as people liquidate Mexican holdings," said Paul Farrell, head trader at the Chase Manhattan Bank. "But it isn't real transactions yet. We're seeing the psychological impact."</p>
        <p>Market participants said trading was quiet for the first half of the day, with volume thinning as big banks and brokerage firms closed their books for the year and dealers left for the holidays.</p>
        <p>But around noon, said Callum Henderson, senior analyst at MMS International, several short-term investment funds sold large amounts of British pounds, first buying German marks and then selling those for dollars, in a speculative effort to push the dollar higher.</p>
        <p>"It became a technical rally," Mr. Farrell said.</p>
        <p>With volume extremely light, a small number of trades were able to cause a fairly significant jump in exchange rates.  FUTURES MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
