<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Trouble in Prince William Sound</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="630789"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TANKERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALMON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXXON VALDEZ (TANKER)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PRINCE WILLIAM SOUND (ALASKA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL ACCOUNTING OFFICE (GAO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BABBITT, BRUCE (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tankers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D7173BF936A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="473" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Trouble in Prince William Sound</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is an anxious time for Alaskans who live and work on Prince William Sound, scene of the Exxon Valdez oil spill four years ago.</p>
        <p>The Government Accounting Office has found blatant mismanagement of the fund that is supposed to restore and protect the Prince William habitat. In addition, this year's salmon harvest is the smallest in 20 years, raising fears that damage to the sound might be far worse than was previously thought.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is an anxious time for Alaskans who live and work on Prince William Sound, scene of the Exxon Valdez oil spill four years ago.</p>
        <p>The Government Accounting Office has found blatant mismanagement of the fund that is supposed to restore and protect the Prince William habitat. In addition, this year's salmon harvest is the smallest in 20 years, raising fears that damage to the sound might be far worse than was previously thought.</p>
        <p>Even as the report appeared, local fishermen, frustrated as much by official bungling as by the dwindling harvest, blockaded the Valdez Narrows, preventing tankers from reaching the Alaska pipeline.</p>
        <p>All this poses a challenge for Secretary of Interior Bruce Babbitt. He needs to ride herd on the restoration fund. And his department must also help determine whether this year's scarcity of fish is a natural development or a symptom of a deeper sickness in the sound.</p>
        <p>In 1989 the supertanker Exxon Valdez ran aground, spilling 11 million gallons of crude and ravaging 1,200 miles of shoreline -- the worst spill in U.S. history.</p>
        <p>Two years later the courts approved a settlement between Exxon, the Federal Government and the State of Alaska to resolve civil and criminal claims. Under the civil settlement, Exxon agreed to pay $900 million in 11 annual payments -- a miserly sum considering the extent of the damage, but one that seemed preferable to a lengthy court battle. The money was to be administered by a trustee council that would restore the sound and protect the area. One method is purchasing fish and animal habitats and placing them off limits to development.</p>
        <p>It hasn't worked out that way. The money collected from Exxon through 1992 was used primarily to reimburse state and Federal agencies -- as well as Exxon -- for expenses related to the spill. The G.A.O. report documents sweetheart deals, shabby accounting and dubious studies. The report noted that a land acquisition plan has yet to be approved.</p>
        <p>Prince William Sound is one of Alaska's most important fisheries. But this year's run of pink salmon was frighteningly small. Forecasters expected a harvest of more than 25 million fish; with the season nearly over, only about 4 million have been taken.</p>
        <p>Some fishermen say Prince William Sound is becoming a "dead zone" because of the spill. Exxon counters that fishing in the years just after the spill was good, and that therefore the shortage of salmon can't be related to the spill. The issue might well be scientifically complex. But bounteous harvests in other Alaska fisheries suggest that Prince William Sound has a unique problem.</p>
        <p>Secretary Babbitt has spurred the trustees to acquire more land, but he'll have to keep after them. He can be of further help by putting the best scientific minds he can find to work on what's happening to the fish.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
