<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge's Order Bars Walkout On Amtrak</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="630860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAILROADS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIKES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMTRAK (NATIONAL RAILROAD PASSENGER CORP)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HENNEBERGER, MELINDA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DF143FF936A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge's Order Bars Walkout On Amtrak</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA HENNEBERGER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HENNEBERGER, MELINDA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Federal judge signed a temporary restraining order yesterday that prevented today's rush hour from going nowhere on rail lines tied to Amtrak.</p>
        <p>The order, from Federal District Judge Stanley Harris in Washington, came near the end of a day that rail officials spent scrambling to make sure they were prepared for a threatened walkout that would have affected 62,000 riders on Amtrak throughout the country, as well as commuters on Metro North and the Long Island Rail Road.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Federal judge signed a temporary restraining order yesterday that prevented today's rush hour from going nowhere on rail lines tied to Amtrak.</p>
        <p>The order, from Federal District Judge Stanley Harris in Washington, came near the end of a day that rail officials spent scrambling to make sure they were prepared for a threatened walkout that would have affected 62,000 riders on Amtrak throughout the country, as well as commuters on Metro North and the Long Island Rail Road.</p>
        <p>Many commuters seemed unaware that their lives could be affected by a labor dispute at a Los Angeles commuter rail maintenance yard. Commuters Unaware</p>
        <p>At Penn Station in Manhattan, which is owned by Amtrak and would be closed in the event of a strike by the United Transportation Union, a college student en route to Philadelphia said she had not heard anything about it.</p>
        <p>"I've been on Martha's Vineyard where all the news is about the President," said Katharine Grandfield, who will be a sophomore this fall at Wesleyan College.</p>
        <p>Thomas Finn, a redcap who has worked for Amtrak since 1974, said he has been through other strikes and was relatively unconcerned about the prospect of another one.</p>
        <p>"Nobody likes to lose money these days, but physically it would be nice to have a couple of weeks off," he said. Scrambling for Alternatives</p>
        <p>John Sullivan, an attorney for the United Transportation Union, which represents 2,350 conductors nationwide, told Reuters that the union would honor the ruling although it would continue to argue the jobs issue. In the ruling, Judge Harris said a hearing on Amtrak's request for a preliminary injunction would be scheduled later.</p>
        <p>As Amtrak officials went to court, officials of the Long Island Rail Road drew up plans for alternative routes for New York commuters.</p>
        <p>"We won't be able to run further than Queens, so they'd have to transfer from there to the subway trains" to get to Manhattan, said a spokeswoman for the railroad, Susan McGowan.</p>
        <p>And a spokesman for Metro North, Dan Brucker, said officials there were prepared to go to court themselves if the judge in Washington did not sign the temporary restraining order. A walkout would have affected 45,000 customers on Metro North's New Haven line because it shares a train yard there with Amtrak and could have shut down Metro North's entire operation if its workers joined the strike in solidarity with union members who work for Amtrak.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
