<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nassau Urges Courts to Sentence Graffiti Vandals to Cleanup Jobs</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="630872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VANDALISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SENTENCES (CRIMINAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRAFFITI</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NASSAU COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DILLON, DENIS E (DIST ATTY)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vandalism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DD173EF936A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nassau Urges Courts to Sentence Graffiti Vandals to Cleanup Jobs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>MINEOLA, L.I., Aug. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It winds its way along the south wall of the Long Island Rail Road embankment at Sunrise Highway in Bellmore, a serpentine splash of letters in blue, red, black and green spelling out "ELF," "BURNT," "ABONE" and other code names, graffiti signatures all painted by teen-agers.</p>
        <p>Many of the vandals carry cameras, snapping photos of their work and placing them in scrapbooks that they take to school to show their friends.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It winds its way along the south wall of the Long Island Rail Road embankment at Sunrise Highway in Bellmore, a serpentine splash of letters in blue, red, black and green spelling out "ELF," "BURNT," "ABONE" and other code names, graffiti signatures all painted by teen-agers.</p>
        <p>Many of the vandals carry cameras, snapping photos of their work and placing them in scrapbooks that they take to school to show their friends.</p>
        <p>But under a plan proposed today by the Nassau County District Attorney, these youths could wind up holding brooms and sponges instead of spray cans.</p>
        <p>The District Attorney, Denis Dillon, and County Executive Thomas S. Gulotta said at a news conference that they would ask the courts to impose sentences of community service on those convicted of petty offenses like painting graffiti. Hard Work and a Fine</p>
        <p>Under the plan, judges could order defendants convicted of such offenses to perform 3 to 10 days of labor, like cleaning up litter and removing graffiti. And the defendants would be required to pay a $50 registration fee to cover county administrative costs.</p>
        <p>"Graffiti is more than just a petty offense," said Mr. Gulotta. "It costs our taxpayers over $1 million a year in cleanup costs. When the person committing the act of graffiti is forced to use their own labor to rectify the act they have created, maybe they will think twice before committing the act again."</p>
        <p>In June, the County Board of Supervisors passed a law doubling the maximum fine for painting graffiti to $1,000 and making parents liable for damages or cleanup costs of up to $5,000. In addition, store owners who sell spray paint are required to lock the cans in display cases.</p>
        <p>The police said that 773 cases of criminal mischief were reported in the county last year. "The bulk of them were graffiti cases," said Ed Grilli, a spokesman for Mr. Dillon. And the police report the number of cases is on the rise.</p>
        <p>"The graffiti that we are seeing out here is very different than the graffiti that we were seeing in the city," said Gary Hudes, past president and legislative counsel to the Bellmore Chamber of Commerce. "It is not the tastefully color-coordinated artistic jobs that you would see and say, 'That kid has some artistic talent.' What we are seeing is blatant destruction and vandalism. There is no talent, they are just putting their mark on something."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hudes said he and other members of the Nassau Chamber of Commerce have noticed a sharp increase over the last year in the amount of graffiti in Nassau. "Two out of 5 buildings and 5 out of 10 phone booths in the county have had or now have graffiti," he said. "Store owners spent thousands of dollars last year cleaning their buildings."</p>
        <p>The latest target for graffiti vandals is fences, Mr Hudes said. "These kids come along when the fence is brand-new, and they do the whole fence," he said. "Within minutes, your investment of $3,000 to $5,000 is gone."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
