<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fur-Import Ban Seen as Threat in New York</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="59" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="654166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HUNTING AND TRAPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRUELTY TO ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEAVERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RACCOONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSKRATS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COYOTES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOLVES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BADGERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HUNTING AND TRAPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRUELTY TO ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEAVERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RACCOONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSKRATS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COYOTES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOLVES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BADGERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABER, HAROLD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABER, HAROLD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D81430F936A35751C1A965958260" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fur-Import Ban Seen as Threat in New York</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HAROLD FABER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABER, HAROLD</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Dec. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The beaver, New York's state mammal, has become the focus of an international trade controversy.</p>
        <p>The dispute centers on the use of leghold traps, the most common and efficient way of trapping beavers and other fur-bearing animals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The beaver, New York's state mammal, has become the focus of an international trade controversy.</p>
        <p>The dispute centers on the use of leghold traps, the most common and efficient way of trapping beavers and other fur-bearing animals.</p>
        <p>While animal-rights groups say the traps are inhumane, state wildlife officials defend their use in efforts to control an expanding population of beavers, which can cause considerable damage in rural areas.</p>
        <p>The European Community has adopted a regulation barring imports of furs from any country where animals are caught by the traps, which use steel jaws to grasp animals by their limbs. Exports to Europe</p>
        <p>Several states, including New Jersey, have banned the traps, but they are still widely used in New York, where 70 percent of the pelts obtained by trapping are exported to Europe.</p>
        <p>Beginning in 1995, any country that exports fur from beavers and 12 other species to Europe must either ban leghold traps or adopt international humane trapping standards, which are being written with the participation of New York officials.</p>
        <p>Besides beaver, the most popular of the furs, the regulation covers raccoon, muskrat, river otter, coyote, fisher, American marten, bobcat, lynx, ermine, wolf, Russian sable and badger.</p>
        <p>With the beaver population steadily rising in New York and trapping in decline, state conservation officials say the loss of the European market could have serious consequences for wildlife-management programs in New York and other states.</p>
        <p>By cutting down trees to dam streams, beavers cause floods that cost farmers, landowners and highway departments in New York more than $2 million a year in corrective measures, according to the Conservation Department.</p>
        <p>If beavers proliferate even more because of the loss of the European market, the department estimates that the damage could rise to $9 million a year. 'A Significant Impact'</p>
        <p>"This will have a significant impact on the public," said Gordon Bacheller, leader of the Furbearer Project of the Bureau of Wildlife in the State Department of Environmental Conservation. The department regulates trapping, hunting and fishing in the state.</p>
        <p>In 1975, biologists counted 3,200 beaver colonies in New York, each with an estimated four animals, for a population of about 13,000. By 1990, the population had more than quintupled, to 68,000 in 17,000 colonies.</p>
        <p>If the European market is lost, the number of colonies may rise to 46,000 with a beaver population of about 184,000 by 2000, the wildlife biologists say.</p>
        <p>"Once the beaver population triples, they will show up in places they have never been before and there will be a lot of unhappy people," Mr. Bacheller said.</p>
        <p>Last year, his department received 3,000 complaints about beavers, up from 2,600 in 1990 and 700 in 1975.</p>
        <p>As the beaver population is rising, Mr. Bacheller said, trapping is falling. For 1992-93, he said, 7,559 trapping licenses were issued in the state, down from 16,050 in 1989-90; and 13,542 beaver were trapped, down from 15,982 in 1991-92. Pelt Prices Fall</p>
        <p>In 1988-89, the average price paid to a trapper for a beaver pelt was $25. By 1992-93, Mr. Bacheller said, the average price was under $10.</p>
        <p>With the opening of a new trapping season this year, on Nov. 27 in southern New York, Willard Smith, president of the State Trappers Association, said pelts were bringing $3 to $30, depending on their size and quality, about the same as last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith, who lives in Napanoch, said he was going out to trap despite the low price.</p>
        <p>"Most of us do it for the sport," he said.</p>
        <p>An international committee, to which Mr. Bacheller belongs, is drafting standards to meet the European Community's requirement. It will meet in Ottawa in February to consider its recommendations, which then must be adopted by the European Community and the trapping nations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
