<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lingering Federal Shutdown Tearing at Threads of Safety Net</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="818736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LABOR DEPARTMENT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINES, FRANCIS X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEEDF1239F93BA15751C1A963958260" item-length="1020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lingering Federal Shutdown Tearing at Threads of Safety Net</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLINES, FRANCIS X</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beyond the Vermeers, there wait the garment workers.</p>
        <p>While much of the nation looks upon the partial shutdown of the Federal Government as a vague puzzle best measured by the closing and reopening of tourist exhibits like the Vermeer show, the effects of the budget standoff are gradually reaching across the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beyond the Vermeers, there wait the garment workers.</p>
        <p>While much of the nation looks upon the partial shutdown of the Federal Government as a vague puzzle best measured by the closing and reopening of tourist exhibits like the Vermeer show, the effects of the budget standoff are gradually reaching across the country.</p>
        <p>For example, aggrieved workers in the garment industry, and other areas with regular complaints of substandard wages, are being ignored by furloughed investigators from the Department of Labor.</p>
        <p>With almost 13,000 Labor Department workers barred from labor, the backlog affecting civilians through the agency's wage-and-hour division includes 980 enforcement cases placed on hold during the shutdown. Even complaints investigated earlier and adjudged legitimate have been frozen, with 5,800 workers in the private sector told that they will have to wait upon a political  denouement in Washington for $3.25 million due them in back pay.</p>
        <p>"Federal workers very much feel like hostages," said Nancy Coffey, a spokeswoman for the department, explaining the sense of demoralization that comes to Federal employees who would rather work than suffer further complaints  from cynics about feckless bureaucrats. "The frustration is that people don't understand what the workers really do and how badly needed it can be when, for example, your pension plan is being ripped off and no one's around to investigate it."</p>
        <p>Here at the heart of the Federal lockout, the effects of the budget fight between the Congress and the White House reach down to the predicament suffered  by Adam Schneiberg, a business student searching the job market. He needs to get his passport renewed to get to London next Tuesday for a job interview, but he was told that the passport office was shut except for "life and death" travel problems.</p>
        <p>The anxiety was palpable today outside the passport office on 19th Street, north of the White House. Karlene Zepp faced a sign that said: "Welcome. So Nice to See You." But the door was closed and locked, with no one in sight to replace her stolen passport in time for her Saturday flight overseas.</p>
        <p>"I kind of knew there was this shutdown, but I didn't know it was this extreme," Ms. Zepp said as the budget crisis brushed her life. "I mean, we're American citizens and we're kind of prisoners in our own country. Now I'm thinking of the poor Federal workers not being paid."</p>
        <p>Her sense of grievance was not eased by the sight of a similarly troubled citizen who had managed to get a passport. "I was pretty persistent," said the successful applicant, Sam Juravel. He received special consideration after calling the office of his Representative, Benjamin L. Cardin, a Maryland Democrat -- a deliverance that did not delight those shut outside the passport office who blamed their plight on Congress.</p>
        <p>The city's mood was tart today. The telephone hot line at the American Federation of Government Employees, which represents many of the affected workers, explained, "As you know, Congress has gone on recess -- that is to say, gone on vacation" -- without dealing with the shutdown.</p>
        <p>"We've got a lot of very, very nervous people out there, and most of them are working," said Kitty Peddicord, chairwoman of the federation's Lockout Task Force, referring to the prospect that even those workers not furloughed will get only half a paycheck next Tuesday because of the budget bill standoff and the crimped payroll accounting procedures.</p>
        <p>An estimated 750,000 workers -- three times the number now furloughed -- face the half-paycheck problem as January bills come due. Political leaders have promised full pay to all after the crisis is settled. But so far this week, the  budget negotiators' standoff has been notable mainly for the absence of a sense  of urgency.</p>
        <p>"Many people live paycheck to paycheck, and it doesn't take much to put them  on the edge," said Steve Bauer, executive director of the Federal Employee Education and Assistance Fund, a nonprofit organization in Denver that extends small, no-interest loans to Government workers with family budget problems.</p>
        <p>"We've had hundreds of inquiries," Mr. Bauer said, "and the way things are going, I anticipate we'll have to do six months' worth of business in two weeks' time."</p>
        <p>The limbo of the partial shutdown has prompted a lawsuit, filed by the National Treasury Employees Union, contending that the Constitution bans partial shutdowns.</p>
        <p>"If we succeed, nobody works," said Robert M. Tobias, the president of the union, which has 155,000 members.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tobias argued that this would put more pressure on the politicians responsible for the struggle and added, "What we have now is a pseudo-situation, with the workers caught in the middle."</p>
        <p>As the mood here drifts closer to crankiness than crisis, Secretary of Labor  Robert B. Reich said it was well to understand that much of what the Government  does is analogous to insuring taxpayers, bland as that sounds. Thus, the sense of crisis is selective, striking only those "who suddenly find themselves unprotected," Mr. Reich said, like the 2,400 workers burned out of their jobs last month when a Massachusetts clothing mill was destroyed. They quickly received millions of dollars in Federal help for job retraining and child care.</p>
        <p>A similar need arose more recently among 2,000 Rhode Island workers who lost  their jobs in the sudden closing of the Almacs grocery chain, when the current Federal shutdown was already under way.</p>
        <p>While many Americans have been thinking of the shutdown in terms of political posturing, that was not the case for those workers whose pleas for help had to be denied.</p>
        <p>"It's as if a vast insurance policy were suddenly canceled," Mr. Reich said,  as the standoff drifted toward the new year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
