<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="01DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1436761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4D91E3FF932A35752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>S.E.C. Chairman at Center Of Furor Over Audit Chief  Three investigations began into the Securities and Exchange Commission's choice of William H. Webster to head a new board overseeing the accounting profession. House and Senate Democrats called for the resignations of both Mr. Webster and Harvey L. Pitt, the commission's chairman.</p>
        <p>The White House expressed support for Mr. Webster as well as for Mr. Pitt, who was harshly criticized for failing to inform other commissioners before they approved the choice of Mr. Webster that he had led the audit committee of a company facing fraud accusations. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>S.E.C. Chairman at Center Of Furor Over Audit Chief  Three investigations began into the Securities and Exchange Commission's choice of William H. Webster to head a new board overseeing the accounting profession. House and Senate Democrats called for the resignations of both Mr. Webster and Harvey L. Pitt, the commission's chairman.</p>
        <p>The White House expressed support for Mr. Webster as well as for Mr. Pitt, who was harshly criticized for failing to inform other commissioners before they approved the choice of Mr. Webster that he had led the audit committee of a company facing fraud accusations. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Microsoft Ruling Is Expected Today  The judge overseeing the Microsoft antitrust case will issue a ruling today, determining whether to impose sanctions beyond the proposed settlement reached last year. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Former Enron Executive Is Indicted  Andrew S. Fastow, left, the former chief financial officer of Enron, was indicted on 78 counts of fraud, money laundering, conspiracy and obstructing justice. The indictment is the first to be brought against an Enron executive since the company collapsed last year. John W. Keker, a lawyer for Mr. Fastow, said his client would be exonerated. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Tests Planned on Anemia Treatment  A biotechnology company, Ariad Pharmaceuticals, hopes to begin clinical trials next year on the use of gene therapy to patients with the anemia drug erythropoietin. [C6.]</p>
        <p>ImClone and Bristol-Myers Squibb are planning two large trials of the cancer drug Erbitux in an effort to have it approved. [C6.]</p>
        <p>China Telecom Delays Share Offering  China Telecom has abruptly postponed its $3.68 billion initial public offering. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Suit Filed to Stop EchoStar Deal  The Justice Department and 23 state attorneys general sued to block EchoStar's proposed $26 billion acquisition of DirecTV. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Lower Earnings for Oil Companies  Exxon Mobil and Royal Dutch/Shell Group said that third-quarter profits fell 17 percent, and ChevronTexaco reported a loss. [C12.]</p>
        <p>Amazon.com Previews Apparel Site  Amazon.com has switched on a preview of its widely anticipated apparel department, announcing it in an e-mail message to many of its best customers. The site included clothing and footwear from 400 retailers and manufacturers including the Gap, Nordstrom, Eddie Bauer, Foot Locker, Guess and Phillips-Van Heusen. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Equity Group Is Seeking Vivendi Unit  Vivendi Universal has entered into exclusive negotiations with a group of private equity investors to sell its Houghton Mifflin publishing unit for $1.7 billion. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Nasdaq Rises; Other Markets Fall  The Dow Jones industrial average fell 30.38 points, to 8,397.03. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index was down 4.95 points, to 885.76. The Nasdaq was up 3.02 points, at 1,329.75. [C6.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
