<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wired at Birth, Buzzing for a Lifetime</title>
    <meta content="20BRFOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1360990"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grubin, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blakeslee, Sandra</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Secret Life of the Brain, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DC143BF933A15752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wired at Birth, Buzzing for a Lifetime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDRA BLAKESLEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blakeslee, Sandra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Five-part documentary series The Secret Life of the Brain, set for Channel 13, explores how brain develops over lifetime, focusing on key stages of human development; executive producer David Grubin comments, interview; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN trying to convey a sense of the brain's complexity, neuroscientists are fond of mind-boggling comparisons. Did you know that your brain has more connections than there are stars in the universe? A bit of your brain about the size of a sand grain contains 100,000 neurons and a billion synapses. Somehow this three-pound lump of tissue generates thoughts and emotions, holds memories, creates movements, makes possible the creative acts peculiar to our species and gives rise to the mysterious sense of consciousness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN trying to convey a sense of the brain's complexity, neuroscientists are fond of mind-boggling comparisons. Did you know that your brain has more connections than there are stars in the universe? A bit of your brain about the size of a sand grain contains 100,000 neurons and a billion synapses. Somehow this three-pound lump of tissue generates thoughts and emotions, holds memories, creates movements, makes possible the creative acts peculiar to our species and gives rise to the mysterious sense of consciousness.</p>
        <p>So in writing the proposal for a television documentary about the brain six years ago, the filmmaker David Grubin had a problem: how to develop a narrow story line about something so staggeringly complex. To get started, Mr. Grubin called on June Kinsohita, a freelance science writer. Together they wrestled with ideas, looking at functions like memory, language acquisition and vision. Each could fill an hour, no problem.</p>
        <p>''Then it hit us,'' Mr. Grubin said in a telephone interview from his home in Manhattan. ''We realized we could do the whole series based on the overarching question of how the brain develops over a lifetime. Scientists work on pieces of his puzzle. But we could look at the entire picture in terms of development.''</p>
        <p>The result is ''The Secret Life of the Brain,'' which has its premiere on Channel 13 at 9 p.m. on Tuesday. The five-part series explores key stages of human development: infancy, childhood, adolescence, adulthood and old age. The central theme of each segment is brain ''plasticity'' - the relatively recent insight changes throughout our lifetimes.</p>
        <p>As recently as a decade ago, the dogma among brain scientists was that you were born with all the brain cells you would ever have. Taken literally, it meant that once a brain was wired up, it wouldn't change very much. This actually makes sense. You wouldn't want a brain that makes lots of new cells, turning itself over every few years. How would you be able to hold onto your memories and individuality? The brain needs stability.</p>
        <p>The new view of the brain is far more dynamic. It's true that you are born with most of the brain cells you will ever have. But those cells are little dynamos in terms of making and remodeling connections well into old age. Moreover, a small number of new cells are constantly being made and seem to migrate within the mature brain.</p>
        <p>''The brain and its capacity for change became the central theme of our series,'' Mr. Grubin said. Each program was framed by key questions: How is the brain constructed before birth and in the first year of life? How do nature and nurture interact to make an individual? How does a child learn to extract language from a sea of sounds and later learn to decode meaning from strings of written symbols? Is there a connection between brain development during adolescence, the onset of schizophrenia and the prevalence of teenage addiction? How does an adult find balance between reason and emotion? How does the adult brain repair itself after stroke and can this process be nudged along? Why do some people remain energetic and vital in old age while others do not?</p>
        <p>The entire series, narrated by Blair Brown, who played Margrethe Bohr in the Broadway production of ''Copenhagen,'' cost more than $4 million. Mr. Grubin produced the first two segments and brought in Edward Gray, Tom Jennings, Michael Penland and Amanada Pollock to produce the other three. The documentary is the first major science production for Mr. Grubin, who is known for his biographies and arts programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grubin acknowledged that he ''played it safe'' in terms of choosing for his series major scientists whose work reflects today's dominant paradigms of how the brain works. Neuroscience, like every field of science, is rife with rivalries and claims that the other fellow is going too far or not far enough. Thus two exciting aspects of plasticity are played down or omitted in the series. The finding that the brain makes new neurons in adulthood is described in animals but not elaborated on in humans, even though there is evidence for the latter. The first real application of using plasticity to treat a human problem, dyslexia, is not mentioned because of internal fights in the field.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the series manages to explain a great deal of complex material without dumbing it down. ''I suddenly saw why science had always been so difficult for me,'' Mr. Grubin said. ''Lost in a thicket of proliferating questions, I was never able to find my way back to that initial curiosity and wonder that inspired the investigation in the first place.'' Scientists get caught up in ever smaller levels of analysis, he said. To explain those levels without losing sight of the overarching questions, the filmmakers relied on several techniques.</p>
        <p>Animated segments show how neurons make and lose connections and ''talk'' to one another by spitting out chemicals. Each installment of the series is dramatized with the stories of people who are struggling with neurological problems. In trying to understand normal brain function, neuroscientists tend to study damaged brains. Thus families and patients tell stories of the premature brain, what happens when an infant has a cataract, the fate of children who have half their brains removed to control epileptic seizures, how dyslexia, attention deficit disorder and schizophrenia come to be, the causes of post-traumatic stress disorder and the ravages caused by stroke, Parkinson's disease and Alzheimer's disease.</p>
        <p>Scientists go on camera to explain their work, often conveying a sense of wonder and excitement as they pose the questions that keep them at the laboratory bench year after year.</p>
        <p>A decade ago, the brain was a black box. But brain imaging techniques developed in the 1990's now show where key functions like language and planning reside and how these change over time. The modern images show black backgrounds with blotches of color - blue for areas that use little energy and red for regions that consume larger amounts. While such images often smack of neophrenology, they make great visuals for television.</p>
        <p>''We tried to give people a sense of excitement about brain research without promising too much,'' Mr. Grubin said. For example, a segment on Alzheimer's disease talks about a vaccine to prevent memory loss. But the vaccine works only in animals and may never be practical for people. (A companion book, ''The Secret Life of the Brain,'' by Dr. Richard Restak, provides more details for people who want to investigate treatments and progress concerning various conditions.)</p>
        <p>As a poetry fan, Mr. Grubin said that he wanted to bring insights from poets into the practice of science. ''Poets remind us of the mystery of this enterprise,'' he said. ''They give us another way of experiencing the insights that scientists bring.'' Thus the first episode opens with words from Emily Dickinson - ''The brain is wider than the sky'' - and the last episode ends with the poet laureate Stanley Kunitz, a nonagenarian, intoning:</p>
        <p>I've walked through many lives,</p>
        <p>some of them my own.</p>
        <p>And I am not who I was,</p>
        <p>though some principle of being abides</p>
        <p>from which I struggle not to stray.</p>
        <p>No doubt the next chapter</p>
        <p>in my book of transformations</p>
        <p>is already written.</p>
        <p>I am not done with my changes.</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
