<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Temporary Davis Bid For UAL</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="387214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UAL CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED AIRLINES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERG, ERIC N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAVIS, MARVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENWALD, GERALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE113DF93BA1575AC0A966958260" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Temporary Davis Bid For UAL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC N. BERG, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERG, ERIC N</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Sept. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The long and tumultuous struggle for control of UAL Inc. took a new and surprising turn today when Marvin Davis, the Los Angeles-based billionaire, said he would buy the airline temporarily, then turn it over in two years to the employee group that is attempting a buyout of the carrier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The long and tumultuous struggle for control of UAL Inc. took a new and surprising turn today when Marvin Davis, the Los Angeles-based billionaire, said he would buy the airline temporarily, then turn it over in two years to the employee group that is attempting a buyout of the carrier.</p>
        <p>The long and tumultuous struggle for control of UAL Inc. took a new and surprising turn today when Marvin Davis, the Los Angeles-based billionaire, said he would buy the airline temporarily, then turn it over in two years to the employee group that is attempting a buyout of the carrier.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Gerald Greenwald, the former Chrysler Corporation executive who is leading the employee buyout effort, Mr. Davis said his idea was to provide the employees with, in effect, two years' worth of breathing room during which time they could line up financing for their own $201-a-share, $4 billion offer for the airline. UAL's board has already accepted that offer, but Wall Street has doubted the employee group's ability to line up financing for the bid.</p>
        <p>At the end of the two-year period, Mr. Davis wrote, the employees would have the right to buy back UAL from Mr. Davis at a price that would allow him to earn an adequate return on his investment.</p>
        <p>''Basically, Davis sees an opportunity not only to make money for himself but to facilitate the employees' efforts,'' one person familiar with the situation said late today.</p>
        <p>Other than to say that he and his partners would bring $750 million in equity to the deal, Mr. Davis failed to disclose the price he would pay to acquire UAL, making it unclear whether the board would even be amenable to a Davis offer. But any offer from Mr. Davis would probably at least have to match the employees' offer of $201 a share.</p>
        <p>The Davis proposal, which follows his $275-a-share bid for the airline proposed slightly more than a year ago, could send UAL's stock soaring. Wall Street's skepticism about the ability of the employees to finance their bid has caused UAL's stock to sag in recent weeks. UAL's stock closed down today at $90.625, off $1.375, in Big Board trading.</p>
        <p>Indeed, because the UAL board had given the employee group only until Oct. 9 to obtain financing, the consensus in the investment community was that a takeover of the airline was virtually impossible at this point.</p>
        <p>But the Davis offer today changes the calculus of the situation entirely. To use his words, Mr. Davis is proposing to ''bridge the acquisition of United for its labor and employee groups for a period of two years.''</p>
        <p>James Fingeroth, Mr. Davis's spokesman at Kekst &amp; Company, the New York-based public relations firm, had no further comment. Peter Rosenthal, the public-relations man for the employee buyout group, also had no comment other than to say that the employee group had received the Davis letter and was reviewing it.</p>
        <p>But in his letter, which was sent to the press, Mr. Davis did provide some details of his plan. Specifically, he said that if his plan had the employees' support he would commence negotiations immediately with the UAL board with an eye toward acquiring the company at a price that is prudent ''in the present environment.''</p>
        <p>According to people close to the situation, Mr. Davis was referring to the sluggish economy and to the higher fuel costs that all airlines have been forced to pay of late. It thus appeared that Mr. Davis would try to persuade the UAL board to accept an offer lower than $201 a share. That offer was made well before the price of oil began to rise.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis said that if his proposal could be consummated, the employees would be given an immediate 20 percent ownership in UAL in exchange for labor concessions of equal worth. They would also be given minority representation on the new UAL board proportionate to their 20 percent interest in the company.</p>
        <p>UAL has been consumed by takeover activity, both real and rumored, since 1987. It first received an offer from the pilots' union, which was followed by Mr. Davis's first offer. Since then, thecompany has received two offers from broader employee groups, including the one now pending.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
