<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Broadway's Season Of Name-Dropping</title>
    <meta content="31CAST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/31/theater/newsandfeatures/31CAST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040804T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1600529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">League of American Theaters and Producers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Jed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/New York Theater Workshop</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD6113DF932A05754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Broadway's Season Of Name-Dropping</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Broadway's Season of Name-Dropping</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on summertime Broadway season, when bevy of former television stars, pop idols and others with recognizable names take on stage roles; League of American Theaters and Producers president Jed Bernstein says summertime audiences, often from outside tristate area, may be drawn to shows they know nothing about but have familiar leads; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the last few years, there have been certain absolutes to summertime in New York. The Yankees will be winning, no doubt, and Mets fans will be in therapy. There will be Shakespeare in Central Park, festivals at Lincoln Center, and an assortment of very odd theater at the Fringe.</p>
        <p>And of course, on the city's biggest stage of all -- Broadway -- summertime means you will inevitably find a bevy of former television stars, lapsed pop idols and other vaguely familiar names.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Broadway, summertime brings a bevy of former television stars, lapsed pop idols and other vaguely familiar names to the boards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the last few years, there have been certain absolutes to summertime in New York. The Yankees will be winning, no doubt, and Mets fans will be in therapy. There will be Shakespeare in Central Park, festivals at Lincoln Center, and an assortment of very odd theater at the Fringe.</p>
        <p>And of course, on the city's biggest stage of all -- Broadway -- summertime means you will inevitably find a bevy of former television stars, lapsed pop idols and other vaguely familiar names.</p>
        <p>Just a quick gaze at today's theater listings can give a person the distinct sensation of watching a particularly poignant episode of ''I Love the 90's.'' There's Joey Fatone, formerly of the boy band N'Sync, playing a meek shopkeeper with a plant problem in ''Little Shop of Horrors.'' There's Melanie Brown, a k a Scary Spice from the Spice Girls, playing an H.I.V.-positive performance artist in ''Rent.'' There's Joey McIntyre, once the littlest New Kid on the Block, in ''Wicked,'' and the R&amp;B specialist Deborah Cox in ''Aida,'' and the childrens' television star Christy Carlson Romano in ''Beauty and the Beast.''. . .</p>
        <p>You get the idea. As soon as the temperatures rise, it seems, many Broadway producers start speed-dialing recognizable names regardless of how little acting experience they have. This summer's cast of ''Rent,'' for example, has not only featured Ms. Brown (or Ms. Scary, depending on how well you know her), but also Frenchie Davis, a former ''American Idol'' star, and Jai Rodriguez, the culture specialist from ''Queer Eye for the Straight Guy.''</p>
        <p>In their defense, some of the celebrity stand-ins have some stage experience -- Mr. Rodriguez was a ''Rent'' chorus guy before he was a queer eye -- while others have actually surprised skeptical critics.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Fatone played the supersensitive narrator Marc in ''Rent'' in August 2002, another summertime casting, Bruce Weber of The New York Times had some nice things to say about his singing and acting, among them that he was ''wisely and appropriately modest in his performance.''</p>
        <p>While that's not exactly a rave, its not really critics that the producers are trying to impress. It's tourists.</p>
        <p>''Because the audiences during the summertime are much more likely to be from outside the tristate area, they may be drawn to shows that they know nothing about but will go to because of the familiarity of the leads,'' said Jed Bernstein, the president of the League of American Theaters and Producers, a Broadway trade group. ''And a lot of them are doing pretty good jobs.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, during the summer months, with many natives fleeing for the beach or the country on the weekends, most theatergoers are out-of-towners, who may not closely follow the theater but who know that Mr. McIntyre can carry a tune (not to mention wreack havoc on preteen hormones). This summer has been particularly popular with overseas tourists, producers say, because of the weak dollar.</p>
        <p>''In the winter, you better please the theatergoers of the tristate area,'' said Barry Weissler, a lead producer of ''Chicago,'' where Paige Davis, of the television remodeling show, ''Trading Spaces,'' is currently playing Roxie Hart. ''But during the summer, naturally there are more tourists in town, especially Friday through Sunday, so you want to please them, too.''</p>
        <p>There are a couple of other reasons for the seasonal surge, including the availability of television stars, who are generally on hiatus during the summer. Producers of older shows -- like ''Beauty and the Beast,'' which has played on Broadway for more than 10 years -- also see the summertime as a prime opportunity to introduce their shows to younger theatergoers, who might not have been aware of the word ''drama'' when the production opened.</p>
        <p>''We're looking for talent and looking for people to rediscover our show,'' said Kevin McCollum, a producer of ''Rent,'' which has been on Broadway for eight years. ''And celebrities help us do that.''</p>
        <p>The trend is not limited to Broadway. David Hasselhoff, he of television's epic ''Baywatch,'' is doing a summertime stint as the slick lawyer Billy Flynn in the London version of ''Chicago,'' while the lesser-known Vanessa Oliveras, a finalist in ''American Idol'' last year, is playing the heavy-set lead, Tracy Turnblad, in the Toronto production of ''Hairspray.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weissler has long been regarded on Broadway as the most voluable proponent of stunt casting, having used it to great success with ''Grease'' (which ran from 1994 to 1998 and featured Rosie O'Donnell, Brooke Shields and John Secada, at various times) and less successfully with ''Seussical: The Musical'' (the 2000 flop that not even Aaron Carter, Ms. O'Donnell and Cathy Rigby could save).</p>
        <p>No show, however, has had more celebrity casts than ''Chicago,'' which has been running on Broadway since 1996. Between then and now, the show has been host to countless celebrity Roxies and Velmas (the show's villains), and Billys, including: Jasmine Guy (of ''A Different World'' fame), George Hamilton (his Broadway debut), Marilu Henner (of television's ''Taxi'' and ''Evening Shade''), Sharon Lawrence (''NYPD Blue''), Alan Thicke (''Growing Pains'') and Robert Urich. Of those, there have been successes, like Melanie Griffith, who wowed critics and crowds last year. And there have been failures, like Louis Gossett Jr., who lasted less than a week, in 2002.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weissler makes no apologies; Mr. Hasselhoff, after all, is coming to the New York production of ''Chicago'' soon, he said.</p>
        <p>''Listen, if I'd have staged an epic musical opera, like 'Phantom of the Opera' or 'Les Misérables,' or if I'd opened in a less expensive setting, such as London, I'd do without stars, but I've never been that fortunate,'' he said. ''Because its expensive, and because you want to safeguard your investment, you cement the experience by bringing in high-profile people.''</p>
        <p>He added that tourists don't care what New York critics say. ''Give the public a show and a star that they know,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And the success of his and others' casting largely gives credence to the strategy. That said, it doesn't always work. While Mr. Fatone caused a spike in sales for ''Rent,'' which grossed an average of $75,000 more a week during his run, he wasn't able to pull off the same magic with ''Little Shop.'' Earlier this week, the production, which Mr. Fatone joined on June 20, announced it will close on Aug. 22.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 4, 2004, Wednesday  An article in Arts &amp; Ideas on Saturday about summer casting on Broadway misstated Jai Rodriguez's history with ''Rent,'' in which he is playing Angel. Mr. Rodriguez has played Angel before; he was not in the chorus. The article also misstated the occupation of Mimi, another character in ''Rent,'' played by Melanie Brown. She is a dancer, not a performance artist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 4, 2004, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Arts &amp; Ideas on Saturday about summer casting on Broadway misstated Jai Rodriguez's history with ''Rent,'' in which he is playing Angel. Mr. Rodriguez has played Angel before; he was not in the chorus. The article also misstated the occupation of Mimi, another character in ''Rent,'' played by Melanie Brown. She is a dancer, not a performance artist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
