<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Dance Helps Music Express Itself</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="851318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="OPERA REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OPERA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLLAND, BERNARD MARK MORRIS</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ORFEO ED EURIDICE (OPERA)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EFDC1339F93BA25756C0A960958260" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Dance Helps Music Express Itself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLLAND, BERNARD MARK MORRIS;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dancers have things to tell us about opera, so when Mark Morris and his dance group address "Orfeo ed Euridice," as they did at the Brooklyn Academy of Music  on Thursday, we do well to pay attention.</p>
        <p>Opera has two hearts that want very much to beat as one but rarely do. There  is the musical heart, and it beats slowly. Musical sentences take time; repetition gives them shape and completeness. Words and dramatic action have an  altogether swifter heart rate. Said and done one time, they do not need to be said and done a second. So in opera, the play within finds itself surging ahead, then is forced to stand idly, repeating itself, until the music catches up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dancers have things to tell us about opera, so when Mark Morris and his dance group address "Orfeo ed Euridice," as they did at the Brooklyn Academy of Music  on Thursday, we do well to pay attention.</p>
        <p>Opera has two hearts that want very much to beat as one but rarely do. There  is the musical heart, and it beats slowly. Musical sentences take time; repetition gives them shape and completeness. Words and dramatic action have an  altogether swifter heart rate. Said and done one time, they do not need to be said and done a second. So in opera, the play within finds itself surging ahead, then is forced to stand idly, repeating itself, until the music catches up.</p>
        <p>Nowhere do dramatic movement and language capitulate so abjectly to music as in the stand-and-deliver arias of the late Baroque. And it is this so-called opera seria style that Gluck's 1762 opera so vehemently attacks. "Orfeo" does indeed pare away much that was ornamental and static; theater, to a degree, is released from total paralysis. Yet the symptoms are more ameliorated than done away with. The condition has remained.</p>
        <p>Dancing, as Mr. Morris's choreography suggests, offers opera a promising therapy. Physical movement in the midst of Orfeo's long and stationary explanations of himself, for example, mediate between words and music. In the same way, Mr. Morris's Nymphs and Shepherds in the opening scene act out their mourning for Euridice, but at the same time they are transferring rhythm, meter  and tempo to the eye. The dancers do not distract us from the music; they add to it. The absence of supertitles here seems a conscious decision: Mr. Morris wants our attention in one place.</p>
        <p>This is more than eurythmics. Hands and arms convey phrasing and accent; dancing is made a metaphor for musical expression and is not a Xerox copy of it. Mr. Morris is clearly on to something, though his bright ideas could not quite save this production from its weaker elements.</p>
        <p>The presentation is simplicity itself: tall, swirling white curtains, a chorus in evening dress, principals and dancers in various tunics. Michael Chance sings Orfeo in a ringing alto compromised only by the rough, bumpy no man's land at the bottom of his voice. As Euridice, Dana Hanchard has less to do but does it well. I particularly admired Christine Brandes's Amor and her way of translating beautifully shaped language into pure music.</p>
        <p>There are good reasons to perform "Orfeo" with period instruments, none of them really historical. First and foremost are the muted string resonances and raw wind colors capable of providing a balanced backdrop for the high-voiced cast. The original Viennese version used here underlines Gluck's yen for simplicity, but its choice is an escape from all the variants that came after. "Orfeo" has had a habit of reinventing itself: first at the composer's hands in  Parma and in Paris, and then in Berlioz's popular pastiche devised many years later. Rest assured, if Gluck were alive today, he would have scrapped historical piety and given us a Brooklyn version to fit the times.</p>
        <p>Christopher Hogwood conducted the Haydn and Handel Society Orchestra of Boston, and for just the reasons that get the early-music movement into trouble. The overture was a disaster; Act I not much better. Here, brass playing more or  less crumbled. Different sections were poorly tuned within themselves and with one another. After the first intermission, the players pulled themselves together (helped partly by the score's demands) but everywhere present was a hectic sense of hanging on, everywhere absent the ease of complete competence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hogwood phrased and accented like a sound musician, but he needed better  players. Their pervasive sourness of string ensemble, the kind once accepted as  "authentic," has long since been repudiated by top-of-the-line orchestras in Germany, Britain and the Netherlands, all of whom show us that violins played in tune can also sound in tune.</p>
        <p>Far better on this occasion would have been an "unauthentic" pickup band of modern instruments, even an ensemble of kazoos provided they played with confident rhythm and intonation. Gluck would have been baffled by our reverence  for history, and here history did him no good at all. There is a final performance tonight at 8.</p>
        <p>ORFEO ED EURIDICE Opera in three acts by Christoph Willibald von Gluck; libretto by Raniero de'Calzabigi; conductor, Christopher Hogwood; director and choreographer, Mark Morris; sets by Adrianne Lobel; costumes by Martin Pakledinaz; lighting by Michael Chybowski. Presented by the Mark Morris Dance Group and the Handel and Haydn Society Orchestra and Chorus at the Brooklyn Academy of Music.</p>
        <p>WITH: Michael Chance (Orfeo), Dana Hanchard (Euridice) and Christine Brandes (Amor).</p>
        <p>OPERA REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
