<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Business; The Nursing Home With Everything (for a Price)</title>
    <meta content="17HOME$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/17/business/17HOME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1302383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nursing Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Concierge (Houston, Tex, Nursing Home)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Concierge Care Nursing Centers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russell, Robert A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nursing Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nursing Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0D61731F934A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Business; The Nursing Home With Everything (for a Price)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>the nursing home with ever</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROBERT A. RUSSELL remembers well the first two nursing homes he visited six years ago as he searched for a place for his elderly father, who suffered from advanced stages of Parkinson's disease.</p>
        <p>''They smelled of urine,'' he recalled. ''People were lined up in the hallways in their wheelchairs. And these were what were supposed to be nice nursing homes.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROBERT A. RUSSELL remembers well the first two nursing homes he visited six years ago as he searched for a place for his elderly father, who suffered from advanced stages of Parkinson's disease.</p>
        <p>''They smelled of urine,'' he recalled. ''People were lined up in the hallways in their wheelchairs. And these were what were supposed to be nice nursing homes.''</p>
        <p>He visited about 20 nursing homes in the Denver area before settling on one. But Mr. Russell, a longtime real estate developer, later decided that if any home was to meet his high standards, he would have to build it himself. His goal, he said, was to create an upscale home where people like his father could spend their remaining years in relative comfort.</p>
        <p>His vision was realized in October with the opening of the 96-room, 106-bed Concierge, a sprawling two-story home set on 4 1/2 acres in Houston and within walking distance of some of the city's most affluent neighborhoods. (His father, Charles H. Russell, a retired advertising executive, could not be the first resident as planned; he died at 92, more than a year before the opening.)</p>
        <p>While some private nursing homes offer high-end services, including deluxe accommodations and larger nursing staffs, the Concierge is among the first to provide them on such a grand scale. Starting with its valet parking and airy foyer with marble floors and fresh flowers, the Concierge looks more like a luxury hotel than a nursing home. And each room, furnished in fine mahogany and cherry pieces, offers resort-style amenities like plush terry-cloth robes embroidered with the resident's name, and mini-refrigerators stocked to his or her specifications. Rooms range from 250 to 560 square feet, and for every 12 rooms there are communal living, activity and dining areas.</p>
        <p>The Concierge also offers satellite television and, for residents with personal computers, high-speed Internet access. Other features include a therapy pool (with a hydraulic wheelchair lift), a small movie theater, an ice cream parlor and an air-conditioned kennel for pets. A playground is available to visiting children. Tea and cookies are served daily in the lobby.</p>
        <p>''This is not a place for people to go and die; this is a place for people to go to live the rest of their lives,'' said Mr. Russell, using a line also found in the Concierge's promotional video. He is the founder and a co-owner of Concierge Care Nursing Centers, which is based in Greenwood Village, Colo., and runs the Houston home. It plans to open similar ones over the next few years in affluent areas like Beverly Hills, Calif.</p>
        <p>OF course, such amenities do not come cheap. Residents pay $7,000 to $11,000 a month. That is significantly higher than the average cost of a nursing home stay in the United States, which is $153 per day, or around $4,600 a month, although prices vary widely by region.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russell is betting that demand for his five-star homes will grow as people become more frustrated by the state of care in most nursing homes, and as wealthy baby boomers enter retirement. The population of Americans 65 and older, in fact, is projected to double over the next 30 years.</p>
        <p>Industry experts say the Concierge is entering a market that has changed greatly over the last decade. ''We have really seen an acceleration of different types of options becoming available,'' said David S. Schless, president of the American Seniors Housing Association, a trade group in Washington. The Concierge, he said, ''is building on the theme of greater options, more and different types of settings for seniors with varying degrees of health care need to choose from.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schless said he did not expect that other nursing homes would be the main competition for the Concierge. Instead, he predicted that competition would come from around-the-clock private nursing services, which allow people to remain in their own homes.</p>
        <p>Stephen Guillard, chief executive of the Harborside Healthcare Corporation in Boston, which operates 48 nursing homes and two assisted-living facilities in nine states, agreed.</p>
        <p>''I don't care how nice it is,'' Mr. Guillard said. ''People want to go home.''</p>
        <p>He said other upscale companies had tried to attract residents who could pay for such services but struggled to keep their rooms consistently filled. Most nursing homes, he added, are paid for primarily by Medicaid, the government program that pays for long-term care for the indigent, and Medicare, the government program that pays for short-term rehabilitation.</p>
        <p>But Jon Ellefson, the president of Concierge Care, said the first 30 residents of the Concierge were not from ''superwealthy'' families.</p>
        <p>Madeline Westbrook, 66, of Houston, whose mother was among the first residents, said the $265-a-day average price of the Concierge initially seemed overwhelming. But after being unhappy with a variety of assisted-living arrangements and nursing homes for her mother, Maxine Henderson, she and her husband Bill decided to find a way to make the payments. ''We had really tried everything,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In fact, by the time they came to the Concierge, Mrs. Henderson's money was almost gone and two pieces of property that were being held to provide inheritances for family members were sold. ''It doesn't matter, because you know you want them to have the best,'' Mrs. Westbrook said.</p>
        <p>Her mother spent the last five months of her life at the Concierge. She died this past winter at 85.</p>
        <p>Of course, Mrs. Westbrook appreciated all the amenities that her mother received, but what really sold her was the number of employees. There is a staff member for every four residents and a nurse for every 12.</p>
        <p>Nursing homes often measure staffing in nursing hours per patient day. Mr. Guillard said the average for his company is 3.3 nursing hours per patient a day. At the Concierge, the average is 8 to 10.</p>
        <p>One Concierge resident, Thomas Mandrell, 84, a retired engineer from Dow Chemical, said he appreciated the extra attention.</p>
        <p>''The staff, they're the kind that when you have problems and you call on them a whole bunch you apologize for being such a pest and they say, 'That's what we're here for;  call us anytime,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>SELLING the idea of the Concierge to investors, however, was not easy. In recent years, relatively few new nursing homes have been built, and capital markets have dried up as some homes have gone bankrupt primarily because of changes in government reimbursements.</p>
        <p>''This was the toughest deal to get financed,'' Mr. Russell said. He said that he and investors put up around $9 million in cash toward the $20 million home and that banks provided the rest. ''Banks just had doubts that people would pay $7,000 to $11,000 a month for this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Westbrook said she had only one regret about the payments. Noting that her husband's mother died with only $600 after paying to live in a nursing home for many years, she said, ''I wish my mom could have lived long enough at the Concierge to have $600 when she died.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
