<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Future So Bright, He's Already Seen It</title>
    <meta content="17STRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/17/arts/17STRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1302194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DE113EF934A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1307" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Future So Bright, He's Already Seen It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Ryan Adams, whose brooding mixture of rock, folk and country is winning him accolades and record deals; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHILE he was in the studio recording his second solo album, ''Gold,'' Ryan Adams ran into Bonnie Raitt. ''I know who you are,'' she told him. ''The it kid. The next thing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Adams lowered his head, and she continued: ''Boy, I've been there, all that pressure It's not easy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHILE he was in the studio recording his second solo album, ''Gold,'' Ryan Adams ran into Bonnie Raitt. ''I know who you are,'' she told him. ''The it kid. The next thing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Adams lowered his head, and she continued: ''Boy, I've been there, all that pressure It's not easy.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Adams, dealing with the pressure may be a little easier than it is for most. In his case, the question is not ''Is he overrated?'' The accolades that have been heaped on his brooding, timeless mixture of rock, folk and country are well-deserved. More accurately, the question is, ''Does he overrate himself?''</p>
        <p>A former member of the roots-rock band Whiskeytown, Mr. Adams has released one solo album, ''Heartbreaker,'' a moving, occasionally humorous suite of acoustic songs that pine over an ex-girlfriend. Released last year, ''Heartbreaker'' (Bloodshot) sounds like a classic after one or one-hundred listens (especially songs like ''Amy'' and ''Come Pick Me Up''). It makes its point as clear and cutting as possible, as when Mr. Adams drawls, ''Oh, why do they leave on the days that you need them the most?''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Adams talks to the audience during his charmingly and purposely disarrayed concerts, he reels off pop-music references with the conviction of a music fan who knows the devastating potential energy that can be compressed into a three-and-a-half-minute song. He also clearly yearns to be a part of the musical legacy he worships, and often seems acutely concerned about creating his own myth. But, with just one solo album to his name, Mr. Adams's legacy is like a work of conceptual art. It exists, but not necessarily as a concrete or commercial object. It dwells in his mind, not because he is delusional but because he has the odd trait of talking about his future projects as if they are already in his back catalog.</p>
        <p>'' 'Gold' is done,'' he said of the album, which is due in September on Lost Highway/Mercury, as he bowled an erratic game at Bowlmor Lanes in Greenwich Village recently. The album contains 16 tracks. Ten songs that didn't make the final cut will be released on EP's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Adams has already recorded eight songs for another project due in November: a quick, loud and sloppy 10-song, 40-minute record with his rock band, the Pink Hearts. After that, around his 27th birthday (when he says he will be at his moodiest), he plans to record, with another backing band he has already assembled, the ultimate alt.country album -- as a prank of sorts to commemorate the death of the genre.</p>
        <p>But that's not all. While on a three-week tour of Europe recently, Mr. Adams wrote another album's worth of songs, promptly called executives at his record label and performed the 11 songs for them in London.</p>
        <p>''So,'' Mr. Adams said, pausing in his recitation, ''I'm peaking.''</p>
        <p>In a music world in which an artist is lucky to release even one album every two years, Mr. Adams has four albums and several EP's lined up for the near future -- not counting some 20 CD's full of unreleased material he has compiled in the last few years. ''The kid's so prolific it's unreal,'' said Luke Lewis, the chairman of Mercury Nashville. He added that he would try to release as many records as Mr. Adams wants and ''hope that somewhere in the middle of it all, a radio hit pops out.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Adams began his fascination with music in his birthplace, Jacksonville, N. C., where he picked up punk and new-wave albums. He dropped out of school in 10th grade, formed a punk band and moved to Raleigh. There the first of his many broken hearts led him to discover the weepy world of country and country rock. In 1994 he formed Whiskeytown, which for many listeners went on to be the nadir of alt.country, with Mr. Adams as its unpredictable, often besotted frontman. The band recorded its third album, ''Pneumonia,'' in 1999, but before it was released, Whiskeytown's label, Outpost, folded. Soon after, the band, already fractious, dissipated as members took up solo projects. In the meantime, ''Pneumonia,'' thanks in part to Napster, began to attract a cult following as a lost alt.country gem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Adams moved from North Carolina to New York to be near his girlfriend, a music publicist who became the catalyst for ''Heartbreaker.'' Mr. Adams soon wound up in Nashville, where he recorded ''Heartbreaker'' with Emmylou Harris, Kim Richey and Gillian Welch providing back-up vocals. He then moved to Los Angeles -- for a relationship, of course, which quickly went sour -- and discovered the world of acupuncture and celebrity culture while recording ''Gold.''</p>
        <p>Tracing Mr. Adams's lovelorn journey from New York to Nashville to Los Angeles, ''Gold'' is a more self-conscious attempt at greatness than ''Heartbreaker.'' Mr. Adams said he wrote the lyrics so that they would be as compelling on paper as they were when sung.</p>
        <p>Mr. Adams continued to discuss ''Gold'' as he left the bowling alley and walked to the record store Other Music, where he saw ''Pneumonia'' on a rack for the first time. His reaction was a grimace, not because the album release had taken so long but because the record label had put a sticker on the cover calling Mr. Adams the alt.country equivalent of Kurt Cobain.</p>
        <p>With the much-delayed release of ''Pneumonia'' in mind, Mr. Adams sat at a nearby restaurant and considered the prospects of his musical future not turning out as planned. What if your label suddenly folds and won't give you the rights to all the records that you've started recording? ''That's O.K.,'' he said. ''I'll have two more by then anyway. I'll go right back to Bloodshot, say 'Hi, let's make a record,' and they'll say, 'Hi, Ryan, O.K.' ''</p>
        <p>Will you feel bad about the records left unreleased? ''I won't because they will be done and finished.''</p>
        <p>So what's important for you is simply creating the music, and it doesn't matter if anyone actually hears it? ''Usually, it's just that I want one particular person to hear it,'' he said. ''I don't sit down and try and write a song to the world and ask everybody to sing together, 'We are O.K., you are O.K.' It's usually me playing to one person that I'm thinking about when I'm singing, and everything is really not O.K. It's me asking, 'Why are you a satellite floating away from me?' Or sometimes it's like, 'Your satellite just ran into mine and damaged half of my radar equipment, what's up with that?' ''</p>
        <p>Were the songs on ''Gold'' written for someone?  '' 'Gold' was meant as an open letter for me and this one other person in the entire world, who shall go unnamed. And that record's for her. Not that she cares.''</p>
        <p>As he talked, Mr. Adams began to grow antsy. Since he has been in Manhattan, he has felt stressed and unsettled. As a result, he has been writing songs in his hotel that he describes as sounding ''amazingly hurt.''</p>
        <p>''I had an idea before I left the hotel today,'' he said. ''An A minor to G up to C thing was kind of bugging me. It's that afternoon itch.''</p>
        <p>With those words, Mr. Adams rose to leave and went on his way to add one more album to the enormous back catalog of his future.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
