<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="10INT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1302103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EFDA133FF934A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anita Gates</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WATCHING Brad Pitt is always a pleasure, but it's particularly enjoyable in Terry Gilliam's wonderfully nightmarish 12 MONKEYS (1995). As a very rich mental patient, Mr. Pitt is wild-eyed with some interesting physical tics and a tendency toward irrational but entertaining outbursts; the role earned him an Oscar nomination for best supporting actor. The film's lead, Bruce Willis is a time traveler from the future sent back to research the viral war of 1996 that killed most of the human race and sent the survivors underground for decades. Madeleine Stowe is the psychiatrist who doesn't believe a word he says - Saturday at 8 p.m. on Channel 7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WATCHING Brad Pitt is always a pleasure, but it's particularly enjoyable in Terry Gilliam's wonderfully nightmarish 12 MONKEYS (1995). As a very rich mental patient, Mr. Pitt is wild-eyed with some interesting physical tics and a tendency toward irrational but entertaining outbursts; the role earned him an Oscar nomination for best supporting actor. The film's lead, Bruce Willis is a time traveler from the future sent back to research the viral war of 1996 that killed most of the human race and sent the survivors underground for decades. Madeleine Stowe is the psychiatrist who doesn't believe a word he says - Saturday at 8 p.m. on Channel 7.</p>
        <p>The most famous line in THE NIGHT OF THE IGUANA (1964) belongs to Deborah Kerr's character, a fortyish spinster caricature artist. ''There are worse things than chastity, Mr. Shannon,'' she informs Richard Burton's character, a defrocked minister who has just been dismissed from his tour guide job midtour. He got too close to that under-age blonde (Sue Lyon, two years after ''Lolita''). Tennessee Williams never met a decadent character he didn't like, and this adaptation of his play, directed by John Huston, has its share. Ava Gardner plays the owner of the dumpy Mexican hotel were the story unfolds. She keeps herself amused with two bare-chested young beach boys, who hover in the background, Williams style, as symbols of the dark side - Wednesday at 6 p.m. on TCM.</p>
        <p>When Ingmar Bergman's PERSONA (1967) opened in the United States, Bosley Crowther, writing in The New York Times, called it ''a veritable poem of two feminine spirits exchanging their longings, repressions and mental woes.'' The two women are a perfectly healthy actress who has inexplicably stopped speaking (Liv Ullmann) and her nurse (Bibi Andersson). Sharing a summer cottage, the nurse talks, the actress listens, and their personalities appear to merge. The cinematographer Sven Nykvist symbolizes it in the famous closeup in which the two stars' faces merge as well. The National Society of Film Critics gave ''Persona'' its best picutre, director and actress (Ms. Andersson) awards - Sunday at 3 p.m., Sunday/Early Monday at 5 a.m. and Friday at 9 a.m. and 11 p.m. on Sundance.</p>
        <p>Robin Williams has a field day in Chris Columbus's MRS. DOUBTFIRE (1993) as an irresponsible child-at-heart father who gets in touch with his disciplinarian side. After his wife asks for a divorce, Mr. Williams's character disguises himself in drag to get the job of nanny to his own children. Iphigenia Doubtfire, who has a English accent of indeterminate origin, is a hit with everybody, even the children's mother (Salley Field). Of course, the nanny is not very fond of Mom's dashing new boyfriend (Pierce Brosnan). There's some low humor here, but Mr. Williams's comedy works on many levels - Sunday at 5:30 p.m. and Monday at 8 p.m. on Fox Family.</p>
        <p>What's a pretty young sanitarium owner to do? In A DAY AT THE RACES (1937), Judy (a very young Maureen O'Sullivan) is on the verge of having to close down the family business. Her last-ditch effort is to hire a new chief of staff, the supposedly distinguished Dr. Hackenbush (Groucho Marx), who is actually a horse doctor. But there's a racetrack nearby, so his skills may come in handy. The Marx brothers are in fine form, directed by Sam Wood, and Margaret Dumont is on hand as a hypochondriac who just adores the doctor - Saturday at 6 a.m. on TCM.</p>
        <p>Anita Gates</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
