<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NASA to Send Craft to Study Asteroid</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19931218T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="656254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTEROIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTEROIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D81438F935A25751C1A965958260" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NASA to Send Craft to Study Asteroid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The space agency announced plans today to launch the first spacecraft to orbit an asteroid, the first project in a new program to fly smaller, simpler and cheaper space science missions.</p>
        <p>An unmanned spacecraft is to be launched toward the asteroid Eros in February 1996. After a circuitous journey that will take it through the asteroid belt that lies between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter and bring it back to the Earth for a gravity boost, the 1,700-pound craft is to arrive at Eros in December 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The space agency announced plans today to launch the first spacecraft to orbit an asteroid, the first project in a new program to fly smaller, simpler and cheaper space science missions.</p>
        <p>An unmanned spacecraft is to be launched toward the asteroid Eros in February 1996. After a circuitous journey that will take it through the asteroid belt that lies between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter and bring it back to the Earth for a gravity boost, the 1,700-pound craft is to arrive at Eros in December 1998.</p>
        <p>The goal of the mission, known as the Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous, or NEAR, is to measure the asteroid and study its composition, geology and magnetic fields for a year or more.</p>
        <p>The spacecraft is to be built and operated for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration by Johns Hopkins University's Applied Physics Laboratory in Laurel, Md. This will be the first NASA planetary mission ever conducted by a space center that is not part of NASA.</p>
        <p>The trip to Eros will also be the first mission in the space agency's new Discovery program, an effort to undertake space science studies with smaller, cheaper and simpler spacecraft.</p>
        <p>Instead of billion-dollar projects that take a decade or two to plan and execute, Discovery projects are to be conceived, developed and executed in less than five years at a fifth of the cost. The program's guidelines call for missions using spacecraft that will cost no more than $150 million to develop, build and prepare for launching.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stamatios Krimigis, director of the Johns Hopkins laboratory space department, said it would cost an additional $50 million to launch NEAR on a Delta 2 rocket and about $30 million to operate the mission.</p>
        <p>Senator Barbara A. Mikulski of Maryland, chairwoman of the Senate Appropriations subcommittee that oversees NASA's budget, praised the mission. "NEAR is important because it is putting the principle of 'faster, cheaper, better' at NASA into practice," she said.</p>
        <p>Asteroids are thought to include debris left over from the earliest days of planetary formation in the solar system about 4.5 billion years ago. The rocky bodies are most abundant in a belt between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter. Near-Earth asteroids are those whose orbits cross the orbit of the Earth; they are believed to occasionally crash into the Earth and its moon. Many scientists believe one such collision was responsible for the extinction of dinosaurs 65 million years ago.</p>
        <p>Eros, an irregularly shaped body whose dimensions are estimated to be 22 miles by 9 miles by 8 miles, is one of the largest and best-observed near-Earth asteroids. Its most recent close pass to the Earth was in 1975 when it came within 14 million miles.</p>
        <p>On its way to Eros, the NEAR spacecraft is to fly past a small asteroid named Iliya in August 1996. The craft is to swing back around Earth in January 1998 to get an energy boost from the planet's gravity for the Eros interception. Eros will be about 230 million miles from Earth at the time of its rendezvous with NEAR.</p>
        <p>Scientists said Eros would be the smallest body ever orbited by a spacecraft, giving them their first long-term, close-up looks at an asteroid. Because of Eros's small mass -- and thus its tiny gravitational pull -- mission planners said they would have to use rockets aboard the spacecraft to adjust its orbit each week.</p>
        <p>Scientists hope to orbit as low as 15 miles above the asteroid's surface, allowing the spacecraft's color camera to photograph details as small as three feet in diameter. Other instruments aboard the craft will include an X-ray and gamma-ray spectrometer to study the asteroid's composition, a magnetometer for detecting magnetic fields and a laser altimeter to help with navigation in low orbits.</p>
        <p>In 1991, the Galileo spacecraft flew within 1,000 miles of a potato-shaped asteroid named Gaspra. In 1993, Galileo also flew past the asteroid Ida at a distance of 600 miles.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Testing of Hubble Is Under Way</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, Dec. 15 (AP) -- The Hubble Space Telescope is doing well after being repaired.</p>
        <p>"The equipment appears to function exactly the way we expected," Preston Burch, an official with NASA's Hubble team said today.</p>
        <p>The Hubble was returned to orbit on Friday after five days of repairs by astronauts from the shuttle Endeavour. It will take three months for engineers on the ground to check it out. They will not know until February, for instance, whether the Hubble's vision problems have been corrected.</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 18, 1993, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about a plan to launch a spacecraft to orbit the asteroid Eros misstated the planets reached by the Voyager spacecraft in some copies. They were Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune, but not Mars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 18, 1993, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about a plan to launch a spacecraft to orbit the asteroid Eros misstated the planets reached by the Voyager spacecraft in some copies. They were Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune, but not Mars.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
