<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holiday Dilemma at Schools: Is That a Legal Decoration?</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="656401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELIGION AND CHURCHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOLIDAYS AND SPECIAL OCCASIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHURCH-STATE RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELIGION AND CHURCHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOLIDAYS AND SPECIAL OCCASIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHURCH-STATE RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCLARIN, KIMBERLY J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCLARIN, KIMBERLY J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DC1530F935A25751C1A965958260" item-length="1463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holiday Dilemma at Schools: Is That a Legal Decoration?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIMBERLY J. McLARIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCLARIN, KIMBERLY J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pity the public school principal in December. Between Hanukkah, Christmas and Kwanzaa, this long last month lays a minefield of grand proportions for educators trying to acknowledge the holidays without bridging the separation of church and state.</p>
        <p>Every decoration is fraught with peril. Every lesson and every song must pass the "does not promote religion" test. Red and green cookies? Maybe. "A Christmas Carol?" Maybe. "Silent Night?" Definitely not. Teaching, Not Celebrating</p>
        <p>Between parents who want their religion in the schools, parents who want less of some other religion in the schools and parents who want no religion at all in the schools, school officials in the New York region know that come December, their phones will be jingling. They also have to deal with cultural events like Kwanzaa, a black American holiday that celebrates family and community and is based on African harvest festivals, and the Chinese New Year, a month or so later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pity the public school principal in December. Between Hanukkah, Christmas and Kwanzaa, this long last month lays a minefield of grand proportions for educators trying to acknowledge the holidays without bridging the separation of church and state.</p>
        <p>Every decoration is fraught with peril. Every lesson and every song must pass the "does not promote religion" test. Red and green cookies? Maybe. "A Christmas Carol?" Maybe. "Silent Night?" Definitely not. Teaching, Not Celebrating</p>
        <p>Between parents who want their religion in the schools, parents who want less of some other religion in the schools and parents who want no religion at all in the schools, school officials in the New York region know that come December, their phones will be jingling. They also have to deal with cultural events like Kwanzaa, a black American holiday that celebrates family and community and is based on African harvest festivals, and the Chinese New Year, a month or so later.</p>
        <p>"At this time of year, emotions run so high," said Ralph Lieber, Superintendent of the South Orange-Maplewood school district in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Most districts in the region try to chart a middle course through the holidays, relying on the United States Supreme Court and copious suggestions from parents, religious groups and the American Civil Liberties Union. Some districts, for example, draw heavily on a pair of 1989 Supreme Court rulings that upheld a display of a menorah next to a Christmas tree on the steps of the Pittsburgh City Hall, but said a creche standing alone at the county courthouse was unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>The key, said William Olds, executive director of the Connecticut chapter of the A.C.L.U., is to teach religion without celebrating it, and to treat all religions and atheism equally. The policy of the West Hartford public schools, for example, is to recognize Buddhism, Christianity, Hinduism, Islam and Judaism and their holidays without celebrating their beliefs in any way.</p>
        <p>"We do not object to the teaching of various religions in the historical sense," Mr. Olds said. "But too many school districts have used Christmas in what seems to be an attempt to teach religion instead of teaching about religion."</p>
        <p>News that the South Orange-Maplewood school board is at work on a holiday observance policy has sent rumors flying. One parent worried that Thanksgiving would be banned.</p>
        <p>"Of course not," said Mr. Lieber, the Superintendent. "We don't raise high walls and say the holidays can't come into the schools. It's all a misinterpretation of the discussion the board has had to date."</p>
        <p>The district already forgoes placing Christmas trees or menorahs in school hallways, although candy canes are allowed. The new policy will focus primarily on art and music, two areas in which people tend to cross the line from teaching religion to celebration, Mr. Lieber said.</p>
        <p>"What it will likely say is that songs that are religiously based, songs one would normally hear in church or temple or in a religious celebration at home may not be appropriate for public schools," he said. "I think when people understand the policy they will see minuscule changes from what we used to do." Backlash Against Complaints</p>
        <p>Two years ago, school officials in Voorhees, N.J., decided they needed a policy to guide them through the holiday season. Until that point the district had been operating mostly on a squeaky-wheel basis.</p>
        <p>"Someone would complain about this, so we would eliminate it. Someone would complain about that, so we would eliminate it," said Geri Borbe, a spokeswoman for the district.</p>
        <p>"We were to the point where people were objecting to red and green sprinkled on cookies, and to St. Valentine's Day," she said. "And it was forming a backlash."</p>
        <p>The school board had scarcely begun work on the policy when one member of a school-parent association issued a memo for parents interested in organizing spring parties. She suggested that to avoid problems, party designers steer clear of Easter baskets, the colors purple and yellow, and jelly beans. 'The Jelly Beans Did It'</p>
        <p>"I think the jelly beans did it," Ms. Borbe said.</p>
        <p>Frustrated Christian parents held a meeting and began a petition drive.  Jewish parents rallied to prevent the pendulum from swinging the other way. The issue threatened to divide the 3,000-student district.</p>
        <p>But in the end the event seemed to serve as a sort of catharsis, said Nancy Seigle, a parent. Tensions were brought out, views were heard and the district created a policy that seems to be working. Trees are allowed; religious decorations and Nativity scenes are not. Menorahs are allowed, but there is no daily lighting of candles. Concerts and parties are prefaced with the words holiday or winter instead of Christmas.</p>
        <p>"The majority feeling was that one of the reasons many parents moved into the area was because of the diverse, multicultural aspect," Mrs. Seigle said. "It reassured those of us who feel strongly about having multiculturalism embraced."</p>
        <p>A committee whose members include a rabbi, a priest and two ministers helps resolve any disputes. No 'Sterile Environment'</p>
        <p>"The only alternative would be to have a very sterile environment," Ms. Borbe said. "But you cannot have students walking through the malls and everywhere and not acknowledge that something is happening."</p>
        <p>Even some private schools have problems. Because of the cultural and religious diversity at the Bank Street School in Manhattan, there are no Christmas trees or menorahs there.</p>
        <p>"Even if we were to celebrate all of the possible holidays it still wouldn't serve the needs of parents who really want that to be their own personal choice," said George C. Burns, the middle school coordinator.</p>
        <p>Although the holidays are discussed in class, the private school tries to take a low-key approach during this season, Mr. Burns said.</p>
        <p>"Kids have lots of energy at this time of year and I've always felt the energy is much better put into really productive things in the classroom," Mr. Burns said. "It's like Halloween. They have so much time to think about it outside of school it's almost a relief when they come to school and don't think about it."</p>
        <p>Observing the Bank Street policy takes vigilance. Occasionally a new teacher will want to erect a Christmas tree, or a parent will express surprise at the lack of decorations.</p>
        <p>"But if some holiday thing sticks its head up somewhere, there is much more of a reaction to that," he said.</p>
        <p>But not all districts use strict avoidance. This month, the Cherry Hill school district won its fight to distribute class calendars with holidays marked by religious symbols.</p>
        <p>A Federal judge in Camden ruled that the calendars were part of a policy to teach tolerance and respect for different cultures and religions.</p>
        <p>"Religion is a pervasive and enduring human phenomenon which is an appropriate, if not desirable, subject of secular study," wrote District Court Judge Joseph E. Irenas. "It is hard to imagine how such study can be undertaken without exposing students to the religious doctrines and symbols of others." Jewish-Christian Division</p>
        <p>The dispute began in 1991, over a Nativity display on a bulletin board at an elementary school. School officials removed the display when Jewish parents complained, setting off a furor among some Christian parents. A previous Hanukkah exhibit had gone unchallenged.</p>
        <p>In response, the district adopted a policy that mandates placing in a central location in each elementary and junior high school a large calendar noting holidays throughout the world. A copy of the calendar is displayed in each classroom.</p>
        <p>The November calendar refers to Sikhism, Hinduism and the Baha'i faith. The December calendar includes Hanukkah, Kwanzaa, Human Rights Day, Thailand National Day and Las Posadas, a candlelight festival in Spanish-speaking countries.</p>
        <p>The complaint, brought by the A.C.L.U. on behalf of a group of parents, focused on the pictures used to illustrate the holidays. For example, Christmas is marked with a Nativity scene; Hanukkah with a lighted menorah. But Judge Irenas dismissed the suit, saying that respect for different religions is an important lesson to teach. The civil liberties union is considering an appeal.</p>
        <p>In New York City's public schools, religious decorations are banned, but symbols like Santa Claus, Christmas trees and menorahs are allowed. Cultural celebrations like Kwanzaa and the Chinese New Year are noted. A spokeswoman, Pat Bell-Murray, said she knew of no reason why choirs could not sing Christmas carols. "Those are kind of standard," she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bell-Murray said that the issue seemed to generate less heat in New York than in other school districts.</p>
        <p>"Hey, New York City is a melting pot," she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
