<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Talk of London; Tension Lifts in London Over Orchestra Funds</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="656271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENTAL AID (NON-US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONDON (ENG)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONDON SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONDON PHILHARMONIC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROYAL PHILHARMONIC
ORCHESTRA</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PHILHARMONIA ORCHESTRA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROCKWELL, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PALUMBO (LORD)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governmental Aid (Non-US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2DB1E38F935A25751C1A965958260" item-length="1358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Talk of London; Tension Lifts in London Over Orchestra Funds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ROCKWELL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROCKWELL, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Dec. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After all the talking, the furious newspaper columns and anguished letters to the editor, and months of behind-the-scenes lobbying and whispered vilifications, nothing much happened after all.</p>
        <p>Late this afternoon, the Arts Council of Great Britain, which had threatened to eliminate public financing of two London orchestras, announced that it would modify only slightly its pattern of support.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After all the talking, the furious newspaper columns and anguished letters to the editor, and months of behind-the-scenes lobbying and whispered vilifications, nothing much happened after all.</p>
        <p>Late this afternoon, the Arts Council of Great Britain, which had threatened to eliminate public financing of two London orchestras, announced that it would modify only slightly its pattern of support.</p>
        <p>Yes, the basis of the grant to the London Philharmonic was shifted, so that a part will now be funneled through the South Bank Center to support its residency there. But in the end the Philharmonic and the London Symphony, at $1.7 million each, and the Philharmonia, at $1 million, will get the same as before. The Royal Philharmonic's smaller subsidy will be cut by only $150,000.</p>
        <p>All of which may seem pretty irrelevant to outsiders, a minor bureaucratic adjustment. But it will be widely taken in Britain as further proof of the incompetence of the Arts Council, which is the British equivalent of the National Endowment for the Arts and which has been under steady attack for months.</p>
        <p>The National Endowment comes under attack for political reasons. The Arts Council's "hands off" policy protects it from that. The council's problem is money, or the lack of it. For most of the Margaret Thatcher-John Major years, the council's appropriation failed to keep pace with inflation. But this year the council is seeing an actual cut for the first time, and the pain that cut is causing the council's beneficiaries, and the backbiting among those competing for dwindling resources, is considerable.</p>
        <p>Looking longingly at the new Grand Louvre in Paris, The Independent complained bitterly that "in this country, the idea of spending nearly L1 billion on an art institution could only emanate from the Raving Monster Loony Party. We seem keener on destroying art than placing it at the center of civic life." Another's Bad Year</p>
        <p>But there is another reason for widespread dissatisfaction with the Arts Council, and that is the perception that Lord Peter Palumbo, its chairman, has failed in his own goals. The Daily Telegraph called this Lord Palumbo's "annus horribilis," echoing Queen Elizabeth II's 1992 assessment of the House of Windsor's year. The article promised to "explain how his grandiose dreams turned to dust." The Guardian called him "the rich undertaker of the arts."</p>
        <p>Lord Palumbo clearly means well, but he has a penchant for announcing grand gestures that he has been singularly unable to execute. Today's orchestra announcement -- before which Arts Council members declined all public comment --is merely the latest bold design that came to nothing in the face of entrenched opposition.</p>
        <p>On July 8, the council announced a plan to "enhance" the subsidies of two of the four orchestras it supports (the BBC Symphony is not part of its responsibilities) and to let the other two carry on by themselves. The London Symphony was announced from the start as one of the winning pair, while the other three would have to fight it out for the remaining plum. Just how much of the eliminated subsidies was to have gone to the winners, how much to multicultural projects and how much to simple savings was left unclear.</p>
        <p>It is this "beauty contest" that has provoked such anguish in recent months. And that is why today's announcement seems so anti-climactic. Having already retreated, in the face of public outcry, on plans to reduce funds for regional theater and the Glyndebourne Touring Opera, the council has now caused all manner of agony for five months and wound up doing almost nothing at all.</p>
        <p>As Judy Grahame, the disappointed spokeswoman for the Philharmonia, put it this evening, "They saved L100,000, most of which was probably spent on the review process."</p>
        <p>The announced purpose of the "beauty contest" was to focus attention on two orchestras and to build them into what many observers have long felt was lacking in orchestra-rich London: a "superorchestra" on a par with the Vienna Philharmonic or the Chicago Symphony or the Cleveland Orchestra.</p>
        <p>Whether the goal is realistic or whether the procedure announced on July 8 was the proper one has been much debated. As Nicholas Snowman, the director of the South Bank Center, put it on Tuesday, "This superorchestra business is a lot of nonsense unless you put L10 million on the table." (In other words, $15 million.) Competition Winner</p>
        <p>In addition, just a year ago, after another protracted "beauty contest," the Philharmonic was chosen over the Philharmonia as resident orchestra at the South Bank, and got an "enhanced" grant for that purpose. The residency had several goals. Dearest to Mr. Snowman's heart was that the Philharmonic could explore unusual, and especially contemporary, repertory and stretch the conventional orchestra audience. So far, that has worked problematically, since attendance at the South Bank has fallen.</p>
        <p>But another reason was to build the Philharmonic itself into just the sort of superorchestra the Arts Council envisaged. So why engage this year in a second contest that threatened to overthrow a decision already reached?</p>
        <p>One answer may be that a messy internal struggle led to the defection of a number of the Philharmonic's musicians, administrators (including Miss Grahame) and supporters to the Philharmonia. This, in London's incestuous musical world, encouraged in turn the furious lobbying, threats of lawsuits and (barely controlled) hysteria that influenced today's Arts Council retreat.</p>
        <p>There are those here who argue that there may indeed be too many orchestras in London (if you count the BBC and the two opera orchestras, there are seven, as well as the Academy of St. Martin-in-the-Fields, the Orchestra of the Age of Enlightenment, the Hanover Band, the London Classical Players and more). But many insiders, among them David Whelton, the director of the Philharmonia, also contend that given the historical autonomy of a London musician's career, any edict from on high to impose a "superorchestra" is inherently quixotic.</p>
        <p>How many of the arguments that led to today's decision were dispassionate and how many represented vested interests will never be known. "Sadly," said Christopher Lawrence, the new manager of the Philharmonic, "this battle is not about music."</p>
        <p>For Mr. Snowman, all the squabbling seemed more sad than productive. A onetime administrator for Pierre Boulez, with whom he founded the Ensemble Intercontemporain in Paris, he is another who gazes with regret across the English Channel to the lavishness of French arts support.</p>
        <p>"If you want to make a grand geste, you've got to have grandes poches," he said, meaning that grand gestures require deep pockets. "All this process has done is present an image of the British arts community cutting itself up over crumbs." Out of the Fray</p>
        <p>The reason the London Symphony didn't have to participate in the beauty contest was that it is widely perceived as beautiful already, as the best-run (with support from the city of London as well as ample private sponsorship) and artistically surest of all the London orchestras. And its longtime residency at the Barbican Center put it out of the South Bank residency battles.</p>
        <p>Its elevated status was reaffirmed last week when Sir Colin Davis, who will replace Michael Tilson Thomas as principal conductor in 1995 (there is no music director), led three concert performances of Berlioz's "Troyens." The first two were each spread over two consecutive nights, with a complete performance on Sunday afternoon and evening as the grand finale.</p>
        <p>The critical response was adulatory, and justly so. What the concert reaffirmed, along with Sir Colin's longstanding credentials as a Berliozian and the sterling quality of the London Symphony Chorus, was that the London Symphony is indeed a top-notch ensemble these days.</p>
        <p>A "superorchestra?" Maybe not, with its lack of the brilliant homogeneity that defines such elite ensembles. But one fully capable of providing profound musical pleasure, which may really be all that London, or any city, needs in the first place.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
