<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Owners Pitch High and Inside to Players</title>
    <meta content="07ARAT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/07/sports/07ARAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1340776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Selig, Bud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2DB1039F934A35752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Owners Pitch High and Inside to Players</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Owners Pitch High and Inside</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column discusses proposal by major league baseball to eliminate two franchises next season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here, finally, baseball's band of merry multimillionaires, its A-Rods and other assorted lightning rods, have been confronted with the flip side of unencumbered financial freedom. The owners have said, well, we can't seem to convince you at the bargaining table that we are suffering from a dire competition gap so we'll have to deal with the problem in the only way we probably don't need the consent of the union. We'll lop off the weakest of the weak, and possibly even two at a time.</p>
        <p>''There were a lot of people in the game who are in favor of four-team contraction,'' Commissioner Bud Selig ominously said after the owners voted yesterday in Chicago to begin with the elimination of two teams. We can guess which are the teams likeliest to go to their graves while leaving few mourners behind but their identities have not been revealed or even determined, making them the proverbial teams to be contracted later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball's merry multimillionaire players have been confronted with the flip side of unencumbered financial freedom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here, finally, baseball's band of merry multimillionaires, its A-Rods and other assorted lightning rods, have been confronted with the flip side of unencumbered financial freedom. The owners have said, well, we can't seem to convince you at the bargaining table that we are suffering from a dire competition gap so we'll have to deal with the problem in the only way we probably don't need the consent of the union. We'll lop off the weakest of the weak, and possibly even two at a time.</p>
        <p>''There were a lot of people in the game who are in favor of four-team contraction,'' Commissioner Bud Selig ominously said after the owners voted yesterday in Chicago to begin with the elimination of two teams. We can guess which are the teams likeliest to go to their graves while leaving few mourners behind but their identities have not been revealed or even determined, making them the proverbial teams to be contracted later.</p>
        <p>My sources tell me there is no truth to the rumor that the Red Sox and Cubs were proposed for contraction, on humanitarian grounds. Even if none of their fans are likely soon to be taking a swim at a new Fenway Park or Wrigley Field, they have earned the right to suffer well into the 21st century.</p>
        <p>So which teams have likely left the field, never to return? National League schedule makers will surely not be getting ahead of themselves by purging the Expos files. Montreal has been a hopeless baseball city for years, and, as Selig said, ''The teams to be contracted have a long record of failing to generate enough revenues to operate a viable major league franchise.''</p>
        <p>Of course, the delay in announcing which cities are about to lose major league baseball gives Minneapolis and Miami -- two of the other most oft-mentioned candidates for contraction -- some time to reconsider hard lines against using public tax dollars for new fan-fab ballparks. Election Day may be over but, as Selig apparently knows, it's never too late for a referendum.</p>
        <p>While the Expos have been in a losers' league all their own, trading off a virtual All-Star team rather than build a winner and hope to make people pay attention, it gets trickier with the other candidates. The Twins, for instance, won a couple of World Series and had reasonable fan support before the gulf between big and small markets became roughly equal to the one between North America and Europe. As for the Florida Marlins, they won the 1997 World Series in their fifth year of operation, before peddling their assets when the anticipated taxpayer largesse didn't come.</p>
        <p>With its large Cuban population and its radio wave access heading into the baseball-loving Caribbean, South Florida should have been one of the linchpin franchises. Before jettisoning the Marlins and reinvesting in a truly moribund operation like the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, Selig and Co. may want to consider seeking a privately financed BOB-like ballpark in Miami, retractable roof and all, for the good of the game, of course.</p>
        <p>''It makes no sense for Major League Baseball to be in markets that generate insufficient local revenues,'' Selig said. ''We have every intention of doing it.''</p>
        <p>If the owners' contraction announcement isn't a bluff in response to stalled negotiations for a new collective bargaining agreement, then Donald Fehr, the players' union chief with the knack for bringing owners to their knees, will finally have some explaining to do to his rank-and-file. He'll have to convince his membership that the imminent loss of at least 50 major league jobs and hundreds of minor league positions are worth a continued resistance to some form of salary cap that has already been in place for years in the N.F.L. and N.B.A.</p>
        <p>David Cone always made impassioned and convincing arguments against a salary cap but, frankly, the money is too staggering for me to care anymore about what kind of system professional athletes ultimately end up with. It is worth remembering that basketball players accepted a cap in the early 1980's when the owners opened their books and said, Fellas, we need some relief or four teams will soon disappear.</p>
        <p>Superagents like Scott Boras have been saying for years that the owners were bluffing, that they wouldn't be stretching salary structures and thereby endangering small markets by doling out $250 million deals if they couldn't afford them. Well, now they are saying their business needs help and, far from opening the books, they'll be closing down teams. Extracting, finally, a price for years of the players' unencumbered financial freedom.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
