<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>S.I. Couple Charged With Murder of Daughter, 3</title>
    <meta content="07CHIL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/07/nyregion/07CHIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20011108T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1340802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fries, Jacob H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herrnkind, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herrnkind, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herrnkind, Sylena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Staten Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Staten Island University Hospital</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Borakove, Ellen</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEEDA1039F934A35752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>S.I. Couple Charged With Murder of Daughter, 3</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">S.I. Couple Charged With Murder of Daughter, 3</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON and JACOB H. FRIES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fries, Jacob H; Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City police charge Staten Island couple Matthew and Julie Herrnkind with second-degree murder in death of their 3-year-old daughter Sylena (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The police charged a Staten Island couple with second-degree murder yesterday in the death of their 3-year-old daughter who, the medical examiner's office said, had been beaten repeatedly and forced to eat soap.</p>
        <p>The toddler, identified as Sylena Herrnkind, was taken to St. Vincent's Staten Island Hospital by the police at 3:30 p.m. on Monday after the police were called to her house on 176 Boyd Street in Stapleton on a report of a child not breathing. Investigators said the child's father, Matthew Herrnkind, 27, told them that he had found Sylena lying unconscious on a bedroom floor. She was pronounced dead at the hospital shortly afterward, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Staten Island couple was charged with second-degree murder in the death of their 3-year-old daughter, the medical examiner's office said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The police charged a Staten Island couple with second-degree murder yesterday in the death of their 3-year-old daughter who, the medical examiner's office said, had been beaten repeatedly and forced to eat soap.</p>
        <p>The toddler, identified as Sylena Herrnkind, was taken to St. Vincent's Staten Island Hospital by the police at 3:30 p.m. on Monday after the police were called to her house on 176 Boyd Street in Stapleton on a report of a child not breathing. Investigators said the child's father, Matthew Herrnkind, 27, told them that he had found Sylena lying unconscious on a bedroom floor. She was pronounced dead at the hospital shortly afterward, the police said.</p>
        <p>The girl had bruises all over her body that indicated she had been beaten, said Ellen Borakove, a spokeswoman for the medical examiner's office. Ms. Borakove said it appeared that Sylena had also been held under water for some time before she died.</p>
        <p>Sylena's 4-year-old sister, Diane, had burns and bruises below her waist and was taken to Staten Island University Hospital, the police said. A third child, the Herrnkinds' 14-month-old boy, Jose, was treated for broken ribs at Staten Island University Hospital, the police said.</p>
        <p>The police charged Mr. Herrnkind and his wife, Julie, 24, with second-degree murder, second-degree assault and three counts of endangering the welfare of a child. The police said that their investigation was continuing and that additional charges might be filed. Officials said that the couple's two other children, Missy, 5, and Alexia, 2, had been placed in a foster home.</p>
        <p>In all, the city's Administration for Children's Services had investigated the family six times in four years. The most recent questioning came in August, when the Family Resource Program, a private agency that has a contract with the city and works with troubled families to try to keep them together, reported that Sylena had bruises under her eyes, officials said. But the child welfare agency accepted the parents' explanation that the bruises had come from her autistic older sister Diane, and concluded that the report was unfounded.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Falk, a spokeswoman for the Administration for Children's Services, also said that Sylena had had a broken leg during the summer and that she had been treated at Staten Island University Hospital, which did not report the injury as abuse.</p>
        <p>An earlier investigation had led to the couple's arrest on child-abuse charges involving Diane. The child welfare agency said its report of that investigation, from 1998, showed that Diane had bruises. The investigators concluded that she had been abused. It was not clear last night what the status of the 1998 case was.</p>
        <p>The new charges came as a shock to neighbors on the Herrnkinds' block, in a hardscrabble neighborhood where an empty lot was filled with abandoned cars and broken-down boats. People said they never heard the parents raise their voices to the children. From the front window of the Herrnkinds' Cape Cod-style house, more than a dozen framed photographs of children could be seen, and toys were strewn across the floor. A black-and-white cat sat in the window.</p>
        <p>''I'm surprised by it, I really am,'' said a neighbor, Mary Charnes. ''They really seemed like a nice couple.''</p>
        <p>Officials said that two of the Herrnkinds' children, Diane and Missy, had been placed in foster care in 1998. Sylena went into foster care a few days after she was born in October of that year. In 1999, their foster mother reported that they were dirty when they returned from a visit with their parents, Ms. Falk said. They were returned to their parents' household in March of last year.</p>
        <p>The charges against the Herrnkinds were filed as voters weighed a ballot proposal to make the Administration for Children's Services a permanent unit of city government, a move that the commissioner of the agency, Nicholas Scoppetta, has said is necessary to keep attention and resources focused on child welfare services. Before Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani separated the child welfare agency from the Human Resources Administration, it had gone through a series of name changes and had had a troubled history.</p>
        <p>The move to make the agency a permanent part of city government comes six years after 6-year-old Elisa Izquierdo was beaten to death by her mother in 1995 while she was nominally under the city's protection. In response to public outcry, Mayor Giuliani vowed to overhaul the child welfare system and named Mr. Scoppetta commissioner of a new agency, the city's Administration for Children's Services.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Scoppetta has called his transformation of the child welfare system unfinished, he has said he will not stay on under a new mayor because the time was ripe for him to write, speak and teach about what had been accomplished so far. Last night, he was giving the keynote speech at a child and family policy conference in Washington, and could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 8, 2001, Thursday  An article yesterday about a Staten Island couple charged with second-degree murder in the death of their 3-year-old daughter referred incorrectly to the availability of Nicholas Scoppetta, the commissioner of children's services, for comment. He was not unavailable, having returned to New York from Washington. His comment and other new developments are reported today on Page A1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 8, 2001, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about a Staten Island couple charged with second-degree murder in the death of their 3-year-old daughter referred incorrectly to the availability of Nicholas Scoppetta, the commissioner of children's services, for comment. He was not unavailable, having returned to New York from Washington. His comment and other new developments are reported today on Page A1.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
