<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Un-Nominated</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="837027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACADEMY AWARDS (OSCARS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEIGH, JENNIFER JASON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MASLIN, JANET JENNIFER JASON LEIGH</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GEORGIA (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards/Academy Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7D91639F934A25750C0A960958260" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Un-Nominated</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Janet Maslin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MASLIN, JANET JENNIFER JASON LEIGH;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN "GEORGIA," JENNIFER JASON LEIGH SAT ON THE sidelines while the audience went wild for her sister, her own face blazing with mixed emotions. If she does  it again as the Academy Awards are handed out next Monday night, who can blame her? The Academy overlooked her scorching performance as a needy, no-talent singer, but it nominated Mare Winningham (a very worthy contender) for playing the composed and beloved country music star in the family. Leigh cannot have failed to get the message. She's a fearless actress and, in "Georgia," a great one. But America's sweetheart she's not.</p>
        <p>Far from it: instead, she has made an increasingly impressive career out of playing strange and abrasive women, never stepping back to reassure audiences that it's only a game. If her affinity with dark, disturbing characters seems strikingly modern, the pure and uninflected way she lets such roles absorb her is even more so. Few movie actresses let themselves vanish so absolutely or strip away the need to invite viewers' empathy, yet Leigh has freed herself to explore the void. Artistically daring as it is, that approach has its professional limitations. She looks great in tattoos and beads and raccoon eye shadow, but she's all wrong for the girl next door.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN "GEORGIA," JENNIFER JASON LEIGH SAT ON THE sidelines while the audience went wild for her sister, her own face blazing with mixed emotions. If she does  it again as the Academy Awards are handed out next Monday night, who can blame her? The Academy overlooked her scorching performance as a needy, no-talent singer, but it nominated Mare Winningham (a very worthy contender) for playing the composed and beloved country music star in the family. Leigh cannot have failed to get the message. She's a fearless actress and, in "Georgia," a great one. But America's sweetheart she's not.</p>
        <p>Far from it: instead, she has made an increasingly impressive career out of playing strange and abrasive women, never stepping back to reassure audiences that it's only a game. If her affinity with dark, disturbing characters seems strikingly modern, the pure and uninflected way she lets such roles absorb her is even more so. Few movie actresses let themselves vanish so absolutely or strip away the need to invite viewers' empathy, yet Leigh has freed herself to explore the void. Artistically daring as it is, that approach has its professional limitations. She looks great in tattoos and beads and raccoon eye shadow, but she's all wrong for the girl next door.</p>
        <p>Not that the Academy's snub can be ascribed solely to Leigh's taste for troubled characters -- not in a year when 3 out of 10 nominated actresses play hookers or hustlers. As Hollywood sees it, an actress can play those women with  impunity, as long as she plays them without much sting.</p>
        <p>But sting is Leigh's specialty, and the essence of most of the challenging roles she has chosen. So her characters are never as uncomplicated or user-friendly as the prostitutes played by Elisabeth Shue and Mira Sorvino in their Oscar-nominated roles. And had she landed the role that won Jessica Lange  her "Blue Sky" Oscar, that wanton Army wife would have seemed more slatternly than sexy, excruciatingly pathetic instead of lovably lost.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, a style this polarizing has its detractors: there are those who think watching her is like hearing fingernails scrape a blackboard, and they're not all wrong. Leigh has often been accused of wallowing in the misery of some of the people she has played, and of failing to offer much in the way of catharsis or redemption. And the descent into sordidness is a big feature on her resume, whether the subject is drugs ("Rush") or phone sex ("Short Cuts") or prostitution ("Last Exit to Brooklyn," in which she played a cheap whore who initiates her own hideous gang-rape). Not one of these is among Oscar's favorite modes of actressy self-expression.</p>
        <p>It gets worse: the lack of a larger-than-life star personality sometimes leaves Leigh looking too much the mimic, placing her emphasis on hothouse technique rather than raw emotion. (Think of her uncanny but bizarrely stylized  chatterbox in "The Hudsucker Proxy.") She seldom leaves her own fingerprints on  a role, often turning up as the quieter, more mysterious half of a two-character team. Her most emblematic role was in "Single White Female," as a disturbingly indistinct young woman determined, at all costs, to make herself a replica of somebody else.</p>
        <p>And she has never done much to capture the public imagination. She stays out  of sight, doesn't speak readily about her private life and by all accounts, has  no great flair for the Hollywood schmooze. All this can be construed as failure  to campaign for the kind of mass acceptance that Academy recognition brings. Or  it can be seen as part of a seriousness and singularity that, more and more, make her an actress boldly venturing onto unexplored terrain.</p>
        <p>She took huge risks playing Dorothy Parker with nary a sentimental concession to the audience, even if "Mrs. Parker and the Vicious Circle" seemed like heresy to devotees of Algonquin wit. Awash in mannerisms, her performance crackled with an honest bitterness that fully caught Parker's sad, self-destructive side. There was no gloss of Hollywood triumph to sugar-coat this lonely life, but Leigh delivered a caustically self-destructive, wrenchingly real modern heroine. And in "Georgia" she has created an even more darkly fascinating portrait, this  one made entirely out of whole cloth.</p>
        <p>Has there ever been a movie character quite like Leigh's Sadie Flood? (There  are rock stars this raw, not to mention novelists or painters -- other art forms allow feminine fury a lot more leeway.) No, and not only because so much of Sadie's frustration and glitter take the form of deliberately dismal singing. In Sadie's mix of flirtiness, wayward charisma, blind optimism and boozy self-loathing, the performance captures a volatile young woman whose psychic crises are laid utterly bare. And Leigh's insistence that an audience feel her pain has never before paid off in a such a perceptive, vibrantly detailed portrait burning with so much heart and soul.</p>
        <p>It's so good that it places her first among this year's Oscar oversights, who constitute an unusually distinguished lineup in a year of wild-card nominees. What with Nicole Kidman, Denzel Washington, Tom Hanks and Martin Scorsese among  those slighted, Leigh can commiserate in fine company. And she can take comfort  in knowing that her tough, fearless methods make her a performer not only ahead  of Jane Austen's time, but ahead of her own.</p>
        <p>Janet Maslin is the chief film critic of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Janet Maslin is the chief film critic of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
