<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>50 Cents Off! 2 for 1! But Get Them While You Can.</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="837285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="SPENDING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES (FARES, FEES AND RATES)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORROW, DAVID J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFD71639F934A25750C0A960958260" item-length="1302" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>50 Cents Off! 2 for 1! But Get Them While You Can.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID J. MORROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORROW, DAVID J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAVID KAISER is a cognitive research psychologist who lives in the affluent Brentwood section of Los Angeles. He and his wife make a total of $70,000 a year and frequently spend long weekends in Santa Barbara.</p>
        <p>So what was he doing on a recent Sunday evening? Making a run through Ralphs  supermarket with a bulging envelope of grocery coupons in hand. Darting toward the pet food section, he passed over the Purina brands on sale and nabbed six bags of Whisker Lickins to match six coupons, each saving him up to 40 cents off the $1.19 price. In an hour, he scored similar coups in every aisle. For his effort, he cut his grocery bill by more than 40 percent, to $48.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAVID KAISER is a cognitive research psychologist who lives in the affluent Brentwood section of Los Angeles. He and his wife make a total of $70,000 a year and frequently spend long weekends in Santa Barbara.</p>
        <p>So what was he doing on a recent Sunday evening? Making a run through Ralphs  supermarket with a bulging envelope of grocery coupons in hand. Darting toward the pet food section, he passed over the Purina brands on sale and nabbed six bags of Whisker Lickins to match six coupons, each saving him up to 40 cents off the $1.19 price. In an hour, he scored similar coups in every aisle. For his effort, he cut his grocery bill by more than 40 percent, to $48.</p>
        <p>Coupons are as good as cash," said Mr. Kaiser, savoring the $34 in savings  on that one trip. "I've saved around $6,000 over the past seven years. My wife and I use that money to take vacations or buy extras for the house. It really adds up fast."</p>
        <p>Nearly 115 million Americans clip coupons and redeem them at some point during the year. Of that group, Mr. Kaiser is part of the hard-core group called couponers, bargain hunters who seldom buy anything at the grocery store unless it is discounted and who plan their shopping around days when stores double their coupons. This group accounts for most of the coupons redeemed each year, and the practice has spawned something of a secondary market on the Internet and among military personnel.</p>
        <p>Often thought of as the weekday pastime of suburban homemakers, couponing is  not just for people who are stingy or living on limited budgets. The average annual income of couponers nationwide was up 10.5 percent last year, to $41,000, according to NCH Promotional Services, a coupon processing company in Lincolnshire, Ill. Some of these people are professionals who, burdened with retirements to finance and children to educate, use coupons to sandbag their budgets. But most say couponing is really a sport, a piece of turf to conquer.</p>
        <p>Never has this personal challenge been greater. During the last several years, virtually all major consumer products companies, including giants like General Mills and Philip Morris, have steadily sliced the number of discount coupons offered on their brands. Last year the number of coupons in circulation  slipped 6 percent, to 292 billion, according to NCH. Even then, fewer than 2 percent of coupons were redeemed, reflecting the attitude among many consumers that the chore of clipping and redeeming coupons is not worth the effort.</p>
        <p>Die-hard couponers have other worries, too. While the average face value of coupons increased 8 percent last year, to 68 cents, the length of time before expiration shrank to an all-time low of 3.3 months. "Consumer goods companies have long known that making a national coupon drop isn't the most efficient way  to market their products," said Jane Perrin, executive vice president of NCH. "Shortening the length of time when a coupon can be redeemed is one way to increase their impact."</p>
        <p>More trouble may be on the way. Procter &amp; Gamble, which recently cut its spending on coupons in half, began a test last month in upstate New York that bans coupons on all its products. In exchange, the company slashed its prices on everything except coffee. The practice of replacing coupons with everyday low prices has spread nationwide, Procter &amp; Gamble said. While no one predicts the total demise of coupons, their decline is likely to continue. To reach 55 million Americans with coupons, a company spends $1 million, roughly twice the amount needed for a 30-second television commercial on a top-rated program.</p>
        <p>The trick for marketers will be to get coupons into certain shoppers' hands.  "You'll see these consumer products companies doing more target marketing," said Burt Flickinger, director of Management Horizons, a consulting arm of Price Waterhouse. "They'll still use coupons, but they won't be the free-standing ones you find in newspapers. You'll get them through the mail or the checkout counter."</p>
        <p>But couponers are not taking the drubbing lightly. Riled by the recent coupon cutbacks, many have ways to stretch the value of their discounts, while others track their coupon inventories on software more often used by managers at small  companies.</p>
        <p>Some strategies could put Jack Benny to shame. Fabre Sanders manages a doctor's office in Boston. To broker her collection of 1,000 coupons, Ms. Sanders goes on line to Coupon Net (http://www.couponnet.com) to trade with other people nationwide.</p>
        <p>Anyone trying this trick needs to learn the language. Couponers have an argot that is so complex it would confuse professional rappers. A sampling: "B1G1F,B2G1F" is a buy-one-get-one-free, buy-two-get-one-free offer. "C notes" aren't $100 bills, but proof-of-purchase labels from packs of Camel cigarettes.  People looking for an "Hgt" don't want a hit from a drug, but a hanging tag from a product in the grocery store.</p>
        <p>From her on-line network, Ms. Sanders has a specific bounty in mind: coupons  from the West Coast. "Out there, few of the grocery stores double or triple coupons," said Ms. Sanders, who is 24. "Nearly all of them do here. To make up for the difference, companies will issue coupons worth 75 cents or more. You'd never see that here. They're like gold if you can get them."</p>
        <p>Mining these gems was a cinch. Within weeks of her request, Ms. Sanders recruited several couponers, who sent her envelopes full of 75-cents-off coupons in exchange for ones she didn't want. The process is simple. Coupon traders compare "wish lists" -- coupons they have and those they need -- by electronic mail and then drop the order in the mail the next morning.</p>
        <p>"I'll get a 75-cent coupon on Cap'n Crunch cereal from someone in California  and take it to my store, which doubles coupons, and get $1.50 off," Ms. Sanders  said. "I've been able to increase my savings by 25 percent through the Internet. I should save $2,000 this year and perhaps more."</p>
        <p>Finding the right coupon has become a science. Couponers, knowing when companies dump heavy discounts, hoard newspapers and mailers during those weeks. Prime times for grocery products, according to NCH, are any major holiday from Memorial Day to Christmas, with peak months of January, March and October. For beauty and health care products, May and October are best, followed by January,  August and November.</p>
        <p>"I use Microsoft Word to keep track of when the coupons are set to come out,  which ones I have in stock and a list of what I products I need," said Janet Wright, a homemaker in Kennesaw, Ga., whose husband is an electronics technician for Sony. "I do the same for my rebates. You have to treat this like a business. It pays to be organized."</p>
        <p>It also pays to be resourceful. A fast-expiring coupon is no problem for shrewd traders. Most military personnel can still use coupons at a base's supermarket six months after their expiration date. The extra time is meant to accommodate a foreign mail service so slow that coupons expire before they reach an overseas base.</p>
        <p>"All of us have a source in the military to take our expired coupons or trade with us," Ms. Sanders said. "You know, sometimes I just donate them to the military people if they don't have any to trade. There's just something about coupons. I just can't let them go to waste."</p>
        <p>SPENDING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
