<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Film-Theater Hybrid, Who's the Real Who?</title>
    <meta content="26zomb" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/26/theater/reviews/26zomb.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1734780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ontological Theater at St Mark's Church</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Foreman, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Zomboid (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E2DA103FF935A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1179" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Film-Theater Hybrid, Who's the Real Who?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Film-Theater Hybrid, Who's the Real Who?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Someone has just opened a window in the funhouse. Daylight has flooded the little stage at St. Mark's Church, long the theatrical fief of the avant-garde auteur Richard Foreman, and boy, do things look excitingly different. What once was sinister, shadowy and perfectly self-contained now appears quaint, vulnerable, exposed.</p>
        <p>Little wonder that the whey-faced, kohl-eyed creatures who have been hanging out for decades in this tiny, self-contained amusement park -- who were Goths before Goth was a fashion -- have the startled air of nocturnal animals surprised by the dawn. They have been invaded, you see, by a ravishing alternative reality, with its own landscape and bizarrely natural-looking cast of characters, who pursue independent (if two-dimensional) lives. O, the heresy of it! With ''Zomboid!,'' his latest work, Mr. Foreman has resolutely introduced film into his theater, and it looks as if these seemingly antithetical art forms will just have to learn to get along.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his new hybrid mode, the avant-garde auteur Richard Foreman retains the power to make audience members wonder if they might not be his creations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Someone has just opened a window in the funhouse. Daylight has flooded the little stage at St. Mark's Church, long the theatrical fief of the avant-garde auteur Richard Foreman, and boy, do things look excitingly different. What once was sinister, shadowy and perfectly self-contained now appears quaint, vulnerable, exposed.</p>
        <p>Little wonder that the whey-faced, kohl-eyed creatures who have been hanging out for decades in this tiny, self-contained amusement park -- who were Goths before Goth was a fashion -- have the startled air of nocturnal animals surprised by the dawn. They have been invaded, you see, by a ravishing alternative reality, with its own landscape and bizarrely natural-looking cast of characters, who pursue independent (if two-dimensional) lives. O, the heresy of it! With ''Zomboid!,'' his latest work, Mr. Foreman has resolutely introduced film into his theater, and it looks as if these seemingly antithetical art forms will just have to learn to get along.</p>
        <p>Et tu, Richard? Could this be the same man who has been writing, directing and designing exquisitely artificial vaudevilles with philosophical themes for his Ontological-Hysteric company since the late 1960's? The man who in 1988 staged a show called ''Film Is Evil, Radio Is Good,'' devoted to the premise that the literal-mindedness of movies stifles creative response?</p>
        <p>Actually, it's not as if Mr. Foreman hadn't given his fans fair warning. A year ago, he announced, with the effect of a thunderclap, that he would be forsaking his annual theatrical presentations to experiment with other forms. His ''Gods Are Pounding on My Head! (a k a Lumberjack Messiah),'' which opened in January 2005, would, it seemed, be the last of those mind-scrambling shows that downtown theater cultists had come to look forward to as exotic seasonal treats, like fiddlehead ferns in the spring. So it was a shock when the invitation arrived, stating that there would indeed be another Foreman production -- same time, same place. Even the posters, which sprouted on surfaces throughout the East Village, looked the same.</p>
        <p>Let's just say that Mr. Foreman is in a period of transition, with one leg in the brand of hallucinogenic theater that has become his signature and another in sharply shot film. ''Zomboid!'' wears a hybrid subtitle: ''(Film/Performance Project No. 1).'' Fortunately, such hedging brings out the best in this contemplative showman. Juxtaposing two art forms allows him to underscore in resonant new ways what he has been saying for years: Reality is, well, relative. And no single interpretation should ever be taken as definitive.</p>
        <p>Much of what the audience sees on entering the Ontological Theater, where ''Zomboid!'' officially opened last night, is comfortingly familiar. The stage is tricked out, as usual, in the manner of a German Expressionist variation on a Joseph Cornell box. Among the props and furnishings in this dark-toned playpen are oversized eyeballs, mannequin heads, lettered cubes and a giant, festively wrapped package -- you know, basically, the same old toys.</p>
        <p>But the inevitable strings with which Mr. Foreman traditionally vivisects theatrical spaces are, in this case, attached to two immense photographic images of a woman's face. It is a plain, rugged face, without a trace of makeup. She blinks. A troupe of live, typically Foremanesque performers arrive -- looking like extras from a silent movie about blood-sucking pirates -- and the action begins.</p>
        <p>What follows is a counterpoint of two universes that may or may not intersect but certainly appear parallel in some ways. The plainly dressed, austere figures in the film (which was shot in Melbourne, Australia) often wear blindfolds, as do the elaborately costumed five actors on stage.</p>
        <p>The filmed people are mostly serene, often frozen in sun-drenched tableaus that bring to mind the video art of Bill Viola. The live performers are more agitated and seem particularly perturbed by the presence of a large toy donkey, which evidently has deep metaphoric value. Occasionally they look up at the screen, mildly curious and uncomprehending, the way cats sometimes regard programs on television. When they reach toward the filmed images, they recoil as if from a violent shock.</p>
        <p>Words and phrases are spoken, by both sets of actors and by recorded mystic voiceovers. A lot of what is said is in the classic Foreman mold. A silly, haunting song is sung -- part nursery rhyme, part existential aphorism. (''Donkey, you and me, one is prisoner, one is free.'')</p>
        <p>There are cryptically intoned single words (''rules,'' ''inevitable,'' ''reminder'') and assorted Socratic questions, usually beginning with ''Suppose I were to postulate'' and ending with semi-Kantian considerations of the fluid nature of perception and the thing perceived. ''Suppose I were to postulate  an opinion must always be an internal misunderstanding,'' says a woman in the film, in a sing-song voice. Another speaks of ''feelings for other people like glass, touchable but not seen.''</p>
        <p>Obscure as such lines may sound out of context, they feel appropriate to the divided mise-en-scène created here. As your focus keeps shifting, the two sets of characters seem to call each other's existence into question, especially with shocking shifts of lighting that render one group or another virtually invisible. You start to wonder, bizarrely, if the people on screen are aware of the people on stage. And you often aren't sure where all the voices are coming from.</p>
        <p>''Remember, it is not possible to look and listen at the same time -- deeply,'' says a rumbling disembodied voice. Nor, it would seem, is it possible to absorb two representations of reality in a single glance. On one level, such speculation is straight out of freshman philosophy. But Mr. Foreman's melting visual style infects your perceptions in sophisticated ways, and it leaves you self-conscious about how you look at things for hours after.</p>
        <p>As we were leaving the theater, my date started to put on a pair of sunglasses and then laughed. ''Suppose I were to postulate that a person wear dark glasses at night?'' she said happily. Hey, yet another way to change perspective. In his new hybrid mode, Mr. Foreman retains the power to make audience members wonder, at least for a moment, if they might not be his creations.</p>
        <p>Zomboid!  (Film/Performance Project No. 1)</p>
        <p>Writer, director, designer (Film and Performance) plus sound and lights, Richard Foreman. Managing director/production manager, Morgan von Prelle Pecelli; technical director, Paul DiPietro; assistant director, Anthony Cerrato; costumes, Oana Botez-Ban; video, Vivian Wenli Lin. Presented by the Ontological-Hysteric Theater at St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village; (212) 352-3101. Through April 9. Running time: 1 hour 5 minutes.</p>
        <p>WITH: Katherine Brook, Temple Crocker, Ben Horner, Caitlin McDonough Thayer and Stephanie Silver.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
