<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>By 2 Wheels and 4 Through France's South</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="138980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOGAN, MARGARET</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED6133DF937A15757C0A96E948260" item-length="2623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>By 2 Wheels and 4 Through France's South</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGARET LOGAN; MARGARET LOGAN, who lives in Boston, is the author of the newly published mystery novel, ''Deathampton Summer'' (Walker).</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LOGAN, MARGARET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE airport security guard knew we were bicyclists - our carry-on luggage included helmets and handlebar packs. Even so, the X-rayed contents of an additional knapsack mystified him, and he asked us to open it for a closer look. A nuisance, but forgivable. How many couples, embarking on a cycling vacation in</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE airport security guard knew we were bicyclists - our carry-on luggage included helmets and handlebar packs. Even so, the X-rayed contents of an additional knapsack mystified him, and he asked us to open it for a closer look. A nuisance, but forgivable. How many couples, embarking on a cycling vacation in</p>
        <p>THE airport security guard knew we were bicyclists - our carry-on luggage included helmets and handlebar packs. Even so, the X-rayed contents of an additional knapsack mystified him, and he asked us to open it for a closer look. A nuisance, but forgivable. How many couples, embarking on a cycling vacation in France, equip themselves with a folding car rack?</p>
        <p>Certainly it was the first time we had incorporated a rental car into our cycling plans. Over the last decade, we've bicycled in Normandy, Burgundy, the Loire Valley and from hill town to hill town in Italy. One long trip included Germany, Czechoslovakia, Austria, Hungary and Rumania. We've pedaled up the Bosporus in Europe and down the Bosporus in Asia. Charlie has looped Ireland with his sons, I've crossed the Alps with my daughter. Thousands of miles, not one of them sullied by the cyclist's archenemy, the automobile.</p>
        <p>Repacking the rack, I had to stifle an impulse to explain to the security guard. ''Don't get the wrong idea,'' I wanted to say. ''We're not capitulating. We rent a car, we buy ourselves more cycling time in the Dordogne and Provence. A means to an end, nothing more.''</p>
        <p>It will be clear from this defensiveness that we were carrying, along with our packs and bikes, a measure of ambivalence. With good reason. Man, the toolmaking animal, is inevitably remade by his tools. We weren't sure how this new tool - it turned out to be an Opel hatchback - would remake us.</p>
        <p>Looking back, this concern must have contributed to the embarrassingly lengthy shakedown period we went through before we figured out a successful integration of bike and car. But ambivalence was only part of it. The two modes of travel are, after all, radically different.</p>
        <p>Cars are for getting from point to point. The scenery passes in swift accumulation and your thoughts move irresistibly toward your planned destination. Bikes, in contrast, encourage a sense of being in the present moment. You spot a cluster of pale pink by the roadside, brake, and determine that it is indeed a wild cyclamen, just like a florist's cyclamen except miniature. Small pleasures like this fend off the impatience and craving for speed that is bred in us by cars. Arrival, destination, is secondary to what you hear, see, smell, along the way. After the first week, we became more adept at switching modes, but it was never easy or automatic. One day, bikes on the rack, we drove toward the Mediterranean and the medieval ramparts of Aigues-Mortes. Aigues-Mortes, whose fortifications were meant to act on the 13th-century mind much as S.D.I. is supposed to act on ours, had been a childhood favorite of Charlie's. His nostalgia - it had been, incredibly, 50 years - was contagious, and both of us were raring to go. Our plan was to leave the car about 20 miles out and cycle the remaining distance.</p>
        <p>We found a good place to park - on the road, but right next to a small farm called Rancho Toro. We were deep in the Camargue, France's Wyoming Territory. After seeing Aigues-Mortes, we intended to explore the less-developed eastern area of the Camargue, looking for flamingo flocks, wild horses and herds of the nimble black cattle that supply bulls to the corrida at Arles.</p>
        <p>Rancho Toro's proprietor, jeans low under a Texas-sized belly, wide-brimmed leather hat, steerhead slide on his string tie, said ''pas de probleme'' when we asked if we could park there. We chatted briefly about bulls. Despite its name, the farm housed none its owner could show us. Were the bulls in the Camargue really wild? I asked. Middle wild, he said, rocking his hand. A joke about our wild horses, our bikes, and we were off.</p>
        <p>A good beginning. Easy contact with local people is a major benefit of the biking mode. Unfortunately, though, we couldn't seem to make the rest of the transition. The strong headwind rushing past our ears prevented us from hearing birdsong or our own attempts at conversation. The road didn't help either. Stretching uninterrupted to the vanishing point of a featureless and arid landscape, it offered no promise of novelty around the bend, no hills to alternate the stresses on our muscles and bones.</p>
        <p>Worse, hard as we worked against the wind, we couldn't shake the terror of the hot drive that had brought us here. Unable to find anything to appreciate in the present moment, to achieve the sense of being there, we craved destination. Every pedal stroke forward felt diluted by a tug backward to Rancho Toro and the hatchback. If we'd driven the whole way, I kept thinking, we'd have gotten there by now.</p>
        <p>THE most memorable instance of our inability to shed the driving mode happened in Cahors. (Maybe it's the 13th century that gives us trouble. Cahors was that era's Wall Street.) The small city is tightly packed into a U-shaped bend of the Lot River. Having just finished cycling the castle-crested bends of the Dordogne, some 60 miles north, we thought we'd see what this less famous river had to offer.</p>
        <p>Approaching Cahors from the north, you're supposed to turn off the national highway onto a smaller road that will soon produce an overall view of battlements, belfries and fortified towers. But when we tried to do this, a police barricade blocked our way, shunting us into a canyon of bumper-to-bumper traffic from which there seemed no escape.</p>
        <p>France stoutly resists emission controls -la liberte, presumably - and the air, this windless day, was very bad. I wanted to forget it, go someplace else, but Charlie was determined. Trouble was, every time he tried to turn into the city, we encountered yet another police barricade.</p>
        <p>Fed up, feeling sick from the smog, we passively followed the traffic across a bridge -not, alas, the city's splendid turreted Valentre Bridge, just an ordinary span - and fled upriver to the simplicities of Carjeac.</p>
        <p>There, too late, we learned why Cahors was closed. It was the finish line of the second stage of the Tour de l'Avenir, an important international bicycle race. We had managed to miss an ideal day for visiting Cahors by bike. Stuck in the car mode, we had forgotten we could park, ride the bikes back across the bridge, and slip through the barricades - to streets wonderfully free of traffic and exhaust fumes. Despite hitches like these, we came home from our vacation convinced that biking with a rental car, once you get the hang of it, makes a good thing decidedly better. The day after the Cahors debacle dawned cold and rainy. It was pretty nice to chuck the Lot and head south to Provence's promise of eternal sunshine. And when seeing Aigues-Mortes stirred a yearning in Charlie for Carcasonne, another walled medieval childhood favorite, a brief driving detour produced it.</p>
        <p>Someone once said that as soon as basic survival is assured, the two central issues of life become, How do I lose weight and where do I park the car? I thought of this at the very beginning of our vacation, the evening we drove through the gates of Castle Novel, a converted chateau near Brive. The following morning we'd be on our bikes, beginning a long slow loop through the Dordogne region.</p>
        <p>We had selected the chateau very deliberately - for its rural setting and spacious grounds. With so much land to spare, we hoped, monsieur the owner wouldn't mind keeping the hatchback safe during the week or more that we'd be off biking. Security was important, since the car would be a closet for our extra murder mysteries and the cold weather clothes we might never need but had felt impelled to bring from home.</p>
        <p>Weight control was on my mind because Castel Novel has a one-star restaurant. We ordered pate to start and then the house specialties - duck for Charlie and lotte, salmon and oysters richly lapped with Roquefort sauce for me. For wine, we took monsieur's advice - an apt Bergerac. Unable to decide on dessert, we ordered the pastry cart and tried everything.</p>
        <p>OVER Armagnac and coffee, we settled, with monsieur, life's second great question. Of course we could leave the car, for as long as we liked. Not only that, he was a cyclist himself and eager to share his knowledge of local terrain and points of interest.</p>
        <p>And the other great question? That was settled late the following morning, when, having followed monsieur's route, we arrived at magical Turenne.</p>
        <p>Turenne has what guidebooks call a commanding setting. A steep climb through the compact, picturesque village leads to the castle. A further climb up a long circular staircase leads to the top of a tower and a wide panorama.</p>
        <p>It is a panorama of climbs. To the north lay the hills of our morning exertions, to the south the exertions that would compose our afternoon. By now, we'd worked off most of the preceding night's dinner. The hills of afternoon would work off the rest and lunch. Rolling into our next stop, we'd be in a state of ravenous deficit.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, we'd be in foie gras country, calories in glorious supply. And fortunately, on a bike tour, weight control is pas de probleme.</p>
        <p>Along the Dordogne River we encountered numerous other cyclists - alone, in couples and in groups of 15 or 20. During earlier vacations, whenever Charlie and I would see a cycle group spinning along, their baggage traveling separately by what's usually termed the sag wagon, we had envied their sportive, unencumbered state. Maybe, we always thought, we should give group biking a try, if only to shed these packs.</p>
        <p>Now that we've converted to car-supported biking, I suppose we'll never investigate. My hunch is that the social cohesion of the group, added to conscientiousness about visiting major attractions, would overwhelm random impulse. And since our most memorable days have sprung from just that, we may not be temperamentally suited to grouping.</p>
        <p>Our Dordogne loop lasted eight days. Another time, we'll try two smaller loops, leaving even more behind in our mobile closet.</p>
        <p>The loop appeals, when cycling, because you never need backtrack. Novelty contributes importantly to the sense of being there, being in the moment. In Provence, however, we tried something different - establishing a base camp hub and spoking out from it on day trips. One exceptionally satisfying spoke took us 25 miles to small, urbane Uzes, with its towers, arcades and ducal palace. Along the way, at midmorning, we stopped at that Roman astonishment, the Pont du Gard.</p>
        <p>Like most people, I usually view obligatory sights through a haze of preconception and duty, but the sheer force of this monument banished every distraction. As I stepped carefully along the bridge's topmost stones, the shallow, clean Gardon River 160 feet below, I was glad the return trip would give us a second look. If not, it would be hard to tear myself away.</p>
        <p>Our base camp for this spoke was Beaucaire, selected for several reasons. With a population of around 10,000, there'd be enough to see and do if a rainy day closed down the cycling. Beaucaire is particularly good in this respect, because Tarascon, of similar size, lies right across the Rhone. Together, each with its own castle and traditions, they could keep us happy for two rainy days. At the same time, neither town is so large that every day's cycling expedition would begin and end with a nerve-shattering zone of urban sprawl.</p>
        <p>But the main reason for choosing Beaucaire had to do with its place on the map. Within day trip range were, besides Uzes, a wealth of promising targets - Arles, Les Baux, St.-Remy, the Routes du Vin of the Cotes du Rhone wine region and, with car assist, Aigues-Mortes and the Camargue. Nimes and Avignon are additional possibilities, although the industrialization of these cities makes biking there less than pleasant.</p>
        <p>In essence, adding a car subtracted arduousness. If coping with bad weather, flat, tedious routes or our packs began to seem like toil, we could take the easy way out.</p>
        <p>ADMITTING this, I know I'm on thin ice. Righteous cyclists scorn the easy way out. They could not admire our use of the hatchback as a closet. Righteous cyclists carry clothes for every contingency, plus their own bed, roof and kitchen, and never dream of complaining about the weight and drag. The freedom they gain is well worth it, they say.</p>
        <p>When I began cycling in Europe, I felt much the same way. Though I never bothered with kitchen gear - why would anyone, in this land of good cheap restaurants and superb takeout? - I always had my sleeping bag and tent. The alternative, making the reservations that would obligate a fixed itinerary, seemed contrary to the freewheeling nature of cycle touring.</p>
        <p>Then Charlie, who hates to sleep on the ground, discovered something. The proprietors of small inns and hotels are either willing or downright eager to recommend your next night's lodging. With tonight's host calling ahead to reserve, you can be freewheeling without the burdens of sleeping bag and tent. I should add that neither of us has tested this strategy in July or August. In June or September, however, it's never failed.</p>
        <p>What we learned by renting the car may prove equally influential on future tours. Spain, which has always seemed too big for us, the cities and towns too far apart for a pleasant day's effort, now looks much more feasible.</p>
        <p>To opt for the easy way out is also to confess a limitation of middle age. It's not exactly physical. Even though our average age is 57, after a week of steady cycling we feel as physically strong as we ever have in our cycling lives.</p>
        <p>Rather, the limitation we feel is connected with the will. It's will that keeps you slogging along when the terrain is dull and there's a fierce headwind. It's will that pushes you up mountains when your bed, roof, kitchen and all-weather wardrobe are dragging you relentlessly downgrade.</p>
        <p>In the mountainous Vaucluse, cycling up and down one of Hannibal's presumed routes to the Alps, we climbed the Perty Pass. We carried only sweaters, water, first aid and repair kits, and an emergency box of salted peanuts.</p>
        <p>Our vacation was nearly over. By this time tomorrow, the bikes would be on the rack and we'd be driving toward Paris.</p>
        <p>It was hot. Afternoon nap time. No automobile traffic. The air smelled of roadside boxwood and drying lavender, a major crop of the region. The mileposts told us how high we were and how much farther we had to go.</p>
        <p>By 3,500 feet, the fierce sun was getting to me. We'd filled our water bottles at a deliciously cold spring at the base of the Perty, but up here all springs were dry. Despite thirst, we had to ration ourselves. Occasionally a row of roadside sycamores provided a shade break, but five pedal strokes and - blam! - the sun was back in force.</p>
        <p>Hairpinning still higher, all I could think of was will. Hannibal, obviously, had been loaded with it, with plenty to spare whenever the troops needed a pep talk. The Romans went Hannibal one better, conquering and civilizing the Gaulish wilderness, building the arched bridges we had ridden over earlier this morning and establishing the luxurious imperial outpost whose ruins we'd investigated yesterday in Vaison-la-Romaine.</p>
        <p>Surrounded by so much evidence of the importance of will in human enterprise, I felt again a twinge of the ambivalence I'd begun with back in Logan Airport. This long, hard climb - was it the real thing? Hadn't we cheated by leaving our packs in the hatchback?</p>
        <p>At the top of the pass, 4,210 feet, we hiked up 500 more to the lookout. Here a glazed ceramic table identified the peaks and defiles Hannibal and his elephants had struggled with and, far to the east, the blue beginnings of the Alps he had yet to scale.</p>
        <p>I told Charlie what I'd been thinking about will and cheating. ''No easy way out for Hannibal,'' I said.</p>
        <p>''Hannibal,'' he reminded me, ''wasn't on vacation.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
