<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Mental Workout</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19920729T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="545872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="PERIPHERALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOFTWARE PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MINDLINK (CO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHANNON, L R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DB1F3CF93BA15754C0A964958260" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Mental Workout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By L. R. SHANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHANNON, L R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STUCK for an idea? Here is a computer program that may get those creative juices flowing.</p>
        <p>Mindlink Problem Solver, from Mindlink of North Pomfret, Vt., has four parts: the Gym, Idea Generation, Guided Problem Solving and Problem Solving. The Gym is for a mental workout; the Idea Generation module is a simple way to come up with ideas; Guided Problem Solving is a tutorial on a structured method of approaching problem solving, and Problem Solving is the complete tool "for generating and organizing wishes, ideas and potential solutions," to quote the manual.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STUCK for an idea? Here is a computer program that may get those creative juices flowing.</p>
        <p>Mindlink Problem Solver, from Mindlink of North Pomfret, Vt., has four parts: the Gym, Idea Generation, Guided Problem Solving and Problem Solving. The Gym is for a mental workout; the Idea Generation module is a simple way to come up with ideas; Guided Problem Solving is a tutorial on a structured method of approaching problem solving, and Problem Solving is the complete tool "for generating and organizing wishes, ideas and potential solutions," to quote the manual.</p>
        <p>Mindlink is intended to be a business tool -- "I want to make more sales in the Southwest region" rather than "I want a date with that certain someone" -- but there is no reason it couldn't be used as a personal problem solver as well. The main program guides you through a series of steps: naming and describing the problem, listing wishes about it, getting ideas and forming a solution. Using the program is simplicity itself; the screen tells you what to do every step of the way. At times, a quotation, picture or poem may pop up to suggest new connections.</p>
        <p>Here is part of a sample session in the Gym (I'm keeping my problems to myself):</p>
        <p>First comes the Warehouse, where you recall experiences and memories. It asks you to list several ways to use a watch and several other situations in which a watch would be of no use. Then, a digression into imaging. Describe how it feels to chew aluminum foil. Then, back to the Warehouse. Tell how you could use a watch in the situations where you said one would be useless. Next, you get a score based on the number of ways you said you could use, or could not use, a watch. Next, improvisation, but I'll stop here, about halfway through the Gym.</p>
        <p>There are many objects and ideas in the program, and they are picked at random. There is little chance that any two sessions will be the same.</p>
        <p>You are, of course, a wildly creative person who does not need computer help. Me, too. But there are people, otherwise perfectly competent, who could use an artificial nudge. Besides, you do have to solve your own problems, as always. The computer does not attempt to propose solutions. It merely takes you through an organized routine, and you could do much the same thing with paper and pencil. It is just a lot easier on a computer.</p>
        <p>The Mindlink program grows out of the research and practice of Synectics, a management consulting firm with a long list of big-name corporate clients.</p>
        <p>Mindlink Problem Solver is available for either Windows 3.0 or 3.1 or the Macintosh. The Windows version, which I used, requires at least four megabytes of memory, a hard disk and E.G.A. or better video. The Mac version requires at least one megabyte of memory, a hard disk, System 6.0.5 or later and Hypercard 2.0 or later. Either version is $299. The telephone number for information or orders is (800) 253-1844.  Quick Memory Fix</p>
        <p>The internal memory of the main machine here, a 386, was getting low again, dangerously near 500 kilobytes. Of course, there are ways of freeing more of this conventional memory with DOS 5.0, but I wanted a quick fix. Quarterdeck's memory manager is a great program, but not when you can't find it. QMAPS, from Quadtel of Costa Mesa, Calif., was at hand in the in basket.</p>
        <p>I installed QMAPS, answering several questions about the system; ran Smartmov, the subprogram that looks for programs that can be loaded in high memory, and, in literally minutes, had 631,280 bytes free, about a megabyte more than I had started with.</p>
        <p>That was the simple-minded way to use QMAPS, now in version 2.1. If you are, or want to be, a real memory guru, you can do much more. The suggested list price is $59.95.</p>
        <p>PERIPHERALS  Correction:  July 29, 1992, Wednesday</p>
        <p>The Peripherals column in Science Times yesterday misstated the amount of extra memory made available for the writer's personal computer by the use of a program called QMAPS, from Quadtel. It was about 100 kilobytes, not 1 kilobyte.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 29, 1992, Wednesday</p>
        <p>The Peripherals column in Science Times yesterday misstated the amount of extra memory made available for the writer's personal computer by the use of a program called QMAPS, from Quadtel. It was about 100 kilobytes, not 1 kilobyte.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
