<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heat Costs Expected To Surge</title>
    <meta content="30fuel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/30/business/30fuel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1706079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating Fuel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mercantile Exchange</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mouawad, Jad</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Gulf of Mexico</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5DA1330F933A0575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1199" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heat Costs Expected To Surge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Heat Costs Expected to Surge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAD MOUAWAD; Vikas Bajaj contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mouawad, Jad</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Natural gas prices set record, pointing to sharply higher heating bills for majority of Americans this winter and soaring costs for makers of plastics and chemicals, which use natural gas as their main fuel and raw material; price of natural gas has doubled since beginning of summer; recent estimates by Energy Dept show that Americans are likely to pay roughly $400 more for their natural gas this winter, with average bills jumping to $1,130; natural gas prices for November delivery close at $14.196 a thousand cubic feet, gain of 9.6 cents on New York Mercantile Exchange; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Natural gas prices set a record yesterday, pointing to sharply higher heating bills for a majority of Americans this winter and soaring costs for makers of plastics and chemicals, which use natural gas as their main fuel and raw material.</p>
        <p>Since the beginning of the summer, the price of natural gas has doubled. But unlike crude oil or gasoline, whose recent price increases have been widely felt by most Americans, the price surge in natural gas -- the most popular source for home heating across the colder regions of the country -- has so far gone largely unnoticed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Natural gas prices set a record yesterday, pointing to sharply higher heating bills for a majority of Americans this winter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Natural gas prices set a record yesterday, pointing to sharply higher heating bills for a majority of Americans this winter and soaring costs for makers of plastics and chemicals, which use natural gas as their main fuel and raw material.</p>
        <p>Since the beginning of the summer, the price of natural gas has doubled. But unlike crude oil or gasoline, whose recent price increases have been widely felt by most Americans, the price surge in natural gas -- the most popular source for home heating across the colder regions of the country -- has so far gone largely unnoticed.</p>
        <p>That is about to change as colder weather sets in. After the hot summer pushed up natural gas consumption by electricity companies, the prospect of a harsher winter than last year's on top of two devastating punches to the nation's energy hub on the Gulf Coast has led to a significant tightening of natural gas supplies. And unlike the situation with petroleum, which can be readily stored in bulk for long periods of time, there is no National Gas Reserve to turn to when shortages arise.</p>
        <p>''It's still under most people's radar screen right now,'' said Carl Neill, an analyst at Risk Management Inc., a natural gas consultant and brokerage firm in Chicago. ''The public has absolutely no idea how high prices are going to be this year. It's going to be mind-boggling.''</p>
        <p>According to recent estimates by the Energy Department, Americans are likely to pay roughly $400 more for their natural gas this winter than last year, with average bills jumping to $1,130. Many analysts, however, warn that these figures may prove too low and are likely to be updated when the government issues its winter price outlook next month.</p>
        <p>While commercial stockpiles of natural gas are currently above a five-year average, prices are now being driven by the uncertainties surrounding the impact of Hurricane Rita on energy installations in the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
        <p>Natural gas prices for November delivery closed at $14.196 a thousand cubic feet, a gain of 9.6 cents on the New York Mercantile Exchange. Crude oil rose 44 cents and closed at $66.79 a barrel. Natural gas now costs more than three times its average of $4.70 from 2000 to 2005 and seven times the 1990's average price of $2 a thousand cubic feet.</p>
        <p>President Bush, who called on Americans this week to conserve gasoline by driving less, did not mention natural gas in his remarks. While high prices will increase the incentive to drill for more gas, there is little to restrain the market in the short term.</p>
        <p>Some government and industry officials are now warning consumers to expect higher heating bills. Guy F. Caruso, the administrator of the Energy Information Administration, which is part of the Energy Department, told the National Association for Business Economics in Chicago on Sunday that he did not expect natural gas prices to drop below $10 per thousand cubic feet this winter, and warned of ''substantial price increases this winter.''</p>
        <p>Only 20 percent of natural gas production in the gulf has been restored nearly a week after Hurricane Rita hit. The region supplies 10 billion cubic feet of natural gas a day, or 16 percent of what is used in homes, businesses, industries and power plants across the nation.</p>
        <p>On shore, dozens of gas-processing facilities, which act like refineries for natural gas, were disabled by the storm and remain closed, creating another bottleneck. The Henry Hub terminal for natural gas in Louisiana, the trading point for the Nymex gas spot contract, has been shut for more than a week. That prompted Nymex to declare ''force majeure'' for September and October deliveries, meaning there is no guarantee the contracts will be fulfilled.</p>
        <p>Natural gas prices have been setting records since Hurricane Katrina pushed prices beyond $10.10 a thousand cubic feet for the first time.</p>
        <p>''Call it supply constraints or whatever, we have a natural gas market that is tight,'' said Chris McGill, the managing director for policy analysis at the American Gas Association. ''We're meeting demand but at significantly higher prices.''</p>
        <p>Gas suppliers will still be able to meet residential demands and most other uses. But some industrial companies might be briefly cut off from natural gas supplies this winter.</p>
        <p>''We've had huge supply dislocations from the gulf and now the question becomes, Will supplies come back in time to meet winter demand?'' said Owen Kean, an analyst at the American Chemistry Council.</p>
        <p>The United States produces about 80 percent of the natural gas it consumes. The rest is mostly imported by pipelines from Canada, with a small proportion, about 3 percent, shipped in as liquefied natural gas from North Africa and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Even if Canada can export more gas to the United States, there are few other alternatives to make up for the loss in domestic gas supplies.</p>
        <p>''Because we have little import capacity, the United States has a recipe to see very high natural gas prices very quickly,'' said Kenneth B. Medlock, a research fellow in energy studies at the Baker Institute of Rice University.</p>
        <p>Households that rely on government assistance to pay bills could face an especially difficult winter.</p>
        <p>Congress has budgeted about $2 billion for the Low Income Home Energy Assistance Program, or Liheap, for the 2006 fiscal year. But that is no more than last year, when costs were markedly lower.</p>
        <p>Families qualifying for the assistance would receive an average of $300 a year under the current allocation. Billy Jack Gregg, a state consumer advocate in West Virginia, said that was expected to fall well short of the estimated $600 to $700 increase that many families on the East Coast and Midwest will face this winter.</p>
        <p>For months, Tim Thompson, the municipal administrator for the town of Lewisport, Ky., has been watching natural gas prices go up. He is in charge of buying the town's yearly supplies and he kept waiting for an opportune time to lock in a better price.</p>
        <p>''Prices used to fluctuate pennies from year to year,'' Mr. Thompson said. ''Now, I have to knock on doors and try to figure out how much people will be able to pay. This is going to be very hard on ordinary folks.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
