<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Stoic Old Stowe, a New Era</title>
    <meta content="25STOW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/25/realestate/luxury/25stowe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1652555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="HAVENS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Stowe (Vt)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vermont</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stowe Mountain Resort (Vt)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American International Group Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lawlor, Julia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont/Stowe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Vermont</location>
        <org class="online_producer">American International Group</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E5DC173DF936A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Stoic Old Stowe, a New Era</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Stoic Old Stowe, a New Era</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA LAWLOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lawlor, Julia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on planned $300-million, 10-year makeover and expansion of Stowe Mountain ski resort in Vermont owned by American International Group; loyal lovers of New England mountains say changes may make Stowe unrecognizable; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SKIERS who love Stowe have learned to accept some sacrifices. Take Peter Van Raalte, a New York investment banker who heads there with his family every winter weekend. First there is the 300-mile drive to northern Vermont from the Van Raaltes' house in Briarcliff Manor, N.Y. Then the creaky old lifts, the patchy snowmaking, the jouncing bus to the other side of the resort, the busy days when the cramped lodge is full.</p>
        <p>One thrilling run down Mount Mansfield, though, with perhaps the most challenging terrain east of the Rockies, and all is forgiven. At almost every turn, yet another view of unspoiled peaks stretching far into the distance tempts you to stop, rip off your goggles and gape.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Stowe Mountain Resort in Vermont is undergoing a $300 million, 10-year expansion to improve its ski slopes and add luxury accommodations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SKIERS who love Stowe have learned to accept some sacrifices. Take Peter Van Raalte, a New York investment banker who heads there with his family every winter weekend. First there is the 300-mile drive to northern Vermont from the Van Raaltes' house in Briarcliff Manor, N.Y. Then the creaky old lifts, the patchy snowmaking, the jouncing bus to the other side of the resort, the busy days when the cramped lodge is full.</p>
        <p>One thrilling run down Mount Mansfield, though, with perhaps the most challenging terrain east of the Rockies, and all is forgiven. At almost every turn, yet another view of unspoiled peaks stretching far into the distance tempts you to stop, rip off your goggles and gape.</p>
        <p>''It's the greatest ski area in the East,'' Mr. Van Raalte said.</p>
        <p>But as rival ski areas improve slopes and add luxury accommodations, threatening to chip away at Stowe's reputation for supremacy, the Stowe Mountain Resort, owned by the American International Group, the insurance giant, is doing what it believes it has to do -- remaking Stowe. The $300 million, 10-year expansion will give skiers the convenience and services they have learned to expect at places like Vail in Colorado and Whistler in British Columbia. But for loyal lovers of the New England mountains, the changes may also make Stowe unrecognizable. The resort is adding high-speed lifts, snowmaking ponds and equipment, new and remodeled lodges and a transfer lift high above Route 108 to eliminate the shuttle bus between Mount Mansfield and its other mountain, Spruce Peak.</p>
        <p>Most unsettling to those who are attached to the Stowe of tradition is that 32 acres of what is now mostly open space (part of it a large parking lot) will become a cluster of development, including five-story condominiums, a hotel, a skating rink and a community of town houses and single-family homes. There will be new restaurants, a performance center, shops, a parking garage and a spa. A golf course will be built into the side of Spruce Peak itself.</p>
        <p>A.I.G., Stowe's sole owner since 1988, is after a growing group of increasingly finicky skiers who demand slopeside ski-in, ski-out lodging and are willing to pay a premium for it. ''Many have been flying to Colorado or other places out West to get the experience,'' said Hank Lunde, the president of the Stowe Mountain Resort. ''Now they can get it here.'' He estimated that Stowe would attract 500,000 skiers a year, compared with 350,000 now.</p>
        <p>BUT could success spoil Stowe?</p>
        <p>Much of its appeal has been its carefully preserved rural character. Farms are close by, and village shops are small and family-owned.</p>
        <p>Stowe is quiet in summer and has ''a great hiking trail network,'' said Larry Lackey, a local resident active in environmental groups and an opponent of the resort expansion. ''Now there will be a little city at the base.''</p>
        <p>That city is already taking shape. Since last year, 10 lots, one-third to one-half acre in size, have been sold for an average of $1.1 million each, said Gary Gosztonyi, the director of sales and marketing for Spruce Peak Realty, part of A.I.G.'s operations. (In the village of Stowe, seven miles from the ski area, comparable lots cost less than $200,000.) Street signs with names like Hayride Drive and Inspiration Lane have popped up.</p>
        <p>Skiers can now look down from almost any trail on Spruce Peak at the skeletons of a handful of wooden town houses peeking out of the snow. Eleven town houses have been sold, at an average price of $1.8 million. Nearby, 36 acres of pine, spruce, maple and poplar were cut last summer to make way for the first six holes of the 18-hole golf course.</p>
        <p>In May, construction will start on the new Spruce Peak base lodge, with condominium units priced at $3 million to $5 million on the top two floors. The Stowe Mountain Lodge, a condo hotel, is scheduled to open in 2007, with 99 units priced from $350,000 to $1.6 million and two floors of time-share units.</p>
        <p>Some skiers see the expansion of Stowe as inevitable. ''No one wants to chop down trees,'' said James Keravich of Exeter, N.H., as he took a break outside the Mount Mansfield lodge one Sunday last month. ''But we want the ski area to flourish. Improvements are necessary -- especially snow quality.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lunde, the resort's president, said it was exactly this reasoning that led to the new project. In 1991, the State of Vermont told Stowe it would have to cut its intake of water for snowmaking from a nearby river because fish were dying downstream. A.I.G. agreed to invest $15 million to build snowmaking ponds, to store water throughout the year and to ease pressure on the river, but only if it could develop land to offset the cost.</p>
        <p>At the same time, competitors like Stratton in southern Vermont and Mont-Tremblant in Quebec were adding slopeside condos and pedestrian villages with shops and restaurants.</p>
        <p>''People don't want to have to drive every day to the ski-area parking lot,'' said Michael Berry, the president of the National Ski Areas Association in Lakewood, Colo. ''They want to be able to walk out of their condo, take a stroll in the evening, have dinner, then stroll back. A lot of resorts have come to grips with this and have addressed it. Stowe's customers were still coming, but they were getting older. And they weren't attracting a new, younger group.''</p>
        <p>Stowe became a summer resort in the 19th century, when a toll road brought carriages to a grand hotel at the 4,393-foot summit of Mount Mansfield. In the 1930's, the Civilian Conservation Corps cut ski trails on Mount Mansfield by hand, creating its top-to-bottom, thrill-a-minute runs. Later, Stowe produced Olympic skiers (Billy Kidd was a medalist in 1964) and drew guests to the lodge run by the Trapp family, whose story inspired ''The Sound of Music.''</p>
        <p>A.I.G.'s connection to Stowe started when C.V. Starr, the company's founder, invested in the resort in 1946. (A.I.G.'s current chairman and chief executive, Maurice R. Greenberg, 79, has a home in Stowe and still skis.) Stowe is A.I.G.'s sole ski business, an anomaly in an industry dominated by three large players -- Vail Resorts, Intrawest and American Skiing -- that have gobbled up small, independent operations. But Stowe, backed by the deep pockets of A.I.G. (the company had revenue of $98.6 billion last year), is hardly a typical independently owned resort.</p>
        <p>A.I.G. insists that its recent legal problems will have no effect on Stowe. Last year, it agreed to pay $126 million to settle federal investigations into transactions it arranged that helped other companies inflate the appearance of financial strength.</p>
        <p>''We're building 420 units -- that's one-fifth the size of what Stratton built,'' said Jeff Wise, a spokesman for the resort. ''If you look at the size of the Stowe area, that's a really small and tasteful alpine village.'' The company has agreed to cede title to more than 2,000 acres for preservation and to preserve another 800 acres permanently. (Because Mount Mansfield is within the Green Mountain State Forest, that section of the resort was already protected from further development.)</p>
        <p>BUT some people still say the project is too big. Village stores already worry that skiers will pass them by. ''It's scary how busy this town can be, and people aren't walking on Main Street,'' said Gail Wheel, who plans to close her Wild Life Gift Shop this summer, after seven years.</p>
        <p>Real estate prices, among the highest in Vermont and on the rise, are pushing out some local workers, and 45 percent of the housing units in Stowe are second homes. The median sale price of a house is about $450,000. A two-bedroom condo in town can be had for as little as $150,000; larger units closer to the mountain go for as much as $840,000.</p>
        <p>The three other resorts in Stowe that cater to the luxury market are working hard to update their own properties, hoping to ride the wave of the Stowe Mountain Resort's expansion.</p>
        <p>Stoweflake, a 120-room hotel and conference center, has spent $25 million the last six years, adding meeting space and a 50,000-square-foot spa. Topnotch, also with 120 rooms, is remodeling and enlarging its spa.</p>
        <p>High above the valley, Johannes von Trapp, the youngest of the singing Trapp family and owner of the 96-room Trapp Family Lodge, is critical of those who resist change. ''The state is full of flatlanders with guilt complexes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Last summer, he decided to put aside plans to develop a 500-acre parcel he owns after encountering community opposition. But he has begun selling time shares in a 40-unit town house development he started last year on his property.</p>
        <p>''Skiers don't want to rough it anymore,'' he said. ''Forty years ago, people went skiing and didn't mind sleeping in a dormitory with 20 other people and eating family style. Stowe was lovely then. But everybody was broke.''</p>
        <p>HAVENS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
