<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Christopher Unlikely to Meet Dissidents</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="673639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOST-FAVORED-NATION TREATMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHINA-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHRISTOPHER, WARREN M (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Most-Favored-Nation Treatment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1D7143DF932A25750C0A962958260" item-length="1020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Christopher Unlikely to Meet Dissidents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, March 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite wide anticipation among Chinese dissidents that Secretary of State Warren Christopher would meet with them during his three-day visit to Beijing, he said today that he had no plan at the moment to do so.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher gave no reason for his decision, which he disclosed at a briefing after meeting with Japanese Government leaders today. Asked by a reporter whether he would meet with political dissidents during the visit, his first to China as Secretary of State, he replied, "I don't have any plans to do so at the present time."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite wide anticipation among Chinese dissidents that Secretary of State Warren Christopher would meet with them during his three-day visit to Beijing, he said today that he had no plan at the moment to do so.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher gave no reason for his decision, which he disclosed at a briefing after meeting with Japanese Government leaders today. Asked by a reporter whether he would meet with political dissidents during the visit, his first to China as Secretary of State, he replied, "I don't have any plans to do so at the present time."</p>
        <p>There has been considerable speculation in China that Mr. Christopher may use what is shaping up as a high-stakes trip to hold a symbolically important meeting with Wei Jingsheng, China's most prominent dissident.</p>
        <p>But the State Department spokesman, Michael McCurry, said that such a meeting is unlikely because Mr. Christopher does not want to divert attention from the main purpose of his trip, which is to impress upon the Chinese Government that it must improve its human rights record if the United States is to extend China's preferential trade status in June.  Putting Dissidents at Risk</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher is also concerned that by holding such a meeting, he could put more dissidents at risk, Mr. McCurry added.</p>
        <p>Asked whether dissidents who are viewed as potential candidates for a meeting with Mr. Christopher could find themselves at risk, Mr. McCurry said: "It's pretty clear that's what's happening. That's what Wei Jingsheng would conclude."</p>
        <p>After John Shattuck, the Assistant Secretary of State for Human Rights, met with Mr. Wei last week, Mr. Wei was detained for 30 hours and interrogated.</p>
        <p>Other senior officials traveling with Mr. Christopher said they had argued that such a meeting could be counterproductive because it could further antagonize the Chinese. America Is a Crucial Market</p>
        <p>The World Bank estimates that preferential low tariffs affect 96 percent of China's exports to the United States. If China's preferential trade status were eliminated, its trade surplus with the United States, which was $18.2 billion last year and could reach $24 billion this year, would dramatically shrink, jeopardizing a cash flow that is crucial for China's expanding economy.</p>
        <p>[ In an expression of support for Mr. Christopher's difficult mission, 275 members of the House of Representatives signed a letter urging him to press for "substantial progress in human rights and full compliance with the President's executive order outlining conditions for renewal of most-favored-nation trade status." ]</p>
        <p>The Chinese have not demanded outright that Mr. Christopher refrain from meeting with dissidents, but have expressed their concern more subtly, the American officials said.</p>
        <p>"They haven't made any threats; they have expressed a keen interest into what all of his meetings are," said one official. "They have said, 'We consider internal matters should not be part of the dialogue. How we enforce our laws shouldn't be part of the discussions.' "</p>
        <p>China's leaders have rejected American pressure to ease political repression, arguing that it amounts to blatant interference in their internal affairs. But in mid-January, the Administration thought it was making some headway when President Jiang Zemin told a Congressional delegation that China was "going to make an effort" to meet American concerns about rights. Planning Has Been Difficult</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Christopher's senior aides have suggested that he consider canceling some of the meetings his delegation is planning or cut short his trip if it starts off badly.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCurry indicated that planning with the Chinese had been so difficult that "they were still arguing about what type of car Christopher would drive in." He added that "some of the meetings are not coming together."</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher is also planning to spend part of Sunday on a sightseeing tour of the capital, but that could be canceled if he does not want to appear too friendly to his hosts.</p>
        <p>Among the meetings that could be canceled or cut short are military talks that are to be conducted by Frank G.  Wisner, the Under Secretary of Defense for Policy, senior Administration officials said. For now Mr. Wisner, who would be the highest-ranking Pentagon official to visit Beijing since before the 1989 crackdown against the democracy movement, intends to remain in China after Mr. Christopher leaves to discuss ways to upgrade the military relationship between the two countries.</p>
        <p>Such links could include cooperative military efforts in peacekeeping, disaster relief and conversion of defense industries.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Wisner's visit is also intended to open a channel for human rights discussions with the military establishment, another key constituency of the Chinese leadership, a senior State Department official said. Lecturing Japanese Leaders</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher spent much of his day in Tokyo lecturing Japanese leaders on the need for them to live up to the specific pledges they made last July to cut their trade surplus with Washington. But he did not engage in serious negotiating and made no headway in convincing the Japanese to take concrete action.</p>
        <p>His visit to Beijing promises to be even more difficult because of the recent crackdown on dissidents in Beijing and Shanghai, which has left American policymakers baffled and disturbed.</p>
        <p>Other Secretaries of State have learned the hard way that calling on the Chinese does not necessarily produce diplomatic victories.</p>
        <p>During a farewell visit to Beijing in the summer of 1988, George P. Shultz was warmly told by Foreign Minister Qian Qichen, "The door of China is forever open to you." But the outgoing Secretary of State failed to convince his Chinese hosts to curb their sales of missiles to the Middle East.</p>
        <p>In November 1991, the last time a Secretary of State visited China, James A. Baker 3d ended talks without progress toward easing China's suppression of rights and left the country with the misimpression that the Chinese would adhere to pledges not to export missile technology in violation of an international accord.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
