<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buenos Aires Journal;   Menems' Marriage: Well-Matched Pillow Fights?</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="347019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARGENTINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHRISTIAN, SHIRLEY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MENEM, CARLOS SAUL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SENEM, ZULEMA YOMA DE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D6103DF936A15757C0A966958260" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buenos Aires Journal;   Menems' Marriage: Well-Matched Pillow Fights?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHIRLEY CHRISTIAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHRISTIAN, SHIRLEY</byline>
      <dateline>BUENOS AIRES, April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A group of retirees interrupted a hunger strike in front of a Government office recently to call on Zulema Yoma de Menem, the Argentine First Lady, and press demands for pension increases to cover inflation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A group of retirees interrupted a hunger strike in front of a Government office recently to call on Zulema Yoma de Menem, the Argentine First Lady, and press demands for pension increases to cover inflation.</p>
        <p>A group of retirees interrupted a hunger strike in front of a Government office recently to call on Zulema Yoma de Menem, the Argentine First Lady, and press demands for pension increases to cover inflation.</p>
        <p>''She told us to keep fighting out here and she would keep fighting from inside,'' a leader of the delegation said after the meeting at the presidential residence in the suburb of Olivos.</p>
        <p>Such comments would fit into a pattern of statements and actions that make the wife of President Carlos Saul Menem appear to be one of the strongest critics of her husband's policies, if not an outright opponent.</p>
        <p>At times, she seems to be advocating one set of policies from the house in Olivos, while he seems to be directing another from his offices in the downtown Government house, known as Casa Rosada. In theory, although not always in practice, they both live at Olivos.</p>
        <p>''At this point,'' Mr. Menem said recently, ''I'm not going to go around hiding our diversity of opinions.''</p>
        <p>In the Footsteps of Eva Peron</p>
        <p>While Mr. Menem has set out to turn back half a century of state dominance of the Argentine economy, much of it attributed to past policies of his own Peronist party, she prefers a more traditional Peronist approach that would allow her to play the social benefactress role that Eva Peron once filled.</p>
        <p>She has repeatedly asserted that her husband is surrounded by corrupt or untrustworthy people and has pointed the finger at, among others, Health and Social Action Minister Eduardo Bauza and Senator Eduardo Menem, the President's younger brother.</p>
        <p>She recently complained that one of the secretaries in Casa Rosa wore her skirts too short and her blouses too tight.</p>
        <p>Also, she has had frequent friendly conversations with two of her husband's most strident critics: Col. Mohamed Ali Seineldin, a leader of a dissident faction of the army, and Saul Ubaldini, a labor leader.</p>
        <p>When a journalist asked Mr. Menem about those meetings, he responded, ''What do you want me to do about it?''</p>
        <p>Moves Into an Apartment</p>
        <p>At the beginning of the year, saying the telephones in the presidential residence were all bugged, Mrs. Menem moved into an apartment she owns in the most chic part of the city for several weeks. But many political analysts thought the real reason was her differences with her husband over policies and Government appointments.</p>
        <p>Until Mr. Menem took office last July, the differences for which he and his wife were known were primarily those linked to his proudly admitted womanizing. The 54-year-old President recently said his reputation was ''very exaggerated, of course, because I'm not as seductive as it seems.''</p>
        <p>The Menems had two long separations while he was Governor of the province of La Rioja, during which the slick magazines carried details like his demand for divorce on the ground that her ''cultural level'' did not match his. She responded in a document to the judge saying his complaints were a sign of his ''moral mediocrity'' since he had lived with her for years.</p>
        <p>The divorce proceeding was quietly halted early in 1988, a few months before he was nominated for the presidency, but he continued telling people he was separated. Then a newspaper advertisement appeared, signed by their two college-age children, denying the separation and asserting that the entire family was living together in the Governor's residence in La Rioja.</p>
        <p>A Meeting in Damascus</p>
        <p>The Menems' marriage 23 years ago was, by all accounts, arranged by the two families, both of them tightknit Arab clans that immigrated from Syria early in the century. Although both were from La Rioja, the couple met in Damascus.</p>
        <p>The Yoma family, bigger and richer than the Menems, had returned there because the father wanted to live his final years in his homeland. The Menems, unhappy over their son's romance with a divorced young woman with a child, took him to Syria for the express purpose of finding a proper wife.</p>
        <p>Some versions say that despite the arranged nature of the union, there was an attraction between the two from the moment they met, although she has said the marriage was rocky from the outset because he continued to see his first love.</p>
        <p>Their reconciliation at the outset of his presidential campaign was, by all accounts, a political arrangement, not a romantic one. Nevertheless, she was at his side throughout the campaign, and they often displayed affection for each other. As First Lady, she has taken a more public role at her husband's side than has been the case in Argentina, except for the wives of Juan Peron.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Menem, who lists her age as 46 but has been put at several years older in some published accounts, encourages people to call her Zulema, which she considers a sign of affection.</p>
        <p>'The Most Peronist'</p>
        <p>With her fluffy blond hair and a fashionable wardrobe that leans toward reds and beiges, Mrs. Menem cuts a striking figure. She acknowledges having had surgery to flatten her stomach and refine her nose but says she has not yet had a facelift.</p>
        <p>Calling herself ''the most Peronist'' member of the Government, Mrs. Menem is a frequent visitor to hospitals and schools, calling attention to the serious shortages of medicine, food and equipment that are common in these days of public belt-tightening in Argentina. Businesses and individuals send her donations that she turns over to such institutions, and she receives countless delegations of people needing help.</p>
        <p>Her goal, she said, is to see to it that the price of the economic changes her husband is trying to make ''should not be so heavy on the most humble sectors of society.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
