<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Richer's Third Goal Conquers Capitals in Overtime</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="488388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON CAPITALS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY DEVILS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">YANNIS, ALEX</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Washington Capitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D71E38F932A15752C1A967958260" item-length="1099" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Richer's Third Goal Conquers Capitals in Overtime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YANNIS, ALEX</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Nov. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils have had difficulty motivating themselves against teams in the National Hockey League's lower echelons, but they seem to be in sync against the league's elite.</p>
        <p>After losses to the Islanders and the Winnipeg Jets, the Devils played their best game in a while tonight in achieving a 6-5 overtime triumph over the Washington Capitals at Byrne Meadowlands Arena. It was the first Patrick Division defeat for Washington this season after nine victories in nine games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils have had difficulty motivating themselves against teams in the National Hockey League's lower echelons, but they seem to be in sync against the league's elite.</p>
        <p>After losses to the Islanders and the Winnipeg Jets, the Devils played their best game in a while tonight in achieving a 6-5 overtime triumph over the Washington Capitals at Byrne Meadowlands Arena. It was the first Patrick Division defeat for Washington this season after nine victories in nine games.</p>
        <p>Stephane Richer, who was without a goal in four games, led the Devils with three goals, including the winner, 1 minute 41 seconds into overtime.</p>
        <p>"It was a huge win for our team," said Tom McVie, the coach of the Devils. "When they scored with 17 seconds left, it showed the character of our team." MacLean Out for Season</p>
        <p>The triumph over the team with the league's best winning percentage (15-5-0 for .750) was tempered by the news that John MacLean would be lost for the remainder of the season.</p>
        <p>MacLean, a 40-plus goal scorer the last three seasons for the Devils, will undergo reconstructive surgery within a week for the torn anterior cruciate ligament in his right knee he suffered in an exhibition game against the Islanders on Sept. 30.</p>
        <p>The operation will be performed by Dr. Barry Fisher, the team orthopedist. MacLean said that he was deeply involved in the decision to have surgery.</p>
        <p>"We tried rehabilition and it didn't work," MacLean said. "The last couple of weeks the knee just didn't get any stronger. It didn't respond."</p>
        <p>The Capitals responded tonight, after the Devils built a 4-1 lead early in the second period and led by 5-3 with 5:36 left in the second. Washington tied it on goals by Mike Ridley with 4:05 left in the second and Peter Bondra with 17 seconds left in regulation.</p>
        <p>Bondra's goal, his 12th of the season, came after the Capitals had pulled their goalie, Don Beaupre, for an extra skater.</p>
        <p>The Devils kept their heads up after Bondra's goal and took the initiative in the overtime, with Richer giving the Devils the triumph with his 11th goal of the season.</p>
        <p>The Devils displayed their offensive tendencies from the opening face-off in the overtime, the first of the season for the Capitals, forcing the play near Beaupre.</p>
        <p>Richer's game-winner gave him the seventh hat trick in his career. It came seconds after he had hit the right post with a blistering shot. Richer Unleashes Backhander</p>
        <p>Richer ended up with the puck after it had gone through his teammate Aleksei Kasatonov. He beat Beaupre with a backhander from close range on the right.</p>
        <p>Kasatonov, Slava Fetisov and Claude Lemieux also had goals for the Devils (12-9-0) against Beaupre, who faced 36 shots, including two in the overtime.</p>
        <p>Dale Hunter, Sylvain Cote and Dimitri Khristich had the early goals for the Capitals against Craig Billington, who made only his second start of the season. Billington faced 28 shots, none in the overtime, and looked sharp despite his inactivity.</p>
        <p>Washington's loss was the first in five games and had little effect on Coach Terry Murray, who sounded like a winner after the game.</p>
        <p>"We were gambling quite a bit," Murray said. "One of our defensemen was jumping into the play a little too quickly. Nothing that cannot be corrected. We have a productive team."</p>
        <p>"Call it job-sharing," Ridley said about the vast contribution by different Capitals. "Every night, it seems like a different player is making a contribution."</p>
        <p>Hunter opened the scoring 4:12 into thr game, but the Devils came back for the next four goals.</p>
        <p>Kasatonov started the Devils' rally with his second of the season and first since opening night, 13:55 into the game.</p>
        <p>Richer followed with his first two goals, at 16:19 of the first and 37 seconds into the middle period, before Lemieux extended the Devils' lead to 4-1, shoetly after the Devils had killed their first penalty of the night.</p>
        <p>Washington narrowed the gap on goals by Cote at 11:26 of the second and Khristich less than two minutes later. Both came shortly after the Devils had missed chances at the other end.</p>
        <p>Not to be outdone by Kasatonov, Fetisov matched his Soviet counterpart by scoring his first goal since opening night for a 5-3 lead, 14 minutes 24 seconds into the period, after a pinpoint pass from Kevin Todd on the right. Jets 3, Islanders 1</p>
        <p>WINNIPEG, Manitoba (AP) -- Goaltender Bob Essensa kicked out 40 shots to record his third straight victory and 50th of his National Hockey League career as Winnipeg beat the Islanders.</p>
        <p>Essensa, named the N.H.L.'s player of the week last week, had the announced crowd of 10,224 chanting his name as he stood his ground several times to foil the Islanders.</p>
        <p>Petri Skriko and Darrin Shannon also scored for the Jets, who climbed into second place in the Smythe Division with a record of 10-8-4.</p>
        <p>Dave McLlwain scored for the Islanders, who were playing their second game in two nights following a 7-4 win at Minnesota.</p>
        <p>Danny Lorenz, playing first game in goal for Islanders this season, also put in a strong performance with 26 saves.</p>
        <p>The Jets opened the scoring at 7:17 of the first period with a goal by Skriko, his second of the season and first since being obtained from the Boston Bruins last month. Skriko swooped in over the blue line and fired a wrist shot from the faceoff circle.</p>
        <p>McLlwain tied the score 5 minutes later on a power play by slipping a rebound under Essensa.</p>
        <p>Romaniuk gave the Jets a 2-1 lead on a second-period power play when he whipped in a Phil Housley pass from the faceoff circle.</p>
        <p>Shannon scored into an empty net with 7 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Both goalies made several stops on players who were in alone. Essensa, who has allowed only four goals in his last four starts, blocked successive shots from the crease by Joe Reekie and Derek King. Lorenz stopped Romaniuk from in close twice and Shannon from the crease.</p>
        <p>The two goalies also had a little luck: two shots that got by Lorenz hit the post, while Essensa watched from his back as the puck banked out off the cross bar.</p>
        <p>Jets defenseman Dean Kennedy left the game in the first period with an injured left knee, which will require further tests Thursday. Blues 5, Maple Leafs 2</p>
        <p>ST. LOUIS (AP) -- Brett Hull ended a season-long frustration against goaltender Grant Fuhr with two goals and two assists and Jeff Brown also scored twice as St. Louis defeated Toronto.</p>
        <p>Before Hull's goal in the first period, Fuhr had stopped him 18 straight times in four games, including 11 shots in one game. The goals gave Hull the league lead with 18, one ahead of Quebec's Owen Nolan.  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
