<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Again, the Hoffa Name Rouses the Teamsters' Union</title>
    <meta content="17TEAM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="890485"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">James P. Hoffa</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Brotherhood of Teamsters</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffa, James P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffa, James R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carey, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0D6153AF934A25752C1A960958260" item-length="1914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Again, the Hoffa Name Rouses the Teamsters' Union</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>MINNEAPOLIS, Nov. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James P Hoffa, son of James R Hoffa, is waging campaign to unseat Ron Carey as head of International Brotherhood of Teamsters, nation's largest private-sector union; he vows to restore Teamsters union to greatness it had under his fabled father; by most accounts, it is neck-and-neck race, pitting one of most famous labor names of last 50 years against man hailed by many outsiders for cleansing a notoriously corrupt union; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was 10 below zero in the frozen-food warehouse, and suddenly the whirring of the forklifts stopped as bundled-up workers rushed over to meet James P. Hoffa and hear him vow to restore the International Brotherhood of Teamsters to the greatness it had under his fabled father.</p>
        <p>Wearing just a windbreaker over a sweater, Mr. Hoffa led his retinue past boxes of frozen turkeys and broccoli piled 20 feet high, all the time urging workers in the warehouse near here to vote for him for teamsters' union president. Excited by the Hoffa name and ignoring his opponent's accusations that he is close to organized crime, the workers gave him wide-open smiles. Made comfortable by his easy manner, many gave him a friendly chuck on the shoulder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was 10 below zero in the frozen-food warehouse, and suddenly the whirring of the forklifts stopped as bundled-up workers rushed over to meet James P. Hoffa and hear him vow to restore the International Brotherhood of Teamsters to the greatness it had under his fabled father.</p>
        <p>Wearing just a windbreaker over a sweater, Mr. Hoffa led his retinue past boxes of frozen turkeys and broccoli piled 20 feet high, all the time urging workers in the warehouse near here to vote for him for teamsters' union president. Excited by the Hoffa name and ignoring his opponent's accusations that he is close to organized crime, the workers gave him wide-open smiles. Made comfortable by his easy manner, many gave him a friendly chuck on the shoulder.</p>
        <p>In a nearby lunchroom, it took Mr. Hoffa 30 seconds to get five dozen warehousemen shouting and clapping. ''It's shameful that what used to be the most powerful union in the free world has sunk to such levels,'' he said in a voice almost as thunderous as that of his father, James R. Hoffa. ''The union's divided. It's weak. You have a once-in-a-lifetime chance to remake the teamsters.''</p>
        <p>Outside the lunchroom, Jerry Bruns, a forklift operator, shouted,  ''A friend of mine told me to tell you that if you're 10 percent of what your father was, you'll be a great leader.''</p>
        <p>In a contest that has all the vigor and vitriol the race for the White House lacked, Mr. Hoffa is challenging Ron Carey, the incumbent, to head the nation's largest private-sector union. By most accounts, it is a neck-and-neck race, pitting one of the most famous labor names of the last 50 years against a man hailed by many outsiders for cleansing a notoriously corrupt union.</p>
        <p>''The stakes are extremely high,'' said Kate Bronfenbrenner, research director at the Cornell School of Industrial and Labor Relations. ''The whole labor movement is watching.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carey is also crisscrossing the country for votes, fighting criticism that he has left the union, which has 1.4 million members, in a shambles.</p>
        <p>He boasts that he has ousted corrupt officials, reversed a membership decline and balanced the union's budget. He says that if Mr. Hoffa is elected to a five-year term, the corrupt old guard will regain control and the mob will again call the shots in a union that includes warehouse workers, police officers, freight haulers, flight attendants and school bus drivers.</p>
        <p>In the four decades before Mr. Carey took office, in 1992, three teamsters presidents went to prison, including Mr. Hoffa's charismatic father, who led the union from 1957 to 1967. The elder Hoffa, a streetwise seventh-grade dropout who turned the teamsters into a powerhouse, went to prison for jury tampering and disappeared in 1975 in what was widely seen as a mob execution.</p>
        <p>The younger Hoffa, a stocky 55-year-old labor lawyer who has not worked as a teamster since college, is more polished, and less muscled, than his father. But he promises to bring back the teamsters' glory by borrowing the best from the elder Hoffa: his grit at the bargaining table, his knack for inspiring members and his ability to cripple the nation by calling out his truckers. The younger Hoffa's backers affectionately call him Jimmy Jr.; his foes sneeringly refer to him as Junior.</p>
        <p>Of the family name, Mr. Hoffa said: ''It's an asset. Everywhere I go, people say, 'Without your father, I wouldn't be in the middle class. I couldn't send my kids to college.' It's because of Jimmy Hoffa that a lot of these people have good incomes. He doubled and tripled their incomes.''</p>
        <p>The candidates are brutally blunt, trading charges of corruption and incompetence and smear campaigns.</p>
        <p>''He's an empty suit,'' said Mr. Carey, a 60-year-old former delivery man from Queens and longtime president of the local representing New York's United Parcel Service workers. ''He's a front man for the mob. If he didn't have that last name, he wouldn't have a chance. He'd be back at his country club playing golf.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa responded: ''He's over his head. He doesn't know what he's doing. He lacks star quality. By any measure, this has been the worst five years in the history of the union. It's on the brink of bankruptcy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa bases his appeals on concerns that the union has lost clout. But Mr. Carey's backers say that stems from tougher management attitudes toward labor and from trucking deregulation, which squeezed profits and contributed to the teamsters' loss of 500,000 members, far more than most unions, before Mr. Carey took office.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, ballots went out in an all-mail election supervised by the Federal Government. Ballot counting will begin on Dec. 10.</p>
        <p>In 1989, the teamsters settled a lawsuit brought by the Government, which charged in its complaint that the union had a ''devil's pact'' with the Mafia. In the breakthrough settlement, the union agreed to rank-and-file elections for president and to an Independent Review Board, which is charged with ferreting out corruption and includes William H. Webster, the former director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</p>
        <p>In 1991, Mr. Carey was elected president in the union's first rank-and-file election, receiving 48.5 percent of the vote and beating two veteran insiders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carey has put 67 of the union's 600 locals into trusteeship, usually after the review board found corruption. Under trusteeship, national union officials appoint someone to run the local.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa has said he will give more power back to the locals, a move Mr. Carey says will give corrupt heads of locals more autonomy to run their fiefdoms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carey says that if he is re-elected, he will step up efforts to attract new members. He also promises to continue searching for corporate pressure points -- by, for example, attacking top executives' salaries -- to help win good contracts.</p>
        <p>The Hoffa-Carey showdown has the trappings of a Presidential race, though smaller. There are banners, buttons, phone banks, pollsters and audiotapes sent to voters. In the past week, Mr. Hoffa has held rallies or fund raisers in six states; Mr. Carey has campaigned in four. Both have also appeared on radio shows.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa, a graduate of the University of Michigan Law School, asserts that if he wins, he will provide fresh, dynamic leadership like that of John J. Sweeney, who won the A.F.L.-C.I.O presidency last year with Mr. Carey's support.</p>
        <p>But some union leaders say a Hoffa victory could sabotage the movement because the Hoffa name could steal Mr. Sweeney's spotlight and because some of his opponent's prominent associates have criminal records and ties to organized crime, according to Government officials.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Hoffa denied ever associating with organized crime. But the Carey campaign has sought to rebut such denials by linking Mr. Hoffa to Mafia figures and publicizing the criminal records and mob ties of some of his associates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa long served as legal counsel to a Michigan teamsters local whose president, George Vitale, was convicted of taking kickbacks and was suspended by the Independent Review Board for embezzling $10,116 and attempting to appropriate a car. Mr. Hoffa was also counsel to a Michigan teamsters' health and welfare fund when the Federal Government ordered its officers to repay $725,000 in excessive expenses, including the costs of golf trips and bar tabs for adult entertainment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa once invested in a partnership with Allen Dorfman, an associate of his father who was murdered in 1983 and who lent tens of millions of dollars in teamsters pension funds to mobsters. Mr. Hoffa said he had withdrawn when he learned of Mr. Dorfman's involvement.</p>
        <p>Frank Ragano, a longtime lawyer for the elder Hoffa, has said that two Mafia leaders, Santo Traficante and Carlos Marcello, each gave the younger Hoffa $5,000 as a wedding present. Mr. Hoffa has called Mr. Ragano a liar.</p>
        <p>William Hogan Jr., Mr. Hoffa's running mate for secretary-treasurer, quit the slate last summer when the union put his Chicago-based local under trusteeship because of a conflict of interest in which several Hogan relatives were officers in the local and investors in companies that did business with the local. Government officials said one investor was  fronting for a Chicago mobster.</p>
        <p>Noting that Mr. Hogan has not been charged with anything, Mr. Hoffa said Mr. Carey had put the Chicago local into trusteeship to embarrass the Hoffa slate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa, who says he will eradicate corruption, condemned Mr. Carey for publicizing charges of corruption. ''It's a smear campaign,'' he said. ''It's a calculated effort to avoid talking about the real issues.''</p>
        <p>The campaign, he insists, should focus on the incumbent's record. He said his opponent had let the teamsters' membership slide by 40,000 since he took office and had allowed the union's assets to shrink to $20 million from $153 million. He has also attacked Mr. Carey for signing a national freight agreement that doubles the amount of freight that trucking companies can transport by rail.</p>
        <p>''He's running away from his record,'' Mr. Hoffa said. ''The union is systematically being destroyed because of a lack of organizing, horrible contracts and the drop in assets.''</p>
        <p>He also accuses Mr. Carey of corruption. He says a Government witness, Alphonse D'Arco, once the acting head of the Lucchese crime family, said Mr. Carey had cooperated with him by having his local honor picket lines put up by mob-controlled unions.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Carey denied knowing Mr. D'Arco. He noted that the Independent Review Board had cleared him on these charges. ''It's a smear campaign,'' he said. ''To destroy you, they will say anything.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa said his opponent was wrong to negotiate with United Parcel when Mr. Carey's father, a onetime United Parcel driver, owned $1.9 million of the company's stock,  as his purchase of eight original shares in 1935 mushroomed in value. Mr. Carey said he knew nothing of his father's holdings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffa also questioned how Mr. Carey could make more than $700,000 in real estate investments in the 1980's when his salary was less than $45,000. Mr. Carey said that relatives had invested some of the money and that he was making money on properties he had sold.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carey passionately defended his record. To save money, he cut his salary to $150,000, from $225,000, sold the teamsters' two jets and eliminated a corruption-filled layer of bureaucracy, known as area conferences, which cost $11 million a year.  He said the union's membership grew by 4,000 last year, the first increase since 1979.</p>
        <p>Noting that the union's budget was balanced last year -- the first time in more than a decade -- he explained that the union's assets had dwindled mostly because predecessors had quadrupled strike benefits without providing for a way to pay for them. As for the national freight contract, he said he had had to make some compromises but had managed to rebuff demands to replace thousands of drivers with part-timers.</p>
        <p>But his proudest achievement of all, he said, was ousting or suspending more than 200 corrupt officials.</p>
        <p>''Whenever corruption raised its ugly head,'' he said, ''we moved to cut it off.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
