<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Katydids, Male Rivalry Poses as Synchrony</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="629412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KATYDIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSECTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CICADAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRICKETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FROGS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">YOON, CAROL KAESUK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amphibians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D71E3FF934A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Katydids, Male Rivalry Poses as Synchrony</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YOON, CAROL KAESUK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMONG the natural world's most spectacular sound and light shows are synchronized courtships, displays in which groups of males all croak or flash simultaneously to show their romantic intent to females. In Asia, a group of male fireflies can blink on and off together in the branches of a tree like long, perfect strings of Christmas lights. All around the world, male frogs, katydids, crickets and cicadas fill the night with the deafening alignment of their love songs.</p>
        <p>So impressively precise is the orchestration of these courting males that biologists have long assumed that they must be cooperating to keep their signals closely matched. But in a new study published in this week's issue of Nature, researchers say they have found that the males, rather than cooperating, are actually competing fiercely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMONG the natural world's most spectacular sound and light shows are synchronized courtships, displays in which groups of males all croak or flash simultaneously to show their romantic intent to females. In Asia, a group of male fireflies can blink on and off together in the branches of a tree like long, perfect strings of Christmas lights. All around the world, male frogs, katydids, crickets and cicadas fill the night with the deafening alignment of their love songs.</p>
        <p>So impressively precise is the orchestration of these courting males that biologists have long assumed that they must be cooperating to keep their signals closely matched. But in a new study published in this week's issue of Nature, researchers say they have found that the males, rather than cooperating, are actually competing fiercely.</p>
        <p>The new study, of conehead katydids, suggests that the males are trying to sing just ahead of their fellow choristers, not with them. The alignment of their songs is an incidental byproduct of their competition, but the human ear, with its crude sensitivity, perceives the songs as beautifully synchronized.</p>
        <p>"It's an important study," said Dr. Michael Ryan, a behavioral biologist at the University of Texas at Austin. "Now we don't need to try to explain why they're cooperating because in fact they're not cooperating. They're competing."</p>
        <p>Dr. Stanley Rand, a biologist at the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute in Panama, said: "I think it's quite an exciting study, and I think it's going to be influential. It's certainly going to affect the way I go around looking at the question of chorusing in frogs."</p>
        <p>Researchers had previously concentrated on hypotheses that attempted to explain what males might gain from synchronizing. Among them was the idea that individual males singing simultaneously with others might be more difficult for predators to locate by their songs. Another hypothesis suggested that a synchronous chorus would preserve intact the species-specific song or flashing pattern, keeping females interested instead of turning them away with a discombobulated mess of jammed signals. But no evidence of any advantage to synchronizing was found in the conehead study, said one of the researchers, Dr. Michael D. Greenfield, a behavioral ecologist at the University of Kansas.</p>
        <p>In a series of experiments that scientists have described as "elegant" and "beautifully executed," Dr. Greenfield and Igor Roizen, a computer scientist at the University of California at Los Angeles, deciphered the rules of competition that govern the timing of a male's singing.</p>
        <p>Male conehead katydids "sing" their song by rubbing their front wings together, producing a series of fairly regularly timed chirps, two to three per second for several minutes at a time. When Dr. Greenfield played recordings of the songs to katydids in the field in Panama, he found to his surprise that males did not synchronize with the recording. Instead, they appeared to reset their internal chirping metronome to start consistently just milliseconds before their recorded competitor's next chirp. Researchers were a bit befuddled by the males' determination to be the chorus leader, until they tested females to see what songs they preferred. In laboratory tests, when katydid females were given the choice of two speakers playing nearly simultaneous chirps, they consistently nuzzled the speaker playing the song with the leading chirp, even if it led the other by as little as a hundredth of a second. While theories abound, the researchers remain in the dark as to why conehead females should prefer the chorus leader.</p>
        <p>While a katydid might always be able to beat out a slow, regular recorded competitor to become the lead chirper, actual competitors can be faster and slower and can themselves change their speed. In the wild, katydids adjust to jump in as the leading chirper only as often as they can.  Presumably, he who sings first most, mates best.</p>
        <p>Early in the study of synchronous choruses, some doubted that the males were actually trying to synchronize, suggesting instead that such patterns were figments of the imaginations of a few scientists.</p>
        <p>To test whether males were actually synchronizing, a researcher asked naive observers to listen to different groups of singing crickets. Some groups of crickets had been made deaf so they could not respond to each others' songs, while others could hear. Observers described the hearing crickets as singing synchronously and the deaf crickets as singing every which way. The experiment has made synchrony an accepted natural phenomenon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
