<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gun Charges and Trouble South of the Border</title>
    <meta content="Y23GUN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1056224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DA113DF930A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gun Charges and Trouble South of the Border</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>CIUDAD JUAREZ, Mexico, Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Increasing number of Americans are landing in Mexican jails for gun possession; there are 78 United States citizens in Mexican jails after being arrested this year on arms charges; 72 of them were arrested at or near border and most, American officials say, were apparently guilty of simple blunders; some cases cited; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Johnny Manuel sat in the interview room at the Centro de Readaptacion Social Para Adultas, a dusty and sun-bleached prison at the foot of the Sierra de Juarez, telling his story in the bitter monotone of a man who has seen his nightmares grow bones.</p>
        <p>''It's like you've been swallowed up by a big monster,'' said Mr. Manuel, a slight man who drew hungrily on one menthol cigarette after another. ''I made a bad, bad mistake. Ruined my whole damn life, I guess.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Johnny Manuel sat in the interview room at the Centro de Readaptacion Social Para Adultas, a dusty and sun-bleached prison at the foot of the Sierra de Juarez, telling his story in the bitter monotone of a man who has seen his nightmares grow bones.</p>
        <p>''It's like you've been swallowed up by a big monster,'' said Mr. Manuel, a slight man who drew hungrily on one menthol cigarette after another. ''I made a bad, bad mistake. Ruined my whole damn life, I guess.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Manuel said his mistake was inadvertently crossing an international bridge while looking for a parking space -- with three guns belonging to his fiancee, a prison guard, in his car. He has been in the Juarez prison for nearly eight months, barely cracking the five-year sentence he drew for arms smuggling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manuel, a 49-year-old butcher from Lake Charles, La., is one of 78 United States citizens in Mexican jails after being arrested this year on arms charges. Seventy-two of them were arrested at or near the border and most, American officials say, were apparently guilty of simple blunders.</p>
        <p>Joseph Albanese, 24, and William Patterson, 25, friends from Ohio who were on a rattlesnake and coyote hunting trip to West Texas, said they, too, found themselves on the Mexican side of the border, with their hunting guns, before they could turn around. Robert Brown, 48, was leading 15 members of his family in two rented vans from Birmingham, Ala., to Oakland, Calif., when he said he made a wrong turn and ended up on a bridge he did not intend to cross with a shotgun and a World War II rifle. James Gray was taking his family camping in New Mexico when he decided to visit Ciudad Juarez for a Mexican dinner, not thinking about the 9-mm pistol in his vehicle, he said.</p>
        <p>In the most recent case, five Louisiana men in their late teens and early 20s, including two members of the University of Southwestern Louisiana football team, were arrested at an international crossing in Nuevo Laredo on Oct. 10 while on a South Texas hunting trip.</p>
        <p>Officials on both sides of the border are debating the reasons -- from lenient gun laws in Texas to overzealousness by Mexican authorities -- but the arrests have caused enough concern that the issue was raised in talks in June between the United States Secretary of State and her Mexican counterpart.</p>
        <p>In all, 135 Americans have been  arrested this year on firearms charges. Fifty-seven were released on bond, had their charges dropped or were convicted and sent back to the United States as part of a prisoner exchange program. The rest, like Mr. Manuel, sit in crowded Mexican jails and count the seconds.</p>
        <p>And it is not simply having guns. The same charges apply to possession of ammunition that apply to possession of a weapon, and some United States citizens have been jailed for having anywhere from a box of bullets to a handful of shotgun shells in the car. The charge depends to some degree on the caliber of weapon involved. Anything more powerful than a .38-caliber gun is considered a military weapon.</p>
        <p>The number of Americans imprisoned on arms charges in Mexican border towns has soared from just a handful last year to the scores this year, State Department officials said, not because more people have been arrested but because Mexican officials have been prosecuting more cases to the fullest.</p>
        <p>''There is not a heck of a lot of difference in the number of arrests,'' said a State Department official, who spoke on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>''What is different, is the outcome of the cases,'' the official said. ''Before, when someone inadvertently entered Mexico with a weapon they were briefly detained and usually informally allowed to return to the U.S. with the weapon seized. Now, in the same situation, they could end up in jail a long, long time.''</p>
        <p>Mexican customs and police officials deny this, and say they have no explanation for the increase in weapons prosecutions.</p>
        <p>''The policy in Mexico has not changed, it is the same,'' said Juan Manuel Rodriguez Cid, administrator of Mexican customs for the crossings in and near El Paso. ''We don't know what the reason is for this increase.''</p>
        <p>James L. Ward, United States consul general in Ciudad Juarez, said he, too, was not sure why more weapons prosecutions had been occurring. It could be that the Mexican Government decided to crack down on weapons cases, Mr. Ward said, or simply that looser gun laws in Texas and other states, combined with eased travel restrictions, led to more people driving into Mexico with guns in their cars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward and State Department officials emphasized that the Mexicans had legitimate concerns about guns crossing their border. Mexico has seen an increase in the number of weapons coming south, partly because of the drug trade and partly because of arms-for-profit schemes involving criminal gangs or rebels.</p>
        <p>''But the border officials tell us they don't have the discretion, or at least they perceive they don't have the discretion, to distinguish between cases that reach them,'' Mr. Ward said. ''Even when it's fairly clear that it is not an arms smuggler that they're dealing with, that it's a person who made a simple mistake, they often make no distinction. We're not saying Americans should get off scot-free. But to imagine that some guy would take two vans filled with 15 people in order to smuggle two weapons into Mexico just strains credulity.''</p>
        <p>The United States citizens arrested at the border tend to fall into three categories, American officials said: those who did not intend to enter Mexico, those who forgot they had  firearms in their vehicles and those who were not aware they carried  firearms.</p>
        <p>''There are also genuine cases of arms smugglers,'' one American official said, ''though in our experience these are few and far between.''</p>
        <p>The issue was discussed in talks in June between Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright and Foreign Secretary Rosario Green of Mexico,  and the State Department issued an announcement on Aug. 3 warning American citizens against taking weapons or ammunition into Mexico.</p>
        <p>A bill is under consideration in the Mexican Congress that would give border officials more discretion in deciding which cases to pursue most vigorously.</p>
        <p>None of this does anything for those under arrest and in prison, and especially for the handful, like Mr. Manuel, who have been convicted and sentenced. Families of those in prison say they have spent thousands of dollars, sometimes tens of thousands, fighting weapons charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Albanese and Mr. Patterson had their charges reduced from possession of military weapons -- a .22 semiautomatic rifle, a 20-gauge bolt action and a 12-gauge pump shotgun -- to a lesser charge and were expecting to pay a bond and soon be released and return home to Ohio.</p>
        <p>Mr. Albanese and Mr. Patterson were in high spirits recently when they returned from a hearing where they learned that the prosecutor's effort to reinstate the harsher charges against them had failed.</p>
        <p>''It's almost over, I can't believe it,'' Mr. Patterson said. ''It's like you fell into a big black hole and there's no way out.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Manuel offered them a cigarette, but his eyes clouded when he heard their good news. ''I wish I was going home with you guys,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In El Paso, where Interstate 10 runs less than a quarter-mile from the Rio Grande and a wrong exit can easily feed a driver onto a border bridge, United States officials say they have been improving the signs warning Americans about carrying firearms into Mexico.</p>
        <p>On the Mexican side of the bridge in Ciudad Juarez, there are 10 lanes for those with nothing to declare and 2 for those with items to declare.</p>
        <p>''If they come to us and declare that they have a firearm, we will allow them to leave it with us and pick it up on their way out of Mexico, no problem,'' said Mr. Rodriguez Cid, who added that no one had ever done this. ''But if they go through one of the other lanes and are pulled over and searched and we find firearms after that, even if they volunteer them to us, we must consider that they have intentionally not declared them and that they are being brought illegally into Mexico.''</p>
        <p>The best idea, Mr. Rodriguez Cid said, is for Americans ''to leave their weapons at home.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, the man who was leading two vans of relatives to California and now is awaiting trial on weapons charges, said he wished he had done that.</p>
        <p>His wife died of breast cancer in July. The trip to California in August was, in part, an effort to break out of the grief from that loss, he said. As he sat in a corner of the noisy prison yard, his eyes misted and he talked about his 16-year-old daughter and 14-year-old son, now left without their mother and him.</p>
        <p>''I could go through anything myself, but when I think about those kids,'' he said, then stopped and wiped his eyes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, who like the other Americans in the jail here said he had been treated well, recently started to work out and had asked permission to run laps on a jogging track. He has to toughen himself, he said, in case he ends up spending five years or more in the prison.</p>
        <p>He took another deep breath and looked through the bars toward the distant peaks of the Sierra de Juarez, leading back toward El Paso.</p>
        <p>''I told the people I was sorry,'' he said. ''What else can I do?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
