<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Giants' Defense Is a Study in Teamwork</title>
    <meta content="17GIAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/17/sports/football/17GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1424442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Rams</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/St. Louis Rams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="online_producer">St Louis Rams</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFDE1430F934A2575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1042" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Giants' Defense Is a Study in Teamwork</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giants' Defense a Study in Teamwork</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Sept. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants defense receives most credit by team and media for win over St Louis Rams (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As if they were law students presenting cases in a study group, the Giants' defensive backs met Saturday night to assess the subject assigned to each of them. Will Peterson talked about St. Louis receiver Torry Holt, Will Allen discussed the talents and tendencies of Isaac Bruce, and Jason Sehorn gave a dissertation on Ricky Proehl.</p>
        <p>Their dialogue covered crossing routes and slants, strengths and weaknesses. The Giants applied all the information and the schemes produced by the defensive coordinator, Johnnie Lynn, and shocked St. Louis on Sunday, 26-21.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After just two games, Giants veterans are saying this defense compares favorably with any they have been a part of.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As if they were law students presenting cases in a study group, the Giants' defensive backs met Saturday night to assess the subject assigned to each of them. Will Peterson talked about St. Louis receiver Torry Holt, Will Allen discussed the talents and tendencies of Isaac Bruce, and Jason Sehorn gave a dissertation on Ricky Proehl.</p>
        <p>Their dialogue covered crossing routes and slants, strengths and weaknesses. The Giants applied all the information and the schemes produced by the defensive coordinator, Johnnie Lynn, and shocked St. Louis on Sunday, 26-21.</p>
        <p>After just two games, Giants veterans are saying this defense compares favorably with any they have been a part of -- particularly the cornerbacks and the safeties.</p>
        <p>The Giants' 1-1 record is not, in itself, an indicator of promise. But they have played two of the league's best teams of 2001, and they defeated the defending National Football Conference champion Rams in their stadium -- a sign that Coach Jim Fassel's team is a serious playoff contender. The Giants are young and are gaining experience week by week, and as they proceed into what appears to be a weaker segment of their schedule -- they face Seattle here Sunday -- they could gather momentum.</p>
        <p>''I really believe that had we lost that game,'' Fassel said today of the Rams matchup, ''this team would not have lost its fight. With that said, this thing could really catapult us -- if we handle it correctly.''</p>
        <p>The Giants faced two of the finest offenses in the first two weeks of the season -- losing to the 49ers, 16-13, before defeating the Rams. Defending against quarterbacks Jeff Garcia and Kurt Warner, running backs Garrison Hearst and Marshall Faulk and wide receivers Terrell Owens, Bruce and Holt, the Giants' defense has generally controlled play. The longest touchdown allowed was a 9-yard catch-and-run by San Francisco's Hearst.</p>
        <p>The Giants have allowed only 11 plays of 15 yards or more, and their offense has generated 17 plays of 15 yards or more.</p>
        <p>Lynn has simplified what has been one of the league's more complex defenses, streamlining the game plans, focusing on fundamental principles and trying to eliminate confusion. He has rarely asked the linebackers and the defensive backs to join in the pursuit of the quarterback, instead choosing to keep seven and sometimes eight in pass coverage, confident this group can smother or at least slow the offense.</p>
        <p>The Giants' linemen have one sack in two games, but they have applied enough pressure to force Garcia and then Warner to release the ball sooner, and at shorter distances, than they would have preferred. At the same time, the linebackers and defensive backs have blanketed the receivers and given the linemen more time to pressure the quarterback. In these ways, the defense has functioned well as a unit.</p>
        <p>''Our defensive backs have been incredible,'' defensive end Michael Strahan said. ''The defense, as a whole, is playing well because everybody understands their role, and staying within that role and doing what you're supposed to do. No one cares about who's the superstar, who makes the plays. We only care about winning, and it's such an unselfish attitude.''</p>
        <p>It could not have happened if Peterson and Allen were not thriving as cornerbacks. Linebacker Micheal Barrow and defensive tackle Keith Hamilton talked separately about the second-year corners today, but Barrow and Hamilton used the same word to describe their work habits -- professional -- and each mentioned how much time the corners devoted to their craft, in the study of video and in the daily practice of technique.</p>
        <p>''I come in at 7 in the morning and Will Peterson is in here working, and Will Allen,'' Hamilton said. ''Both of them are out there after practice, working out. They're learning how to be professionals earlier than I did, and that's great to see. They know what it takes. I don't know if it's because of the leadership here or the work ethic they have -- maybe it's a little bit of both -- but to have such a work ethic when they're so young is a great thing.''</p>
        <p>Barrow said Allen and Peterson were very mature. ''You see Will A., Will P. here early in the morning watching film; they're here late watching film,'' he said. ''They're always working on the little things, and they have a desire and a passion to be the best. Most young guys who are talented like those guys are don't put in the work they put in. They rely on their athletic ability. To really take your game to another level is really 90 percent mental, and those guys are really aware of what's going on. They've become students of the game.''</p>
        <p>DeWayne Walker, who assumed Lynn's former role as coach of the defensive backs, asks each of them to study an aspect of the opponent's passing attack -- the players, the tendency of the team in the red zone -- before reporting his findings in the position meeting the day before the game. It is a system that forces a player to watch film, Sehorn said, and prods a greater understanding of what the opponent is trying to do. When Bruce and Holt lined up side by side, the defensive backs could make an educated guess that Bruce would probably take a crossing route and that Holt would make a vertical move down the field.</p>
        <p>Peterson says he takes the observations of the other defensive backs, compares them with his own, ''and you come up with a good conclusion of how to play against a guy, or how to play the offense.''</p>
        <p>Warner threw 11 passes in the direction of Peterson -- who played the entire game despite dislocating a toe in the first half -- and completed five. Peterson intercepted Warner's final pass to close out the victory, positive reinforcement for a player, a study group and a team working diligently.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
