<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Last One Out, Turn Off the TV; Labor Strife Has Sports Bar Owners Crying in Their Beers</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="719734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BARS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIKES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LEE MAZZILLI'S SPORTS CAFE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6DD163FF931A15753C1A962958260" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Last One Out, Turn Off the TV; Labor Strife Has Sports Bar Owners Crying in Their Beers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Kramer opened Lee Mazzilli's Sports Cafe on the Upper West Side in June, the week the Rangers won the Stanley Cup for the first time in 54 years. The Yankees seemed destined for the American League playoffs and maybe even the World Series. Mr. Kramer's long oak bar was crowded. The tables in the back were filled with neck-craning fans, staring up at the 100-channel video screens.</p>
        <p>What a difference a baseball strike can make. Not to mention a hockey lockout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Peter Kramer opened Lee Mazzilli's Sports Cafe on the Upper West Side in June, the week the Rangers won the Stanley Cup for the first time in 54 years. The Yankees seemed destined for the American League playoffs and maybe even the World Series. Mr. Kramer's long oak bar was crowded. The tables in the back were filled with neck-craning fans, staring up at the 100-channel video screens.</p>
        <p>What a difference a baseball strike can make. Not to mention a hockey lockout.</p>
        <p>"No baseball, no hockey, maybe no basketball," said Mr. Kramer, Lee Mazzilli's managing general partner. "It's like we put a jinx on sports."</p>
        <p>If off-the-field disputes were not keeping players from face-to-face ones with umpires or referees, the World Series would be starting tonight and the hockey season would be in its third week. But when there are no sports -- all right, almost no sports; there's football and preseason basketball, and there's always bowling -- New York's sports bars struggle.</p>
        <p>Even David Letterman jokes that the only thing they can find to fill those wall-to-wall televisions, the kind that show a double play in double life size, are "surveillance tapes from the Gap."</p>
        <p>For restaurants and bars catering to fans who eat, drink and breathe sports -- and pay for the eating and drinking part of it -- the price of a sports-limited fall has been higher than a player's salary. The City Comptroller's office estimates that the baseball and hockey labor headaches have cost businesses in New York $163 million. Of that, up to $40 million would have gone to sports-related restaurants and stadium concessions, with the restaurants losing the largest chunk.</p>
        <p>John Tepper Marlin, the number-crunching economist who prepared the estimates, said restaurant losses have more of an effect on the local economy than lost television or ticket revenues. He figures that each home game adds $2 million to the city's economy.</p>
        <p>But when it comes to restaurant revenue, he said that his conventional yardstick -- that each dollar a consumer spends on a home game typically generates $1.52 for the city's economy -- may be low by 33 percent.</p>
        <p>Sports restaurateurs do not need their calculators to tote up the effects of the baseball strike, which began on Aug. 12 over owners' demand for a cap on players' salaries.</p>
        <p>"It's hurting them," said Tim Zagat, who has stopped at up to 600 restaurants in the last three weeks for his restaurant guide. "They were so high last spring and summer, when the Rangers and Knicks were in the finals. They're way off from that. They're all kind of half-empty."</p>
        <p>To be sure, the spring and summer were unusually victorious, not just for the teams but also for restaurants that live or die by fans.</p>
        <p>After spending $500,000 for renovations in the spring, turning a storefront at 208 West 70th Street into a sports restaurant, with baseball bats on the ceiling and autographed photos of players on the walls, Mr. Kramer estimated that business was 50 percent below his first-year projections. He had expected to take in up to $2 million in his first 12 months. He had also expected 28 days of sold-out business from the playoffs and World Series. Instead, at 11 P.M. last Friday, he had 18 customers in a restaurant that seats 350.</p>
        <p>On the same night, Mickey Mantle's, a 160-seat restaurant on Central Park South, was half full. When the teams are on the field instead of on strike, Mickey Mantle's is S.R.O., and by the end of a home-game evening some of the players may stop by. "We were sitting around imagining what it would have been like if there had been a Yankees-Cleveland playoff," said an owner, William Liederman.</p>
        <p>Rand Neveloff, an owner at Boomer's Sports Club, named for Boomer Esiason, a quarterback for the Jets, was philosophical.</p>
        <p>"People are not thinking about sports," he said after surveying the 200 mostly empty seats at his restaurant and bar at 349 Amsterdam Avenue, between 76th and 77th Streets. "Short term, I am upset, yes, but there have been strikes before. A strike is a temporary thing. I have a 15-year lease. I'm here for the long term."</p>
        <p>The baseball strike is now the longest work stoppage in sports history. The National Hockey League season, to start on Oct. 1, was indefinitely postponed amid a similar dispute over salary caps. Now there's fear that the labor strife will spread to the National Basketball Association, whose season is to begin on Nov. 4.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kramer said there was a cushion in Lee Mazzilli's budget. "But we can't go much longer," he said. "If basketball is to go on strike and the hockey season is to be lost, you'll probably see, without exaggeration, 75 percent of the sports bars in the city go out of business."</p>
        <p>But gloom-and-doom forecasts are not universal. Mr. Liederman said that June had been so good with the Knicks and Rangers that Mickey Mantle's is still ahead of last year's volume, despite the baseball strike.</p>
        <p>Billy Rose, an owner of the Sporting Club, at 99 Hudson Street, was also upbeat. "Saturdays and Sundays are much better than last year," he said, "because fans are starved for something. Anything. Fridays, there's still the after-work crowd, but they don't stay as long because there's nothing to watch."</p>
        <p>To fill the video void, he has concentrated on the college football crowd, inviting alumni groups from Big Ten and Pac-10 schools when their games are shown on cable or satellite channels. These fans tend to spend less per person than the baseball or hockey crowds, he said, "but there are so many of them that they spend enough to make it worthwhile."</p>
        <p>But there is a but. Not having the Yankees go into the World Series has "probably cost me $100,000 in business," Mr. Rose said. "That's dollars you cannot get back. A blow."</p>
        <p>Until football started in early September, he said, there were nights when last call was between 9 and 10. And nights that cricket or croquet might have seemed more exciting than what was on television.</p>
        <p>"I had nights I had bowling on," said Mr. Kramer. "We must have watched the Muhammad Ali-Joe Frazier match a hundred times already. We must have watched the '86 World Series, with Lee at home plate with the tying run, a thousand times."</p>
        <p>Perhaps the fact that anyone was there at all was evidence that people go to sports bars for more than meeting Mr. or Ms. Right -- some do go for sports. Still, in the autumn of fans' discontent, not everyone finds big-screen time-killers a boring room-emptier.</p>
        <p>"I'm really enjoying watching these muscle men on TV," said Theresa Guarino, a nurse, eyes glued to a monitor at Lee Mazzilli's that was showing body builders. "I could sit here and watch these guys pump iron for hours."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
