<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Romania Struggles to Improve Its Image</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="368688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="EVOLUTION IN EUROPE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROMANIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASTASE, ADRIAN (MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDD1731F935A25754C0A966958260" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Romania Struggles to Improve Its Image</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>BUCHAREST, Romania, July 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: While Czechoslovakia's Foreign Minister argues for a new political architecture in Europe and Poland's Foreign Minister concentrates on safeguarding his nation's postwar borders, Romania's new Foreign Minister, Adrian Nastase, has a different focus: helping his nation join the family of Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: While Czechoslovakia's Foreign Minister argues for a new political architecture in Europe and Poland's Foreign Minister concentrates on safeguarding his nation's postwar borders, Romania's new Foreign Minister, Adrian Nastase, has a different focus: helping his nation join the family of Europe.</p>
        <p>While Czechoslovakia's Foreign Minister argues for a new political architecture in Europe and Poland's Foreign Minister concentrates on safeguarding his nation's postwar borders, Romania's new Foreign Minister, Adrian Nastase, has a different focus: helping his nation join the family of Europe.</p>
        <p>The 40-year-old minister is frustrated that even though Romania had the most difficult of the wave of revolutions in Eastern Europe, his nation again finds itself in Europe's doghouse. This time it is over the Government's summons to thousands of miners last month to put down protests.</p>
        <p>In an interview, the Foreign Minister said he saw his role as helping nudge his nation along, in a series of small steps at home and abroad, to show that Romania is on the road to democracy and to a market economy, after the overthrow of the Communist dictator, Nicolae Ceausescu, in December.</p>
        <p>'No One Is Perfect'</p>
        <p>''What we need is not a stamp of good conduct,'' Mr. Nastase said. ''No one is perfect. What we need is normal support from countries that have a lot of experience in democracy to help us improve the democratic structures in our country.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nastase said that Romania had already gone far toward democracy and human rights, allowing free elections, free emigration, freedom of speech and freedom of the press. He concedes that there have been slips, but he says the West has paid far more attention to this new democracy's blemishes than to its achievements.</p>
        <p>''It's a strange paradox that Romania, which made such a huge change, suffers from a lack of trust,'' he said. ''What we would like is to have a balanced image abroad, not to forget what is negative but trying to put things in clear perspective.''</p>
        <p>Nowadays, Mr. Nastase and other Romanian officials are so eager to shed their outcast status that they seem obsessed with their image abroad. In the face of criticism that it is a grab-bag of Ceausescu-era Communists, Romania's Government is straining to publicize its new program to adopt a market economy.</p>
        <p>Critics say freedom of speech in Romania falls short of Western standards. They note that the president of Bucharest's student association, Marian Munteanu, has been charged with inciting disorder. Many students say his only offense was outspokenly opposing the Government.</p>
        <p>Critics also say the Government's calling in of the miners, who went on a rampage against students, intellectuals, opposition leaders and others, shows a lack of faith in democracy.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Nastase said the Government called in the miners because it was threatened with being overthrown. Critics say there was no such threat. ''I am sure this kind of thing can't happen again,'' he said, frustrated that the miners' incident caused 24 Western nations to deny economic aid to Romania.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nastase was appointed Foreign Minister in early July after serving as spokesman for the ruling National Salvation Front. Under Mr. Ceausescu he was an international lawyer at Bucharest's Institute of Legal Reseach. Fluent in English and French, he is one of the stars in the new Cabinet of technocrats appointed by Prime Minister Petre Roman.</p>
        <p>'We Want to Be a Partner'</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister boasts that these young technocrats will push this impoverished nation forward. The Government also hopes that urbane young officials like Mr. Nastase will bolster Romania's image abroad.</p>
        <p>He says he would like Romania to join the European Community ''next week,'' if that were possible. He also wants to improve relations with Washington, which condemned Romania's Government for calling in the miners and for arresting student protesters. He said he was eager for young Romanians to study in the United States to learn how a market economy works.</p>
        <p>Unlike officials in Hungary, who are eager to leave the Warsaw Pact, Mr. Nastase suggests that pushing for withdrawal would be grandstanding. ''There is no need to jump from a car that doesn't have enough fuel to go forward,'' he said. ''The Warsaw Pact doesn't mean too much nowadays.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nastase also said that Romania was eager to avoid tensions over nationalist passions in the region.</p>
        <p>EVOLUTION IN EUROPE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
