<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Covenant House's New Broom</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="368680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COVENANT HOUSE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCGEADY, MARY ROSE (SISTER)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DA1631F935A25754C0A966958260" item-length="278" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Covenant House's New Broom</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Sister Mary Rose McGeady's priorities are very clear. She told an interviewer she's not aware of any more important job in America than ''taking care of our troubled young people.'' Fortunately for thousands of troubled young people, she's earned the chance to do just that, as the new director of Covenant</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Sister Mary Rose McGeady's priorities are very clear. She told an interviewer she's not aware of any more important job in America than ''taking care of our troubled young people.'' Fortunately for thousands of troubled young people, she's earned the chance to do just that, as the new director of Covenant</p>
        <p>Sister Mary Rose McGeady's priorities are very clear. She told an interviewer she's not aware of any more important job in America than ''taking care of our troubled young people.'' Fortunately for thousands of troubled young people, she's earned the chance to do just that, as the new director of Covenant House.</p>
        <p>This home for runaways founded by Father Bruce Ritter in 1968 fell into serious trouble last year. Or, rather, he did. Because Father Ritter and his shelter were virtually synonymous, Covenant House suffered grievously from the allegations of sexual and fiscal misconduct leveled against Father Ritter. Private donations, which account for almost all of the shelter's $87 million budget, slowed considerably and tragically. Staff and programs were cut back. It seemed that Covenant House would go down with its founder. It didn't, fortunately. It has a new board, and in Sister McGeady, a ''winner.'' That's how she is described by Sister Margaret John Kelly, her successor as a Provincial Mother Superior of the Daughters of Charity of St. Vincent de Paul. And that's how she's described by the Covenant House board.</p>
        <p>Sister McGeady started working with homeless and disturbed children and their families more than 30 years ago. She is associate executive director of Catholic Charities of the Diocese of Brooklyn, and in charge of a big staff, a big budget and a big range of local social service programs. Now she's got a big challenge: restoring luster, and lucre, to an organization that every year helps 28,000 youngsters in 15 cities.</p>
        <p>''People need this place,'' a Covenant House kid told a Times reporter last winter. ''Where you gonna go?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
