<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italian Leader In Showdown With Ex-Ally</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="732574"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ITALY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERLUSCONI, SILVIO (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COWELL, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0DA1038F932A15751C1A962958260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italian Leader In Showdown With Ex-Ally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COWELL, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, Dec. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi is approaching a showdown with his political adversaries -- possibly by Wednesday and certainly within days -- that will determine whether his Government will fall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berlusconi's battle against a revolt by the Northern League, a party in his coalition, will formally begin when the Prime Minister addresses Parliament on Wednesday. What happens next is as uncertain as the Government's future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi is approaching a showdown with his political adversaries -- possibly by Wednesday and certainly within days -- that will determine whether his Government will fall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berlusconi's battle against a revolt by the Northern League, a party in his coalition, will formally begin when the Prime Minister addresses Parliament on Wednesday. What happens next is as uncertain as the Government's future.</p>
        <p>A senior aide to Mr. Berlusconi, Giuliano Ferrara, predicted that Parliament would vote on a motion of confidence in the Government on Thursday or Friday. But Deputy Prime Minister Giuseppe Tatarella, a member of the neo-Fascist National Alliance, which supports Mr. Berlusconi, predicted the Government would step down earlier.</p>
        <p>"The Government will resign tomorrow," he said today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferrara said it was "highly probable" that Mr. Berlusconi would seek on Wednesday to pre-empt three no-confidence motions presented by his opponents and instead demand a vote of confidence himself.</p>
        <p>"If the confidence motion fails, the Government will obviously resign," Mr. Ferrara said. Mr. Ferrara described new elections as "the only way to clean the atmosphere."</p>
        <p>In a speech Monday night in Milan that was carried on television, Mr. Berlusconi urged his followers to take to the streets in a "great march for liberty" if Parliament votes against him.</p>
        <p>Il Manifesto, a hard-line Communist newspaper, indignantly compared the Prime Minister's proposal to the 1922 March on Rome that brought Mussolini's Fascist regime to power.</p>
        <p>The immediate cause of the current crisis is a decision by the federalist Northern League, which is part of the rightist coalition along with Mr. Berlusconi's Forza Italia and the National Alliance, to forge a new coalition, with parties of the center-right and the left, strong enough to form a Government without new elections.</p>
        <p>Umberto Bossi, the Northern League leader, has aligned himself with the Democratic Party of the Left, as the former Communist Party calls itself, and the Popular Party, the successor to the defunct Christian Democrats, to muster what he claims are 325 of the 630 votes in the lower house of Parliament.</p>
        <p>It is not clear, however, whether defections from Mr. Bossi's ranks could yet swing a confidence vote in favor of Mr. Berlusconi. Italian radio reports said that 45 Northern League lawmakers had rebelled against Mr. Bossi's maneuver.</p>
        <p>Even if the Prime Minister wins a confidence vote in Parliament, it is doubtful the Government can continue in its present form. The break between Mr. Berlusconi and Mr. Bossi seems beyond repair, and the Prime Minister may be calculating that new elections offer his best chance to hold on to power.</p>
        <p>To add to the complexities, a confidence vote in the lower house of Parliament could easily be canceled out in the upper house, the Senate, where hard-line Communists have put forward a separate no-confidence motion. Mr. Berlusconi does have a majority in the Senate, however, and would be expected to win a confidence vote there.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Berlusconi loses a confidence vote in Parliament, he must resign his Government to President Oscar Luigi Scalfaro. Mr. Scalfaro will then decide whether to call new elections or ask Mr. Berlusconi or some other leader to try to form a working coalition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bossi wants Mr. Scalfaro to authorize negotiations for a government based on his new alliance with the ex-Communists and the Popular Party without holding elections, in which the Northern League's fortunes would be doubtful.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
