<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Push Is On to Limit Aid to Rich Universities</title>
    <meta content="Y26COLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/26/education/26COLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1569253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Western States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Assn of Financial Aid Administrators</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winter, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3D81230F935A15750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Push Is On to Limit Aid to Rich Universities</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Push Is On to Limit Aid to Rich Universities</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG WINTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winter, Greg</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush plans for revision of aid-distribution formula to colleges in his budget, calling present system inequitable; House Republicans say they will push to overhaul system that often sends disproportionate share of federal education money to wealthy universities with relatively few low-income students; proposal would send more aid to Southern and Western states, drawing money from educational stronghold in Northeast; National Assn of Financial Aid Administrators calls for 'fair share' formula, but expects objections from Northeastern legislators (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following the Bush administration's lead, Republicans in the House say they will push to overhaul a financial aid system that often sends a disproportionate share of federal education money to wealthy universities with relatively few low-income students.</p>
        <p>For decades, hundreds of millions of federal aid dollars have been channeled to universities through a system that sets aside a minimum amount, typically called a base guarantee, to select institutions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>House Republicans plan to overhaul a financial aid system that often sends more federal money to wealthy universities with relatively few low-income students.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following the Bush administration's lead, Republicans in the House say they will push to overhaul a financial aid system that often sends a disproportionate share of federal education money to wealthy universities with relatively few low-income students.</p>
        <p>For decades, hundreds of millions of federal aid dollars have been channeled to universities through a system that sets aside a minimum amount, typically called a base guarantee, to select institutions.</p>
        <p>Such set-asides do not stem from the number of low-income students at a given university, the Republicans contend. Instead, they show how successful each institution was at securing its share in the 1970's, when money for programs like work-study was meted out as much through artful negotiation as need.</p>
        <p>With many of the old guarantees still in place, Harvard, Princeton and Yale -- or any other member of the Ivy League, for that matter -- received 5 to 12 times the median amount per financial aid applicant given to the nation's colleges to run their low-interest loan programs in 2000-01, according to an analysis of federal data for more than 4,000 universities by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>The Ivy League universities were also given 5 to 8 times more than the median to pay their students in work-study jobs. And they received 5 to 20 times the median amount of grant money to look after the everyday needs of poor students, despite having some of the largest endowments in the nation.</p>
        <p>In his budget, President Bush described the aid distribution as inequitable and said the formulas should be revised. That call has been echoed by Representatives John A. Boehner of Ohio, chairman of the House Committee on Education and the Workforce, and Howard P. McKeon of California, two Republicans who had proposed penalties for institutions that raised their tuitions too quickly. They have since withdrawn the proposal, saying many colleges and universities have acted on their own to restrain costs.</p>
        <p>In the coming weeks, Congressional staff members said, House Republicans will propose legislation to scale back the guarantees awarded to colleges. The idea is not to eliminate the set-asides, but to reduce them by about 40 percent within about six years.</p>
        <p>Mr. McKeon called the approach a compromise. ''Politically, this is a tough thing to do,'' Mr. McKeon said. ''You get lots of talk about good policy, but the real fights come over money. This will be a tough one.''</p>
        <p>As the set-asides decrease and the money is parceled out according to where low-income students go to college, financial aid administrators expect a significant geographic shift. Southern and Western states, where student populations have grown in recent years, would almost certainly draw money from the educational stronghold in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, community colleges and for-profit universities, two kinds of institutions that have had growth spurts, would also draw money from public and private universities.</p>
        <p>''I know it's going to be politically difficult,'' said Dallas Martin, president of the National Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators, which represents most of the nation's financial aid officers.</p>
        <p>The association argues that the guarantees should be eliminated entirely, so that all the money is distributed through what it calls a ''fair share'' formula. But given the objections expected from Northeastern legislators, Mr. Martin said, ''I'm not surprised that they would not want to go as far as we proposed.''</p>
        <p>Even some lawmakers from states that would probably benefit from redistribution are wary of it. Representative George Miller, Democrat of California, said that while he supported the notion of equity, he worried that unless the programs being discussed received enough money, redistribution would simply take money away from one poor student and give it to another.</p>
        <p>''We need to level the playing field,'' Mr. Miller said, ''but we can't do that if there is no field to play on.''</p>
        <p>The proposal to scale back the financial aid guarantees is likely to be a contentious issue in the debate this year over reauthorization of the Higher Education Act.</p>
        <p>Another is whether students should continue to be allowed to consolidate loans at fixed low rates, even when market interest rates rise. Because the government ends up paying the difference, some lawmakers argue that consolidation has become a de facto subsidy program. Ending it, others contend, would increase the cost of education by requiring higher payments by graduates.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
