<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Secure Home-Court Edge for Raptor Series</title>
    <meta content="19KNIC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/19/sports/19KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1286762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario/Toronto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Detroit</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Toronto</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Van</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Houston</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Spencer, Felton</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Oakley, Charles</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Childs, Chris</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jackson, Mark</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Vince</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Van Gundy, Jeff</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Camby, Marcus</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rice, Glen</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Houston, Allan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E6DC1530F93AA25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Secure Home-Court Edge for Raptor Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers defeat Detroit Pistons, 94-88; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is the Knicks' very last big man, one who, despite his imposing appearance, receives playing time only when absolutely no one else is available. But last night, in a game that had postseason repercussions, Felton Spencer was nobody's scrub.</p>
        <p>Forced into action midway through the first quarter, the 7-foot, 265-pound Spencer scored 15 first-half points to jump-start the Knicks to an early lead that matured into a 94-88 victory over the Detroit Pistons at Madison Square Garden. The victory gave the Knicks the fourth seeding and home-court advantage in the first round of the Eastern Conference playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He is the Knicks' very last big man, one who, despite his imposing appearance, receives playing time only when absolutely no one else is available. But last night, in a game that had postseason repercussions, Felton Spencer was nobody's scrub.</p>
        <p>Forced into action midway through the first quarter, the 7-foot, 265-pound Spencer scored 15 first-half points to jump-start the Knicks to an early lead that matured into a 94-88 victory over the Detroit Pistons at Madison Square Garden. The victory gave the Knicks the fourth seeding and home-court advantage in the first round of the Eastern Conference playoffs.</p>
        <p>In a rematch of last season's first-round series, the Knicks (48-34) will be host to the Toronto Raptors (47-35) in what certainly qualifies as a grudge match. Game 1 is Sunday at 12:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>''Toronto finished the season strong and we've finished somewhat on a down note, so it was important for us to get the home court,'' Latrell Sprewell said. ''I'm sure they're looking for a little revenge after we were able to put them out last year.''</p>
        <p>The series may be volatile for several reasons.</p>
        <p>Toronto features Charles Oakley and Chris Childs, former Knicks who were disappointed to be traded. Oakley, the Knicks' former enforcer, has expressed a beef with forward Kurt Thomas, and Childs has exchanged insults with point guard Mark Jackson.</p>
        <p>The Raptors defeated the Knicks six of the last seven times they played in the regular season, including three of four this season. They are looking to exact revenge for being swept in three games by the Knicks in last year's playoffs.</p>
        <p>And Vince Carter will be intent on atoning for being outplayed by Sprewell during the sweep. Carter also accused Coach Jeff Van Gundy of telling Thomas to throw a cheap shot at him in the Knicks' 88-72 victory on March 15.</p>
        <p>The Knicks have more pressing issues. They played short-handed again last night, missing Marcus Camby (bruised left hip) and Larry Johnson (sore back). But Camby, who sat out his fourth straight game, said he would play in Game 1.</p>
        <p>''See you Sunday at 12:30,'' Camby said. ''It's for real now. I'm going to have to be ready. You don't want to miss any playoff games. I don't expect to be pain free, but I've got mobility now. That's something I didn't have a couple of days ago.''</p>
        <p>Johnson is more of a question mark, and even if he plays, Van Gundy seems prepared to start Thomas. Thomas has been outstanding in Johnson's absence, and last night he led the Knicks with 20 points and 14 rebounds.</p>
        <p>''I think everyone wants to start, but whatever's best for the team,'' Thomas said. ''We have to be concerned with Toronto's size and of course, about Vince.''</p>
        <p>Last night's victory was just the second in five games for the Knicks, but they expect to play much better now that it's playoff time. When the Knicks are pressed, Sprewell said, ''the guys on our team step it up.''</p>
        <p>''We can fight through difficult times,'' he said, ''so this is no different.''</p>
        <p>With the Knicks' durability in question, Spencer may be called on in the playoffs. Spencer, 33, had played in 17 games before last night, averaging 1.4 points and 1.8 rebounds in 5.6 minutes.</p>
        <p>But when he entered at the 5-minute-17-second mark of the first quarter, Spencer looked unstoppable. He scored 9 points, grabbed 3 rebounds and blocked a shot to spark a 20-12 run that gave the Knicks a 33-24 lead after one quarter. By halftime, he had all 15 of his points and all 5 of his rebounds and the Knicks led, 60-49.</p>
        <p>''Just because Coach doesn't play me doesn't mean I can't play,'' Spencer said with a smile.</p>
        <p>Detroit pulled to 4 points back in the third quarter, but the Knicks' Glen Rice scored 7 points in the final minutes of the period to push the margin back to 78-69 heading into the fourth quarter. Rice, who finished with 12 points, closed the quarter with a buzzer-beating 3-pointer.</p>
        <p>The Pistons put together a small rally, again moving to 4 points back with less than a minute to play, but the Knicks held them off.</p>
        <p>Now comes the serious part. Allan Houston reminded reporters that the Raptors would not be the only ones who were fired up.</p>
        <p>''We're hungry too,'' said Houston, who scored 18 points. ''We know what happened last year and they know what happened too. So we're not going to expect them to just lie down because of what happened last year. We know we can play much better than we played during the regular season and we want to go out and prove it to ourselves.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>LUC LONGLEY, who has been on the injured list with a left ankle injury since March 6, said he was unable to play and did not expect to be on the playoff roster. ''It's very disappointing,'' said Longley, who appeared in only 25 games. ''I sort of expected it. It's a degenerative thing that I can't do anything surgically about.'' Longley, who has three years left on a six-year, $32 million contract, said he would have to think about retirement in the off-season. . . . OTHELLA HARRINGTON, filling in as a starter, had his second straight foul-plagued performance, finishing with 4 points, 7 rebounds and 5 fouls in 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
