<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hosts Greet Athletes Seeking Olympic Gold</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="771761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPECIAL OLYMPICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HANDICAPPED</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ORANGE (CONN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, KIRK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DB123EF93BA15755C0A963958260" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hosts Greet Athletes Seeking Olympic Gold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, KIRK</byline>
      <dateline>ORANGE, Conn., June 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christopher Marriot, a 15-year-old from Zimbabwe, left his home near Bulawayo last Wednesday for an international adventure that landed him at a place of exquisite foreignness: Ken Robinson's house in suburban Connecticut, just in time for Sunday dinner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson hung a Zimbabwean flag from his front porch and served lasagna and Italian bread, which he tore into large chunks and tossed on the dinner plates as Christopher watched, his eyes wide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Christopher Marriot, a 15-year-old from Zimbabwe, left his home near Bulawayo last Wednesday for an international adventure that landed him at a place of exquisite foreignness: Ken Robinson's house in suburban Connecticut, just in time for Sunday dinner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson hung a Zimbabwean flag from his front porch and served lasagna and Italian bread, which he tore into large chunks and tossed on the dinner plates as Christopher watched, his eyes wide.</p>
        <p>"As foreign as all this is to us, it's more so to them," Mr. Robinson said of his guests, two retarded teen-agers and their adult coach, part of the 52-member Zimbabwean team for the Special Olympics World Games, which will begin on Saturday in New Haven.</p>
        <p>The entire Zimbabwean team is staying through Wednesday night in 25 private homes in Orange, where volunteers like Mr. Robinson, a widower in his 70's, have offered empty bedrooms and homespun hospitality. The pattern is being repeated in every town in the state, where more than 1,000 residents have become temporary hoteliers to 4,800 guests -- from the 87 Russian athletes in New Milford to the 59 from Honduras in Wolcott -- participating in what international experts say is by far the largest cultural exchange ever involving private homes.</p>
        <p>"It's so hard to arrange this sort of thing," Stanley N. Katz said. "This is heroic." Mr. Katz is president of the American Council of Learned Societies, a private nonprofit group that advocates humanities studies and cultural exchange.</p>
        <p>It can also be confusing. At Mr. Robinson's table, communication was a three-part effort. Christopher, a thin, shy soccer player, speaks a tribal language, Ndebele, and a little English. Phillip Kabeya, 19, a teammate from Harare, speaks Shona and almost no English. The coach, Bharat Patel, a gold-mine manager in Bulawayo who usually advises Zimbabwe's equestrian team, speaks Hindi and English, and understands the boys' languages, but can't speak them.</p>
        <p>When Phillip finished his chocolate cake, he gestured with his hand to his mouth and spoke across the table to Mr. Robinson's friend, Irene Chaisson, apparently expecting her to understand him. Ms. Chaisson glanced at Mr. Patel, who supplied the desired word: napkin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson, a former construction company owner and pilot who still flies his own small planes, was adjusting to having anyone around at all. He said he usually eats alone, with one plate he can rinse in the sink and no table manners. On the first night of his newly full house, he mostly smiled a lot.</p>
        <p>"We'll talk all right," he said, patting Phillip's hand after a particularly difficult moment when not even Mr. Patel could understand what the boy had been trying to say.</p>
        <p>The point of the town host program, which the Special Olympics World Games is trying for the first time this year, is not simply to create a few warm moments over dinner. The games' president, Timothy P. Shriver, son of Sargent Shriver and Eunice Kennedy Shriver, said he hoped to build enthusiasm, and thus attendance, at the nine-day event by establishing an emotional connection between residents and athletes.</p>
        <p>Wherever possible, countries were paired with towns that had an ethnic or religious connection. The 42-member Polish delegation, for example, is staying in New Britain, a city near Hartford that has become a magnet for Polish immigrants. The 18-member Israeli team is staying in West Hartford, which has a large Jewish population. The Lebanese team is staying in Danbury, where Lebanese immigrants came at one time to work in the hat-making industry.</p>
        <p>After that, however, planning the guests' activities was left entirely to volunteer committees. In New Milford, for example, the Russian team will meet at the high school on Wednesday morning for a 15-minute interactive video connection with the Russian Mir space station, during which astronauts will wish the team good luck. Smaller towns are holding potluck suppers and parties at town halls to meet the athletes.</p>
        <p>Orange has no connection to Zimbabwe that anyone knows about, but enthusiasts say that makes the exchange all the more meaningful.</p>
        <p>"Won't this be great," said Linda D'Andrea, chairwoman of the Orange Host Town Program. "We have nothing in common!" She arranged the itinerary of the four-day visit, including a picnic on the beach in Milford with the Swiss delegation, which is staying in Bethany, and a night at the baseball park to see the minor league New Haven Ravens.</p>
        <p>For hosts and guests, the learning curve began as soon as the buses arrived, depositing the Zimbabweans in the parking lot of the Holy Infant Roman Catholic Church before several dozen people cheering, applauding and waving tiny American flags. Like Mr. Robinson, most knew only their guests' names and home towns. A few, like Linda Raskin, made special requests.</p>
        <p>"I wanted basketball players," she said. "We're a basketball house."</p>
        <p>She got her wish. Bobby Musekiwa, 24, and Nobert Zvomuya, 23, both on the basketball team, and their coach, Mike Mazonde, a high school teacher in Harare, sat around her breakfast table Monday morning eating blueberry pancakes.</p>
        <p>Other host families said they had abandoned all thought of planned activities. Susan A. Clark, host to three teen-age soccer players and their coach, had at first arranged for a whirlwind tour of south central Connecticut, but on second thought decided that teen-agers, whatever their backgrounds and abilities, are essentially alike.</p>
        <p>"We're going to hang out like adolescents," Ms. Clark said.</p>
        <p>Besides, she added, her guests seem so happy exploring close-to-home worlds like the shopping mall and the cable television dial that more organized trips are almost an overload. Harare, the capital of Zimbabwe, has two television stations, the coaches said. Bulawayo has one.</p>
        <p>"They're just amazed and delighted at surfing with the clicker on TV," Ms. Clark said. "They don't watch anything, they just push the button."</p>
        <p>Food is another matter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson said he lacked the remotest clue what kind of food his guests knew or liked. But he did some research.</p>
        <p>"Every country in the world has chickens," he said before the group's arrival. "So I bought a lot of eggs."</p>
        <p>That was a mistake. Mr. Patel is a strict vegetarian who declined to eat Ms. Chaisson's homemade lasagna because it contained sausage. Eggs were out too. Fortunately, Mr. Robinson also bought a lot of fruit.</p>
        <p>"Everybody eats fruit," Mr. Robinson said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
