<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Board to Eliminate Rule On Moving to Another Market</title>
    <meta content="Y08RULE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/08/business/08RULE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1510401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Stock Exchange</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nasdaq Stock Market</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Floyd Norris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">The New York Stock Exchange</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EFDD1431F93BA3575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Board to Eliminate Rule On Moving to Another Market</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Big Board to Eliminate Rule on Moving to Another Market</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Stock Exchange will drop rule that has made it difficult for companies whose shares are listed on exchange to leave it and move to another market, like Nasdaq stock market; rule, known as Rule 500, has long drawn bitter complaint fropm Nasdaq (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Stock Exchange said yesterday that it would drop a rule that has made it difficult for companies whose shares are listed on the exchange to leave it and move to another market, like the Nasdaq stock market.</p>
        <p>The rule, known as Rule 500, has long drawn bitter complaints from Nasdaq. To leave, the exchange required a company to obtain approval from its audit committee as well as from its full board and to notify the company's 35 largest investors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Stock Exchange is dropping a rule that made it difficult for companies whose shares are listed on the exchange to leave it and move to another market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York Stock Exchange said yesterday that it would drop a rule that has made it difficult for companies whose shares are listed on the exchange to leave it and move to another market, like the Nasdaq stock market.</p>
        <p>The rule, known as Rule 500, has long drawn bitter complaints from Nasdaq. To leave, the exchange required a company to obtain approval from its audit committee as well as from its full board and to notify the company's 35 largest investors.</p>
        <p>''The rationale for requiring separate audit committee approval of a delisting was to ensure that independent directors approved the decision,'' said Catherine R. Kinney, president and co-chief operating officer of the Big Board.</p>
        <p>''In our work on listing standards, we have seen that a majority-independent board has already become the norm among many of our companies,'' Ms. Kinney said. ''After our currently pending governance proposals become final, a majority-independent board will become an exchange standard. As a result, we believe that in this new environment, board approval of a transfer should suffice, and the rule is no longer necessary.''</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq market's complaints, which at one point included a spokesman calling it a ''roach motel'' rule, led to the rule's being weakened in 1999, dropping a requirement for a shareholder vote. But only one company made the move after that.</p>
        <p>In May, Nasdaq resumed its effort, filing a petition with the Securities and Exchange Commission asking that the rule be repealed. Annette Nazareth, the commission's director for market regulation, said yesterday that the commission had not applied pressure for the change.</p>
        <p>''It was at their initiative,'' she said of the Big Board decision. ''It is a very constructive step that the exchange elected to re-evaluate the rule in the light of changes in corporate governance that have occurred since Sarbanes-Oxley,'' the law passed last year that mandated independent audit committees, among other things.</p>
        <p>At Nasdaq, Bethany Sherman, a spokeswoman, said, ''We're encouraged that New York is proposing elimination of a rule that the industry has always believed to be anticompetitive.''</p>
        <p>She declined to say whether Nasdaq expected more companies to move once they can do so with a simple board vote and a short S.E.C. filing.</p>
        <p>The only company to move after the rule was weakened in 1999 was Aeroflex, a technology company in Plainview, N.Y. It made the move on March 21, 2000, 11 days after the Nasdaq composite index peaked at 5,048.62. Since then, Aeroflex shares have lost 60 percent of their value, while the Nasdaq index is down 67 percent from its high.</p>
        <p>During the last several years, dozens of companies have moved from Nasdaq to the Big Board.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
