<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barrasso's Return Puts Devils In Knots</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="758381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PITTSBURGH PENGUINS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY DEVILS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">YANNIS, ALEX</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3D6123FF934A15757C0A963958260" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barrasso's Return Puts Devils In Knots</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YANNIS, ALEX</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Barrasso made his first appearance of the season in goal for the Penguins tonight and looked as sharp as ever as Pittsburgh gained a 3-3 tie with the Devils.</p>
        <p>"I'm glad to have a tie," said Devils Coach Jacques Lemaire, "because five or six of our guys were not at their best and we took some penalties against a dangerous team."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Barrasso made his first appearance of the season in goal for the Penguins tonight and looked as sharp as ever as Pittsburgh gained a 3-3 tie with the Devils.</p>
        <p>"I'm glad to have a tie," said Devils Coach Jacques Lemaire, "because five or six of our guys were not at their best and we took some penalties against a dangerous team."</p>
        <p>The Devils found themselves short-handed three times, and the Penguins capitalized once. The Devils had six manpower advantages and capitalized just once against Barrasso, who faced 34 shots, including three in the overtime.</p>
        <p>John MacLean, Sergei Brylin and Valery Zelepukin scored the goals to earn a valuable point for the Devils, who came a step closer to clinching a playoff berth in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>Kevin Stevens scored the first two goals and Tomas Sandstrom got the other goal for the Penguins, who took 30 shots, including two in the overtime.</p>
        <p>Barrasso made his first appearance in almost a year. His previous game was last April 27, when he lost the sixth game of the playoff series with the Washington Capitals.</p>
        <p>He looked his sharpest in the seventh minute of the middle period when he sprawled to his right to stop Stephane Richer and denied MacLean's backhander from the slot a few seconds later.</p>
        <p>"Tommy played well and he will probably play again on Sunday," Coach Ed Johnston said of Barrasso. "He made the saves he had to when we needed it."</p>
        <p>While Barrasso was sharp, the Devils' goaltending was average. Lemaire started with Chris Terreri, but he replaced him with Martin Brodeur for the start of the third after Terreri had allowed two goals on 15 shots.</p>
        <p>"I thought Chris was not aggressive in every shot he had," Lemaire said. "I know he hasn't played enough, but he looked good in practice and he deserved a start."</p>
        <p>Brodeur allowed Sandstrom's 20th goal on the first shot he faced that tied the score at 3-3, 2 minutes 11 seconds into the third, but he settled down after that and made no other mistakes.</p>
        <p>Lemaire was particulaly happy with the way Zelepukin played in only his second game of the season.</p>
        <p>"His line was the best line," Lemaire said about Zelepukin's line that had Brylin at center and Billy Guerin at right wing. But the coach did not use the line in the overtime, with Zelepukin playing a shift or two with two other combinations.</p>
        <p>Zelepukin assisted on Brylin's goal that gave the Devils a 2-1 lead, 7:57 into the middle period, and scored his first of the season with 2:14 left in the period to extend the lead.</p>
        <p>Zelepukin's goal came from the inside perimeter of the right circle that beat Barrasso to the stick side after a pass from the left by Guerin, who was the right wing on Zelepukin's line last season.</p>
        <p>"I was kind of surprised," Guerin said about not playing in the overtime. "Maybe we weren't as aggressive as we should be. We were on our heels a little."  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
