<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long Island Q&amp;A: Edward J. Shubel;In the Forefront of High-Power Communications</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="840289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEPHONES AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CELLULAR TELEPHONES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICALINFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MICROWAVE POWER DEVICES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KONIG, SUSAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHUBEL, EDWARD J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3D61539F932A05750C0A960958260" item-length="1838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long Island Q&amp;A: Edward J. Shubel;In the Forefront of High-Power Communications</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN KONIG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KONIG, SUSAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PEOPLE should not be surprised when they receive a telephone call or fax from an airplane 30,000 feet over the ocean. Edward J. Shubel would not be.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shubel is chief executive of Microwave Power Devices Inc. in Hauppauge and, after years of developing high-power amplifiers for the military, the company has moved into wireless communications. Amplifiers that it once built for the airplanes of the special forces are being installed on commercial planes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PEOPLE should not be surprised when they receive a telephone call or fax from an airplane 30,000 feet over the ocean. Edward J. Shubel would not be.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shubel is chief executive of Microwave Power Devices Inc. in Hauppauge and, after years of developing high-power amplifiers for the military, the company has moved into wireless communications. Amplifiers that it once built for the airplanes of the special forces are being installed on commercial planes.</p>
        <p>When he became chief executive in 1991, Microwave Power was exclusively a military contractor. Mr. Shubel transferred its technology from that shrinking market, although it continues to carry out some military work, to wireless and satellite communications. Today Microwave Power is the third-largest supplier of amplifiers to those fields.</p>
        <p>The company, which went public in September, reported revenues of $27 million last year. It has contracts with Rockwell International and AT&amp;T. The company expects earnings this year to exceed $60 million. It has 400 employees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shubel has been a military engineer for more than 40 years and has headed several companies, including Maxson Electronics and EJS Products, both on Long Island. When he was about to retire in 1991, a friend at the Charterhouse Group  in Manhattan, which invests in high-growth companies, asked about Microwave Power. When Mr. Shubel recommended buying the company, Charterhouse asked him to run it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shubel was born in Queens 65 years ago. He received a B.S. and credits toward a master's in engineering from the Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute, now New York Polytechnic.</p>
        <p>He lives in Cold Spring Harbor with his wife, Josephine. They have two sons and four grandchildren</p>
        <p>Q.  Why did you recommend buying a military company as the Government was cutting military spending?</p>
        <p>A.  M.P.D. was an electronics business. And though the Government wasn't buying new military equipment, they were upgrading their old equipment, and that's just the kind of business we did. So I figured the wind-down would be slower for us, and that would give me time figure out how we could use our technology in the commercial sector.</p>
        <p>Q.  What was the first step?</p>
        <p>A.  I started looking for places to parlay this tremendous technology that we had. This was the first company in the world to build high-power solid-state amplifiers. And, I thought, "I've got to parlay this into commercial markets." I knew it could be done. I looked at three markets, medicine, satellite communications, and cellular communications.</p>
        <p>First we acquired a company that built driver amplifiers for cancer-treatment machines. That's how we got into medicine. Then we developed an amplifier for Inmarsat, which is a technical term for satellite communication over water. It allows the captain of an airplane or the passengers to communicate with people on the ground while they're flying over water. For example if you're on a plane  to England you've got a laptop computer and you want to send a fax, you can send it while you're over the ocean through a satellite down to the ground. Over land that's easy to do, because there are land-based stations. But over the ocean, you do it with satellites.</p>
        <p>You'll also notice many airplanes now have telephones. You can just walk up to the galley and pick up a phone. But that, too, is just while you're over land. This Inmarsat system lets you make these calls over water.</p>
        <p>Q.  Did Microwave Power pioneer that technology?</p>
        <p>A.  We make the amplifiers, which are what allow you do all of this. We take  a very low-level signal and amplify it to a high-level signal, so that it can reach the satellite. We're really a tier in the whole process.</p>
        <p>Q.  Does the company make amplifiers for wireless and cellular telephone systems, as well?</p>
        <p>A.  We've really just begun. We make equipment for original equipment manufacturers, who then make base-station equipment for companies like Steinbrecher, Motorola, Goldstar and, of course, AT&amp;T. We sell our equipment to  the wireless infrastructure o.e.m.'s. They sell equipment to the service providers, the people we deal with as consumers. In this region it's companies like Cellular One, which is now AT&amp;T Wireless Services.</p>
        <p>Q.  Why have celluar-telephone subscribers grown from 45 million in 1994 to 78 million worldwide?</p>
        <p>A.  Well, there's been a huge increase in the number of cellular base stations worldwide, which means that more people can use cell phones. But, aside from the number of users, the amount of time people spend on cell phones has gone way up. We're using them much more often. We've become accustomed to having them in our cars or as personal phones.</p>
        <p>Q.  Is the cost of cellular phone transmission still an obstacle?</p>
        <p>A.  Yes, but it's going to come down. And when the cost per call comes down,  wireless is going to be a competitor of wired telephone systems, which currently account for about 99 percent of the telephone business in the U.S. Over the next 10 years, I think, it will shift to about 75 percent wired and 25 percent wireless.</p>
        <p>Q.  What does wireless communications cost, and where is it going?</p>
        <p>A.  Wireless calls cost 50 to 60 cents per minute during prime time and between 30 and 40 cents off-prime. Wired phones cost about 10 cents a minute. But wireless is going to come down to 10 cents a minute. And though you also have to pay for incoming calls on cell phones, there are laws being considered which would require the sender to pay for air time. I think that by the year 2000 or 2005 the cost for wired and wireless telephones will be about the same.</p>
        <p>Q.  Will wireless providers be competing with wired-service providers?</p>
        <p>A.  They're really one and the same. AT&amp;T. Wireless and AT&amp;T Wired are the same company. They compete with other service providers.</p>
        <p>Q.  What engineers does Microwave Power look for, and do they need to train or learn new technology?</p>
        <p>A.  Those who have the technology, which lends itself to amplifiers, definitely have a place with us, especially radio-frequency and microwave engineers. We've hired many people from Unisys and Cardion over the last year or so.</p>
        <p>If you get an experienced RF engineer, however, I don't want to say you have  to "train" him, because he's a seasoned professional. But now what he designs he must design to cost and customer needs, as opposed to military specs. This is a  distinctly different thing, and it's something he has to learn.</p>
        <p>Q.  How is it different?</p>
        <p>A.  With the Government, as long as you meet their specs, whether or not your equipment works in the next position is not your problem. But in the commercial  market if your equipment doesn't work in their overall system, they're in trouble, and you're in trouble. And the commercial world moves very quickly. The customer doesn't have the same kind of time that the military has.</p>
        <p>Q.  Is that a difficult transition?</p>
        <p>A.  Well, there's a reason we're here on Long Island. We have RF and microwave engineering talent, which just doesn't exist in other parts of this country. Our firm has only five competitors -- three are on the West Coast, and  two are on the East Coast -- because that's where the RF engineers are. They all come out of defense.</p>
        <p>If you look around the world, there are probably hundreds of RF amplifier companies of various types. Yet only five are in the cellular and wireless market. The reason is that they come from the military. The wireless market commands very high performance, the same kind of performance required in defense. So in that sense it's almost an ideal transition.</p>
        <p>Q.  Then military engineers are not necessarily becoming obsolete?</p>
        <p>A.  Not those with microwave and RF technology, no. In fact, there's a shortage of RF people, because it is something of a black art. But others are being phased out. If we made landing gears for the F-16, for example, I don't know where we'd be right now.</p>
        <p>Q.  Why do you say you keep manufacturing on Long Island because it is more cost effective?</p>
        <p>A.  In commercial markets you pay a lot more attention to cost. We looked at  a number of ways to cut our manufacturing costs. One was to have our assembly done in maquilladoras in Mexico, for example, where people will work for 60 cents a day.  But I visited some of them last year and, with all due respect to  their talents and capabilities, I found they just couldn't build RF amplifiers.  And I presume we'd have the same problems in offshore locations like Taiwan, China and Korea. The reason is the requirements for wireless technology are very high. You're constantly making changes to meet new demands. You can't make changes quickly with manual assembly.</p>
        <p>Around the same as I was investigating Mexico, we won a contract with AT&amp;T to build special amplifiers. They invited us to visit their high-velocity manufacturing plant in Columbus, Ohio. It was automated pick-and-place technology, and the speed was just incredible. These machines could manufacture  in three to four minutes what it would take us five or six hours to do manually. That quick turnaround time is essential to this business, so we decided to mimic what we saw there here.</p>
        <p>Q.  Does that require higher skills?</p>
        <p>A.  Definitely. But the good news for Long Island is that they're in great supply here.</p>
        <p>Q.  What is the future of wireless communications?</p>
        <p>A.  As the number of cell-phone subscribers goes up, the cost will come way down, strictly because it is operating cost, not the cost of equipment, which determines the price. In the United States, you can expect that, between the years 2000 and 2005, 25 to 40 percent of the population will be connected with some kind of wireless communicator, a pager, a miniature PC, a wireless phone and so forth. So in 5 or 10 years I expect 100 million people will be walking around with some type of electronic gadget on them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
