<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pay For a Stay At Weston Jail?</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="840441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRISONS AND PRISONERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OVERTIME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTON (CONN)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOMUSCIO, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, LOUIS S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E7DE1239F932A05750C0A960958260" item-length="1634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pay For a Stay At Weston Jail?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES LOMUSCIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LOMUSCIO, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A TOILET, a cot, cold steel bars and an occasional sandwich are the only amenities a prisoner will find in one of Weston's two small holding cells.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A TOILET, a cot, cold steel bars and an occasional sandwich are the only amenities a prisoner will find in one of Weston's two small holding cells.</p>
        <p>But a night in the slammer in this affluent town could wind up costing a prisoner more than a night at Manhattan's Plaza Hotel if Louis S. Goldberg gets  his way.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldberg, who serves on Weston's seven-member police commission, says the town should be able to bill prisoners for their incarceration to help pay for the police overtime required for cell watch. With a cost of $250 per shift to watch a prisoner, and three shifts a day, Mr. Goldberg says cell watch costs  can add up -- especially for prisoners held over the weekend while they await transportation to Norwalk Superior Court.</p>
        <p>"Why should I pay for it?" asked Mr. Goldberg. "I didn't break the law. People should be responsible for the actions they cause and the cost associated  with that. Why should the taxpayer be left holding the bag?"</p>
        <p>However appealing a notion in tight-money times, however, the idea of charging for jail time has stirred up quite a few critics, including the local police chief, on points ranging from constitutional issues to practicalities: How to make people pay?</p>
        <p>About $120,000 of the Weston Police Department's approximately $1 million annual budget goes toward overtime, and only about 5 percent of that $120,000 is attributed to cell watch. But Mr. Goldberg says he wants to slice costs wherever possible to help the taxpayer.</p>
        <p>One person who finds merit in Mr. Goldberg's proposal is Weston First Selectman George Guidera, who says he has little sympathy for lawbreakers -- especially drunk drivers, since his father was killed by one. And Mr. Guidera is supporting Mr. Goldberg's bid to local legislators for a state law that would allow municipalities to charge prison cell user fees. To assure the constitutionality of such a law, Mr. Guidera said, prisoners would be billed only if they were found guilty or pled to lesser charges. If a person were found innocent or the case was thrown out of court, no bill would follow.</p>
        <p>"If we could get the law passed, the law would save the town tremendous amounts of money," said Mr. Guidera. "We are looking at every penny in the budget.</p>
        <p>"There's a saying, 'Don't do the crime if you can't do the time,' " he added. "And I'm saying, 'If you can't pay the fee, don't go on a crime spree' in Weston.' "</p>
        <p>Last month Mr. Goldberg, a corporate personnel consultant and a former State  Commissioner of the Department of Motor Vehicles, pitched his idea to Weston's Police Commission. He suggested that the state's Cost of Corrections Act, which  was passed during the 1995 legislative session, could be amended to allow municipalities to recover expenses from individuals held in their cells. The state law allows Connecticut to charge convicted felons for some of their expenses, "for the extras, such as electricity for their televisions or radios," said William Flower, a spokesman for the State Department of Corrections.</p>
        <p>"The State of Connecticut can't say 'We can charge for incarceration' and then turn to the towns and say, 'You're our poor stepsisters, and you can't do it,' " said Mr. Guidera. "The beauty of a law like this is that it would cost the state nothing, and everybody would get something back for its law enforcement dollar."</p>
        <p>While Mr. Goldberg has support from the town's First Selectman, others on the police commission and Police Chief Anthony Land -- not to mention the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union -- feel the proposal is seriously flawed.</p>
        <p>"Not everything that would help the taxpayer is constitutional, and we've had 200 years to attest to that fact," said Emanuel Margolis, a Stamford attorney and legal counsel to the C.C.L.U. "I think it is outrageous."</p>
        <p>"It's like, 'Welcome to Weston's only downtown hotel,' " he added. "We don't  offer much and there are no chocolates on the pillow, but our prices are lower than anyone else's."</p>
        <p>Mr. Margolis likened Mr. Goldberg's idea to a fire department billing for its services because someone had been smoking in bed. And he said a municipal prison cell user fee law would violate two fundamental constitutional rights -- to due  process and to equal protection under the law.</p>
        <p>Due process would be threatened, he said, because it is unconstitutional to punish people until they have had their day in court. Even billing prisoners retroactively, if they are found guilty, would be "on very shaky ground," said Joseph Grabarz, executive director of the C.C.L.U. in Hartford. That is because  the town would be "imposing a secret fine" on a prisoner, he said, during a time he or she was technically innocent.</p>
        <p>"And it's a denial of equal protection," said Mr. Margolis, "because the rich guy who's booked by the police, and who's earning $200,000 a year is going to be bonded out in 15 minutes, and the person who will not be bonded out will still be forced to pay."</p>
        <p>Chief Land agreed, saying such cell user fees could have snobbish, even racial overtones, since poorer prisoners are the ones who would be penalized most, pre- and post-trial.</p>
        <p>"No. 1, there's the whole question of the constitutionality of it," said Chief Land. "Then there's the question of practicality. We'll wind up spending more money trying to collect from people who can't pay."</p>
        <p>Saying that the United States Supreme Court would have the final say on the matter, Mr. Guidera pointed out that most of the people arrested in Weston are not judgment-proof and can afford the fees for incarcerations. Most of the people arrested in the town are also white, he added, in response to the chief's concern about racial implications.</p>
        <p>Still, the proposal has Phyllis McGrath, chairwoman of the Police Commission, concerned.</p>
        <p>"If this is unconstitutional and impractical, I don't want Weston to be the lead player in this," she said, "because as an affluent town we would look elitist."</p>
        <p>Chief Land said the town could effect much greater savings by computerizing the department's records division to cut down filing and research time. "Right now we're using old leather bound books from the days of Al Capone," he said.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the chief said the idea of cell user fees has triggered jokes among the department's 14 officers. Will there be cuff rentals? Blanket charges? Peanut dispensers and honor boxes outside the cells?</p>
        <p>"They all think it's pretty silly," said Chief Land.</p>
        <p>On the serious side, he noted that such a law could create the impression that there was a financial motivation for holding prisoners.</p>
        <p>"They might think that we would be inclined to put higher bonds on people just to hold them," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldberg's response?</p>
        <p>"Why don't they stop more people now just to get more overtime?" he asked. "All those excuses are code words for those who don't want change, those who are obstructionists, and for the liberal agenda that really doesn't care how we spend the taxpayers' money.</p>
        <p>"And I really don't care if this is only 5 percent of the overtime," added Mr. Goldberg. "If you don't start somewhere and challenge the system, and if you don't use this as a catalyst for surfacing other ideas, then the taxpayer will see no initiative."</p>
        <p>Should his call for cell user fees fail, Mr. Goldberg has also proposed asking either the Connecticut State Police or the County Sheriff's Department to assume the burden of caring for prisoners. He said either department could possibly establish a single location where pretrial prisoners could be sent as soon as they are arrested. The state, he explained, would then assume all responsibility for the handling of prisoners and their transportation to court.</p>
        <p>"The Rowland Administration has an objective to eliminate unfunded mandates,  and this mandate is not funded by the state," said Mr. Goldberg, who served as the state's commissioner of administrative services during 1995 before he went into private consulting. "I'm saying help us take care of those law breakers in  a cost-effective manner, or B, allow us to collect money from those who cause us that expense."</p>
        <p>State Representative John Stripp, a Weston resident and a Republican representing the 135th district, is studying Mr. Goldberg's proposal for municipal holding cell fees.</p>
        <p>"Obviously it would be inappropriate to charge someone who was found innocent," said Mr. Stripp. "But whether it could be set up so that if you're found guilty you could be billed later, that's something we're looking at. It's  an interesting idea that should be investigated."</p>
        <p>But Ms. McGrath, stressing that she is a fiscal conservative and a dyed-in-the-wool Republican, called the plan a kneejerk reaction that would in the long run work against towns.</p>
        <p>"I would doubt that throughout history anyone has ever been charged for the basics of incarceration," she said. "If you go back to Marie Antoinette in prison, yeah, they did bring money with them, but it was to pay for the extras.  It's a basic function of government, the protection of its citizenry."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
