<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexican Federal Police and Army Move to Retake Oaxaca</title>
    <meta content="30mexico" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/30/world/americas/30mexico.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1800951"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oaxaca (Mexico)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lacey, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruiz, Ulises (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Mexico</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDF123FF933A05753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1037" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexican Federal Police and Army Move to Retake Oaxaca</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mexican Forces Move to Retake Oaxaca</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC LACEY; Antonio Betancourt and James C. McKinley Jr. contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lacey, Marc</byline>
      <dateline>OAXACA, Mexico, Oct. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal police armed with water cannons and backed by heavily armed soldiers advance on protesters in Oaxaca, Mex, who have occupied main square of city during five-month standoff; operation, ordered by Pres Vicente Fox in his final month in office, does not become bloodbath that many had feared; protesters are seeking removal of governor of Oaxaca State, Ulises Ruiz, who sent in poorly trained riot police officers to oust striking teachers in June, and who has been accused of rigging 2004 gubernatorial election and ruling state with iron hand; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal forces moved to take back this picturesque tourist town one cobblestone street at a time on Sunday, bashing through barricades and pushing back activists who had seized the downtown five months ago in an increasingly ugly dispute with the state governor.</p>
        <p>Police officers wearing riot gear and carrying shields were backed by water cannons, police helicopters and heavily armed soldiers as they marched from all directions toward Oaxaca's main square, the Zócalo, which used to draw tourists but in recent months has been a giant encampment for an array of groups intent on toppling Ulises Ruiz, the governor of Oaxaca State.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal forces bashed through barricades and pushed back activists who had seized the downtown five months ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal forces moved to take back this picturesque tourist town one cobblestone street at a time on Sunday, bashing through barricades and pushing back activists who had seized the downtown five months ago in an increasingly ugly dispute with the state governor.</p>
        <p>Police officers wearing riot gear and carrying shields were backed by water cannons, police helicopters and heavily armed soldiers as they marched from all directions toward Oaxaca's main square, the Zócalo, which used to draw tourists but in recent months has been a giant encampment for an array of groups intent on toppling Ulises Ruiz, the governor of Oaxaca State.</p>
        <p>The police, estimated to number in the thousands, met resistance in some areas. Demonstrators clutching rocks and sticks tried to stop them. Buses shuttling police officers to the center of town were pelted with stones, and bonfires in the middle of streets sent huge plumes of smoke into the sky.</p>
        <p>By Sunday night, the Zócalo was ringed by police officers in riot gear and appeared to be controlled by federal forces.</p>
        <p>The tension here spilled over into Mexico City on Sunday, with supporters of the Oaxaca protesters surrounding a hotel where Governor Ruiz was thought to be staying and shouting: ''Murderer! Murderer!''</p>
        <p>The operation, ordered by President Vicente Fox in his final month in office, did not become the bloodbath that many had feared. Mr. Fox ordered the raid on Saturday after two protesters and an American activist working as a journalist here were killed Friday, the latest in a string of deaths for which protesters blamed provocateurs linked to the government.</p>
        <p>Protesters said the police killed one of their supporters in the raid, although police officials did not confirm the death.</p>
        <p>The Fox administration said in a statement on Sunday night that it had acted because state and local authorities could no longer guarantee public security and ''radical groups, out of control, had put at risk the peace of the citizenry.''</p>
        <p>The unrest began in May as a teachers' strike. But when Mr. Ruiz sent the police to break up the peaceful demonstrations, other activists joined in and the situation quickly spiraled out of control.</p>
        <p>The original dispute with the teachers was recently settled with a pay raise. The teachers have said they intend to return to classes on Monday, allowing 1.3 million children to resume their studies.</p>
        <p>But on Sunday, many demonstrators, some with bandanas pulled over their noses to protect against tear gas, vowed to continue pressing for the removal of Mr. Ruiz. They accuse him of rigging the 2004 gubernatorial election and ruling the state with an iron hand.</p>
        <p>''The very hour that the governor leaves, we will stop these protests and go home,'' said Joel Santiago, 38, who stood on the front lines of one standoff with officers on Sunday. ''The people are tired of this man treating us as though we're nothing.''</p>
        <p>Some residents were clearly tired of the protesters, as well. As troops advanced, some people came out of their homes to applaud their arrival, and what they hoped was the end of the lawlessness that had taken over Oaxaca. ''Thank you for coming to the rescue of our city,'' said Teófilo Rodríguez, 56, a businessman.</p>
        <p>Oaxaca, a six-hour drive southeast of Mexico City, is known for its colonial charm, with centuries-old architecture and a distinct regional cuisine. But on Sunday it more closely resembled an urban jungle. Protesters from the Oaxaca People's Popular Assembly, or A.P.P.O., a loose coalition of interests that had laid siege to the Zócalo and taken over radio stations, hustled through the streets, taunting the authorities and then fleeing at each advance.</p>
        <p>Protest slogans were painted on buildings everywhere and the burned-out remains of cars and buses litter the roads. On Sunday night, protestors were torching buses in the center of town.</p>
        <p>On the main highway leading to Mexico City, police officers in riot gear spent most of Sunday standing in formation, eyeing several hundred protesters manning a barricade of stones and tree trunks 200 feet away.</p>
        <p>At one point, a woman approached the officers and stuck white roses and carnations in their all-black uniforms. ''It makes me sad that they want to kill my people,'' she said. ''I want to change their hearts.''</p>
        <p>Other demonstrators drew their own blood to protest the arrival of the authorities. They had health workers stick needles in their veins, and the blood that flowed out was then dripped onto street signs and used to paint messages on their chests.</p>
        <p>At about 3 p.m., the police officers began advancing. Water cannons were fired on people who did not clear the way. Chaos ensued as men, women and children fled.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, bulldozers cleared some of the hundreds of barricades that had been erected around the town.</p>
        <p>The roots of the conflict have less to do with leftist ideology or a peasant uprising than with political patronage and old political rivalries, people here say.</p>
        <p>Over the past two decades, as Mexico's political system has opened up, brutally poor Oaxaca has remained a virtual one-party state, controlled by the Institutional Revolutionary Party, the machinelike organization that ruled the entire country until Mr. Fox's victory in 2000.</p>
        <p>After taking office in a disputed election, Mr. Ruiz eliminated millions in community subsidies and began a series of public works projects that involved condemning land, often taking it from farmers at rock-bottom prices, protesters say. He also forbade marches and protests in the Zócalo, angering groups that routinely used protests to demand more government aid.</p>
        <p>''He didn't realize it, but he was closing the escape valves that let the pressure off,'' said Flavio Sosa, the head of the New Left of Oaxaca, a political pressure group, and a leader of the A.P.P.O.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Ruiz sent in poorly trained riot police officers to oust striking teachers from the Zócalo on June 14, the crisis began.</p>
        <p>''This is a fight about power, about money, and the problem of poverty, as well,'' said Rosa Nida Villalobos, the head of Priista Women, a group that supports the governor, in an interview last week. ''It's a monster with a thousand heads and a thousand interests.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
