<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long Journey After Hope Of Triple Crown Faded</title>
    <meta content="19horse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/19/sports/othersports/19horse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1848333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Preakness Stakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E4D81131F93AA25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long Journey After Hope Of Triple Crown Faded</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Long Journey After Hope of Crown Faded</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <dateline>UPPERVILLE, Va., May 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bert and Diana Firestone will not be at the Preakness Stakes on Saturday, but they will be watching, and more intently than most. This is the time of year when their memories of the 1980 Triple Crown campaign and their terrific filly Genuine Risk come flooding back.</p>
        <p>A couple of weeks ago, it was about the Kentucky Derby, a race won by Genuine Risk, only the second filly to ever win that race. This week, it is about the Preakness, a race they still believe was stolen from them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a disputed loss in the Preakness 27 years ago, the champion filly Genuine Risk’s legacy was hampered by injury and the failure to produce champion offspring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bert and Diana Firestone will not be at the Preakness Stakes on Saturday, but they will be watching, and more intently than most. This is the time of year when their memories of the 1980 Triple Crown campaign and their terrific filly Genuine Risk come flooding back.</p>
        <p>A couple of weeks ago, it was about the Kentucky Derby, a race won by Genuine Risk, only the second filly to ever win that race. This week, it is about the Preakness, a race they still believe was stolen from them.</p>
        <p>Genuine Risk, now 30 and the oldest living Kentucky Derby winner, did not cross the wire first that day 27 years ago at Pimlico in Baltimore. A horse named Codex did. But the Firestones and much of the public felt that Codex interfered with Genuine Risk, costing her the victory by carrying her wide on the far turn.</p>
        <p>A foul claim by Genuine Risk's jockey, Jacinto Vasquez, was rejected by the track stewards, as was an appeal to the Maryland Racing Commission. The official winner remained Codex, trained by D. Wayne Lukas and ridden by Angel Cordero Jr.</p>
        <p>''We have always thought that Codex should have been taken down,'' Bert Firestone said. ''We did what we thought was the right thing to do. It didn't work out in our favor.''</p>
        <p>The Firestones, still active in the sport, have not had a Preakness starter since. They had hoped to get there with one of Genuine Risk's offspring, but it did not work out.</p>
        <p>Genuine Risk appeared to come out of the Preakness with a bright future as a racehorse and as a broodmare. But she won only three more races before her career ended because of a freakish injury, and she delivered only two live foals, neither of whom ever started in a race.</p>
        <p>Genuine Risk finished second in the Belmont Stakes in June before winning one of two starts the remainder of her 3-year-old season. She won two of three starts as a 4-year-old, but they were allowance races. One morning on the backstretch at Belmont Park, she got loose, ran into a fire hydrant and sustained a career-ending knee injury.</p>
        <p>Still, there did not seem to be any reason Genuine Risk would not pass her talents on to her offspring. She was bred to Secretariat in her initial assignment, the first time two Kentucky Derby winners were mated. The foal, a colt, was stillborn.</p>
        <p>''It was devastating to lose that first foal,'' said the Firestone's farm manager, John Moore. ''It was a great thing, breeding a Derby winner to a Derby winner.''</p>
        <p>She was bred back to Secretariat. Again, she failed to produce a live foal. It became a recurring story. After retiring from the track in 1981, Genuine Risk did not deliver her first live foal until 1993. The foal, Genuine Reward, was a healthy chestnut by the sire Rahy. It soon became apparent, though, that he had no future in racing.</p>
        <p>Genuine Risk continued to struggle to reproduce until 1996, when she delivered Count Our Blessing, a son of the sire Chief Honcho. But he had no more ability as a racehorse than Genuine Reward did.</p>
        <p>''With their pedigrees, if they couldn't run up to the ability of their families, it was decided it would be better to place them in careers in which they could be successful,'' said the Firestones' son, Matthew, who as a 14-year-old picked out Genuine Risk at a yearling sale and persuaded his parents to buy her for $32,000. Genuine Reward was sent to Wyoming, where he is a sire of polo ponies. Count Our Blessing was turned into a show horse. After four more unproductive matings, Genuine Risk was retired from breeding duties in 2000 and now lives at the Firestones' Newstead Farm here.</p>
        <p>''She was a great race mare,'' Bert Firestone said. ''It would have been nice for her to be a great broodmare, too. But it doesn't always work out that way. If I could have had my choice, I'd take having a great race mare over having a great broodmare.''</p>
        <p>Genuine Risk's life these days is slow and relaxed. She is doted on by the Firestones and the staff at Newstead and gets all the peppermints she wants, plus her favorite treat, Tic Tacs. Much of her day is spent grazing in a lush paddock at the farm, often in the accompaniment of another mare.</p>
        <p>''When we get one of our fillies back from the track and we need someone to turn them out with, we used Genuine Risk as a baby sitter,'' Moore said. ''That's why I call her Grandma. She keeps the other horses quiet. They come here from the track and they need time off and they need to settle down. She does a good job getting them to do that. But she stands her ground. No one bosses her around.''</p>
        <p>Her only physical problem is an arthritic left front knee, the same one she banged up in the accident at Belmont.</p>
        <p>''She's gotten very old, but she sure is hanging in there well,'' Moore said. ''Maybe it's something in her genes.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
