<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>India Sets Inquiry into Pilgrim Deaths; Toll at 239</title>
    <meta content="01KASH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="874806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hinduism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pilgrimages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Himalayas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gupta, Indrajit (Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hinduism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3D91538F932A3575AC0A960958260" item-length="336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>India Sets Inquiry into Pilgrim Deaths; Toll at 239</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Aug. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Official toll of Hindu pilgrims killed in blizzard in Himalayas rises to 239; Interior Minister of India, Indrajit Gupta, tells Parliament that Government will begin inquiry into why officials allowed more than 100,000 people to embark on 27-mile ascent into mountains ahead of the storm; Gupta says inqiury would not be headed by any officials who oversaw arrangements for the pilgrimage (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The official toll of Hindu pilgrims killed in a blizzard in the Himalayas has risen to 239, and the Interior Minister has told Parliament that the Government will begin an inquiry into why officials allowed more than 100,000 people to embark on a 27-mile ascent into the mountains ahead of the storm.</p>
        <p>The minister, Indrajit Gupta, said on Friday that the inquiry would not be headed by any officials from the state of Jammu and Kashmir, which oversaw arrangements for the pilgrimage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The official toll of Hindu pilgrims killed in a blizzard in the Himalayas has risen to 239, and the Interior Minister has told Parliament that the Government will begin an inquiry into why officials allowed more than 100,000 people to embark on a 27-mile ascent into the mountains ahead of the storm.</p>
        <p>The minister, Indrajit Gupta, said on Friday that the inquiry would not be headed by any officials from the state of Jammu and Kashmir, which oversaw arrangements for the pilgrimage.</p>
        <p>In the past, families of disaster victims in India have often complained that inquiries were conducted by officials whose duties linked them to the disasters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gupta said rescue parties continued to search along the ascent to the Amarnath Cave, which is regarded as one of Hinduism's most sacred shrines, and it seemed likely that the death toll would continue to rise. Opposition members of Parliament flying in army helicopters over the area said they had seen many bodies still lying on the mountain on Wednesday. Mr. Gupta said rescue parties continued to search along wide stretches of the ascent.</p>
        <p>Officials have said that many of the pilgrims ignored Government warnings to take warm clothing, but Mr. Gupta said today that 70 of the bodies recovered so far were those of porters hired by the pilgrims, who were local men familiar with mountain conditions.</p>
        <p>The Interior Minister also hinted at a Government failure to react quickly enough to the snowstorm and torrential rains that precipitated the disaster. He told Parliament that during an unrelated visit he made on Aug. 22 to Srinagar, 50 miles from the disaster area, it was already ''raining heavily, with icy winds.''</p>
        <p>Officials did not stop pilgrims from setting out until last Friday morning, when many of the victims were already dead.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
