<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Russian Crime Drama Deepens With Arrests</title>
    <meta content="Y21RUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/21/international/europe/21RUSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1442467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Petersburg (Russia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starovoitova, Galina V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/St. Petersburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE6D71739F932A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Russian Crime Drama Deepens With Arrests</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Russian Crime Drama Deepens With Arrests</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Russia, Nov. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recent arrest of six men charged in 1998 St Petersburg, Russia, murder of prominent Parliament member Galina V Starovoitova has only deepened mystery surrounding her death; officials refuse to identify suspects, saying probe is still under way; murky probe shows how faintly death of leading champion of democracy resonates in nation where assassination is part of politics and rule of law still struggles to find its way through secrecy, criminality and corruption; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For four years little but rumor swirled around the killing of Galina V. Starovoitova, a prominent member of Parliament who was shot three times in the head in her apartment stairwell. Much of it was false, some of it lurid.</p>
        <p>Then, 10 days ago, the cloak of secrecy that has shrouded the investigation lifted, ever so briefly. Russia's Federal Security Service, or F.S.B., a successor of the Soviet K.G.B., announced that investigators had arrested and charged six men in the case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The investigation into the killing of a prominent member of Parliament remains cloaked of secrecy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For four years little but rumor swirled around the killing of Galina V. Starovoitova, a prominent member of Parliament who was shot three times in the head in her apartment stairwell. Much of it was false, some of it lurid.</p>
        <p>Then, 10 days ago, the cloak of secrecy that has shrouded the investigation lifted, ever so briefly. Russia's Federal Security Service, or F.S.B., a successor of the Soviet K.G.B., announced that investigators had arrested and charged six men in the case.</p>
        <p>Far from resolving the mystery, however, the arrests have deepened it.</p>
        <p>While the suspects have been indicted, officials refused to identify them, saying the investigation is still under way. More suspects apparently remain at large. Investigators refused to discuss any facts of the case and told Ms. Starovoitova's sister and her aide, who was gravely wounded in the attack, not to discuss any of the details they had been told.</p>
        <p>Ms. Starovoitova's killing -- four years ago on Wednesday -- represented a body blow to Russia's nascent democracy. The murky investigation represents the state of Russia's democratic transition today, illustrating how faintly her death resonates in a country where assassination is a macabre feature of politics and the rule of law still struggles to find its way through secrecy, criminality and corruption.</p>
        <p>''Many of us regard the apprehension and punishment of Galina's assassins as a fundamental test for the Russian state,'' wrote Margaret Thatcher, the former British prime minister.</p>
        <p>That was more than two years ago.</p>
        <p>The arrests have raised hopes that a breakthrough might be near, though Ms. Starovoitova's allies remain skeptical, saying that arrests and suspects have been reported before, only to prove unfounded.</p>
        <p>What is clear is that Ms. Starovoitova's killing was not a random, isolated attack, but rather a broadly organized plot to assassinate one of Russia's most outspoken champions of democracy. Someone ordered her killed, but so far no one knows -- or will say -- who or why.</p>
        <p>''I have always expressed the point of view that either the investigators know who killed her but don't have the evidence to make arrests or that the traces of this crime lead so far to the top that the investigative bodies don't want to look any further,'' said Yuri M. Schmidt, a lawyer who has represented Ms. Starovoitova's family.</p>
        <p>The common denominator of the string of political assassinations in Russia -- including, most recently, the killing of the governor of the Far Eastern province Magadan in broad daylight on one of Moscow's busiest streets -- is that they are rarely solved.</p>
        <p>Most have been linked to the victims' ''business dealings,'' the Russian euphemism for the pervasive corruption of political officials. The killings are so common that Russians respond with resignation more than outrage.</p>
        <p>The killing of Ms. Starovoitova, however, was different. Ms. Starovoitova, who was 52, was an ethnographer who rose to political prominence in the 1980's. She was elected to the Soviet Parliament in 1989, representing Armenia, after writing a spirited letter supporting the Armenian quest for independence.</p>
        <p>She later advised Russia's first elected president, Boris N. Yeltsin, co-founded the Democratic Russia party and became an advocate of economic, political and judicial changes, railing against Communists, nationalists and others who resisted these reforms. She was twice elected to the new Russian Parliament, representing St. Petersburg.</p>
        <p>On the night of Nov. 20, 1998, she arrived here on a flight from Moscow and, with her aide, Ruslan Linkov, returned to her apartment on the embankment of one of St. Petersburg's elegant, winding canals. Mr. Linkov, in an interview, recalled few details of the shooting except that he saw two figures moving down the staircase and firing at Ms. Starovoitova. Mr. Linkov, shot in the neck and head, then lost consciousness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin vowed to find the assassins, ordering his interior minister and the head of the F.S.B. at the time, Vladimir V. Putin, to oversee the investigation personally. His order reflected the political significance of the crime, but having the F.S.B. take a lead also ensured the investigation would proceed in utter secrecy.</p>
        <p>The police found two weapons, strong leads to pursue, but the investigation appeared to stall from the start. Early on, investigators questioned journalists, who later reported that the questions focused not on the killers but on Ms. Starovoitova, her finances and even the sexual proclivities of supporters.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the F.S.B. here, Yelena O. Tikhonova, said investigators had worked tirelessly, interviewing more than 1,000 witnesses and carrying out dozens of searches and forensic tests. But neither she nor Gen. Mikhail Milushkin, the agency's deputy director who announced the arrests on Nov. 6, would discuss the case.</p>
        <p>It was not clear why General Milushkin would announce arrests but not provide the suspects' names, though Ms. Starovoitova's supporters believe that investigators felt pressure to show progress as yet another anniversary of the killing approached.</p>
        <p>Ms. Starovoitova's sister, Olga, said investigators had briefed her on some of the evidence, but asked her not to divulge details. All she could say was that the suspects were believed to belong to a criminal organization, the Tambov Group, which is reputed to wield influence over much of St. Petersburg's economy and politics. Among those arrested is a former member of Russia's military intelligence. The killers and their accomplices, she said, rented an apartment near Ms. Starovoitova's, followed her car from the airport that night and, intriguingly, recorded her television appearances leading up to the killing.</p>
        <p>''There are only versions,'' she replied when asked if the investigators had suggested a motive for the killing. ''It's only the first step,'' Ms. Starovoitova's sister added, referring to the arrests. ''And nobody is sure whether the next step will be taken.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Linkov complained that investigators never interrogated the political leaders who had clashed with Ms. Starovoitova. They include Vladimir A. Yakovlev, St. Peterburg's governor since 1996; Gennadi N. Seleznyov, the former Communist leader who remains speaker of the Parliament; and Albert M. Makashov, a retired major general and former nationalist deputy.</p>
        <p>Yuri A. Kravtsov, a former member of St. Petersburg's city council, said it might be impossible to discern the motive amid the swirling power struggles that still afflict Russia.</p>
        <p>''She was an obstacle to so many who saw her standing in their way,'' he said, ''but of course no one can say absolutely that they killed her.''</p>
        <p>As the investigation drags on, Ms. Starovoitova's supporters have tried to keep alive the values she espoused, at times, it seems, in the face of public indifference. Her office, in a stately building on Bolshaya Morskaya Street, is now a small museum, but few visit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Linkov is now the chairman of the St. Petersburg chapter of her Democratic Russia party. When Ms. Starovoitova died, the party had four representatives in Parliament. Today it has none.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
