<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cool, at Least for a Few Minutes</title>
    <meta content="14misshape" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/14/fashion/14misshape.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060921T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1789779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fringe Groups and Movements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Groups and Movements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0D71531F937A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cool, at Least for a Few Minutes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cool, at Least for a Few Minutes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was five minutes past 1 a.m. Sunday. The line for the MisShapes, a popular dance party held every Saturday at Don Hill's in SoHo, stretched down the block. Fashion Week had started, and the MisShapes -- three D.J.'s named Geordon Nicol, Greg Krelenstein and Leigh Lezark -- had put out word that the singer Kelis was coming, along with the models Gemma Ward and Lily Donaldson.</p>
        <p>Don Hill's is little more than a dingy bar, but that night it was packed with art world and music stars, as well as hundreds of fiendishly dressed young people who had adopted the MisShapes style of wearing a heavy curtain of jet-black hair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week, MisShapes will select the music for either the shows or afterparties of Calvin Klein, Tory Burch and L.A.M.B, the label of Gwen Stefani.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was five minutes past 1 a.m. Sunday. The line for the MisShapes, a popular dance party held every Saturday at Don Hill's in SoHo, stretched down the block. Fashion Week had started, and the MisShapes -- three D.J.'s named Geordon Nicol, Greg Krelenstein and Leigh Lezark -- had put out word that the singer Kelis was coming, along with the models Gemma Ward and Lily Donaldson.</p>
        <p>Don Hill's is little more than a dingy bar, but that night it was packed with art world and music stars, as well as hundreds of fiendishly dressed young people who had adopted the MisShapes style of wearing a heavy curtain of jet-black hair.</p>
        <p>Max Minghella came outside for a cigarette. Mr. Minghella, an actor and Columbia student whose father is the well-known director, wore a blue blazer, a rumpled white shirt and jeans. He didn't, on the surface, look like the kind of young man who would be at the MisShapes party, much less be part of the inner circle that hangs out in Don Hill's basement.</p>
        <p>But that was the thing about the MisShapes, he said. They don't throw up any barriers to admission, in spite of their intimidatingly cool facade. Ms. Lezark, for whom half the guys in the basement probably nursed a serious crush, has been dubbed Princess Coldstare on the Web. But that's not how Mr. Minghella saw them. ''Geordon, Greg and Leigh are the sweetest people on the planet,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The MisShapes are, at least, a phenomenon, if not a puzzle. Mr. Krelenstein is 25; his partners both 23. The products of comfortable suburban or small-town upbringings, they formed the MisShapes almost as a fluke nearly three years ago, taking the name from a Jarvis Cocker song.</p>
        <p>Partly because of the way they look -- the men are reed thin and favor a severe bowl-shaped haircut, Ms. Lezark is a femme fatale version of Ali MacGraw -- and partly because they have an entourage, they have been compared to Andy Warhol and other figures of the 1960's underground.</p>
        <p>Yet the MisShapes are really a contemporary idea, their status derived less from any recognizable achievement, like making art, music or films, than by their celebrity on the Internet. Their Web site (www.misshapes.com) includes thousands of pictures from their parties, documenting virtually every kind of new and bizarre style.</p>
        <p>In places like the Philippines and Brazil, there are Web diaries and role-playing sites devoted to the activities of the MisShapes. When they flew to Miami to do a party for a boy's 18th birthday, they found their images plastered on his bedroom walls. ''He knew everything about their personalities,'' said Gordon Hull, a friend of the group's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hull, 29, who runs Surface2Air, an art direction, design and publishing company with offices in New York and Paris, continued: ''Every five or 10 years there has to be something new for the young people coming to New York. These kids are even more savvy because the Internet came along at the same time that they did. The fact is their Web site made them big, because of the whole party-pix phenomenon.''</p>
        <p>The group recently engaged an agent to find a book deal for their Web images. (The MisShapes make most of their money not from their weekly party but from D.J.ing events for magazines and designers.)</p>
        <p>It is on the fashion world, though, that the MisShapes have had the most impact. This week they will select the music for either the shows or afterparties of Calvin Klein, Tory Burch and L.A.M.B, the label of Gwen Stefani. Ten days ago, they were in Las Vegas to D.J. a party at Magic, the apparel trade fair. The group has been approached by the London designer Vivienne Westwood to give creative advice for a new store here. And this past July, much to their surprise, the MisShapes' skinny mop-haired look served as inspiration for Hedi Slimane's Dior Homme show in Paris.</p>
        <p>''It was so funny,'' Mr. Nicol said over dinner with Ms. Lezark and Mr. Krelenstein as he recalled his reaction to seeing his style transferred to Mr. Slimane's runway.</p>
        <p>''It was scary,'' said Ms. Lezark, who also attended the show, sitting across from Karl Lagerfeld and Elton John. ''When the first model came down the runway, I said to Geordon, 'Uh, he really looks like you.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Slimane, who is known for mining the styles of obscure bands and club scenes, visited Don Hill's at least once, for a party in 2005 to promote his photographic book ''Birth of a Cult.''</p>
        <p>Fashion designers have long shown a vampire interest in the style and tastes of fringe groups, sucking them dry, and older houses, in particular, have depended on them for cachet with young fashion consumers. For the MisShapes, there is a danger they will lose credibility if they are seen as being in the pocket of big companies. Gawker, the media gossip site, has taken a number of swipes at the MisShapes, implying that a backlash is under way.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicol, who serves as the de facto manager of the group (Mr. Krelenstein works for a casting agency and Ms. Lezark is in college), said he doesn't see a downside to working for fashion brands that have little in common with the MisShapes' hip image.</p>
        <p>''Gawker has been saying there's a backlash for more than two years,'' Mr. Nicol said. ''But the head count of the MisShapes parties has been exactly the same, give or take 100 people. And the amount of money made at the bar is the same.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Krelenstein added that contrary to the perception that the MisShapes are too cool for school, the D.J.'s have always taken an inclusive approach to the parties. They play all types of music, and there's no guest list at the door. For instance, on Monday, the group will do music for a party for the Hard Rock Cafe in Times Square, performing with Mötley Crüe.</p>
        <p>''I'm really excited about that,'' Mr. Krelenstein said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nicol nodded. ''We're going to actually be on stage with Mötley Crüe. Then we're doing a Teen Vogue party in L.A.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Krelenstein laughed. ''Mötley Crüe to Teen Vogue.'' He added, ''I think that's our tastes. And I think it's one of the reasons we've been so successful. For instance, we like the new Beyoncé song. It's not the coolest, but it's a good song.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Hull, whose company designed some of the printed fabrics for Marc Jacobs's collection this week, has his doubts, which he has voiced to the MisShapes.</p>
        <p>''I love them to pieces but I don't think they understand a lot of what they're doing,'' he said. ''They are really young. When they told me they were doing the music for Tory Burch, I said, 'What the hell are you doing that for?' And they said, 'Because she's an important socialite.' I told them, 'You guys need to be smart about what you're doing because you're going to lose the cachet you didn't even try to get.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hull thinks the MisShapes can have a career after the parties wind down, as consultants to youth-oriented brands. But he says they have to be careful about the choices they make.</p>
        <p>''I know they admire Raf Simons and Martin Margiela,'' Mr. Hull said, referring to designers who have a high degree of credibility among fashion insiders, in part because they've kept such low profiles. ''But the kids are obsessed with Hedi Slimane and Karl Lagerfeld, and that's a totally different perspective.''</p>
        <p>To the MisShapes' generation, however, the underground doesn't really exist. The Internet exposes everything in about two seconds. Alexis Page, another friend of the group's, who develops products for MAC cosmetics, said: ''Gordon derives his view from the way he and his partners work at Surface2Air. They're very selective. Lately, Geordon has been eager that the MisShapes do other things. They are kind of everywhere at the moment, but I don't think it's going to hurt them.''</p>
        <p>Certainly the MisShapes agree. A few months ago they were invited up to Sotheby's to play music for a party kicking off a sale of contemporary Russian art. The average age of the guests, Ms. Lezark reckoned, was about 35.</p>
        <p>''Everybody loved it,'' Mr. Krelenstein said, sounding surprised himself. ''People kept coming up to us and saying, 'Do you have a card?' ''</p>
        <p>This summer the MisShapes officially became a corporation.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 21, 2006, Thursday  A picture caption last Thursday with an article about the MisShapes, a group of D.J.'s, misspelled the name of a fashion designer shown at one of their parties. He is Alexandre Herchcovitch, not Alexander Herckovitch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 21, 2006, Thursday</p>
        <p>A picture caption last Thursday with an article about the MisShapes, a group of D.J.'s, misspelled the name of a fashion designer shown at one of their parties. He is Alexandre Herchcovitch, not Alexander Herckovitch.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
