<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The French Art of Living, Back in Business in Paris</title>
    <meta content="14muse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/14/arts/design/14muse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1789795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris (France)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Dubuffet, Jean</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Guimard, Hector</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EED71531F937A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The French Art of Living, Back in Business in Paris</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The French Art of Living, Back in Business in Paris</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Sept. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even in a city that last year boasted close to 60 million visitors to its myriad cultural institutions, a major museum that remains closed for a decade risks being forgotten. So in a sense when the Musée des Arts Décoratifs finally reopens here on Friday after a $46 million makeover, it will be starting afresh in trying to woo the public.</p>
        <p>Those in the business -- designers, manufacturers, collectors and dealers -- are of course delighted that the decorative arts again have a Paris home. And, by no coincidence, many are already gathering here from around the world for the 23rd Biennale des Antiquaires, which also opens on Friday and runs through Sept. 24 at the Grand Palais.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now at the Musée des Arts Décoratifs in Paris, which is reopening after being closed for the last decade: textiles, glassware and savoir-faire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even in a city that last year boasted close to 60 million visitors to its myriad cultural institutions, a major museum that remains closed for a decade risks being forgotten. So in a sense when the Musée des Arts Décoratifs finally reopens here on Friday after a $46 million makeover, it will be starting afresh in trying to woo the public.</p>
        <p>Those in the business -- designers, manufacturers, collectors and dealers -- are of course delighted that the decorative arts again have a Paris home. And, by no coincidence, many are already gathering here from around the world for the 23rd Biennale des Antiquaires, which also opens on Friday and runs through Sept. 24 at the Grand Palais.</p>
        <p>But art lovers more accustomed to looking at paintings, sculptures and antiquities in, say, the Louvre or the Musée d'Orsay may need more persuading to include this museum in their circuit. After all, not everyone finds a Sèvres vase or an 18th-century chest of drawers as instantly appealing as a Leonardo or a Monet.</p>
        <p>Still, the museum has one strong card: it addresses what has long been a source of French pride and the envy of foreigners.</p>
        <p>Put differently, it tells the story of France's art de vivre -- its interior decoration, its changing style, its affection for luxury, its love of food and its obsession with taste -- through furniture, ceramics, porcelain, glassware, textiles, jewelry and even toys.</p>
        <p>''It's the only French museum that covers the whole sweep of French history,'' its director, Béatrice Salmon, said, noting that the collection starts in the Middle Ages and ends with today's design. ''Its aim is to promote French industry, French art de vivre and French savoir-faire.''</p>
        <p>It also has elegantly refurbished quarters to match that ambition.</p>
        <p>Its location in the 19th-century Marsan Wing of the Louvre Palace along the Rue de Rivoli has not changed since the museum opened in 1905. But the removal of a mezzanine now brings natural light into its soaring main gallery from a glass roof five floors above, while newly opened windows offer panoramic views of the rest of the Louvre and the Tuileries Gardens.</p>
        <p>The museum's display -- some 6,000 items from its 150,000-piece collection -- has also been reorganized along broadly chronological lines, albeit with pauses for special features, like galleries on the ''arts'' of resting and eating, as well as the toy section and a room of paintings donated in the 1960's by Jean Dubuffet.</p>
        <p>Among the highlights are 10 beautifully recreated period rooms peppered throughout the museum. Organized by the designer François-Joseph Graf, they give visitors an almost voyeuristic look inside the homes -- O.K., the castles and mansions -- of French aristocrats and wealthy bourgeois from the late 15th to the early 20th century.</p>
        <p>What the rooms also illustrate is how, while individual artists in Italy and northern Europe were already famous by the time of Renaissance, little is known about the weavers, carpenters, silversmiths and potters who created the tapestries, furnishings and tableware for privileged homes before the 19th century. Unlike Piero della Francesca and Dürer, they are anonymous.</p>
        <p>Does this mean that the decorative arts are -- or were -- somehow inferior to painting and sculpture?</p>
        <p>These are dangerous waters. In terms of offering the creator both immediate prestige and a place in posterity, for a long time painters and sculptors won out. Yet, if judged by how they enhanced the image and social standing of the homeowner, craftsmen were undoubtedly of immense value.</p>
        <p>Then, as industrialization facilitated production, the designer appeared between the artist and the craftsman. He was more concerned with creating a style than an individual object; and he was sought out by the wealthy as a kind of guarantor of good taste. Soon, as he does today, he came to enjoy as many kudos as many leading artists.</p>
        <p>Thus around 1880 Eugène Grasset was invited by his friend the art collector Charles Gillot to design an elaborate dining room, which is one of the period rooms here. Entered through a stained-glass door, it is peopled with ornamental figures, animals and plants. The creators of these objects are not identified. The room, as such, is ''signed'' by Grasset.</p>
        <p>But the designer could not trump the patron. One striking period suite comprises a boudoir, bedroom and bathroom designed in the early 1920's by Albert-Armand Rateau for the prominent couturier Jeanne Lanvin. The rooms are discreetly furnished in an Art Deco style, with the walls of the bedroom and boudoir covered in blue silk. And they are known as the Lanvin -- not the Rateau -- rooms.</p>
        <p>More of a showpiece for Art Deco is an office-library in the round designed by Pierre Chareau for the French Embassy pavilion at the 1925 Paris International Exhibition. It contains Chareau's original chair and black desk, but its most distinguishing feature is a domed ceiling with a leaflike wooden mechanism that reveals or hides book shelves.</p>
        <p>In the rest of the collection there is a similar passage from objects of historical importance to designs carrying famous names. The oldest pieces are religious paintings and ornate retables, works which could easily be in the Louvre but here underline the early blurring between public and domestic art. Soon, though, the focus turns to the home, from beds and tables to ceramics and glass.</p>
        <p>The sophistication of the objects increases as cabinetmakers add mosaic inlays and porcelain absorbs Chinese influence. Wood paneling in turn became an art in itself, later replaced by silk and eventually by beautifully painted wallpaper. These features are also well illustrated in various period rooms.</p>
        <p>But from the late 19th century on, names take over: Charles Christofle was followed by René Lalique as jewelers to the rich; Hector Guimard was an influential Art Nouveau architect; Art Deco made the names of Robert Mallet-Stevens as well as of Rateau; and early Le Corbusier represents the Bauhaus. Philippe Starck, France's most famous designer today, completes the litany of stars.</p>
        <p>Perhaps unsurprisingly, then, it was the emergence of decorative arts as an industry that inspired the creation of the Musée des Arts Décoratifs in 1905. And, unusually for France, it was founded as -- and remains -- a privately run museum, which answers to patrons, collectors and industrialists.</p>
        <p>The government financed 60 percent of the cost of its recent renovation, but a private association called Les Arts Décoratifs owns its collection. The association also operates the adjacent Musée de la Mode et du Textile and the Musée de la Publicité, as well as the Musée Nissim Comondo, formerly a private mansion, in the city's Eighth Arrondissement.</p>
        <p>With this week's reopening of the Musée des Arts Décoratifs, the association is once again assuming its patriotic role of promoting France as the ultimate arbiter of style, taste and luxury. Lovers of the decorative arts naturally have good reason to celebrate, but this is serious business. And the museum has a new gift shop and restaurant to prove it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
