<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Visions of New York's Future</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="819539"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK, NY, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOLFE, GEORGE C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARDY, HUGH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVINE, DOUG</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">IMPERATORE, ARTHUR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLY,KEVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERRERA, CAROLINA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MATSIL, MARC A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MONK, MEREDITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABAZZ, SHARIEF</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEVINE, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SASSEN, SASKIA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STODDARD, TOM (PROF)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARTGROVE, BILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIFTON, ROBERT J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REGAN, JUDITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUSTO, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARKER, DEB ANDREW LLOYD WEBBER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/George C Wolfe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3D61239F932A05751C1A963958260" item-length="4573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Visions of New York's Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of course, New York isn't the only city that attracts dreamers. But having organized its port a century-and-a-half ago with a savvy and ruthlessness that left Boston and Philadelphia dazzled in defeat, New York perhaps has a birthright to predict the future.</p>
        <p>Ask for visions and themes emerge. The computer is a major focus, as if it were a torpedo thrust at our vanity and our reason to be -- physical proximity.  There is fascination with the future shape of the city. Will it be vertical? Will our waistline center remain the inland of Manhattan, or will development move toward the rivers, or even skip over the waters, into Queens and the South  Bronx?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Of course, New York isn't the only city that attracts dreamers. But having organized its port a century-and-a-half ago with a savvy and ruthlessness that left Boston and Philadelphia dazzled in defeat, New York perhaps has a birthright to predict the future.</p>
        <p>Ask for visions and themes emerge. The computer is a major focus, as if it were a torpedo thrust at our vanity and our reason to be -- physical proximity.  There is fascination with the future shape of the city. Will it be vertical? Will our waistline center remain the inland of Manhattan, or will development move toward the rivers, or even skip over the waters, into Queens and the South  Bronx?</p>
        <p>Some fear a loss of idiosyncrasy; others see fringe groups gaining more influence in an information age. There is intense concern about racial and class fragmentation and the uneducated in a city that will demand more education. There is also hope and excitement.</p>
        <p>THEATER TRAUMA</p>
        <p>George C. Wolfe Artistic Director of the Public Theater</p>
        <p>The nightmare version is that New York City becomes one giant Andrew Lloyd Webber theme park with theaters showing all Andrew Lloyd Webber shows, with tubes connecting the theaters. Oh yes, and revivals -- maybe in the tunnels you  could pass the revivals as you go from one Andrew Lloyd Webber show to the next.</p>
        <p>Now, my fantasy is there is no concept of uptown and downtown theater, but just theater showing extraordinary American plays by playwrights that reflect of all American realities, and people trying to reinvent the musical form and that the New York audience looks like all of New York City, because right now it doesn't.</p>
        <p>It's a very bleak time. At this point in time there are people in power who don't understand why culture is important, and that's scary because it's become  cultural survival of the fittest.</p>
        <p>There's a Russian proverb that goes: you must support the most talented people because untalented people will support themselves. And that's important.  Right now the biggest challenge is economic; theaters are just going to die. The ecology of New York theater is intricate. Off Off Broadway houses -- the theaters that tend and grow playwrights and artists for a year or two before a larger theater like the the Public or Lincoln Center can help -- a lot of those  theaters could conceivably die.</p>
        <p>If that does happen, the nightmare I described is more likely to happen. And  if you continue to nurture, then my fantasy will happen.</p>
        <p>Meredith Monk Performance Artist</p>
        <p>I do think you'll see decentralization. I've had this vision of being an art  farmer, where I'd plant my seeds and do my gardening elsewhere, and then just come into city at the harvest. I don't know if artists have to be here to do the work itself, but you need the city, the audience to share the work. To have the  experience of the city in reality will always be part of the artists' lives, but it may not be the only way of going.</p>
        <p>One thing I sense happening now is that because of adversity, young people coming here have to have a lot more imagination. When I first came in '64, there was a lot of energy, a lot of performing spaces opening, but the financial aspect wasn't the prime aspect. But now it's very hard for young people. What would be ideal would be all kinds of gathering places where there would a kind of energy and exchange. Maybe take down some buildings and put down some grass.  Sometimes I feel like a Luddite. "Get out that hammer for the computer!"</p>
        <p>The dystopic view is that everything closes down and the gatekeepers become more and more powerful and the young people get so discouraged they leave and then there'll be no energy or imagination. You have to build the courage to take the risk. Past, present, the future. That's the beauty of art, to risk the unknown.</p>
        <p>VERTICAL CITY?</p>
        <p>Hugh Hardy The architect who restored the New Victory Theater, the New York Botanical Garden, the Rainbow Room and Windows on the World.</p>
        <p>One of the things that is lasting about New York is the vertical density. Things are squashed together here by the 19th, well it's really an 18th century  street grid. So it won't be possible to change that. And this will always make New York a great place with a lot of elbowing and shoving. Even virtual reality  can't do that for you!</p>
        <p>Wall Street has to be reinvented because its role as a financial center is changing. With computers there has been an enormous shift in the daytime population downtown. In the future, lower Manhattan will be a place where people live, work and play. The city is actually encouraging this with tax abatements.</p>
        <p>I think about what the city will look like all the time. I do think there will be fanciful large structures made with new technology. Buildings will be built, for instance, with glass that changes opacity with the sunlight. So you will be able to see into them when it's dark and not when it's light. And there will be ever greater extremes between the old and the new. No architect in town has challenged the visual status quo much, but they will.</p>
        <p>For one thing there won't be the need for large, boxy buildings with many workers in the future. In the 1980's people built large buildings with open floors. There will still be large buildings but they will be mixed use between residential and business. Or many businesses. The era of the single-owned office building is ending.</p>
        <p>I can well imagine new subways completed and a connection to the airports constructed. And there might be water taxis to the airports. How funny! An old idea adapted to new technology. We won't have jet packs, but I can imagine a trolley system on the streets. Americans always want the future to be made out of something they have never seen before, but I think the future could be using  old things in a new way.</p>
        <p>Kevin Kelly Executive Editor of Wired magazine</p>
        <p>My suspicion is that in the short term it's bad news for a place like New York City. Skyscrapers are over. There's so little reason for them because people don't need height. The question is going to be what to do with all those  tall buildings. People don't need to be that tight anymore. Skyscrapers were emblematic of achievement, but we don't believe in that kind of progress any more. It was high-tech because we could do it, with telephone and elevators, but there are other kinds of technology now -- fiber optics and overnight delivery,  so you're going to end up with something that more resembles edge cites. Skyscrapers might end up as storage units or something.</p>
        <p>The future of New York City may be an inversion, with the outskirts being the engine, driving the city. And the intellectual and cultural centers might move to places that are not that dense. I mean, people write off the Bronx, or write  off Queens, that nothing consequential is happening there. But I could imagine in 25 years something happening like in San Francisco, where what to do with downtown is a problem. Maybe they become the projects; Manhattan as the projects and Queens as a multi-media alley or multi-media gulch.</p>
        <p>Cities will live on as long as meeting someone face to face is more powerful  than an electronic encounter.</p>
        <p>FITNESS</p>
        <p>Doug Levine Owner of Crunch, the fitness conglomerate In two to three years the gyms will be full of virtual reality technology. It's  going to be huge. You're going to be able to get on a bicycle and say, "I'm going to race the second day of the Tour de France," and depending on your mood  you can race against Greg LeMond and be able to say "Greg I'm going to beat you," and he'll answer you back.</p>
        <p>There will be a screen surrounding you on the bicycle on three sides. This will immerse you in the image.</p>
        <p>Right now there is virtual reality, but the simulators that are out there are very crude. It's like looking at a television screen.  It's developing, it's about two to three years away until it's cool.</p>
        <p>The second thing that is going to happen much sooner is that boxing, which started as a fad two years ago (when white-collar boxing and women for the first time entered the sport), will become mainstream. Boxing used to be a sport full  of cigars and corruption and all of sudden it started to be cool to do martial arts and to box. Now it's past the cool stage and it's become a legitimate exercise category with people hitting speed bags, heavy bags and jumping bags.</p>
        <p>And, there will be a molding of entertainment and fitness, where you're going to see people watching first-run movies while running on a treadmill.</p>
        <p>The whole population has moved from working 9 A.M. to 6 P.M. to 9 to 9 and they are stressed out. I think there will be a return to the eastern disciplines like Yoga, Meditation and Pilates, an old system of posture developed by a dancer to teach people alignment.</p>
        <p>In New York you're going to see -- as the paths along the river develop -- people will be using the waterfront more. You're going to see people skate boarding, roller-blading and running and biking around all of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>Carolina Herrera Fashion designer I think New York has taken over a lot, especially now that all the fashion shows are in one place in Bryant Park, and everyone doesn't have to run around.</p>
        <p>New York fashion is going to go very far. If we keep it together, New York will become a real competitor with Paris. Well, it already is, but Paris is still the fashion capital of the world.</p>
        <p>In New York, there's a lot of talent. A lot of the main European designers are inspired by the sportswear of the Gap and Banana Republic. It's very American. The designers are inspired by the running shoes, the T-shirts, the jeans and khakis. It's very New York. As for all the black clothes in New York,  it's very international. It's a sea of black.</p>
        <p>Still, it's very difficult for New York fashion designers to be accepted in Europe. Ralph Lauren is an exception.</p>
        <p>I think New York is fantastic. All the European designers want to do business in New York -- that's what they aspire to.</p>
        <p>Clothes are going to continue to be timeless, classic but with a modern twist. The younger generation is getting more elegant and more fashionable. There will be a return to classic elegance. People will try to look less grungy.</p>
        <p>Hopefully there will be less of the tennis sneakers with the skirts in New York. That's so unflattering, as are those leggings that everyone wears with the big jackets. Unless you're very young and have a great figure, you're simply a fashion victim.</p>
        <p>There will be a lot of sportswear in the day but the young women will be more elegant and glamourous at night.</p>
        <p>There will be less excessive makeup. Women look so much better when they don't wear too much makeup. I hate everything that is in excess.</p>
        <p>Americans are getting better looking, great figures, great looking.</p>
        <p>DEVELOPMENT</p>
        <p>Arthur Imperatore Developer and chairman of the board of NY Waterway.</p>
        <p>I believe there will be a great impetus, a kind of a wave of future growth in ancillary mass transport. New ways just to get to the highways, to the tunnels,  to the bridge networks, to park and rides. Lots of ferry locations on the Hudson, on Staten Island -- in places like Kill Van Kull, and in places like South Jersey, where you wouldn't think. . .</p>
        <p>And where this happens you're going to engender development, you're going to  see a change in quality of life, in improved property value and commercial development in those areas, and it will open the economy of the region.</p>
        <p>For example, Kill Van Kull is not the most picturesque place, but 50 years from now the old industrial sites will likely change into sites for recreation,  and residential housing. I see that. You have to envision a whole change in the  transportation pattern.</p>
        <p>There will be an increased emphasis on intermodality -- buses to boats, rails to buses. People will change modes; we've proven that. And transportation is the catalyst that has to precede any sort of development.</p>
        <p>Even in Queens, for example, and in Manhattan, in the TriBeCa area, you're seeing everyone building out toward the river. The city 150 years ago was different -- they filled the river and land area was made. The sites were operated by major transportation sources, seagoing commerce. But that's all changed. I anticipate development building toward the river and utilizing land that had been unavailable. Twenty-five, 50 years in the future you'll have office buildings on what is now the edge of river. Look at Battery Park.</p>
        <p>It will be an evolution of uses and zoning and economic opportunities used to gentrify many parts that are in disuse. The South Bronx could be a wonderful opportunity, cheap land taken over by the city. I think you'll see new hubs in Queens, and redevelopment of parts of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>I see service big time on the East River, stops at 78th Street, 61st Street,  51st Street, 34th Street, all up and down the East Side, with boats going down to the financial district. Communities -- you bet they'll grow.</p>
        <p>It's the enhancement of travel.  Incrementality, interconnectivity, intermodality, those are the key words.</p>
        <p>CLASS, RACE, SECURITY</p>
        <p>Sharief Shabazz Nation of Islam community security force Bedford-Stuyvesant</p>
        <p>I see the future as economically worse. The future looks very chaotic. People are walking around with no hope, despair. They are walking time bombs. Two years from now it will be worse. Race relations will be worse. There used to be economic programs for black people back in the 60's. Now there are no more programs. Black people have nothing. Do not be shocked in a year or so. Blood will be running in the streets like water from that fire hydrant. It's reality.</p>
        <p>John Devine Adjunct Professor of Education at New York University. Expert in troubled schools</p>
        <p>If the present trend continues, you're going to find more and more schools with metal detectors. The security guard force is going to get bigger and bigger. If you look at it, it's a straight line curve going up; in 1969, we had  zero security guards. Now, the present number, last time I counted, is 3,000 plus and growing, which is slightly less than the entire police force in Boston. It would be the ninth largest police force in the country. More metal detectors  are going to be moving up to the middle-class schools, to the more integrated high schools. The knee-jerk reaction is going to be metal detectors.</p>
        <p>The public space in these schools, and by public I mean everything but the classroom, is being patrolled by security guards. More importantly, and significantly, there's been a change in the role of the teacher outside of classroom space. There's the absence of the superiority gaze. That role has been taken over by the guards. Guards have an influence that can surpass that of the  teachers, both positively and negatively.</p>
        <p>The security guards are mostly community people, but the trend has been to have them just thrown into a school. They are the dominant adults in the public  spaces -- they're hanging out with the kids; they are much closer to them in a human way than most of the teachers are. They're giving kids guidance, preventing suicides, giving religious advice. Maybe in the future they should be trained as counselors. But educators are not focused on this. It's not chic to run programs for security guards. Most advanced thinking thinks that they should be trained by police.</p>
        <p>Saskia Sassen Professor of urban planning at Columbia University, and author of "Cities in a World Economy" (Pine Forge-Sage, 1994)</p>
        <p>This is no longer the era of an imperial capital, like Amsterdam in the 1600's, and London in the 1800's or New York after World War II. Things have really changed. Its going to be a while before these new ways of thinking come about. The fluidity of this time is immense. In the last 10 years there's been a radical reconfiguration. That's not going to be easy for New York -- not being No. 1 any more. That doesn't mean there's another city that's No. 1, but this is an era of the network. This is the era of telecommunications, of highly mobile culture.</p>
        <p>I'll tell you the weak point. It doesn't lie at the top, it lies at the middle and the lower middle. In New York, you can get the best, and you can also get the low-wage dirty work. The immigrants do that work and they will work, hard, hard, hard. What you don't have enough of is the solid middle. This is what you hear employers say again and again. The Achilles heel might well be in  the public education sector. That whole infrastructure, public education, that allows lower- and middle-class to survive in the city needs far more resources,  more attention. It creates a real void in the middle of this labor market -- you need good secretaries, good workers, good service and administrative workers in  the middle, and they're likely to come out of the public schools.</p>
        <p>My gut feeling is that I've been in enough meetings with business managers to know there is a growing awareness, in elite business sectors, that the lower  half of the city matters, that public education matters. But recognition is one  thing; doing it is another. The whole civic milieu needs to be mobilized. THE FAMILY</p>
        <p>Tom Stoddard Law professor, civil libertarian and AIDS patient.</p>
        <p>I'm certain gay marriages will be fully recognized. In fact, the state will  recognize all forms of family. Families will be defined by the people living in  them. Say, two senior citizens living together. Or two men or two women will be  a family. Whatever form of relationship nurtures and promotes love. The statutes will have to be rewritten, so that family isn't just a matter of blood or marriage.</p>
        <p>We will evolve to a kinder, more realistic world by 2010.</p>
        <p>The media dominates everything, and it will even more so. By 2010, we'll do  all our communication by computer. And we'll have many more voices than now. I think it'll make the world more democratic.</p>
        <p>By 2010, we will have reached such a crisis in health care that it will have to be totally reconfigured. The crisis will be the inability of most Americans to receive the kind of care they need. That's what managed care will bring them. Middle-class people will face the kind of problems that poor people face: not being able to go to the doctor of their choice, not being able to obtain necessary services, having to pay for their own medication. Plans won't include  some medicines, or mammograms.</p>
        <p>We'll have a cure for AIDS before 2010. The progress is incremental, so it's hard for people to see how much progress has been made. The progress over the last six months has been amazing. I'm in much better shape than I was six months ago.</p>
        <p>Isn't that the great irony? Our health care will become less accessible just at the moment that medical knowledge is exploding beyond our wildest dreams.</p>
        <p>Bill Hartgrove Night manager, Frank E. Campbell Funeral Chapel</p>
        <p>One thing I see, and I know it's going to be a growing idea: a lot of people are coming in to preplan, prearrange and prepay their funerals.</p>
        <p>It's beginning to be very important to people to say, down the line, things  might be different. Many times, the people are sick for a long time, or their financial situation changes. They think, "I have the opportunity now to pay for  what I want," and then the price is frozen.</p>
        <p>People are becoming more accepting of death. I think they know, in our world today, that people are all over, that families aren't together anymore. You have the older people moving to Florida, and they have to think: What are we going to do? You used to stay within the family, and the family took care of things.</p>
        <p>As far as where people will be buried, there's still a lot of land around when you get out of the city. You might go to cemeteries in Westchester, Long Island and New Jersey. And many cemeteries are building mausoleums and crypts. So there is space.</p>
        <p>INFORMATION, THE SOCIAL CITY</p>
        <p>Robert J. Lifton Distinguished Professor of Psychology and Psychiatry at City University</p>
        <p>The availability of information is going to increase, so everybody in New York City is going to have even more opinions. That's sort of a scary idea. The  mass media technology, including computers, changes the setting of the city. You can't isolate groups -- groups that are suffering can be more quickly outspoken, and more quickly heard. It's not clear where that leads; everything is open-ended. It depends on what we do with it.</p>
        <p>The city will continue to be part of the nerve of America, a nerve that's easily irritated and can lead to nasty behavior, but it's an active nerve nonetheless.</p>
        <p>One of my more recent books, "The Protean Self: Human Resilience in a Time of Fragmentation," talks about the relatively more flexible many-sided self that each of us has much of, that we somehow make work. That's in opposition to the fundamentalist self, the sort of all or nothing self. New York has a lot of the  Protean, collectively and individually. It's there in the literature and art. And while many artists and writers have moved away, they still have a foot or a  hand or an easel or a computer in New York, I mean some form of connection with  New York.</p>
        <p>I hear it again and again, from friends from Europe, and friends from Japan.  They say they feel more alive in New York than everywhere else. Something is touched or awakened or threatened -- all of that -- by its very intensity.</p>
        <p>Judith Regan Head of Regan Books Publisher of Howard Stern's "Miss America"</p>
        <p>The publishing business is centered in New York, and it's not going to change anytime soon. All the talent is in New York. Book publishers and editors are going to act as readers for the film and television industry. We're the ones who will be doing the hard labor. Our own little world is coinciding with all these  other worlds.</p>
        <p>I think the publishing industry is going become more marketing-driven. Books  will be more celebrity-driven. But try to find people to write! Try to find people who can work in publishing houses. People graduating from college don't know anything. It's very shocking. They can't read, and they can't write. The level of writing has gone down and down.</p>
        <p>I think that this is going to change because our values are becoming more conservative, and instead of doing what feels good there's going to be restructuring of the education.</p>
        <p>Yes, the Internet will be a presence, but the Internet is the written word. You still have to sit there and read. The old news is the new news. What it comes down to is the story. It's whether you have a good story or you have important information to tell.</p>
        <p>Michael Musto Gossip columnist for The Village Voice</p>
        <p>I see no reason why gossip mania won't continue to grow, to the point where,  in 2010, it will not only have supplanted hard news, it will have obliterated it.</p>
        <p>The Post will have news only on Page 6, and gossip on every other page. And we will know more about celebrities than celebrities will know about themselves. Recently the meaning of the word celebrity has broadened to include somebody who crashed on the couch of someone who's tried for double murder. Celebrities can now be ordinary, or subordinary, people who fall into extraordinary circumstances. And that trend will continue.</p>
        <p>Deb Parker Co-manager of the Beauty Bar, on East 14th Street</p>
        <p>In 10 years, if I'm still in New York, New York might be the most pathetic city around. All the coolest people are moving away; all my friends are moving elsewhere, to smaller towns. So New York might get to be like a bunch of little  small towns, too. Nobody ever goes beyond a 20-block radius anyway.</p>
        <p>The city will probably be really expensive to live in, so the only people living here will have some scam, like a $200 apartment or great windfalls of money.</p>
        <p>In 10 years, it'll be a city of people who were something, has-beens, and people starting to come up. And I'll have 'em all in my bar. Some are going to be slumming, and some are going to come in to ask me questions. And I'll still be there, making money. I'll have the Donald Trumps and the coked-out strippers. That's what I like -- a mix. That's what New York is good for.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
