<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raspy but Democratic, Kazoos Corner Market; A Company in Eden, N.Y., Hums Along</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="588339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KAZOOS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EDEN (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">KAZOO CO INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERGHASH, DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF1F3CF935A35751C0A965958260" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raspy but Democratic, Kazoos Corner Market; A Company in Eden, N.Y., Hums Along</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDSEY GRUSON,</byline>
      <dateline>EDEN, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is said that a kazoo is to music what a full body cast is to ballet.</p>
        <p>But in this one-stoplight town, the rasp of the kazoo is a sweet serenade, the Magna Carta and Constitution of musical democracy.</p>
        <p>That's because Eden is the home of "The One and Only, Original Kazoo Company Inc.," the world's only remaining factory for metal kazoos -- the Stradivarius of kazoos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is said that a kazoo is to music what a full body cast is to ballet.</p>
        <p>But in this one-stoplight town, the rasp of the kazoo is a sweet serenade, the Magna Carta and Constitution of musical democracy.</p>
        <p>That's because Eden is the home of "The One and Only, Original Kazoo Company Inc.," the world's only remaining factory for metal kazoos -- the Stradivarius of kazoos.</p>
        <p>"It's the most democratic of all instruments," said David Berghash, the president of Brimms, a manufacturer of toys, health and beauty aids and the Kazoo Company's parent. "Without a doubt it's the most American of all instruments, because everyone can play."</p>
        <p>The kazoo, which a few years ago appeared to be going the way of the Hula Hoop, has made something of a comeback. Mr. Berghash said the company, which, with 11 workers, is one of the town's largest employers, annually ships 2 million to 3 million metal kazoos.  From Country to Classics</p>
        <p>"It's been around for 100 years and I think it's going to be around for another 100," Mr. Berghash said. "It's like plastic dinosaurs and Matchbox cars -- one of those steady toys that'll be around forever."</p>
        <p>Musicologists and music lovers, particularly parents, may dismiss kazoos as a child's toy or, more likely, akin to inviting the neighborhood menace into their home to spend a few hours running his fingernails down a blackboard. But kazoos had an important role in blues and jazz at the turn of the century and, horrifying as it may seem or sound, some still consider them serious instruments.</p>
        <p>Ringo Starr played the kazoo on the 1974 top-of-the-charts classic, "You're 16." The kazoo's distinctive buzz also added to musical interludes on recordings by the Lovin' Spoonful and Brooklyn Bridge. And country music, which has a traditional twang that seems well suited to kazoos, has produced notable kazooists such as Jimmie Rodgers and Gene Autry. Kazoophony in Concert</p>
        <p>The kazoo has yet to carve out much of a role in classical music. But Leonard Bernstein did use a kazoo in his concert celebrating the dedication of the Kennedy Center in Washington. The Kazoophony, an ensemble that is the current maestro of symphonic kazooing, has pushed Mr. Bernstein's musical envelope in performances with the Syracuse Symphony, the Tulsa Philharmonic and the San Antonio Symphony.</p>
        <p>Set up 20 years ago in the shadow of Rochester's Eastman School of Music, Kazoophony aims to make kazoo-playing recognized as an art form. The group started as the 80-piece Ludakravian Philharmonic, recalled Barbara Stewart, the group's founder, in her seminal work, "How to Kazoo: The Complete Method Book." But budget cuts soon reduced the orchestra to the six members of what they call "the world's largest quartet."</p>
        <p>"They are absolutely fantastic," said Mr. Berghash, a nonpracticing flutist who with his wife, a French horn player, makes up a two-person chamber orchestra. (But two young children have forced them to give up their home to Big Bird serenades.) "They really make nice music and I've heard a lot, a whole lot of kazooists -- people like myself, who sound like fingers screeching down a blackboard."</p>
        <p>The key to good kazoo-playing is, of course, the fundamental rule of all good musicianship: precise technique and practice, practice, practice -- far, far away from the neighbors. Mrs. Stewart also instructs her students to keep their lips soft and flexible, articulate clearly, produce vibrato in even pulses and hit perfect pitch. But anyone who can do all that is probably a pretty good vocalist. For them, the kazoo is a muzzle.</p>
        <p>Although overlooked by music stores -- which may explain why so many go bankrupt -- the kazoo is probably America's most popular instrument. There are an estimated 15,000 kazoo bands in the country. And even a couple of orchestras.</p>
        <p>"My generation loved kazoos, but the baby boom generation hardly knew what they were," said Shirley Keller, a machinist at the factory who usually keeps four kazoo rejects in her purse as emergency gifts for her friends and 14 grandchildren. "I'm hoping our new packaging and distribution will introduce a new generation to the fun of kazooing." 'A Great Get-Together'</p>
        <p>But children buy no more than half the kazoos sold, much to the surprise of the hundreds of visitors who annually tour the factory, three blocks south of the only stoplight in this village in western New York, about 20 miles south of Buffalo.</p>
        <p>Elderly kazooists are at least the second largest segment of the market, Mr. Berghash said. Shriners like kazoos. And kazoos are particularly popular in the South, especially Florida, Texas and Louisiana, as well as in Japan and Germany.</p>
        <p>"It's a great get-together," Mrs. Keller said in explaining the kazoo's appeal. "Instead of one person playing the piano while everyone else sleeps, they're all in it. They don't have to go to music school. They put it in their mouths and hum. And sure enough, they're playing an instrument. Before you know it, they're all laughing and singing along."</p>
        <p>But there are other reasons to buy a kazoo, if not to play it. In the Lettermanesque list of top 10 secondary uses for the kazoo, compiled by Mrs. Stewart, No. 10 is "to lead cavalry charges in military units without buglers," No. 2 is "to replace stolen hood ornaments on Rolls Royces," and No. 1, the top secondary use of a kazoo, is "to snuff out candles."</p>
        <p>Although the kazoo has become as American as apple pie, it has an African heritage. In her book, Mrs. Stewart notes that its forerunners were mirlitons -- instruments that disguise or modify vocal sounds through vibrating membranes -- used in ceremonies to impersonate the voices of the dead. They were supposed to make terrifying sounds and frighten friends and foes into submission. A Yuppie Kazoo, Too</p>
        <p>It's unclear exactly how they evolved into their well-known submarine shape. Legend has it that an American, Alabama Vest, invented the kazoo and that Thaddeus Von Clegg, a clockmaker, made it to his specifications. It supposedly was exhibited at the 1852 Georgia State Fair before being sold to a toy manufacturer who produced it as the "Down South Submarine."</p>
        <p>But at the Kazoo Company factory, kazoo history starts in 1916. That's when Emil Sorg, Michael McIntyre and Harry Richardson applied for a patent and began producing the classic "King Kazoos" in Mr. Richardson's sheet-metal workshop here. It was a sideline to their barbecue, furnace-parts, metal-dog-beds, fishing-tackle-boxes, peanut-vending-machine business.</p>
        <p>Mr. McIntyre eventually bought out his partners and, 100 million or so kazoos later, turned Eden from a rural paradise into what residents now proudly call "The Kazoo Capital of the World."</p>
        <p>The Kazoo factory has tried to make sure its product keeps up with the times. So it celebrated the end of Prohibition with liquor-bottle-shaped kazoos, and the Yuppies of the 80's got a gold-plated, 24-karat kazoo -- now $7.98 retail in the Kazoo Company's gift shop, versus $2.09 for a metal kazoo and $1.40 for a plastic kazoo.</p>
        <p>There were also Toot-a-Zoo kazoos, trumpet kazoos and French horn kazoos. But most variations dropped away to become pieces of Americana. The most popular, now as always, is the submarine-shaped kazoo.</p>
        <p>Various companies, including ones in Japan, have tried to break the Kazoo Company's monopoly on the metal kazoo. All have failed, crushed under the overhead of buying equipment to complete the 37 steps needed to manufacture a kazoo that looks like a trombone. The Kazoo Company survives only because it's ancient. Most of its machinery was working in 1901 when the shop was a sheet-metal factory and is still powered by 18 oversized belts driven by a rotor running down the center of the shop's ceiling.</p>
        <p>"It's a nice business," Mr. Berghash said. "If you can't come to work and smile, why come to work?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
