<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 43rd PRESIDENT: THE CHOICE -- Man in the News; A Stalwart of the Right -- John David Ashcroft</title>
    <meta content="124087SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1257537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">John David Ashcroft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DF153FF930A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 43rd PRESIDENT: THE CHOICE -- Man in the News; A Stalwart of the Right -- John David Ashcroft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his 1998 autobiography, John Ashcroft recalled how his minister father advised him that if he dressed ''for the job you want, not the job you have,'' shined his shoes every day and wore a ''sharp white shirt and tie, you can carry off virtually anything.''</p>
        <p>As President-elect George W. Bush's choice to be attorney general, Mr. Ashcroft may need his best spit shine and more to succeed as the government's chief legal officer, considering the painful experiences of many of his predecessors, who have left office battle-scarred, wearied, and often as not, with their reputations barely intact.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his 1998 autobiography, John Ashcroft recalled how his minister father advised him that if he dressed ''for the job you want, not the job you have,'' shined his shoes every day and wore a ''sharp white shirt and tie, you can carry off virtually anything.''</p>
        <p>As President-elect George W. Bush's choice to be attorney general, Mr. Ashcroft may need his best spit shine and more to succeed as the government's chief legal officer, considering the painful experiences of many of his predecessors, who have left office battle-scarred, wearied, and often as not, with their reputations barely intact.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Ashcroft is Mr. Bush's most conservative appointment so far and, if confirmed by the Senate, in what could be bruising confirmation hearings, he would be the most outspokenly ideological attorney general since President Ronald Reagan's era of social conservatism at the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>A pro-death-penalty, anti-abortion Republican senator from Missouri who lost a re-election campaign last month, Mr. Ashcroft's selection raises the possibility of potentially serious fights over the myriad flash points of legal policy, like judicial selection, civil rights, criminal justice and antitrust matters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ashcroft has served in the Senate since 1995 and briefly considered a run for the Republican presidential nomination in 2000, with backing from religious conservatives. Last year, he received an honorary degree from Bob Jones University, the South Carolina evangelical university that Democrats have denounced for policies like its ban on interracial dating. The university changed the policy this year to permit interracial dating by students who have parental permission.</p>
        <p>Before his election to the Senate, he served two terms as Missouri's governor from 1984 to 1992, after two terms as the state's attorney general. This year he lost his re-election effort to Gov. Mel Carnahan, whose name was on the ballot even though he had died a few weeks earlier in a plane crash.</p>
        <p>To his critics, Mr. Ashcroft is a zealous Republican hard-liner, a sometimes polarizing figure prone to self-righteous moralizing. Appearing at conservative gatherings, Mr. Ashcroft frequently spoke about his opposition to abortion and his position against, federal financing for clean needle exchange programs for addicts, the National Endowment for the Arts and some of President Clinton's judicial nominees, whom he branded as liberal activists.</p>
        <p>A deeply religious man with strong ties to the Christian Coalition, and conservative evangelical figures like Pat Robertson, Mr. Ashcroft was quoted in the Pentecostal Evangel magazine two years ago as saying, ''The spiritual well-being of America has been threatened more by judges out of control than by virtually any other governmental instrumentality.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ashcroft shares Mr. Bush's admiration for Justice Clarence Thomas of the Supreme Court. Mr. Ashcroft praised Justice Thomas in a recent article in the law review of Regent University, which is operated by the evangelist Pat Robertson.</p>
        <p>He said that Justice Thomas was a leader on the court and a powerful defender of respecting the limits of federal power. ''Too many judges believe they can legislate from the bench,'' Mr. Ashcroft complained. In contrast, he said that Justice Thomas subordinates his personal views to the Constitution.</p>
        <p>Ratings by advocacy groups suggest the sharp edge of Mr. Ashcroft's political thinking. The Christian Coalition gave Mr. Ashcroft a 100 percent rating for 2000 and he voted 100 percent of the time for the positions supported by the Eagle Forum, a conservative social policy group.</p>
        <p>But at the same time, both the National Organization for Women and the League of Conservation Voters, an environmental advocacy group, gave him zero ratings.</p>
        <p>Still, colleagues in both parties said that he is an ethical, fair-minded and highly intelligent lawmaker who graciously handled the awkward situation in Missouri this fall in which he was defeated by a dead man. Mr. Ashcroft has some friends in the Senate, including the majority leader Trent Lott, with whom he performed as a member of the Singing Senators.</p>
        <p>Jon Kyl, a Republican senator from Arizona and close friend who has worked closely with Mr. Ashcroft on the Judiciary Committee, said: ''He is a person of absolute integrity who really is the kind of person who can restore the dignity to the office that conservatives at least think was tarnished under Janet Reno.</p>
        <p>''John Ashcroft will be pulled and tugged by political forces but will have integrity to do what's right,'' Mr. Kyl said.</p>
        <p>Senator Robert G. Torricelli, Democrat of New Jersey, said that Mr. Bush had a right to choose someone with whom he is ideologically attuned. ''There aren't a lot of issues on which he and I agree,'' Mr. Torricelli said. ''But it is difficult to make an argument that he is not a person of great ability and integrity.''</p>
        <p>In his private and public life, faith has been a central focus for John David Ashcroft. Born May 9, 1942 in Chicago, he grew up in Springfield, Mo., where his family had moved to be nearer the world headquarters of the Assembly of God Church.</p>
        <p>His father was a minister in the church and a dominant influence on Mr. Ashcroft, as the senator explained in his book, ''Lessons From a Father to His Son,'' published by Thomas Nelson publishers, which distributes inspirational titles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ashcroft, who attended Hillcrest High School in Springfield, said he woke up every morning hearing ''the magisterial wake-up call'' of his father's prayers. ''Dad's prayers were not the quiet, whispered entreaties of a timid Sunday school teacher,'' Mr. Ashcroft wrote. ''My father prayed as if his family's life and vitality were even then being debated on high as he bowed low.''</p>
        <p>Today, civil liberties advocates reacted to Mr. Ashcroft's appointment with shock and dismay. Some liberal groups vowed to fight his confirmation and several Democratic senators said that they expected a spirited confirmation hearing, but that they believed he would be confirmed.</p>
        <p>One senior Democratic Senate staff member said that a former Senator like Mr. Ashcroft would be hard to defeat barring the emergence of a personal issue.</p>
        <p>The aide said that it was also likely that Bush aides had sounded out moderate Republicans before choosing Mr. Ashcroft and determined that they would vote for him. ''If they haven't done that and there's a possibility of moderate Republicans voting against him there's a chance he wouldn't succeed,'' the aide said. ''But if they've got the commitment of moderate Republicans it will be very difficult to block.''</p>
        <p>Patrick J. Leahy of Vermont, the senior Democrat on the Judiciary Committee, said he expected opposition to Mr. Ashcroft, in part because Republicans had for years tried to block some of President Clinton's nominees to Justice Department posts. ''The justice system has been badly damaged by politics and partisanship by Republicans the last six years,'' he said. ''But I've been urging, 'Don't try to engage in payback or revenge because ultimately the justice system suffers.' ''</p>
        <p>One issue that appears likely to provoke debate at Mr. Ashcroft's confirmation hearings is the role he played in 1999 when he successfully led the opposition to the nomination of Ronnie White, the first black justice on the Missouri Supreme Court, to a federal district court seat.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. White's nomination had been made two years earlier, Mr. Ashcroft suddenly assailed him as ''pro-criminal'' and the most anti-death penalty judge on the State Supreme Court. The record showed that as a judge, Mr. White had voted to affirm the death penalty in 41 of the 59 cases that came before him.</p>
        <p>Moreover, in 10 of the 18 cases in which he voted against imposing the death penalty, he was in the company of a unanimous court. The St. Louis Post-Dispatch reported that three of those named to the court by Mr. Ashcroft when he was governor voted to reverse the death penalty a greater percentage of the time than did Judge White.</p>
        <p>After the Senate voted to reject the White nomination on strict party lines by a vote of 54 to 45, Mr. Clinton denounced the action as ''a disgraceful act of partisan politics by the Republican majority and creates real doubt on the ability of the Senate to fairly perform its constitutional duty to advise and consent.''</p>
        <p>He said that what happened ''provides strong evidence for those who believe that the Senate treats minority and women judicial nominees unequally,'' a comment that angered many Republicans who said that race played no role in their vote.</p>
        <p>Conservative groups expressed delight in the choice of Mr. Ashcroft. Clint Bolick, vice president for litigation for the Institute for Justice, a conservative public interest law firm, said the Justice Department was likely to undergo a change.</p>
        <p>''I do think that projecting forward from today we will see very different types of case being filed by the Justice Department, particularly in the areas of voting rights, employment and education.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolick said there were several cases working their way toward the Supreme Court, among them appeals of circuit court decisions upholding affirmative action admissions programs at the University of Wisconsin and the University of Michigan.</p>
        <p>So far the Clinton administration had not taken an official legal position regarding those cases, but Mr. Bolick predicted that might change in the Bush administration. ''We've got a number of areas where the Justice Department will be called upon to weigh in on the issue of racial preferences in higher education,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Representatives of liberal advocacy groups expressed outrage over the selection and predicted a fight.</p>
        <p>Ralph G. Neas, president of People for the American Way, said the choice of Mr. Ashcroft was a mistake. ''John Ashcroft is the antithesis of the person required to lead the Department of Justice,'' he said. ''With the possible exception of Senator Jesse Helms, I do not believe anyone in the United States has a more abysmal record on civil rights and civil liberties.'' Mr. Neas helped lead the liberal coalition that defeated the Supreme Court nomination of Robert Bork.</p>
        <p>Kate Michelman, president of the National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League, said the appointment cast Mr. Bush in a new and harsher light.</p>
        <p>''It's terribly ominous,'' she said. ''He didn't just choose someone who is philosophically in line with him in opposing Roe v. Wade and freedom of choice. He chose someone who made the centerpiece of his public career taking away women's constitutional right.''</p>
        <p>Profile  John David Ashcroft</p>
        <p>Born: May 9, 1942, in Chicago  Hometown: Springfield, Mo.  Education: Hillcrest High School, Springfield; B.A., Yale University, 1964; J.D., University of Chicago, 1967.  Career Highlights: Private law practice in Springfield, 1967-73; professor, Southwest Missouri State University, 1968-73; Missouri auditor, 1973-75; Missouri assistant attorney general 1975-76; Missouri attorney general, 1977-84; Missouri governor 1985-92; lawyer with Suelthaus &amp; Kaplan, 1993-94; Missouri senator, 1995-present.  Family: Married to Janet Elise; two sons and one daughter.  Hobbies: Baseball fan, gospel singing and playing the piano.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
