<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Habitats/22nd Street Between Park Avenue South and Broadway; Her Duplex Arithmetic: 1+1+1+1 = 2,500 Sq. Ft.</title>
    <meta content="13HABI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/13/realestate/13HABI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1358784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Habitats"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ganot, Bonita</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Trish</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1DB1339F930A25752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1235" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Habitats/22nd Street Between Park Avenue South and Broadway; Her Duplex Arithmetic: 1+1+1+1 = 2,500 Sq. Ft.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">22nd Street Between Park Avenue South and Broadway</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRISH HALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hall, Trish</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>habitats/22nd streets between park avenue south and broadway: her duplex ar</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Bonita Ganot was growing up in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, in a small railroad flat with her parents and three siblings, she slept on a sofa in the living room, first with her older sister and then with her younger one.</p>
        <p>Her clothes filled two small drawers in her parents' bedroom. On cold days her mother turned on the stove to keep them warm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Combining four studios to create a wide-open space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Bonita Ganot was growing up in Williamsburg, Brooklyn, in a small railroad flat with her parents and three siblings, she slept on a sofa in the living room, first with her older sister and then with her younger one.</p>
        <p>Her clothes filled two small drawers in her parents' bedroom. On cold days her mother turned on the stove to keep them warm.</p>
        <p>The memory of a childhood she calls ''very, very poor'' has never left her. It gave her, she said, a desire for beauty that has grown only stronger as she has grown older.</p>
        <p>Now, after spending 18 years in Jamaica Estates, Queens, where she raised her three children in a typical Cape-style house, she is living in  Manhattan in a place that is her personal expression of that desire for beauty. After buying four nondescript studios several years ago, she merged them and designed her own space, creating a 2,500-square-foot duplex apartment, elegant and filled with light.</p>
        <p>Just finding four contiguous apartments, two on one floor and two directly above, was something of a miracle. ''It never happens,'' said Ms. Ganot, who recently finished decorating her space. She bought the four co-op apartments, on East 22nd Street between Park Avenue South and Broadway in a building constructed in the 1920's to house printing businesses, for about $1 million in January 1999.</p>
        <p>She spent the next six months working on the design and getting permission from her co-op to renovate, and then the rest of that year gutting and reconstructing the apartments.</p>
        <p>In December 1999, she moved in to the still-unfinished apartment with her three children, Ariana, Gabriel and Ethan. Although Ariana, 25, has since moved to Florida, the apartment has become a full-time home to Ethan, 22, who has graduated from Lehigh University and moved back to New York, where he is working for a major accounting firm in Midtown. Gabriel, 18, graduated from the Bronx High School of Science and is now a freshman at Lehigh.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ganot bought the apartment with her husband, Harvey Ganot, an executive at MTV, but they are no longer together. Ms. Ganot worked for a number of years as a school psychologist but is now looking for a different kind of job. Even before she started the renovation, she had been taking some courses in design at the New School, thinking she might go into that field.</p>
        <p>Still, the apartment was her first project, and a huge challenge. ''I gutted everything,'' she said. ''Even the windows are new.'' The hardest part of the design, she said, was the total freedom it offered. ''When you start from scratch,'' she said, ''you have nothing to match anything to.''</p>
        <p>She hired a contractor to coordinate the work but she found some of her own subcontractors, including the ones that did the kitchen and the windows.</p>
        <p>On the first level, she created a foyer with a floor of tumbled limestone, which continues uninterrupted into the adjacent bathroom and closets. All the space flows smoothly, without any saddles to mark the dividing points.</p>
        <p>The foyer opens into one large  room, with a kitchen across from nearly floor-to-ceiling windows that face south. She designed the open kitchen, with maple cabinets and granite counters, to suit her desire for openness.</p>
        <p>''You really have to think, how do you live,'' she said. ''I'm a person who wants to be with my people. I wanted everything to be open, so you can talk to everyone.'' In her house in Queens, she said, ''I had a living room, and no one ever sat in it.''</p>
        <p>Here, she often serves meals at the granite counter. Its hard, cool surface comes in handy for a number of things. ''I use it to make hamantaschen,'' the triangular pastries that symbolize Purim, she said -- and her younger son used it as a resting place after a particularly bad sunburn.</p>
        <p>In the living area, she has put just a few pieces of furniture, all modern and clean-lined. She brought almost nothing from her house in Queens -- just an upright piano, a table and a chair. The care put into the place is evident in many of the small touches, like the outlets in the floors that allow all the furniture to float in the middle of the space.</p>
        <p>For her, Ms. Ganot said, the most frustrating part of the project was the staircase, which is made of wood and steel. ''The banister was the hardest thing,'' she said, because it dominates one end of the room and getting the design right was difficult. The result pleases her, but it took a number of efforts to get there.</p>
        <p>Upstairs is a master-bedroom suite with a very large bathroom with floors and walls in a pale limestone, a glass enclosed shower, a tub and two sinks. It is reached by walking through a doorless closet. ''I hate doors,'' Ms. Ganot said, because they cut out the light. To let sunshine into the windowless bathroom, the door into the area has a glass transom.</p>
        <p>ALSO on the second floor is a room for her two sons, with a loft bed above for one and a futon below. Barely noticeable at the top are two doors leading to a large storage area, where she keeps some books and clothes her children used when they were young. Another room is set up with a sofa that pulls out into a bed, for her daughter or for friends often brought by her children. ''There's always someone sleeping there,'' she said, ''which I love. I feed anybody, anytime.''</p>
        <p>In the center of the upstairs is an open area furnished as a den, with a television set, stereo and family photos on the wall. There is a second bath too, for her children and guests, done in a dark slate.</p>
        <p>Pointing to the glass enclosure for a shower that reaches three-quarters of the way to the ceiling, Ms. Ganot remembered all the details that had to be decided during the construction. Eventually, she said, it was exhausting. ''Toward the end,'' she said, ''it was like, would somebody just decide for me.''</p>
        <p>Throughout the apartment, except for the bathrooms and foyer, the floors are birch, the only choice she regrets. ''I would never do it again,'' she said. ''It's too soft.'' And because of the softness, it shows every nick and scratch.</p>
        <p>Still, the apartment seems pristine, although Ms. Ganot and her two sons, both there during the recent holiday, say its openness and high ceilings make it perfect for everything they like to do.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ganot said she jumps rope in the living room; her son Ethan said  he can even practice his golf swing. And all three have been getting in some Frisbee playing, which did only minor damage; the clock on the kitchen wall was broken. On sunny days, Ms. Ganot sits on the low cabinet that runs under the window and provides not only a seat but storage.</p>
        <p>''I feel so completely lucky,'' she said. ''I can live with anything. But space is important, and beauty is important.''</p>
        <p>Habitats</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
