<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Recession Talk, Economists Shift to the Past Tense</title>
    <meta content="13PORT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/13/business/yourmoney/13PORT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1358917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PORTFOLIOS, ETC."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Portfolios Etc</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenspan, Alan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DD1F39F930A25752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Recession Talk, Economists Shift to the Past Tense</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Recession Talk, Economists Shift to the Past Tense</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Fuerbringer column on growing consensus among economists that recession has already ended, which suggests that sharp jump in long-term interest rates at end of 2001 was more reasonable than many analysts thought at time and that same may be true for surge in stock market; new forecasts are result of persistent strength in consumer spending and new strength in manufacturing; table (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST before the new year, James E. Glassman and his associates at J. P. Morgan made a big change in their economic outlook, updating their growth forecast for the first quarter to zero from a decline, at an annual rate, of 2 percent.</p>
        <p>A zero may not seem like much. But for economists, it means that the recession is not going to end in the spring, as they had predicted. It's over now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For economists, a growth forecast for the first quarter of zero means that the recession is not going to end in the spring, as they had predicted. It's over now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST before the new year, James E. Glassman and his associates at J. P. Morgan made a big change in their economic outlook, updating their growth forecast for the first quarter to zero from a decline, at an annual rate, of 2 percent.</p>
        <p>A zero may not seem like much. But for economists, it means that the recession is not going to end in the spring, as they had predicted. It's over now.</p>
        <p>Other forecasters have joined in. At Goldman, Sachs, the first-quarter forecast has shifted even more radically, from minus 1 percent to plus 2 percent. At Morgan Stanley, the shift was more modest, to plus 0.1 percent from minus 0.6 percent. But the effect would be the same: the recession would end this quarter.</p>
        <p>''When I see people changing their minds so quickly, it makes me think they were not prepared for the economy to be so resilient,'' said Mr. Glassman, senior United States economist at J. P. Morgan, including himself in his criticism. ''Economists need to be humble. We have always misjudged the turn.''</p>
        <p>The sudden speed-up means that Federal Reserve officials, meeting at the end of this month, may decide that there is no need to cut their benchmark short-term interest rate by another quarter-point, to 1.5 percent. Many analysts are still betting on another rate cut, but more positive news in the next few weeks could change that view.</p>
        <p>The shift in outlook also suggests that the sharp jump in long-term interest rates at the end of 2001 -- in anticipation of a nice recovery soon -- was more reasonable than many analysts thought at the time. The same may be true for the surge in the stock market, which, like the bond market, is supposed to be forward-looking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glassman also says the early end to  the recession may mean that the subsequent recovery will be stronger than the mild rebound that many economists have forecast. ''The fact that the bottom is coming early makes me feel better about the outlook,'' he said. So it is possible that long-term interest rates, already at relatively high levels, could move even higher.</p>
        <p>The new forecasts are a result of the persistent strength in consumer spending even as businesses reduced their orders sharply. ''Right now, the level of production is significantly below final demand,'' said Jan Hatzius, senior economist at Goldman, Sachs.</p>
        <p>A result is that product inventories fell sharply in the fourth quarter, a decline now estimated at $100 billion to $120 billion at an annual rate. (Fourth-quarter data on the  gross domestic product will not be released until Jan. 30.)</p>
        <p>Because of that steep drop, economists expect the inventory drain to slow greatly in the current quarter, maybe to around $40 billion. But in the calculation of G.D.P. numbers, this slowdown in the rate of decline becomes a positive.</p>
        <p>Also contributing to the changing outlook is new strength in manufacturing. The manufacturing index of the Institute of Supply Management rose to 48.2 in December --  still in recession territory but close to breaking through 50 into recovery. In addition, the index for new orders, considered a good predictor of future manufacturing activity, shot up to 54.9, its highest point in 20 months.</p>
        <p>An increase of 2.3 percent in chain-store sales in December showed that many retailers had a better Christmas than expected.</p>
        <p>''There is something you can hang your hat on if you want to claim that the economy is at an inflection point,'' said Louis Crandall, chief economist at Wrightson Associates, referring to an end of the recession.</p>
        <p>So what are Federal Reserve officials thinking, after all this new data? Several regional bank presidents said last week that the recovery would come later in the year. Alan Greenspan, chairman of the Federal Reserve, agreed with these comments in a speech on Friday. He warned that ''despite a number of encouraging signs of stabilization, it is still premature to conclude that the forces restraining economic activity here and abroad have abated enough to allow a steady recovery to take hold.''</p>
        <p>Private economists must react quickly to new data. (Ahead of his colleagues, Ian Shepherdson of High Frequency Economics predicted in October that there would be recovery signs before the end of the year.)</p>
        <p>Fed officials must be more cautious. Still, one wonders if they are just trying too hard to talk down stubbornly high long-term interest rates while locking themselves into one more rate cut on Jan. 30. If they continue with this cautious view, a decision not to cut rates will be a big surprise.</p>
        <p>PORTFOLIOS, ETC.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
