<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Pain, Cone Gets Game 1 Nod</title>
    <meta content="29BOMB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="961289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cone, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E4DD123AF93AA1575AC0A961958260" item-length="520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Pain, Cone Gets Game 1 Nod</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees say pitcher David Cone will start first game of playoff series against Cleveland Indians (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Cone is not at 100 percent strength, he is not sure whether he will be able to control a wayward fastball and Manager Joe Torre considers him a five-inning pitcher. But the pain in Cone's right shoulder is not totally throttling him, so he will pitch Game 1 of the division playoffs Tuesday against the Cleveland Indians.</p>
        <p>''You'll get it officially tomorrow,'' Torre said today. ''He's always wanted to pitch. He could be on his death bed. He feels good. Yesterday was not a mirage.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Cone is not at 100 percent strength, he is not sure whether he will be able to control a wayward fastball and Manager Joe Torre considers him a five-inning pitcher. But the pain in Cone's right shoulder is not totally throttling him, so he will pitch Game 1 of the division playoffs Tuesday against the Cleveland Indians.</p>
        <p>''You'll get it officially tomorrow,'' Torre said today. ''He's always wanted to pitch. He could be on his death bed. He feels good. Yesterday was not a mirage.''</p>
        <p>After testing his arm for seven minutes on Saturday, Cone will lob a ball at a Yankee Stadium workout Monday afternoon and try not to think about the limitations that he must tolerate because of tendinitis.</p>
        <p>''I'm worried about doing the best I can with what I have and going as long as I can,'' Cone said. ''I feel like I'm good enough. I think I've made it over the hump.''</p>
        <p>The 34-year-old Cone is confident he can pitch twice if the series stretches to five games and he is also looking for a boost from the post-season excitement.</p>
        <p>''I'm hoping the extra energy or extra adrenaline you get during a game will help,'' Cone said. ''It's a variable that's tough to quantify. I hope it's going to be there.''</p>
        <p>Too Late for Irabu?</p>
        <p>At least Hideki Irabu made it interesting. Irabu made perhaps his most dependable start since a victory in his July 10 major league debut against the Tigers by striking out six and allowing one run and two hits today in a 7-2 victory over Detroit. But the effort was probably too late to earn him the 10th and final spot on the post-season pitching staff ahead of Graeme Lloyd.</p>
        <p>''It's something I have no control over,'' Irabu said. ''I'll wait and see.''</p>
        <p>Torre avoided questions about Irabu's future, but said: ''He was terrific. He had a good splitter and good velocity on his fastball. This should have a nice effect on him since he had a little bit of a rocky start.''</p>
        <p>Was Torre providing Irabu's epitaph for the season? Probably. Torre has said he wants two left-handers in the bullpen, so the final spot is probably a choice between Lloyd and Kenny Rogers. Lloyd, who had a stiff left elbow last week, pitched a scoreless inning in three of the team's last five games to make himself the leading candidate. Rogers, who would become a $20 million cheerleader if he is left off the roster, worked a shutout inning today.</p>
        <p>''I'm ready to go,'' Lloyd said.</p>
        <p>Irabu, who signed a $12.8 million contract after pitching in Japan, finished the season with a 5-4 record and a 7.09 earned run average. But he was 2-0 with a 1.98 e.r.a. and 19 strikeouts in 13 2/3 innings against Detroit.</p>
        <p>''It was only half a season, but the Yankees brought me up to the big leagues and there were so many experiences I went through,'' Irabu said. ''It was a learning process, a learning year and I have learned a lot.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
