<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Menopause Begins Silently, Before Its Symptoms</title>
    <meta content="27MENO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="990822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Menopause</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Personal Health (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Menopause</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Menopause</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DF113BF934A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="1148" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Menopause Begins Silently, Before Its Symptoms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane E Brody Personal Health column on gaining a better understanding of perimenopause, years leading up to near-shutdown of ovarian function; emphasizes that menopause is a process, not discrete event; notes there is gradual decline in hormone production over about 15 years, a decline that can produce sometimes mystifying symptoms and set stage for serious health problems later on; says that a better understanding of perimenopause and its common symptoms and ways to cope with them can make tremendous difference in quality of women's lives and their future health; drawing; table gives menopause timetable, showing typical ages for various symptoms (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I WAS in my mid-40's and still menstruating regularly when my gynecologist suggested that I start taking estrogen. But I thought he was jumping the gun since I would probably not enter menopause for five more years.</p>
        <p>Now that I have a better understanding of the perimenopause, the years leading up to a near-shutdown of ovarian function, I can see his point, albeit belatedly. Menopause is a process, not a discrete event. Ovaries do not stop working abruptly unless they are shut down by chemotherapy or surgical removal. Rather, there is a gradual decline in hormone production over about 15 years, a decline that can produce sometimes mystifying symptoms and set the stage for serious health problems later on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I WAS in my mid-40's and still menstruating regularly when my gynecologist suggested that I start taking estrogen. But I thought he was jumping the gun since I would probably not enter menopause for five more years.</p>
        <p>Now that I have a better understanding of the perimenopause, the years leading up to a near-shutdown of ovarian function, I can see his point, albeit belatedly. Menopause is a process, not a discrete event. Ovaries do not stop working abruptly unless they are shut down by chemotherapy or surgical removal. Rather, there is a gradual decline in hormone production over about 15 years, a decline that can produce sometimes mystifying symptoms and set the stage for serious health problems later on.</p>
        <p>Millions of American women, those between the ages of 35 and the early 50's, are now in their perimenopause, and a better understanding of its common symptoms and ways to cope with them can make a tremendous difference in the quality of these women's lives and their future health.</p>
        <p>Signs of Perimenopause</p>
        <p>Estrogen production usually starts declining gradually when a woman is in her mid-30's; by the mid-40's, she may begin to experience clear symptoms of estrogen deficiency. Her menstrual periods may become somewhat irregular -- shorter or longer, lighter or heavier -- or she may experience premenstrual syndrome, menstrual cramps or headaches that are showing up for the first time or worse than in the past. Hot flashes may become bothersome during the day, and night sweats may disrupt her sleep, resulting in increased irritability, fatigue and difficulty concentrating.</p>
        <p>But the symptoms of perimenopause are often more subtle. According to Dr. Nancy Lee Teaff and Kim Wright Wiley, authors of ''Perimenopause: Preparing for the Change'' (Prima, Rocklin, Calif., 1996, $12.05), ''When they first begin to appear, perimenopausal symptoms may seem unrelated to each other, and women often treat each problem individually, not seeing the connection until years later.'' Among the possible symptoms are insomnia, difficulty concentrating, poor memory, reduced stamina, itchy or dry skin, wrinkling, urinary incontinence or frequency, vaginal dryness, headaches, declining libido and mood swings.</p>
        <p>''A woman may say, 'I'm falling apart,' failing to recognize that she has only one condition, perimenopause, that is manifesting itself in many ways,'' Dr. Teaff and Ms. Wiley wrote.</p>
        <p>At the same time, other hidden changes may be taking place that can increase a woman's risk of future health problems. High levels of estrogen during a woman's childbearing years protect against heart disease, which is why women rarely develop it before they turn 50. Estrogen helps raise the blood levels of the ''good'' cholesterol, HDL, which counters arterial clogging. It also maintains the elasticity of blood vessels and diminishes the tendency of the blood to form clots.</p>
        <p>In the book ''Perimenopause: Changes in a Woman's Health After 35'' (New Harbinger, 1997, $13.95), Drs. James E. Huston and L. Darlene Lanka point out that heart disease is the leading killer of women 50 to 75 years old, claiming five times as many lives as breast cancer.</p>
        <p>Estrogen also helps maintain bone density and ward off the later development of osteoporosis. Few women realize that they begin to lose bone in their 30's; the loss merely accelerates at menopause if estrogen is not taken along with an adequate amount of calcium through food or supplements.</p>
        <p>''During the approximately 15 years of perimenopause, you have a good shot at averting the adverse changes these two conditions can wreak on your body later in life,'' Drs. Huston and Lanka said.</p>
        <p>What You Can Do</p>
        <p>Dr. Teaff recommends that perimenopausal women who are experiencing symptoms have their estrogen level tested during the second, third or fourth days of the menstrual cycle. If symptoms include changes in menstrual patterns or hot flashes, another test, for FSH (follicle-stimulating hormone, produced by the pituitary), should be done on blood drawn during the first six days of the menstrual cycle and repeated the next month.</p>
        <p>It would also be a good idea at this time to have a base-line bone density test, as well as a test for total cholesterol and its various fractions. In fact, while you are at it, the perimenopause is a good time to undergo a complete physical, including a mammogram and electrocardiogram. The results may prompt you to take a greater interest in your future well-being. That entails paying more attention to your diet and exercise habits.</p>
        <p>As ovarian function slowly declines, muscle mass may begin to wane, accompanied by a rise in body fat and a gradual thickening around the waist and abdomen. You can minimize these changes by adhering to a diet low in fat and rich in vegetables, fruit and whole grain foods,  along with moderate amounts of lean protein. Do not forget low-fat and nonfat dairy products; they are your best sources of calcium. A quart of skim milk or its equivalent can supply a perimenopausal woman's daily calcium requirement.</p>
        <p>Regular exercise, including aerobic, muscle-building and flexibility-enhancing activities, are vital to countering the physical and emotional effects of declining levels of estrogen. That holds true even if you take hormone replacement, which is not nearly so effective in protecting the health of a sedentary woman as it is in a woman who remains physically active through menopause and beyond.</p>
        <p>Then there is hormone replacement, which a growing number of gynecologists believe should begin years before a woman ceases to have regular menstrual periods. The most common, estrogen and progestin in a pill, is not the only regimen. If you are troubled by a loss of sexual desire, a testosterone supplement may restore your libido (testosterone is the libido hormone for both men and women). If vaginal or urinary problems are your only symptoms, estrogen cream inserted daily into the vagina may do the trick, although the amount of estrogen that would reach the bloodstream is not adequate to protect your heart and bones.</p>
        <p>You can increase your body's overall estrogen supply naturally by eating flaxseed (two or three tablespoons a day) and more soy-based foods, including tofu, soy milk, soybeans and soy nuts. Consult ''Estrogen: The Natural Way'' by Nina Shandler (Villard, 1997, $24.95) for amounts and recipes using foods rich in plant estrogens. But eating large amounts of estrogen-rich foods exposes you to unopposed estrogen, which, without the balancing effects of progestin, may result in overstimulation of the uterine lining and heavier menstrual bleeding. When hormone replacement is given in pill form to a woman who still has a uterus, estrogen is combined with a progestin to diminish the risk of uterine overstimulation and prevent uterine cancer. Even if you are still menstruating regularly, hormone replacement can help to reduce perimenopausal symptoms.  PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
