<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Appellate Ruling May Return Woman to Jail in a Murder Case</title>
    <meta content="27SLAY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="990786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Lisa Michelle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dalzell, Stewart (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Jan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2D8103BF934A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Appellate Ruling May Return Woman to Jail in a Murder Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Jan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lisa Michell Lambert, who was declared innocent of first-degree murder by Philadelphia Federal Judge, Stewart Dalzell, is step closer to being returned to prison after split decision by appellate court, which turned down petition by defense lawyers to rehear appeal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a split decision by an appellate court, a woman who had been declared innocent of first-degree murder last spring by a Philadelphia Federal judge came one step closer yesterday to being returned to prison.</p>
        <p>The woman, Lisa Michelle Lambert, had been freed last April by the Federal judge, Stewart Dalzell, after a 14-day hearing in which he had found that the state trial in 1992 in which she was charged with the murder of a Lancaster County teen-ager had been corrupted by perjury, witness tampering, fabrication of evidence and the withholding of key information. His ruling, which barred state prosecutors from retrying Ms. Lambert, was seen by some legal experts as exemplifying the power of the Federal court as a bulwark against a runaway state prosecution, and by others as an abuse of that power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a split decision by an appellate court, a woman who had been declared innocent of first-degree murder last spring by a Philadelphia Federal judge came one step closer yesterday to being returned to prison.</p>
        <p>The woman, Lisa Michelle Lambert, had been freed last April by the Federal judge, Stewart Dalzell, after a 14-day hearing in which he had found that the state trial in 1992 in which she was charged with the murder of a Lancaster County teen-ager had been corrupted by perjury, witness tampering, fabrication of evidence and the withholding of key information. His ruling, which barred state prosecutors from retrying Ms. Lambert, was seen by some legal experts as exemplifying the power of the Federal court as a bulwark against a runaway state prosecution, and by others as an abuse of that power.</p>
        <p>Judge Dalzell found that Ms. Lambert, a battered woman, was ''actually innocent'' of the murder of Laurie Show, for which she had been serving a life sentence. The killer, he wrote, had probably been Ms. Lambert's former boyfriend, who testified against her in exchange for leniency.</p>
        <p>On Dec. 29, a three-judge panel for the United States Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit ruled against Ms. Lambert, now 25, saying only that she had failed to exhaust remedies available in the state system before turning to the Federal court with a petition of habeas corpus.</p>
        <p>Lancaster County prosecutors agreed to let her remain free, pending the decision yesterday, in which the court voted whether to rehear Ms. Lambert's appeal. A majority was needed. Eight judges, who did not issue a written opinion, voted against the rehearing and four voted in favor.</p>
        <p>Writing for the dissenters, Judge Jane R. Roth said that she had read substantial portions of the 3,300-page transcript of the Federal hearing. ''I am aware of the evidence of prosecutorial misconduct that occurred during Lambert's original trial,'' she wrote. ''I find it to be truly shocking.'' Chastising the three-judge panel for not considering the facts unearthed in Judge Dalzell's hearing, she added, ''I find it impossible to conclude that a habeas petitioner, who has proven by clear and convincing evidence that she has suffered a miscarriage of justice, must return to a prison cell to start her petitions all over again.''</p>
        <p>The decision yesterday means that within seven days Judge Dalzell must formally deny Ms. Lambert permission for the hearing that has already taken place. She would then return to prison and restart her appeals in the state system.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for the prosecutors, Edward R. Kennett, said the state would now press to have Ms. Lambert returned to prison.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lambert has a handful of recourses in the Federal system and an emergency appeal available in the state system. Her lawyers can apply to the Supreme Court, on the theory that the case fits a category of ''exceptional circumstances.'' She  has a motion before the Third Circuit asking that she remain free until all her appeals are finished.</p>
        <p>Her lawyer, Peter S. Greenberg, said that Ms. Lambert has vowed to commit suicide ''before she'll go back to prison for a day, and an expert who examined her said it was a serious risk and to be expected for someone who had been abused in prison.''</p>
        <p>While she was incarcerated, a Pennsylvania prison guard was convicted of repeatedly raping Ms. Lambert, and she had been transferred to a New Jersey state prison.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
