<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AIDS Is Now the Leading Killer of Americans From 25 to 44</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="740674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACQUIRED IMMUNE DEFICIENCY SYNDROME (AIDS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGE, CHRONOLOGICAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATISTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PNEUMONCYSTIS CARINII PNEUMONIA (PCP)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CENTERS FOR DISEASE CONTROL AND PREVENTION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CENTERS FOR DISEASE CONTROL AND PREVENTION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALTMAN, LAWRENCE K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pneumonia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DF1E3CF932A05752C0A963958260" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AIDS Is Now the Leading Killer of Americans From 25 to 44</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ALTMAN, LAWRENCE K</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AIDS has become the leading cause of death among all Americans aged 25 to 44, new Federal data show. The data were reported for the first time at a scientific meeting here today.</p>
        <p>AIDS surpassed unintentional injury, the Government's category for accidents, which dropped to second place in this age group, said Dr. Harold W. Jaffe, a top AIDS official at the Federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta.  Cancer and heart disease were third and fourth, followed by homicides and suicides.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AIDS has become the leading cause of death among all Americans aged 25 to 44, new Federal data show. The data were reported for the first time at a scientific meeting here today.</p>
        <p>AIDS surpassed unintentional injury, the Government's category for accidents, which dropped to second place in this age group, said Dr. Harold W. Jaffe, a top AIDS official at the Federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta.  Cancer and heart disease were third and fourth, followed by homicides and suicides.</p>
        <p>"AIDS was expected to rise to the top of the list eventually, but no one had predicted which year," Dr. Jaffe said in an interview at a meeting on human retroviruses and related infections.</p>
        <p>The AIDS curve for deaths among Americans from 25 to 44 has risen steadily and steeply since the disease was first recognized in 1981. "The dramatic rise is due to the accumulating toll from AIDS and is almost certain to continue because AIDS deaths reflect infections from H.I.V., the AIDS virus, that were acquired several years earlier," Dr. Jaffe said.</p>
        <p>The tabulations were based on preliminary analysis of data for 1993, the latest year available, Dr. Jaffe said.</p>
        <p>AIDS became the leading cause of death among men from 25 to 44 in 1992. It remains fourth among women, behind cancer, unintentional injuries and heart disease, but is expected to replace heart disease and to rise to second place for women in the next few years, Dr. Jaffe said. It surpassed homicide and suicide among women in 1992.</p>
        <p>More than 440,000 cases of AIDS, including more than 6,000 among children, have been reported to the centers since the epidemic was first recognized. More than 250,000 people have died from AIDS or AIDS-related causes. About 75 percent of cases have been reported in the 25-to-44 age group.</p>
        <p>AIDS is also the leading cause of death in men and women in 79 of 169 American cities with populations greater than 100,000 population. For women, AIDS is now the leading cause of death in 15 of the 135 largest cities. They are Hartford, New Haven and Bridgeport, Conn., Worcester, Mass., Providence, R.I., New York City, Yonkers, Elizabeth, N.J., Jersey City, Newark, Paterson, N.J., Baltimore, Columbia, S.C., Fort Lauderdale, Fla., and Miami.</p>
        <p>In 1992, heterosexual transmission became the leading route of transmission of H.I.V. in women. Dr. Jaffe said, "The one clear take-home message in all areas is the increasing importance of the heterosexual AIDS epidemic in this country."</p>
        <p>In the northeastern United States, where the rate of infection is higher among intravenous drug users than it is among gay men, the incidence of AIDS continues to rise.</p>
        <p>Although the AIDS epidemic seems to have stabilized among gay men in some areas of the country, there is evidence of a future second wave in that group, Dr. Jaffe said. He cited recent studies in San Francisco, Denver and Chicago showing an incidence of 2 to 3 percent a year for new infections in gay men, a high number.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jaffe also said that Federal health officials were revising guidelines for the treatment of AIDS in children. A very large percentage of H.I.V.-infected infants are not initially tested for the virus, nor are they given preventive treatment for P.C.P., a common complication of the disease.</p>
        <p>P.C.P., or pneumocystis carinii pneumonia, is the leading opportunistic infection in H.I.V.-infected children and adults and a major cause of death from AIDS.</p>
        <p>A study conducted by Dr. Robert J. Simonds of the Federal centers showed that the risk of P.C.P. was highest in young infants, with more than half of such cases occurring in children 3 to 6 months old.</p>
        <p>Guidelines published in 1991 and aimed at reducing the incidence of P.C.P. in children infected with the virus called for identifying infants born to infected mothers as soon as possible. The guidelines then called for measuring the children's counts of CD-4 immune cells, and administering preventive drug therapy for those with low numbers of the cells.</p>
        <p>The study found little change in the estimated P.C.P. incidence during the first year of life. Only 16 percent were taking prophylaxis at the time of the diagnosis of the first P.C.P. attack and 76 percent had never taken such therapy. About two-thirds had not been evaluated for H.I.V. infection before the diagnosis of P.C.P. and of those who were evaluated two-thirds had no records of a CD-4 cell count.</p>
        <p>The study also found that CD-4 cell counts in infants might drop sharply in the few months before the diagnosis of P.C.P. so that infrequent monitoring of CD-4 counts might fail to detect infants in need of preventive drug therapy.</p>
        <p>The new guidelines will stress the need to diagnose H.I.V. infection during pregnancy and to start all infants born to infected mothers on prophylactic therapy between 4 and 6 weeks of age, regardless of CD-4 counts. Prophylaxis would be stopped if a child is found not to be infected. Beyond the age of 1, infected children would receive prophylaxis based on laboratory and clinical information.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
