<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Airlines Test Tighter Rules On Baggage</title>
    <meta content="Y28BAG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="976260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Luggage</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Northwest Airlines</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdowell, Edwin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Luggage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB123AF93BA15752C1A961958260" item-length="1315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Airlines Test Tighter Rules On Baggage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWIN McDOWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcdowell, Edwin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Airlines, after years of complaints, are moving to clear out their increasingly crowded baggage areas in airplane cabins, by limiting amount of bags and baggage passengers can bring on board with them; they are likely to face new round of complaints, from infrequent leisure travelers, since most business travelers apparently will be exempt from baggage restrictions; Northwest Airlines is already limiting many passengers to one carry-on bag on its routes, and United Airlines unit of UAL Corp will try out similar restrictions; jammed overhead bins in airplane cabins have long been an irritant to full-fare business passenger--airlines' most valued customer, who typically pay three to four times the fare of leisure passenger on same flight, and who together account for as much as 60 percent of an airline's revenue (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After years of complaints, the airlines are moving to clear out their increasingly crowded baggage rooms in the sky, by limiting the amount of bags and baggage passengers can bring on board with them.  But they are likely to face a new round of complaints, from infrequent leisure travelers, since most business travelers apparently will be exempt from the baggage restrictions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After years of complaints, the airlines are moving to clear out their increasingly crowded baggage rooms in the sky, by limiting the amount of bags and baggage passengers can bring on board with them.  But they are likely to face a new round of complaints, from infrequent leisure travelers, since most business travelers apparently will be exempt from the baggage restrictions.</p>
        <p>Northwest Airlines is already limiting many passengers to one carry-on bag on its routes, and the United Airlines unit of the UAL Corporation will try out similar restrictions on some routes on Monday.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the rest of the industry is keeping close watch. So are airlines from Singapore to Switzerland: carriers that fly  international routes are doubly bedeviled by carry-on woes, because of the duty-free purchases that are jammed into overhead bins or wind up in passengers' laps.</p>
        <p>''My guess is that if Northwest's policy doesn't create too much opposition, all the carriers will go that route,'' said Lynn Hayes, chairman of the Association of Retail Travel Agents, whose observation is seconded by many other travel industry and airline officials.</p>
        <p>Although safety considerations also underlie the move to tighten restrictions on carry-on baggage, the main reason the airline industry is acting now is economic.</p>
        <p>After losing $13 billion from 1990 to 1994, the industry is finally flush, with planes often nearly full and business fares at record levels. So now airlines are betting they can risk angering some of their lower-paying customers by tightening their carry-on regulations, with little fear of losing business.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the jammed overhead bins in airplane cabins have long been an irritant to the full-fare business traveler -- the airlines' most valued customer, who typically pays three to four times the fare of a leisure passenger on the same flight, and who together account for as much as 60 percent of an airline's revenue.</p>
        <p>In addition, the airlines have become more aggressive in dealing with delayed departures, which cost them millions of dollars a year. One source of those delays has been passengers jostling to find space for their carry-on items. For more than a decade, pilots and flight attendants have called, to little avail, for new restrictions limiting carry-on luggage to one item, saying that excess baggage posed a safety hazard to passengers and crew and disrupted on-time performance.</p>
        <p>But if carry-on luggage has long been a  problem, by almost all accounts it is much worse today. Record passenger loads, smaller aircraft and the airlines' willingness for most of this decade to turn a blind eye to their own limits on carry-on luggage have created conditions that passengers as well as flight crews decry as intolerable.</p>
        <p>Adding to the overcrowding are the increasing number of seats put into coach class by most airlines, often so that they can expand their first-class and business-class cabins. The Consumer Reports Travel Letter recently noted that airlines stuff six seats into rows on single-aisle Boeing planes that are wide enough for only five passengers. Even on widebodies, including L-1011's, DC-10's or MD-11's, a few carriers put 10 seats into rows designed for 9. And more rows of seats have been added as well, cutting into legroom and the storage space beneath the seats. In the meantime, the number of available overbins has generally remained the same, or has even been reduced. As a result, on almost any given plane more passengers than before are competing for the increasingly scarce carry-on baggage space.</p>
        <p>The airlines, of course, are not indifferent to safety problems posed by jam-packed overhead bins -- not when more than 4,000 airline passengers were injured last year by items that fell from those bins, the Association of Flight Attendants estimates.  But the broader financial considerations have given the airlines all the more reason to crack down on carry-on baggage now.</p>
        <p>Thus, Northwest Airlines began last Friday to limit almost all passengers in economy class to one carry-on bag plus either a briefcase, a laptop computer or purse. The only exceptions, the airline said, are for its most frequent fliers, plus passengers in first class and business class. And beginning Monday, on flights to and from Des Moines, United Airlines will limit passengers who pay the lowest fare to one carry-on bag a flight, instead of the usual two.</p>
        <p>Travel agents say few leisure passengers even know about the baggage limitations yet, but might not be happy when they find out. The main reason passengers carry luggage aboard, agents say, is to prevent it from disappearing into the luggage equivalent of a black hole. Last year, almost 2.5 million complaints of lost or misplaced baggage aboard airlines were reported to the Transportation Department, or 5.3 for every 1,000 passengers, compared with almost 2.2 million in 1991, or 5.38 per 1,000 passengers.</p>
        <p>Lost or misplaced baggage affects business and leisure travelers alike, but business travelers have complained that they have been forced to have carry-on items stored in the belly of the plane. ''A lot of times by the time they get to their seats, there's no room in the overhead bins,'' said Norman Sherlock, the executive director of the National Business Travel Association. ''So our members will applaud the airlines for cracking down on people bringing on lots of items.''</p>
        <p>United said its experiment was motivated by precisely that complaint from full-fare passengers in economy class. Similarly, Michael E. Levine, a Northwest executive vice president, noted that having to take luggage back out of the cabin, tag it and hand-carry it down to the tarmac for loading into the cargo holds, creates delays. The airlines are trying hard to avoid unnecessary delays, largely to avoid inconveniencing and alienating business travelers.</p>
        <p>But not everyone thinks full-fare travelers are above reproach. ''I find that businessmen also abuse the limits on carry-on luggage,'' said Carol A. Poppel, the owner of the Travel Wise agency in Clark, N.J. ''In fact, I've actually demanded that stewardesses remove businessmen's large bags from the overhead racks, and they've done it.''</p>
        <p>American Airlines, part of the AMR Corporation, while continuing to allow two carry-on items, nevertheless recently joined with its pilots and flight attendants in asking the Federal Aviation Administration to impose a two-bag carry-on limit for United States carriers, arguing that a uniform standard would eliminate competition among airlines.</p>
        <p>''One problem has been that the majority of our competitors don't monitor the size or amount of carry-on baggage very closely,'' said Tim Smith, an American spokesman. A few months ago, he said, an American employee flew four flights on a rival carrier, with three carry-on bags, ''and he was never once challenged.''</p>
        <p>In 1988 airlines were allowed to develop and enforce their own carry-on policies, subject to agency approval. But at a recent conference in Washington of the Association of Flight Attendants, spokesmen for the F.A.A. said that the agency did not want to become involved in regulating behavior. If it does not, airline officials say, they will impose and enforce their own regulations, as have Northwest or United -- depending, of course, on public reaction to those experiments.</p>
        <p>Jill Gallagher, a spokeswoman for the flight attendants' union, which represents more than 40,000 employees on 27 carriers, is not convinced  that the F.A.A. has concerns about regulating behavior. ''The F.A.A. regulates behavior by banning smoking on airplanes,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her association favors an industrywide carry-on standard based on total volume, determined by placing every carry-on item in a container similar to the measuring frames, or ''sizers,'' widely available (but too seldom used, in the opinion of critics) to measure carry-on items at check-in counters and gates.</p>
        <p>''But we don't want the sizers at the gate,'' Ms. Gallagher said. ''We want them placed before the gate, when the stress level isn't as high if a passenger is told he's carrying on too much.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
