<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pilots Dead, Many Missing In Fiery Los Angeles Crash</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="419848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOS ANGELES INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOEING 737 AIRPLANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PILOTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">USAIR INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SKYWEST AIRLINES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pilots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DA1E3BF930A35751C0A967958260" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pilots Dead, Many Missing In Fiery Los Angeles Crash</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Feb. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rescue workers at Los Angeles International Airport searched today for bodies in the charred wreckage of a USAir passenger jet and a small commuter plane as Federal investigators began their effort to determine why a seemingly normal landing by the jet turned into a fiery runway crash with the smaller craft Friday night.</p>
        <p>The investigation was expected to be hampered by the fact that the dead included both pilots of the commuter plane and the captain of the USAir jet, a Boeing 737, which witnesses said slammed into the smaller plane as it set down on the runway under clear skies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rescue workers at Los Angeles International Airport searched today for bodies in the charred wreckage of a USAir passenger jet and a small commuter plane as Federal investigators began their effort to determine why a seemingly normal landing by the jet turned into a fiery runway crash with the smaller craft Friday night.</p>
        <p>The investigation was expected to be hampered by the fact that the dead included both pilots of the commuter plane and the captain of the USAir jet, a Boeing 737, which witnesses said slammed into the smaller plane as it set down on the runway under clear skies.</p>
        <p>Officials USAir and the commuter airline, SkyWest, said at least 18 people were dead.  Edwin I. Colodny, chairman of USAir, said the captain and five other people aboard the jet were killed.  Ron Reber, a SkyWest spokesman, said all 10 passengers and both pilots of the twin-engine propeller plane, a Fairchild Metro III, had died. "We've given up hope," Mr. Reber said.</p>
        <p>Of the 83 passengers and 6 crew members aboard USAir Flight 1493, on the way from Columbus, Ohio, to Los Angeles, 19 were still unaccounted for this afternoon, said airline officials. The airline identified the captain as Colin Shaw, 48 years old, who was based in Washington and had 16,300 hours of flight experience, including 1,300 hours on a 737.  Co-Pilot in Intensive Care</p>
        <p>USAir said that 23 of those aboard had been hospitalized with injuries ranging from critical to minor; 13 were released today. The airline said 41 people walked away from the crash without requiring hospitalization.</p>
        <p>The injured included the co-pilot, David Kelly, 32, who has logged more than 9,000 flight hours, about 1,000 on a 737. He was in intensive care at a local hospital with respiratory burns.</p>
        <p>Investigators from the National Transportation Safety Board refused to speculate on the cause of the accident. But the inquiry was expected to focus on why the commuter plane was on an active runway at the time and whether, as one airport worker suggested last night, the pilots had mistaken it for a taxiway that parallels the runway. The weather and visibility were good.</p>
        <p>The USAir flight originated in Syracuse, with stops in Washington and Columbus, Ohio. The crash occurred at 6:04 P.M. as it touched down on Runway 24-Left. It struck the smaller plane, SkyWest Flight 5569, which was taxiing to take off , nearly obliterating the 19-seat craft and veering into a vacated fire station not far from the international terminal. The Skywest plane originated in Palm Springs and was headed for Palmdale, a Los Angeles suburb.</p>
        <p>Survivors from the USAir jet said there was no warning of trouble. "We had a good landing; we were braking the engine," said Gary Dunham of Los Angeles. He added that there was a "big thud, then a flash of fire" on the left side of the plane.</p>
        <p>Other survivors described a scene of panic as choking passengers scrambled through flames to evacuate the shattered fuselage. "The row ahead of us just disappeared," Laurel Bravo of Cleveland, told The Associated Press. "The seats all went flying downward. I thought at first it was a rough landing. But then I really thought I was going to die." No Sign of Sabotage</p>
        <p>Officials appear to have ruled out sabotage as a cause of the crash. "As far was we know, everything was operating normally on landing," said Agnes Huff, a spokeswoman for USAir, which is based in Arlington, Va. "There is no evidence of sabotage or terrorism. The USAir plane came in with a normal landing. There was an impact, then they veered off to the left."</p>
        <p>SkyWest identified the two dead pilots as Captain Andy J. Lucas, 33, who had worked for the airline since 1985 and logged 15,000 flight hours, and First Officer Frank Prentice, employed since 1989. Both were from San Luis Obispo, Calif.</p>
        <p>James E. Burnett Jr., the member of the national safety board who is supervising the investigation, said that the jet's flight data recorder and cockpit voice recorder had been recovered and were being sent to Washington for analysis. The commuter plane was not equipped with such devices. Mr. Burnett said tapes of air traffic control instructions to the two planes would also be analyzed. Wreckage and Skid Marks</p>
        <p>Wreckage of the two planes remains strewn from a point just east of the parallel taxiway to the vacated fire station where the jet finally came to a halt, about 350 yards away. Three sets of skid marks, presumably from the USAir plane, run down the runway, veer left, then cross a dirt strip, the taxiway and a service road.</p>
        <p>Twenty-nine rows of seats back from the nose, the jet is broken in two. A deflated emergency chute hangs out of the right rear emergency exit. The entire mass is charred except for the nose and tail. Under the fuselage is the shattered remains of the commuter plane, one propeller under the jet's right engine, the other under the left.</p>
        <p>"It's a miracle anybody survived this," said Mr. Reber of SkyWest. "You cannot tell at what point the two planes impacted. Our aircraft is not intact. It is visible under the fuselage of the other plane."</p>
        <p>Mr. Colodny, chairman of USAir, expressed "deepest sadness on the tragedy of last evening."</p>
        <p>Two runways remained closed today, causing delays of up to two hours at Los Angeles International, the third busiest airport in the nation after O'Hare in Chicago and the Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport. Confusion and Fire</p>
        <p>Survivors said that the emergency evacuation last night went reasonably well. They said the emergency slides were deployed from the exits and that passengers left quickly amid much confusion, smoke and fire.</p>
        <p>"I went out the slide on the rear and took off running because there was a hell of a lot of fire," Dan Goss, who works at the China Lake Naval Weapons Station, told reporters.</p>
        <p>"I thought it was just the tires blowing out," said Dr. Chul Hong of Kenton, Ohio. "Then I saw the flames and everybody started screaming their heads off." He said he looked back and saw the jet engulfed in flames. He was shaken up but apparently unharmed.</p>
        <p>SkyWest, which flies in eight western states is based in St. George, in the southwestern corner of Utah. The airline, which has been in operation since 1982, is partly owned by Delta Air Lines and feeds into its routes. SkyWest flies in eight western states and has hubs in Salt Lake City and and Los Angeles. Before the crash Friday the airline had a fleet of 48 commuter planes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
