<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Testaverde May Get First Start As a Jet</title>
    <meta content="12JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1038540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Ravens</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Testaverde, Vinnie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Baltimore Ravens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7D6143AF931A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Testaverde May Get First Start As a Jet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Aug. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vinnie Testaverde is expected to start at quarterback for New York Jets in preseason game against Baltimore Ravens; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill Parcells can be a pleasant sort of fellow, especially in commercials when he affects an almost jolly air. And sometimes he is enigmatic, such as he was today. Or was he?</p>
        <p>For Parcells, perhaps inadvertently, perhaps purposely, perhaps innocently, added drama to the Jets' exhibition game against the Baltimore Ravens on Saturday night -- if not to the entire Jets' season. He said today there was ''a pretty good chance'' he would start Vinny Testaverde at quarterback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bill Parcells can be a pleasant sort of fellow, especially in commercials when he affects an almost jolly air. And sometimes he is enigmatic, such as he was today. Or was he?</p>
        <p>For Parcells, perhaps inadvertently, perhaps purposely, perhaps innocently, added drama to the Jets' exhibition game against the Baltimore Ravens on Saturday night -- if not to the entire Jets' season. He said today there was ''a pretty good chance'' he would start Vinny Testaverde at quarterback.</p>
        <p>And yet Parcells also said, when asked about his starting quarterback down the road, ''Nothing has changed in this situation.'' That would seem to indicate that Glenn Foley is still No. 1.</p>
        <p>But the decision on who starts Saturday will be made on Wednesday, after Parcells discusses it with his staff, he said. The news, even though it was hardly official, seemed to rattle Foley when reporters repeated it as he was leaving lunch. He is, after all, the Jets' starting quarterback and was told by Parcells that in the competition for the job, he gets ''the benefit of the doubt.'' But suddenly, here were his freckles virtually draining from his face as he tried to deal with the surprising news.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know that,'' he said. But then he quickly added, minimizing the significance of it, ''It's just a rotation.''</p>
        <p>Someone pointed out he didn't seem happy about it.</p>
        <p>''I need reps with the first unit if he wants me to be the starting quarterback,'' Foley responded. Foley speaks often about how little work he has had over the years, first as a No. 3 quarterback, then as a backup, in a career hampered by shoulder and knee injuries.</p>
        <p>Testaverde was said to be at the dentist's at lunchtime today, and was not available for comment. Meanwhile, Foley, despite the look of someone who had just had eight cavities filled, handled most of snaps at today's workout, just as has done from the first day of training camp.</p>
        <p>Throughout much of camp, the 34-year-old Testaverde has seemed sharper and looser than Foley, a gritty competitor who is a slow summertime starter.</p>
        <p>But against the Eagles last Thursday in the Jets' exhibition opener,  Foley recovered from a stuttering opening quarter as he completed five of his last six passes. The Jets scored 10 points in his three possessions, while Testaverde helped generate 10 points in the next four drives. Testaverde had an impressive scrambling opening pass of 39 yards to Alex Van Dyke.</p>
        <p>Today, Parcells said of Testaverde, ''I think I've got to give this guy a chance to play with the better guys, or the ones we think are the better guys.''</p>
        <p>After practice, Parcells made it sound elemental: he wanted to see Testaverde with the first-string offense.</p>
        <p>''Wouldn't you like to see Vinny with Keyshawn Johnson?'' the coach asked rhetorically. ''With the Giants,  I used to bring in Phil Simms third. It would be Rutledge, Hostetler, Simms. I'm doing it with a bunch of guys on Saturday.''</p>
        <p>Of course, it never seems that simple with Parcells, who tries to think of everything that can go wrong before he considers what can go right. These could be some other reasons he is starting Testaverde:</p>
        <p>The Jets face the Ravens in Game 2 of the regular season. By limiting Foley's appearance on Saturday, they will not get a chance to become very familiar with him.</p>
        <p>Perhaps he wants to raise Foley's aggression by creating a virtual official competition.</p>
        <p>He may want to be put Testaverde in a situation to pump him up. Testaverde was cut by the Ravens, for whom he played the last two years.</p>
        <p>He is preparing a quarterback shootout.</p>
        <p>Interestingly, Testaverde's father, Al, admitted he had mixed emotions about his son starting this weekend. Al Testaverde has not seen his son play in person since suffering a heart attack at a game in Tampa Bay 10 years ago. Even when his son went to the Pro Bowl in Hawaii two years ago, Al Testaverde went back to his hotel on Waikiki Beach to watch the game on television. He is simply too nervous at the game.</p>
        <p>''It's great for Vinny,'' Al Testaverde said today. ''But it's bad for me.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The exhibition game against the Ravens starts at 5 P.M. so that the Jets' huge New York television market doesn't intrude on CBS's return to the N.F.L. The network had been away four years, and is coming back with an 8 P.M. game between the 49ers and Seahawks. The Jets, who will be on Channel 11 Saturday, drew more viewers in the regular season last year than any other team in the league. . . . For $300, many players have rented golf carts for the summer. They take them from practice to meals or their dorms, which is a five-minute walk from the practice field. . . . JUMBO ELLIOTT stopped practicing at his left tackle position Tuesday and spent the rest of the time soaking his right ankle in a bucket of ice water.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
