<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.B.I. Is Retailoring to Meet New Threats but Stretched Thin, Reports Say</title>
    <meta content="Y19TER$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/19/politics/19TERR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1498100"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THREATS AND RESPONSES: TERROR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Accounting Office</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Academy of Public Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lichtblau, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mueller, Robert S III (Dir)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">General Accounting Office</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2D81138F93AA25755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.B.I. Is Retailoring to Meet New Threats but Stretched Thin, Reports Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">F.B.I. Is Reshaping Itself but Stretched Thin, Reports Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LICHTBLAU</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lichtblau, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two reports conclude that FBI has made strong progress in reinventing itself since attacks of Sept 11, 2001, but doubts remain over its long-term ability to balance terrorism investigations with its traditional duties; reports are delivered to Congress by General Accounting Office and National Academy of Public Administration; among chief concerns are FBI's overhaul of its outdated technology systems, its ability to share terror intelligence with other agencies and its commitment to fully investigate nonterrrorism crimes; FBI director Robert S Mueller III tells hearing that 'sea change' is required to avoid another Sept 11; Mueller draws strong praise from Republicans and Democrats alike; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The F.B.I. has made strong progress in reinventing itself since the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, but doubts remain over its long-term ability to balance terrorism investigations with its traditional crime-fighting duties, two major reports concluded today.</p>
        <p>Among the chief concerns, the reports said, are the F.B.I.'s overhaul of its outdated technology systems, its ability to share terror intelligence with other agencies and its commitment to fully investigate nonterrorism crimes like drugs and white-collar crime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The F.B.I. has made progress in reinventing itself since the Sept. 11 attacks, but doubts remain over its long-term ability to balance its duties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The F.B.I. has made strong progress in reinventing itself since the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, but doubts remain over its long-term ability to balance terrorism investigations with its traditional crime-fighting duties, two major reports concluded today.</p>
        <p>Among the chief concerns, the reports said, are the F.B.I.'s overhaul of its outdated technology systems, its ability to share terror intelligence with other agencies and its commitment to fully investigate nonterrorism crimes like drugs and white-collar crime.</p>
        <p>The General Accounting Office, the investigative arm of Congress, said in a report to a House subcommittee that it ''is encouraged by the progress that the F.B.I. has made in some areas in the past year, but a number of major challenges remain.''</p>
        <p>That optimistic-but-cautious tone was echoed by a second report delivered to Congress by the National Academy of Public Administration. Together, the two studies represented the most comprehensive progress report to date on the Federal Bureau of Investigation's efforts to remake itself into a front line of defense against terrorism.</p>
        <p>After the attacks on the World Trade Center and the Pentagon, the bureau was widely criticized for its failure to pick up on potential warning signs in the months before the hijackings.</p>
        <p>Some critics have suggested the creation of a new agency for counterterrorism and domestic intelligence, but the Bush administration has resisted that idea. Instead, the administration has made it a priority to turn the bureau into an agency devoted to preventing attacks, rather than simply solving crimes that have occurred.</p>
        <p>''We cannot afford another Sept. 11, and that requires a sea change'' in priorities and tactics, Robert S. Mueller III, the director of the bureau, said at today's hearing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mueller drew strong praise from Republicans and Democrats alike at the hearing, as did the authors of both reports and the president of the F.B.I. agents' association.</p>
        <p>Dick Thornburgh, the former attorney general who led the National Academy of Public Administration's study, said Mr. Mueller had succeeded in ''instilling a new sense of mission and dedication'' at the bureau and bringing in the right people and devoting the needed resources to achieve the restructuring.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mueller cited as important advances the restructuring of the bureau's administration as well as its redeployment of more than 500 criminal agents to counterterrorism and an additional 167 agents to counterintelligence. The bureau has more than 11,000 agents.</p>
        <p>But several lawmakers questioned whether that shift had taken too great a toll in fighting traditional crimes.</p>
        <p>The accounting office study found that drug enforcement by the F.B.I. had ''diminished significantly,'' with a drop of about 15 percent in 2002 and 2003 in criminal referrals and prosecutions.</p>
        <p>Representative Harold Rogers, Republican of Kentucky, told Mr. Mueller that with 400 agents transferred from drug investigations to terrorism, state and local authorities in regions like his were having a tough time keeping pace with the drug dealers.</p>
        <p>''I'm afraid it's going to leave a big hole,'' Mr. Rogers said.</p>
        <p>Representative Frank R. Wolf, the Virginia Republican who led the hearing, said he shared that concern. Mr. Wolf said he believed that there were important areas like public corruption that the F.B.I. was not aggressively investigating. Congress may need to authorize money for more agents to fill the gap, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mueller acknowledged that ''we are stretched'' because of the bureau's expanded counterterrorism duties. ''We have to pick and choose,'' he said. But he said the bureau remained committed to investigating major public corruption and white-collar crime.</p>
        <p>Another area of concern cited by several lawmakers centered on the new Terrorism Threat Integration Center, which the Bush administration created earlier this year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf said that while he supported the idea of an independent center to filter terrorist intelligence across the government, he was bothered because the center was run by the Central Intelligence Agency.</p>
        <p>''You are not an equal partner there,'' he told Mr. Mueller, but ''more an arm of the C.I.A.''</p>
        <p>Several lawmakers said they feared that the C.I.A., because of a history of turf wars, would be unwilling to share crucial intelligence with other agencies.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Mueller said he believed that the setup was working well. He said that the new center's mission was limited to analyzing intelligence, rather than operational activities, and that it represented an important effort ''to drop down the walls'' between agencies.</p>
        <p>THREATS AND RESPONSES: TERROR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
