<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lots of Cheer From R.I.M., But No News On Options</title>
    <meta content="25rim" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/25/technology/25rim.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1814335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Research in Motion</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ontario Securities Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Balsillie, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austen, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Research In Motion</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DF1E31F936A15751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1196" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lots of Cheer From R.I.M., But No News On Options</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lots of Cheer From R.I.M., but No News on Options</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN AUSTEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Austen, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA, Dec. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Research In Motion chairman and co-chief executive James L Balsillie said quarterly profit was up 47 percent from same period year ago and sales increased 49 percent during investor conference call last week; Balsillie had no comment on review of RIM's stock options grants being undertaken by independent board directors; eight-page letter company submitted at beginning of last week for Ontario Securities Commission hearing only added to uncertainty; it indicated that review was 'proceeding more slowly than anticipated' and that various complications 'substantially increase' $25 million to $45 million in restatements company initially anticipated; lack of information is baffling to investors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>James L. Balsillie, the chairman and co-chief executive of Research In Motion, offered plenty of cheery news during an investor conference call last week: quarterly profit up 47 percent from the same period a year ago and a sales increase of 49 percent, largely based on the company's successful move into the consumer market.</p>
        <p>On another issue, Mr. Balsillie had no comment: the review of R.I.M.'s stock options grants being undertaken by the independent board directors. The lack of information follows a pattern at R.I.M., the Canadian company that created the BlackBerry and made it a global brand. Ever since late September, when R.I.M. said it had started the review, the company has offered investors and regulators few details, making it difficult to assess its potential impact or full extent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Research In Motion has offered investors few details about the review of its stock options grants, making it difficult to assess its potential impact.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>James L. Balsillie, the chairman and co-chief executive of Research In Motion, offered plenty of cheery news during an investor conference call last week: quarterly profit up 47 percent from the same period a year ago and a sales increase of 49 percent, largely based on the company's successful move into the consumer market.</p>
        <p>On another issue, Mr. Balsillie had no comment: the review of R.I.M.'s stock options grants being undertaken by the independent board directors. The lack of information follows a pattern at R.I.M., the Canadian company that created the BlackBerry and made it a global brand. Ever since late September, when R.I.M. said it had started the review, the company has offered investors and regulators few details, making it difficult to assess its potential impact or full extent.</p>
        <p>An eight-page letter it submitted at the beginning of last week for an Ontario Securities Commission hearing only added to the uncertainty. It indicated that the review was ''proceeding more slowly than anticipated'' and that various complications ''substantially increase'' the $25 million to $45 million in restatements the company initially anticipated.</p>
        <p>The lack of information is baffling to investors, particularly at a time when the company's stock on the Nasdaq has climbed to $130 on Friday, from $81.93 at the beginning of September.</p>
        <p>''If I were a portfolio manager, I would have a hard time figuring out how significant this issue is,'' said Henry T. C. Hu, a professor of corporate and securities law at the University of Texas in Austin.</p>
        <p>''I can't figure out what the best case is,'' he said. '' 'Substantially increase,' does that mean we ought to apply a multiple of 2 or a higher multiple? All we know is that there are enough zeros that they're using the word substantially.''</p>
        <p>R.I.M. has yet to disclose the nature of the problems with its options-granting policies, including whether the company backdated some options to allow employees and executives to purchase stock at lower prices. Nor is it clear if the options situation directly involves Mr. Balsillie or Michael Lazaridis, the company's president and other co-chief executive.</p>
        <p>And at least one small Canadian institutional investor, the Ironworkers Ontario Pension Fund, through a lawyer who specializes in securities-related class-action lawsuits, is raising questions about the wisdom of having the review supervised by directors who themselves benefited from R.I.M. stock options.</p>
        <p>R.I.M. is one of many companies facing questions over their options practices. The Securities and Exchange Commission is investigating at least 120 companies, including Apple Computer, UnitedHealth Group and dozens of technology companies, for possible stock-options manipulation, and the Justice Department and the Internal Revenue Service are conducting separate reviews.</p>
        <p>For the moment, however, the uncertainties at R.I.M. appear to have been swept aside in most investors' and analysts' minds by R.I.M.'s overwhelming dominance of the wireless e-mail market for business users and by the immediate, and surprisingly strong, success of its first BlackBerry built for consumers, the Pearl.</p>
        <p>This much is known about the situation: four independent directors on R.I.M.'s audit committee, assisted by outside lawyers and accountants, are examining about 3,200 stock options given to about 2,000 employees that date back at least 10 years. The company began trading publicly in 1997.</p>
        <p>Searches of the company's computer system, its data backup and something the company calls ''forensic imaging'' have produced about 650,000 documents related to the options. The delay in the investigation, the company said in its letter, largely comes from the fact that the audit committee is dealing with 250,000 more documents than it originally expected.</p>
        <p>What remains unclear is why the company now expects to make a larger-than-expected financial restatement. In its filings, R.I.M. has said only that ''certain accounting errors'' understated noncash charges from the options and effectively inflated earnings. Exactly what those noncash items are is not known.</p>
        <p>Since starting the investigation, the committee has found an ''additional error'' in accounting that substantially understated the options-related charges.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the day after Mr. Balsillie's conference call, Peter Misek, a technology analyst with Canaccord Adams in Toronto, appeared on Report on Business Television, a Canadian cable channel. Like many other analysts, he was effusive about R.I.M.'s results and the company's potential, particularly in the consumer market.</p>
        <p>''They were blow-out results,'' Mr. Misek told viewers. ''This is a table pounder for us. You've got to own the stock.''</p>
        <p>During a subsequent interview, Mr. Misek, whose firm trades R.I.M. shares on behalf of clients but has no holdings or dealings with the company, acknowledged that the uncertainty surrounding the options review made him uneasy.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to deny that I'm nervous,'' Mr. Misek said, ''but I'm going to continue to believe that this was a past issue that was unfortunate. And, I think in the end management will do the right thing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Misek estimates that the restatement is in the range of $100 million, although he acknowledged that the figure is a guess. Mr. Misek does not believe that options were adjusted to improperly benefit employees. Instead, he believes that the review will find that bookkeeping systems at the company failed to keep pace with the rapid growth at R.I.M. that followed the introduction of the BlackBerry in January 1999.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Misek's anxiety goes beyond the potential amount of the financial restatement. R.I.M.'s success can largely be traced to both Mr. Balsillie and Mr. Lazaridis. Anything that jeopardized their positions within the company would most likely depress R.I.M.'s stock.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazaridis's engineering skills are widely admired. His innovations include obvious features such as the BlackBerry's thumb-operated keyboard, as well as critical technical innovations in the device's radio system, electronics and, above all, the software it uses to route e-mail messages.</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Balsillie's aggressive enthusiasm for the BlackBerry that first persuaded major wireless service providers in the United States and Europe to offer an untried product and service from an obscure maker of wireless modems in Canada.</p>
        <p>Having known Mr. Balsillie and Mr. Lazaridis for more than six years, Mr. Misek said he did not believe that they would have acted improperly for personal gain.</p>
        <p>''I have no love for any executive, but I don't see it in this case,'' said Mr. Misek, who is an accountant by training. ''Mike's not motivated by money,'' he added, referring to Mr. Lazaridis.</p>
        <p>R.I.M. and its directors have consistently declined to discuss the review. But in its letter to the Ontario regulator, the company argued that the amount of information it is providing ''is more detailed and informative than the information provided by comparable companies in the United States in similar circumstances.''</p>
        <p>During the conference call, Mr. Balsillie spoke at length about the Pearl, which is the first BlackBerry with multimedia capabilities, saying it is just the beginning of a range of new products and services from R.I.M. And while he was talking about new technologies, Mr. Balsillie made a comment that might also apply to the options review.</p>
        <p>''Those of you that follow us closely, I would argue that if you really paid attention to us and you are a real expert, you might have a sense of 20 percent of what's really going on,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
