<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets Draft Talented Guard, Just in Case</title>
    <meta content="27NETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/27/sports/basketball/27nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1500308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Croatia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Planinic, Zoran</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kidd, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kidd, Jason</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D61E3BF934A15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets Draft Talented Guard, Just in Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nets Draft Talented Guard, Just in Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., June 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Nets draft Croatian point guard Zoran Planinic with No.22 pick in first round; Planinic will back up free agent guard Jason Kidd if he decides to stay with team; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets had been coveting one particular point guard for two weeks, and they secured him tonight with the No. 22 pick in the first round of the N.B.A. draft.</p>
        <p>Whether or not Jason Kidd returns next season -- his agent said tonight that Kidd planned to visit San Antonio and a couple of other cities after he becomes a free agent on Tuesday -- the Nets will have a slim 6-foot-7 point guard, Zoran Planinic, coming off the bench.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whether or not Jason Kidd returns to the Nets next season, New Jersey will have a backup point guard in 6-foot-7 Zoran Planinic of Croatia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nets had been coveting one particular point guard for two weeks, and they secured him tonight with the No. 22 pick in the first round of the N.B.A. draft.</p>
        <p>Whether or not Jason Kidd returns next season -- his agent said tonight that Kidd planned to visit San Antonio and a couple of other cities after he becomes a free agent on Tuesday -- the Nets will have a slim 6-foot-7 point guard, Zoran Planinic, coming off the bench.</p>
        <p>Planinic, 20, becomes the Nets' first Croatian player since Drazen Petrovic, the All-Star and Hall of Famer who died in a car accident 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>''Let's hope he's as good as Drazen,'' Rod Thorn, the Nets' president, said. ''Drazen obviously is the greatest Croatian player ever. I'm not going to say he's Drazen Petrovic. He's a very talented kid. Drazen shot it and he could handle it well; this kid handles it real well and doesn't shoot it like Drazen.''</p>
        <p>Planinic grew up idolizing Petrovic, and his favorite point guard is Kidd. Planinic was in New York for the draft and was excited when he heard his name called.</p>
        <p>''It was great,'' Planinic said. ''I really hoped the Nets selected me because the team is incredibly good and I want to play on a winning team. So I think my way of play and the Nets, we are going to be good.''</p>
        <p>Planinic is under contract with a Euroleague team, Cibona, for which Petrovic also played. But unlike last year's first-round pick, Nenad Krstic of Serbia and Montenegro, who is playing in Belgrade and may not be released from his contract this season, Planinic has a buyout in his contract, Thorn said.</p>
        <p>''It's not a problem -- I'm going to play for the Nets,'' Planinic said.</p>
        <p>Thorn said the Nets wanted to have Planinic play in an N.B.A. summer league to get him started.</p>
        <p>''His skill set is outstanding; his size, I like players with size,'' Thorn said.</p>
        <p>In Croatia this season, Planinic averaged 7.8 points and 2.8 assists a game and shot 52.4 percent. His season got off to a rocky start when he sustained a concussion in a car accident in September.</p>
        <p>Thorn, who said that Planinic broke an ankle two years ago, added that Planinic played ''much better the latter part of the season, once he got well.''</p>
        <p>''We examined him in the workout,'' Thorn said. ''He was jumping all over the place and there certainly didn't seem like there was anything wrong with him.''</p>
        <p>The Nets worked out Planinic twice. In his last workout, on June 11, he tweaked his back.</p>
        <p>''Ideally, he's a backup point and maybe play some two, but we'll have to see,'' Thorn said. ''He's not a great shooter, but there's nothing broken about his shot.</p>
        <p>''We felt this kid has a real upside, a young kid. He's big defensively. He'll be challenged, at least immediately. When you look at our team, he could do a lot of things.</p>
        <p>''We needed a talented player,'' Thorn said, adding with a smile, ''just in case.''</p>
        <p>That case became a little more uncertain tonight. Jeff Schwartz, Kidd's agent, said in a telephone interview that Kidd would visit other teams besides the Nets once the free agency period begins Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''He's going to go visit a couple of different teams,'' Schwartz said. ''The dates have not been locked in.''</p>
        <p>Schwartz said that Kidd was tentatively scheduled to visit the Spurs on July 6 and 7.</p>
        <p>A report on ESPN said Kidd intended to visit Dallas and possibly Denver, but Schwartz said the other cities had not been confirmed yet.</p>
        <p>''I assumed that he was going to visit San Antonio,'' Thorn said. ''Denver doesn't act like it plays into what he's looking for, but obviously they would have a lot of money they can offer.</p>
        <p>''The only way he could ever go to Dallas is in some sort of sign-and-trade, so that's very far-fetched. That would be a last resort that might happen in December.'' Dallas is over the salary cap.</p>
        <p>Thorn said he and Schwartz had not been able to talk today before Thorn first heard about Kidd's plan from the ESPN report during the draft. Schwartz said he would talk to the Nets as soon as he could.</p>
        <p>''He's going to have an itinerary and he's going to do what he's going to do,'' Thorn said of Kidd.</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>With their second-round pick, 51st over all, the Nets took Creighton forward KYLE KORVER, and sold him to Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
