<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arts Groups In New York Brace for Cuts In City Funds</title>
    <meta content="20CUTS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/20/arts/20CUTS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1393873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Serrano, Jose</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EED91438F933A15756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1275" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arts Groups In New York Brace for Cuts In City Funds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Arts Groups in New York Brace for Cuts in City Funds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many of New York City's largest city-supported cultural institutions brace for budget cuts; City Council, coming to grips with nearly $5 billion deficit and reality that almost entire council is made up of new members, may not be in position to restore funds cut by Mayor Michael Bloomberg; Bloomberg has asked Cultural Affairs Department to cut its capital budget by $263 million over next five years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When representatives of many of the large city-supported cultural institutions gathered for a news conference on Thursday to protest Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's proposed budget cuts, the speeches seemed more dutiful than fiery, and the auditorium at El Museo del Barrio was practically empty.</p>
        <p>Only James A. Lebenthal, the municipal bond magnate who serves on the board of the Museum of the City of New York, managed to muster some passion in warning the 10 or so people in attendance, ''You take away any part of the cultural life of this city and you strike at the very heart of what all public investment is supposed to do, and that is improve the quality of life.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many of the large city-supported cultural institutions gathered for a news conference on Thursday to protest Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's proposed budget cuts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When representatives of many of the large city-supported cultural institutions gathered for a news conference on Thursday to protest Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's proposed budget cuts, the speeches seemed more dutiful than fiery, and the auditorium at El Museo del Barrio was practically empty.</p>
        <p>Only James A. Lebenthal, the municipal bond magnate who serves on the board of the Museum of the City of New York, managed to muster some passion in warning the 10 or so people in attendance, ''You take away any part of the cultural life of this city and you strike at the very heart of what all public investment is supposed to do, and that is improve the quality of life.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the city's cultural groups are finding it tough to get all worked up for a fight they seem largely resigned to losing, or maybe they are hoping to be rescued, at least to some extent, by the City Council, as they have been in past years.</p>
        <p>Typically this is the season of the dance in which the mayor cuts the cultural budget, and the City Council restores the funds. The budget is to be adopted June 5 and to take effect July 1. But with the city facing a deficit of nearly $5 billion and an almost entirely new roster of Council members learning the ropes of budget negotiations, this year may well be different.</p>
        <p>''We don't know if we're going to be able to do it the way we have in years past because we're facing such a shortfall,'' said Jose Serrano, a freshman councilman who heads the committee on culture and libraries.</p>
        <p>In his preliminary budget, Mayor Bloomberg proposed cuts of $19.1 million to the Cultural Affairs Department. This breaks down to reductions of about 18 percent to the 34 members of the Cultural Institutions Group, institutions whose buildings or land is owned in part or whole by the city, and about 13 percent to the more than 500 institutions that are considered program groups. The Cultural Institutions Group includes the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Studio Museum in Harlem; among the program groups are the Museum of Modern Art, the Pan Asian Repertory Theater and the Queens Historical Society.</p>
        <p>Mayor Bloomberg has asked the Cultural Affairs Department staff to cut its capital budget by $263 million over the next five years, down from the current $862 million. Over his eight years in office, former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani spent $487.7 million on capital cultural projects.</p>
        <p>Everybody knows there is less money to go around. As the economy was turning down, the events of Sept. 11 drastically escalated the slump, and every city agency expects to be in for severe sacrifices. Mayor Bloomberg has proposed contingency cuts of $63 million from the Police Department, nearly $17 million from libraries and $10 million from the Sanitation Department.</p>
        <p>''I'm having difficulty figuring out how the Council is going to restore funds to any constituency unless the question of revenues is resolved,'' said Norma P. Munn, chairwoman of the New York City Arts Coalition, a citywide advocacy group.</p>
        <p>During most of his eight years in office, Mayor Giuliani proposed cuts for the members of the Cultural Institutions Group, but these cuts were restored by the Council in an almost ritualistic way that Mr. Giuliani foresaw and participated in. But Kate D. Levin, the city's commissioner of cultural affairs, said that given the severe projected budget shortfall, Mayor Bloomberg's budget proposal was real, not a starting point.</p>
        <p>''We devised the cuts with the charge: If the music stops here, what would be the best way to allocate funding knowing we're facing a horrible fiscal crisis, and what can we do to help culturals sustain themselves in a very difficult period?'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg's would not be the first city administration to argue at the outset that there was no room for horse trading and then have to negotiate with the State Legislature. The City Council has already called for maximum cuts of only 2 percent, compared to Mr. Bloomberg's double-digit proposal.</p>
        <p>The mayor's proposed cuts ''will severely impact the ability of cultural groups to provide services that are essential to who we are as a city,'' said Gifford Miller, the speaker of the City Council.</p>
        <p>But the 2 percent cuts are dependent on tax revenues that are highly unlikely, budget experts say: City Council proposals to reinstate the commuter tax and impose a personal income tax surcharge. Mayor Bloomberg has said he would veto any budget that included tax increases, for fear they would drive New Yorkers out of the city, and a commuter tax would also have to go through the Legislature, where it is thought to be a virtual nonstarter.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile many cultural organizations are struggling with lower ticket sales because of the dramatic drop in tourists and reduced contributions from foundations, corporations and individuals. Many have cut staff, reduced programming or postponed construction plans.</p>
        <p>David E. McKinney, president of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, said that attendance was still down 30 percent from last year, having dropped by 60 percent right after Sept. 11, largely because of the reduction of tourists from the West Coast, Europe and Japan. In the fiscal year 2001 the museum had 5 million visitors; attendance is expected to be down to 3.9 million for the fiscal year 2002, which ends in June.</p>
        <p>''It's a severe impact,'' Mr. McKinney said. ''And we're expecting that to continue.''</p>
        <p>How much money will be available to the City Council after it negotiates with the mayor is one great unknown. Another is which services will be most successful in competing for whatever funds remain. Rather than proposing across-the-board cuts, the Cultural Affairs Department for the first time this year cut some organizations more than others, depending on their size and strength, Ms. Levin said. ''The mayor wanted us to give particular consideration to the groups having the hardest time financially,'' she added.</p>
        <p>At Thursday's news conference, officials of El Museo del Barrio said the proposed cuts would force their museum to lay off one-quarter of its guards, shut down its permanent Caribbean exhibition and close the institution one day a week.</p>
        <p>Arts executives like Lowery Stokes Sims, director of the Studio Museum in Harlem, and Donna Walker-Kuhne, the director of community outreach and education initiatives at the Joseph Papp Public Theater, said the cuts are likely to hurt their education programs most.</p>
        <p>The city's cultural groups are stressing their importance to the economy of the city. They point out that the member organizations of the Cultural Institutions Group employ 11,000 people and last year brought 19 million visitors into their buildings. For every dollar the city spends on the arts, it collects $2 in tax receipts, said a study by the Alliance for the Arts, an advocacy group.</p>
        <p>Councilman Serrano said, ''Cultural institutions are a core service for New York City because they are a fiscal engine.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Levin said Mr. Bloomberg understood that. ''The mayor values what the cultural sector does for New York very highly,'' she said. ''The problem is, you can't wish away a $5 billion deficit.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
