<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kuwait Prevents an Opposition Protest</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="439636"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="AFTER THE WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KUWAIT-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, JAMES A 3D (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SABAH, JABER AL-AHMED AL- (SHEIK) (EMIR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GARGAN, EDWARD A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DE103DF930A15757C0A967958260" item-length="1319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kuwait Prevents an Opposition Protest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD A. GARGAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GARGAN, EDWARD A</byline>
      <dateline>KUWAIT CITY, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the day Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d visited here to evaluate Kuwait's progress toward democracy and rebuilding the country, the Government moved forcefully to halt an attempt by opposition groups to denounce the country's new Cabinet.</p>
        <p>The groups intended to meet with foreign journalists today to declare that the Cabinet appointed on Saturday was simply a shuffling of ministers, almost all of them members of the ruling Sabah family, whom the opposition blames for the crisis leading up to he Iraqi invasion of Aug. 2.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the day Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d visited here to evaluate Kuwait's progress toward democracy and rebuilding the country, the Government moved forcefully to halt an attempt by opposition groups to denounce the country's new Cabinet.</p>
        <p>The groups intended to meet with foreign journalists today to declare that the Cabinet appointed on Saturday was simply a shuffling of ministers, almost all of them members of the ruling Sabah family, whom the opposition blames for the crisis leading up to he Iraqi invasion of Aug. 2.</p>
        <p>This morning, about two dozen opposition figures gathered in the Goverment-owned Kuwait International Hotel to speak at a scheduled news conference. Some time during the night, however, someone had gone through the hotel, the center for most of the international press corps, removing printed announcements of the briefing, which had been posted throughout the building. No Approval Granted</p>
        <p>As Government critics milled about, passing out copies of their statement on the new Cabinet, a hotel manager hustled into the ballroom to declare that the meeting could not be held because it had not been approved by the Information Ministry. An armed Government security guard in camouflage fatigues switched off the lights, forcing everyone into the hallways.</p>
        <p>In the Information Ministry's office in the hotel, the daughter of Kuwait's Crown Prince, Jamail al-Sabah, was hurriedly giving directions to ministry staffers. Although she holds no formal position, her place in the royal family accords her unchallenged authority within the Government. In some cases, it has been she alone who has approved credentials for foreign journalists.</p>
        <p>A flustered ministry official, Hissa al-Shaheen, said that her office had ordered that the opposition news conference be halted.</p>
        <p>"Yes," she said, "the ministry has to approve it. You can't just hold a conference. If they want a specific arrangement, they have to send a letter and we then approve it."  Baker Sees the Emir</p>
        <p>The opposition news session was thwarted as Mr. Baker paid a brief visit and told the Emir of Kuwait, Sheik Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah, that Washington's willingness to continue to support Kuwait militarily and politically would be influenced by its commitment to human rights and democratization. Mr. Baker said afterward that he had received assurances from the Emir that the Government was working to uphold democratic principles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker interrupted his Mideast peace mission to meet with the Kuwaiti leadership at the behest of President Bush. The visit was apparently prompted by mounting concern in the Administration that the flagging pace of reconstruction in Kuwait, and recent allegations of human rights abuses there, were raising politically explosive questions about just what sort of government the United States had fought to restore.</p>
        <p>Speaking to reporters after his hourlong meeting with the Emir and the Prime Minister, Crown Prince Saad al-Abdullah al-Sabah, Mr. Baker said he told the Kuwaiti leaders that "the ability of the United States to continue to support Kuwait politically and from a security standpoint, in a manner in which we supported them against the brutal aggression of Saddam Hussein, would be enhanced if they evidenced full respect and commitment to the preservation of human rights."</p>
        <p>Asked whether he had received any assurance from the Emir and the Crown Prince on human rights and the expansion of democracy in Kuwait, Mr. Baker replied:</p>
        <p>"Yes, I did. The Emir and the Crown Prince and their colleagues were very forthcoming on both of those issues." He cited the Emir's recent pledge to hold elections next year and to consider voting rights for women.  Opposition Gathers Momentum</p>
        <p>Since the new Cabinet was announced Saturday, opposition groups have been meeting throughout Kuwait City to draft the statement made public today denouncing the Government and its policies. Critics say the Cabinet does not represent the Kuwaiti people, especially those who remained during the seven-month Iraqi occupation.</p>
        <p>The Emir, who suspended an elected National Assembly in 1986, has promised elections for sometime next year, but has refused to specify when the vote will be held or who will be permitted to cast ballots. Many opposition figures, some of whom were jailed by both the Kuwaiti Government before Aug. 2, and by the Iraqis during the occupation, are incensed at what they say is an effort to preserve the prewar government structure.</p>
        <p>"We have no democracy in Kuwait," said an angry Mohammed al-Khadiri, a leader of the Democratic Forum, a secular, liberal opposition group. "It's very clear. We are asking for democracy, the implementation of the suspended Constitution, forming a real democratic government and to have human rights -- individual rights to speak, to read, to write, to have a small conference, which is forbidden."</p>
        <p>Mr. Khadiri, who spent a week in jail in July for human rights activities and then two weeks in Iraqi prisons in February, said the failure of the Government to permit opposition groups to speak out was an ominous sign. Unrepresentative Government</p>
        <p>"We have the same problem as before," he said. "All we are asking for is a government that represents all political parties and respects the program of the people. This Government does not represent the program of the people."</p>
        <p>Standing in the dimly lit hotel ballroom amid a confusion of voices after the news conference was thwarted, Sami al-Katrash, a professor of economics at Kuwait University and a member of the Islamic Constitutional Movement, held an impromptu news conference of his own to read from the oppposition statement.</p>
        <p>The opposition, he said, demands a return to the nation's Constitution of 1962, which guarantees a free press and free elections. In addition, he said, a specific date for the election must be set and a Cabinet chosen not in the councils of the Sabah family, but as a product of representative government.</p>
        <p>And last, Mr. Katrash said alluding to the Iraqi invasion and occupation, the opposition insists on "holding to account all officials responsible for the catastrophe and not excusing their responsibility for what happened before and during the ordeal." Resentment of Those Who Left</p>
        <p>Among perhaps 150,000 Kuwaitis who remained here during the occupation, there is growing resentment against those who fled into exile, including the royal family and the Government.</p>
        <p>Although it is difficult to assess the exact degree to which existing opposition groups represent popular opinion, it appears from many conversations that together they broadly express the dissatisfaction of Kuwaitis now in the country. Altogether, seven groups signed the opposition statement, ranging from fundamentalist Muslim to vaguely socialist.</p>
        <p>Today's action by the Government was an unusually visible clampdown on its critics, given the recent weeks of relative freedom.</p>
        <p>As the new Cabinet comes under heavy criticism, Kuwaitis and experts on the region also say its makeup may reflect another chapter in a lively feud between two branches of the ruling family -- the Jabers, to which the Emir belongs, and the Salems, to which Crown Prince Saad belongs. The Salems Now Dominate</p>
        <p>"This family fight has resolved itself for now with the crushing victory of the Salems," Jean Gueyras, the Mideast expert of the French daily Le Monde said in a commentary today, noting that four of the five ministries allotted to members of the ruling family went to relatives of the Crown Prince.</p>
        <p>This is a reversal of fortune. In the past, relatives of the Emir tended to dominate major portfolios.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gueyras said in his analysis that regardless of the feuding among the Sabahs, the family continues to keep control of major decision-making, denying any real participation by members of the democracy movement.</p>
        <p>AFTER THE WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
