<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Satisfied With Their Choices</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="439420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRAFT AND RECRUITMENT (SPORTS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDB1439F930A15757C0A967958260" item-length="620" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Satisfied With Their Choices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY,</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the National Football League draft ended today, the Giants seemed to have done well for themselves.</p>
        <p>Over two days, they added a fullback (Jarrod Bunch of Michigan) and an outside linebacker (Kanavis McGhee of Colorado), two potential stars. They added a wide receiver who is also a classroom star (Ed McCaffrey of Stanford), an inside linebacker who may become a tight end (Corey Miller of South Carolina) and a big safety who played for four colleges (Lamar McGriggs).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the National Football League draft ended today, the Giants seemed to have done well for themselves.</p>
        <p>Over two days, they added a fullback (Jarrod Bunch of Michigan) and an outside linebacker (Kanavis McGhee of Colorado), two potential stars. They added a wide receiver who is also a classroom star (Ed McCaffrey of Stanford), an inside linebacker who may become a tight end (Corey Miller of South Carolina) and a big safety who played for four colleges (Lamar McGriggs).</p>
        <p>In all, the Giants drafted seven players on offense (two wide receivers, a tight end, a quarterback, a fullback, a tackle and a guard). They took five on defense (three linebackers, a cornerback and a safety).</p>
        <p>They wanted a quarterback and took one in the 12th round with the last pick of the draft. He was Larry Wanke of John Carroll in Cleveland, a Division III college. In 1987, as a Pittsburgh substitute, he threw three touchdown passes against Texas in the Bluebonnet Bowl. Parcells Is Pleased</p>
        <p>Coach Bill Parcells said he was pleased. He said he felt better this year than last because in most of the early-round choices he had first-hand information on his new players from coaches or up to six scouting people. But he was also cautious.</p>
        <p>"I've been doing this too long not to be overly optimistic or overly discouraged," he said. "But you never know. When you get to training camp, you find out what you have. Until then, it's conjecture."</p>
        <p>Some of his new players have unusual backgrounds. McCaffrey, the 6- foot-5-inch wide receiver from Stanford drafted on the third round, was a GTE Academic all-American. He has a 3.40 grade-point average, and when the semester ends he will receive a bachelor's degree in economics and a master's in sociology.</p>
        <p>The Giants' three linebacker picks came in the first six rounds. In addition to McGhee, they were Anthony Moss of Florida State and Corey Miller of South Carolina. However, Miller may wind up at tight end.</p>
        <p>Miller started college as a tight end. After Miller's freshman year, South Carolina went to a run-and-shoot offense and did not need tight ends, so he played defensive end and some at inside linebacker. He weighs 255 pounds and has bench pressed 460 pounds. Help Sought at Tight End</p>
        <p>The Giants want help at tight end because Mark Bavaro is recuperating from a bone graft to replace dead bone in his left knee. They also want help at linebacker, where Lawrence McGrew is 33 and Lawrence Taylor and Johnie Cooks 32.</p>
        <p>Because Taylor and Carl Banks are such outstanding outside linebackers, McGhee can learn from them before he is thrust into a starting job.</p>
        <p>"McGhee is a little different from Taylor and Banks," Parcells said. "He's bigger, 20 pounds heavier than they were when they were drafted. You don't want to take any outside linebacker unless he can play on the tight end, and he can."</p>
        <p>"I did some of everything for Colorado," McGhee said, "pass rush, some man-on-man, dropping back into a zone. I'm versatile."</p>
        <p>McGriggs, the safety chosen in the eighth round, is versatile in a different way. He played one year each at Arizona Western, Ellsworth Community College in Iowa, Oklahoma State and Western Illinois.</p>
        <p>Parcells was especially happy about Bunch, the first-round draft choice. He said he would start him out as a backup to Maurice Carthon.</p>
        <p>"He's 250 pounds and fast and tough," Parcells said. "He's used to playing in cold weather. He comes from a good program. He's a team guy. He can catch fairly well. He's an excellent blocker, and he can block against the blitz.</p>
        <p>"All our people think he can run in a one-back offense. He should be able to push the pile, and in a one-back, that's one of the things you have to be able to do."  FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
