<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Honeymoon Sours for Haiti President</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="439711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARISTIDE, JEAN-BERTRAND (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRENCH, HOWARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D8153EF930A15757C0A967958260" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Honeymoon Sours for Haiti President</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRENCH, HOWARD W</byline>
      <dateline>PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide was elected President by an overwhelming margin in December, crowds of jubilant Haitians filled the air with cries proclaiming their country's rebirth.</p>
        <p>But a couple of months into Father Aristide's presidency, the optimism has begun to give way to a realization that Haiti's road to economic and political revival is thickly strewn with obstacles, and many wonder whether the new Government has the ability to surmount them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide was elected President by an overwhelming margin in December, crowds of jubilant Haitians filled the air with cries proclaiming their country's rebirth.</p>
        <p>But a couple of months into Father Aristide's presidency, the optimism has begun to give way to a realization that Haiti's road to economic and political revival is thickly strewn with obstacles, and many wonder whether the new Government has the ability to surmount them.</p>
        <p>The President's critics generally give the politically inexperienced priest high marks for having tamed a power-hungry army and for ending a long series of street robberies.</p>
        <p>But even many ofhis allies complain that the new Government, which has few experienced high-level officials, has shown little grasp of economic issues or matters of governing.</p>
        <p>Proclaiming control over inflation as a top priority, the Government last month froze prices for some basic goods. When this failed to stop prices from rising, or goods from disappearing from the shelves, the official press cast blame on "the invisible hand of a few foreign powers." chants.</p>
        <p>While the Government gropes for economic answers, popular frustration has been rising. On April 15, one person was killed and several hurt in a northern city, Cap-Haitien, in a demonstration against rising prices.</p>
        <p>The next night, after a suspicious fire that destroyed the Marche Hyppolite, a 19th-century market that was a major commercial center here, crowds of angry Haitians coursed through the streets of Port-au-Prince.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Rene Preval, a former baker, called in a broadcast for calm and said "this Government will serve for five years, not one day more or one day less."</p>
        <p>Jean-Robert Martinez, a Senator from the National Front for Democratic Change, which sponsored Father Aristide's candidacy, echoed criticism by other legislators. "Right now," he said, "we are falling into a cascade of incidents, a certain anarchy, with no sense of direction."  Settling Old Scores</p>
        <p>Friends and critics of the Government have said that instead of capitalizing on its enormous post-inauguration popular support to push through new programs, it has squandered good will by pursuing perceived demons from governments past.</p>
        <p>In the most hotly discussed incident, the Government arrested and briefly jailed former President Ertha Pascal-Trouillot in connection with a failed coup attempt by rightists in January. The move drew chilly reactions from the United States and other donor countries whose financial help the Government actively seeks.</p>
        <p>Many Haitians were dismayed by what they saw as a gratuitous slap at Mrs. Pascal-Trouillot.</p>
        <p>"This country needs tourists and investors," said a dismayed human rights campaigner who has supported the Government. "Even if you have something serious against Madame Trouillot, it can wait six months. What they did was send out the exact opposite of the kind of signal the country needs to be transmitting to the world right now."</p>
        <p>The new Government's ties with the Haitian legislature, after a brief honeymoon in which Father Aristide was granted special powers to speed through administrative changes, have also grown troubled. Senators, including several from the party that sponsored his candidacy, have complained that the Government has ignored the Senate's consultative role in important appointments.</p>
        <p>Recently, the Government asked private business to lend it "thousands and millions of dollars," within the space of four days, in order to "create jobs and fight inflation."</p>
        <p>When journalists asked whether businesses would not feel coerced, Commerce Minister Smarck Michel said, "This is not an ultimatum." When the deadline passed, the Government announced it had collected $5.3 million, mostly from state-controlled corporations. Many business owners grumbled privately that despite the Commerce Minister's disclaimer, they found the approach intimidating.</p>
        <p>"Nobody is crazy enough not to give," said a merchant, who despite his resentment lent $2,000. "In Haiti it doesn't matter what the Government says. If your name is not on the list, you won't feel completely safe."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
