<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a French Cave, Wildlife Scenes From a Long-Gone World</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="739051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHEOLOGY AND ANTHROPOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAVES AND CAVERNS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RHINOCEROSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEARS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STONE AGE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VALLON-PONT-D'ARC (FRANCE)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARDECHE (FRANCE)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Caves and Caverns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rhinoceroses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D8133CF937A15752C0A963958260" item-length="546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a French Cave, Wildlife Scenes From a Long-Gone World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Jan. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stone Age murals discovered last month in southern France come in red hematite, ochre yellow and hues of charcoal, and specialists believe they were made some 20,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>French explorers found the 300-odd paintings and engravings beautifully preserved in the darkness of a great underground limestone cavern. The team of two men and one woman were probing a gorge not far from the Ardeche River near the town of Vallon-Pont-d'Arc when they spotted their first clue: a draft coming through the stones. After clearing a narrow passage, the team dropped down 30 feet and landed on the floor of a great chamber. Here they saw the first red markings on the walls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stone Age murals discovered last month in southern France come in red hematite, ochre yellow and hues of charcoal, and specialists believe they were made some 20,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>French explorers found the 300-odd paintings and engravings beautifully preserved in the darkness of a great underground limestone cavern. The team of two men and one woman were probing a gorge not far from the Ardeche River near the town of Vallon-Pont-d'Arc when they spotted their first clue: a draft coming through the stones. After clearing a narrow passage, the team dropped down 30 feet and landed on the floor of a great chamber. Here they saw the first red markings on the walls.</p>
        <p>Soon hordes of beasts loomed in their lights: lions running, a group of horse's heads, cave bears with their mouths open, a pair of rhinoceroses fighting. The large animals roaming through what was then a cold landscape of tundras, birches and pine trees must have inspired the early hunting people with awe. Archeologists say the find, which was announced last Wednesday, is exceptional because of the many animal groupings made at a time when images more commonly stood on their own. They also wonder about the unusually large number of bears and rhinoceroses. Were these part of a cult? All of Europe's Stone Age murals add up to no more than 20 or so images of the extinct woolly haired species; here they found at least 50.</p>
        <p>Overjoyed specialists said this was the first large cave from the Paleolithic era to be found undisturbed, perhaps even in the state it was left millenniums ago. A landslide apparently sealed off the natural entrance. The explorers saw what they believe to be human footprints as well as the large, broad imprints of bears. Other relics from the cave users include knapped flints and blackened hearths with fragments of burnt bones.</p>
        <p>Researchers believe they will find more images as they explore the four large chambers connected by smaller galleries. They estimated that the compound was about five times as large as the famous cave of Lascaux, and said that its art work was as breathtaking. Radiocarbon testing to determine the date of the relics has not been done but archeologists who have visited the cave say they are convinced of its antiquity.</p>
        <p>"I have no doubts," said Jean Clottes, France's foremost rock art specialist, who spent seven hours in the cavern. Up close, he said, the paintings and engravings showed the natural degradation of age. Some were covered with very old calcite deposits. The hematite of the red dots, the symbolism of which is not understood, was deeply encrusted into the limestone. In front of one panel of paintings, Mr. Clottes went on, there is a deep hole where the earth evidently caved in a long time ago and that could not have been reached by a modern visitor without leaving evident marks.</p>
        <p>This weekend Mr. Clottes recalled in a telephone interview that after the first hour of scrutinizing the art and slowly accepting its authenticity, he paused. "I stood in front of that exquisite panel with the four horses' heads and I felt I was watching the work of a great master," he said. "I was so overcome that I cried. It was like going into an attic and finding a da Vinci. Except that this great master was unknown."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
