<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dinner at 8? San Francisco Will Be Feasting by Then</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="739088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUPER BOWL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO CHARGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEORGE, THOMAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/San Diego Chargers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/San Francisco 49ers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DB103FF937A15752C0A963958260" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dinner at 8? San Francisco Will Be Feasting by Then</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas George</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GEORGE, THOMAS</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ARE you ready for Super Bowl XXIX (that's 29)? Get ready for another blowout. Another half-game. Another half Super Bowl. So here are XIV and a half (that's 14 1/2) reasons why the San Francisco 49ers will rip the San Diego Chargers:</p>
        <p>I San Francisco has the Golden Gate Bridge, Twin Peaks and is The City by the Bay. San Diego has the zoo. Where do you want to spend your vacation?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ARE you ready for Super Bowl XXIX (that's 29)? Get ready for another blowout. Another half-game. Another half Super Bowl. So here are XIV and a half (that's 14 1/2) reasons why the San Francisco 49ers will rip the San Diego Chargers:</p>
        <p>I San Francisco has the Golden Gate Bridge, Twin Peaks and is The City by the Bay. San Diego has the zoo. Where do you want to spend your vacation?</p>
        <p>II This is the fifth Super Bowl for the 49ers, the first for the Chargers. The Chargers will be blinded by the Super Bowl light, glitz and hype. Kind of like a deer trapped in a room with 500 photographers flashing their bulbs simultaneously.</p>
        <p>III There's the California thing. Not long ago, four National Football League teams played in California -- the Rams, Raiders, Chargers and 49ers. Of the four, the 49ers have been the dominant team in recent years. They beat each of the other three this season, including the Chargers by 38-15 in San Diego. And when they play the Chargers, they approach them with supreme confidence. It's kind of like a 25-year-old dad taking his 6-year-old kid out back to shoot hoops. The kid only scores when dad is kind.</p>
        <p>IV The Chargers have a nice thing going on offense. They pound you with running back Natrone Means and set you up for the big play. It is run, run, run, home run. The 49er offense, however, is home run, home run, home run, home run.</p>
        <p>V The 49ers have more stars, more publicity and more All-Pros. You flash 49ers this week, you get the house seat. Everybody will check twice on the Chargers I.D. before entry. The snub treatment should get the Chargers more riled come game day, but it will likely make the inferiority complex double.</p>
        <p>VI The 49ers will wear their throwback uniforms. The 49ers have won every game in them since Week 6 except for one loss, at Minnesota, in the regular-season finale, when they sat some starters and already had their division and home-field playoff advantage wrapped up.</p>
        <p>VII Jerry Rice, John Taylor and Brent Jones versus the Charger secondary. This could be the game's biggest mismatch.</p>
        <p>VIII Two weeks to prepare for the Super Bowl. Chargers Coach Bobby Ross is very strong, very meticulous. But giving the 49ers entire coaching staff two weeks to get ready for one team is like giving the United States Army two weeks to prepare to invade Rhode Island.</p>
        <p>IX Charger John Carney gets the edge over 49er Doug Brien in place-kicking. But the 49er special teams are certainly as good and possibly quicker and bigger hitters.</p>
        <p>X Stan Humphries versus Steve Young. Humphries has moxie. Young has that and scrambling ability plus several more offensive options.</p>
        <p>XI The 49er defense. It has several big-name free agents and they have played and produced that way.</p>
        <p>XII Deion Sanders might return kicks for the 49ers. Already a prize cornerback, that prospect offers double trouble for the Chargers.</p>
        <p>XIII The American Football Conference has lost 10 consecutive Super Bowls. The Chargers represent the American Football Conference.</p>
        <p>XIV The 49ers can become the first franchise in league history to win five Super Bowls. They don't need an extra incentive, but that one won't hurt.</p>
        <p>XIV 1/2 49ers 36, Chargers 13.  ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
