<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tenor, a Baritone And 'Winterreise'</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="739069"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHUBERT, GERARD J (REV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHREIER, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAGEGARD, HAKAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLLAND, BERNARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD7173FF937A15752C0A963958260" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tenor, a Baritone And 'Winterreise'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLLAND, BERNARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Singers of songs fall into two categories: the actors and the tellers. The first take us straight to the song's source, using a theater of sorts to recreate people, places and thoughts.</p>
        <p>It is no easy job, standing relatively immobile and nearly alone, with only a piano to lean back on. This is acting in sound: altering the color and force of the voice, slowing down or speeding up, making musical accent a metaphor for impulses of the heart: all as surrogates for the poet's imagination. Peter Schreier, who with Alexei Lubimov performed Schubert's "Winterreise" at Carnegie Hall on Friday night, is an actor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Singers of songs fall into two categories: the actors and the tellers. The first take us straight to the song's source, using a theater of sorts to recreate people, places and thoughts.</p>
        <p>It is no easy job, standing relatively immobile and nearly alone, with only a piano to lean back on. This is acting in sound: altering the color and force of the voice, slowing down or speeding up, making musical accent a metaphor for impulses of the heart: all as surrogates for the poet's imagination. Peter Schreier, who with Alexei Lubimov performed Schubert's "Winterreise" at Carnegie Hall on Friday night, is an actor.</p>
        <p>Yet the beauty of a story can be as much in the telling as in what is told. Dull events conveyed with art surpass the most vivid picture botched in transmission. Here the singer occupies a space between the listener and the song, becoming both funnel and filter. A personal narrative style is set in motion guided by a coherent tone. Singers like this react to the song; then we react to them. Hakan Hagegard, who with Warren Jones sang "Winterreise" at Alice Tully Hall on Sunday afternoon, is a teller.</p>
        <p>The appearance of both men in the same repertory within three days makes choices moot. Both sides of the argument were there, both questioned, both profited from. The successes and failures of these concerts had mostly to do with things beyond the interpreter's art and, often, control. Mr. Schreier, first of all, is a tenor, and Schubert's choices of key throughout these 24 songs suggest that the tenor's range and timbre are what he had in mind.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schreier's sound is bright, strong and penetrating. It is neither terribly beautiful nor all that flexible, but he is a supremely thoughtful musical actor and can alter color and emphasis when the moment arrives. A hall of 2,800 seats posed him problems despite his carrying power. Wilhelm Muller's sad little story -- 24 poems that follow an ousted lover's progress on a lonely winter's journey -- is not ideally served by the level of declamation needed for mass communication like this.</p>
        <p>And what an audience! A few strays began applauding after the opening "Gute Nacht." Waves of coughing throughout the evening announced yet another visitation of influenza to our city. Such things made Mr. Schreier work harder for attention, and this the music did not need. Mr. Lubimov's piano playing had an easier time, offering a shining, easy beauty that filled the hall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hakegard had a more manageable space to sing in and often a better class of listener. Public respiratory distress, though evident, was not nearly as disruptive. One missed the yearning tenorial quality in some of the songs, but then again Mr. Hakegard's baritonal transpositions respond to the poetry's bleakness of scene. It is a voice without much color, but it is used with care and steadfastness. The Hakegard-Jones tempos were generally much faster than those from Schreier-Lubimov; this was in keeping with "Winterreise" as a story told, a narrative in motion, rather than a set of scenes acted out one by one. Mr. Jones does not have Mr. Lubimov's strength or glow of sound, but he played very beautifully.</p>
        <p>Musicologists had a few things to argue about. Does Mr. Jones misread the dotted rhythms in "Wasserflut"? I think he does; so evidently does Mr. Lubimov, who on Friday played them as triplets. (The 18th century's eccentric ways of notating rhythm lasted longer into the 19th than a lot of us think.) Schubert marks "Die Nebensonnen" "not too slowly." Mr. Hakegard couldn't resist ignoring the score, and to dreary effect, I am afraid.</p>
        <p>"Winterreise," however, is one of music's great icons. It admits debate, opens its arms to diversity and continues to speak to us as few other pieces do. Over the weekend it spoke twice.  CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
