<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using News Media as a Conduit Has Worked, Some Officers Say</title>
    <meta content="Y22TAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/22/national/22TALK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1433988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE HUNT FOR A SNIPER: THE INVESTIGATORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Serial Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maryland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Virginia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montgomery County (Md)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butterfield, Fox</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Serial Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Maryland</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DC163CF931A15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using News Media as a Conduit Has Worked, Some Officers Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Using News Media as a Conduit Has Worked, Some Officers Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FOX BUTTERFIELD and KEVIN FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Kevin; Butterfield, Fox</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Police rarely talk to suspects through news media as law enforcement officials are trying with sniper in Washington area, but police commanders in few cities say they have used technique successfully; photo; some cases recalled (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is rare for the police to talk to suspects through the news media as law enforcement officials are trying with the sniper in the Washington area, but police commanders in a few cities say they have used the technique successfully.</p>
        <p>In Seattle, the police used television stations and newspapers to communicate with a suspect in a 2000 bank robbery in which a police officer was wounded in a shootout, said Gil Kerlikowske, Seattle's police commissioner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is rare for the police to try to talk to suspects through the news media, as is being done with the sniper in the Washington area, but it has worked a few times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is rare for the police to talk to suspects through the news media as law enforcement officials are trying with the sniper in the Washington area, but police commanders in a few cities say they have used the technique successfully.</p>
        <p>In Seattle, the police used television stations and newspapers to communicate with a suspect in a 2000 bank robbery in which a police officer was wounded in a shootout, said Gil Kerlikowske, Seattle's police commissioner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerlikowske said the suspect, who was black, expressed fears through the news media that racist police would shoot and kill him on sight because he had wounded the officer. ''I tried to assure him by telling him that we would use all available resources to arrest him, but that we would protect him,'' Mr. Kerlikowske said.</p>
        <p>After lengthy negotiations, some of which were in the news media, the suspect surrendered through his lawyer, coming back from Jamaica where he had fled. He has since been convicted and sentenced to 25 years in prison.</p>
        <p>''It makes a good deal of sense to try to communicate like this,'' Mr. Kerlikowske said. ''It reassures the public that the police are doing everything they can, and it shows the suspect that we take him seriously and that may lead to more communications.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the best-known case of the police talking to a suspect through the news media involved David Berkowitz, known as Son of Sam, who confessed to killing six people and wounding seven as they sat in cars parked on the streets of New York City in 1976 and 1977.</p>
        <p>After months in which New Yorkers were terrorized by the unidentified killer, Mr. Berkowitz left his first communication after killing a couple on a service road off the Hutchinson Parkway. The letter was addressed to Capt. Joseph Borrelli, who was in charge of the task force investigating the killings.</p>
        <p>A few weeks earlier, Captain Borrelli had been interviewed by Irene Cornell, a reporter for WCBS radio, who had questioned him about whether the killer appeared to hate women. Capt. Borrelli replied, ''Well, many of his victims have been young women.''</p>
        <p>Now the letter gave every indication that the killer was listening to that radio broadcast and other news reports.</p>
        <p>''Dear Captain Borrelli,'' the letter began. ''I am not a weoman-hater [sic].''</p>
        <p>Mr. Borrelli, who later became chief of detectives for the New York Police Department, said police officials never publicly discussed the letter at the time or addressed the killer directly. But at news conferences, they sent out messages to indicate that they would like to hear from him.</p>
        <p>''You have mixed feelings,'' Mr. Borrelli said in an interview. ''You really feel like telling him what you think of him. But the profilers and common sense are telling you that that might set him off. So you have to respond in carefully worded statements.''</p>
        <p>Hugh McGowan, a retired police supervisor who directed the New York Police Department's hostage negotiating team for 13 years, said it was difficult to create a dialogue with a suspect when very little about the person was known.</p>
        <p>By contrast, in a hostage situation, Mr. McGowan said, the police not only have the suspect surrounded, they also usually have some understanding of the identity and motive of the hostage-taker, and those can be used to advantage.</p>
        <p>The sniper situation is more akin to a kidnapping, he said. ''In a kidnapping, you have no leverage.''</p>
        <p>Robert Louden, a professor at John Jay College of Criminal Justice in Manhattan who led the New York Police Department's hostage negotiating team for six years, said that the current sniper case seemed unique in many respects, but that it was important that law enforcement speak with one voice.</p>
        <p>This is especially true, Mr. Louden said, since the sniper has covered so many jurisdictions.</p>
        <p>By using a single speaker, Chief Charles A. Moose of the Montgomery County, Md., police, the authorities are trying to eliminate potential confusion about the message, Mr. Louden said. Having a single speaker also opens the possibility that some rapport may develop with the sniper, or snipers, he said.</p>
        <p>But James Alan Fox, a professor of criminal justice at Northeastern University who has written several books about serial killers, expressed skepticism that the police effort to talk to the sniper was doing any good.</p>
        <p>''He is just playing the police like a fiddle,'' Professor Fox said. ''He is having a delightful time, and all this is making him feel even more in charge.''</p>
        <p>THE HUNT FOR A SNIPER: THE INVESTIGATORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
